
   
      
         
            How superior powers oght to be obeyd of their subiects and wherin they may lawfully by Gods Worde be disobeyed and resisted. Wherin also is declared the cause of all this present miserie in England, and the onely way to remedy the same. By Christopher Goodman.
            Goodman, Christopher, 1520?-1603.
         
         
            
               1558
            
         
         Approx. 297 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 120 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01880
            STC 12020
            ESTC S103263
            99839020
            99839020
            3414
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01880)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3414)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1173:15)
         
         
            
               
                  How superior powers oght to be obeyd of their subiects and wherin they may lawfully by Gods Worde be disobeyed and resisted. Wherin also is declared the cause of all this present miserie in England, and the onely way to remedy the same. By Christopher Goodman.
                  Goodman, Christopher, 1520?-1603.
               
               234, [6] p.   
               
                  By Iohn Crispin,
                  Printed at Geneua :
                  M.D.LVIII. [1558]
               
               
                  Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: a-p.
                  "William Kethe to the reader", verse, p6r-p7r.
                  Running title reads: How to obey or disobey.
                  Page p7v has the cut in one of two states, with or without the motto "Intrate per arctam viam" in a scroll.
                  Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
               Government, Resistance to --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.
               Great Britain --  History --  Mary I, 1553-1558 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-04
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2006-04
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            HOW SVPERIOR POWERS OGHT TO BE OBEYD OF THEIR ſubiects: and Wherin they may lawfully by Gods Worde be diſobeyed and reſiſted. Wherin alſo is declared the cauſe of all this preſent miſerie in England, and the onely way to remedy the ſame.
            BY CHRISTOPHER GOODMAN.
            
               ¶The Lord hath broght vpon them a nation from a farre contrey, an impudent nation and of a strange langage.
               Baruch 4. Deut. 28.
               
            
            Printed at Geneua by Iohn Criſpin. M.D.LVIII.
         
         
            
            
            VVILLIAM VVHITINGHAM TO ALL THEM that loue to knoWe the trueth and foloWe it: Grace and peace.
            
               IGnorance the mother of error and profeſſed ennemie to Gods Trueth, hath two daughters by whoſe flatteries and ſubtile practiſes ſhe blyndeth mens eyes, obſcureth the Trueth, and withdraweth vs from the way of knollage: Cuſtome, and Negligence. Wherof the firſt ſo bewitcheth vs, that althogh we wallowe and walter in darcke blyndenes, yet as it were by dreaming we ſeme to walke in the bright ſunne ſhyning: ſo that Cuſtome and compagnie may farre ſoner drawe vs to perdition, then Trueth and reaſon bring vs to the vnderſtanding of our error. The other being a domeſtical ſeruante and wel acquaynted with our maners, by crafty flatterie doth ouercome vs. For the fleſhe is prowde and ſwelleth againſt God, ſhe glorieth in her owne wiſdome, ſhe loueth her owne conſel, ſhe deliteth in her owne imaginatiō and policie: and albeit we knowe that ſlothful Negligence is an impediment and blocke in our nature to ſtoppe vs from Trueth: yet willingly we gyue place to her

flattering perſuaſions, and ſuffre her to trayne vs to wilful deſtruction. So that betwixt Cuſtome and Negligence we rather holde with damnable Ignorance, and wiſſhe to be plonged in abominable errors, then by diligent ſtudy and ſerching of the Trueth learne to knowe our duetie to God, ād what he requireth of vs to do towardes our neighbour. Then if we wolde auoyde theſe euils, we muſt loue and embrace the cōtrary vertues: and if Cuſtome be wicked and withholde vs from God, we muſt ſpedely reiect her and cleaue vnto God: and if Negligence haue noſeled vs in the denne of Ignorance, we muſt purchaſe by diligence to proffit in the ſchole of knollage. For the acheuing wherof (whē M. Chriſtopher Goodman one of our miniſters, according to the courſe of the text, expounded bothe faithfully and cōfortably this place of the Actes of the Apoſtles,Act. 4. d. 
               Iudge whether it be iuste before God to obey you rather then God) certeyne learned and godly men moſte inſtantly, and at ſondry tymes required hī to dilate more at large that his Sermon, and to ſuffre it to be printed, that not onely we here preſent, but our bretherne in England and other places might be perſuaded in the trueth of that doctrine concerninge obedience to the magiſtrat, and ſo glorifie God with vs. Whiche requeſt he admitted not eaſely, til at lēgth wel wayinge how many periſhed in their ignorance

for lack of meanes to attaine to the knollage of the trueth: and alſo conferringe his articles and chief propoſitions with the beſt learned in theſe partes (who approued them) he cōſented to enlarge the ſaid Sermō and ſo to print it, as a token of his duetie and good affection towarde the Churche of God: and then if it were thoght good to the iudgement of the godly, to tranſlate the ſame into other lāgages that the proffit ther of might be more vniuerſal. Ther is no doute but many ouercome with olde Cuſtome, or yelding to negligēt Slothfulnes wil ether diſpraiſe this proffitable worke, or neglect it. For euel Cuſtome deliting in Ignorance wil ſtraight way flie to her wonted argumēt: What is this newe doctrine?Mar. 1 c. Act. 17. c and whē
               ce is it? Negligence on the other part crieth maliciouſly: We haue bookes ynough: what nede we yet to be ſet to ſchole? Thus Satan with double ſubteltie deludeth the worlde, keping his euer ſo faſt tyed in the bandes of blynde Ignorance, that they can nether ſtirre hand nor fote: they are blynde and can not ſe what is good: and thogh it be offered, yet are they inſenſible and can not fele it. The trueth of Gods worde is to them moſte odious: but mans dreames and deuils doctrines are in greate eſtimatiō and reuerence. Their falſe prophets and papiſtical prieſts haue ſo charmed them, that Ignorance is holden for knollage, error for

trueth, ſuperſtition for religion, diſobedience for obedience, the Maſſe for the Lordes Supper, Purgatorie for Chriſts blood, workes for faith, Belial for God, and as S. Paul ſaieth,2. Cor. 11. d
                If they bring you into ſlauerie, ye endure it: if they deuoure you, ye ſuffre it: if they ſpoile you of your goods, ye are content: if they preferre them ſelues and thruſt you downe, ye forbeare it: if they ſmite you on the face, yet ye can ſuſteine it. And thus the children of Satan had rather rot in their barbarous ignorance, then by ſubmitting thē ſelues to the mercies of God, aſpire to the perfect vnderſtanding of his heauenly will reueiled vnto vs by his worde. But thou the ſonne of God, ſhewe thy duetie and loue towarde thy merciful Father, endeuour to knowe his wil, declare thy affection towardes his Scriptures, be zealous of his glorie, reuerence his miniſters, and receaue thankfully his graces geuen to his Churche by them. Proue diligently and trie by the touchſtone who ſpeake the wordes of God in pure ſimplicitie as in Gods preſēce,2. Cor. 2. d.
                and who cehoppe and change the ſame, making marchandiſe therof to traffique according to mans pleaſure. Nether do we deſire onely that you ſhulde be perſuaded in this trueth becauſe we our ſelues ſo beleue: but we exhort you,Iob. 4. f. that as the Samaritās dyd not onely beleue in our Sauiour Chriſt becauſe of the womās report which broght the newes,

but foraſmuche as they them ſelues heard him, and knewe that Chriſt was the Sauiour of the worlde: ſo whē you ſhal wel examine theſe things by the rule of Gods worde, you wolde not ſo much by our report as by your owne iudgement and knowlage credit the trueth. Remēbring that the worthy people of Beroe were cōmēded by the holy Goſt,Act. 17. c. becauſe they tryed by Gods worde whether the miniſters preachīg agreed with the ſame or no. Seing then by theſe examples we are bonde to ſeke the wil of God manifeſted vnto vs in his Scriptures, what excuſe ſhal we alledge for our pretenſed ignorance? Beholde here▪ thou heareſt the Eternal ſpeaking by his miniſter, in whoſe mouthe he hath put his worde, and whoſe lippes muſt kepe the Lawe ād the vnderſtāding therof, as wryteth the Prophet Malachie.Chap. 2. a Beware therfore that thou neglect not him that brīgeth the worde of God, but quickely gyue eare ād obey. For if thou deſireſt to knowe thy duetie to thy Prince, and his charge likewiſe ouer thee, read this book and thou ſhalt wel vnderſtāde both: If thou wiſhe for Chriſtiā libertie, come and ſe how it may eaſely be had: If thou woldeſt loue God aboue man, here thou ſhalt knowe how to obey God rather then mā. Let the Apoſtles of Chriſt here be thy ſchole maiſters, and then the more thou learneſt: the leſſe occaſiō ſhalt thou haue to repent. Obedience is neceſſarie where

God is glorified, but if God be diſhonored thy obedience is abominable in the ſight of God, be it neuer ſo beautiful in mans eyes. Gods worde is our guyde to leade vs in our doings: when it commandeth vs to obey God, we muſt diſobey man in the contrary: for no man can ſerue two maiſters: and when our heauēly maiſter cōmandeth obedience to man, it is euer to be vnderſtand, in the Lord. So that obedience to Gods Lawes by diſſobeyīg mās wicked lawes is muche commendable, but to diſobey God for any duetie to mā is all to gether damnable: as in the diſcourſe of this booke thou ſhalt fully be aſſeured, if God open thyn eyes to ſe the trueth, ād moue thy heart to embrace it. The Spirit of God, which is the ſcholemaiſtre to leade vs into all trueth, lighten your hartes, gyue you myndes to vnderſtande, and courage to execute his holy wil, to the ſetting forth of Chriſtes kingdome, the proffit of his Churche and confuſion of Satans power and Antichriſts. Amen. From Geneua this firſt of Ianuarie. 1558.
         
         
            
            THE PREFACE.
            
               AS there is nothīge to be cōpared to true obediē
               ce, in preſeruīge the cō
               mō welth of townes, cities, and kingdoms: or in maynteyninge true religiō,True obedience rendreth to God due honor &amp; alſo to man as his office requireth. what great daunger it is, not to put differē
                  ce betwene obedience and diſobedience. Chriſtiā peace &amp; cōcorde (for therby euery mā is inſtructed how to render vnto God his due honour &amp; glorie: &amp; to man that, whiche his office requireth) Euē ſo is ther nothinge more hatefull to God, nether more hurtefull to mā, then ſo to be bewitched with Satans falſe illuſions, that they are not able to put difference betwyxte obedience &amp; diſobedience: but as men without all iudgemēt and naturall ſenſe, take thone for thother, beinge in them ſelues playne contrarie, whiche is the onelie cauſe of all diſorder and lamentable confuſion, where with the whole worlde is bothe this daie, and hath bene alſo frō the beginning, moſt miſerably defaced and oppreſſed. For when vile man, repleniſhed with pride, vayne glorie, and groſſe ignorance, will meaſure obedience with the crowked lyne of his owne corrupte iudgement,

and not with the infallible trueth of Goddes holie worde, he muſt nedes preferre his owne decrees, phantaſies, and ordināces, to the cōfortable Lawes and liuelie preceptes of God his creator. Then in place of iuſtice, he receaueth iniuſtice, for right wronge, for vertue vice, for lawe will, for loue hatred, for trueth falſhod, for playne dealing diſſimulation,what plags come for diſobediēce. for religion ſuperſtition, for true worſhippe deteſtable idolatrie: and to be ſhorte, for God Sathan, for Chriſt Antichriſt, and with him ſuche plages of God, and diſorder amonge mē, as are this daye ſet before oure eyes to beholde in all places throughout the vniuerſal worlde, and haue bene likewiſe euen from the beginninge. When Adam was placed in paradiſe,
                  Gen. 3. beinge a creature moſte perfecte, and abundinge in all wiſdome and heauenlie knowledge, and wolde at the perſuaſion of his wif meaſure obedience rather by his owne reaſon,Adam diſobeied God and was greuouſlie puniſhed. then by the worde &amp; ſentence of God before pronounced: behold, he was not onelie ſpoyled of wiſdome &amp; knowledge, becomminge a verie foole, in compariſon of that, whiche

he was before: but alſo ſodaynlie deſtitute of all other ſinguler giftes, as of innocencie, and immortalitie, was confoūded at the voyce of the Lord, aſſhamed at his owne nakedneſſe, and felt the dredfull indignation and curſe of God, whiche he had procured, not onelie to him ſelf, but broght the ſame alſo vpon all his poſteritie after him.All mākinde was iuſtly puniſhed for Adams diſobediēce When the whole worlde was ſo corrupted in their owne wayes in the dayes of faithfull Noha, no regarde was at all to the obedience of the liuinge Lorde, nor yet to the godlie admonitions of iuſt Noha:
                  Gen. 6. but euerie man was ſo drowned in his owne luſtes,The worlde plaged in Nohas dayes for diſobediēce that the ſpace of an hundreth &amp; twenty yeares was not ſufficiēt to moue them to repentance. And therfore could they not eſcape the ſtrange and horrible iudgement of God, whiche immediatlie after folowed moſte iuſtlie. And althogh in that wicked generation abonded all kinde of wickedneſſe, as well agaynſt God as man, in ſo muche as the earthe then might be compted a verie hell, yet from whence proceaded all this rebellion againſt Goddes mightie maieſtie, but onelie for that they

meaſured all thinges after their owne corrupt reaſon,The cauſe of all diſobedience is, not to meaſure oure doings by Godds worde. Rom. 2.
                and not by his holie Lawes and preceptes? Whiche they had now receaued of their forefathers, hearde of Noah, yea, and had them ingrafted naturally in their hartes. The probation wherof might eaſilie be deduced from all ages euen to oure tyme by innumerable and euident examples, if it were nedefull in ſo playne a matter. For who is ſo blynde that maye not ſe how man ſheweth his rebellion,We must not meaſure our obedience after our oune phanteſies. neuer ſo muche, as when he woulde be moſte obedient in his owne ſight and iudgement? not meaſuringe the ſame by the ſtreght lyne and true toucheſtone, whiche is the Lawe and worde of God, but ſuffringe him ſelf to be led by his owne corrupte iudgemēt and affectiōs.
            This turned the Wiſdome of the Gentiles into mere foliſhneſſe, inuētinge ſhamefull idolatrye for true worſhipp,
                  Rom. 1. as witneſſethe the Apoſtle.
            
               
                  Mat. 15.This blynded the Ieues with hypocriſie and cloked holyneſſe, makinge the Lawe of the liuinge Lorde to geue place to their inuented traditions by man.Diſobedience is the puddle of all heriſies and error. Out of this ſtinkinge puddle of

mans brayne haue iſſued forthe ſo great diuerſitie of opinions and daungerous heriſies, wherwith the Churche of God hathe bē at all tymes horriblye tormented. Finallie from hence hathe Antichriſte filled his peſtilente cupp of all ſortes of deadlie poyſon,Apo. 17. Antichriſte is the plage of God for mās diſobedience. where of he hathe made the whole earthe almoſt, and her kinges and Princes, not onelie to drinke: but to be moſt vilelie ouercome and dronken. In whoſe defence they haue armed them ſelues againſt the Lorde ād Chriſte his Son:
                  Pſal. 2. whō notwithſtanding with impudent mouthes they profeſſe, where as in verie dede they perſecute him moſte cruellie in his Saincts by all means poſsible,The tyrāts are Antichriſtes tormentours and perſecute Chriſt fightinge, as men in a rage, vnder the banner of that filthie beaſt. And yet theſe men in the middle of their furie, without all obedience &amp; ordre, ſubuertinge the Lawes of God and of nature, will be called notwithſtandinge the defenders of the faithe, mayntayners of true religiō, autours of peace, teachers of obedience, ād moſt diſcrete gouernours of common weales and policies. To the intent therfore that theſe diſguiſed perſonnes

(whiche abuſe the whole worlde) may appeare in their owne liuely ſhape, and be knowen as they are in dede, I haue thoght it good,Thoccaſion wherefore this treatiſe was writ, and what proffit we may gather therof. hauinge occaſion by this worthie anſwere of Peter and Iohn, and beinge hereto of diuers godlie perſons prouoked, ſomewhat to wryte of true obedience: to wit, what God him ſelf requiereth of vs, and what he commandethe to be geuen alſo to men. Wherby (God willinge) the diſguiſed clokes, and craftie pretences of obedience, vſed and practiſed by the vngodlie worldlings, ſhalbe diſcouered: who haue ſoght alwayes, and yet do ſeeke vnder the pleaſant name of obedience, onlie to mayntayne their ambition, pride and libertie: wherby we ſhall learne alſo how in tymes paſt we haue bene ſhamfullie abuſed in yelding to the willfull wil of man, in obeying his vngodlie commandements, and fearinge man more then God: and finallie how it behoueth vs to repent oure former ignoraunce, and with diligence to redreſſe the ſame, hauinge more lighte and fuller knowledge.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               PETER AND IOHN ANSWERED VNTO thē, and ſaid: Whether it be right in the ſight of God to obey you rather thē God, iudge you.
               Act. 4.
            
            CHAP. I. 
            
               ¶To whome this anſwere was geuen, and vpon what occaſion, how litle the malice of the Iues preuailed agaynst the Apostles, in ſekinge to ſtopp the Goſpell by their craftie fetches and chaſtiſynges.
            
            
               TO the end we may haue more ſenſible fealinge of all theſe things,The circū
                  ſtance of the anſwere wayed. let vs diligentlie conſider this anſwere of S. Peter &amp; Iohn: aſwell to whō it was made, as vpon what occaſion. After that theſe ii Apoſtles, through the malice of the Prieſts, the Gouernoure of the Tēple and the Sadduces,
                  Act. 4. were violentlie throwne into priſon the night before, for preaching to the people at Ieruſalem in the porche of Salomon, the reſurrection from death in the Name of Ieſus: and the next

daye folowīge were ſet forthe, ād preſented to the whole Senate and Concile of Ieruſalem, where was aſſembled all the chief Rulers and Elders of the people of Iſraell, Annas alſo the hie Prieſt, and Caiaphas, ād Iohn, and Alexandre, men of great reputation, with others of the kinred of the high Biſſhopp, to be examined of thē, in whoſe name or power they had cured the lame criple (who beinge aboue 40 yeres olde, and lame from his birthe was daylie broght to the porche of Salomō to begge his almes) Peter repleniſſhed with the holie Spirit, āſwered withe great boldneſſe, that they wroght that miracle in the Name and power of Ieſus Chriſt the true Nazarit, Whome the Ieues had crucified, and God had rayſed from the death: in ſo muche as the mouthes of the whole Concile were ſtopped &amp; had nothinge to ſaye againſt them, but as men aſtunniſſhed wondred at the conſtant boldeneſſe of Peter and Iohn in their anſwere. Then (ſaithe S. Luke) did the whole Concile, that is, all theſe forenamed Magiſtrates by common conſent

ſtraytelie charge the Apoſtels Peter and Iohn,The magiſtrats cō
                  mande the Apostles not to preach Chriſte. hereafter not ſo muche as once to ſpeake to anie man, muche leſſe to preache in the Name of Ieſus: thinking by this means to ſtoppe the courſe of the Goſpell, ād hinder the glorie of Chriſt, whō they before had crucified as a malefactor and blaſphemer of Gods Name. And althoghe they were deſtitute of all reaſon and Scripture to anſwere the Apoſtels, who had all redie cōfounded the: yet throughe auctoritie and poniſhmēte, whiche they threatned, they thoght craftelie to put the Apoſtles to ſilence, and ſo at length to obtayne the victorie. As we ſee this daye the Papiſtes their ſucceſſors, expreſſe enimies of the Goſpel,The papists ſuccead the Iewes in malice ād perſecutiō. ād ſworne ſoldiars of Antichriſte, euery where practiſe, who beinge ouercome with the manifeſt Scriptures, and their blaſphemous mouthes ſtopped with the truthe of Gods worde, fight notwithſtanding maliciouſlie agaynſt Chriſte with power, auctoritie, threatnyngs,Papiſts are the generation of Vipers. Iohn. 8.
                horrible poniſhmentes, and cruell murther, reſemblinge that old ſerpēt, whoſe broude they are, whiche was a murtherer

from the begyninge.
            But when the whole aſſembly had craftelie cōſulted, and wrought all that they coulde agaynſt the faithfull ſeruā
               tes of God:The Goſpell increaſeth when it is perſecuted. they were neuer the leſſe diſapoynted of their porpoſe. For the glorie of Chriſte more brightelie ſhyned, and the truthe of his Goſpell was better knowen ād farther publiſhed, and their falſhod and raginge madneſſe more eſpied, and abhorred of the godlie. For what extreame madneſſe was this to ſet them ſelues agaynſt God, ſo to truſte in their owne power as thoughe they were able to reſyſte and ouercome the power of the all mightie,
                  Rom. 1. whiche is the Goſpell of oure Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte (as witneſſe the the Apoſtle) To thinke that the threatnings of mē, ſhulde more preuayle with the Apoſtels of Chriſte, then the threatnings of God ād his horrible iudgementes apoynted for the diſobediēt?We must rather feare Goddes iudgemēts then mans threatnyngs. Coulde not the Iewes diſtroye Chriſte and his doctrine, whiles he was mortall and liued amongeſt them in the fleſhe, to whom they did almoſte what they liſt, an yet would after

thinke to bringe it to paſſe, when he was riſen agayne by his mightie power, and made immortall? Yf they coulde not keape him in the graue for al their diligent watche, when he was dead and buried: thinke they it poſſible to pluke him downe from heauē, from the righthande of his father, where he fitteth and reigneth in euerlaſtīge glorie? Oh vayne and fooliſhe men: he hathe ouercome al readie the whole world, and caſt forthe of it the Chief Prince &amp; Ruler Satan, who is no more able to preuayle agaynſt his truthe and ſeruauntes.Chriſte ād his word are inuinſible. Are you more ſubtile or ſtronger then Satan, who is your lorde and maiſter ſo longe as you fight agaynſt Chriſte the Sonne of God? Coulde not ſo mightie a Prince with ſtande his power, and you leawde ſouldiars of his, wil thīke to optayne the victorie? Deathe, whiche no man can eſcape, coulde not holde him, neither the power of hell praeuayle agaynſt him: and yet would you haue him at your commandement, moſte maliciouſlie and traitrouſlie ſighfightinge againſt his hōnor, who ſoght

by all means, and yet doth, to do you good and ſaue you? But ô miſerable and vile wretches, double is your condemnation in the ſight of God, which not contented to forſake Chriſte your ſelues, do ſo maliciouſly with your threatenings labour to fruſtrate others of his moſte confortable graces.
                  Mat. 23. Full wel doth our Sauiour Chriſt paynt forth your raginge enuie, ſainge, Wo be to you Scribes, Phariſies, and hypocrites, becauſe you ſhutt the kingdome of heauen before men, not entering your ſelues, neither wil you ſuffer ſuch as come, to enter.
         
         
            CHAP. II. 
            
               ¶ How the papiſticall Churche and Conciles can not but erre, and how they beinge compared to the Iewes, are no leſſe deniers and blaſphemers of Chriſt▪ then the Iewes.
            
            
               Great occaſions of repentance offered to the Iewes.
               I wil not here rehearſe what iuſte occaſiō of repentance was offered to this whole aſſemblie of the Iewes (if their hartes had not bene hardened) as wel by the playne and ſenſible

doctrine taught by the Apoſtels, whiche they coulde not improue with all their learninge:An horrible falling awaye frō God. as by the mightie powere of God declared in ſo manie and wonderful miracles wroght by them in the name of Chriſte to cōfirme his Goſpel and reſurrection, whiche the Iewes notwithſtāding ſtubbernly did reiecte: Nether yet wil I ſpeake of the ſtrange defection and notable falling awaie from God amongeſt them in Ieruſalem,Rom. 3. and 9. The Ieweſhe churche errethe. whiche at that tyme (in the iudgement of mā) appeared to be the onelie Churche of God, to whom appartayned the promiſes, who of al other nations had the Lawe, and Prophetes to inſtructe them, who onelie profeſſed the true and euerliuinge God: and yet amongeſt them all that were aſſembled, was not ſo muche as one man to ſtande vpon Chriſtes parte with the Apoſtels, but cō
               ſented and agreed with one accorde, that in the Name of Chriſte they ſhulde preache no more to the people. Onelie this I woulde put you in remembrance of, before we proceade anie further, how vayne and vncertayne the doctrine of the blaſphemous Papiſtes is, whiche

is grounded vpon no other foundation,The papiſtes churche erreth. then vpon the auctoritie of their Churche, their Councils, and decrees of men. And here in dare I make the papiſtes them ſelues iudges,The Iew iſhe chmrche was firſte. whither their Churche be of more auctoritie or antiquite, then was the Churche of the Iewes whiche was the firſt of all, ād auctoriſed by God immediatlie: Or whither their Concils at the appoyntment of the Romiſhe Antichriſte, were more orderlie called and aſſembled, then was this Concil holden at Ieruſalem by the appoyntmēt of the Chief prieſt and Biſhopp? As for their Churche, the Iewes had the manifeſte worde and promeſſe of God· yea, there was no other Churche, then viſible vpon the earthe, beſides that whiche the Apoſtels then began to buylde vpon the true conerſtone Ieſus Chriſte: where as the papiſtes haue not ſo muche as one worde or promeſſe to proue that they are (as they impudentlie bragge) the Churche of God, but manie rather moſte playnlie prouinge them to be the verie Synagoge of Satan, and liuelie members

of Antichriſte. Yf then this, whiche ſeemed the true Churche of God, ād auctoriſed by him, ſo ſhamefullie erred: maruel it is that the papiſticall Synagoge and members of Satan ſhuld be founde eſtabliſhers of the veritie, which alwayes ſince they haue bene rayſed vp from hell, haue ſoght nothing but the vtter ſubuerſion therof? Nether can they defende them ſelues by anie auctoritie to aſſemble, or by anie learninge, or outwarde ſhewe of holyneſſe:The locuſts which came out of the bottō
                  les pit. ſeīg in none of theſe poyntes they may be compared to this aſſemble, wher of S. Luke maketh mētion. For here was the highe Prieſte Annas, here was Caiaphas, here were the temporal Magiſtrates, the gouuerners of the Temple, the Seniors of Ieruſalem, the learned Scribes, and Phariſies. And what coulde anie man wiſhe fore in the iudgment of man, that there was not, to make a lawfull Concil? And yet thou ſeeſt the councluſion was agaynſt the Lorde ād his anoynted Sōne. Wilt thou then hope for anie better at the papiſtes aſſembles and Concils, who in perſecuting Chriſte continuallie,

and his holie worde, ſhewe them ſelues open enemies to bothe? Doeſt thou here beholde the Iewes, whiche profeſſed the true liuinge God, without all apiſhe maumetrie and Idolls, forbidden in their Lawe: neuertheleſſe malitiouſlie to conſulte agaynſte their true Meſsias: and will not yet ceaſe to credit the papiſtes, ſayng, That their Churches and Concils can not erre,The papiſtes are more wicked then Iewes. where as they diſhonor the liuinge Lorde, hauing their Temples repleniſhed with all kinde of idolatrie: yea, when their owne conſciences do condemne them, that there was neuer the like impietie committed in all Iſrael, as their filthie Concils haue taught and commended? But thou wilt ſay perchaunce, that there is no cōpariſon betwixt the Iewes, playnelie denying Chriſt,The papiſtes denye Chriſt, as well as the Iewes do. and the papiſtes whiche do confeſſe him: and therupon wilt conclude, that the papiſtical Concils may not ſo eaſilie erre, as thoſe whiche were holdē of the Iewes at Ieruſalem, againſte the Apoſtels and their doctrine. As concerninge their Concils, I may not anſwere

now: for that were an infinite worke to repeate all their abſurdities. Yf any mā wolde but once reade them ouer, he ſholde nede no other perſuaſion to abhorre them, and to cōfeſſe this my ſaying moſt true in all the Concils holden by the Romiſhe Antichriſte.The papiſtes are more blaſphemous then the Iewes. But to cō
               pare them with the Iewes in denying of Chriſte, thou ſhalt proue them more blaſphemous. For the Iewes after a ſorte did cōfeſſe their Chriſt and Meſsias in wayting for him dayly to delyuer them, and ſaue them from the miſerie wherin they were, and now are, ād from al their enimies accordinge as God promiſed: but when they wolde not acknolledge him, whom their fathers did perſecute and crucifie, and whom the Apoſtels taught to be riſen and aſcended, they playnlie denied Chriſte. They beleued that he ſhulde be their Captayne and delyuerer, but after an other ſorte, then by his deathe and paſsion: and to an other ende, then to ſuffer in this worlde the ſhame of the Croſſe.
            Euenſo do the papiſtes confeſſe Chriſte, but in effecte withe the Iewes

deny him.The papiſtes cōfeſſe Chriſt, but in effect deny him. They confeſſe Chriſte whiche is come in the fleſhe, borne of the virgin Marie, crucified for the ſynnes of the worlde, &amp;c. Whiche all hitherunto is wel, and agreethe with vs. But for as muche as they are not with him contented, but wil haue an other Chriſte beſides him:1. Tim. 2 they are manifeſt deniers of Chriſte. For (as writethe the Apoſtel) There is but one God, one Mediator betwixt God and man, the man Ieſus Chriſte, whiche gaue him ſelfe to be the redemption for all. Now when the papiſtes beleue not onlie in this Chriſte and Sauiour,The papiſtes cōfeſſe Chriſte to be here in the world in the forme of brad a dead God not able to do anye thinge. which came in the fleſhe, and was borne of the virgine, but alſo in that Chriſte, whom they imagine to come, and to be in the worlde in the forme of bread, and borne aboute with the handes of man, not able to go him ſelfe: when they beleue not onelie vpon Chriſte crucified, and hanged vpon the Croſſe, but in the coniured Idoll, hanging by a corde ouer the alter: not onlie in Chriſte glorified vpon the right hande of the father, who liuethe and reignethe for euer, but in

their rownde cake, which (they ſay) is conſecrated, when with out ſenſe and feeling it lieth cloſed in their box,The boxy mowly, wormy, muſty rotten and corrupted Christe. ſubiecte to mowleinge, wormes, and corruption, reſerued &amp; kept to be worſhipped as their God, but to their condemnation for euer. More ouer when they haue other aduocates then Chriſte, other ſacrifices for ſynne, other merites and means of ſaluation: it helpethe them no more to proue that they are Chriſtians, thus impudentlie denying him and his office, then it helpeth the Iewes, in ſaying they beleue in the true Meſsias to come, which is all readie come,The papiſtes vnder the name of Chriſtians worke treaſon agaynst Chriſt. and reueled to the world. Ye ſo muche the more is their condemnation, for that vnder the Name of Chriſte, whom they dare not deny, they worke preuie treaſon agaynſte him, to ſubuerte the truethe of his Goſpel, and whole fruite of his death and paſsion: which is our redemption from death, and hope of euerlaſting life, purchaſed by that perfecte oblation, which was offred once for all,
                  Hebr. 10.1. Ioh. 2. as a ſufficient ſacrifice for the ſynnes of the

the whole worlde.
         
         
            CHAP. III. 
            
               ¶What inconuenience had commē to the Churche of God, if the Apoſtels had ob
                     •
                  yed the commandement of the Concil, and what euills haue commen lately vpon England through the preaching of vnlawful obediēce and yelding to vngodly Rulers.
            
            
               LEt vs leaue the vngodlie papiſtes with their wicked decrees and Concils,The infinit ſlaughter of martyrs in Englande. as mē that paſſe the Iewes in all maner of wilful ſtubberneſſe and cruel perſecution of the trueth, as the horrible ſlaghter of thouſandes of martyrs, which with in theſe few yeres in Englande alone do witneſſe: and returne to the Apoſtels, Peter and Iohn, to examine what anſwere they framed to theſe men of auctoritie, and Rulers, gathered to gether of all ſortes, as you haue harde, as wel of the Cleargie as of the Laitie, of ſuche as thē had the onlie gouernement of Ieruſalem vnder the Romayns, to whom they were then tributaries,

which charge and threatning of the whole Concil, done with ſo great aduiſement and conſultation, oght not lightlie to be eſtemed, eſpeciallie, of the ſeruantes of God,We muſt not yelde in Gods cauſe, when man threatneth. and their ſubiects, as the Apoſtels then were. They were charged and threatned to preache no more in the Name of Chriſte crucified. An heauy commandement doutleſſe to Peter and Iohn, eſpeciallie if it might haue taken place: ſeing it was all together contrarie to their vocation and charge geuen vnto them by their maiſter Chriſt, to preache his Goſpell throughout all the worlde,
                  Luk. 24. act. 1. and to begyn at Ieruſalem, for which cauſe they were called and choſen from amongeſt all others, and had bene of longe tyme inſtructed of their maiſter Chriſt in the knowledge of all his holie Scriptures, ād repleniſhed with wonderful giftes of the holie Goſte, to cure all deſeaſes, to caſt out diuels, to drinke poyſon, to tread vpon ſerpentes, and to diſtribute the holye Spirit, and all thoſe to be as it were ſeales and cōfirmatiōs of their doctrine, whiche all had bene to no porpoſe, yf this commandement and threatninge

of the Magiſtrats ſhuld haue bene obeyed,Relenting of the miniſters moſte dangerous. &amp; the Apoſtels yelded to their auctoritie. Then the foundation of the Churche ſhuld haue ben ſhaken, and the whole aſſemble diſcouraged: for the two Chief Captayns gyuinge ouer, who durſte haue preſumed further?
            And truelie, if the Apoſtels at that tyme had bene no further inſtructed, then the moſte parte of men are in theſe our dayes, and eſpeciallie haue bene, and yet be in our miſerable countrie of Englande: they would haue bene in great perplexitie, and ſore afrayde to haue made this, or the like anſwere ſayng:we maye ſafely folowe the example of the Apoſtels aproued by the holy Gost. Iudge you whither it be lawful before God to obeye you, rather then God. For the moſte parte of men, yea and of thoſe whiche haue bene both learned and godlie, and haue geuen worthie teſtymonie of their profeſsion to the glorie of God: haue thoght and taught (by the permiſsion of God for our ſynnes) that it was not lawful in anie caſe to reſiſt and diſobeye the ſuperior powers:A dangerous doctrine. but rather to laye downe their heades, and ſubmitte them ſelues to all kindes of puniſhmentes and tyrannye,

thinkinge them ſelues ſufficientlie diſcharged before God of their vocation and duetie, hauing onlie the commandement of the ſuperiour power to the contrarie, were it neuer ſo vngodlie ād cleāe againſte all natural reaſon:
                  1. Cor. 3 Man can not diſpē
                  ce with that which God commandeth. wherby manye hauinge commandement to preache no more Ieſus chriſt to the people, without anie trouble of conſcience haue keapt ſilence, and thought thē ſelues ſufficientlie diſcharged: nether cō
               ſidering that they were made ſtewards of Godes holye myſteries, and that not at the appointment of man, or for them ſelues, but by the ordināce of our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, and to be faithful diſtributers to others. Nether yet markinge this preſent anſwere of Peter and Iohn, whom they might ſafely haue folowed with better aſſurance: who in ſuche caſe,Falſe brethern which betray God and his trueth in yelding to the papists. haue lefte this leſſon for all men, rather to obaye God then mā. Others, hearinge the Name of God blaſphemed by the falſe doctrine of the wicked and ſhaueling prieſtes, durſte not once open their mouthes to ſpeak one worde in their maiſters behalff and his infallible truethe: but ſtopt

theyr mouthes as dōme dogges, ād durſte not barke againſt the rauenīge wolff when they knew and ſaw him cōming. Many not minding to obiecte them ſelues to anie daunger, regardinge more their owne ſafetie, then the preſeruatiō of their flocke,No miniſter oght to flie and forſake his flocke, except he be perſecuted onely, and not his flocke. wolde not abide the wilde beaſte commyng, but moſte ſhamefullie fledde before the daunger came, ſhewing them ſelues playne hirelings, and no true paſtores: leauinge the ſelie ſhepe of God to be deuoured, and that becauſe they had entred in to the folde before to feede of the flocke, to eate the fleſhe, and deuoure the people of God as bread,
                  Pſal. 14. rather then to do their dueties.
            
               They which pleaſe man rather then obey God.But all theſe and ſuche like are here condemned and conuicted of euel, which fearing man more then God, gaue eare and obedience to man, rather then to God. Wherof, beſides the iuſte ſhame that came vpon them ſelues, and the diſpleaſure of God powred generally vpon all (for as muche as we all were betrayers of our maiſter, thoghe not all a like) iuſt occaſion of offence and of like diſobediēce to God, was miniſtred

to all ſorts of men, of what vocation ſo euer they were.we muſt obey the preachers onely whē they bring Gods worde. For when they ſawe the teachers and leaders of others to ſet vp obedience of man rather then of God, and the ſame confirmed by their owne example: thoſe whiche knewe no other, thoght it their parte to do the like alſo in their vocation and office. And ſuche as were playne enimies to God,The papiſtes laughe in their ſleues, when they ſee their wicked proceadinges promoted by vnlawfull obedience. the wicked papiſtes or diſſolute perſons, laughed in their ſleues: ſeing bothe them and their wicked proceadings therby promoted and furthered. Where as to defend their kyngdome of darckenes, ambitiō and idle belies, there is no kyng ſo godly, no contrey ſo peaceable, nor no kyngdome ſo ſtronge, which through their deuiliſhe entrepriſes and wicked perſuaſions, they haue not ſtudyed vtterly to ſubuert and deſtroy. As the example of that deſperat Moncke,A moncke who to poiſon king Iohn, wittingly and willingly poyſoned him ſelf. O malicious deuil. Likewiſe the oration of that moſte traiterous and peſtilent Cardinal Pole,Cardinal Pole. doth yet witenes to all the papiſts ſhame and confuſion: wherin he goeth

about to perſwade the wicked Emperour rather to tourne his power ād armie agaīſt Kynge Hēry the eight ād Englād, this doggs owne cōtrey, thē againſt the infidels, Turckes, and Sarracenes: blaſphemouſlie termīg the worde of God ād Goſpel of ſaluation to be the Turckeſh ſede. O impudēt mouth: ô blaſphemous beaſt, which ſaiſt in thi heart, Ther is no God. And yet to all your ſhame ād vtter deſtructiō of your cōtrie, you haue receaued him as a God, whome before in your lawful kyngs dayes, you moſte iuſtely condemned as a traitour and very ſonne of Antichriſt. The Counſellers, whoſe office is to brydle the affectiōs of their Princes ād Gouuernours, in geuīg ſuch counſele as might promote the glorie of God, ād the welthe of their cōtrie by this perſuaſion of obediēce, haue hitherto ſought, and yet apearinglie do, how to accōpliſhe and ſatisfie the vngodly luſtes of their vngodlie ād vnlawful Gouerneſſe, wicked Ieſabel: who for our ſynnes, contrarie to nature and the manyfeſte worde of God, is ſuffred to raigne ouer vs in Goddes furie, ād haue therby moſte wickedlie betrayed Chriſte, their countrie, and thē ſelues (ſo muche

as lieth in thē) to become ſlaues to a ſtrange and foren nation, the prowde Spaniards. The Nobles alſo, which (thoghe vnworthilie wil be ſo called) hearing no other preaching,To obey is good, but whome, wherin, ād howe farre, ought to be cōſidered but that they muſt obeye their Prince, neither knowing whō, wherin, nor how farre, haue in like maner, as men diſguiſed vpon a ſtage, turned their nobilite to open ſhame amongeſt all nations, whiche now beholde their follie, and wōder ther at: ſeinge they are made inſtrumētes of impietie, and deſtroyers of their natiue countrie, which firſte were ordayned in Realmes to ſtande in defence of trewe religion, lawes, and welth of their nation, and to be a ſhylde (to their power) agaynſt their enimies in tyme of warre, and a brydel at home to their Princes in tyme of peace: neither to ſuffer them in this ſorte to rage agaynſt God, and vtterlie to conteme the holſome lawes of the Realme, to ſatisfie their filthie luſte and vayne glorie, nor ſo cruelie to murther, and agaynſt nature to deuoure the people of God, their ſubiects, whom they are charged by their office to ſuccoure and defende, and haue therfore a

feareful compt to make for donige the contrarie.
            
               The iuſtices &amp; other vnder officers.The Iuſtices likewiſe in Townes and Cities, as Maieres, Shryffs, Baylyfes, Conſtables, Iealers and all ſuche inferior officers, folowing the ſame exſample of vnlawful obedience, whoſe office and charge it is to miniſter iuſtice whithout reſpecte of perſōs,Officers ād Iudges degenerat. to defende the ſymple and innocēt, and to puniſhe all tranſgreſſors and malefactors, blaſphemours of Goddes holie Name, violent oppreſſers of innocentes, as be the bloudthurſtie papiſtes: are nowe become miniſters of iniuſtice, and tyranny, made tormentours of their owne naturall Countrye men, moſt blouddie butchers of their brethren, and mercileſſe murtherers of the childrē of God: and that in ſuche cruel ſorte, as neuer was hearde of before ſince the deathe of Chriſte, where anie profeſsion of his Name hathe bene. In ſo muche that they are made a ſpectacle and gaſinge-ſtock to all countries and nations, amongeſt whom is anie feare of God or ciuile policie, whiche woulde not haue beleued it to be poſsible, if their eares

and eyes were not this day ſufficient wittneſſes. For to vnderſtand that the papiſtes were cruell butchers and vnſatiable bloudſuckers,The papiſtes naturally thurſt for bloud. had bene no newes at all, they haue bene ſuch from the beginninge. But when they bothe heare and ſee thoſe that profeſſe the Goſpel, and woulde be counted Chriſtes ſhepe,Fals Goſpelers, ſlaues vnto papiſtes. turned for feare of diſpleaſure, or loſinge of their office in to the nature of bloudthurſtie woulues, to execute agaynſt God and their conſcience, the vngodlie commandements of the papiſtes: to be at commandement, not onlie to their vnlawful Quene, but alſo to euery ſhauen Sir Iohn, to imbrue their handes with them in innocent bloude: this makethe all men to wonder and be aſtoniſhed.
            To conclude,The cōmon people. the reſidue of the comon people, ſeing their ſuperiours of all degrees ād eſtates, by whom they ſhulde be gouerned with godlie lawes, and to whom they ought obedience in the feare of God onelie, thus couardly to forſake their obedience to God, and vtterlie contemne the office wherwith he had charged them, to ſatisfie the vnlawful

commandements of their wilful Gouerneſſe: thinke it in no caſe their parte to deny to her like obedience: but with bodies and goodes,Men that do againſt their conſcience and Godes worde. at home ād abrode, to fulfill and mayntayne her will ād tyranny, not withſtandinge their owne conſcience doth condemne thē, and the worde of God dothe playnelie teſtifie, that it is euell and vngodlie which they are commanded to do. Being deceaued by miſunderſtanding this place of Paule and ſuch like:
                  Rom. 13. It behoueth euery ſoule to be ſubiecte to ſuperior powers, becauſe there is no power but of God. For the powers that are, be ordinances of God: ād therfore he that reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinaunce of God.
            But how litle this and other like obiectiōs make for their purpoſe, we ſhall God willinge vnderſtande, after that we haue better examined this preſent anſwere of Peter and Iohn: who are not cō
               trarie to Paul, nor Paul to them, rightly cōſidered▪ For thoghe this anſwere was made of Peter ād Iohn in their owne cauſe to the Magieſtrates ād Rulers of Ieruſalem: yet is it no leſſe generall then the ſaynge of. S. Paule: and partayneth to al

conditions of men, as wel Magieſtrates and Rulers, as inferior perſons and ſubiectes: teaching them bothe their office moſte rightlie: the one, what to commande, and how to rule: the other, whom to obeye, and wherin to be ſubiecte, as in their places folowinge ſhall euidentlie appeare.
         
         
            CHAP. IIII. 
            
               The trueth of this anſwere was ſo ſenſible, that the verie aduerſaries coulde not withſtand it.
            
            
               ANd firſte to returne to the anſwere,The enemies of God cā not denye this anſwere to be treue. we may be aſſured that it is certayne ād an vndouted true the, that in all things, and of all men, ād in all places, God is to be obeyed before mē. In ſo muche as the Apoſtels were not afrayed to cōmite the iudgement therof vnto their extreame enemies: whom they knewe right well, would haue geuen contrarie ſentence, if their anſwere had not bene withe out all controuerſie. As thoghe they would haue ſayed. After that we haue bene

charged with this office to preache to all people and nations, ād that by God him ſelffe, to whom all powers are ſubiecte, and all men are bownd to obeye, whoſe iudgementes none can eſcape, and whoſe wrathe no fleſhe is able to abyde:
                  Pſal. 104. whiche with the breathe of his mouthe, moueth the heauens, and makethe the mightie mountaynes to ſhake and tremble, and dryueth all powers (be they neuer ſo ſtronge) to duſt ād powder. We are contēted to make you iudges, which charge vs to the contrarie: whither this dreadful God may approue our doings in obeyēge you beīg men, and his creatures, yea earthe, verie duſt and aſſhes in compariſon of his Maieſtie? Whither man, of what auctoritie ſo euer he be, is able to diſcharge vs in the preſence of oure God, if in holding our peace at your commandement,Preachers muſt preach Chriſte in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon. we tranſgreſſe the expreſſe commandemēt of God? That is, not to preache Ieſus Chriſt crucified: who hathe choſē vs to the ſame ēd, indued vs with knowledge, reuealed vnto vs his ſecret counſels, the myſterie of our redemption, and armed vs with all giftes

of the holie Goſt, neceſſarie for the accompliſhement of ſo waightie an entrepriſe. We nede not herein to vſe many wordes or reaſons: nor to deſier anie arbiters to define this matter: be you your ſelues iudges. Which kinde of ſpeaking, men commonlie vſe, when the matter is euident and out of doubte, knowen to all men, be they of neuer ſo ſlender iudgement, and nede no further reaſons, or Scriptures to proue it. The like kinde of reaſoninge, the Apoſtle vſeth agaynſt the Corinthians:1. Cor. 11. who permitted their wemē to praye bareheaded in the Congregation, which he condemned as an vndecent cuſtome, not becommyng the Sayncts of God. For amongeſt other reaſons, he likewiſe makethe them ſelues iudges in the matter, ſayeng: Iudge ye amonge your ſelues, whither it be cumlie for a womā to praye bareheaded in the Congregation. Cōcludinge, that verie nature dothe teache the contrarye. In like maner this anſwere is ſo true and ſenſible (that rather God is to be obeyed then man) that there cā be none ſo malitious or ignorante, whom verie nature will not

compel to confeſſe it, if he had no further knowledge. Nether had theſe men, for all their great a doo, lōge conſultacion, hie learninge and wiſdome (deſierous alſo to take occaſion agaynſt the Apoſtels) anie thinge to ſaye for the cō
               trary. But as Gods enemies are accuſtomed, when their mouthes are ſtopt, either with raylinges, or threatnings, to expreſſe their rage: ſo did they with Peter &amp; Iohn,They ſhuld not ſo haue eſcaped if they had bene befor our cruell Counſelors Phariſies and Hypocrits of Englande. dimitting them at the laſt with bitter wordes and menaces: and they departed notwithſtandinge from the Concile, by the means of this anſwere, conquerours.
         
         
            CHAP. V. 
            
               ¶To obeye man in anie thinge agaynſt God, is Vnlawfull ind playne diſobedience.
            
            NOw for as muche as we are aſſured of the trueth ād certantie of their anſwere,what things are to be conſidered. wherof none can iuſtlie doute: let vs ſomewhat further conſider what thinges are prīcipallie here in conteyned. Firſt we maye hereof iuſtlie conclude, that to obeye man in anie thinge contrary to God, or his precepts thoghe he be in hieſt auctoritie, or neuer

ſo orderly called there vnto (as theſe men, wherof Luke ſpeaketh, were) is no obedience at all, but diſobedience.
            Secondlie, that it is not a ſufficient diſcharge for vs before God, whē we denye to accōplyſhe their vnlawful demā
               des and threatnings, except we do the cōtrarie euery man in his vocation and office, as occaſion is offred, and as his power will ſerue. Whiche thīges playnlie vnderſtāde, as they ſhal geue a clere light in this controuerſie: ſo do I not doute by this preſent anſwere and facte of Peter and Iohn, to proue moſte manifeſtlie, that althoghe we were deſtitute of other examples, yet this might appeare ſufficient. As touchinge the firſte,Obedience against God is diſobedience, that there is no obedience agaynſt God which is not playne diſobedience: the Apoſtles ſay, Iudge you whither it be right or iuſt in Godds ſight to obeye you rather thē God: which is as muche as thei would ſaye, It is not iuſte nor lawful. Thē if it be not lawful and iuſt in Goddes ſight, who iudgeth things truelie ād as thei be in dede, it muſt nedes folowe that all maner of obediēce agaynſt God ād his worde, is playne diſobediēce, and

the workers therof likewiſe condemned as rebells. Why? Bycauſe it is vniuſt and vnlawfull before God: And all true obedience is lawful, which muſt not be meaſured by the will of mā, but by the iuſte Lawes and ordinances of the liuinge Lorde.what God once willith in his Law to be done or not to be done that cā no man diſpence with be it neuer ſo ſmal in the ſight of man. So that after God hathe once pronounced anie thinge that he would haue done, either in his Lawe or otherwiſe: there is no man that may or can diſpence therwith, ſeeme it of neuer ſo litle importance in the iudgement of men. He that commandeth the contrarie, is a rebell: and he that obeyeth likewiſe. Neither dothe this appertayne to the Apoſtles and miniſters onlie in their office, but is a generall argument for all ſortes, eſtates, and degrees of men: for as muche as God hathe like auctoritie of all, and all owe vnto him firſt and principall obedience: and ſecondly vnto men for him, and in him onlie: except they wil be enimies to God, and deny him to be their Lorde. For ſo muche it is in effecte, when we preferre men to God, obedience to man, before the obedience to God. It is not the auctoritie of the Prince, or the feare of his

puniſhmēt, that cā excuſe in his preſence: who cōmādeth his people generalie,
                  Deu. 4. high and lowe, riche and poore, man ād womā, to heare his voyce, and to obſerue his ſtatutes. Nether to declyne vpon the right hand, nor vpon the lefte: nether to adde anie thinge therto, or to take anie thinge from it: but to do that onlie, whiche the liuinge Lorde commā
               deth. And if we be the ſhepe of the Lordes foulde, it is not ſufficiēt for vs to heare the voyce of our paſtor, ād to folowe him, except we alſo deny to heare, muche more to folowe anie other: that is, which calleth not with the voyce of the true paſtor.
                  Ioh. 10. And as there ought to be no creature of like auctoritie amongeſt vs, as our ſoueraygne Lorde and God, whoſe creatures we be, and the workemanſhip of his owne hādes: euen ſo, there is none like to him in dignitie, or may be cōpared to him in power, none like to him in riches, or ſo able to rewarde his ſubiectes, beinge Lorde of heauē and earthe, diſpoſer of all things preſent and to come: diſtributer not onlie of all corporall and earthlie bleſſings to thoſe that feare and ſerue him:

but alſo powreth vpon them all ſpirituall and heauenlie graces in great aboundance. Moreouer, as by his auctoritie, power, dignitie, riches and liberalitie, he maye of right demande of vs obedience: ſo muſt we perſuade our ſelues in not rēdring the ſame to him willinglie, that none cā deliuer vs from his horrible puniſhementes and deſtruction, whiche he threatneth vpon all ſuch as wilfully trangreſſe his holie preceptes,Deu. 28, and .30. No cōmandement ſhall excuſe vs in the daye of vengeance. ād declyne from his Lawes. Nether wil he regarde by what means, or by whoſe cōmandement we tranſgreſſe his lawes. For that can be no excuſe for vs, thoghe he be Kinge, Quene, or Emperour that commandeth or threatneth vs. For what is kinge, Quene, or Emperour compared to God? Is the puniſhement of earthe,
                  Eſai. 2. aſhes, of vile man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrilles, more to be feared then the plages of God, who hath power both of body and ſoule to deſtroye thē euerlaſtingly? Was it any earthly power that broght the waters vpon the vniuerſall worlde,
                  Gen. 7 and drowned all mankinde for ſynne, viii perſons excepted? Did man deſtroye Sodome and Gomorrhe

with fier and brymſtone?
                  Gen. 14. Exod. 3 4.5.6.14. Came the plages of Egypt, the drowninge of Pharao, the ouertrow of the Cananites, the ſubuerſion of Ieruſalem, by the power of man? If theſe be the workes of man and not of God, feare man and not God:
                  Amos 3. but if there be none of theſe euells which cometh vpon anie Citie, or contrie, wherof the Lorde is not the worker: beware that the feare of mans puniſhment, cauſe thee not to fall in to the handes of this mightie reuēger, whiche is an horrible thinge, as the Apoſtle writeth.
                  Heb. 13. Princes therfore, and all powers vpon thee arth, are not to be compared vnto God, whoſe Lieutenants onlie they ſhuld be, and are no longer then he wil, in whoſe handes their hartes are,
                  Pro. 21. to moue and turne at his pleaſure. And for that cauſe it is their duetie to ſeke all means poſsible, wherbie the glorie of God might be aduanced, by whom they are them ſelues ſo highlie exalted aboue their brethern, and in no cauſe to miniſter occaſion of rebellion agaynſt his mightie Maieſtie: but rather to be examples to others (ouer whom they are conſtitute) of all Godlie liffe and lawfull obedience.

In conſideration wherof, God him ſelfe appoyntīg his people to haue a kinge, which, when they ſhulde come in to the lande of promeſſe (for that was the firſt promotion that God ordeyned amongeſt his people,what maner of man the Lorde woulde haue choſen kinge. Deut. 17.
                which yet came not to ſuche pride to deſire an Emperour) did with great circumſpection, as well appoynt them what maner of man they ſhulde choſe, as the lawes by the whiche he ſhuld rule others, and be obeyed of them. When thou commeſt (ſaithe the Lorde by Moyſes) to the lande which thy Lorde geueth thee, and ſhalt poſſeſſe it, thou ſhalt with out doute, put or conſtitute a kinge to thee: but whō thy Lorde thy God ſhall choſe. Moreouer he ſaith, from the middle of thy brethern ſhalt thow appoynt a Kīge ouer thee. For thou mayſt not appoynt a ſtrāger, which is not thy brother. Which lawe, as it proceaded from the wiſedome of God, who thoght it neceſſarie for his people: euen ſo is our miſerable ignorance and vnſpeakeable ingratitude to be lamented, which nether do vnderſtand the goodneſſe of God in theſe lawes, not yet will voucheſaffe to conſult

with his heauēly wiſedome: all men rather ſckinge to choſe and procure them ſelues Princes and kinges after their owne phātaſie, ād by vngodlie fetches and policies, then to folowe the appoyntment of the Almightie: preferringe theyr owne wittes to the wiſedome of God, whiche neuer fayleth them that folowe it. In compariſon of whom all others at lengh, ſhall ſhewe them ſelues to be meere fooles.Gods Lawes muſt diligentlie be folowed in election of kinges ād Rulers and not mans phā
                  taſie. Yf we wilbe the people of God, let vs then ſearche and diligentlie folowe the Lawes of God, eſpeciallie in ſo weightie matters, as the election of kinges and Princes, by whom Realmes and nations are either preſerued if they be Godlie, or vtterly diſtroyed, and ſhamefullie oppreſſed if they be vngodlie. The firſt poynt or cautiō that God requireth of his people to obſerue, is,The firſte note and obſeruatiō in choſinge of a kynge Ezechi. 20
                that they choſe ſuche a kinge, as the Lorde dothe appoynt, and not as they phantaſie. And what one is he or how ſhuld he be knowē? The people of Iſrael (you will ſaie) had their kī
               ges appoynted them by the mouthe of God and anoynted of his Prophets: as

Dauid, and his ſonne Salomon. For Saule, thoghe he was appoynted ād anoyeted in Goddes furie, yet was he not of the Lordes choſinge after this meaning of Moyſes, who willethe them to appoynte a kinge that the Lorde ſhal choſe: to wit, of his fauour and goodneſſe, ſuche a one as ſhall obſerue the Lawes folowing,Two notes to knowe whether a kinge be choſen of God or no as we ſhall ſee here after. Two means had the Iſraelites to knowe their kinge, whither he was of God electe or no. The firſte, by the expreſſe commandement and promeſſe made to ſome eſpeciall man, wherof they neded not to doute: as was made to Dauid, ād to Salomō his ſonne expreſſlie. The ſecōde is by his worde, which he hathe now left to all men to be the ordinarie means to reueale his will and appoyntment. Which (if we vnfaynedly folowe in our doings) we nede no more to doute, then if God ſhulde now ſpeake vnto vs out of the heauens, as then he did to the Iſraelites. The worde then geueth vs theſe notes to know whither he be of God or not, whom we woulde choſe for our kinge. Firſte (as was ſayd) if he

be a man that hathe the feare of God before his eyes, and zeluſlye with Dauid, and Ioſias, dothe ſtudie to ſet forthe the ſame, hatinge vnfaynedlie al papiſtrie and idolatrie. For this cauſe God willeth that he ſhuld be choſen from amongeſte his brethern, and ſhulde be no ſtranger: bycauſe ſuche then had not the feare of God, but were idolaters, to whom no promeſſe of anie kingdome was made, and who alſo would leade the people to idolatrie. Alſo in that his exerciſe is appoynted,None oght to be choſen a kinge or Ruler but ſuch as wil maintaine and promote Godes Lawes. The ſecōd note why kinges ar choſen frō amongeſt their brethern. the worde, Lawes &amp; ſtatutes of God, it is manifeſte that he is not choſen of God, except he be ſuch a one: and oght not to be anoynted or elected as their kinge and Gouernour, what title or right ſo euer he ſeeme to haue therūto, by ciuile policie, except he be a promoter &amp; ſetter forthe of Godds Lawes and glorie, for whiche cauſe chieſlie, this office was ordeyned.
            The nexte rule to be obſerued is, that he ſhulde be one of their brethern, meaninge of the Iſraelits: partlie to exclude the oppreſsion and

idolatrie, whiche commeth in by ſtrangers, as our Contrie now is an example: and partlye, for that ſtrangers cannot beare ſuch a natural zeale to ſtraunge realmes and peoples, as become the brethern:The gouernement of women is againſt nature, and Gods ordinance. but chieflie to auoyde that monſter in nature, and diſordre amongeſt men, whiche is the Empire ād gouernement of a woman, ſayinge expreſlie: From the myddle of thy brethren ſhalt thou choſe thee a kinge, and not amongiſt thy ſiſters. For God is not contrarie to him ſelf,
                  Gen. 3. whiche at the begynninge appoynted the woman to be in ſubiection to her houſbande, and the man to be head of the woman (as ſaithe the Apoſtle) who wil not permitte ſo muche to the womā,1. Cor. 14 1. Tim. 2. as to ſpeake in the Aſſemblie of men, mucheleſſe to be Ruler of a Realme or nation. Yf women be not permitted by Ciuile policies to rule in inferior offices, to be Coūſellours, Pears of a realme,women by ciuell police are excluded frōe all offices in a comon welth. Iuſtices, Shireffs, Bay liues and ſuch like: I make your ſelues iudges, whither it be mete for them to gouerne whole Realmes and natiōs?
            If the worde of God can not perſuade

you, by which ſhe is made ſubiect to her houſbande, muche more to the Counſelle and auctoritie of an whole realme, which worde alſo appoynteth your kinges to be choſen from amonge their brethern, and not from their ſiſters: who are forbidden as perſons vnmete to ſpeake in a Congregacion▪ be you your ſelues iudges, and let nature teache you the abſurditie therof.
            And thus muche haue I of pourpoſe noted in this matter, to let you ſee to all our ſhames, how farre ye haue bene led beſydes your commun ſenſes and the manifeſt worde of God, in electing,Wincheſter proueth her a baſtard in his boke de Vera obedientia, and Bōner alſo in the preface of the ſame boke. kyng Edward the VI.
                anoynting, and crowninge a woman to be your Quene ād Gouerneſſe, and ſhe in verie dede a baſtarde, and vnlawfully begotten. But beit that ſhe were no baſtarde, but the kinges daughter as lawfullie begotten as was her ſiſter, that Godlie Lady, ād meke Lambe, voyde of all Spaniſhe pride, and ſtrange bloude: yet in the ſickneſſe, and at the deathe of our lawfull Prince of Godlie memorie kynge Edwarde the ſixt, this ſhulde not haue bene your

firſte counſele or queſtion, who ſhulde be your Quene, what womā you ſhul de crowne, if you had bene preferrers of Goddes glorie, and wiſe coūſelours, or naturallie affected towardes your countrie. But firſte and principallie, who had bene moſte meeteſt amengeſt your, brethern to haue had the gouernement ouer you, and the whole gouernement of the realme, to rule them carefullie in the feare of God,They haue now plentie of both ſortes. and to preſerue them agaynſt all oppreſsion of inwarde tyrants and outwarde enemies. Wherbie you might haue bene aſſured to eſkape all this miſerable &amp; vnſpeakable diſordre, and ſhamefull confuſion, whiche now by contrarie counſele is broght worthely vpon vs. I knowe ye will ſaye, the Crowne is not intayled to the heyre males onelie, but appartaynethe aſwel to the daughters:The title of the Crowne belongeth onely by Gods worde, to the heyres males. and therfore by the Lawes of the Realme, you coulde not otherwiſe do. But yf it be true, yet miſerable is this anſwere of ſuche as had ſo longe tyme profeſſed the Goſpel, and the lyuelie worde of God. Yf it had bene made of pagās and heathens, whiche knew not God by his

worde, it might better haue bene borne with all. But amōgeſt them that beare the Name of Godds people, with whō his Lawes ſhulde haue chief auctoritie: this anſwere is not tollerable to make the conſtant and vndouted Lawe of God, whiche oght to be the lyne of all ordinaunces, to geue place to the vayne and vngodlie decrees of men, as experience hath now taught you. Moreouer, in anoynting her as if ſhe had bene a man, was no leſſe abſurditie, vſinge thervnto ſuche greaſinges ād ſhā
               leſſe Ceremonies, ād that in the face of all the people: as thoghe Moyſes lawe yet were in force,Youre owne Lawes dothe not prefer abaſtard to her that is lauful begotten▪
                and Chriſt our Sauiour not comē: which hath put an end to all ſuche outwarde Ceremonies: whoſe annoyntings were ſpirituall. For as he was repleniſhed with all graces of the holie Goſt, and that with out meaſure, and aboue all his felows, kings, Prieſts, and Prophetes: ſo hathe he left no other annoyntinge to be vſed of his ſeruaunts: but of the ſame ſorte, that is,
                  Heb. 1. Pſal. 45. ſpirituall. And yf Moyſes with his Ceremonies were now in full auctoritie, as he was before Chriſte: Yet were it

not lawful by him to anoynte anie woman,
                  Leuit. 8. 1. Sam. 15. 1 Reg. 19 to ani maner of office or dignitie, ſeing that this Ceremonie was neuer appoynted to anie other but onelie to Prieſts, kinges, and Prophetes. How durſte you then be ſo bolde and impudent ô Papiſts, (for this was your entrepriſe) to tranſgreſſe the order of God in the Lawe of Moyſes by anoyntīge a womā? And alſo to contemne the libertie of the Goſpell, in reducinge and bringing agayn the Iewiſhe Ceremonies, from whiche by Chriſte we are delyuered? But it is no maruell if you be all waies like your ſelues, ſtubberne and rebellious enimies to God and contemners of Chriſte. And therfore leauinge you to your ſelues, we will retourne to Goddes appoynted limites in his Lawe, for the lawfull election of kinges and Princes. Ye haue hearde the two firſte cautions or rules, that is, how he muſte be of Godds appoyntment, and not of mans▪
               The thirde rule to be obſerued in electing of kinges. And alſo from amongeſt your brethren and not of your ſiſters, and why. The thirde caution that God ſpecifieth in this election is, that he be none ſuch as hath great nomber

of horſes: meaning, as truſteth in his owne power, and preparation of all thinges, for defence of him ſelfe, ād to ouercome his enemies. For vnder this name of horſes, he comprehendeth all ingeynes and furniture of warre: ſuche a one, as truſteth in them, and makethe not God his arme and bockler, with faitheful Dauid, is not meete to be kinge of the Lordes people.
                  Pſal. 52.
            
            For by ſuch means ſhulde they be broght to Egypte agayne, to their olde miſerie and ſlauerie, if they delited in their horſes, from whence the Lorde woulde haue them kepte, and not in anie caſe to returne. As no doute, he woulde haue had vs miſerable Engliſhe men, warelie to haue kepte vs in that libertie of Ieſus Chriſte and our conſciences, wherin ſo mercifullie he had broght vs: and not by placeinge an infidel woman ouer vs, to returne to our olde vomite, muche more viler thē the ſlauerie of Egypte, I meane the ſeruitude of that Romiſhe Antichriſte.What other notes God geueth to choſe by.
            
            Other obſeruations he geueth alſo, not to ſeke manie wiues, nor to heape vp muche golde: but chiflie that he haue

an example of Goddes Lawes preſcribed vnto him, to reade in them all the dayes of his life, that he maye learne to feare the Lorde and to keepe his cō
               mandements, and not to lifte him ſelf vp aboue his brethren: meaning, he ſhulde rule with all holyneſſe and humbleneſſe, as did Moyſes and Dauid. And therby, dothe God promiſſe that his dayes, and the dayes of his children ſhall be prolonged in the middle of Iſraell.
            Of the whiche we may iuſtlie conclude, that by the ordinance of God, no other kinges or Rulers, oght to be choſen to rule ouer vs, but ſuche as will ſeeke his honor and glorie, and will commaunde and do nothing contrarie to his Lawe.As the kings charge is greater, ſo is he more bonde to God to performe the ſame. Wherewith they are no leſſe, ye muche more charged, then the common people: becauſe their charge is double: that is, not onelie to feare God them ſelues, but to ſee that their people feare him alſo, to whom they owe in that caſe all humble obedience and reuerence. For they be (as was ſayed) Goddes ſubiectes and Lieutenantes, for whoſe cauſe they muſt be reuerenced, doinge their duetie. But if they will

abuſe his power, liftinge them ſelues aboue God and aboue their brethern, to drawe them to idolatrie, and to oppreſſe them, and their contrie: then are they nomore to be obeyed in any commandements tending to that ende: but to be cōtemned as vile Sergeantes in compariſon of the high Iudge and Magiſtrate, who oght to do nothing, but as he is commaunded to do by the Iudge ād ſuperior power according to the lawe. Other wiſe, if he lift him ſelfe aboue the chief Iudge, lokyng to be honored and obeyed more then he: who would not abhorre ſuche a Sergeant, ād not onelie to withſtande his cōmandement, but to accuſe him as a rebellious traytor, and baniſhe him from a mongeſt them? And yet here is but rebellion agaynſt man, who is but mortall. What oght we thē to do vnto that kinge or Prince, that lifteth him ſelfe vp agaynſt the Maieſtie of God,If it be heynous to diſobey mā, much more God the Lorde of al thinges. who is immortal, to whome belongeth all power, dominion and honor? Is he anie more in compariſon of God, then the Sergeant in reſpecte of the Iudge? Shall the Sergeant be puniſhed as a traytor, and this man honored as a kinge, which doth no

parte of the office therunto belonginge? Or rather is not his crime and treaſon greater, and deſeruith ſo muche more, as God is more excellent, compared to anie worldlie power, then is anie kinge or Prince compared to the moſte vileſte Sergeant?
            Moreouer, whence hathe he this honor? Of him ſelfe? Is anie man naturallie borne a kinge, Or hathe he it of God? And if of God, wherto, but to vſe it with God, ād not agaynſte him. Seing then it is not iuſte in Goddes ſight to obeye man rather then God: neither that their is anie diſpenſacion of man that cā diſpēce with his holie cōmandements,
                  Kinges oght to rule in Gods feare with him ād not againſte him.
                  To obey a wicked Prince in his wickednes is plaine diſobedience to God.
                neither the auctoritie of Prince, nor feare of puniſhment can excuſe vs. Seing alſo, that kinges are inſtitute to rule in Goddes feare and Lawes, as ſubiectes and Sergeants to God, and not agaynſte his Lawes, and aboue him: it muſte nedes followe (as we firſte ſayed) that all obedience geuen to ſuche, wicked Princes agaynſte God, is playne rebellion in his iudgemente. And in that caſe to obeye God, and diſobeye man, is true obedience, how ſo euer the

worlde iudgeth. For as none will condemne Peter and Iohn of diſobedience, becauſe they woulde not herein obeye their ordynarie Magiſtrates: nomore will anie which haue right iudgement, condemne the like reſiſtance in others, which alike is lawfull to all.
            Or ells ſhulde the Iſraelites be excuſed,1. king. 1. by cauſe they obeyed their wicked kinge Ieroboam in worſhippinge his calues in Dan, and Bethel.
            Then ſhuld that cruell butcher Doeg,1. Sam. 22 in killinge Ahimalech with LXXXV Prieſts or Leuites, and the whole towne of Nob, at the commandement of vngodlie kinge Saul,Mat. 2. They will make all theſe blāles (the papiſtes are 
                     •
                  o impudēt) rather thē they will ſeme to offende. Mat. 27.
                haue bene preferred to the reſte of all his ſeruantes and ſouldiars. And the ſouldiars alſo of cruell Herode ſhuld be blameleſſe in murtherīg ād ſheading the bloude of ſo many infantes in Bethlehem at Herods commandement. Then ſhulde the wicked Iewes be gyltleſſe of Chriſtes deathe ād his Prophets, whom they conſented to murther by the parſuaſion of their Rulers. And the counterfayte Chriſtians this day, which euerie where (but eſpeciallie in our miſerable countrie) impriſon,

famiſhe, murther, hange, and burne their owne countriemen, and deare children of God, at the commandement of furious Ieſabel, and her falſe Prieſtes and Prophetes, the blouddie Biſſhopps and ſhauelynges, ſhulde be giltleſſe in all their doinges. But all theſe doth God (who is a Ielious ād righteous God, and cannot abide his honor to be geuen to any other,
                  Exod. 20. Pſalm 9. Gen. 4. nor ſuffer the bloude of the innocent longe to crie vnto him for vengeance) condemne as blaſphemers, idolatres, and cruell murtherers: which ſaithe: Thou ſhalt haue no other Goddes but me. Thou ſhalt not kill. And if God dothe make this, diſobedience (as thou mayſt playnely ſee) what commandement of man can aulter his ſentence, before whom there is no obedience in euil thinges? Yea, if the whole multitude, from the hieſt to the loweſt, wolde agree and conſent to do euel,The commandemēt of the Prince ſhall not excuſe thee in euill doyng. yet muſte not thou followe them ſaith the Lorde. For if thou do (notwithſtanding the commandement of thy Prince, or example of all others) thou art with them a rebell, and a rebell agaynſt thy Lorde and God: from whoſe

wrathe and heauie indignation, no man can defende thee in the dreadfull daie of his viſitacion, which is at hande.
         
         
            CHAP. VI. 
            
               How it is not inough to denye wicked commandemēts of all kinde of Rulers, except we withſtand them alſo, euery man accordinge to his vocation, in doing the contrary.
            
            
               AS by this anſwere afore mentioned, we haue bene taught not to geue place to the vnlawfull commandemētes of Magiſtrates, in what auctoritie ſo euer they be, becauſe it is nothing but rebellion in the iudgement of God: euen ſo may we learne by the ſame anſwere and example of the Apoſtles, how God requiereth more at our handes, that is, to withſtande their preceptes, in doing the contrary: euery man accordinge to his office and eſtate wherin God hathe placed him. For as man thinketh him ſelf not fullie

obeyed,It is not inoughe not to do the wiked commaundement of a kynge, but alſo to do the contrarie. when we abſtayne from thoſe thinges which he forbiddeth, except moreouer we do the contrary, which he commandeth: euenſo may we muche more thinke, that God is not fullie obeyed, when we will not do the vngodlie commandements of men, except alſo we applye our ſelues with all diligence to do the contrary. So did Peter and Iohn make anſwere, denying to do as they were comaunded by the Magiſtrates. And as they denyed in wordes, ſo did they, ād the reſt of the Apoſtles in effecte, as the courſe of the hiſtorie doth witneſſe.
                  Act. 5. Who went all to gether to the Temple after they were dimiſſed, and preached openlie in the face of all the people Ieſus Chriſte crucified, not with ſtanding all the afore named threatnynges and menacinges, yea afterwarde, when they had bene impriſoned and then by the Angel of God deliuered, and whipped moſte vilely, as if they had bene ſlaues: yet were they nothing therby diſcouraged, but continued in one mynde and anſwere, ſayng as they did before with one voyce and conſent: God muſte be obeyed before

man, and boldlie preached their maiſter Chriſt, contemning all diſpleaſures which they for his Names ſake ſuſtened,
                  Act. 5. remembring well his ſure and confortable promeſſes who ſaid: Bleſſed are you when men reuile you and ſklander you,
                  Matth. 5. and ſpeake all euill againſte you, lying, for my ſake: be glad and reioce, for greate is your rewarde in the kingdome of heauen. For ſo did they perſecute the prophetes before you.
            Thus ſee we thē, how the trueth of this doctrine is not proued onely by the firſte examination of Peter and Iohn:Al the apoſtels to gether ſhewed the like conſtancie. but alſo confirmed the ſecond tyme by the reſt of all the Apoſtels agreeinge therin, and ſuffringe vile ſcourginge for the ſame: not onely boldlie affirminge it in the preſence of all the Magiſtrates at Ieruſalem, but as conſtantly approuinge it in their doinges: when contrarie to their commandemētes, they ceaſed not more diligentlye to publiſhe the doctrine of ſaluation: reioyſinge and prayſinge God, who had made them worthie to ſuffer for his Sōnes ſake, their Lorde and maiſter. O worthy and manful ſouldiars, O moſte truſtie and payneful

ſeruantes: neither feringe the prowde lokes and malitious threatninges of the whole Senate and power of Ieruſalem:No power can preuail againſt the faithfull. nor ſhrinking in their office, for all their cruel puniſhments. But the more they were forbidden, and the oftener they were puniſhed: the ſtouter, ſtronger, and mightier were they to fight againſt their enemes with the ſpiritual ſworde, wherwith they were charged in their maiſters quarel: beinge aſſured allwayes of this, that he who gaue thē auctoritie to preach, woulde geue thē ſtrengh alſo for the performance therof, as he had promeſed▪ ſayinge:
                  Mar 28. I will be with you to the end of the worlde. And he beinge with thē, (as the Apoſtle ſaithe) what ſhould they care who were againſt them?
                  Rom. 8· A worthie example ād mirour for all ſuch to beholde as are called of God to be his meſſengers and diſpoſers of his holie myſteries, how faithful they oght to be in the diſtribution of the ſame,1. Cor. 4. omitting no maner of occaſions, obeying no contrarie commandements, nor fearing the cruel threatninges of men.
            
               God hath geuen them the charge of moſte pretious iewels, and ineſtimable riches: not to be hid in a corner, or retayned with them ſelues:
                  Ephe. 3. but rather (as the Apoſtle exhorteth) to ſtyrre vp the gyfte of God, which is in them, and not to neglect it,1. Tim. 4. to preache the worde of God, and to be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, to conuince,2. Tim. 4. reproue, and exhorte with all ſoftneſſe and learning.
                  Ephe. 6. For this is that ſharpe and two edged ſworde wherewith God hath not onely armed them agaynſte their enimies:
                  Heb. 4. but to fight alſo manfullie for others agaynſt all powers worldly and ſpiritual, with this mightie and ſpiritual ſworde the worde of God.
            For otherwiſe, if Chriſte him ſelf had ceaſed to preache his Fathers will, for which cauſe partly he was ſent in to the worlde, for feare of threatninges, conſpiracies, commandements, and puniſhments of men: where had bene this comfortable doctrine of ſaluation? When ſhulde he haue ſuffred death, for our redemption and delyuerance?
            How ſhuld the Apoſtles and all

other faithfull martyrs, which by their deathes in all ages, haue geuen glorie to Chriſt,Chriſt diſobeyed wicked magiſtrates and ſo ſaued vs: but we obey vniuſt magiſtrates and deſtroy our ſelues. haue left behinde them ſo worthie monumentes, and comfortable writinges, beſides the notable examples of conſtancie in ſealinge vp their doctrine with the ſheading of their bloud, if they had yealded or ſhronke in executinge their office for feare of anie power. And in oure miſerable Countrie, where Antichriſt this day is againe for oure ſynnes exalted, if commandemēts of tyrantes ſhuld haue taken place in all men, as it did with many hirelinge preachers, ſome moſte ſhamefullie denying their Maiſter Chriſte, taking vpon them the marke of the beaſte, miniſtring poyſon for foode to their flocke, ſome in makinge a ſpoyle and praye of their flocke, and as cowardes takeyng them to their feete, leauing the poore lambes of God with out all comforte, to be deuoured of the wilde rauenous beaſtes▪ ſome alſo in playng on both partes with the halting Iſraelites,1. kin. 18. 2. Cor. 6. thinke to ſerue God and Baal: if in all others (I ſaie) as in theſe, the vngodlie decrees of men ſhulde haue

taken place: how coulde we haue had theſe worthie examples of ſo many hundreth martyrs, who haue glorified Chriſte moſte conſtantlie,Obedience to death. in offringe vp their liues as a moſte ſwete ſauour to the Lorde? And that of all ſortes of men and women, young and olde, riche and poore, learned and vnlearned, all being herein perſuaded (not able perchaunce to do anie more for the comfort of others, in ſo generall a defection from God) haue choſē rather with the loſſe of this corporall lyfe, to obeye God, then otherwiſe to lyue in welthe and obeye man. For the which, the Name of God be prayſed for euer, who ſtyrre vp our hartes by their examples, and prepare vs with the grace of his holie Spirite to the like conſtancie and obedience.
            Beſides this we learne by the cōmandements of God, that ſo oft as he forbiddeth any thing which he wolde not to be done, in the ſelf ſame,When God forbiddeth one thinge he commā
                  deth the contrarie. he commandeth vs the contrarie, as for example: Thow ſhalt not murther, Steale, Commit adultrie, or Beare falſe wittnes. It is not ynough to abſtaine frome theſe

thinges, neither is God therin fullie obeyed, except we do the contrarie, ſo oft as occaſion is miniſtred, that is, to ſaue, preſerue, and defende, as well the goodes as the perſones of our brethren and neghbours. And this is a certayne and general rule, not onely in theſe examples here named: but in all other preceptes whither they be of the Ten commandments, or anie other beſides conteyned in the Scriptures: that what ſo euer God forbiddeth anie man, in the ſame he is charged to do the contrarie according to his power, thogh all the worlde would ſtande agaynſt him. In confirmation wherof, let vs onelie conſider the notable example of the Godlie Prophet Daniel,
                  Dani. 6. who when he was commanded in the name of kinge Darius (by whome he had bene promoted to great honor,Daniel was no Engliſhe courtier: for he coulde not flatter. and of all other was in beſt fauor, and hieſt reputation with him) to aſke nothing of his God, or anie other for the ſpace of thirtie dayes, but onely of Darius his kinge, according to the decree made at the requeſte of his vngodlie counſel, purpoſlie

agaynſt Daniel, would not obeye the commandement, being not ignorant that it was a publike decree, which all (he onely excepte) obeyed. And alſo how death (and that moſte terrible, to be caſt among the hungry lyons) was appoynted for a puniſhment to the tranſgreſſors.Note this al ye Gentelmen ād Nobles of Inglande But Daniel not contented to do as he was commanded, did as he was accuſtomed, the contrary▪ not once, but thriſe euery day, tranſgreſsinge the kinges commā
               dement, prayinge to the liuinge Lorde his God. And to the intent it might be knowen abrode to al men, that he contemned this vngodly commandement,Daniel burned with the zeal of Gods glory and wolde not hide it he ſet open his windowes more then cuſtome, to the ītēt that all whiche wolde, might beholde his doing: ſo glad was he to be knowen to ſerue the true and mightie God. Here wolde our worldly wiſe men, no dout, condemne Daniel of raſhnes and follye in doing, more then was expedient. What nede he thus to prouoke the indignation of a Prince, who had power with a worde of his mouth to diſtroye

him? Yf he wolde not aſke anie thinge in the Name of Darius as others did,The coūſel of the wordlye diſſemblers yet might he haue abſtayned from praying to God for that ſpace. Was thirtie dayes ſo great a matter, that he might not abſtayne from praying to God, to gratifie therby his Prince to whome he was ſo muche bounde? And if he wolde nedes praye to God, could he not haue done it preuely and ſecretly? What nede he to ſet open his window in the ſight of al men? This was an open contempte of the kinges Maieſtie: this was a greater offence,Carnal Goſpelers are halters ō both ſides then the facte it ſelf. Thus wolde the politike ād worldlinges reaſon, as our carnall Goſpellers do daylie, to mayntayne their ſhameles halting vpon both partes, to cloke their owne impietie, and to intice others to do the like. But faythful Daniel had learned an other leſſon, and of a more faithfull ſcholemaiſter: euen the verie ſame that inſtructed here the Apoſtles, the Spirite of God, the auctor of wiſedome,
                  Ioh. 16. and trueth: that he oght not onelie to contemne the kinges vnlawfull commandement,

but to do the plaine contrarie.Daniel was not ſo wyſe as our glauering Goſpellers. Nether thoght he it ſufficient to do this ſecretly, except openly he ſhewed to all the worlde whoſe ſeruante he was, and what God he honored. Otherwiſe, how colde he haue declared to the people, that he loued his God with all his harte, ſoule and power, as was commanded?
         
         
            CHAP. VII. 
            
               All men are bound to follow the like example, as wel as the Apoſtles and Daniel, of what eſtate and condition ſo euer they be.
            
            
               HEre are all excuſes taken away from all men, that will be true Chriſtians, and haue the Apoſtles and Daniel for their inſtructers and teachers: whither they be Counſellers, Nobles, Peares,Engliſhemē will nether be Apoſtles Prophets nor good men. or inferior and ciuile officiers. But they will peraduēture excuſe them ſelues, as thogh God had no thing to do with thē, becauſe they be not Apoſtels, nor Prophets. Neuertheles they may be aſſured, they ſhall be as they euer haue bene, ſubiecte to his plages

and puniſhments: and ſo will he haue a do with them, thogh they would haue noght to do with hym. Yf the temperall ſworde had bene committed to the Apoſtels, as wel as was the ſpirituall: if they had bene Pears of a realme, and knowen ſo wel their duetie towarde God and their contrye, as they did to Chriſt and his Churche, being Apoſtels, woulde they haue lyfted vp their ſworde agaynſt Goddes glorie, to the ſubuerſion of the trueth and their nation, at the commandement of their Prince and kinge? Or wolde they not rather haue anſwered: we are appoynted of God to ſet forthe his glorie, and to defend his people, and cannot therfore obeye you?How ſhould they iudge well of other mēs matteres, that cō
                  demne thē ſelues in their owne If that woulde not ſerue, muſt they then haue ceaſed at their threatninges with death and diſpleaſure? Is that ſufficient to diſcharge them, if in not vſing their power to ſuppreſſe tyranny and idolatrie, they ſuffer the people of God to be deuoured? Iudge you your ſelues that beare this Name, whither God coulde approue their doinges.
            
               Matathias that worthie Captayne of the Iewes,1. Mac. 
                  
                     •
                  . as it is wryten in the firſte boke of the Machabees, coulde not ſo lightly excuſe him ſelf when he was commanded by the cruel officiers of wicked Antiochus (which had ſpoyled their Tēpel, raſed their waules, murthered their brethern, and ſet vp idolatrie, in ſo muche as all for the moſt parte, applied them ſelues to their wicked parſuations) that he, with the reſidue ſhulde forſake the Lawes and ſacrifices of their God, to worſhipp ſtrange Goddes: he made anſwere,
                  A notable anſwere for all true Chriſtians to practiſe. to the officer of Antiochus the kinge (which would to God our Noble men had perfetly learned) That thoghe all Nations apparteyning to kinge Antiochus ſhulde obeye him, ſo that euery man would declyne from the Lawes of his countrie: yet I, (ſaieth he) my children, and brethern, wil ſtand in the conuenant of our fathers &amp;c. Which thing he performe din dede to the glorie of God, to his owne ſaluation, and comforte of his brethern and countrie for euer.
            And euen at the ſelf ſame tyme

he ſlewe, not onely a Iewe, one of his owne brethern, which came to ſacrifice in his preſence at the alter Modim, according to the preſcript of Antiochus: but killed alſo the kīges officer, that cō
               pelled him therto, and afterwarde diſtroyed the altar, ād folowed the Lawe of God with a zeale, as did Phinees. Matathias had then a litle power amongeſt his brethern, but nothing to defende him ſelf agaynſt the kinge, and alſo being charged with children and kinſfolk (which ſemed to be all his power) woulde nether pollute him ſelf, nor ſuffer thē to be polluted with wicked idolatrie, nor coūſeles, to be oppreſſed with tyrannie.Matathias was no publik perſone. And yet we reade of no auctoritie or office he had to excuſe him by: but onelie this one thing which was comon to all other of his natiō, the Lawes of their countrie, and couenant of their fathers. Which cauſe he thoght ſufficiēt to diſcharge his cōſcience before God, and to approue his doings. For as muche as God had commanded him not onely to denie to do the commandement of the cruell tyrant Antiochus (vnder whō all Ieruſalem then was by conqueſte)

but manfully to profeſſe him and his, as open aduerſaries to his Lawes and to reſiſte idolatrie by force,Loke wel vpon this example al ye inhabitantes of Englande in killing the idolatrer and the kinges ſeruant (by whom he was compelled) and in ſubuerting the altar, where vpō the idolatrous ſacrifice ſhuld haue bene done. Which was, as you ſee, manifeſte reſiſting of the ſuperior power, being but mā, to the intent he might ſhewe true obedience to his Lorde and God, īn defending and maynteyning his Lawes (which he calleth the couenant of their fathers) yea and with the temporal ſworde to the vttermoſt of his power. Thē if Matathias herein did diſcharge his conſciēce before God and man, in reſiſting by temporal power the kinge, his commandements and officiers: it is not onely the office of Apoſtles ād preachers, to reſiſt, but the dewtie likewiſe of all others according to their eſtate and vocation. But you will ſay perchance, that this boke of the Macabees is not of ſufficient auctoririe to perſuade your conſciences in the like caſe, becauſe it is not reputed to be amongeſt thoſe bokes which are autentique, and named

Canonical. Trueth it is, but that thou (which art in like and better eſtate, becauſe of thy power and auctoritie, wherewith thou art as wel charged before God as kinge or Emperour) mayſt and ſhuldeſt with a ſafe conſcience, folowe this worthie example, it is moſte true and certayne.Mattathias fact depēdethe not of the auctoritie of the hiſtory but of the worde of God. Mattathias doing ād the Apoſtels are both like. For the facte of Mattathias dependeth not vpon the auctoritie of the boke, wherin it is conteyned: but vpon the worde of God, whervpon it was grownded. For hathe he done anie otherwiſe in his vocation, then the Apoſtles did in theirs? Did not they ſay, that God is to be obeyed rather then man? And ſo ſayed Mattathias, and muche more playner: that thoghe all nations woulde obeye Antiochus: yet he, and ſo many as he coulde procure, ſhulde obeye the true God and his Lawes. And like as the Apoſtles, according to their anſwer, openlie and playnly in fight of the people did vſe the ſpiritual ſworde, manfully fighting agaynſt all rebellion of man in Goddes cauſe: ſo did Mattathias vſe the temporall ſworde according to his power,

moued by the ſame reaſon agaynſt idolatrie and oppreſsion which is manifeſte rebellion agaynſt God. Yea and if their were nether example nor Scripture to proue his facte: yet would verie natural reaſon compel euery man to alowe the ſame, as moſte Godlie. And that therin he did nothing but his duetie, which thing was approued in the iudgement of that age, and as a lawful facte and monument wryte and left to be red and practiſed of all poſteritie, the Lawe of nature ſo directing their iudgments.
            But to put you out of all doute, we will confirme it with an other teſtimonie moſt ſurely auctoriſed, and the very ſame in effect,Ioſua made the like anſwere to the Iſraelites. Ioſue. 24.
                of that renowmed and worthie Capitayne Ioſua, the ſonne of Nun, whome God him ſelf had choſen to ſuccede Moyſes in the gouernement, and leading of the people of Iſrael: who after he had declared the benefites of God done vnto them, from the tyme that he had choſen them to be his people, (namelie to Abraham whom he called

from idolatrie, to Iſaac and Iacob, and to the reſt of the people, their poſteritie, in deliuering them out of Egypt, preſeruinge them in the wilderneſſe, and geuing to them his Lawes) ſpake theſe wordes to the Elders ād all the multitude, ſayng: Now therfore feare ye the Lord, ſerue him vnfaynedlie and faithfullie, take away the Goddes which your fathers worſhipped, beyonde the Riuer, and in Egypte, and ſerue the Lorde. But yf you wil not ſerue the Lorde, choſe vnto you this day whom you will ſerue▪ whither ye wil ſerue the Goddes beyonde the Riuer, or the Gods of the Amorites in whoſe lande ye dwele. As for me and my familie, we will ſerue the Lorde: anſwering as did Matathias. And this ſpake he in his later dayes,The papiſts wil ſaye, becauſe he was olde that he doted. to admoniſhe them afore hande not to incline to idolatrie and to neglecte the Lawes of God, which is the cauſe of all euill, and gapp to all miſchiff. Which ſayng of Ioſua, the true ſeruāt of God, ſeemed ſo Godlie in the ſight of all the people, that all were compelled with a uehemencie of ſpirite to ſay: God forbid, that we ſhulde forſake the Lorde,

to ſerue ſtrange Goddes. For the Lorde our God him ſelf, broght vs out of Egypt and from the houſe of bondage.
            What wilt thou more to proue this facte of Mattathias, ād therbie thy duetie alſo, whither thou be of the Seniors of the people, or of the multitude? Here is thy confeſsion, if thou be of God. Yf all men would ſerue ſtrange Godds,Forget not this yf ye feare God and loue your liues. yet will I and my familie ſerue the liuinge Lorde. And agayne, God forbid that we ſhulde leaue the obedience of our God, by whome we are created, rede
                  ••
               d and ſaued, to ſerue ſtrange Goddes. And how caneſte thou ſay that thou ſerueſt God thy Lorde, except thou vſe all ſuche means as he hath geuen to thee in defence of his glorie, beit counſel, learning, auctoritie, power in bodie or in ſoule? All muſte ſerue the Lorde, when he demaundeth it. And when demaundeth God theſe thinges of vs, if not then chieflie, whē Satā begynneth to rage, the worde of God deſpiced, his Name blaſphemed, his Churche ſcattered, his children miſerably oppreſſed, impriſoned, famiſhed and murthered? Either now muſt the counſele of the Coūſeller, the

learning of the learned,Other now ſerue the Lorde or neuer. Luk. 3.
                the auctoritie of the honorable, the power of the Nobles, the bodies of the ſubiectes ſerue the Lorde, or neuer. For now will the Lorde trye who are his people in ſeparating the chaffe frō the corne, thoſe that loue the Lorde vnfaynedlie, ād wil ſerue him in dede from the halting diſſemblers ād hypocrites, who thīking therby to eſcape preſent daūgers, runne headlonge to their owne deſtructiō, thiking therby to eſcape the feareful voyce of the Lorde, fall in to the pit. And if they come foorthe of the pit,
                  Eſai 24. Iere. 48 Hoſa
                        •
                     . 6 they are taken in the net, and cannot eſcape ſaithe the Lorde.
            There is no waye but one, to turne agayne vnto the Lorde, who hathe woū
               ded vs,Repent o countriemen your vnlawfull obedience, ād now at laſt turne to your Lord God and he will heale vs: he hathe ſtriken vs, for our ſynnes, and he will bynde vs vp agayn, ād within two dayes will he reſtore vs to lyffe, ād the thirde day rayſe vs vp, and we ſhal come before his face ſaithe the Prophet. And by what other means can we turne vnto the Lorde to be healed of our woundes, to be reſtored to lyffe agayne, to be lifted vp and broght before his preſence:

but by vnfayned repentance, euerie man of what eſtate, or condition ſoeuer he be? Conſidering with teares how ſhamefullie he hathe fallen from God, and by what means, and to call for grace and ſtrength to turne back by the ſelf ſame means and wayes,
                  Rom. 6. to obey God in walking the contrarie. And to Folowe the counſell of the Apoſtle, that as before we haue geuen our members to ſerue vnclennes and iniquitie: ſo now (after true repentance) make them to ſerue rightouſnes and holyneſſe. Wher before we ſerued men and not God, now to ſerue God and not man, but in God: Where as we abuſed all the gyftes of God to mayntayne idolatrie and tyranny, now to vſe the ſame to the reſtoring of Gods glorie, and preſeruation of his humble and afflicted children:God grant this for Chriſtes ſake, to ſinke in your myndes. where as before we haue troughe contempt of his graces, eſpeciallie the worde and Goſpel of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte broght vpon vs ſhame and confuſion, now by reuerent receauing of them agayne, and framing our liues thervnto, we may remoue theſe plagues, ād finde

fauore ād grace in the ſight of our God, who for this cauſe hathe ſtriken vs, and by all maner of means callethe vs backe from our wickedneſſe, readier to receaue vs, then we to deſier him.
         
         
            CHAP. VIII. 
            
               The concluſion of theſe two parts with a farther declaration of the ſame, that it is both Lawful and neceſſarie ſome tymes to diſobeye and alſo to reſiſte Vngodly magiſtrats and wherin.
            
            
               VVherfore (deare brethern in the Lorde) to returne to our pourpoſe, you may well vnderſtāde of theſe thīgs which haue bene hitherto mentioned, not only the cauſe of all our miſerie in England this day, to haue bene for that we nether taught, knewe, nor vſed true obedience: but alſo what obediēce God requireth of all mē,Obedience ād what he cō
               demnethe for diſobedience. Obedience is to heare God rather then man, and to reſiſte man rather then God, as by the anſwere and doinges of the Apoſtles, and examples of others ye haue bene inſtructed. Whereī you may ſee how litle

the commandments, threatnynges, power, auctoritie, or puniſhments of anie kinge, Prince or Emperour, oght to preuayle with vs agaynſt the commandement of God, where with we are charged.
            Can we then pretende ignoraunce any more? Beholde,Ignorance can not excuſe you much leſſe when the trueth is ſo plainlye taught. verie nature doth teache all men, which be not deſtitute of their comō ſenſe ād reaſon, that God oght rather to be obeyed then man: in ſo muche as the Apoſtles therin feared not the iudgment of their enimies.
            Shall auctoritie of man, or power of Princes bleare our eyes anie lōger:We muſt not yelde to autoritie and power. ſeing there is none ſo ignorant whoſe conſciēce doth not beare him witneſſe, that God is moſte worthie of all honor, and onely to be feared for his power: who made the heauens and the earthe, and man ruler therof, by whoſe power and wiſdome, as all thinges were created, ſo by his wonderful prouidence are all thinges preſerued and gouerned?
            Shall the threatnings of man or puniſhment of Princes moue vs to leaue vndone that which he commandeth,Threaninges oght not to fear vs. ād our vocation requireth? Shulde we honour

thē for their offices and great titles, becauſe they are called kīges, Princes, or Emperours? This muſte we do ſo longe as they will be ſubiectes to God, and promoters of his glorie,This doctrine of obediēce, is dayly ſealed with the bloude of Sainctes of whome they haue their auctoritie, as the examples of the Godlie Patriarkes, and Prophets, of Chriſte him ſelf, and his Apoſtles, and of all martyrs in all ages vntil this day do witneſſ. Which with their bloude haue ſealed vp this doctrine for an vndouted veritie: that there is no obedience agaynſt God, which in his iudgment is not manifeſte rebellion.
            Doeſt thou then vnfaynedly beleue in God, and haſte geuen thy ſelf to ſerue him, and after art commanded of thy Prince or Ruler, what name ſo euer he beare, to committ idolatrie in worſhippīg a piece of bread for thy Sauiour (as do the Papiſtes) which is open blaſphemie agaynſt the Sonne of God?
            
               1. Cor. 10Arte thou willed to be preſent at the idole ſeruice, which the Apoſtle S. Paul forbiddeth: or ells to make, or erect images in Churches or tēples, to heare Maſſes, to trot on pilgremage, to purcheſſe pardōs, to cōfeſſe the Popes auctoritie, to eſteme Gods worde for hereſie▪
            
            
               Art thou charged to be a tormentour of the Saincts of God, to lay holde vpō thē as did the Scribes ād Phariſies, the chief Biſhopp and Prieſts whith their officiers vpon Chriſte and his Apoſtles: to bringe them before the Concile to caſte then in priſon, to flatter them to reuile thē opēly, to famiſhe them ſecreatly, and hange them in their gayles, to racke them,The Shirefs 
                     •
                  ealers and other inferior officers condemned to bringe them to the galows, to the ſtake, and cōſumyng fier: to ſee execution done vpon then, as vpon theues, murtherers, villains, whoremongers, adulterours, traytors, idolaters, &amp; blaſphemers: when inwardlye thy conſcience cryeth vnto thee, Take heede ād beware what thou doeſt to theſe men, for they are the verie ſeruantes of God,Mat 27. Euery mās anſwere to vnlawfull diſſobedience. as Pilate was admoniſhed by his wiffe? Art thou (I ſaye) cōmanded to do anie of theſe thīges, and feareſt God? Beholde, here art thou taught what anſwere it behoueth thee to make, and that by the Apoſtles of Chriſte: which is, Iudge you whither it be lawfull in Godds ſight to obey you rather then God. And agayne, God muſt be obeyed before man.
            
               
               Loſſe of lininges is not a ſufficiēt excuſe to indāger thy ſoule.If thou wilt alleadge the daunger of loſinge thy lyuing and office, wherby thou and thy familie are founde: conſider it is a greater matter to loſe thy ſoule, and to bring the curſſe of God vpon thy whole houſholde, to whome it were farre better to begg in the feare of God,God is the reuenger of inocentes bloude. Pſal. 9.
                thē to be gyltie of innocēt bloud, which the Lorde muſt nedes reuēge according to his promeſſe. Yf thy innocēt brother, which is broght to thee, becauſe he is the ſeruant of God, be ready for Chriſtes ſake to offre vp his life in ſacrifice: what great thing is it for thee to offre vp thy vile liuing for the ſame cauſe of rightouſneſſe?
                  Mat. 16. For as he in loſinge his life hath aſſurance to finde it euerlaſtingly: euen ſo mayſt thou be aſſured in forgoing thy office, becauſe thou wilt be no tormentour of Goddes children, agaynſt thy duetie and conſcience,To looſe in the world, is to gayne in the heavens. Mat. 10. Pſal. 105,
                to haue the rewarde of rightouſneſſe at the hands of God, who eſtemeth all thinges done to anie of theſe litle ones, as done to him ſelf: and forbideth thee to touche them, ſayng, Touche not myne anoynted ones.
            
               Therfore, as there is no power or puniſhment that ſhuld cauſe thee to do euil: ſo is there no office or promotion, which thou ſhuldeſt not willingly forgoe, rather then in reteyninge it to be an inſtrument of iniurious oppreſsion, hauinge this rule of our Sauiour Chriſte alwayes before thine eyes:
                  Mat. 7. What ſo euer ye would that men ſhulde do to you, that do you to them alſo.
            Neither is this ynough, rather to ſuffer iniurie and loſſe, then that thou wouldeſt be a worker of iniurie to others by any means: but more ouer it is thy parte to be a withſtander of euil,withſtand the euil, ād ſupporte the Godly and a ſupporter of the Godly to the vttermoſte of thy power, as thou haſt partly harde all ready, ād partly ſhalt heare now folowing. For as God hath not created vs for our ſelues,
                  Gen. 2. 1. Cor. 10. Gala. 6. but to ſeke his honor and glorie, and the profit of our neighbour, eſpecially of ſuch as be of the houſholde of faithe: euen ſo are we īdetted to God, to beſtowe all thoſe gyftes, be they ſpiritual or corporal,Our detts to God. wherewith God hath bleſſed vs to the ſelf ſame end, ſtryuing agaynſt all impediments, helping, defending, comforting,

and deliuering to the vttermoſte of our power all ſuch as we are aſſured do feare God,Defend, helpe, conforte, and deliuer the godly oppreſſed, and deleuer your owne ſoules. Exod 23.
                and ſtande in nede of our ayde and ſupporte. Otherwiſe we ſhewe our ſelues to haue more compaſsion vpon brute beaſtes, as our neighbours oxe, aſſe, or ſhepe, which Gods Lawe dothe charge vs to helpe, ſaue, or drawe forthe of the diche, althoghe it were the beaſte of our enemie.
            
               Shall we helpe our neighbours beaſt and not him ſelfe?Are we then bound to do this to vnreaſonable and brute beaſtes, yea to any thing belonging to our neighbour, and ſhall we be afrayde to do the like to him ſelf, what tyme he is in neceſsitie? Yf his ſhepe or other of his cattel were readie to be deuoured in our preſence of wolues, or ſuche wilde beaſtes: are we not bounde as wel in conſcience as by the Lawe of God, to driue the wilde beaſte awaye and ſaue his cattel, who can deny this to be our duetie? Can we be excuſed then in ſuffringe the ſoules and bodies of the children of God our brethern, to be moſte pitifully diſtroyed of Gods enemies, by falſe doctrine and cruel murthering, and put not to our handes and power to deliuer

them?
            The verie Gentils with out God were taught ſo muche of nature,Not to wi
                  
                     •
                  thſtande euill, the very Gentils codē
                  ned as iniurie. that to do wronge to a nother is not onely iniurie, but alſo they condemne him as an iniurious perſone, which can, and will not withſtande wrōge done to a nother. Wo be to thee thē (ô miſerable Englande) amonge other nations and peoples,wo to England and her vngodly Magiſtrates. which haſt a longe tyme delited in iniuſtice and cruel oppreſsion. Wo be vnto you moſte vngodlye and careles counſellers. Wo be to you Rulers and Magiſtrats, from the hieſte to the loweſte: for that you ruling with out the feare of God,The wolu
                     •
                  ſhe papiſts. ſee your owne fleſhe ād bloude, the very lābes of God dayly to fall by flockes, not in to the diche or pit, but in to the vnſaciable mouthes of the wolueſhe papiſtes:your horrible plagues are at hāde yf ye amēd not. not onely to be hurte and iniuried, but cruelly to be deuoured both bodie and goodes, and their poore wiues, children, and families deſtroyed, ād go a begginge. And yet neither the ſorouful ſobbes, ād cōtinual teares of the lamētable mothers, nor the pitiful crye of the ſpoyled infātes, nor the extreame neceſsitie of their diſperſed ſeruāts,

beſides the ſhamefull betrayinge ād ſubuertiō of the whole Realme daylie approchinge,Ye haue your honours to defē
                  de and helpe the godly, yea ād all others from oppreſſion and in iurie. can once moue your harde ād ſtonie hartes with pitie to defende their cauſe, and delyuer them frō tyranny: beinge promoted to your honours and offices to that end. Can you, eſcape the condemnation of the Lawe, whiche prefer the preſeruation of your beaſtes and cattell to the pretious lyues of your owne brethern,
                  Eſai. 1. the Image of the liuinge Lorde,The Gentiles ſhall condemne you in the workes of the lawe. Rom. 2.
                whom you are bounde to loue as your ſelues? Shall not the Gentils, whiche lyue beſides the Lawe, ſtand in iudgment agaynſte you whiche profeſſe the Lawe, when they are more preſte to defende their people from iniuries, then you yours? Your owne offices, auctoritie, and power, ſhall in that daye put you to ſilence, and confounde you.
            Was there euer the like contempt of Gods worde in Capernaum? The like idolatrie amonge the heathen? Or like tyranny and cruell murthering at Ieruſalem?
                  Luk. 10. And yet to Capernaum Chriſt hathe threatned that it ſhall be eaſier for Tyre and Sidon in the laſt day, then

for it.
                  Nomb. 33. Exod. 23. and. 34. The Gentiles he commanded to be diſtroyed as his extreame enimies. And as for Ieruſalem that worthie Citie of the Lorde, eſcaped not his ſeuere iudgement:
                  Mat. 24. not leauinge one ſtone vpon another, as oure Sauiour himſelf afore prophecied, ād as their miſerable ſtate and diſpertion this daye doth teſtifie.Englande ſhall not eſcape. Will God then ſpare Englande alone, and puniſhe all other nations for leſſe impietie?
            Can he of his iuſtice ſpare you counſellers, you Nobles and inferior officers: Whiche ſpare not to ſpoyle, oppreſſe, accuſe, condemne, and murther the people of God, to deface his glory, and to diſtroye the whole Engliſhe Natiō from the earthe, ſo moche as in you lieth?
            Repent, repent you miſerable mē: for your ſynnes be at the higheſt,Repent ſhortly: for Goddes heauy wrath is at hande Eſai. 29.
                your cupp of iniquitie is full, and the houre of your heuy viſitation is come: when it will be to late for you to flee from the great wrath of Gods indignation, whiche ſhortlye is like to be powred vpon you. Then ſhall you well perceaue that there is no ſaluation but vnder

Gods protection, no comforte with out Chriſte,The cauſe of all theſe miſeries. no obedience agaynſt God, no power that can diſpence with the charge of the Almightie and his commandements: eſpeciallie when all your counſels agaynſt him and his poore ſeruants ſhall fall vpon your owne heades: your wiſedome turned to follie, your nobleneſſe to vileneſſe, your rule and dominion taken from you, and you made ſlaues to others:Write this vpon your dore poſtes ād in your wel decked chābers. For it will ſuerly come yf ye repēt not. your fayre howſes and gorgeous buildinges deſtroyed, your great poſſeſsions geuen to your enimies, your wiues to be rauiſhed, your mayds deflowred, and children murthered with out mercy, your pride and hie lokes abated, your welthe turned to miſerie, your delicate faare and coſtlie aparell to extreame hunger and beggerye, your ioye and paſtance to weepinge and continuall ſorrowe, and in the end ſhamefull deathe as you haue deſerued. And why? Bycauſe you haue choſen to obeye man rather then G
                  ••
               , and ſought rather to mayntayne 
                  〈◊〉
                owne pride and dignitie, then his honor and glory.
            
               And therfore beholde ô prowde man,
                  Ierre. 50. I am come to thee (ſaithe the Lorde of hoſtes) becauſe thy daye is come, and the tyme when i will viſite thee. For the prowde ſhall fall and be diſtroyed, and there ſhall be noman to lift him vp. I will kindle a fire in his Cities, that ſhall conſume all thinges aboute them, &amp;c.
            And iuſtly maye the Lorde do all this to you, ſeinge he gaue you not this dignitie, makinge you Coūſellers, Noble men, Rulers, Iuſtices, Mayers, Shireffs, Bayliffs, Counſtables, or Gaylers to exalt your ſelues agaynſt his Maieſtie,The end of all offices and to fight agaynſt Chriſte and his members: but to humble your ſelues in his preſence, to promote his glorie, and to defende all thoſe whom he committed to your charge. How commeth it then to paſſe, that ye haue thus betrayde him and his people, in baniſhinge his truthe to receaue falſehod, and haue changed Religion in to ſuperſtition, true honoringe of God, in to blaſphemous idolatrie, and now (to finiſhe your procedinges) are readye to

to ſell your ſubiects for ſlaues to the prowde Spaniards,The Spaniardes are godles a people with out God.
            That wicked woman, whom you vntruely make your Quene, hath (ſaye ye) ſo cōmanded. O vayne &amp; miſerable men.Maries vnlauful gouernement. To what vileneſſe are you broght, and yet as men blynd, ſee not? Becauſe you would not haue God to raigne ouer you, and his worde to be a light vnto your footeſtepps, beholde, he hath not geuen an hypocrite onely to raigne ouer you (as he promiſed) but an Idolatreſſe alſo:
                  Iob. 34. 
               God forbiddeth women to raigne, and nature abhorreth the ſame. not a man accordinge to his appoyntment, but a woman, whiche his Lawe forbiddeth, and nature abhorreth: whoſe reigne was neuer counted lawfull by the worde of God, but an expreſſe ſigne of Gods wrathe, and notable plague for the ſynnes of the people. As was the raygne of cruell Ieſabel, and vngodlie Athalia, eſpeciall inſtrumentes of Satan, and whipps to his people of Iſrael.
            This you ſee not, blynded with ignorance: yea, whiche is more ſhame, where as the worde of God freethe you from the obedience of anie Prince, be

he neuer ſo mightie, wiſe, or politike, commanding anye thinge whiche God forbiddeth, and herein geuethe you auctoritie to withſtand the ſame, as you haue harde: Yet are you willingly become as it were,Marie a baſtard. bondemen to the luſtes of a moſt impotent and vnbrydled woman: a woman begotten in adultrie a baſtard by birthe, contrarie to the worde of God ād your owne lawes.Reade H
                     •
                  lles Cronicle in the 24. of the reinge of kinge Henry. 8. Oxforde. Cambridge. Orliance. Paris. Angiers. Burges. Bononie. Padua. Tholoſa. Leu. 10 Deu. 19 Eph. 2. Gala. 3.
                And therfore cōdemned as a baſtarde by the iudgement of all Vniuerſities in Englā
               de, France, and Italie: as well of the Ciuilians, as Diuines. For now are we freede from that Ieweſhe yoke to rayſe vp ſeede to our brethern departing with out iſſue, by the comyng of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte, who hathe deſtroyed the walle and diſtāce betwixt the Iewes and Gentiles, and hathe no more reſpecte to anie Tribes (for conſeruation wherof this was permitted) but all are made one in him with out diſtinction, which acknowledge him vnfaynedlie to be the Sonne of God and Sauiour of the worlde. For in Chriſte Ieſus there is nether Iewe nor Gentile, Grecian or Barbarous, bonde nor free, &amp;c. And therfore

it muſte nedes followe, that kinge Henrie the eight, in marying with his brothers wife, did vtterly contemne the free grace of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte, which longe before had deliuered vs from the ſeruitude of that lawe:kinge Henry cō
                  mitted inceſt in begettinge Marie. and alſo committed adulterous inceſt contrary to the worde of God, when he begate this vngodlie ſerpent Marie, the chief inſtrument of all this preſent miſerie in Englande.
            And if any would ſaie, it was of a zele to fulfyll the lawe which then was abrogated, he muſt confeſſe alſo that the kinge did not marie of carnall luſte, but to rayſe vp ſeede to his brother: when the contrarie is well knowne to all men. Let no man therfore be offended, that I call her by her propre name, a baſtarde, and vnlawfully begotton: ſeing the worde of God, which cānot lye, dothe geue wittneſſe vpon my parte. And moreouer, that ſuche as are baſtardes ſhulde be depriued of all honor:
                  Deu. 23. in ſo muche as by the Lawe of Moyſes they were prohibited to haue entrance in to the Cōgregatiō or aſſembly of the Lorde to the tenth generation. Conſider thē your vngodlie proceadinges in defrawding

your cōtrie of a lawfull kinge: and preferringe a baſtarde to the lawful begotten dawghter, and exaltinge her whiche is, and will be a comon plague ād euerſion of altogether: for as muche as ſhe is a traytor to God,The Goſp
                     •
                  ll
                     •
                  rs holpe her to the crown and ſhe burneth thē. &amp; promis breaker to her deareſt frindes, who helpinge her to their power to her vnlawfull reigne, were promiſed to inioye that religion which was preached vnder kinge Edwarde: which not withſtanding in a ſhorte ſpace after, ſhe moſte falſely ouerthrewe and aboliſhed. So that now both by Gods Lawes and mās, ſhe oght to be puniſhed with death, as an opē idolatres in the ſight of God, ād a cruel murtherer of his Saīts before mē, ād merciles traytoreſſe to her owne natiue coūtrie.
            For Gods worde ſhe abhorreth, Antichriſte hathe ſhe reſtored, her fathers Lawes contemned, her promeſſe brokē, and her brother Godly kinge Edwarde as an heretique condemned▪
               M. Bucer Paulus Phagius, maistris Martyr, &amp;c. not thinkinge it ynoughe to expreſſe her tyranny vpon thē that liued, except ſhe ſhewed crueltie, or rather a raging madneſſe on the bodies of Gods ſeruāts lōge before buried, drawīg thē forth of their graues to

burne thē as heretikes. And in fine vtterly abhorring the Engliſhe nation, hath ioyned her ſelf to adulterous Philip, the Spaniſhe kinge:who is more blind then they that can and will not ſee? Here vnto the lawes of the real me, the will and prophecie of her father doth prouok thē
                to whome ſhe hathe, and dothe continually labor to betray the whole kingdome. And yet ye cannot, or will not ſee it, nether yet for all this be ſtirred vp to bridell her affections, and withſtand her vngodly doinges, to promote the glorie of God, and to preſerue your brethren, and your ſelues: but thinking to reteyne your promotions by flattery, do haſtelie drawe Gods vengeance vpon your ſelues and others.
            For do you thinke that Philip will be crowned kinge of Englande, and reteyne in honor Engliſhe counſellers? Will he credite them withe the gouernement of his eſtate, who haue betrayed their owne? Shall his nobilitie be Spaniardes, with out your landes and poſſeſsions? And ſhall they poſſeſſe your promotiōs and lyuinges, and your heads vpō your ſhulders? Come they to make a ſpoyle of the whole Realme, and leaue you ād yours vntouched? Where is your great wiſdome become? Your ſubtile counſels

and policies, where of you bragge ſo muche, to whome theſe thinges be hid, that euerie childe eſpieth?
            If Eſai the Prophet had not foreſpoken theſe ſecret iudgments of God,
                  Eſa. 3.4 29. in blynding the eyes of the prowde contemners, I coulde not ceaſe to wonder at your groſſe ignorance, as now I conſider with greife of harte, the miſerie which is like ſhortly to come vpon you in full meaſure, for this calamitie, alreadie powred vpon others, through your procurements and ſtudies. Which fearefull iudgment of God loke neuer to eſcape, except ſuddaynlie ye repent and change your vngodlie purpoſe.
                  Eſai· 28. If you be at a couenant with deathe (as you thinke) you ſhall not auoyde it, if you thinke to eſcape the comon deſtructiō, making diſsimulation and lyes your refuge, yet ſhall you be reuealed: for the Lord him ſelf will deſtroye all your counſels, becauſe they are not of him.
            Yt is not your going to the Maſſe, your prayſing of the Pope, your flattring of your Quene, and ſhauen Prieſts of Baal, that can defende you in

that day: nether yet your licences whiche ſome of you purchaſſe of an infidel to departe out of your countrie,Licences purchaſed of infidels and lyinge in idolatrous places, is thought good inough of carnall goſpelers. ſome lyinge in idolatrous places, differing no thinge from them in ther diſſolute liuinge, ſome paſſinge in to Italie to pleaſe their Quene, and to get an opinion of men that they approue her procedings, rather coueting to haue the name of a blaſphemouſe papiſte, then of Chriſte our Sauiour. Thikinge by ſuche vnlawfull meanes to worke miracles: but their gaines at length will be confuſion,Their dea
                     ••
                   proue what they be. as now their frute whiche they haue brohgt thence do witneſſe that is the want of Gods feare and open diſſimulation.
            This is not the way (ô vaine men) to winne Gods fauour, and to eſcape his fearfull iudgmentes: but to increaſe his wrathe and haſtē his vengeance, who will not be mocked, nether ſuffer his holye Name lōge to be blaſphemed. Cō
               ſider with your ſelues, and returne to the right way, and walke in it while ye haue tyme, and I will ſhewe it vnto you.
            
               You haue ſynned moſte greuouſlie agaynſt the Lorde:The onely means to eſcape miſerie. Pſal. 103.
                knowe your tranſgreſsions, and with teares confeſſe thē, euery man vnfaynedlie vnto the Lorde, who is redie to mercie and ſlowe to anger. You haue deſpiſed and abuſed the worde of his dearely beloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, the Author of ſaluatiō, in the dayes of our Godlie kinge Edwarde (which is the cauſe why God hath thus plaged vs with a tyrant) ſeke after the worde agayne and receaue it with all reuerence. By geuing auctoritie to an idolatres woman ye haue baniſhed Chriſte and his Goſpell,Folowe wyſe counſel, leaſt ye and al your land periſhe. and in his place reſtored Antichriſte with all his infections, wherin your owne conſciences condemne you of euil. Then in takinge agayne the ſame auctoritie from her, you ſhall reſtore Chriſte and his worde and do well. In obeyinge her, ye haue diſobeyed God. Then in diſobeying her, ye ſhall pleaſe God. Becauſe you haue geuen place to her and her counſells, you are all become idolatrous hypocryts, and alſo traytors to your owne Countrie: then by reſiſting her

ſelues damnation for their tranſgreſsiō and her wicked decrees, you muſt be made true worſhippers of God, ād faithfull Engliſhe men.
            Other meās there are not, but to turne to God by repentāce, to baniſhe falſehode by receauīg the trueth, to ouerthrowe Antichriſte, and all kinde of idolatry by honoring Chriſte and his Goſpell: to ſuppreſſe tyranny by iuſtice: to withſtande oppreſsion and murther by defending the iuſte and innocent, and puniſhing the workers of iniquitie, of what eſtate or condicion ſo euer they be, as after (God willing) ſhall be proued at large. For as by this means onely Gods honor muſt be reſtored,Reſtore goddes honour and eſcape Gods vengeance and you eſcape his vengeance, to obeye thē that obeye God, and reſiſte them that reſiſte his Maieſtie, rēdringe vnto all accordinge to his Lawes: euenſo, when they ſhulde vnderſtand that their ſubiectes be no more as it were brute beaſtes with out ſenſe or iudgment: but that they knowe wherein, ād how farre they owe obediēce, ād would no more be led by their deuiliſhe and vngodlie luſtes, as they haue bene and yet are preſentlie.
            
               Then woulde their Princes and Rulers alſo geue them ſelues with all diligence,yf they knewe rightly how to obey and wherin, thē ſhulde theſe thinges here mentioned come to paſse. Deu. 17.
                to ſtudie and applie the ſame Lawe of God: then woulde they do nothinge them ſelues, nor commande others, where in they where not aſſured to pleaſe him. Then woulde they learne to obeye God, which now rebel agaynſt him: and to folow the examples of the Godlie kings and Rulers, hauing the boke of the Lorde euer with them, neuer ſuffring it to departe from them.Gods boke teache the true obedience. But as worthie Ioſua, Ioſias, and Ioſaphat, to reade and ſtudie in it day and night. Not to declyne from it them ſelues, nor yet to ſuffer their ſubiects therin to be ignorāt, which is the onlie wiſedome of God and comforte of all mens conſciences. Then ſhulde the Rulers loue and preſerue their ſubiectes. And the ſubiects likewiſe reuerentlie obeye their ſuperiours. To conclude, then ſhuld all be bleſſed of God, feared of their enimies, ſure from all daūgers, voyde of all idolatrie and falſe religiō,
                  Deu. 4. and eſtemed of all nations the wyſeſt and mightieſte people vpon the earthe, as God promiſſed to Iſrael, ſo longe as

they ſhulde lyue.
         
         
            CHAP. IX. 
            
               Anſwers to the contrarie obiections of ſuch as teache all maner of obedience to Magiſtrats to be lawful, taken forthe of the New Teſtament.
            
            
               BVt for as muche as there is nothing ſo manifeſt and true, which is not either obſcured vtterlie by contrary reaſons of mans brayne, or ells diſcredited by other places of Scripture wrōgfully vnderſtāde and applyed by many: I haue here thoght expedient before I proceade anie further, for the better eſtabliſhing of the trueth, to anſwer and ſatiſfie, ſo far as ſhal pleaſe God to geue vnto me, all ſuche reaſons, auctorities, and Scriptures, as are aleadged to the contrarie: to the intent that we may not onlye ſee the trueth, and ſo be ſtyrred to imbrace it, but alſo may eſpie the falſehod, ād learne to auoyde it.
            And becauſe amongeſt all other auctorities ād reaſōs, there is none of greater force thē that which is wryten in the Epiſtle of S.
                  Rom. 13. Paul to the Romains: we will firſte of all others begin with it.The firſte obiection. Let euerie ſoule (ſaith he) ſubmitt him ſelf

to the auctoritie of the higher powers: for there is no power but of God, and the powers that be, are ordeyned of God. Who ſoeuer therfore reſiſteth power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God: and they that reſiſt, ſhal receaue vnto them ſelues damnation. Here (ſay they) is a general doctrine affirmed by the Apoſtle, that euery man (none excepted) muſt be ſubiecte to ſuperiour powers: and if euery man muſte be ſubiect, none oght to diſobey.
            Beſides this, beholde the Apoſtle doth not barely affirme this propoſitiō, ſayīg: Euery perſon (for that he meanethe by euery ſoule) muſt be ſubiecte to the Magiſtrates and Rulers, of what condition ſo euer he be, but proueth the ſame with a moſte ſure argument gathered of the ordinance of God▪ becauſe there is no power but of God. And therfore to reſiſte powers, is to reſiſte God him ſelf, whoſe ordinance it is. And not contented with one reaſon, he confirmeth the ſame with a nother depending of Gods puniſhments, which he hath appoynted for all them that reſiſte, which is, to receaue to them ſelues damnation for their tranſgreſsiō:

ſo that they cōclude, that it is not onely Paules auctoritie that maketh all men ſubiecte to their ſuperiours (which notwithſtanding were ſufficient, being the Apoſtle of Chriſte) but alſo the ſame is by good and ſtronge reaſons confirmed.
            
               AnſwereIn anſwering to this obiection, I will not longe holde you in rēdring the cauſe,The cauſe wherfore the Apoſtle was moued thus to write. which as we may probably gether mouid the Apoſtle to write this to the Romains cōcerning obedience to their ſuperiours: but in few wordes touche ſo muche as ſeemeth neceſſarie. It may apeare very credible (which ſome Godlie and learned do wryte) that amōgeſt the Romayns, after they had receaued the Goſpel, there were many vnder that name, which woulde be deliuered from all ſubiection: thinking the office of Magiſtrates nomore neceſſarie to them that profeſſed Chriſte: as do this day the Anabaptiſts and Libertins.Anabaptiſts. Libertins Others, who had bene once freed from tribute and cuſtome paying, to ſtrange Magiſtrates, woulde therat take an occaſion by preaching of the Goſpell to paye no more tribute to their ſuperiours. Such

were diuers of the Iewes,Denyars of tribute who coūted it for abōdage. And that kīde of ſecte was rayſed vp euen in Chriſtes dayes, as appeareth whē the Phariſies ſent their diſciples with Herodes ſeruātes to knowe his iudgment, whither it were lawful for them to paye tribute to Caeſar or no.
                  Mat. 22 And in the Actes, Gamaliel maketh mention of one Iudas Galilaeus,
                  Act. 5. which was autor of that ſecte, and moued muche trouble amōgeſt the people, ſayng: It was not lawful to paye tribute. By theſe and ſuche like opinions, the Apoſtle (perceauing the office of Magiſtrates to come in to contempte, and men to eſteme it not lawful, which God him ſelf ordeyned in defence of his religion and Ciuile policie (was moued to wryte as is before mencioned▪ exhorting all men to eſteme the office of Magiſtrates as Gods ordinance, and to obeye them whom God had appoynted Rulers ouer them.
            Then as the Apoſtle wryteth we confeſſe, and ſo muche as he ſpeaketh we graūte, that is, that all men are bownd 
                  •
               o obey ſuch Magiſtrates, whome God 
                  •
               athe ordeyned ouer vs lawfully according

to his worde, which rule in his feare according to their office, as God hathe appoynted. For thogh the Apoſtle ſaith: There is no power but of God: yet doth he not here meane anie other-powers, but ſuch as are orderly and lawfullie inſtitute of God. Ether els ſhulde he approue all tyranny and oppreſsion, which cometh to anie commonwelth by means of wicked and vngodlie Rulers, which are to be called rightlie diſorders, and ſubuerſions in comon welthes, and not Gods ordinaunce. For he neuer ordeyned anie lawes to approue, but to reproue and puniſhe tyrantes, idolaters,we may reſiſte tyrantes and yet not Godes ordinance. papiſtes and oppreſſors. Then when they are ſuche, they are not Gods ordinaunce. And in diſobeying and reſiſting ſuch, we do not reſiſte Gods ordinaūce, but Satā, and our ſynne, which is the cauſe of ſuch. Or els, if we ſhall ſo conclude with the wordes of the Apoſtle,By the papiſtes gatherīg. Satan oght not to be reſiſted. that all powers what ſo euer they be muſt be obeyed and not reſiſted, then muſt we confeſſe alſo, that Satan and all his infernall powers are to be obeyed. Why? becauſe they are

powers and haue their powers alſo of God,
                  Iob 12. Iam. 4 which cannot touche man any farther then God permitteth. But S. Iames geuethe vs, contrarie commandement, ſaing: Reſiſte the deuel and he will flee awaye from you.
            And that the Apoſtle Paule dothe ſo reſtrayne his wordes to all lawfull powers, we nede not to ſeke far of. For in the ſelf ſame Chap.The proffe of this anſwere. after he dothe expounde his mynde: that is, what powers and Magiſtrates he meaneth: Such (ſaith he) as if thou doeſt well, thou nedeſte not to feare, but if thou doeſt euel. And agayne wilt thou be out of feare of the power? Do wel then: and ſo ſhalt thou be prayſed of the ſame. For he is the miniſter of God for thy welthe. But if thou doeſt euill, feare: for he beareth not the ſworde for noght: for he is the miniſter of God, to take vengeance of them that do euill &amp;c. Whereby we may playnly vnderſtāde, that althoghe, he ſaithe, There is no power but of God: yet he meaneth ſuche power as is his ordināce and lawfull: whoſe office ſtādeth in theſe two poyntes, to defēd the good, and to puniſhe the euel: not to be feared

for wel doing, but for euil, to whom the ſworde is geuen for that purpoſe. And to ſuch, with the Apoſtle we graūt alſo, that euery perſone muſt be ſubiecte ād obedient:The papiſts argument is fully anſwered for they are Gods ordinaunce. And to diſobey or reſiſte ſuch, is to diſobey and reſiſte God him ſelf. And therfore do deſerue iuſtlie to receaue Gods puniſhment, which, as the Apoſtle threatneth, is damnation. And this makethe nothing agaynſt our former ſentence, but rather confirmeth the ſame: approuīng no obedience but that which is lawful, that is to ſay, according to Gods appoyntment and ordinance, as doth more euidētly appere in his wordes folowing: partly in that he demaundeth obedience to ſuch for conſcience ſake, and not for feare of vengeance onely. As thogh he would ſaye: ſo farre is it from reaſon and Gods worde that any man ſhulde diſobey or contemne the Magiſtrates, ordeyned by God to puniſhe vice and mantayne vertue, that he nedeth no other to reproue him of euil in ſo doing, then his owne propre cōſcience, which will (iuſtly examined) teache him how Gods ordinance oght

to be reuerenced, eſpecially ſeruing to the preſeruation of the people, in ſuppreſſing wickedneſſe, and promoting Godlyneſſe.
            For that cauſe he willeth after to paye their tribute, not to euery man that will demande (for vnlawful demandes may be lawfully denied) but to whome tribute belongeth, cuſtome to whom cuſtome, feare to whom feare, and honour to whom honour is due.
            Obedience then he requireth of all mē, tribute alſo, cuſtome, feare,Obedience is cōmaunded to all men: but yet vnder cōdition. and honor: but vnder this condition of iuſtice and aequitie, to render theſe dueties to them that haue iuſte title thereūto. And who are they, but (as I ſayed before) ſuch as God hath appoynted to rule ouer vs in his feare, for our profit, and preſeruation of the comon welthe?
            To this alſo dothe the ſayng of S.The ſeconde obiectiō ād anſwere 1. Pet. 2
                Peter wel agree, thoghe it be broght in of the other partie to proue the contrary: Submit your ſelues to euery ordinaūce of mā for the Lordes ſake: whither it be to kīge as to the chief, or vnto Rulers as vnto them that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of euel doers, and the prayſe

of thē that do well. Beholde how Peter here nether diſſenteth from him ſelf in his anſwere before to the Cōcile, nor here diſagreeth from Paule, willīg obedience to kinges and inferior Rulers: not to all, but to ſuch as are appoynted to puniſhe euill doers, and prayſe the contrary: and to diſobey ſuch, muſte nedes be condemned for wicked and vngodlie rebelliō. For ſuche there were as maye playnly appere by. S. Peters wordes folowing, whiche vnder the pretence of libertie woulde couer and cloke their malice. And this the Apoſtle forbiddeth in all maner of ſubiectes, and iuſtlye.
            
               The thyrde obiection and anſwere.But you will ſaye, the wordes of Peter folowing concerning the obedience of ſeruantes to Maiſters, dothe charge vs farther then with godlie Rulers, and ſuch as rule according to their office. For to ſeruantes he writeth on this wiſe. Seruantes obeye your Maiſters with all feare, not onely if they be good and curteous, but alſo thogh they be frowarde:
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                for ſo the greke worde dothe ſignifie, a cōbrous, frowarde, or a perſone harde to pleaſe and ſelfe willy. Wherof

they will conclude, that Peter commandeth obedience to all kinde of perſones, good and bad: what ſo euer they commande muſt be done. and why? becauſe he ſo chargeth ſeruants to obey their maiſters.
            Neuertheles this is to be obſerued in reading the wordes of Peter (as alſo in all the holy Scriptures) that we muſt ſo take them as they agree with him ſelf, and not agaynſt him.Anſwere. For the Spirit of God changeth not his meaning: but what he ſaithe once, he ſaythe for euer. Saint Peter here ſeemeth to preuent the obiection which ſeruantes (deſierous of libertie) might haue obiected, being willed to obey their Maiſters: as thoghe he would ſaye: I am not ignorant that there are many Maiſters trobleſome, frowarde, and importune ouer you:Of what maner of maiſters Peter ſpeaketh. which are not ſo gentle and curteous towardes you as becomethe them: well: that is their faut and infirmitie, which you muſt for Chriſtes ſake, whom you profeſſe, patiently ſuſtayne and beare. For thogh your Maiſters be roughe or frowarde (he ſaith not wicked and vngodly) that is no

cauſe why ye ſhuld not faithfully ſerue them for the tyme of your ſeruitude, ſo longe as they will nothing of you, but that which is good and godlie.
            Then the mynde of S. Peter is that the ſhreudneſſe or frowardnes of Maiſters, is no lawful or iuſt occaſion why the ſeruantes ſhulde be diſobediēt. And as this is the verie meaning of the Apoſtle in that place ſo is it not like that he would write contrarie to him ſelf, when he ſayed:
                  Act. 4. God oght rather to be obeyed then man. Nether can he be iudged contrary to the Apoſtle Paul,The true knot of obedience. Ephe. 6.
                who bindeth vp all lawful obediēce whith this knot, In the Lorde: ſpeaking vnto childrē, ād exhortyng thē to obeye their fathers &amp; mothers. But how? In the Lorde ſaith he. And why? For that is iuſt. Then if Paule charge not children with further obedience to their parentes, then in the Lorde, to whom principallie they are by Gods commandement and nature bounde, will Peter bynde ſeruantes to their Maiſters anie further thē in the Lorde? And if it be iuſte obedience onlie which is in the Lorde: can ther be any lawful obediēce agaynſt him, either of childrē
               
towardes ther parētes, ſeruātes towardes their Maiſters,God is our chief Father, Lorde and maiſter. or ſubiectes towardes their Rulers or Magiſtrates? No, God is the firſt and principal Father, Maiſter ād Lorde, to whō firſte obedience muſte be geuen as he doth demāde: and to others in him, and for him onely, as we were taught at the beginning.
            And that S. Peter had onely reſpecte to the rough condicions of Maiſters, and not to their vnlawful commandement agaynſt God and their conſcience (which they are bownde to do for no mans pleaſure) the wordes do playnelie witneſſe. For this is thākes worthye (ſaithe he) if a man for conſcience towardes God indure grief, ſuffring wongfully. For what prayſe is it, if when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye take it patientlye? &amp;c. Then ye ſee the meanyng of S. Peter is not to make vs ſubiecte to anie euill or vngodlie commādementes, but to perſuade all ſeruantes not to caſt of their duetie, during the tyme of their ſeruitude,S Peter approueth not frowarde maiſters. notwithſtāding they be roughlie dealt with all of their Maiſters, which thing is not ſpoken here of S. Peter to incourage or mayntayne

frowarde Maſters in their frowardnes, nor yet to forbid the ſeruantes which feare God to ſeke after lawful remedie at the hādes of ſuperior powers, who for that cauſe are ordeyned to ſee iuſtice adminiſtred to all ſortes of mē,Seruantes oppreſſed may ſeke lawfull remedy againſt their maiſters. as well to ſeruantes as others: but that they ſhulde not thīke the ſharpneſſe of their Maiſters to be a cauſe ſufficiēt to free them from doing their duetie vpō the othér parte.
            In like caſe may we conclude of Princes ād Magiſtrats,How far wicked Princes may be obeyed. thogh they be rough and frowarde: yea, thoghe before God they are wicked, vngodlie, and reprobate perſons (as was Saule) yet ſo longe as their wikedneſſe braſteth not out manifeſtly agaynſt God, ād his Lawes, but outwardly will ſee them obſerued and kept of others, puniſhing the tranſgreſſors, and defending the innocent: ſo longe are we bounde to render vnto ſuch, obedience, as to euill and roughe Maiſters: becauſe we may not take Gods office in hande to iudge of the harte any farther then their outwarde deedes do geue manifeſt teſtimony. Otherwiſe, if without feare they tranſgreſſe Gods Lawes them ſelues and cōmande others to do the like, then haue they loſt that

honor and obedience which otherwiſe their ſubiectes did owe vnto them: and oght no more to be taken for Magiſtrates: but puniſhed as priuate trāſgreſſors, as after I haue promiſed to proue.
            Here vnto they adde the ſaying of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte to Peter,The fourth obiection. Mat. 26. Ioh. 18.
                which bad him put vp his ſworde, after he had ſtrickē the ſeruāt of the high Prieſt, and cut of his eare: not mynding by the ſworde to make reſiſtance. Wherevpon they gather that althogh it be lawful in doctrine and preaching for the ſeruants of God to withſtād and reproue the enimies, as Chriſt him ſelf and his Apoſtles did: yet it is not permitted to do the ſame by anie outwarde or bodely force. For thē as Chriſt anſwered, he might haue obtayend of his Father 12. Legions of Angels for his defence.
            To this we ſhall ſone anſwere,Anſwere. if we conſider who ſpake this, to whom, and for what cauſe it was ſpokē. Which circumſtances well waied, geue a great light to all like facts and ſayinges. Firſt we muſt diligently conſider the office of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte, which as it was in all poyntes ſpirituall, aſwell

concerning his kingdome which he himſelf affirmeth not to be of this worlde, as his Prieſthod and Prophecie: euen ſo for his owne parte,
                  Ioh 18. coulde he vſe no temporal force or power for the accompleſhment of the ſame, becauſe he denieth that he either came to raigne in this worlde, or ells to be a iudge therin: as he anſwered the man, which would haue had him to comande his brother to deuide the landes bewixt them, ſayng: Man,Luk 12. who made me a iudge or deuider ouer you? And being demanded to geue iudgment agaynſt the woman taken in adultrie,
                  Ioh. 
                  
                     •
                  . he woulde not take that office vpon him, but ſayd vnto the woman, when her accuſers were gone: Nether do I condemne thee: go thy waye, and ſynne no more.
            
               why Chriſt vſed not the d
                     •
                  f
                     •
                  nce of the temporal power.Thus as concerning Chriſtes owne perſone, who had all thinges and powers both in heauen and in earth at his comandement, it is euident that he woulde vſe no temporal power agaynſt his enimies: for that he was not therwith charged. Which exāple taketh not waye the office or duetie of ſuch as are charged

with the tēporall ſworde, to vſe it in defence chieflye of Gods glorye, and the preſeruation of thoſe that are vnder them.
            Secondly why he forbad Peter alſo,Why Peter was forbyd to vſe the ſworde. and in him all the reſte of the Apoſtles, we can not be ignorant. For who knoweth not that the Apoſtles were witneſſes of Ieſus Chriſte choſen forthe of the worlde (as S.
                  Act 1. Ioh 
                  
                     ••
                  
                Iohn ſaithe) not to defende their Maiſter by the temporall ſworde (for that were to vſurpe vpon another mans office, not apperteyninge to th
                  •
               m) to whom onelie the ſpirituall ſworde was comitted, to fight manfullie with it agaynſt the worlde,
                  Epheſ. 
                  
                     •
                  . Hebr 4. Satan and all ſpirituall powers. For as the Apoſtle ſaith: Thoghe we walke compaſſed with the fleſhe,2 Cor. 1
                     •
                  . yet do we not warre fleſhlie. For the weapōs of our warrfare are not carnall thinges, but ſtronge by the power of God to caſt downe holdes: wherwith we ouerthrowe imaginatiōs of euery high thinge that is exalted agaynſt the knowlege of God, and bringe in to captiuitie euery thoght to the obediēce of Chriſte. Wherfore, ſeīg the office of the Apoſtles alſo is ſpirituall,

as their Maiſters was: and had onely ſpirituall weapons to vſe in the defence of the Goſpell, wherof they were miniſters: it is not good reaſon to conclude their purpoſe,The abſurdite of this reaſon. that Magiſtrates and other inferior officers, oght not to vſe the temporall ſworde in defenſe of religion: becauſe Chriſte woulde not ſuffer Peter to fight with the temporall ſworde. But rather as Chriſte requireth of Peter and of all the reſt, the faithfull vſe of the ſpirituall ſworde, where with they were charged, or ells they ſhulde be ſubiecte to malediction and iudgmēt: For wo be to me (ſaith Paule) if I preache not:
                  1. Cor. 9. As the preachers are charged to vſe the ſpiritual ſworde, ſo are the Magiſtrats bonde to ſet forthe Gods glorie poral ſworde. euēſo may not they eſcape iudgment ād the curſe of God, which vſe not the temporall ſworde cōmitted vnto them with all indeuour in the defence of Gods glorie and his Church, wherewith euery man is charged, according to his vocation and power, none except.
            To be ſhorte, if our Sauiour Chriſt ſhulde, as he might by his power, haue withſtand the Iewes that came to apprehend him and put him to death, how ſhuld he haue dronken of that cup which his Father had geuen him? That is, how ſhulde

he by his deathe and paſsion haue redemed vs,
                  Rom. 5. Iohn. 10. for which cauſe he came in to the worlde: not to haue his liffe takē from him agaynſt his will, but willinglie to lay it downe for all.
            Then we ſee that there is nothing in this ſaying of Chriſte to Peter, which can condemne lawfull reſiſting of vngodlie Rulers in their vngodly commandementes. For thogh it was profitable to all men that Chriſt without any reſiſtance ſhulde be crucified, being the ſacrifice appoynted of God the Father to ſaluation: yet is it not therfore lawfull for the inferior officers, or permitted to the ſubiectes, to ſuffre the blaſphemie and oppreſsion of their ſuperiors to ouerflow their whole countrie and nation, when both power and means is geuen vnto them lawfully to withſtand it, and they by their profeſſion and office are no leſſe bounde to put it in execution.
         
         
            CHAP. X. 
            
               Obiections out of the olde Teſtament, and Anſwers to the ſame.
            
            
               
               THis muche being ſpokē to ſatiſfie ſuch obiections as are comonlye alledged forthe of the New Teſtament: let vs ſee alſo what may be ſayed agaynſt vs in the old, and after what ſorte they may be truely anſwered.The firſte obiection out of Ier. 29.
                Ieremie they alleadge in his letter ſent from Ieruſalem to the captaynes in Babylon, to the Prieſts and Prophetts, and to all the people of Iſraell that then were in Babylon, counſelling them how to behaue them ſelues, and to eſcape danger. The effect wherof was this: not to rebell, that they might eſcape, but to remayne ſtill and abide the appoynted tyme of the Lorde: yea, to ſeke the peace of the Citie wherinto God had broght them, and to praye to God for it. For (ſaithe he) with the peace of that Citie, ſhall your peace be alſo.
            
               
                  Baruch. 1.And the like is wryten in Baruch the Prophet tending to the ſame end, that they ſhulde pray for the longe liffe of Nabuchadnezer ād Balthazer his ſone, that vnder their ſhaddow (that is protection) they might lyue and ſerue them

a longe tyme. Wheerin (ſaye they) two things are to be noted agaynſt our opinion. The firſte, that he forbiddeth them to rebell, and exhorteth them paciently to abide the tyme appoynted of their delyuerance. The ſeconde, that they are bownd to pray for their enimies, and welthe of their Cities, and therin alſo are bounde to obey them.
            This Epiſtle or letter of Ieremie ſent to the Iewes at Babylon then captiues,Anſwere. we maye not deny to be his: thoghe of the Prophecie of Baruch ſome do doute, and eſteme it not as Canonicall. Neuertheles becauſe they tend bothe to one effecte in this matter,The cauſe why Ieremie and Baruch thus coū
                  ſelled. we will admitte bothe. Firſte, granting that their counſelle to quietnes and to abſtayne frō rebellion was good and neceſſary becauſe it proceaded from the Spirite of God and of knowledge, which ſpake or wrote nothing that God had not reueled vnto them: and wherof they alſo ſhuld not admoniſhe others, to the intēt they might geue no credit to falſe Prophetes, which woulde ſtirre them vp to ſedition, perſwading them that they ſhulde not longe continewe in Babylon,

when as the Lorde had other wiſe appoynted. Wherof when God aſſured them by his Prophet, it muſt nedes be counted extreame madneſſe and rebellion agaynſt God, if they ſhulde haue done the contrarie, As we reade of wicked Achab,1. Kinges 22. who crediting the flatterīg coūſelle of the falſe Prophetes, diſobeyed God in contēning the trueth tolde hī by Micheas: but to his owne deſtructiō.
            Therfore this matter is ſone āſwered, where we haue the ſecrete counſelle of God reueled vnto vs, admoniſhing vs to abide in any place, ād not to departe til he call vs: we are more then rebells to do the contrarie, ād muſte ſuſtayne the daunger worthelye. But this is not our queſtiō, whether we oght to remayne in any place ſo longe as God hathe commāded vs:The ſtate of the queſtion. but whither we oght to do euill at the commandement of Prince or power, whereſoeuer we be, or in what eſtate, be it neuer ſo miſerable. For thogh Ieremie coūſelled thē with pacience to remayne in Babylon, yet nether he, nor Baruch would permit thē to followe the exaple of the Gētills there, in idolatrie or euell doīg: as the Epiſtle of Ieremie

ſēt alſo to the Iewes captiues in Babylō ād wrytten in the prophecie of Baruch,
                  Baruch. 6 doth abundantlie witneſſe. And as the exāples of Daniel alſo, Sidrach,
                  Dani. 3. Miſach, ād Abdenago do teache vs: which not wihſtāding their Captiuitie, woulde not obey the kīges cōmandemēt to do euill.
            Alſo in that they are willed to pray for the good eſtate of the Citie wherin they dwelled, that is Babylō, and for the lōge liffe of Nabuchadnezer ād his ſōne the cauſe is alſo alleadged, to the ītēt that the peace of that Citie ſhuld alſo be their peace:why the Iewes were willed to pray for Nabuchadnezars longe life. ād for that Nabuchadnezer ād his ſōne ſhuld be their ſhadow ād protectiō, God ſo mouīg their hartes. Which cauſes are ſufficient why the people of God ſhulde be thākfull, that is, to wiſhe well to the places and perſons where, ād of whom they receaue any benefit, eſpecially peace and protection, as was promiſed to the Iewes in Babylon.
            But what is this to the purpoſe? The Iewes were cōmāded of God by the Prophetes eſpeciallie to tarry in Babylō, where thē for their ſyns they were captiues, becauſe their owne Citie Ieruſalē, ād all their coūtrie was deſtroyed ād ſubiecte to

Nabuchadnezer and there remayned no other place where they might haue peace, but in Babylon and vnder his iuriſdiction. Is this then a ſufficient excuſe for you that inioye your countrie and are charged with the defence therof, to ſuffer your ſelues willingly to be ſpoyled of Gods glory, and peace of your conſciences, that is, true religion: and you for the ſame cauſe to be oppreſſed, remoued and murthered, to geue place not onely to them that hate you, but to the greateſt enemies of Chriſt, the papiſtes, and idolatrous Spaniards?
            
               Wherfore the Iewes ſhulde be quiet in Babylon.The Iewes were willed to be quiete in Babylon, becauſe that they and their brethren alſo diſperced ſhuld therby finde more fauour and comforte: ſhall you therfore forſake God and betraye your countrie to bringe the vengeance of God ād his horrible plagues vpō your ſelues and your brethern, wherof you haue alreadie felt ſome portion? The Iewes were willed to praye for Nabuchadnezer and his ſonne, for that by them they ſhulde paſſe ouer a great part of their captiuitie with peace, and

be alſo by them defended from other enemies. Are you therfore excuſed, that permit your ſelues to be made a pray to Satan, Antichriſte, and to all ſortes of Gods enimies, at the commandement of an vngodlie woman? Who ſeeketh but to conſume the Engliſhe nation, and in the end to cut your throtes that nowe are in auctoritie, whom ſhe vſeth as inſtruments, to bring her wicked purpoſes to paſſe.
            Is your condition now all one with the Iewes?The miſerable eſtat of Englād In dede brethren it is like to be muche worſe, and that ſhortly without Gods vnſpeakable mercy: but as yet their is ſome difference. They were captiues ād priſoners vnder their enimies, in a ſtrange countrie, but you are yet in your owne countrie and howſes (thogh moſte vnnaturally you haue dryuen out many by tyranny). You haue yet your owne lawes amongeſt you, that is, the Lawe of God ād of your Realme, if you woulde vſe them: by the which you haue had all peace ād quietnes. And in cō
               temning theſe, ye ſee in to what caſe ye are broght, and in to what miſerie, readie to fall. You may yet with Gods helpe,

and your endeuor promote his glory, vnderprop that Realme and comon welth, which by your falſehod is fallīg in to vtter ruine. The fall wherof, you ād yours chiefly, which haue greateſt charge ſhall haue greateſte cauſe to bewayle.
            If your Ieſabell, thoghe ſhe be an vnlawfull Gouerneſſe, and oght not by Gods word and your owne lawes to rule, would ſeke your peace and protectiō as did Nabuchadnezer to his captiues the Iewes: then might you haue ſome pretence to follow Ieremies counſelle: that is,Nabuchadnezer is to be p
                     ••
                  f
                     •
                  rred to your Ieſab
                     •
                  l in the z
                     •
                  ale of God Nabuchadn
                     •
                  zers decree. Daniel. 3.
                to be quiete, and praye for her liſſe, if ſhe would cōfeſſe the onelie God of the Chriſtians, and not compell you to idolatrie no more then did Nabuchadnezer: who acknowledged the God of the Iewes to be the true and euerlaſting God, and gaue the ſame commādement throughout all his dominiōs, That what ſoeuer people or nation ſpake euill of the God of Iſraell ſhuld be rent in pieces,Ieſabel worſhi
                     •
                  p
                     •
                  th Maozin ād cauſ
                     •
                  th others to do the like. and his howſe counted deteſtable. For (ſaith he) Ther is no other true God that ſo coulde deliuer his ſeruātes, as he did Sidrach Miſach ad Abdenago.
            But becauſe her doīges tēd all to the contrarie, that is to blaſpheme God, ād

alſo compell all others to do the like, what cloke haue you here to permitte this wickedneſſe?
            To be ſhorte, if ſhe at the burninge of three hundreth Martyrs at the leſte, coulde haue bene ſatisfied ād vnfaynedly moued to confeſſe the true Chriſte and Meſsias, and repented her former rebellion in geuing contrarie commandement to all her dominions, charging thē to receaue agayne the true religion and to expell all blaſphemous idolatrie of the peſtilent papiſtes: and that none ſhulde ſpeake any euill agaynſt Chriſte and his Religiō (as did Nabuchadnezer by the exāple of three perſōs onely, whō the fire by the power of God coulde not touche) then were ſhe more to be borne with, and reuerenced as a Ruler (if it were lawfull for a woman to rule at all) then were there alſo ſome probabilitie in the reaſons of the aduerſaries of this doctrīe. Otherwiſe as you now ſee, it maketh nothing at all for their purpoſe.
            Another Argumēt is gathered of the words written in the ſame Prophet Ieremie:The ſecond obiection out of Ieremie. 27.
                ſpeaking of the dominion which God was purpoſed to geue vnto Nabuchadnezer kīge of Babylō on this wiſe:

I haue made the earthe ād mē (ſaithe the Lorde) ād the beaſtes vpō the earthe in my ſtrēgth and ſtretched out hand, and it do I geue to him that pleaſeth me. And therfore haue I geuē all this lande in to the hands of Nabuchadnezer my ſeruant. And all natiōs and mightie kinges ſhall ſerue him, and till the tyme of his lande do come, that is, till I viſite him, and his countrie alſo. And it ſhall come to paſſe, that I will viſite the nation or kingdome which will not ſerue the kinge of Babell with ſworde, famine, and peſtilēce. Wherfore ſerue ye the kinge of Babell and lyue. Beholde, ſaye they, (who thinke it in no caſe lawfull to withſtande vngodlie Rulers) This wicked kinge is cōſtitute of God, and made his ſeruante. And moreouer thoſe that ſhulde withſtand him, are curſed and threatned with ſword, famine, and peſtilence. And therfore to diſobey ſuche,Anſwere. Ieremie. 5. wherfore Tyrantes are called Gods inſtrumentes. muſte nedes be vnlawfull.
            Nabuchadnezer as it is wrytten in Ieremie, is called the maule of the Lorde, and his inſtrumēt of warre, by the which he was determyned to beate doune all Nations and kingdoms, puniſhing them

for their ſynnes and idolatrie. And therfore the Lorde calleth him his ſeruāte, for that he had choſē him to that office. Nether oght we to maruell that God will vſe the labours of vngodlye perſones, ſeing all being his creatures are at his commandement, as is Satan with all his infernall ſpirites. Then God, hauing appoynted Nabuchadnezer to this office to be his tormentor, as well in ſkourginge ād correcting his owne people, as in deſtroyinge his open enimies: it was requiſite that God ſhuld miniſter vnto him ſufficient power, for the accompliſhment of his determinat counſelle, which the Lorde did in ſuch abundance, as no Nation was able to reſiſte him, that ſhuld not periſhe either with the ſworde of Nabuchadnezer, or famine, either els in that the Lorde hī ſelf would from heauen fight on his parte withe the plague of peſtilence.
            And of this what thing els gather we, but firſte the purpoſe of Ieremie: that was to drawe the Iewes frō their follie, which after they had once forſaken the Lorde by rebellion, did thinke alſo by their policie to eſcape Gods appoynted

puniſhmēt. No no, woulde Ieremie ſay: it is to late,The meaning of the Prophet. and ye are to weake to fight againſte the Lorde whoſe worke this is. When ye were Lordes within your ſelues, and had full libertie to honor your Lorde God, accordīge to the Lawes whiche he gaue vnto you, and whereby ye were aſſured to lyue without feare of all natiōs, you wolde not. And therfore ſhall you ſerue a ſtrange kinge, ſtrange lawes, and a ſtrāge nation til you be wel corrected ād humbled: till you haue felt by experience what an ineſtimable cō
               fort it is to haue the liuinge Lorde to be your kinge ād gouernour. And therfor woulde Ierē. ſay, Serue Nabuchadnezer.
            Seinge thē this is the appoynted plague of God for diſobeyinge him and his Lawes, to ſerue ſtrange kinges, and to be captiues▪ you are hereby warned ād taught, rather to turne with all ſpede to the liuinge Lorde, and to ſet vp his true religiō againe, that he may defend you: thē in proceadinge in your blaſphemye for the cōmandement and feare of any creature, to haſten Gods wrath and Iudgements. The Iſraelites becauſe they woulde not receaue the oft admonitiōs

of Gods P
                  •
               ophetes to feare the Lord, cooulde not afterwarde eſcape his plagues, nor the feare of men: no more ſhal you (ô inhabiters of Englāde) without ſpeedie repētance eſcape the Spayniſhe plague of adoulterous Philippe whom the Lorde will make his ſworde and maul to beate downe your townes and Cities, ād to deuoure the people therof.Mans yoke is vnſupportable. For ſeinge you haue with the Iſraelites forſakē the ſwete ād pleſant yoke of God and Chriſte his Sonne: you ſhal indure the importable yoke of this cruell and beaſtly nation.
            But what, ſhall we obey then ſay you? Yes verely: but againſt your wills in captiuite and thraldom, as did the Iſraelites in Egypt and Babylon, to ſerue them with your bodyes and goodes. Seinge ye woulde departe with nothinge to ſerue our Maiſter and Sauiour Chriſt, thinke you to eſcape this by obeyinge your wicked Rulers? By what other means haue you fallen into the handes of your enemies, but by this kinde of obedience onely? Whiche as you haue harde ſufficiently proued, is in Gods ſight plaine diſobedience and rebellion. But you

will ſay: Ieremie willed the Iewes to ſerue Nabuchadnezer which was a wicked Prince, and then with out the feare of God, and therfore are we bownd to ſerue our Quene, thoghe ſhe be an vngodly idolatres?what obedience and ſeruice Ieremie requireth. Ieremie ſpeaketh but of bodely ſeruice, and ſuch as ſubiectes owe to their ſuperiours in Ciuile ordinaunces, and outwarde doinges, and not to defile their conſciences in committing euill. For in ſuche thīges, both God and his Prophetes, and the examples of all the godly do forbid all obediēce. They were made ſubiectes to the kinge of Babylon to ſerue him with their bodies and goodes, as were his owne people: and alſo to paye tribute to him as did ſtrangers, which he had likewiſe ſubdued. The which thing was for their puniſhment. And therfore of duetie they muſt patientlie beare them.
            Thē in fewe wordes I anſwere, that althoghe it be moſte lawfull with patience to beare the puniſhment of the Lorde for our ſynne, and not to repine or rebell agaynſt it: yet is it our parte neuertheleſſe, and bownden duety, to defende and mayntayne the cauſe of God

with all our might: and to whithſtand all maner of aduerſaries, euen to the loſſe of our goods and liues: being euer aſſured of this promeſſe of our Sauiour and Maiſter, That he that loſeth his liffe for his ſake, ſhall finde it:
                  Mat. 19. and he that loſeth father or mother, frindes or goodes in his cauſe, ſhall be rewarded an hundreth folde in this worlde, and in the worlde to come with liffe euerlaſting.
            It is not then wiſedome to repine at the rodde when it is layde vpon vs to beate vs, but to returne backe to our mercifull Father with vnfayned repentance,Godes plagues oght to moue vs to repentance and not to harden vs in euill. calling for mercy before hande whiles he doth but menace vs. And therfore the threatning or counſelle of Ieremie, is but an admonition for vs to obeye God in true religion whan we haue tyme: that therby we may eſcape the like plagues: ād no defēce at all for our vngodlie behauiour in yelding to the deuiliſhe decrees of anie vngodly Magiſtrates, what names or titles ſoeuer they beare. For this anſwere of the Apoſtles muſt euer more preuaile: God muſt be obeyed rather then man. And there is no obedience in euil that can

pleaſe the almightie.
            Laſte of all we haue to conſider the ſainge and doinge of the worthie ſeruante of God the kinge and Prophet Dauid,The thirde obiection. 
               1. Sā. 24 and .49. who woulde not lift vp his hand againſte kinge Saule, notwithſtanding he ſought to haue murthered Dauid, ſaīge: God forbid that I ſhoulde touche the anoynted of the Lorde: and why? Becauſe he is the anoynted of the Lorde. If it be not lawfull thē to touche the kinge becauſe he is the Lordes anoynted: it is likewiſe vnlawfull to diſobey or reſiſte, for that he is the Lords anoynted.
            
               AnſwereTo whiche I anſwere, that to conſider the bare wordes, it woulde ſeeme true as they ſay: but wayīge the cauſe, the matter is eaſie to anſwere.The cauſe why Dauid was hated of Saule. The occaſion wherfore Saul, hated Dauid, was for that he knewe he ſhould ſucceade him in his kingdome. As Saule him ſelfe doth confeſſe in the ſame Chapter, ſaynge: I knowe of a ſuertie that thou ſhalt reigne, and that the kingdom of Iſraell ſhal be eſtabliſſhed in thy hande.1. Sa. 24 Swere to me therfore by the Lorde, that thou wilte not cut of my ſeed after me, nor deſtroye my name frome my fathers howſe. This

beinge thē Dauids owne priuate cauſe,None oght to reuenge his owne priuate cauſe. it was not lawfull for him in that caſe to ſeke his owne reuengemēt: eſpecially in murtheringe violently his anoynted kinge, and the anoynted of the Lorde. For it is not written of Saule, that he was an idolatrer or conſtrayned his people to worſhippe ſtrange Godes, nor yet was aboute to ſel thē to the enemies of God the Philiſtines, againſt whom he foghte manfully and many tymes. Nether that he was an open oppreſſor and cōtemner of the Lawes of God, as are this day all the rulers in miſerable England. And therfore Dauid beinge but a priuate man, coulde haue done no violence to his kinge without Godes eſpecial inſpiratiō,Rulers cō
                  temninge Gods lawes are as well ſubiect to the puniſhement of the ſame as priuat perſōs. except in reuēginge his priuat cauſe he had vſurped Gods office and ſoght to haue eſtabliſhed him ſelf in his kingdome, not taryīge the Lords appoītmēt.
            But where as the kinges or Rulers are become altogether blaſphemers of God, and oppreſſors and murtherers of their ſubiectes, then oght they to be accōpted no more for kinges or lawfull Magiſtrats, but as priuate mē: and to be examined, accuſed, condemned and puniſhed by the Lawe of God, wherunto

they are and oght to be ſubiect, and being conuicted and puniſhed by that Lawe, it is not mās, but Gods doing: who as he dothe appoynte ſuch Magiſtrates ouer his people by his Lawe, ſo doth he condemne aſwel them as the people trāſgreſsing agaynſte the Lawe. For with God ther is no reſpecte of perſones, as here after folowith more largely.
            Thus we ſee that althoghe Dauid thoght it not lawful in his priuate cauſe to touche Gods anoynted, yet are no people or nation therby cōſtrayned either ot obeye their anoynted in vnlawful demandes, or els forbidden to withſtand the open tranſgreſsion of Gods Lawes and mans. For in that caſe Saules ſeruauntes would not obeye him,1. Sam. 22 commandinge them to murther Ahimelech and the reſt of the Leuites ād Prieſtes:
                  Deu. 17. ſo that not to withſtand ſuch rages of Princes in tyme according as the Lawe requireth (which commandeth that the euill be taken forth from amōgeſt you) is to geue them the bridle to all kynde of miſchiffe, to ſubuerte all Lawes of God and man, to let will rule for reaſon, and therby to inflame Gods wrathe

agaynſt you, wholy, as your ſelues in Englande are this day an example to all natiōs and people that beare the Name of Chriſte.
            Theſe are the obiections for the moſte parte, or at the leaſt the chiefeſt,The obiections do cleare this doctrine and nothinge darken it. which are comonly alleadged agaynſt this veritie moſte playne and euidente: that is that there is no obedience to be alowed agaynſt God, which is not in his ſight diſobedience. Alſo that it is lawfull for all men according to their vocatiō to reſiſte to the vttermoſt of their power all ſuch as are open enimies of God, and labour to make them ſlaues to Satan. Theſe obiections as you playnly ſee, make nothing to the cōtrarie: but if they ſhall be depely conſidered, do rather ſtrongly confirme the ſame. Therfore deare brethern, let no man feare to ſhewe him ſelf Gods ſeruante openly, and to forſake in tyme the ſhamefull bōdage of Satan, to call back the trueth of Gods worde agayne, wherby ye were once in freedome both of conſciēce and bodie: and vtterly to aboliſhe all vile papiſtrie the doctrine of deuils, and onely cauſe of all your calamitie,

both of bodie and ſoule.
         
         
            CHAP. XI. 
            
               It apperteyneth not onely to the Magiſtrates and al oth
                     •
                  r inferior officers to ſee that their Princes be ſubiect to Gods Lawes, but to the comon people alſo: wherby the tyrannie of the Princes and rebellion of the ſubiects may be auoyded.
            
            
               TO reſiſte euill and to mayntayne goodneſſe, to honor God truely and to expel idolatrie, euery man will confeſſe to be a good and godly acte, ād cannot but highlie commende the workers therof, as men acceptable to God, and worthie members of a comon welthe: but when men cōſider the daungers and diſpleaſures, which commonly happen to ſuch, then is there great curteſie made who firſt ſhall take the enterpriſe in hand: and longe diſputations made whither it be their duetie or no: and to what ſortes of men it doth belong, as thogh any were exempted out of that nomber which do profeſſe the Name of God. If the ſuperior power be an idolat
                  •
               er or a cruel tyrant ſuppreſsing true religion and murthering the Sainctes of

God (as Ieſabel of England doth with all her rable of papiſtical Biſhopps, and ſhauelinges) who is ſo ignorant of God, or deſtitute of all humanitie or natural iudgment, that wil not aknowledge ſuch a one to be vnworthie the ſocietie of the godly and honeſt: muche leſſe to haue the auctoritie and rule ouer great nations and whole kingdoms?
            And not with out cauſe. For by the Ciuile Lawes, a foole or idiot borne, and ſo proued, ſhall loſe his landes and inheritance wherunto he is borne, becauſe he is not able to vſe them a right: but eſpecially oght in no caſe to be ſuffered to haue the regiment of a whole nation or kingdome. And it is moſte certeyne that there is no ſuch euil can come to any comon welth by fooles and idiots, as dothe by the rage and furie of vngodly Rulers, maynteyners of idolatrie ād tyrannie. For follie hath comonly ioyned with it ſimplicitie,The gouuernemēt of fooles more tolerable then of tyrants. voyde of malice and eaſie to be ordered: but idolatrie and tyrānie reſēbleth more the nature of wilde beaſtes, cruell beares, ād ragīg lyōs, thē the cōdicion of mā. For ſimplicitie, they are repleniſhed with craftines▪ for loue,

they ſhew malice: and for patience, furious rage ād madneſſe and beinge borne as it were a comō plague to all men, cannot once ſtudie for the preſeruation of a fewe.
            This beſides reaſon, experience teacheth all men to be moſte true, that it were better to haue anie foole, thē ſuch an vntamed beaſte to be ouer thē. And that ſuche being altogether with out God, oght to haue no auctoritie ouer the people of God, who by his worde requireth the contrarie as is moſte manifeſte. And yet to puniſhe, and depoſe ſuch a one according to the commandemēt of God,
                  Deu. 17. there is none that thinketh it Lawfull: or at the leaſt will confeſſe it to appertayne vnto them, either to do it them ſelues, or to ſee it done by others. As for the wicked counſellers, they are playne Gnatos and flatterers,Suche as onelye flatter the apptites of their prince. thinking their office to be applyed vnto their kī
               ges and Quenes will, as thogh they had no charge of the whole Realme. And therfore will labour to cōpaſſe nothīge but that which their Princes luſt after, or may at the leaſt pleaſe them, not paſſing if the whole Realme do periſhe, ſo

they maye obtayne their fauours. Suche, Achitophels deſerue to haue Achitophels rewarde, for their deuiliſhe coū
               ſelle with out mercie. And as it is with them, ſo is it with the reſte of all eſtates, as before hath bene touched. Neuertheleſſe, the matter is ſo euident vpon their partes, that all will cōfeſſe that it chiefly belōgeth to inferior Magiſtrats to ſee a redreſſe in ſuch diſordres: and they thē ſelues can not well deny it.
            But as touching the comon and ſymple people, they thinke them ſelues vtterly diſcharged, whither their Prince be godlie or vngodlye, wiſe or fooliſhe,The vaine excuſe of the cōmū people. a preſeruer of the comon welthe or ells a diſtroyer, all is one to them, they muſte be obedient, becauſe they are ignorant, and muſte be led them ſelues, not meete to leade others. And becauſe their doinges are counted tumultes and rebellion (except they be agreable to the commandmentes, decrees, and proceadinges of their ſuperior powers and Magiſtrates, and ſhal in doing the contrary be as rebells puniſhed) therfore of all others (ſay they) we haue leaſt to do, yea nothing at all withe the doinges of our

Rulers. Yf they rule well, we ſhall fare the better: if they be vngodly they haue the more to anſwere for their vngodlyneſſe. What haue we to do with their matters? Thus do all ſortes of men from the higheſt to the loueſt ſlyppe their heades out of the coller: and as careles perſones not paſsing which end goeth forwarde, geueth the brydle wholie to their Rulers till deſtruction remediles ouerflowe all.
            To the intent therfore that this ſimplicitie, ignorāce, and ſubiection of the inferior people, do not altogether blynde them, and cauſe them (as hitherto it hath bene proued almoſt in all places and countries) to ſuffer them ſelues like brute beaſtes rather then reaſonable creatures, to be led and drawen where ſo euer their Princes commandementes haue called: either to arme them ſelues agaynſt Chriſt their Sauiour in ouerthrowing the truthe of his Goſpel to bringe in Antichriſte and papiſtrie: or els to fyght agaynſt their owne brethern the ſeruātes of God, to robbe them, expel them out of their one howſes, poſſeſsions and countrie, to torment them and cruelly

put them to death: as thoghe the cōmandement of the Prince coulde make that lawfull, which God forbiddeth as deteſtable:Ignorance can not excuſe the people. as thoghe they being made inſtruments to their Princes in executing vngodly tyrannie, ſhulde not be partakers likewiſe with thē of Gods vengeāce in the daye of his dreadfull viſitatiō, whē nether their ignorāce can excuſe, them, nether cōmandement of kinge or Prince defende thē, but they workinge wickedneſſe with their Rulers ſhall drinke of the ſame cup with them alſo.
            To the intent (I ſaie) that they ſhulde be no more ſo blynded, nor runne headlonge (as they do) to their owne deſtruction: I haue thoght good moreouer and beſides that which hitherto hathe bene ſpoken in general (wherof notwithſtanding they might alſo gather what belongeth to them in their condicion and eſtate) to ſnewe vnto them more eſpecially what may be demanded of comon people by Gods worde, and what the people alſo may lawfully deny to do by the ſame worde of God. Which as it oght to be permitted and preached to all men in general: ſo

ſhulde it be the comon and onely rule wherby to frame and ordre all mens liues and doinges.
            And to auoyde all incomodities that are accuſtomed to happen in all comon welthes,
                  Two extremities to be auoyded.
                  To muche libertie is not to be permitted to the people.
                as wel vpon the Magiſtrats parte as of the people, there are two extremities: wherof bothe muſte be warned. The firſt is, that the Magiſtrates permit not to their ſubiectes ouermuche libertie, leaſt therby they fall in to contempte and ſubiection of their people: wherof folowethe for the moſte parte, all kynde of diſſolutneſſe, ād carnall libertie, ſubuertiō of all good Lawes and ordres, alteracion of common welthes and policies, contempt of God and man: and to be ſhorte, all thinges turned to diſorder and confuſion. The ſeconde apparteyneth on the other parte, to the people,The libertie of the people. which oght not to ſuffer all power and libertie to be taken from them, and therby to become brute beaſtes, with out iudgmente and reaſon, thinking all thinges lawfull, which their Rulers do with out exceptiō, commāde them, be they neuer ſo farre from reaſon or godlyneſſe: as thoghe they

were not reaſonable creatures, but brute beaſtes: as thoghe there were no difference betwixt bonde ſlaues, and free ſubiectes: and as thoghe they had no portiō or right at all in the coūtrie where they inhabite: but as they were altogether created of God to ſerue their kinges and gouernors like ſlaues, and not their kings &amp; gouernors appoynted of God to preſerue his people, wher of they are but a portion and members, albeit they occupie the cheif roume ād office, not to bringe the reſt of the members in cōtempte and bondage, but to comforte them, defende them, and noriſhe them as members of the ſame bodie.
            And as the people may be aſſured by Gods worde that this libertie apparteyneth to them, which becommeth members of one bodie and brethern,Deu. 17. Subiectes oght not to ſuffer thē ſelues to be made ſlaues. becauſe the Lorde God him ſelf (from whom kinges haue their auctoritie and power) calleth their ſubiectes and people their brethern, charging them in no caſe to lift them ſelues aboue them, but as brethern to rule in all humbleneſſe and loue ouer them: euenſo, the people, if they ſuffer this right to be taken from them,

which God of his ſinguler fauour hath graunted then are they an occaſiō that their kīges and Rulers are turned to tyrantes,1 Sam 8 and cruel oppreſſors, according as Samuel promiſed the people of Iſrael ſhulde come vpon them, inſomuche as they had refuſed his gouernement, who ruled ouer them, in all iuſtice, and humbleneſſe, and in ſuch ſorte as no man coulde charge him with any crime. And therfore the Scriptures pronounce that they reiected not Samuel, but God him ſelf ī whoſe feare he ruled. This (ſaith Samuel) ſhal be the Lawe of the kīge, which ſhall rule ouer you. Your childrē ſhall he take to ſerue in his chariot, and to be his horſe men,The deſcrip
                     •
                  ion of a wicked kinge and tyrante. and they ſhall runne before his chariot, and he ſhall conſtitute alſo Captayns of a thouſand, and of fiue hundreth, and others to till his grownde, and to gather his harueſte, to make weapons for warre, and harneſſe for his chariots. Moreouer, he ſhall take your daughters to make his anoyntmēts, to ſerue his kitchin, and to be his clothiers: beſides this he ſhall take your fyeldes and your vineyardes, your beſte orchardes of oliues and geue to his ſeruaunts, and of your corne and vines

ſhall he take the tenthes, and geue them to his Eunuches, and ſeruauntes: your ſeruauntes alſo and maydes and the chif of your youthe and your aſſes, ſhall he take to do his worke. And of your cattell ſhall he take the tenth, and you ſhall become his ſeruauntes: and you ſhall crye out that day in the ſight of your kinge whom you haue choſen, and the Lorde God will not heare you that day: and why? Bycauſe they had rather haue a kinge and Ruler of their owne appoyntment, then of the Lordes.
            Wherfore to auoyde the daungers vpon both partes,Both Magiſtrates and cōmōs oght to obey Gods Lawes. it is more then neceſſarie that bothe be ſubiecte to that Rule, and with all diligent care, labour to reteyne it, wherby both maye learne their duetie, and be conſtrayned iuſtly to execute the ſame. For when the comon people and ſubiectes haue ſo large libertie by the negligence of their Rulers, that cuſtomes and vnlawful vſages ſhall be preferred to Gods Lawes, and ſtatutes, and that to maynteyne the ſame cuſtomes, they care nothing if all other good Lawes, either of God or man, do periſhe: how is it poſsible

without daungerous tumultes, and rebellion, to brynge them to any good ordre and reformation, except there be ſome comon, and approued Lawe, which verie nature, and the feare of God will teach them to reuerence, and obeye? As for example: amongs other cuſtomes which mayntayne idlenes, and ſerue the greedy appetite of the bellie (which all men are loth to forgo) how harde a thinge were it to bryng them frome their Sanctes dayes?kinge Edwarde de ſierous that God ſhuld haue had his due honour ſowght the aboliſhment of all Sainctes dayes. The aboliſhment wherof, godly king Edwarde in his tyme coulde not bryng to paſſe. So great was the nomber of Papiſtes in the Perlament houſe, which maīteyned thoſe ſuperſtitiouſe dayes, ſome bearīg the name of mē, ād ſome of womē, aſcrybīg that to the creatures of God, which apperteyneth to him alone, for as muche as euery day is the Lordes worke, and oght to ſerue to his honour onely. They haue nowe in tyme of papiſtrie, dayes of Peter and Paule, Marie,All dayes are the Lordes ād onelye appertayne vnto him and Iohn, withe the reſte of the Apoſtles: they haue Georges daye, and katherines, Dunſtans day the coniurer, and Loye the ſmithe, with innumerable others, which maynteyne the idleneſſe

of them and of their ſeruaunts contrarie to the ordinaunce of God,Sainctes days with the ſeruice appointed vnto them oght by Gods worde to be aboliſhed. appoynting ſix dayes for their trauell, and the ſeuenth daye onely to reſte, and that to the honoring of our Lorde God.
            Alſo by what means may the people be drawen from the dayes of riote and bancketing, which they terme frindly feaſting and goodfelloweſhipp: as from Whitſontides dronkennes and ſurfet, Midſōmers ſhewes and vanities,How harde a thing it is to alter euil cuſtomes. Chriſtmas riote and bawdry, Shroftetweſdayes glottony, and Lents ſuperſtitious obſeruations, excepte by ſome Lawe of greater importance, the rude people be otherwiſe perſwaded? And what other Lawes are there able to bringe this to paſſe beſides the Lawes of God? Wherin if they be not inſtructed, it is impoſsible for any auctoritie or power to withholde them, with out great daunger and tumultes from ſuch kinde of diſordres and vnlawfull cuſtomes.
            Therfore if thou be a Ruler and couete to haue the people obedient to thee in Gods feare,The means to breake euil cuſtome. this muſte be thy firſt and principall ſtudie to, procure

that they may truely know God by the playne and diligent preaching of his worde, wherī if they be well inſtructed, there is no cuſtome ſo longe continued, no idleneſſe ſo longe vſed, no ſuperſticion ſo deeply rooted, which they will not gladly and peaceably for go at thy commandement: yea, there is nothing which is euill, that they can for ſhame ſtande in: nor any good and lawfull demande, that they will deny thee. By theſe means onely ſhalt thou obtayne honour, maintayne thy right, winne the hartes of thy people, and haue them all obedient.
            And as the Magiſtrates by this means, are ſure to finde obedience, and eſcape all rebellion, tumultes and diſordres amonges their ſubiectes: euenſo is there no other rule for the ſubiectes to eſcape the idolatrie, tyrannie, and oppreſsion of their ſuperiors, then in reteyning (as their chief poſſeſsion) the ſelf ſame Lawe and worde of God. Permitting rather all thinges wordlie to be taken from them, as landes, goodes, houſe, cōtrie, father, mother, wiffe, children, yea liffe it ſelf, then to be depriued

by any means of that heauenly treaſure and precious perle,
                  Mat. 13. for the which they muſt ſell althinges. Wherof to be fullie perſwaded, it is neceſſary to vnderſtande what maner of people you are.
            Yf you be the people of God, and vnfayned Chriſtians, then muſte ye alſo knowe that the Lawe of God,what treaſures God hath committed to the charge of his people. and Chriſte your Sauiour, doth appertayne vnto you: wherin, as without ſhame ād condemnation ye may not be ignorāt: euenſo no power, commandment, or threatninges, ſhulde cauſe you to departe from it, wherin onely ſtandethe that comforte and ſaluation, which no creature can reſtore agayne vnto you.
            The heathen which knewe not God a right, but were idolatrers, yet made their religiō to haue the higheſt place in their comon welthes: as Ariſtotle writeth in his Politiques. In the name wherof they might demande any thinge of their kinges and Rulers, and they durſt not denye them: and might alſo with out offence deny all thinges which their Rulers demaunded contrarie to their religion. In ſo muche as this

prouerbe was comon amongeſt all, Vſque ad Aras: meaning that agaynſt their religion (as they were perſwaded) they were bownde to no perſone: father, mother, frende, or gouernour: their loue ād obedience towardes thē coulde ſtretch no further then to the Altars, that is, ſo farre as with obſeruing their religion, they might lawfullye performe.
            Yf the Gentills then had their religion in ſuch honour and reuerence that agaynſt it (thoghe in dede it was meere ſuperſtition and idolatrie) they woulde acknowledge no obedience: in what eſtimation ſhulde Gods worde and the religion of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte be amongeſt vs that profeſſe his Name, and are aſſured of his doctrine to be the vndouted trueth and power of God to ſaluacion of all beleuers?In what reuerence we oght to haue Gods worde. Yf the heathen kinges and Magiſtrates coulde cō
               pell their ſubiectes no farther then the Alters: ſhall any auctoritie or power compell vs farther then God, and his anoynted our chief kinge, Lorde ād Maiſter? Let it be counted ſhame to vs, that the ignorant Gentils ſhuld be founde more carefull and zelous in defending

their ſuperſtition and manifeſte idolatrie, then we are in mayntayning the true worſhip of God and his heauenly wiſedome.
            Yf we were Turkes, Saraſins, Iewes or papiſtes, which either knewe not God a right, or els denied his Sonne Ieſus: it were no great maruell if we were led after the luſtes of our vngodly Princes. For as our Maiſter teacheth, When the blynde leadeth the blynde,
                  Mat. 15. bothe fall in to the diche. But if we will be taken for the people of God and his ſonnes by adoption in Chriſt Ieſus, then it behoueth vs likewiſe to geue obediēce, principally to our Lorde and Maiſter, to our mightie God and moſte louinge Father, as Malachi the Prophet exhorteth.
                  Mala. 1. The ſonne reuerenceth the father, and the ſeruaūt the maiſter: yf I be your Father (ſaith the Lorde) where is the honor that you geue me? Yf I be your Lorde and Maiſter where is my feare? Notinge vnto vs how it is in vayne to call him Father or Lorde, ſo long as we geue him not that honour and reuerence which he demandeth.
            Alſo, if we will not be taken for

blynde and ignorante perſones, then muſt we ſhewe forth this light by walking as becomethe the childrē of light,
                  Ephe. 5. Iohn. 12. as the Apoſtle requirethe indifferently of all Gods children with out exceptiō, or excuſe either of guide or Ruler. For the blyndneſſe of our guide, whither he be of the Cleargie or Laytie may be no excuſe to vs, if in folowing him we fall and periſhe: it is our owne faute, and we muſt beare our owne iudgment. For Chriſte hereof admoniſheth vs:
                  Mat 15. Let thē a lone (ſaithe he) for they are blind guides, and leaders of the blynd. And agayne,
                  Mat. 23. accordinge to their workes, ſee ye do not.
            Yf thou hauynge ſight, had appoynted to thee a blynde guide, wouldeſte thou folowe him into a daungerouſe pit or deepe water, wherin both might periſhe becauſe he was thy guide? Then truely mighteſt thou be iudged of all men worſe then either oxe or aſſe, or any other vnreaſonable beaſte, whiche will not be driuē in ſuch places, as to their outwarde ſēſes appeare daūgerous.
            Nature onely teacheth all creatures this, to flie frome thoſe daungers that

ſhulde hurte them: and to deſier all thinges that do them good.Nature teacheth to flee hurtful thinges And when God hath made this comon to all beaſtes, ād inferior creatures, paynefully to ſeeke their preſeruation: hathe he denied the ſame to man, whome aboue all others he will haue preſerued?God hath created all thinges for mans commodite For whoſe preſeruation chieflie he hath not onely created all thīges and preſcribed his Lawes and commandements to prohibet murther, and euery other thinge tendinge to his deſtruction: but alſo to ſhewe the abundance of his mercies, ſpared not his dearelye belouid Sonne, but gaue him to the cruell death of the Croſſe, that man might haue full ſaluation, not onely here in this world, but euerlaſtingly in the worlde to come.
            Wherfore, if he tender vs ſo muche, as to ſeeke by all meās poſsible our liffe and preſeruation, then muſt it likewiſe followe, that he hath conſtitute no lawes, or ordinances to our deſtruction, ſo longe as we ſhall be founde obedient vnto them. Then is there no power that ruleth accordinge to theſe lawes, which either can or will cōmande vs anie thī
               ge, tēdinge to our deſtructiō. But if anie

ſo do by Gods permiſsion becauſe of our ſynnes,
                  Tobi. 3. Eſai. 3. ād rebellion towardes him (for which cauſe onelie he ſuffreth wicked Princes to be our Gouernours) it is (deare brethren) to drawe vs to repentaunce, and knowledge of our ſynnes, and not that we ſhulde forſake the Lawes of our God, and to contynew in our wonted rebellion, by yelding to the vngodlie commandments of wicked men.
         
         
            CHAP. XII. 
            
               ¶How muche the comon people owe to God for his benefits receaued, what obedience he requirethe, how farre they are charged, what thinges they haue promiſed, and how ignoraunce maye not excuſe them.
            
            
               ALL theſe thinges being well conſidered, it is an eaſie matter for all maner of ſubiectes to knowe what libertie belongeth vnto them, by the worde of God, whiche they maye lawfullie clayme, as their owne poſseſsiō, and are likewiſe bounde at all tymes to practiſe: wherin alſo appeareth what thinges are prohibited vnto them, whiche

they maye in no caſe exerciſe. Yf you therfore be Gods ſubiectes and people, and he your Lorde God and louinge Father, who is aboue all powers ād Princes, ād hath made no Lawes, but ſuch as are for your preſeruation, and ſinguler comforte: then without all controuerſie there maye be nothinge lawfull for you by anie commandment of man, whiche your Lorde God in anie caſe forbiddeth: and nothinge vnlawfull or forbidden to you whiche he commandeth, whither it appartayne to the firſte Table or the Seconde.A rule for all to obſerue. Which rule if ye obſerue, you maye be aſſured to pleaſe God: like as by doinge the contrarie, ye ſhall purchaſe his heauie wrathe and indignation. For no mā can ſerue two Maiſters at once: but he ſhall hate the one, ād loue the other.
                  Mat. 6. And in hatinge your firſte and chief Lorde to obeye and pleaſe man, beholde your impietie is intolerable, prefarringe vile mā his creature, to the Almightie God and creator of all.
            How muche we are bownde to his Maieſtie, our owne conſcience doth beare vs witneſſe: whiche can not deny but

that we haue receauid of him alone our liffe mouing and being, our wiſedome ſtrēgthe, bewtie, riches, childrē, ād all thī
               ges that are good ād profitable, in whoſe power we may do all thīges,
                  Pſ. 1.7.17 ād with out hī all fleſhe is turned to duſt ād powder.
            
               Moyſes charged hys with nothinge that God had not commanded.Remember the example of the worthie Captayne and Prince Moyſes, whō God choſe to delyuer his people from Egypt, who woulde not charge thē with anie thinge at any tyme whiche the Lorde his God had not commanded, euermore ſpeakinge on this wiſe, Theſe are the ſtatutes and preceptes of the Lorde: Thus ſayth the Lorde:
                  Exod. 19. Deu. 4.20 and, Heare ô Iſrael the voyce of the Lord, &amp;c. In ſo muche, as he had this for his onlie ſhilde agaynſte the murmuring people: It is not agaynſt Aaron and me that ye murmure but againſt the Lorde: which beīg choſen and appoynted of the Lorde, did onely execute his will and commandementes. Yea, as for them ſelues they cō
               feſſed that they were nothinge. As for vs (ſayde Moyſes) what are we? meaninge but earth ād aſſhes, the creaturs of God, nothinge differinge from others, ſauing for that auctoritie, wherunto they were

called, ād the obediēce which they ſhewed in executīge not their owne willes, but the will and pleaſure of God.
                  Deut. 10 And why? but becauſe they knew they were the people of God with whō they were charged, and beinge his people,Godes people muſt be gouerned onely by Gods Lawes. Exod. 19.
                how it behoueth them to be ruled by no other Lawes and ordinances, then by ſuch as God had geuen them.
            Wherfore if Moyſes and Aaron, Gods electe and choſen ſeruants had no more power ouer the people then his expreſſe comandement permit, and that the people ſo far and no farther were bownd to obeye them: how can we aſſure our ſelues that we offende not Gods Maieſtie, whoſe people we woulde be called, whē witheout his worde, yea cōtrary to his expreſſe cōmandemēt we ſatisfie the requeſtes and ſtatutes of vngodly rulers?
            For as Moyſes coulde cōmande nothī
               ge but frō the mouthe of the Lorde: ſo coulde the people obey nothing but that whiche proceaded from his mouthe alſo: aſwell becauſe they were his people, as for that they had (opromiſed with one voyce and conſent before God ād Moyſes, whē the Lorde commanded

him to ſay on this wiſe to the people. You haue ſeene what I haue done to the Egyptians, and how I haue caried you vpon the winges of Egels, and led you forthe to me. Yf therfore ye will diligētlye heare my voice, and obſerue my cō
               mandement, you ſhalbe my propre people before all nations: For myne is the earthe. And you ſhalbe vnto me a kyngely Prieſthod, and an holy people. Whiche wordes when Moſes had pronounced before the whole people, they all to gether with one accord,The people promiſs to God and Moſes. āſwered: Whatſoeuer the Lorde ſhall ſpeake, that will we do. And Moyſes praiſed them (or God rather by moyſes) ſainge, They did well in ſo anſwering.
                  Deu. 18. And therfore promiſed to rayſe them vp a Prophet like to him, &amp;c. And this was the couenant onlye that God made with them before he gaue them the Lawe in wrytinge, and the promes that they made to obſerue the ſame Lawe, that they might therby be his deare and choſen people.
            This example ought neuer to departe from the eyes of all ſuch as are, or woulde be Gods people. Wherin as

in a moſt clere glaſſe it dothe appeare how they are bownd to God, what God requireth of them, and what they haue promiſed to him. For as the Lorde God required nothinge of the Iſraelits, but that whiche was their duetie to do, and he by his exceadinge benefits in delyueringe them from their enimies had well deſerued: euen ſo he byndeth thē to nothinge, but to obeye him. Nether did they promiſſe anie farther, ſaynge: We will do all thinges (not what Moyſes or Aaron or anie other after them ſhall of them ſelues commande) but whatſoeuer our Lorde God ſhall ſpeake, that will we do. More then this God required not, nether were they bownde any farther but to the Lawes of God onely, whiche they promiſed for them and their poſteritie to obſerue.All chriſtians are no leſſe bonde to ob
                     •
                  y God and his Lawes, then were the Iſraelits. And God for that cauſe bleſſed them aboue all nations, with his vnſpeakable benefits.
            So are we no leſſe bownde to obeye the ſelf ſame God of Iſrael, whom we alſo profeſſe in Chriſte Ieſu our Moyſes and Captayne, by whom we are not onely delyuered from bodely ſeruitude,

but from the moſte vile and dangerous bondage of Satan through ſynne our ſpirituall enemie. To this worthieſt delyuerer alſo haue we in Baptiſme promiſed no leſe, yea, muche more obedience: becauſe of the more abundance of graces, which by him we haue receaued. And beſides this are moſte ſtraightly charged ſo to do. Not by the voyce of anie earthly creature, but by the mouth of God the Father ſpeakinge frō the heauens: This is my dearely beloued Sonne,
                  Mat. 4.17 in whom I am delited, heare him: whoſe fidelitie alſo no leſſe paſſed the faithfullneſſe of Moyſes, then did his honor and dignitie being the Sonne of God, and promyſed Sauiour, doing nothing at all, nor teaching any thing which his heuenly Father had not appoynted him to do and to teache.
            Wherfore, as the Iewes had the Lawe of God and his commandementes for a ſufficient diſcharge agaynſt all contrarie commandementes, of what auctoritie ſo euer they were, being no farther bownde to any creature thē the ſelf ſame Lawes of God approued: euenſo, all ſuch as beare the Name of Chriſt and woulde be taken for the people of God,

thoghe they be of the baſeſt ād loweſte ſtate of ſubiectes,The cōmā
                  dement of Princes cā
                  not bynd vs contrary to Gods worde. are no farther bownd to any Prince or ſuperior power, nor to their commandementes, then the cō
               mandement of the chief kinge ād Lorde doth approue ād permitte, nor then their promeſſe agayne to him doth require.
            Nether may it be a ſufficiēt diſcharge for thee to alleadge ignorāce, becauſe thou art a ſubiecte, and therfore haſt nothing to do, to inquire of the doinges or to examyne the commandementes of thy ſuperiors or Rulers,The vngodly opinion of the cōmō people. but wilt ſay with the multitude, If they commāde well thou art obedient, if otherwiſe thou art excuſed in doing as thou art cōmanded, and they onely haue to anſwer to God by whō thou art thus charged. Deſceaue not thy ſelf (deare brother) For aswell art thou charged by Gods worde to knowe what they commande thee, and not to do it except it be lawfull,As wel the obeyer of wickednes as the commāder ſhal be puniſhed. as they are charged by their office to will nothīg of thee, which Gods worde approueth not. For as they in commanding ād doing euill, ſhall not eſcape Gods heauy wrathe and iudgmētes: no more ſhalt thou, being made an inſtrument of

their impietie and vngodlyneſſe. Therfore to be ignorant in theſe thinges, althogh thou be a ſubiecte, is to contemne the commandement of God, and to neglecte thine owne ſaluation: for as muche as God hath charged thee beinge one of his people, with the ſame Lawes (the Ceremonies except) wherwithe he charged his people Iſrael before, and willith thee no leſſe to knowe his preceptes, and to obeye them, then he willed the Iſralites.
                  Deu. 6.11 Of them he required to haue his Lawes wrytē vpon their dores and poſtes, to inſtructe their children in the ſame, to talke of them ſitting at home, and when they walked in the waye, when they went to bed, and whē they ſhuld riſe.why the Chriſtiās oght greater obedience to Gods worde thē did the Iewes. Ioh 1.
                But to thee beſides all this, God hath ſent a more ſhining light, our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte: which euery man may clerely beholde, excepte he be wilfully blynde with the ſtubberne Iewes. He is the light that ſhinethe in darkneſſe, and lightneth euery man that commeth in to this worlde. He hathe taken away the ſhaddoues ād Ceremōies of the Lawe, that thou mayſt clerely beholde the will of his Father.

He hath vncouered Moyſes face,
                  Exod 34. 2. Cor. 3. to the-intent thou mayſt fully conſider the ſecrets of God. For theſe are the dayes wherof the Prophet Ioel ſpake,
                  Io
                        •
                     l. 2. Eſai▪
                   44. Act. 2. when all ſhulde be Prophets, and ſee viſiōs. And it ſhal come to paſſe in the latter dayes (ſaith God) that I wil powre furth my Spirite vpō all fleſhe, ād your ſonnes ād daughters ſhall prophecie, your younge men ſhall ſee viſions, and your auntients ſhall dreame dreames. And moreouer vpon my ſeruauntes and handemaydes in thoſe dayes, will I powre my Spirite, and they ſhall prophecie.
                  Act. 2. Which prophecie. S. Peter affirmeth to be fulfilled in the kingdome of Chriſte, where all thinges are as playne and euident to all ſortes of men and women, which profeſſe Chriſte vnfaynedly, as before his tyme they were to the Prophets them ſelues, or to ſuch as God appeared vnto in dreames or viſions.
            And therfore, if ignorance of Gods Lawes coulde not excuſe the Iewes before Chriſtes commyng, which were contynualy ſubiecte to the puniſhment of God for their tranſgreſsions (thoghe many thinges were obſcure as in ſhadowes

and figures: how muche leſſe cā it excuſe any mā now in ſo great lyght of the Goſpel? Seing then thou knoweſt thy ſelf bownd to obeye thy Lorde God aboue all others, becauſe of the ineſtimable benefits thou haſt receaued of him in Chriſte Ieſus, and becauſe he requireth the ſame of thee, and thou haſt alſo promiſed no leſſe to him in thy baptiſme and profeſsion: and laſt of all in that thou caneſt not pretende ignorance in ſuch knowledge▪ and ſhyninge brightneſſe, nor yet eſcape Gods vengeance, which he with out reſpecte of perſones wil powre indifferently vpon all tranſgreſſors, be they ſuperior powers, or inferior ſubiectes. It is thy parte then, beīg a ſubiecte, to learne this leſſon of the Apoſtles (whē ſo euer thou ſhuldeſt be conſtrayned,Both hie ād lowe muſt learn this leſſon of the Apoſtels. by commandement or force of tyrantes to do euill) That God muſt be obeyed before man. Which vnto thee will be as ſufficiēt a defence and buckler in all aſſaultes and daungers, as it is to all other ſortes of men in auctoritie and office: as was before declared.
            Art thow then, being a ſubiecte commaūded to worſhipp ſtockes and ſtones

which this day to our ſhame are erected agayne in Englande?Idols for the true God. Beholde thou haſt Gods commandement for thy defence: Thou ſhalt commit no idolatrie, nor make to thy ſelf any grauen image &amp;c.
                  Exod. 2
                     •
                  . Deu. 5. Art thou charged to be at the idolatrous Maſſe, wherin Chriſte thy Lorde is blaſphemed? Beholde,The abominable maſſe for the holy Supper of the Lords. he hath geuen thee an other charge: that is, to celebrate his Supper, according as he left in example, ſayng: Do you this, that is, which ye ſe me do, ād not which the powers of the worlde, or the peſtilēt papiſtes commande. Alſo do it (ſaith Chriſte) in remembrance of me,Mat. 26 Cōpariſon betwixt the maſſe and the Lordes Supper. 1. Cor. 11
                and not of your frindes alyue or departed, as teache the Papiſtes. For none of thē died for you. More ouer do it to ſhewe forth the deathe of Chriſte, til his coming, as witneſſeth the Apoſtle: and not to make a new ſacrifice for ſynne, as the Papiſts blaſphemouſly both teache and preache.How the Sabbath is abuſed. Art thou commanded by men to diſhonour the Sabbathe day in worſhipping of Sainctes and abſtayning vpon their dayes and euens from thy lawfull buſines? Beholde, God thy Lorde chargeth thee no further then onely with his daye of reſte, ſaying:

See thou keepe holie the Sabbath of the Lorde thy God: and not of Peter, Paule, Marie,To ſwear by Saincts is contrarie to Gods worde. Deut. 6.10 Ioſua. 23. Eſai 45.
                Iames or Iohn. Art thou commā
               ded to ſweare in the name of Marie and all the Saincts in heauen? (which is the papiſtical othe) Beholde, the Lorde ſaithe, Thow ſhalt onely ſweare in the Name of thy Lorde and God. Art thou commanded not onely to take the Name of the Lorde in vayne, but alſo to forſwere thy ſelf moſte ſhamefully agaynſt Gods glorious Maieſtie, and the honor of our Sauiour Chriſte? (as all they haue done which lately haue ſworne to acknowledge Antichriſte the bloudy butcher of Rome to be their head and gouernour) Beholde, The Lorde will not ſuffer his houſe vnpuniſhed that taketh his Name in vayne: muche leſſe ſuch periured and forſworen wretches. Art thou commanded to perſecute thy parentes and frendes, charged not to ſuccour them in their neceſsitie, becauſe they profeſſe the doctrine of ſaluation? Art thow forbidden lawfull mariage, becauſe thou art a miniſter of Gods worde, and permitted to lyue in all kinde of filthie vnclenneſſe, as do the Sodomiticall Prieſtes,

Mōkes, Freers, Nōnes, Cardinales, Deanes, Archdeacons, and all other other orders of Satan:
                  Leu. 20. beholde ſuch dothe the Lorde God as moſt abominable of all other, cōmāde to be put to death.
            To be ſhorte, when they contrarie to their othe and profeſsion, commande thee to receue Antichriſte, the beaſtlie Biſhoppe of Rome, with all his filthie dregges of damnation:The ſume of Antichriſts doctrine to burne the worde of God and the faithfull interpreters and profeſſers of the ſame: to forgo the comfortable preaching of the Goſpel, and reading of the Scriptures: to perſecute Chriſte in his mēbers: to ayde the enimies with thy goods and bodie agaynſt the deare childrē of God: to fight in other countries with out any iuſte cauſe or occaſion, and to ſuffer thy wiffe, children, kinſfolkes and countryemen to be moſte cruelly ſpoyled,Vnlawful warres. oppreſſed and murthered for want of thy defence at home (as they moſt ſhamfully haue done of late, which at the cō
               mandement of that cruell tyrāt,Oh lamē
                  table miſerie. prepared them ſelues to fight agaynſt the Frēche kinge, and their owne brethern the Skottes, whiles the Spaniards put

them ſelues in a redineſſe to entre the Realme and make a generall ſpoyle and pray of all.
            Theſe thinges and many ſuch like are playnly forbidden you by the manifeſt worde of God: and therfore to do them for feare or pleaſure of anie Prince or power, is playne diſobedience and rebellion agaynſt the Almightie. And contrarie wiſe, to anſwere in this caſe, and to do as the Apoſtles haue taught, that is, to obeye God rather then man, is the onely waye to diſcharge your cōſciences, to do your dueties, and to pleaſe God: no more to be made by ignorance the inſtrumentes of his ſworen enimies (what title ſo euer they beare) to ſubuerte Gods glorie, oppreſſe your brethern, and diſtroye your countrie: but repenting your former ignorance and impietie, to be made inſtrumentes of the contrarie to the vttermoſt of your power, leaſt you be taken in your ſynne, and preuented with the bitter cup of Gods indignatiō, alreadie prepared for the workers of iniquitie, and all ſuch, as are ayeders, and partakers with them, when nether power can defend the ſuperiors, nor their commandmentes,

excuſe the ſubiectes.
         
         
            CHAP. XIII. 
            
               The redineſſe of the people to defende idolatrie, ſuperstition, and earthly commodities: and their ſlouthfulneſſe in maynteyning the cōtrarie. How they are charged to ſee the Lawes of God kept, and the tranſgreſsion of the ſame puniſhed, if their rulers do neglecte them. And that they may lawfully puniſh their Magiſtrates as priuate perſones tranſgreſsing the Lordes precepts.
            
            
               BVt what remedie? (ſaye you) we being but ſubiectes with out power, ād wiſedome cannot helpe it. The more pyttie deare Countriemen,Rebellion againſt the lawful gouernement of godly kinge Edwarde ād obedience to the vniuſte vſurpation of wicked Marie. that you haue ſo ſtoutly or rather ſtubbernely ſhewed your willes and power in the dayes of Godly kynge Edwarde the VI. your late Prince and gouernour, and the zelous ſeruant of God: who ſoght to rule you in Gods feare, ād vnder whom you had the confortable worde of God, ād were deliuered from the Romiſhe Antichriſt, and from all ſuperſtition, for the moſt parte, hauing your Realme free from ſtrangers, and quiete from all enimies, enioying your goods and freinds in peace with out all force.

impriſōning, reuilīg, baniſhing, or murthering) It is to be lamented (I ſaye) that then receauing all theſe bleſsinges of God, by the means of ſo worthie a Prince, ye were able to conſpire, riſe and rebell with the daunger of bodies, goods and ſoules, agaynſt your godlie and lawfull kinge: and that chiefly to defende the deuiliſhe Maſſe, and all the puddels of poperie with the Caterpillers and rable of all vncleane ſpirites, as Cardinalls,
                  Reu. 16. Biſhopps, Prieſtes, Monkes, Freers, Nonnes &amp;c. And now in theſe matters wherin conſiſteth the glorie of God, the preſeruation of your owne liues, and defence of your countrie you are without all will, power and helpe.
            To reſtore Antichriſt agayne, whom ons God had baniſhed to all your comfortes,How fare mans iugdment differeth from Gods. you were not aſhamed to terme it obedience, and to counte your ſelues therin no rebells, but lawfull reſiſters: but to defende Chriſte and his confortable Goſpell (which then you had in poſſeſsion) that are you perſuaded to be open rebellion. To arme your ſelues agaynſt your ſuperiors, to defend your

cōmons and earthly commodities with holden from you, by the greedy deſier of new vpſtarte gentlemen, how willing and redie haue you ſhewed your ſelues?Worldely cōmodities preferred to ſpiritual benefites But to holde and reteyne your ſpiritual poſſeſsion not promiſed onely, but geuen in to your handes, you are moſte ſlowe without all hope and courage. Shall not this be to your iuſte condemnation? When God calleth you to a rekening, what cā you haue to anſwere? Are ye any better then the Gergezites,
                  Mat 9. which deſiered Chriſte to departe from them becauſe they loſte their hogges and ſwyne? yea, ye are worſe then they were by muche, becauſe ye haue profeſſed Chriſte ād receaued him and his doctrine, and with him vnſpeakable benefytes and treaſors. And yet notwithſtanding haue not onely deſiered him to departe from amongeſt you as they did: but layde violent handes vpon him, perſecuting him with ſword, baniſhmēt, fire, and cruell death, as thogh he had bene your mortal enimy. O ingratitude intolerable! Chriſte your mercifull Lorde (who deſtroyed nothinge of yours, but preſerued and increaſed, euen your

ſwine &amp; hogges, &amp; all other beaſtes ād cattell in great abūdance) you haue deſpiced and vtterly denied, to haue Antichriſte to be your Lorde ād gouernour, ād with hī all filthie ſwine, wilde beares, wolues, bores, tygers, and lyons to deuoure, deſtroye, ād ouerthrowe all thinges: not your fieldes ād paſtures onely: but villages, Townes, Cities, and Caſtels, yea your ſelues, your wyues, and children, and what ſo euer you counte moſte precious.
            Wel, the day of the Lorde will come, when you ſhal fele what it is to fight for your Maſſe, and to betraye the Goſpell, to riſe and rebell agaynſte your lawfull Prīce, ād to obeye ād defende a baſtarde, and opē enimie to God, an vtter deſtruction of the whole realme: to murther and baniſhe your naturall countriemē ād louing brethern, to honor ād receaue ſtrangers Gods expreſſe aduerſaries: a cruell people, a prowde nation: a people of a farre and of a ſtrange langage,
                  Baruch. 4 Ieremi
                        •
                     . 5. Deut. 28. whoſe tōgue ye ſhall not vnderſtā
               de, an impudēt natiō, ād hard harted people, with out all pitie and mercie, which nether will be moued with the lamē
               table voyce of the mothers, nor ſhewe

anie compaſsion for the pittifull crye of their ſucklinges and infantes. And whi? becauſe ye haue choſē to obeye vile man, yea a raginge and mad
                  •
                womā,
                  A Godly and moſte neceſſarie admonitiō
                rather then the almightie and mercifull God. Repent, repent, ô ye people of England, for your deſtruction is at hande. Forſake with ſpede the vnlawfull obediēce of fleſhe and bloude, ād learne to geue honor ī tyme to the liuīg Lorde, that he maye ſtaye his hāde, ād drawe to him agayne his ſtretched out arme, that you may fynde mercie, and that the bothom of your cupp be not turned vpwarde.
            Alas ſaye you, what is this we heare? Be not the people, of them ſelues as ſhe epe without a paſtor?The vaine excuſes of the people. If the Magiſtrates and other officiers cōtemne their duetie in defending Gods glorie and the Lawes cōmitted to their charge, lieth it in our power to remedie it? Shall we that are ſubiectes take the ſworde in our hādes? It is in dede as you ſay, a great diſcouraging to the people whē they are not ſtirred vp to godlyneſſe by the good exāple of all ſortes of Superiors, Magiſtrates ād officers in the faithefull executīg of their office: ād ſo muche more whē they

are not defended by them in their right and title, as wel concerning religion, as the freedome of their naturall coūtrie: but moſte of all when they, which ſhuld be ther guydes ād Capitayns, are become inſtrumētes to inforce them to wicked impietie. Neuertheles, all this can be no excuſe for you, ſeing, that euil doinges of others, whether they be Lordes, Dukes, Barōs, knights or any inferior officers, may not excuſe you in euil. And thoghe you had no man of power vpon your parte:
                  Deu. 4.5 &amp; 6. 1. Chro. 29. yet, it is a ſufficient aſſurance for you, to haue the warrāt of Godds worde vpon your ſide, and God him ſelf to be your Capitayne who willeth not onely the Magiſtrates ād officers to roote out euil from amongeſt them, beit, idolatrie, blaſphemie or open iniurie, but the whole multitude are therwith charged alſo, to whō a portiō of the ſworde of iuſtice is cōmitted, to execute the iudgementes which the Magiſtrates lawfully commande. And therfore if the Magiſtrates would whollye deſpice and betraye the iuſtice and Lawes of God, you which are ſubiectes with them ſhall be condemned except

you mayntayne and defend the ſame Lawes agaynſt them, ād all others to the vttermoſte of your powers, that is, with all your ſtrēgth, with all your harte and with all your ſoule, for this hath God required of you,
                  Exod. 17 ād this haue you promiſed vnto him not vnder cōdition (if the Rulers will) but without all exceptiōs to do what ſo euer your Lorde and God ſhall commande you.
            As touching idolatrie,
                  Deut. 13. it is worthie to be conſidered what Moyſes wrytethe, or rather the Spirite of God by hī, how the Lorde in that place chargeth the whole people to ſtone to death without mercy the falſe Prophet or dreamer, when anie ſhulde riſe vp amongeſt thē, yea thoghe the thinges came to paſſe which he before ſpake, if that therby he ſoght to perſwade thē or drawe thē to idolatrie. And alſo howe he ſuffred ſuch amōgeſt his people to try ād proue thē, whether they woulde loue him with all their harte and with all their ſoule, meanīg (as euery mā may well perceaue) that if they ſhulde yelde for all their ſignes ād wonders to idolatrie, ād not puniſhe ſuch falſe Prophetes and dreamers as

God had rayſed vp: that thē they loued him not, yea that they had playnly forſaken and denied him, for that he commanded expreſlye that euerie ſuch Prophet ſhuld be put to death, and therfore chargeth to take the euill frō amongeſt them. Which commandemēt as it is not geuen onely to the Rulers and Gouernours (thoghe I confeſſe it chieflie apperteyneth to their office to ſee it executed, for which cauſe they are made Rulers) but alſo is comon to all the people, who are likewiſe bownde to the obſeruation of the ſame: euenſo is the puniſhment appoynted of God, belonging to all maner of perſons without exception, being found tranſgreſſors. For the Lorde is a iuſt puniſher,
                  Eccleſi 35 Deut. 10. Leui. 19. with whom there is no reſpecte of perſons, who willeth his people to be like him in their iudgemē
               tes. In iudgemēte (ſaithe the Lorde) comitte no vnrighteouſnes, nether reſpect the face of the poore, nether be you afrayde at the cōtenaūce of the mightie, but iudge vprightly to your neghbour.
            
               
                  Deut. 13.Moreouer that euery perſone both high and lowe is charged of God with this Lawe, and none freede from the puniſhmēt, it is euidēt in the ſame Chapter

folowing: Where God doth not permit ſomuche as priuie whiſpering in thy eare, tending to idolatrie, vnpuniſhed, no not of thy deareſt frende or kinſmā, ſayng: Yf thine owne naturall brother,What zeale we oght to God in puniſhinge idolatrers. ſonne, daughter, or the wyffe of thine owne boſome, or thy neghboure whom thou loueſte as thine owne liffe, ſecreatly prouoke thee to idolatrie, to ſerue ſtrāge Gods, either farre or neare, geue not place to him, nether heare him, nether let thine eye haue pitie vpō hī, nether ſhalt thou pardō him, or hide him, but ſhalt vtterly ſley hī: thy hande ſhall firſt be vpon ſuch a one to kill him, and then the handes of all the people &amp;c.
            The like commandement is alſo geuen in the 17. and 18. Chap. of the ſame boke, charging all the people of God in generall, to ſee idolatrie puniſhed without mercie, and that in all perſones. Wherfore we may moſte certaynely conclude, that if the Rulers and Magiſtrates in this caſe, woulde not execute the Lawes of God where with they are ſo ſtraightly charged, that then the people are not diſcharged, excepte they put it in execution to take

the euil from amongeſt them, to whom it alſo belongeth. Next, that no perſone is exempted by any Lawe of God from this puniſhment, be he kinge, Quene or Emperour, that is, either openly or priuely knowne to be an idolatrer be he neuer ſo neare or deare vnto vs, he muſt dye the death. For God hath not placed them aboue others to tranſgreſſe his Lawes as they liſte,As al perſones oght to obey Godes Lawes, ſo oght they to be puniſhed if they tranſgreſſe them. but to be ſubiecte vnto them as well as others, ouer whom they gouerne. And if they be ſubiecte vnto his Lawes, they muſte be ſubiect to the puniſhment alſo, when they be fownd diſobedient tranſgreſſors: yea, ſo muche the more as their example is more daungerous. For looke what wickedneſſe reigneth in the Magiſtrates, the ſubiectes comonly take incouragement therby to imitate the ſame,1. king. 14.21. as we ſee in the examples of Ieroboam. Achab and wicked Manaſſes, who being ſuffred in the beginninge to commit idolatrie, and to erecte idoles, made the ſame likewiſe laufull to all their ſubiectes.
                  Num. 25. For the ſame cauſe God commāded Moyſes to hāge vp all the capitaynes and heads of the people, for that by their example they made the people idolatrers alſo: he

had no reſpect to their auctoritie, becauſe they were Rulers, but ſo muche the rather woulde he haue them ſo ſharplie puniſhed, that is, hanged agaynſt the ſunne without mercy: which iudgement, thoghe it was done at Gods commandment firſte, and after at Moyſes, yet were the people executors of the ſame, and all did vnderſtand that it was iuſte: and not for that tyme onely, but to be a perpetuall example for euer, ād a ſure admonition of their duetie in the like defectiō from God, to hāge vp ſuch Rulers as ſhulde drawe them frō him.
            And thoghe it appeare at the firſte ſight a great diſordre, that the people ſhulde take vnto them the puniſhment of tranſgreſsion, yet, when the Magiſtrates and other officers ceaſe to do their duetie, they are as it were, without officers, yea, worſe then if they had none at all, and then God geueth the ſworde in to the peoples hande, and he him ſelf is become immedialty their head (Yf they will ſeeke the accompliſhment of his Lawes) and hath promiſed to defende them and bleſſe them.
                  Leui. 26. Deu 27.30
            
            And althogh the rebellion of the

people, their ingratitude and contempte of Godes Lawes hath bene ſuch at all tymes, that it is a rare thinge to ſhewe their duetie in this behalf, by anye exāple:
                  Iud. 19.20 yet is there one facte of the Iſralites worthie memorie, ād appertaynīg, to this purpoſe, whiche is written in the boke of the Iudges, at what tyme they had no lawfull Magiſtrate in all Iſraell. Who notwithſtandinge roſe vp whollie together agaynſt the Tribe of Beniamī in Gabaa (becauſe of that ſhamefull vilanie, which the ſonnes of Belial had done to the Leuites wiffe) and ſayed or agreed amongeſt them ſelues,The cōmō people with out a Gouernour prepare thē ſelues to warre. that none ſhuld departe to their houſes or tentes, before they were reuenged of their owne brethern the Beniamites, to flea thoſe deteſtable perſons, which had ſo ſhamefully abuſed the Leuites wiffe, albeit ſhe was an harlot, and they without a guide or Capitayne: not knowing when they came to the felde who ſhulde be their gouernour to leade thē, and geue the onſet, before they had cō
               ſulted with God, who appoynted vnto them Iuda. Here do we ſee the eleuen

Tribes, to whome the Leuite made his complaynt, in ſendinge to euery Tribe a portion of his wiffe, did not excuſe them ſelues to ſhew iuſtice, bicauſe they wanted a lawfull Magiſtrate to gouerne them, nor thoght them ſelues diſcharged for that they were as ſheeppe without a paſtor: except they did thus arme them ſelues againſte the ſonnes of Belial the vngodly Beniamites to ſee the Iudgementes of God executed accordinge to his Law (and as they ſaide them ſelues) to cut of the euil frō amongeſt, then demādinge in the end the wicked mē that had cōmitted that vilanie.
            But you wil ſay: It is an other matter for the people to enterprice ſuch an acte being without a Ruler, and when they haue a Ruler appoynted vnto them, without whom they may do nothing. To this I anſwered before, that it is all one to be without a Ruler, and to haue ſuch as will not rule in Gods feare. Yea it is much better to be deſtitut altogether, then to haue a tyrant and murtherer. For then are they nomore publik perſons, contemning their publik

auctoritie in vſinge it agaynſt the Lawes, but are to be taken of all men, as priuate perſones, and ſo examyned and puniſhed. Neuer the leſſe, to the intent ye may vnderſtande, that the gouernour oght not to take away all right from the people, nether diſcharge thē vtterly, from the execution of iuſtice: let vs conſider a like example of the peoples zele vnder the worthie Capitayne Ioſua,
                  Ioſua. 22. who when they but harde that the Sonnes of Ruben, the Sonnes of Gad,The people aſſemble in Gods cauſe. and the half Tribe of Manaſſes, had erected vp an Altar in their portiō, which God had geuen them beyonde Iordane, thinking that they had ſo done, to haue ſacrificed theron, and ſo to haue fallen from God: aſſembled them ſelues together wholly, agaynſt the Rubenytes, Gaddites and half Tribe of Manaſſes to reuenge that defection from God (as they tooke it) thoghe afterwarde they proued it to be nothing ſo. Which facte, as it declared an earneſt true zele in the people for the defence of Gods glorye, and his religion: ſo Ioſua their Capitayne, nether did nor

ought to haue reproued them: yea, happie might Ioſua thinke him ſelf, that had his people ſo readie to mayntayne of their owne accorde the Lawes of God, whiche before in the dayes of Moyſes were ſo ſtubburne and rebellious. And if this redineſſe was commendable, hauing a worthie Magiſtrat and godly Capitayne: how neceſſary is it to be vſed amongeſt the people when they haue vngodly and wicked Princes, who ſeke by all means to drawe them rather from the Lawe of God, then to incourage them to mayntayne the ſame? Wherfore this zele to defend Gods Lawes and preceptes, wherewith all ſortes of men are charged, it is not onely prayſe worthie in all, but requyred of all, not onely in abſtayninge from the tranſgreſsion of the ſayed Lawes, but to ſee the iudgemētes therof executed vpon all maner of perſones with out exception. And that if it be not done by the conſent and ayed of the Superiours, it is lawfull for the people, yea it is their duetie to do it thē ſelues, as well vpon their owne rulers and Magiſtrat,

as vpon other of their bretherē, hauing the worde of God for their warrant, to which all are ſubiecte, and by the ſame charged to caſt forthe all euill from them, and to cut of euery rotten membre, for feare of infecting the whole body, how deare or pretious ſo euer it be. If death be deſerued, death: if other puniſhmētes, to ſee they be executed in all.
            
               
                  Rom. 13.For this cauſe haue you promiſed obedience to your Superiors, that they might herein helpe you: and for the ſame intent haue they taken it vpon them. If they will ſo do, and keepe promiſſe with you accordinge to their office, then do you owe vnto them all humble obedience: If not, you are diſcharged, and no obedience belongeth to them: becauſe they are not obedient to God, nor be his miniſters to puniſhe the euell, and to defend the good. And therfore your ſtudie in this caſe, oght to be, to ſeeke how you may diſpoſe and puniſhe according to the Lawes, ſuch rebells agaynſt God, and oppreſſers of your ſelues and your countrie: and not how to pleaſe them, obeye

them, and flatter them as you do in their impietie. Which is not the waye to obtayne peace, and quietneſſe, but to fall in to the handes of the allmightie God, and to be ſubiecte to his fearefull plagues and puniſhmentes.
         
         
            CHAP. XIIII. 
            
               This is no doctrine of Rebellion, but the onely doctrine of peace and means to inioye quietlie the comfortable bleſsinges of God, which oght not to be wiſſhed for onely of the people, but carefully ſoght for alſo.
            
            
               ANd althoghe this ſeeme a ſtrange doctrine, perrelous, and to moue ſedition amōgeſt the people, and to take from the lawfull Rulers all due obedience: yet whoſo will conſider the matter a right, ſhall finde it ſounde and true doctrine, and the onely doctrine of godly peace and quietneſſe, and means to auoyde all ſtrief and rebellion, by whiche onely Superiors ſhall rule in the feare of God,

and ſubiectes reuerently obeye them without grudging or murmuring. For is there anie lawes more parfit then are the Lawes of God? Or did anie mā better know the nature of man, then he which created man? Or anie more deſierous to keepe them in his feare, and true obedyence, then God him ſelf, who choſe them for his people? Then who is ſo mad and impudēt,God which made man knoweth beſt what Lawes are moſte expedient for his preſeruation. to thinke that peace ād quietneſſe can be amongeſt anie people or nation, by obſeruing the Lawes of wicked men, rather then in reteyning the wholſome Lawes of God? That mā which is not able to rule him ſelfe, can better gouerne his ſubiectes and defende them, than God may his people? That the people ſhall rather enioye all bleſſinges of God, in yelding to the wickedneſſe of the vngodlie Rulers, then to ſee them ſtraightlie puniſhed for tranſgreſſions of the confortable Lawes of the almightie? For after that God had once geuen his Lawes to his people, he ſhewed them playnlie by Moyſes that he required nothing els of them,
                  Deut. 10. but to feare him and to walke in his wayes, to loue him, and ſerue him with all their harte

and to keepe his preceptes and ſtatutes, which he cōmanded them that day. And why? bycauſe (ſaithe Moyſes) he is the God of Gods, the Lorde of Lordes, the greate mightie and dreadful God, whiche hath no reſpecte of perſones, nor taketh anie rewardes. And this fructe ſhall you be ſuer of in keepinge his Lawes. He wilbe your prayſe, ād your God:
                  Deut. 4. that is (as in an other place the ſame Moyſes writeth) He will make you a wiſe people, a mightie Nation, prayſed and cōmēded of all Natiōs, which ſhall ſaye, This is onlie a wiſe people, and a people of vnderſtandinge ād mightie. For what people is ſo great, whiche hath their God ſo friendly and familiar with them, as the Lorde our God is in all thinges that we call to him for? For whiles we obey his Lawes, and ſuffer them in no caſe, ād in no perſone to be tranſgreſſed and left vnpuniſhed (to the vttermoſte of our power) we are aſſured that the bleſſinges which God after promiſed, ſhalbe powred vpō vs: that is to be bleſſed at home and a brode, in the frute of our wombe,
                  Deut. 28. of our lande, of our beaſtes and cattell. And the Lorde will make our enemies

which riſe agaynſt vs to fall before vs, to entre in one waye agaynſt vs, and to flee by ſeuen wayes afore vs. And all the people of the earthe ſhall ſee that the Name of the Lorde is called vpon amongeſt vs, and ſhall be afrayde of vs.
            Yt is then no newe doctrine which God ſo longe ago taught to the Iſraelites, nor no raſhe or perelous doctrine wherby they are onely made wiſe, and moſte ſtrongly defended. Nether yet dothe it miniſter occaſion of rebellion, without which there can be no godlie peace or quietneſſe, as your experience in Englande hath all readie (as I ſuppoſe) ſufficiently taught you: who haue felt rather hellike tormentes, and ſhamefull confuſion, ſince ye permitted the wilde bores to caſte downe the hedge of the Lordes vinyarde, that is, his Lawes and preceptes, then anie maner of godly peace, either in conſciences or bodies:Let your owne conſciēces be Iudges in this behalfe which miſerie ſhall haue no end before you reclayme with a vehement zele and loue, your right title and poſſeſsion of Gods Lawes, which

you haue moſte vnthankfully geuen ouer and neglected.
            Yf the true zele of Gods people had bene in you when poperie began to be preached in the place of the Goſpell, when the Maſſe was reduced in place of the Lordes ſupper, and that by the ignorant Papiſts and malicious ſhauelyngs,The contempt of Gods worde is the dore to all licentious wickednes. when Antichriſt was reſtored to diſplace Chriſt: coulde ye haue ſuffered this vnponiſhed? Or if you had puniſhed it as you were then charged by Gods Lawes and mans, durſte they haue proceaded to ſuch impietie? If you had required the Magiſtrates to rule you in Gods feare and not in tyrannie, and that you woulde reuerence them as Gods miniſters ſo rulinge you, otherwiſe, not to acknowledg them but as his enimies, and ſo to take them: durſt either that Ieſabel ſo ragingly haue trodē Gods worde the Goſpell of Chriſt our Sauiour as a polluted ſowe vnder her feete, either els ſo raſhely deſtroyde her fathers and brothers Lawes before her? Durſte ſhe without all ſhame ſo openly and vnfaythfully haue broken promiſſe to them (whiche

to their owne ſorrow, and all others this day) were her chief promoters? Aſſure your ſelfs no. If you had required all Maſſemongers, and falſe Preachers to haue bene puniſhed with deathe (as is appoynted by Gods worde for ſuch blaſphemers and idolatrers, and if they to whom it apperteyned, had denyed, your ſelues would haue ſeen it performed at all tymes, and in all places) then ſhuld you haue ſhewed that zele of God, which was cōmended in Phinees,
                  Num. 25. deſtroyinge the adulterers: and in the Iſraelites againſte the Beniamités, as before is noted. Ye then had not the Priſtes of Baal ſo ſwarmed abrode, nor the ſeruātes of God haue bene in ſuch abundāce murthered. But great was our ſynnes before, that this deſerued: and colde was our zele to Godwardes after, that this ſhame haue ſuffred: and groſſe is our blynd dulnes, whiche wil not yet ſee nor ſeeke to remedie it.
            
               what rules are to be obſerued in reſiſting the ſuperior powersNeuertheleſſe in all theſe enterpriſes you muſte be certaine and ſure of this one thinge, that vnder the name of Religion and pretence to promote Gods glorie, you ſeeke not either your priuate

gaynes or promotiō, as did all the carnall Goſpelers, and ſuch as would be cō
               ted the chief pillers and mainteyners of the ſame in tymes paſt amongeſt you. And therfore vnder the cloke of Chriſt, ſeekyng the worlde, when Chriſt ſemed to haue the vpper hande: are now returned to their oldemaiſter Antichriſte, to be his hired ſouldiars, and to fight vnder his banner agaynſt Chriſt and his ſeruantes, by whom they were firſte promoted. Which treaſon God is prepared all redie to reuenge, to pluck from them his fethers, and to ſet furth to the whole worlde their ſhame and nakedneſſe. For he is a iuſt God,
                  Pſal. 5. and hateth iniquitie, and therfore will be no cloke to couer their falſhode and couetouſneſſe.
            Alſo ye muſt beware that priuate diſpleaſure, and worldly iniuries moue you not more to ſeeke reuengement of your aduerſaries, then the true zele and thirſte of Gods worde, the liuely foode of your ſoules. For then do you ſeeke your ſelues, and not God: then take you his office out of his hande, to whom ye oght to commit all your priuate diſpleaſures

and iniuries:
                  Deu 32. Ezech. 9. Rom 12. then can ye not loke to haue Gods right hande vpon your parte, but rather may be aſſured to finde him your enimie, and ſtrongly armed againſt you. To reſiſte euill therfore is your parte, and to mayntayne Godlyneſſe, but ſymply and vnfaynedly, for the loue of vertue, and hatred of vice, yf you will be ſure to proſper, and auoyde Gods heauy diſpleaſure,
                  Pſal. 7. Iere. 17. who is the ſercher of your hartes and ſecreats, and will in tyme diſcloſe them and make them knowen to all men.
            But you perchaunce would graunt me all this, that it is both lawfull and godly, if the people wholie together woulde follow the example of zelous Phinees and the Iſraelites,
                  A doute which trobleth the people. as before was mentioned, and take puniſhment them ſelues vpon all blaſphemers of God, manifeſt betrayers of their countrie, and cruell murtherers of their brethern: ſeing the Lawes of God and publycke peace can be by no other means reſtored. But when the people them ſelues agree not,

when they are deuided amongeſt them ſelues, and the greateſt parte of them perchance papiſtes, and will be maynteyners of ſuch vngodly proceadings as are now broght in to Englande, how is it poſsible that by the weaker parte, Gods glory ſhulde be reſtored?
            To this I anſwere, that as I know the reſtoringe of Gods worde,The anſwere. and comfortable doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſte to be the onely worke of God, and of no man (thoghe he forſake not man as a meane external) and alſo am not ignorant that he regardeth not the multitude and ſtrenghe of man to accompliſhe his purpoſe,
                  Num 13. 1 Sam. 14. Iudith: 9. Iudges. 6. who hath bene accuſtomed to geue the victorie to a few in nomber, and weake in ſtrengh, that the glorie might be his: ſo will I not counſelle you raſhely to caſt your ſelues in to danger, but patiently and erneſtly to call to the lyuing Lorde for mercy, and acknowledging your ſynnes (for which this plague is powred vpon you) to deſier him to ſhewe ſome ſigne

of conforte: who hath promiſed to heare your groninges, and to beholde your affliction,
                  Exod. 2.3 as he did the groninges and oppreſsion of his people in Egypt, when they were broght to full repentance ād fealing of their ſynnes: ſo that he came downe from heauen, ād appeared to Moyſes, and ſent him to be their Capitayne, whom they once had forſaken: as you haue done Chriſte.
            
               
                  Iudg. 3.And as he alſo ſent Othoniel to deliuer his people, whē they cryed vnto him in that captiuitie that they were in vnder the idolatrous kynge of Meſopotamia for the ſpace of eight yeres.
                  A ſuer ſigne that God heareth our prayers when he geuith vs a meane to deliuer vs.
            
            Nether is this ynough to call vpon God for helpe, except ye vtterly forſake the wicked doctrine and doinges of the papiſtes, ād ſeeke alſo (to the vttermoſt of your power) for remedie in folowing the example of the people of God, as it is writen: whiche did not onely ſerue God and call to him for helpe, at what tyme they were deſtitute of their worthie Capitayne Iudas Machabeus:1. Mach. 6 but alſo ſoght it, and demanded it where it was like to be founde. And aſſemblinge

them ſelues together, came to Ionathan his brother, deſiering him to be their guide and Capitayne, to helpe them in their miſerie, and to defende them agaynſt the enimies of God, their whole nation being then moſte cruelly oppreſſed on euery ſide, and the moſte parte of them in vile ſlauery, ſeruinge the ſtrāge Gods of the heathen. Thē Ionathā pityinge their eſtate and his owne, did not deny their requeſte, but willingly toke in hande that dangerous enterpriſe, beīge aſſured that the cauſe was lawfull, to maintaine to his power Gods glorie ād to ſuccour his afflicted natiō, as his brother Iudas had done before him. And doinge the ſame with a ſimple eye, accordinge as he was boūde, God proſpered his doinge, and he had good ſucceſſe
            Therfore yf they did well in demā
               dinge ſuccour, and he diſcharged his conſcience in graunting their requeſt, why is it not alſo lawfull for you to ſeeke helpe of thē that be able ād willing: and for them likewiſe to graūte helpe, to whom God hath lente it for that vſe

eſpecially?
            But I know your anſwere: experience (ſaye you) hath taught vs the contrary. For if God had bene pleaſed herein with. Syr Thomas Wyat that valiant Capitayne taking in hande the like enterpriſe: it ſhulde vndoutedly haue had better ſucceſſe. But he being a man, and of God, of great eſtimation amongeſt all goodmen, was notwithſtandinge apprehended, condemned, and at the laſt (althogh he was promiſed his pardon) as a traytor beheaded.Sir Henry Iſley. And beſides him Sir Henry Iſley knight, with many godely men for the ſame facte, hanged, and murthered. The like alſo ye will affir me of that Noble man Henry Lorde Graye, Marques Dorſet, ād Duke of Suffolke:The Duke of Suffolk who onely for the zeale that he had to promote Gods glorie, and the libertie of his countrie, prepared him ſelf with that power he coulde make to the ayde of the ſayed Wyat, accordinge to his promiſſe. But beinge deceaued, or rather betrayed by ſuch as he truſted vnto,The Lorde Thomas Graye. was in the ende alſo apprehended, and with his brother the Lorde Thomas Gray (a Gentleman of great courage,

and towardneſſe, likewiſe beheaded.
            Althogh I minde not to ſtand long in the praiſe of theſe worthye mēs factes, who moſte cowardly were of many betrayed, which ſince perchance haue felt ſome parte of worſe miſery: yet ſo muche muſt I nedes confeſſe in their behalf, that none but papiſtes, or traytors can iuſtly accuſe them of treaſon or diſobedience. Of whō to be miſdained or ſlandered, is in the eyes of the godly, no ſmall cōmendation, ād prayſe. For to paſſe ouer with ſilēce the duke of Sulffolke (whoſe noble parētage and erneſt loue that he bare to the promoting of Chriſtes Goſpell, and the welth of his coūtrie, is to all Engliſhe men ſufficiently knowne) what I beſeche you moued Wyat that worthy knight to riſe? Was it his pouertie? Beholde, he was a famous Gētleman of great landes and poſſeſsions, ſtowt and liberall in the ſeruice of his Prince, faithefull to his countrie, and mercifull to the poore. Soght he ambitiouſly honour? Which of his enemies coulde herewith iuſtly charge him? Did he this bicauſe he was of a troubleſome ād buſy nature, which

coulde not be vnder lawfull gouernement. His great wiſedome, modeſtie, ād gentle behauiour at all tymes, ād to all perſons, did well declare the contrary: euer more being founde a faythfull Capitayne to his Prīce in the fielde, ād an obediēt ſubiecte at home. What thē moued him to this dangerous entrepriſe? Verely, the zeale of Gods trueth and the pitie that he had to his Countrie,what moued M. wy at to this enterpriſe. for the miſeries he ſawe to approche by the vſurped power of vngodly Ieſabell, and her merciles papiſtes the ſowldiars of Antichriſte. Yf it be treaſō to defend the Goſpel and his Countrie frome cruel ſtrangers and enemies, thē was Wyat a traytor ād rebell. but if this was his duetye, and all others that profeſſed Chriſte amōgeſt you, then are all ſuch traytours, as did deceaue him: and ſuch as toke not his parte alſo, whē tyme ād occaſiō by him was iuſtly offered.
            And thogh his enterpriſe had not ſuch ſuceſſe, as we would haue wiſſhed: yet was it no worſe then our cowardneſſe, and vnworthineſſe deſerued. Whiche nether oght of anie therfore to be condemned, nether ſhulde be anie diſcouragemēt

to others in the like. For ſome tymes we ſee the verie ſeruantes of God to haue euill ſucceſſe in their doinges,How dangerous it is to iudge the cauſe by the ſucceſſe. Iud. 29
                according to mās iudgement: and yet God is well pleaſed therwith. As the example of the Iſraelites, wherof we made mention before dothe moſte manifeſtlie approue: at what tyme they armed them ſelues agaynſt the Beniamites, and that at the commandement of God, and yet were twiſe diſconcfyted, loſing the firſt tyme 22. thouſand men: and the next day folowing 18. thowſand: bothe tymes, conſulting with the Lorde, and folowing his commandement.
            If thou wilt here pronounce accordīg to the effecte, behold, thou ſhalt preferre the vile ād adulterous Beniamites to the ſeruaūtes of God: thoſe which moſte abhominably abuſed the Leuites wiffe, to them that with the zele of God ſoght to haue the tranſgreſsion puniſhed. Euen ſo, ſaye I of worthie Wyat: Yf you iudge his facte according to the ſucceſſe in mans reaſon: then ſhall you prefarre to him all the falſe and flattering Counſellers, all wicked and blouddy Biſhoppes, and all others that would be

counted Nobles, which in very dede be traytours to God and his people. But Wyat, I dowte not, departed with prayſe the ſeruant of God, where all theſe are left to perpetual ſhame and deſtruction without ſpeedie repentance. O noble Wyat, thou art now with God, and thoſe worthy men that died for that enterpriſe▪ Happy art thou, and they which are placed in your euerlaſtinge inheritance, and freed from the miſerie of ſuche as were your enimies, in ſo iuſte and lawfull a cauſe: who liue as yet patrones of idolatrers, of theues and murtherers, agaynſt whō thou and thine ſhall ſtande one daye as iudges to their cōdēnation.
            For what can you Nobles or Coūſellers ſaye for yourſelues at that daye, whē God ſhall call you to accompt (ye knowe not how ſone) which haue permitted Wyat, and with him the whole Churche and comon welth of England to fall into the handes of Gods enimies, and would not reſkewe him, ſome of you hauing then in your handes ſufficient power not onely to haue ſupported him and others which feare God accordinge to duety ād promiſſe. but to haue tamed

the rāping lyons, raginge beares, ād raueninge wolues?The condē
                  nation of the Nobles in forſakinge Wyat. Haue ye not herein iuſtly cōdemned your ſelues as faynt harted cowardes and manifeſte trayters, not onely to Wyat, but to God him ſelf, to his poore oppreſſed ſeruantes, and to your owne natiue and ruynous coūtrie? But your vngodly fetches and wicked doinges (wherof I am not all together ignorant) with your names, I do now purpoſlye omitte: perchāce God in the meane ſeaſon will chaunge your myndes, ſoftē your harde hartes, and call you to repentāce. Otherwiſe doute ye nothīge, but God will miniſter either to me, or ſome other (or it belonge) the like occaſion to ſet forth your ſhame and nakedneſſe to all poſteritie, as you moſte worthely haue deſerued: who hithervnto haue ſhewed your ſelues (in contemnyng ſo many ād notable occaſiōs offered by Gods prouidence,Goſpellers fearinge man more then God are made inſtrumēts of Satan. as well ſynce as in the dayes of Wyat) to be mē in whom is nether zele to religion, nor loue to your coūtrie. And therfore I leauinge you to Gods mercies, or fearefull iudgementes, will ſpeake a worde or two by the waye, to thē which will be called Goſpellers, ād

yet haue armed them ſelues agaynſt the Goſpel drawing forth with them out of their countrie to mayntayne Philipps warres, and to pleaſe Ieſabel (who ſeeketh by that means, to cut their throtes craftely) their poore and ignorant tenā
               tes and other ſouldiars without knowledge, whiles their brethern be burned at home and their countrie like to be waſted, ſpoyled, oppreſſed, poſſeſſed, and repleniſhed with vngodly Spanyardes. Is this the loue that ye beare to the worde of God? (ô ye Goſpellers) haue ye bene ſo taught in the Goſpel to be wilfull murtherers of your ſelues, and others abrode, rather then lawfull defenders of Gods people, and your countrie at home? Is Gods cauſe become iniuſte ād not meete to be defended: and the cruel murther and ſhamefull ſlaughter of Princes approued? This hathe not the Goſpell taught you, but chieflye in all your doinges to ſeeke the kingdome of God, next to loue your neighbour as your ſelues: and in no caſe to be murtherers (as all you are) that either for pleaſure of Princes, or hope of promotion, or gayne of wages are become Capitayns, or ſouldiars

in vnlawfull warres, eſpecially in this caſe and daungerous tyme.
            Then which of you all now for ſhame can accuſe that zelous and godly man Wyat, whither ye be of the Nobles, Coūſellers, Lords, knightes, or of the comon ſouldiars? I wil make your owne conſciences iudges in this matter, whither worthie Wyat or you ſhuld be takē for traytors? He,whither wyat and thoſe that died with him: or the Counſelers Nobles and other that yet lyue are traytours. who in the feare of God and loue towardes his countrie ſoght to defende all, ād to diſtroye none: or you, who ſeekinge the defēce of none, labour to deſtroy all? He, who indeuered him ſelf to withſtande wicked Ieſabel, and the onely traytors of Gods truthe, and their coūtrie, as Prieſts, Biſhopps, and papiſtes: or you that haue bene their maynteyners, with ſhildes ād bucklers. He, who according to the worde of God, ſoght with the daunger of all his goods, landes, and liffe, to keepe out ſtrāgers, which were comynge to rule ouer you, and to deuoure you: or you, which haue bene meanes with your liues, lands, and goodes to bringe them in, and to defend them? He, who would be openly knowen in his doinges as he was in harte, their enimie:

or you which hate them inwardly, and yet do what you may to ſhewe your ſelues friendes outwardly? But tell me your gaynes in the end. To conclude, he who did his indeuour amonge his contriemen at home to defend them,Souldiars goinge with their Captayns to vnlawfull warres and leuing their coūtry deſtitute, are rebells to God and traytours to their country. Gen. 9. Deut. 5. Leui. 24. The condē
                  nation of London in forſakinge wyat. or you whiche helpinge your enemies abrode, labour to deſtroie your friēdes and countrie at home?
            Alſo you ſubiectes ād ſouldiars, which are gone with them to butcher your ſelues and others without cauſe or cōſcience, contrarie to the worde of God, be you aſſured that before him you ſhall be condemned as rebells and diſobedient perſones, where as your godly bretheren which in a iuſt and lawfull cauſe died with faithfull Wyat, are alowed before God, and of all goodmen commended.
            O London, London, thou that boaſted thy ſelf to be the Ieruſalem of all Englā
               de, wherin Chriſt chieflie was preached, and the truethe of his Goſpell beſt knowne, remēber how thou forſookeſt that godly Capitayne, ād what promiſſe thou madeſt him. Thou (I ſay) which mighteſt haue bene an example and cōforte to all the Cities, and Townes in Englande, ād

to haue made the papiſtes to tremble ād quake for feare. God graunt that for thy faynt harte in that behalf, and ſhamefull falling from God in murthering then and ſynce ſo many of his ſeruantes and Prophetes, thou be not left likewiſe deſtitute and deſolate, not one ſtone left vpon a nother, as happened to Ieruſalē.
                  Mat. 24. Thou canſt not herein defende thy ſelf, which ſynce haſt bene readie, and yet art to maintayne wicked Ieſabell in her tyrannie at home, ād in her vngodly &amp; nedeles warres abrode with thy goods and bodie at her commandement, being therby made an ayeder, helper, and furtherer of all her vngodly oppreſsion and tyrannie. And therfore muſt nedes be partaker with her of the dreadfull plagues and puniſhments, which God hath appoynted for ſuch impietie.
            Wherfore to conclude this matter, yf Wyats cauſe was iuſte and lawfull, as thou muſte nedes confeſſe: for if he were fautie in anie poynt, it was chieflie in this, that he pretended rather the cauſe of his countrie, then of Gods Religion, which allwayes oght to be preferred,

and with out the which no Realme or nation may long cōtynewe in quietneſſe: for thē God keepeth not watche ouer thē. Yf alſo he was betrayde of others, and ſoght not to betraye any: if he purpoſed Gods glorie, and the defence of his countre: If the iuſtneſſe of the cauſe oght to trye his doīges, ād not the effect that folowed, or the preuētīge of tyme, where vnto he after a ſorte was inforſed: thē oght no perſone, whither he be a Ruler, or ſubiecte, Counſeller, Noble, publicke or priuate to be diſcouraged, but rather incouraged by Wyats example. The people to ſeeke and demande helpe of thē that are able, and they to graūt thē ſuccour willīgly: ſeeking by all means poſsible to reſtore Chriſt agayne, ād his kīgdome, with whom you haue loſt all godlye libertie ād quietneſſe: and to expell Antichriſt and all his adherentes, by whom you are broght in this miſerable ſlauery and bōdage, both of bodies and ſoules.
            And thoghe it ſuccede not the firſt or ſeconde tyme, no more then did the entrepriſe of Wyat, or of the Iſraelites: yet when God ſhall ſee your zele and diligence,

to be applyed onely in ſeekinge to maynteyne his kingdome, and the glorie therof: he wil helpe no dowte at lenghe to confounde all his enimies, as he did the thirde tyme confort the Iſraelits to the vtter deſtructiō of the adulterous Beniamits.We oght to be cōtented with Gods worde onely and loke for no newe reuelation. We muſt now looke for no reuelations from the heauens to teache vs our duety, it being ſo playnely ſet before our eyes in his worde. And if in this caſe conſiderately begone in the feare of God, it ſhuld happen any of you to periſhe, conſider you periſhe but in the fleſhe to lyue with God: leauing in the meane tyme an example behinde you, that you liued in his feare and ſoght his glorie according to your duetye.
         
         
            CHAP. XV. 
            
               What remedy or counſell is left, to the poore and afflicted ſeruantes of God, at what tyme they are deſtitute of all outwarde meās and ſupporte of mē.
            
            
               TO the people of Iſrael, whom God from amonge all nations choſe to be his peculiar people, he did not onely geue his Lawes, ordinances

and ſtatutes: but alſo inſtituted all kinde of officiers to ſee the ſame Lawes put in execution. And beſides this, appoynted ſuch as might be leaders and defenders of them in tyme of warre agaynſt their enimes, and ſuch as ſhuld mayntayne their right at home in tyme of peace: as were their iudges and princes appoynted ouer euery Tribe, beſides their kinge and chief gouernour, to whome it was lawfull for the people ād for euery Tribe to reſorte in tyme of daunger, to aſke counſele and deſier helpe, who were likewiſe bounde to heare their cauſe, and ſupport them, whither it were by counſelle or bodely trauell.
            In like maner God hath no leſſe mercifully delte with you in Englande,The graces of God towardes Englande are moſt abundant if they would vſe thē
                not onely geuing vnto you his Lawes and holy worde, with farre greater light and playner declaration of his will and pleaſure then euer was publiſhed to the Iſraelits: but alſo hath furniſhed you with all ſortes of Magiſtrates, officers, and gouernors neceſſarie for the accompliſhment, or rather execution of the ſame. To whom it oght to be no leſſe lawfull

for you to reſorte for comforte in your neceſsitie, then it was to the Iſraelites, and they as muche bownd to heare you. For this cauſe haue you Mayres, Shiriffs, and Aldermen in Cities, Counſtables ād Bayliffs in Townes, knights ād Iuſtices, in Shires and countries. To theſe oght the people to haue concurſe in neceſsitie, who ſhuld be their refuge and ayde in all trouble and aduerſitie.
            But if all theſe be ſo ſhamfully corrupted, and ſo myndles of their charge and office, that nether the Citezens can be cōforted, nor ſuckered by their Mayres, Shiriffes, and Alder men: nether the poore Townesmen and Tennants by their Iuſtices and Landelordes, but all geuen ouer as it were to Satan, and to ſerue the luſtes of their chief Rulers, care not whether the poore people ſinke or ſwyme,It is impoſſible for the people to peryſhe and the Rulers to eſcape. ſo it be well with them (thogh it be a thinge impoſsible that the people can be diſtroyed and they eſcape daūger, or that their neyghbours houſe cā be conſumed with fyer, and theirs remayne vntouched) Yf all I ſaye, in whō the people ſhuld loke for comforte, were

all together declyned from God (as in dede they apeare to be at this preſent tyme in England, without all feare of his Maieſtie or pitie vpon their brethern) and alſo, yf the leaſt and weakeſt parte of the people in all places feared God, and all outwarde means of helpe vtterly taken from them, nether being able to fynde remedie amōgeſt them ſelues, nether cā ſee how to be ſupported of others: thē aſſure your ſelues (deare brethern and ſeruants of God) there can be no better counſell, nor more comfortable or preſent remedie (which you ſhall proue true, if God graunte you his Spirite and grace to folowe it) then in contynual and dayly inuocation of his Name, to reſt whollie and only vpon him, make him your ſhilde, buckeler and refuge, who hath ſo promiſed to be to all them that are oppreſſed and depend vpon him: to do nothing commanded agaynſt God and your conſcience, preferring at all tymes (as you haue learned before) the will of God, to the will, puniſhments, and tyranny of Princes: ſayng, and anſweringe to all maner of

perſones: This hath God commanded, this muſt we do. That hath God forbiddē, that will we not do yf you will robbe vs and ſpoyle vs for doinge the Lordes will, to the Lorde muſt you make anſwere, and not to vs: for his goodes they are, and not ours. If ye will impriſone vs, behold, ye are oppreſſors. If ye will hange vs or burne vs, beholde ye are murtherers of them which feare the Lorde, and are created to the Image of God: for whoſe contempte ye ſhall be ſtraytly puniſhed. And for our parte, yf you take from vs this vile and corruptible lyffe, we are aſſured the Lorde will geue it vs agayne with ioye, and immortalitie both of bodie and ſoule.
            Yf God geue you grace to make this or the like anſwere, and ſtrengh to contemne their tyrannie, you may be certayne and ſure to finde vnſpeakable conforte and quietnes of conſcience, in the mydle of your danger and greateſt rage of Satan. And thus boldly confeſsinge Chriſt your Sauiour before men (as by the example of thouſandes of your bretheren before your faces

God doth mercifully incourage you) you may with all hope and patience wayte for the ioyfull confeſsion of Chriſt agayne before his Father and Angells in heauen, that you are his obediente and dearely beloued ſeruantes, being alſo aſſured of this,Tyrantes can go no farther then God permittith. that if it be the will of God to haue you anie longer to remayne in this miſerable worlde, that then his prouidence is ſo carefull ouer you, ād preſent with you, that no man or power can take your liffe from you, nether touche your bodie anie further then your Lorde and God will permit them.
                  Mat. 10. Whiche nether ſhall be augmented for your playne confeſſion, nor yet diminiſhed for keepinge of ſilence. For nothing cometh to the ſeruants of God by hap or chaūce, whoſe heares of their heads are numbred. Wherof yf you be ſo aſſured as you oght to be, there can be nothing that ſhuld make you to ſhrinke from the Lorde. If they do caſt you in priſō with Ioſeph, the Lorde will delyuer you: yf they caſt you to wilde beaſts and lyons, as they did Daniel, you ſhall be preſerued: yf in to the ſea with Ionas, ye ſhall not

be drowned: or in to the durtie dongeon with Ieremie, you ſhall be delyuered: either in to the fyrye furnace withe Sidrach, Miſach, and Abednago, yet ſhall you not be conſumed. Contrarie wiſe,None can loſe their lyfe but by Godes appointement yf it be his good pleaſure that you ſhall glorifie his holie Name in your death, what great thing haue you loſte? Changing death for liffe, miſery for felicitie, contynuall vexation and trouble, for perpetuall reſt and quietneſſe: choſinge rather to dye with ſhame of the worlde being the ſeruantes of God, then to lyue amongeſt men in honor being the ſeruantes of Satan, and condemned of God. Otherwiſe, if you geue place to the wickedneſſe of men to eſcape their malice and bodily dangers, you ſhewe your ſelues therin to feare man more then the mightie and dreadfull God: him that hath but power of your bodie, and that at Gods appoyntement, then God him ſelf, who hath power, after he hath deſtroyed the body, to caſt both bodies and ſoules in to hell fyre, there to remayne euerlaſtingly in tormentes vnſpeakable.
            
               And moreouer that which you loke to obtayne by theſe ſhamefull ſhiefts,Shamfull ſhiftes. you ſhall beſure to loſe with gryef and trouble of Conſcience. For this ſaying of our Maiſter being true and certayne,
                  Mat. 16. That they which ſeeke to ſaue their liffe (meanynge by anie worldly reaſon or policie) ſhall loſe it: what ſhall be their gaynes at lengh, when by diſſimulation and yelding to popiſhe blaſphemie, they diſhonor the Maieſtie of God to inioye this ſhorte, miſerable and mortall lyffe: to be caſte from the fauour of God, ād companie of his heauenly Angells, to inioye for a ſhorte tyme their goodes and poſſeſsions amonge their fleſhly and carnall friends:Of ſuch you haue had ſufficient profe before your eyes. when as their conſcience within ſhall be deeply wounded withe hellike tormentes? when goddes curſe and indignation hangeth contynually ouer the heades of ſuch, ready to be powred downe vpon them? when they ſhall finde no comforte, but vtter diſpayer with Iudas, which for this worldly riches (as he did) haue ſolde their Maiſter: ſekinge either to hange them ſelues with Iudas,Iudas. to murther them ſelues with Frances

Spera,Spera. Hales. Morgen. to drowne them ſelues with Iuſtice Hales, either els to fall in to a raginge madneſſe with Iuſtice Morgen? What comforte had Iudas then by his mony receaued for betraynge his Maiſter? Was he not ſhortly after compelled to caſt it from him with this pitifull voyce:
                  Mat. 27. I haue ſynned in betraying innocēt bloud? Coulde anie of theſe forenamed perſons, after they had commytted the like treaſon to our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt finde anie more comforte in their friendes, from whom they were ſo loth to departe? Or anie more pleaſure in their poſſeſsions, or aſſurance in their treaſures? Beholde, they had all moſte miſerable lyues for the tyme, and ſhamefull endes.
            Then deare brethern in Chriſt, what other rewarde can anie of you loke for, commytting the like offences? Haue you anie more aſſurance of Gods mercies then they had? Woulde not Chriſt ſpare his owne Apoſtle Iudas, and yet will pardon you? Did not iudge Hales appearingly profeſſe the Goſpell a longe ſpace, and was greatly commended for a godly man amongeſt

the Godly?wicked Day of Chicheſter was the cauſe of his deſperation And yet after by the importunate perſwations of the peſtilent papiſtes denyinge his Maiſter, ſuſtayned this horrible iudgment, that he and ſuch like might be a perpetuall example for you and all men to feare the like or worſe puniſhemente.
            You ſee therfore how there is no truſte but in God, no comfort but in Chriſt, no aſſurance but in his promiſſe, by whoſe obedience onely you ſhall auoyde all danger. And whatſoeuer you loſe in this world and ſuffer for his Name,
                  Mat. 10. it ſhall be here recompenced with double according to his promiſſe, and in the worlde to come with liffe euerlaſtinge: which is to finde your liffe, when ye are willinge to lay it downe at his commandement.
            
               The ſecond and laſte remedie.I am not ignorant how vnnaturall a thinge it is, and contrarie to the fleſhe, willingly to ſuſtayne ſuche cruell deathe, as the aduerſaries haue appoynted to all the children of God, myndinge conſtantly to ſtand by their profeſsion: which to the ſpirite notwithſtanding is eaſie and ioyful. For thogh the fleſhe be frayle, the ſpirite is prompte and redy.

Wherof (prayſed be the name of God) you haue had notable experience in many of your brethern very martyrs of Chriſte, who with ioye paciētly and tryumphinghe, haue ſuffed and drunke with thurſte of that bitter cupp which nature ſo muche abhorreth: wonderfully ſtrēgthned no dowte by the ſecreat inſpiration of Gods holy Spirite. So that there oght to be none amōgeſt you ſo feeble, weake or timorous, whom the wonderfull examples of Godes preſent power and ſinguler fauour in thoſe perſons, ſhulde not incourage, bolden, and fortifie, to ſhewe the like cōſtancie in the ſame cauſe and profeſsion.
            Neuertheles, great cauſe we haue thankfully to conſider the inſpeakable mercy of God in Chriſte, which hath farther reſpecte to our infirmitie, that when we haue not that boldeneſſe of ſpirite to ſtande to the death, as we ſee others, yet geuing ſo muche to our weakneſſe, he hathe prouided a preſent remedie, that beīg perſecuted in one place, we haue libertie to flee in to a nother: where we cannot be in our owne coūtrie

with a ſafe conſciēce (except we would make opon profeſsion of our religion,Mat 10. The greate cōfort that Engliſhe baniſhhed for Chriſte ſake finde in other Countryes which is euery mans duetie, and ſo be broght to offre vp our liues in ſacrifice to God in teſtimonie that we are his:) he hathe mollyfied and prepared the hartes of ſtranges to receue vs with all pitie and gladneſſe, where you may be alſo not onely delyuered from the feare of death and the papiſticall tyrannie practiſed without all meaſure in that coūtrie: but with great freedome of cō
               ſcience heare the worde of God contynually preached, and the Sacraments of our Sauiour Chriſt purely and duely miniſtred, without all dregges of poperie, or ſuperſticion of mans inuention: to the intent you being with others refreſſhed for a ſpace, and more ſtrongly fortified, may be alſo with others more willing and ready to laye downe your lyues at Gods appoyntment. For that is the chiefeſt grace of God, and greateſt perfection, to fight euen to the bloude vnder Chriſtes banner, and with him to geue our liues.
            But if you will thus flee (welbeloued in the Lord) you muſt not choſe

vnto your ſelues places according as you phantaſie, as many of vs which haue left our countrie haue donne: ſome dwelling in papiſticall places amongeſt the enimies of God in the myddle of impietie: in France, as in Paris, Orliance, and Rone: and ſome in Italy, as in Rome, Vaenice, and Padua. Which perſons in fleeing from their Quene, runne to the Pope: fearing the daunger of their bodies, ſeeke where they may poyſon their ſoules: thinking by this means to be leſſe ſuſpected of Ieſabell, ſhew them ſelues afrayd and aſhamed of the Goſpel, which in tymes paſte they haue ſtowtly profeſſed. And leſt they ſhuld be thoght fauorers of Chriſte, haue purpoſly ridden by the Churches, and Congregations of his ſeruauntes their bretherne, nether mynded to comforte others there, nor to be comforted them ſelues. Wherin they haue ſhewed the coldeneſſe of their zele towarde religion, and geuen no ſmall occaſion of ſlander to the worde of God, which they ſeemed to profeſſe. For beinge returned againe into their Countrie, they either become Idolaters with the papiſtes to pleaſe the

Quene, and kepe their poſſeſsions, or els diſſemblers with the reſt of counterfete chriſtians: but to their owne condemnation at length, except the Lorde graunt vnto them ſpeedie repentance. For who ſo are aſhamed of Chriſt, and his Goſpel,
                  Mat. 10. thus denying him before mē: them hath he promiſed to deny, and be a ſhamed of before his Father, and Angells, in heauen. This maner of fleeinge then is vngodly, and (as you heare) daungerous: and therfore not lawfull for you therin to folow theire example.
            Nether is it ynoughe to keepe you out of the dominions of Antichriſte, ād to place your ſelues in corners where you maye be quiete, and at eaſe, and not burthened withe the chardges of the poore, thinking it ſufficient if you haue a litle exerciſe in your houſes in reading a chapiter or two of the Scriptures, and then wil be counted zelous perſons and great goſpellers. No brethern and ſiſters, this is not the way to ſhowe your ſelues manfull ſouldiars of Chriſt, except you reſorte where his

banner is diſplayed, and his ſtandarde ſett vppe: where the aſſemble of your brethern is, and his worde openly preached, and Sacramentes faithfully miniſtred. For otherwiſe, what may a man iudge, but that ſuch either diſdayne the compagnie of their poore brethern, whome they oght by all means to helpe and comfort, according to that power that God hath geuen them for that ende onely, and not for their owne eaſe: or els that they haue not that zele to the houſe of God, the aſſemble of his ſeruantes, and to the ſpirituall gyftes ād graces (which God hath promiſed to powre vpon the diligent hearers of his worde) as was in Dauid: which deſiered being a kinge, rather to be a dore-keeper in the houſe of God, then to dwel in the tentes of the vngodlye:
                  Pſal. 84. lamentyng nothinge ſo muche the iniuries done vnto him by his ſonne Abſolon (which were not ſmall) as that he was depryued from the comfortable exercices in the Tabernacle of the Lorde, which then was in Sion. Nether dothe there appeare in ſuch perſons

that greedie deſier (wherof Eſai maketh mention) whiche oght to be in the profeſſers of the Goſpell,
                  Eſa. 2. who neuer woulde ceaſe or reſte, till they ſhuld clime vp to the Lordes Hill: meaninge the Churche of Chriſte, ſayng one to a nother: Let vs aſcende vp to the Hill of the Lorde, to the houſe of the God of Iacob, and he will teache vs his wayes, and we ſhall walke in his foote ſteppes. For the Lawe ſhall come forthe of Sion, and the worde of the Lorde from Ieruſalem. Whiche zele the Prophet dothe not mē
               tion in vayne, but to ſhew what a thurſt and erneſt deſier ſhuld be in the true Chriſtians, and how the ſame apeareth in ſeekinge and reſortinge to thoſe places, where it is ſet forthe in greateſte abundance and perfection, as was after Chriſtes aſcention in Ieruſalem. And as that zele ſhewed them to be of Chriſte, by the like muſt we be iudged Chriſtians alſo, that if we flee for Chriſte, the places where vnto we flee may beare witnes for what cauſe we are fledde.
            Nether is yt a ſufficient excuſe

which many aleadge, that they beleue to be ſaued by Chriſte, that they haue ſufficient knowledge of their duety, and the reſte, they can ſupplie by their owne diligence. Whoſe faithe is not ſo muche (I dare ſaye) but they haue neede to defier with the Apoſtles, Lorde increaſe our faithe. And if they will ſo confeſſe, why do they forſake the chiefeſt means that God hathe ordeyned, which is the open Congregations of his people, where his worde, the fountayne of faith, is moſte purely preached, and where the Godly examples of others maye be a ſharper ſpurre to prick them forward. And as for the knowledge and diligence of ſuch, may be no buckler to defend their doinges. For yf they haue thoſe gyftes wherof they boſte, where may they beſtowe them better then in the Churche of God? Except they will ſaye,Worldly reſpects which hinder vs frō God oght to be auoyded. they are borne to them ſelues, and haue the gyftes of God which he would haue comon to others, applyed to their owne priuate fantaſie, which is to lappe them vp in a clowte, and not to put them forth to the vantage of the owner, as did

the vnprofitable ſeruant: and as all they do, to whome God hath geuen either learninge, coūſel, or worldly ſubſtā
               ce, which eithet for the ſtrēght of Cities, pleaſantneſſe of ayre, trafficke or marchādiſe, or for anie other worldely reſpect or politie, do abſente thē ſelues frō the Congregatiō and companie of their poore brethern, where Chriſt hathe aduaunced his ſtandarde, and blowen his troumpet, as is afore ſayed.
            Yf God then geue you not ſtrength-at the firſte to ſtand in his profeſsion to the death, nor that you cannot be quiete in conſcience, abiding in your coūtrie: you ſee how his mercy hath geuen you libertie to flee, and what places he hath appoynted for you to flee vnto,The graces of God towardes Englande are moſt abundant if they would vſe thē
                that is, were ye may do good to your ſelues and others, where ye may be free from ſuperſtition and idolatrie, where your faithe may be increaſed rather then diminiſhed, and your ſelues ſtrengthned, confirmed, and more ſtrongly armed.
            But if you in taryinge will nether ſtande manfully to Chriſte your

Maiſter, but betraye him with the Papiſtes in doinge as they do, nor yet with thankes vſe this remedie that God hath graūted to oure infirmitie, to reſorte to his Churches godly īſtituted: what anſwere ſhall you be able to make to his Maieſtie when he ſhall call for accoumpt of your doinges? How ſhall you auoyde his wrathfull indignation, now redie to be powred vpon his enimies? Aſſure your ſelffe, they ſhalbe taken in there ſynne: ād you alſo as God doth fynde you. Yf in the tentes of his enimies, doinge as they do vnder theire ſtanderde, to be ſtryken with them, and alſo to peryſhe. For in takinge part with theire impietie, you muſt be partakers of theire cupp likewiſe. Nether is this anie newe or hard doctrine that may excede your capacitie, but may rather be termed your a. b. c. &amp; firſt principles, where in none oght to be ignorant. That is if we wylbe Chriſts ſcholers, we moſt learne to beare his croſſe, &amp; to folowe him: not to caſt it ofe our ſhulders with the enimies, and rūne from him. It is the ſame

leſſon which of children we learned in the Lordes prayer, that the Name of God the Father may be ſanctified: His kingdome come: His will be dōne. Marke it brethern, that your daylie prayer turne not to your euerlaſtinge confuſion. For yf you daylye praye, that by you his Name maye be ſanctified, that is, that he may be worthely honored for his maieſtie ād wōderfull power, reuerenced for his mercy and infinite wiſdome, feared for his iuſtice, ād iuſte iudgemētes: and yet for feare of the vngodly, do blaſpheme his Name by diſſimulatiō ād outwarde idolatrie, are ye not herein iudges of your owne condemnation? Prayng that his Name may be honored with your lyppes, and blaſpheame him in your deeds? When you praye that his kingdome may come, and yet you your ſelues do buylde and eſtabliſhe the kingdome of Satan? Whē you deſier that his will may be donne, and contrarie therunto, ſtudie to maintayne and accompliſhe the wil of Satan and his members?
            Wherfore be nomore diſceaued

in ſo playne a matter.
                  1. Kin. 19 The cōcluſion conteyninge the effect of the whole boke. Yf the Lorde be God, folow him: if Baal be God, go after him. Playe no more the hypocrites, praye not with your lippes only, but expreſſe the ſame in your workes. Subiecte your ſelues whollye to God: for he hath redemed you. Honor him alone: for you are his people. Let not the example of any leade you in to errour: for men are but mortall. Truſte in the Lorde: for he is a ſure rocke. Beware of his iudgementes: for they are terrible. Truſt not to your owne ſhiftes: for they will diſceaue you. Marke the end of others, and in tyme be warned. Theſe leſſons are harde to the fleſhe, but eaſie to the ſpirite. The waye of the Lorde is a ſtrayte path, but moſt faithefull, ſure, and comfortable. In this waye haue you alſo promiſed to walke with Chriſt: and for the ſame cauſe do you beare his Name, that you ſhuld forſake the worlde and the fleſhe, to yelde vnto him all honour and obedience, before the face of men in earthe, that he may beſtowe vpon you the glorie of his Father which is in heauen. To whom with

the Sonne, and holy Ghoſt be euerlaſting prayſe, honor and glory for euemore. Amen. From Geneua, this firſt of Ianuarie. M. D.LVIII.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            WILLIAM KETHE TO the Reader.
            
               THe vayne harte of mā, full frayle is and blynde,
               vncerteynely ſetled, and reſt can none fynde:
               Whoſe hap is in wandring, to wade the wronge way,
               As one apte by kinde to runne ſtill aſtray.
            
            
               For, what thīge ſo good by truethe hathe bene wroght,
               Or what ſo well framed hath nature forth brought,
               Which man is not prone by crafte to accuſe,
               And natures good gyftes dothe not ſore abuſe?
            
            
               Thus ſee we how man, contemning Gods grace,
               Is wholie inclyned, that ill ſhulde take place:
               Whoſe will (truethe reiectinge) delitth that to haue,
               Which nature corrupted woulde ſeeme ſtill to craue.
            
            
               Sith man then in iudgeinge, ſo thwartly is bente.
               To ſatisfie fanſie, and not true intente:
               How hardly in this caſe, can ſuch iudge vpright,
               Whē trueth doth but peepe out, as ſemth to our ſight.
            
            
               Ful nedefull then were it, we had this reſpecte,
               Before we receaue oght, or oght do reiect:
               The thinge to decide ſo with Iudgement and ſkill,
               That trueth may be ſtickler, and not our one will.
            
            
               Beholde here a trueth drawne forth of her graue,
               By power ſore oppreſſed, and made a bonde ſlaue:
               Whoſe chaīs, thogh this Autor could not rēt or teare,
               Yet hath he forth broght hir, in to moſte clere ayer.
            
            
               With whome now to reaſon, whoſo wil aſſaye,
               Shal learne how ill Rulers we oght to obeye.
               Whiche kill, how they ca
                     •
                  e not in their cruell rage.
               Reſpectīg their will more, thē lawe, othe, or charge.
            
            
               
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   longe foſtered by ſuffrance and awe,
               Haue right rule ſubuerted, and made will their lawe:
               Whoſe pride, how to temper, this truthe will thee tell,
               So as thou reſiſte mayſte, and yet not rebell.
            
            
               Rebellion is ill, to reſiſte is not ſo,
               When right through reſiſting, is donne to that foo,
               Who ſeeketh, but by ruine, agaynſt right to raigne,
               Not paſsinge what periſhe, ſo ſhe ſpoyle the gayne.
            
            
               A publick weale wretched, and to farre diſgraſte,
               Where the right-head is of cut, and a wronge in ſteed plaſte,
               A brut beaſt vntamed a miſbegotthen;
               More meete to be ruled, then raigne ouer men.
            
            
               A maruelous madneſſe, if we well beholde,
               When ſighes ſhall aſſaut mē, to ſee them ſelues ſolde:
               And yet whē frō ſlauery, their friēds woulde thē free,
               To ſtick to their foes ſo, ſtill ſlaues to be.
            
            
               For France ſpiteth Spayne, which Englend doth threat,
               And England proud Spanyards, with ſalte woulde fayne eate:
               Yet Englande proud Spayne aydeth with men, ſhips, and botes.
               That Spayne, (France ſubdued once) may cut all their throtes.
            
            
               A people peruerſe, repleate with diſdayne,
               Thogh flattrie fayne hide woulde their hate, and vile trayne.
               Whoſe rage, ād hotte luſte, diſceate, crafte and pride,
               Poore Naples their bondeſlaue, with great grefe hath tryed.
            
            
               
               Lo, theſe be the byrdes which Englāde muſte feede,
               By plantinge of whom, to roote out their ſeede
               Their owne landes ād lyues, by them firſte deuourde,
               Their maydes then ād wyues, moſte vilelie deflourde.
            
            
               Is this not ſtronge treaſon, ye vnnoble bloudds?
               To ayde ſuche deſtroyers, both with landes ād goods?
               But when they thus pinche you, and ye put to flight,
               To what forte then flee you: or where will you light?
            
            
               For Englande thus ſolde, for Spaniardes to dwell,
               Ye maye not by right, poſſeſſe that ye ſell.
               They ſeinge your treaſon, agaynſte your owne ſtate,
               Wil not with theirs truſt you, which they know ye hate.
            
            
               To Skotlande or France, yf ye then ſhulde cry,
               Your vile deeds now preſent, they may well reply,
               And Dutchlād abhorth you: this thē doth remayne,
               Whē Spaniards are placed, ye muſte to newe Spayne.
            
            
               But, oh dreadfull plague, ād ſigne of Gods wrothe,
               On ſuch noble Gnatos, ſtronge foes to Gods trothe.
               Whom fonde feare hath framed, to prop ſuch a ſtaye,
               As countrie and people, ſo ſeekth to betraye.
            
            
               Which thinge herein proued, to be with out doute,
               All ſuch full well finde ſhall, as reade it throughout.
               Yf then their hartes fayle them the right to defende,
               Confuſion remayneth for ſuche a meete end.
            
         
         
            
            
               Geue not thy glorie to an other: nether that whiche is profitable for thee, to a ſtrange nation.
               Baruch. 4.
            
            
               
                  
                     The way to life it ſtreicte

and fewe finde it.
                     Mat.7.
                  
               
            
            Imprinted at Geneua by Iohn Creſpin. the firſt of Ianuarie. Anno. D. M.D.LVIII.
            
         
      
   

