
   
      
         
            Hollands leaguer: or, An historical discourse of the life and actions of Dona Britanica Hollandia the arch-mistris of the wicked women of Eutopia VVherein is detected the notorious sinne of panderisme, and the execrable life of the luxurious impudent.
            Goodman, Nicholas.
         
         
            
               1632
            
         
         Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01886
            STC 12027
            ESTC S105768
            99841494
            99841494
            6080
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01886)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6080)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:22)
         
         
            
               
                  Hollands leaguer: or, An historical discourse of the life and actions of Dona Britanica Hollandia the arch-mistris of the wicked women of Eutopia VVherein is detected the notorious sinne of panderisme, and the execrable life of the luxurious impudent.
                  Goodman, Nicholas.
               
               [56] p. : ill.  
               
                  Printed by A[ugustine] M[athewes] for Richard Barnes,
                  London :
                  1632.
               
               
                  Signed at end: Nicholas Goodman. Variant: without Goodman's name.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-G⁴.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2004-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-02
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-03
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2004-03
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
            Noctes atque dies patet atri Ianua Ditis.
            
               
            
            Vnto this Island and great Plutoes Court,
            none are deny'd that willingly resort,
            
               Charon or'e Phlegeton will set on shoare,
            and Cerberus will guard you to the doore:
            Where dainty Deuils drest in humane shape,
            vpon your senses soone will make a rape.
            They that come freely to this house of sinne,
            in Hell as freely may haue entrance in▪
            
         
         
            
            HOLLANDS
LEAGVER:
OR,
AN HISTORICAL
DISCOVRSE OF THE
Life and Actions of Dona Britanica
Hollandia the Arch-Mistris of
the wicked women of
EVTOPIA.
            Wherein is detected the notorious
Sinne of Panderisme, and the Execrable
Life of the luxurious Impudent.
            LONDON,
Printed by A. M. for Richard Barnes.
1632.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            HOLLANDS
LEAGVER:
OR,
AN HISTORICAL
Discourse of the Life and Actions,
of Dona Britanica Hollandia, the Arch-Mistris
of the wicked Women
of Eutopia.
            
               THis History, Tale, or tell-troth,
(take it in which sence you please)
is dedicated to the World, whither
all discourses wander, to the
reformation of vice, which is
Good mens wishes, and to the aduancement of
vertue, which is the ayme of all honest affections

so that making my summe iust with
mine account, I doubt not but I shall discharge
my selfe, of that which I owe to posteritie,
to the ruine of sinne, and the immortall
safe-guarde of piety.
            But you will tell me, to detect sinne is to
teach sinne, the discouery of vice like Hydras
heads, doth rather increase then decrease the
vitious, for vertue is seldome found to spring
from Lacedemonian Tables, and chastity much
lesse from Aretines pictures; that wicked persons,
and wicked actions, should rather bee
damn'd in obscuritie, then preserued for eternity,
that it is a sinne against piety, to giue
wickednesse any life of memory, for so the
villaine became lost that set fire on Diana's
Temple, and Manlius was forgot in Rome,
that did iniury to Rome: wicked names dishonour
fayre report, and if by compulsion the
pen must glance vpon them, they ought euer
to be accompanied with curses, and execrations;
vnrepentant sinne is the Deuils Godsonne,
and when we talke of capital wickednes, we
ought to giue it no other name but deuill;

Yet Brutus and his confederates are not forgot
in Liuie; Sinon liues in Virgil, and Pandarus
in Homer, we haue a Layis memorable in Corinth,
a Lamia in Athens, and a Lestrigon in great
Brittaine, why should we then loose this Eutopian
Legend of Britanica Hollandia, who exceeds
all in insolence, instructs all in impudence,
and runnes through a World of damnable
actions, with improuidence; no, as she
is without paralell in her profession, so I wil
striue to delineate her to the life, that she may
euer liue hatefull to all after succession.
            In the Kingdome of Eutopia, nere the fayre
citie of Maugsun, some fewe Leagues distant,
their liued a Gentleman of indifferent Fortunes,
neither so high that ambition did assaile him,
nor so low that contempt might follow him,
but Anchoring in a smooth low tyde, and a
safe harbor, made himselfe content only with
things necessary; he marryed a wife sutable to
his estate, and agreeable with his affections,
for shee had comelinesse enough to content
an honest eye; cleanlines sufficient for a chast
bed, or a frugall Table, and discretion at will

to gouerne and dispose all things committed
to her Steward-shippe; These had issue one
daughter whom they named Britanica Hollandia,
               Hollandia her birth. by reason of some neere allyances betwixt
them and the Neather-lands. A mayd
in the time of her innocence, and ignorance,
so accomplished and accomodated with all
the ornaments of Nature and education, that
shee farre surpassed all those of her rancke,
and might without the offence of modesty
challenge equalitie with those which were
accounted excellent; for shee had a fayre
Eye, full of strong inchauntment; a modest
cheeke, rich with bashfulnesse; and a face so
generally clothed with beauty, &amp; blushes, that
there was an infinite promise of much ensuing
vertue: her stature was but low, yet compos'd
with such true Cymetrie, and so agreeable
with euery other lineament through
the whole Fabricke of her body, that had Appelles
beheld her, he would haue forsworn his
Idol to haue made her his goddesse; but to leaue
off all further circumstance, let it suffice me to

say shee was truely handsome, exceeding
hopefull, and had not the Deuill beene
too ambitious, shee might have bin most
happy, but where the house is cleanest,
there Sathan desires to entersoonest; and
if the guard of Grace be Idle or vnwatchfull,
repentance may follow, but it cannot
prevent surprizall, and so it fares with this
Creature, for as heaven had bestowed
vpon her all outward imbelishments to
attract vertue vnto▪ her, so had some sinister
power, or the corruption of her
owne flesh married to those bodily beauties,
such a wicked spirit, that all goodnes
became to her an vtter stranger▪ shee was
of such a proud, haughty, and disdainfull
nature, so Masculine in her disposition,
and so mad to encounter any crosse to
her best loued cogitations, that like the
Spider, which turneth all things to poyson
which it tasteth, so she became an vtter
Athiest, and would acknowledge no
God but her own pleasure; She had from
mens prayses, womens envies, and her
glasses plain-dealing, her parents tendernesse,

her friends carefulnes, and her companions
amazednesse, got such a true
knowlege of her handsomnesse, that she
did not onely beleeue it, and loue it, but
mightily doated vpon it; neither did this
foolishnesse of selfe-affection so bind her
to the admiration of her owne beautie,
as a proud and furious conceire of the excellency
of her wit, (aboue the sphere of
other womens capacities) did bind and
slaue her to imbrace to her selfe this conclusion
that she only was excellent
            Now she begins to grow in hate with
her fathers house, the Country is vnpleasant,
vnhabitable, obscure and durtie, that
house-wifely imployments, were slauish
ingagements; to live with parents, was
but to lye with bondage, that al comman
dements were curses, and obedience only
a figure of simplicitie, and ignorance;
shee would often say within her selfe,
what is beautie, if not seene, what seene,
if not admired, what admired, if not desired,
and what any, or all if not enioyed;
and where shall these bee gathered from

the blossomes of trees, heaps of stones the
ouerflowes of fountains, or the dul rabble
of Clownes and heards-men? No, it is the
City that is the spheare of beauty, there are
her Temples, there live her votaries, and
there burnes her sacrifice, the Countrie is
but a rotten chest that conceales holy reliques,
let me live in the Citie, where if I
cannot out-shine all, or at least equall all,
yet a tworst I shall be hidde in an handsome
Cabinet.
            Vpon these, and the like resolutions she
throws her-selfe into a deepe melancholie:
all meates are but course for her dyet,
shee forsakes them; sleepe is too neere a
kinseman to death, she hates it; all company
seemes rude, shee loathes it; all discourses
are vnpollish't, her eare will not
receiue them; and to conclude, as an exanimated
carcasse, she walks with no soule,
and but halfe a motion.
            Her parents quickly perceiue this alteration,
and like noble Phisitians labor to
find out the cause to make the cure more
easie, more speedie, more certaine; but she

that had a lockt vp soule in a fort impregnable,
what through disdaine, the handmaid
of Pride, &amp; Pride it selfe the Lord of
stubborne resolution, she became so impenitrable,
that sooner might they bring
the Poles together, then separate her from
one tittle of her private resolution, so that
finding her fixed, they leaue to molest
her, onely obserue all occasions, and all
circumstances, euery passage, and euery
Action, that might give any light to those
designes on which shee laboured with
such difficultie; in the end, finding her set
one day in a priuate Roome, without any
companion, but solitude &amp; her owne
thoughts, her Father stealing within the
distance of her speeches, might heare her
vtter these wordes. O life, which hast deceiued
so many, seduced so many, blinded so
many, thou art nothing at thy beginning, thy
light is nothing but a shaddow, thou art but
smoake at thy height, thou art sweet to fooles,
thou art bitter to the wise, who loueth thee,
knowes thee not, who knoweth thee, contemnes
thee; and here with a deepe sigh shee

made a full period, when her father pressing
vpon her, demanded the cause of this
quarrell betwixt her and life, vrging her
with much ingratitude, to condemne
that, from which her selfe had receiued
so much luster, applying her beauty, her
youth, her wit, and all her inward, and
outward faculties, as vnrefellible arguments
of infinite beholdingnesse to life,
who had brought them into the World,
&amp; made them beloued of the World; but
she with a silent bashfulnesse (fuller of
deceit then innocence) forbearing to reply
gave him occasion to assaile her with all
the strength that nature, loue, &amp; a fathers
authority could collect together, and did
so vrge her to display, and lay open the
Cabinet of her deerest counsells, that she
either vnwilling to loose so faire an opportunity,
or to apparel her envious griefe
in the robes of obedience, with a seeming
vnwilling willingnesse, did disburden
her heart of that loade of griefe, which
so long had afflicted her: yet not without
many disguises, and false habits, as

not being weary of the Countrey for it's
solitude, but carefull to discharge him of
much cost, and incumbrance; that the City
was more hopefull for her aduancement,
because the two columbes of posteritie,
honorable Mariage, and wealthy
imployment had there a setled residence,
and threw away their fauors blindfold,
like the children of Fortune.
            
            There did need small debatement,Her comming to the City.
When both the parties did agree vpon
one proposition, for he seemed to outrun
her in willingnes, and as if their thoughts
had bene cast in one mould, an equall diligence
made preparation for her speedy
departure, the mothers consent was
not wanting, so that all drawing by one
linke without hinderance, strife or aduantage,
the work was in a trice effected,
the daughter was brought to the City,
and setled in an honest Magnificos seruice.
            Here, after the expence of some small
time, liuing as it were in a Burse of resort,
where men and their minds were continually

trucking for new commodities, it
was impossible for this rich Iewell,
which was without foyle; because it
knew no Art, and without fraud by reason
of an innocent ignorance, should either
stand gaping for a chap-man, or like
an idle prentise, with his hands hid in his
cap, cry, Sir, what lacke you; No, vnsullied
beauty like the Sunne will giue light to
a whole Hemyspheare▪
                and this damosell
had so shot her beames through euery
corner of the City, that her Suitors were
like Coriscas smockes, infinite in number,
many in good opinion, and but one at
one time in imployment, yet with such
seuerity she gouerned her passions, that
the strictest eye of modesty could hardly
detect her gouernment, and she was the
rather induced to this Austerity, by beholding
the pictures of two famous Curtezans,
which did hang in her Masters
Gallery; the first, which vvas lesse faire,
but more fortunate, had this inscription,
Si non Caste tamen Caute, the other which
vvas farre beyond all for beauty, and inferior

to none for Miserie, had vvritten ouer
her. Nec caste, Nec caute; on these two
plaine songs her resolution made sundry
descants, but the close of euery strain was,
That to sinne wisely, was to sinne safely,
that after-thoughts vvere foolish, and had
I wist childish; hence it came that amōgst
the vn-numbred number of her Suitors,
she chose one whom shee knevv honest,Her marriage.
by all mens report, frugall in her owne
experience, industrious in his affaires, and
painefull in euery circumstance of his
profession, one that was handsome enough
to loue, and stout enough to controle,
yet such an Idolater to her beauty, &amp;
such a slave to her commandements, that
neither his eyes, nor eares could carry
credit beyond her sufferance; of this man
she made a husband, and had not the deuill
and womans vveakenesse conspir'd
to make ship vvracke of her vertue, they
might have liued and dyed vvith faire reputation;
but novv shee shakes handes
vvith bashfulnes, and feare, &amp; the manlinesse
of her courage,Her falling from vertue. meeting vvith the libertie

of a bold wives rudenes, she dare both
intice and lend an eare to inticements. 'Tis
true, that loue in her friends, made them call
impudence an high spirit, and losenesse a pleasant
behauiour, but those which had beene
brought vp in the same schoole where shee
learnt her complement, knew that the gate
was wide enough, and the way plaine enough
which leade to the ruine of her vertue.
            Many assault were giuen to this faire Fort,Her subtiltie.
but some she with-stood, to gaine an opinion
of goodnesse, and they were great ones; some
she durst not entertaine for feare of after repentance,
and they were loose ones, some she
held at a distance to draw on benefit, and they
were the rich ones, and some she scorn'd, and
they were fooles, Fidlers, or base ones: But behold,
at last, the deuill himselfe fearing to lose
so rich a prize, which hee knew would not
come to his kingdome alone with her owne
lading, but with the spoyles, and triumphs of
a world of vnfortunate creatures of both
sexes, he sent to assaile her one Ignatius a Puritane
Iesuite;
               The first that made her a whore. a fellow, whom Lucifer had so instructed,
and adorned with all the deceiuable

qualities and inchauntments of a seeming
goodnesse, that vertue herselfe could hardly
have discouered him, without the vse of her
diuinest spectacles; he had al the amiablenesses
of a good face, and a well-shap'd body, which
he made more glorious with grauity &amp; good
cloathes, he had an excellent wit, prompt and
ready, which he witnessed in his discourses, being
full of delight and learning, he was full of
Bounty, and liberalitie; a world of poore deceiued
people (especially women) maintaining
his exchequor, and when the fire of lust
was kindled in him by the deuils bellowes, he
was so full of delicate Petulance, and inchaunting
dallyance, that a cold halfe buried Anchorite
would haue ingendred a flame from his
embers.
            This great General for Hel (not alone in this,
but in a world of other damnable actions)
com's with his Legions of inchantments to besiege
this Redoute, or weake Sconce, euen at the
time when there was a mutynie raised betwixt
her and her best souldiers; for indeed, Modestie
was in disgrace, and accus'd for a Coward, Chastity
was scorn'd as a shaddow &amp; no substance,

               Bashfulnesse was reputed weake and childish,
Honour a Chimera, Good-fame a dreame; and indeed,
all the Vertues stood cashired as enemies
vnto Pleasure; so that there was left none
to withstand him but Frailtie, a Cannon-law,
and a Penall Statute.
            
            Against these hee rais'd such a battery of
sweet discourse, and inchanting perswasions,
that she stood amazed, and staggering at the
first on-set, till feare of the Law, and a little
loue to good report, stept betwixt her and the
enemy, and beat him backe with these, or the
like arguments. First, that her Reputation (not
God or his Iudgements) were so deare and
tender vnto her, that she durst not give eare to
his sorceries: but he with a smile (wherein
a good eye might haue discerned scorne) asked
her what Reputation was; She told him it
was the very Manna, and Nepenthe of generous
Spirits, the Goddesse of great courages,
and the triumph of all Noble Actions; she sayd
it was a thing so delicate, so pure, and so vnspotted,
that the least excesse did blemish it,
any vniust action dishonour it, indiscretion, negligence
or Idlenesse deface it, but Prostitution
               
that did wholly ruine it; it is a constant friend
that will follow and go with any good action,
but if once forsaken, no inquisition, no search,
no prayers, or teares, can euer againe find it: Beleeve
it Sir, (said she) there is no such misery as
to outlive Reputation, nor any follies like that
vvhich puts it in hazard. But he, to whom
Blasphemy was familiar, &amp; Atheistical propositions
more frequent, then holy sentences, had
soone brought her to a Non-plus; so that forsaking
her guardians, she vvas content to hearken
to composition. This capitulation assuring
him of future conquest, he now began to
sing his owne triumph; and to make his conditions
more glorious, the assurance of her affections
more serious, and his laciuious pleasures,
of a long liv'd indurance, he began to discourse
vnto her the liues &amp; Legends, (but not
the deaths and disasters) of divers famous and
renowned Courtezans;
               The tale of Lol
                        •
                     ca Paulina.
                but especially aboue all
the rest, and as a History best agreeing, and paralelling
with her owne Fortunes, as also seeking
to couer his owne luxurious wickednes,
and the wickednesse of his owne coate and
calling, vnder a greater mans wantonnesse, he

insisted most vpon the life and fortunes of Lollea
Paulina, the greatest Courtezan, the basest
Whore, and the deceitfullest Bawde, that euer
Rome did acknowledge; But here you must
vnderstand, that this subtile Enginer, playd but
the flattering Historian, for he only toucht at
her felicities, but either forgot, or leapt ouer
her infinite miseries; he shewed how she was
borne in the City of Fano in Italie,
               Rome. of good,
but poore parentage: how after her Fathers
death, necessitty brought her to seeke shelter,
being accompanied with nothing but a diuine
beauty, an vnmatchable personage, a
boundlesse wit, and an infinite spirit.
            Here Hipolito the great Cardinall of Est, and
brother to the Duke of Ferara, beholding her,
grew enamored on her, bought her at an infinite
price, and maintained her aboue the ranck
of the greatest Princes: Insomuch that at an
enterview of Ambassadors, before the Pope, in
Mounte Angelo (being by torchlight) she came
amongst the Ladies so couered, and onercouered
with Dyamonds, and the richest Iewelry,
that excepting her face, (which the Sun it
selfe was not able to darken) there could nothing

be discerned but a mouing flame of
most glorious fire; and those which had skill
did value her at more then a Million.
            
            It is not to be exprest with what greedines
of spirit, and earnest delight, Britanica's eares
drunke in this Story, for she was infinitly couetous;
not as Misers to cram her chests, but as
a discreete Prodigall to fill her pockets, placing
her delight in giuing, and spending, Ryot, Reuels,
Playes, Feasts, and all manner of wastful delights,
were to her such deare companions, that rather
then loose them, she would lay both life
and soule in pawne for their ransome; nay, she
was such a true admirer of pleasure, that albe
shee knew there was no true pleasure vpon
earth, and that only Griefe Went vp &amp; downe,
couered in pleasures out-side, yet was her soule
so rauisht with delight, that she became dead
flesh, and would not feele vexation as long as
her eyes stood fixt on Pleasures garments.
            
            This Ignatius saw, this he knew, and finding
her Spirits take fire at his words, he againe
pursued his Story, and shewed her
how Paulina hauing nothing but the reuenue
of Lustre, a little beautie, was three times the

richest, the greatest and the most respected Lady
of all Rome; and here he paul'd, for had he
followed the truth of the Story, it would have
shewed him that she was three times also the
poorest, the most deiected &amp; basest, miserable,
despised creature that Rome, or the world had
euer reserued for memory: nay, so exceeding
hatefull was her condition, &amp; so infinite her contempt,
that she gaue her body in prostitution to
the common hang-man, for one meale to sustaine
her; aud in the end dyed without pitty,
and was buried without Ceremonie, had he amplified
any thing vpon this Text, he had mar'd
his owne market, and made a Conuertite: But
they were vvhites beyond his Ayme; confusion
was only within the reach of his Arrow,
and that he hit, for his wordes did so vvell
please her, and his rich promises so assure her,
that freely she gaue him her body in possession;
and he inioyed her for some short space,
vvith out competitor.
            But Lust is a Gangrene,
               Her multiplicity of prostitutions. &amp; hauing once poisoned
a member, neuer leaues spreading till the
vvhole body be cōfounded, she hath now broken
one linke in the golden chaine of Chastity,
               
and she cares not though all the rest be molten
with confusion; hence it com's that she entertaines
more deuils, variety is pleasant, one
ship yelds small custome, great Nauies fil large
Treasures, &amp; her reuenues came in with such
full Tydes, that false Pleasure made her beleeue
there would neuer come ebbing.
            
            In this vnchast Progresse, she took an essay
or tast of all degrees, all professions, and all conditions,
from the Noble, to the Gentile, from the
Camp to the City, her eares had heard al languages,
her purse had receiued all Coynes, and had
not her fortune bin more fauourable then her
affections, her body had bin confounded with
all manner of putrifactions.
            But in the end,She determines to turne Bawd looking back into her selfe,
and beholding into what a crasie and rotten
Barke she had shipt her selfe, on a rough and
tempestuous Sea, where infinit diseases lay gaping
vpon her, the terrour of the lawes ready
to deuoure her, shame and beggerie striuing to ouertake
her, and lastly the cursse of all curses, to
make her last will on a dunghill, or at the best
in a Spittle, this did so perplexe her, that being
cloyd with saciety, and sin as weary of her, as

she was weary of sinning, she began to
turne ouer the leafe of her wickednesse,
and though she had no thought of amendment,
yet she wil take a new course
for the safety of her health and person.
            She will no more be a Layis, but a Lena,
no more a bewitching Whore, but a
deceiuing Bawd, the Sinnes of others shall
maintaine her Sinne, she will no more
trust her-selfe on the Surges, but wil traffique
by Factours, and according to the
wealth of her Wares, so shalbe the encrease or decrease of her Reuenues.
            
            She had no sooner setled her selfe in
this resolution, and sealed it before Hell
and her owne evill Conscience, but presently
she puts it in execution, and that she
might frame all accomodations sutable
to her deseigne; she lookes forth for a better
house, for her owne wanted elbow
roome, she must haue many Meanders,
and many passages, many holes, and many
hides, deedes of darkenesse doe euer require
many darke corners.
            At last she lights vpon an old ruined

Castell newly repaired, so commodiously
placed both for her home-bred customers
and Forreine visitants, as well
for the Hawke, or Buzzard, that Hyes
by day, as the Owle, or Bat, that flutters
in the night, that her heart could not
wish a place of better convenience;
The Sea on one side did beare against
the walles, and both tall Shippes, Flyeboates,
and Pinnaces, might there Anchor
in a safe Harbour; on the other
side, it had some sleight intrenchments,
which albe they were but weake
and assayleable, yet the Sea vpon all assaults,
did grant her both Munition, victual,
and avoydance. And that a good Name
might patronize her many euill actions,
she caused it to bee called by a good old
Dukes Title.
               As we say Dukes place Duke Humfrey, or the like.
            
            Of this house by contract, she got possession,
and her purse being well filled, and
wide open, emptied it selfe to giue it adorment,
there wanted nothing for State,
nothing for Magnificence, nothing for Delight,
nothing for Beauty, nothing for Necessity,
               
howsoeuer the bones that lodg'd in
it were rotten and vnwholsome, yet the
Monument it selfe was wondrous Gaudie,
and hansome; there was nothing now for
her to search for, but liuing furniture, and
that she diuided into three stations.
            
            The first,A Bawdes furniture a stout Ruffian to guard her,
the second, lustie strong Queans, to supply
offices, and the third, petulant painted,
and halfe guilt Mimicks, to giue entertainment;
The first of these shee saued from
the Gallowes, the second she hired from
the Stews, and the last, she had bought vp
by whole sale from the Countrey: there
needed not much search, sin is found in euery
corner, and these creatures like troublesome
water-men plying a rich fare,
will thrust themselues into the deuills
armes beyond hope,With whom she trades. beyond redemption.
            There was not a Carrier that had a
crackt piece, but she had coyne to exchange
it, there was not a Poulterer, that
brought vp a yong or tender pullet, but it
was bought for her dyet, she had charmes
to intice the simple, money to bewitch the

needy, rich clothes to adorne proud spirits,
ease for Idlenesse, pleasure for wantens,
and indeed any thing, or all things to
keepe her Common-wealth from falling.
            Being thus accommodated, and her
Mart proclaimed, there was no doubt of
customers, euery man hath a penny for
a new Tauerne, and euery Letcher hath a
Dollor for a renowned Brothell, and then
this, there was none so famous; and her
visitants came flocking so fast for entertainment,
that her Kitchin was like Aetna,
euer flaming, her Hall was like Augeus
stable, euer stinking with broken meate,
and Mary-bones, her dining-roome, was like
Babell, a mixture of nothing but confused
noyses, and her inward and priuate
Lodgings, like Hell it selfe, where wicked
creatures lay bathing themselues in Lust,
as the damned soules doe in Sulphur, thus
she continued her ryot for a long season,
boasting her-selfe in the strength of her
wickednesse, and not grieuing for any
thing more, then that she could bee no
more wicked.
            
               
But there are Iudgements Registred aboue,Her sinnes calling in question.
and shame and disgraces preserued
belowe, and when either the one, or
the other falls, Woe to the offender; Iudgment
may forbeare, and Iustice may
sleepe, but neither will pardon, it is
only to rayse the Arme higher, that
the Thunder may fall with greater
furie; And now the noyse of these offences
haue awakened Authority and
that ioyning with piety, both send forth
their Ministers to apprehend her; At
first she playes the Rebell, and withstands
their Summons, but finding her
selfe at last inuyroned on all sides, and
that neither Sea, nor Land, affoorded her
safety, how-euer vnwilling, yet with
a seeming willingnesse, she yeelded vp
her-selfe and her retinue, into the hands
of Mercie; From thence they were
brought to the barre of Iustice, where
her Ruffian was perpetually condemned
to labour at the Hempe-beetle;
               A place like our houses of correction. The rest
whom she had seduced,A place like Bridewell.
                were sent for
euer to the house of Repentant Strumpets,
               
only her selfe, who was the chiefe author
and framer of all this Iniquitie,
               A place, like Newgate. she was
sent to the loath some dungeon of Capitoll
offenders, there to remaine till her cause
were heard, and due punishment put in
execution.
            All this as it was decreed,Her carriage in prison. so it was performed,
and each one went to their seuerall
place of sadnesse, but Britanica, who
although shee range in a superlatiue way
of wickednesse, yet did she not want
friends, neither was shee without
her dayly visitants, for there is a correspondencie
amongst the worst, and
wicked ones are sayd euer to hold together.
She had Counsailes of all manner
of creatures, Quirks to avoid Statutes,
Quillets to defraud Iudgements, and Demurres
to protract and put off the dayes
of her Tryall; Shee wanted no Suitors
to pleade for compassion, no aduocate
to blanch her offences, and make her
blacke sinnes white ones, there did need
no teares, she commanded more Crocodils
then Nilus, and for bribes, her Coffers were

full, and she was willing to vnloade
them: But all these and a World of others,
being bound vp together in a Bundle,
and put in the scale against her intollerable
mischiefes, were so light and vnvaluable,
that but dispaire and disgrace
she could find no comforters; Finding
her selfe thus hard beset, she now begins
to call vnto her the strength of a
womans wit, and concludes in her
selfe, that as the Serpent deceiued the first
woman with his flattery, so he may (for amends)
giue her some reliefe with his subtilty,
and indeed her cause was so foule,
that there was no hope but in stratagem,
and to that course she onely now bends
her study, and in this sort she effects it.
            Some few dayes before her tryall,Her escap
                     •
                   from prison. there
came to visit her a Gentleman of very grave
and portly carriage, one that had in his
looks and behauiour, both reuerence and
Authority, hee salutes her by the name of
Neece, and she with low humilitie, and a
riuer of well coind teares, blushing that
shee could not blush faster, returnes

his Salutations, with the name of an
Vnckle, she casts downe her countenance
as ashamed to looke vpon him, he giues
her comfort, but so mixt with seuere
and bitter counsell, that the standers by
might perceiue he came neither to flatter
nor deiect her; these complements finished,
they fell to priuate discourses; those
ended, according to the custome of those
places, and the vse of such visitants, he
calls for Beere, for Ale, for Wine, and a
World of other Iunkets, there is no spare
of cost, his gold flies, the Keeper carouses,
his seruants supplie things wanting,
and no man neere them, but hath
busie imployment.
            After this conflict ended, and the Gentleman
preparing for his departure, he bestowed
vpon the Keeper, a Ring of pretty
valew, vpon his seruants Gold, and on the
poorer sort of prisoners a Bountifull Larges,
descending downe the staires he offers
to take his leaue of his Neece, but
she will attend him as farre as the limits
of the house vvill giue her sufferance, and

so shee brings him downe to the lowest
hall, then offering to leaue him,
hee told the Keeper how sorry hee
was to depart with drye lippes, and
calling to mind a Tauerne that stood
at the next doore, he woes the Keeper
there, by all meanes, to take another
Pottle.
            
            The Keeper is willing to attend
him, and why (quoth the Gentleman)
may not my Neece take share with vs?
for mine owne part, I know not her
Trespasse, therefore I dare not vrge
vnlawfull fauour. Sir, (quoth the
Keeper) her offence is neither Fellony,
nor Treason, shee is neither lyable to
B
                     •
                  nd, nor Execution, and therefore
my selfe will bee her Guardian, and
shee shall waite vpon you; and so
together they goe all three to the
Tauerne; the Vncle calls for Pottle vpon
Pottle, the Neece fills bowle vpon
bowle, and the Keeper drinkes them

vp as if his thirst could never be quenched;
In the midst of these quaffings,
the Keeper and the Vncle, fall into
a discourse of such seriousnesse, that they
neglected all things but their owne
speeches; Britanica taking aduantage at
this Obliuion, rises from the Table, and
as if the Wine had stird in her some
Office of secret occasion, steales out
of doores, and knowing that at the
very entrance of the backe doore,
stoode a Monasterie of Gray Fryers,
looking backe, and seeing her Argus
more and more inchaunted with
Mercurie, like light Salmacis hauing
her heeles at libertie, away she runs,
and finding the doore of the Monasterie
open, like a poore affrighted
Doue, shotte from the Talents
of an eager Faulcon, In she enters for
safety; to the first Brother she meets,
shee falls vpon her knees, and hauing
taught her eyes to weepe at her owne

pleasure, shee deliuers him so pitifull a
story of her misfortune, that h
                  •
               d he bin
as cold as his profession, yet it would
haue mooued in him a Flame of infinite
Compassion, hee takes her vp, and
beeing, as all his Order are, faithfull and
helpefull to womens afflictions, hee
promises her all reliefe, all safetie, which
done, hee conueies her through the
darke corners, and intricate passages
of their cloyster, whether he shewed her
his owne Cell or no, it is vncertaine; But
it is an apparant trueth, that he neuer
forsooke her, till hee had placed her in
that safety, which her selfe desired.
            By this time her Vncle and the Keeper
hauing tyred themselues with needlesse
complements, began to giue their
tongues a little ease, that their eyes
might with more liberty looke about
them.
            The Vncle perceiuing that his
worke was effected, faynes occasion

of hastie departure. The Keeper supposing
his prisoner had beene with
the Mistris of the house, conducteth
him to the doore, and there shakes
handes till their next meeting; then
calling for his Charge, he fi
                  •
               des that
she is vtterly missing; it is vaine to
trouble your eares with the Keepers
amazement, his furie, his fretting, and
his inquisition, let it suffice shee is
gone; her escape is knowne, the
Monastery stands vpon Priuiledge, and
had the Keeper all the charmes of
Medea, or Circes, they were too weake
to open one boult in those places.
            
               Britanica being thus escaped, and by
the helpe of her Confessour, brought to
the place of her owne safetie, she there
lyes hid like the Minataure in the Laborinth,
yet howeuer her body lay concealed,
her mind was full of Action,
and busie molestation, and now shee
sets all her Emmets, and labouring acquaintance

on worke to sue, if not for
a pardon, yet at least for some faire
composition; and hauing the experience
of former occasions, shee knew
there was no way so safe or speedy as
that of Bribes, therefore like a prodigall
she casts away her wealth, and would
not suffer any man to bee imployed for
her, but his pockets were fild with gold
by her; In the end her Proiect prooued
prosperous, and vpon strong Securitie
of a new life to come, and a true Repentance
for Crimes past, her peace was
made, but yet at so deare and high
prized conditions, that looking into
that infinite wealth, of which but little
before shee stood possest, shee now
found her selfe scarse able to subsist or
to bestow one good Meale vppon her
Belly.
            
            There was not a Curse,
               Her miseri
                     ••
                  . an affliction,
a Plague, or what else is more bitter,
that euer was foretolde, or predestinate

to a Strampet, but she had her share
thereof in a downe-pressed and ouerflowing
measure; shee saw her kindred
loathe her, Friends forsake her, her
Companions mocke her, her Slaues commaund
her, and which is an Hell aboue
all other, none but her enemies to pittie
her.
            These afflictions,A new falling. euery one thought
to bee Adamants, powerfull enough
to draw her Soule to heauenly Meditations;
But the effect proued quite conry,
for she euer carried the Deuils Balme
in her Bosome, and could annoint ouer
euery disaster of Fortune, with, what
will be shall be; She had got this Adage,
in her mouth, Things past cure, past care,
and whether it were Enuie, or Furie,
or both, shee became so desperate, that
shee cared not to trust her selfe in the
Seas, on a hurdle.
            After some small time thus spent in
languishment, looking at no marke, but

the old one, (for she could with the
least trouble hit it) shee labours all her
Spirits, all her Imaginations, puts her
Friends, Flatterers, and Companions, to the
Test, leaues no way or meanes vnassayed,
how shee might aduaunce and
set vp againe her old occupation; shee
hath framed to her selfe, new lawes of
seuerer condition, shee will haue Taxes
of a higher, and more profitable Nature,
shee will haue Ryot clothed in Frugalities
shaddow, her Wine, though more in
Measure, yet shall be drunke in lesse Glases;
her Musique shall speake sharply, and
sweetly, but not loud; her Wench
                     •
                  s shall
be faire and handsome, yet but few in
number; for when Supplies are wanting,
shee knowes how to fetch them from
places of fayre Reputation; her Ordinary
seruants, shal be comely and industrious,
and when extremity comes vpon her,
shee will haue disguises to make them
appeare halfe Angels; In briefe, her old

               Common-wealth shall bee turned topsieturvie,
and this new one, made so strong
and permanent, that it shall be to all the
Impudent creatures of the earth, an everlasting
president.
            Vpon these Resolutions, shee thought
her worke was halfe finished, till looking
better into her designe, she found
the Base and ground-worke whereon
shee was to build the foundation of her
proceedings, was yet to find out, and
vtterly beyond both her reach and compasse,
and that was a convenient house;
shee will no more trust Old Ruines, or
Religious Neighbors, the one will endure
no Batterie, the other will abide no
Badde dealing; Shee will haue a house
of Strength, a Fort, a Bulwarke, a place
so impregnable, that when all shall bee
vanquisht, it shall stand in defiance; and
that she might attaine such a safetie, she
ranges through euery part, and promising
place of the Citty, but all in vaine,

those buildings are so linkt one to another,
that all are to be surprised; She
then survayes the Suburbes, but findes
none to content her; at last she betakes
her selfe to the Sea, and makes a discouery
vpon the water, there shee findes
many Rockes, many Islands, to which,
Nature had lent much Strength, but Art
must bee imployed, and that was too
costly; halfe tyred with her search, and
thinking to returne, she is informed
of a place fit for her purpose,Like the Banck side. beeing
wonderous commodiously planted for
all accomodations; it was out of the Citie,
yet in the view of the Citie, only
divided by a delicate Riuer, there was
many handsome buildings, and many
hearty neighbours, yet at the first foundation,
it was renowned for nothing
so much as for the memory of that famous
Amazon, Longa Margarita, who had
there for many yeeres kept a famous infamous
house of open Hospitality.
            
            
               
Shee no sooner heard this report
but presently turning her Sailes, shee
made for that coast, where shee found
such aboundance of Naturall and Arteficiall
intrenchments, that euer the house
seemed to be in it selfe a little City.
            
            Heere shee enquires, what strong
holde,
               The site of her house or Fort, was to bee let for yeerely
Reuenue, and presently shee was
brought to a Fort, Citadell, or Mansion
House, so fortified, and invyroned
with all manner of Fortifications, that
had Impregnable Rhodes taken thence
it's patterne, neither the Turkes wealth,
nor the Traytors wit could euer haue
betrayed it, for e're any Foe could approach
this, hee must march more
then a Musket-shot, on a narrow Banke,
(where three could not goe on Brest)
betwixt two dangerous ditches; then
enter a Port, bulwarked on euery side,
and crosse immured both before and
behinde, with deepe ditches, a Drawbridge,
               
and sundry Pallysadoes, then another
passage, in all poynts like the
former, Sluced with ditches, and Baracadoed
with strong Rampiers.
            
            Then another ditch of of much larger
continent then any before spoke
of, which ranne like a circumference,
and girded in it's Armes all the whole
Mansion, then a World of other Bulwarkes,
Riuers; Ditches, Trenches, and Outworkes,
which hem'd in the Orchards,
Gardens, Base-courts, and Inferiour Offices,
making euery one capable of a
seuerall fight, and euery fight able for
many houres to play with an Armie;
when shee had taken a full survay
of this Forcel
                     •
                  t, and seene how commodious
and fit it was for her purpose,
shee then inquires what other
benefits were appertaining vnto it,
as Neighbour-hood, pleasant walks,
Concourse of Strangers, and things of
like Nature, in all which she receiued

a full satisfaction; especially, and aboue
all the rest, she was most taken with the
report of three famous Amphytheators,
which stood so neere scituated, that
her eye might take view of them from
her lowest Turret, one was the Continent
of the World, because halfe the yeere a
World of Beauties, and braue Spirits resorted
vnto it; the other was a building
of excellent Hope, and though wild beasts
and Gladiators, did most possesse it, yet
the Gallants that came to behold those
combats, though they were of a mixt
Society, yet were many Noble worthies
amongst them; the last which
stood, and as it were shak'd handes
with this Fortresse, beeing in times
past, as famous as any of the other,
was now fallen to decay, and like a
dying Swanne, hanging downe her
head, seemed to sing her owne dierge;
With these reports, Dona Hollandia
was rauisht beyond measure, so that

fearing to loose the instant opportunitie
without further debatement, she
presently stroke vp the Bargaine, possession
is giuen, the Keyes deliuered,
and when she please she may enter.
            After these proceedings,Her new preparations. shee returned
home to prepare Men, and
Munition for defence, Wenches for
vse, and victuall for mainteinance,
as for houshold Ornaments, those
shee intended to increase, according
to the strength of her Coffers. Her
desires were so great, that her haste
in the execution could not bee little,
shee will not loose a minute, but (according
to the old saying) running
from post to piller, and making Hay
in the Sunne-shine, shee fore-slowes
no occasion, till she haue all things
fit for her new worke; which obtained,
she imbarkes her selfe, and makes
for her wished harbour, where in a little
space of time shee landed with one

               Ruffian, whose name was Cerberus, and
rightly, for he was monstrous both in
shape and condition, and to him shee
gaue charge of the gate, the Drawbridge,
and Percullis, she had foure wantons,
the first Beta Breslonia, a huge Bona-Roba,
one impudent aboue measure,
and insolent beyond comparison; the
next Eliza Caunce, for by chance her father
got her, by chance he forsooke her,
by chance shee turned Whore, and by
chance this Bawd light vpon her, she
was yong, little▪ but a wondrous wanton,
she had a white skin &amp; a wel shapt
foot, only her haire was Corral, but couered
with a white Periwig, the third was
Longa Maria, a wench of a good handsome
carriage, not so Rampant as the rest,
not so rude in behauiour, but being seasoned
with better education, she could
boast of some parts, for she had a
good voyce, and could touch the Vyoll;
the last was Maria Petit, a small handfull

of woman, yet pleasant and witty
she was all Motion, and Action, nothing
was more irkesome to her then
sleepe and silence, for by her will shee
would be euer dancing, or singing; She
had three houshold Officers, a Cooke-wench,
a Laundrey-lasse, and a Girle
Scullian.
            Beeing thus landed with this Luggage,
shee presently placed euery one
in their true equipage, gaue them their
seuerall charges, read them the Lawes,
and Ordinances of the house, Proclaiming
a strickt penalty for the breach
of euery condition; this done, shee
hangs foorth her Flagge for custome,
Proclaimes her preparations, and invites
all the world to a generall entertainement.
            Did you euer see Eagles prey on dead
carcasses, Crowes feede vpon carrion,
or hungry dogges deuouring filthie
intrailes, in double that aboundance,

came creatures of all qualities to be vndone
by her, only the empty purse was
expulsed, and could get no admittance,
nay a reasonable stocke many times perished
in the mid-way, and could not
get to the end of his purpose, her Taxes
and customes were so many, and so
mighty: for Cerberus at the first port had
a double impost, one for the gate, another
for the Draw-bridge, the houshold
officers had Fees for the Hall, for the dining-roome,
and the with-drawing
chamber, the rest which were peculiar
to the Bawd her selfe, report hath affirmed
they are sans number: thus euery
day came some tall Ships, some Fly-boats,
some Caruils, and some Frigots, wealthily
laden, but at their returne, they had
not so much as Ballast, but came forth
poore and emptie.
            All her entertainments had a Protean
condition, full of variety and changes,
and shee would euer suite them to the
nature of him that was entertained; if

hee were of worth and respect, hee was
respectiuely vsed, if otherwise, besides
the expence of his coyne, his clothes
were forfaited for his rude behauiour,
&amp; diuers haue bin seene to returne from
thence, both day and night halfe naked.
            These mil-dewes could not chuse but
breed her an infinite world of hony,Her new wealth and
true it is, that her baggs were so many,
and so m
                  •
               ssy, that she had scarce chests
enowe to containe them, this wealth
made her proud, and pride taught her to
be curious, she will not liue at so
low a rate as she hath done, but as shee
hath plenty of meanes, so she will have
plenty of attendants, and hereupon presently
shee contracts and hyres sundry
retayners; as first, a Surgeon that tooke
care of her Spittle, then a Tyre-woman
of Phantasticall Ornaments, a Sempster
for Ruffes, Cuffes, Smocks, and wastcoates,
and a Taylor for cloathes, of all
shapes, and all fashions, and these haue

confest their liuings only to come from
her Coffers.
            But this Sunne-shine must not bee
without some clouds,The cause of new vprore. for now the crue
of those Queanes whom she hath cast
off, and consumed, the accusations of
those whom she had robbed, and reuiled,
and the detestable enormities which
spring from such wicked examples,
come all with one voyce before the
throne of Iustice, appealing for satisfaction;
The plaint is receiued, approued
and pittied, and presently potentes
sent out for her apprehension, and the
razing downe of her Castell
            
            A corporall is forthwith chosen,She is besieged. and a
stoute band of Halberders and Bil-men,
               A Corporall in war is a Constable of peace.
sent to beleaguer this fortres; she stands
vpon her guard, hangs out a Hagge of
defiance, and bids them enter at their
peril; They which had a double Armor
a good cause, and lawful authority, scorning
to be out-braued, prepare for an assault,

she on the other side with her man
deuill, &amp; her she furies, stand to receiue
them, and to make her triumph more
glorious, she sets ope the gate, puts
downe the Bridge, and drawes vp her
Percullis, the enemy brauely enters,
and comming on in good order, they
were no sooner on the Bridge, and had
fil'd it from one end to the other, but by
a secret deuice which shee concealed,
downe fell the Bridge, and the Corporall
and his souldiers were halfe drowned
in the water; where, to see how they
lay plunged in mud and myre, how one
to helpe another, became worse and
worse incumbred, but aboue all, to
heare her scoffes, her Whores taunts, and
her dogs reuilings, and recount them,
would make a Tracte double this volume,
to tell the difficulty of their escape,
their tedious and durty passage to safety▪
what shame they felt in themselues, and
what mocks they receiued from others,

would be pleasant to fooles, but in wise
men it would stirre vp anger.
            The Corporall complaines of this defeate,The continuance of the Leaguer.
but yet still continues the Leaguer,
when presently a Prouost is sent with
new supplyes to assist him,A Prouost is called Prouost Marshall. but shee is as
carelesse of him, as of the other, drawes
him into as great daungers, and derides
him past sufferance, past measure, dayly
new forces come to their ayd, but all in
vaine, they dare not assault her, she is
held halfe immortall, and it is thought
of her enemies, (that were they surviuing)
she was able to encounter with
Bradamant, Marphysa, and Clardana; To
conclude, they dare no more assault her,
but with a continuall Leaguer, meane to
tyre her out, or famish her, how things
will proceed, is vncertaine, only it is supposed,
that if this Leaguer last not so long
as Troy, yet it will far exceed Ostende in
continuance, and so in this martiall businesse,
I must leaue her, concluding her

to be the most famous that euer the Sun
did looke vpon, in her most damned
profession, and that she may write Annales,
and Comentaries to teach Rome, Venice,
Florence, and the Turks Seralia; for vs
here in great Brittaine, we neither either
read, heard, or bred a creature of
her temper, our clime is too cold, our instructions
too seuere, and our punishments
too sharpe and piercing, let
Hollandia then liue stil in Eutopia,
and as it was worthy
to giue her breath so let
it write her Epitaph,
            FINIS.
            
               Nicholas Goodman.
            
         
      
   

