
   
      
         
            The legacye or embassate of the great emperour of Inde prester Iohn, vnto Emanuell kynge of Portyngale, in the yere of our lorde M. v.C.xiii. Of the fayth of the Indyans, ceremonyes, relygyons [&amp;]c. Of the patryarche [and] his offyce. Of the realme, state, power, maiesty, and order of the courte of prester Iohn
            Legatio magni Indorum Imperatoris Presbyteri Ioannis, ad Emanuelem Lusitaniae Regem. English.
            Góis, Damião de, 1502-1574.
         
         
            
               1533
            
         
         Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01828
            STC 11966
            ESTC S116675
            99851891
            99851891
            17184
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01828)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17184)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1687:03)
         
         
            
               
                  The legacye or embassate of the great emperour of Inde prester Iohn, vnto Emanuell kynge of Portyngale, in the yere of our lorde M. v.C.xiii. Of the fayth of the Indyans, ceremonyes, relygyons [&amp;]c. Of the patryarche [and] his offyce. Of the realme, state, power, maiesty, and order of the courte of prester Iohn
                  Legatio magni Indorum Imperatoris Presbyteri Ioannis, ad Emanuelem Lusitaniae Regem. English.
                  Góis, Damião de, 1502-1574.
                  More, John, fl. 1533.
               
               26 [i.e. 30] leaves   
               
                  Printed by w. Rastell in Fletestrete in saynte Brydys chyrch yarde,
                  [[London] :
                  1533]
               
               
                  A translation by John More of Góis, Damião de. Legatio magni Indorum Imperatoris Presbyteri Ioannis, ad Emanuelem Lusitaniae Regem.
                  Place of publication from STC; imprint from colophon.
                  Variant: D2 differs; on the verso section 42 begins: "The housbandes" or "Men marye there".
                  Some leaves misnumbered.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Manuel --  I, --  King of Portugal, 1469-1521 --  Early works to 1800.
               Voyages and travels --  Early works to 1800.
               Portugal --  History --  Manuel, 1495-1521 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ The legacye or embaſſate of the great emperour of Inde preſter Iohn̄, vnto Emanuell kynge of Portyngale, in the yere of our lorde M.v.C.xiii.
            Of the fayth of the Indyans, ceremonyes, relygyons &amp;c.
            Of the patryarche &amp; his offyce.
            Of the realme, ſtate, power, maieſty, and order of the courte of preſter Iohn̄.
         
         
            
            
            Iohn̄ More to the cryſten ſten reader.
            
               FOr as myche as euery mā naturally is deſyrous to here new thinges and ſtraunge (as both authours teſtyfye, and experyence proueth) all though there were none other commodyte therof then the neweltye: I thought yt a thynge worthe the labour, to tranſlate this lyttell worke, late happed in my hande through the helpe of a ſpecyall familyar frende of myne / ſyns ſurely I thought it ſhuld be a worke not onely new, trew, and pleſaunt to the reader, but alſo for ye knowlege of ſundrye thynges therin conteyned very profytable and neceſſary. For in this lytle treatyce be conteyned, the ſtate, the fayth, the relygyon, the ceremonyes, the Patryarche wyth his offyce, the powre, the lawes of the lande and empyre of preſtre Iohn̄, beſydes his royall maieſtie

and order of his courte. All whyche thynges were reherſed vnto ye myghty and puſaunt prynce Emanuell kynge of Portyngale, by the mouth of one Mathew, ſent frō themperour of Inde preſter Iohn̄, vnto the fornamed Emanuel, in the yere of our lord M.v. hundred .xiii. And all though of this preſter Iohn̄ ſyr Iohn̄ Maū
               defeld knyght, in a worke yt he made of the dyſcrypcyon of coūtrees, ſomwhat hath made mencyon: yet this embaſſatour that came from thens to the kynge of Portyngale, as he to whome euery thynge perteynyng eyther to the religyon and fayth of that people, or to the polytyque order of that lande, was myche more perfytely knowen, yt is no meruayle though he myche more perfytely deſcrybe theym, namely to that prynce, whych from poynte to poynte was curyouſe to enquyre. This empyre of preſter Iohn̄ ys reputed as great a maygne countre in a maner (yf yt be not gretter) as all the remanaunt that nowe remayneth chriſtened, except the new founden landes, that haue ben bycomen

chryſtened wythin few yeres of late. And therfore yt greatly may, &amp; of reaſon greatly ought to reioyce all good chryſtē people, to perceyue that though there are dyuerſe thynges wherein they and we dyffere in rytes lawes, cuſtomes, and ceremonyes: yet in all other thynges neceſſaryly perteynynge as well to the vertues of fayth and relygyon, as all other vertues morall, they ſo farreforth accorde and agre wyth theſe criſten nacyons of ours, and wyth the catholyque doctryne of the chyrche, that yt may well appere euen by that thynge alone, that the ſpyryte of god hath wrought and worketh this full agrement &amp; conſent, in ſo many thynges neceſſary to ſaluacyon, thorowe ſo many great countreys and regyōs as ours are and theyres both, ye tone by ſo longe ſpace hauynge ſo lytle acceſſe vnto the tother, that of many yeres tyl nowe very late, we coulde not wel tell whyther they were well criſtened or not. Howe be yt yet appereth well nowe by many thynges, not in this boke onely, but in thoſe letters

alſo, whyche now very late the emperour of that lande that nowe is, &amp; ſon vnto him that ſent thembaſſatour vnto the kynge Emanuell, dyd ſend not onely to the noble kynge of Portyngale that now is, ſonne vnto the ſaid noble kynge Emanuell, but alſo to the popes holyneſſe that now is Clement of that name the .vii. by his embaſſatour, wyth his obedyence after the maner of other chryſten prynces: by this treatyce and thoſe letters yt doth I ſaye well appere, that the ſaid emperour and all the chyrche, that ys to wytte all the chryſten people of that empyre, be of the ſame fayth that we be. And in this treatyſe ye alſo ſe, that ye great thynges whych haue ben byfore this tymes eſtablyſhed agaynſt heretyques by generall counſayles of olde, agaynſt whych old determynacyons theſe new heretyques make newe beſyneſſe nowe, the ſelfe ſame thynges haue the chryſten people of that great chryſten empyre frō the tyme of theyre fyrſte cōuerſyon, whych was forthwyth vpon the deth of Chryſte, cōtynually byleued and

euer obſerued ſtyll. So yt this poynt is able alone yf yt be pondered as yt is worthy, eyther to tourne and conuert or putte to ſylence for ſhame, all the beſye bretherne that wolde make men ſo madde, as to wene that thoſe thynges were new deuyſed and late brought vppe here by preſtes / whych thynges theym ſelfe ſe well ynough (though they dyſſymyle and ſay nay) in the bokes of old holy ſayntes, and whych thynges are now well knowē to haue ben this .xv. hundred yere byleued and vſed thorough that great empyre as great a people as oures, into whyche our preſtes as farre as men can tell of, neuer came henſe to teache them. But ſyth that we begyn nowe eache to heare more of other, I pray god as there is in bothe many thynges very good, and ſome thynges that myght be better: eche peple may lerne &amp; take of other thoſe thynges that be good, and lette the badde go by. And that we may make bothe ſo but one chyrche mylytant here in erth, that we may both be partes of one gloryouſe chyrche, that euer ſhall be tryumphaunt in heuen.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Damyane Gooes a Portyngale, vnto the ryght reuerent father in god lord Iohn̄ ye great Goth, archbyſſhop of wpſalen̄ inhabytyng the countrey of Swetia ſendes gretynge.
            
               THrough the great famylyar frenſhyp (god therof the vndouted autor) that was betwene your holynes &amp; me whē we were to gether at Dantiſke, what tyme I had there maters of my pryncis to do, after often metynges, at the laſt happened vs cōmunycacyon of ye maters of Portīgale, as of ye viages of the Indyans, Arrabies, and Perſes. And alſo of the longe and dyffyculte paſſage into thoſe coūtreys, of the parelles of the mayne Occean ſee alſo, and of the cōtynuall warre that the inhabytours as well on thys

ſyde Gaūge as beyond, made agayn ye Arrabyans, Perſyās, &amp; Indyans, of the yerely inuaſion of the Turkes, whych by theyr mighty naueyes ſent by the ſee of Arrabye vnto Inde the leſſe, all though not venqueſhyd, yet greatly vexed and troblyd our peple. But after we had mych debated this mater, your holynes putte wel in mynde of the high emperour of Inde preſter Iohn̄. From whome ſurely my ſelf ones ſaw an embaſſatour ſent vnto our kynge, and beynge preſent by, harde all that euer he tolde, as well of the fayth, as of the ceremonies and eſtate of preſter Iohn̄s empyre, whyche he parcell mele deſcrybed in the preſens of many of his nobles. All whych when in order I had ſhewed your holynes you requyred me, yf euer yt chaūced me to returne to the lowe countres, that I wolde ſende you all thoſe thynges breuely deſcrybed, wyth the artycles of the fayth, ceremonies, and eſtate of theyr countrey. whyche I faythfully promyſed to do. Therfore, after ones (though a thouſande daungers eſcaped)

I was come ſaufe to the lowe countreys, callynge to mynde your moſte holy company (whych I neuer forget nor neuer ſhall) and therwyth all my promyſe, all thoſe thynges as was your requeſt dylygently haue I done, whyche now here I ſende you. I ſende you chyefely the copye of the letter whyche the hygh and myghtye prynce themperour of Inde preſter Iohn̄, writ on a ſeaſon vnto my mayſtert he kyng of Portyngale / &amp; after that, all the artycles, as the religyon, ceremonies, themperours power, the noblenes of his court, euen in as compendyous maner as the ſame legate deſcrybed them.
            More ouer then this (to thentent the trouth of the mater more playnly may appere) I ſhall ſhewe you bryefly, howe preſently I both harde and ſaw all thoſe thynges.
            In the yere of our lorde a thouſande, fyue hundred, and .xiii. there landed &amp; arryued in Portyngale, an embaſſatour of the high emperour of Inde preſter Iohn̄, and of quene Ellynes his mother, ſent vnto the moſt

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
chryſtened prynce Emanuell kyng of Portingale. Thembaſſatours name was Mathew, an Armenicane born̄, wyth whome was ioyned in commyſſyon a nother noble yonge man an Abeſſyne, brought vp in thēperours preſter Iohn̄s courte, and his name was Iames. Theſe were very well welcomed of ye kynge, in whoſe court they abode and remayned .iii. yeres to gether, &amp; had there in great reputacyon, foūde onely at the kynges coſte and charge / tyll afterward they toke theyr leue, and ſo merely retourned ſaufe home agayn to theyr countrey. This Mathew then, all ſuche thynges as he had in cōmaundemēt, commyſſyon, and charge, ones declared to ye kynges hyghnes, &amp; lykewyſe the letters of his emperours delyueryd: the kynge wythin few days after cauſed thē to be ſent for / &amp; ſo there in the company of certayn well lerned men, and preſence of his nobles, demaunded by an interpretour, of the fayth, ceremonyes, and eſtate of thēpyre of Inde.
            Now thē at this time was I .xii. yere

olde, and one of thoſe chyldrene that are wonte to brynge in the kynges ſeruyce vnto the kynges table. Two yere after I hadde done the kynges grace ſeruyce in that offyce, I was by at all this as other of the court were, and both harde ſaw and vnderſtode all, as myche at leſte ways as my yonge and tender age wolde gyue me leue.
            But here you maye obiecte and ſay, howe couldeſt thow beyng ſo yonge (as then thou waſt) other wryte or remember all thoſe thynges, ſo that thow ſholdeſt thereby be able ſo long tyme after, in euery poynt ſo perfytely to deſcribe yt. I anſwere, I cōfeſſe my yough wold not ſuffer me to do it But after I hadde ſpent full .x. yere in that offyce, the moſte chryſtened prynce kynge Emanuell my brynger vppe, gaue me a new offyce. He ſent me hether to the lowe coūtres on his buſynes. whether as ſone as I was come, I founde a companyon a very noble quycke yonge man, both of the ſame order &amp; offyce I was on, whoſe name was Roderyke Fardynande,

whyche now was there for maters of his prynce (and ſuche a one in theyre vulgare tonge is called a factour) He beyng before ſent as an embaſſatour from the kyng Emanuell vnto Maximiliane themperour, and Alberte the duke of Bauarye, had receyued letters frō Antony Carnere ye kyng Emanuelles ſecretary, in whyche letters theſe artycles whyche ones he hadde wryten before the kyng hadde incluſyd and ſent. Now after I was fully acquaynted wyth thys Roderyke Ferdynāde, &amp; eche had ſhewed a nother others beſineſſe I happened to ſpeke of his legacy into Germany, chaūſed vs alſo to fall in cōmunycacyon of Inde. After which he ſhewed me he hadde receyued from Antony Carner, both thartycles fore remembred, and alſo the copy of the letter yt was ſent vnto the kynge, from the hygh emꝑour of Inde preſter Iohn̄. whych as ſoone as I had hard, incontynent I deſyred he wold let me haue a ſyght of them. He was content. I toke theym, and as well as I could, haue tranſlated them out of the Portyngale

tonge into latyne. To you I dedycate them, to you I ſende them. In which if ye eſpye any Barbarous ſpeche perdon me, as a courtyer and vnlerned, and with great beſynes very myche let and troubled. But how ſo euer they be wryten, trew they be. Al whyche we requyre your holynes to take in good worthe. But nowe heare you, what that hygh and myghty emperour preſter Iohn̄ wrote vnto our kynge, here I ſaye this letter vnto our kyng not fayned, but very trew &amp;, word for word almoſte, tranſlate oute of the Caldeane language (which ſpeche they moſt vſe) into the Portyngale tonge, and ſo agayn out of that into latyne.
            
               
                  The letter of the hygh emperoure of Inde Preſter Iohn̄ vnto the moſte myghtye prynce Emanuell kynge of Portyngale.
                  
                     IN the name of the father the ſonne and ye holy goſt, thre perſons and one god, helth, grace, and the bleſſynge of our lorde and redemer

Ieſu Chryſte ye ſonne of Mary the vyrgyn, borne in the houſe of Bethleem, be wyth our welbeloued brother, the moſte chryſtened kynge Emanuell, lorde of the ſees, the ſubdewrr of the fers and myſbeleuyng Moers. Our lord god proſper you, and ſende you thouer hande of your enymyes, and dylate &amp; enlarge your kyngdomes and realmes through ye deuout prayers of the meſſengers of Ieſu Chryſte our redemer, that is to ſay of the foure euangelyſtes, ſaynte Iohn̄, ſaynt Luke, ſaynt Marke, &amp; ſaynt Mathew, whoſe holynes, and prayers preſerue you.
                  we certyfye you our interely welbeloued brother, that here vnto our coū
                     trey be cōe out of ye hygh noble court of yours, two meſſengers, of whych two one is named Iohn̄ and calleth hym ſelfe a preſt, and thother Gomer who of vs haue deſyred vytayle and ſoudiers. wherfore vnto you we ſend our embaſſatour Mathew wyth the leue of ye patriarch Marce, whych geueth vs his bleſſyng, &amp; ſendes preſtes to Hieruſalem, whych is our father,

and of all thoſe that be vnder our domyon, the pyller of Criſtes fayth and the holy trynyte. He by our cōmaundement hath ſent vnto your great capytayne of them, that in Inde fyght for the fayth of our ſauyoure Ieſu Cryſte, to ſhewe hym that we ſhall be always redy when nede requyreth to ſende them both vitayle ſuſtynaunce and ſoudyours. Therfore the fame goeth that ye prynce of Cayry prepareth many a nauy agaynſte your armyes to be reuenged of the iniurys &amp; damages, that they haue ſuſteyned by the capytayns of your warre that ye haue in Inde. whyche (as yt is informed vs) they haue often ſufferyd, wherin I pray god of his gret goodnes dayly proſper you, that ſo in concluſyon all infydeles may vtterly be ſubdewed. we therfore agaynſt theyr aſſaute ſhall ſende ſoudyours, whiche ſhall abyde and tarye at the ſee of Mecha, that is to wit at Bebalmamdes, or to be ſent (yf you ſo thynke beſte) vnto the hauen of Iuda, or Thor, that ſo at the laſte you maye rydde oute of the way &amp; deſtroye ſuch

myſcreant Moers, ſo that the gyftes and oblacyons, that be offered vppe at the holy ſepulcre frome that tyme forward be not deuoured of dogges.
                  Now is come the tyme that was ꝓmyſed in whych (as they ſay) Cryſt &amp; his bleſſed mother Mary forſhewed, that in the later dayes of the Cryſten countreys in Europe, a certayne kynge ſholde arryſe, whych ſholde deſtroy the hole nacyon of the Babaryanes and Moers. And ſurely this is the ſame ſelfe ſeaſon whych our ſauyour Chryſte promyſed to hys bleſſed mother Mary ſhulde come. Furthermore what ſo euer our embaſſatour Mathew ſhall ſhewe you, accompte you yt, as ſpoken of myne owne mouth &amp; byleue him. For he is one of the chyefe of our courte, and for that cauſe we wylled to ſende hym to you. we wolde haue commytted all this, to your owne meſſengers you ſent hether, had yt not ben that we feryd leſt our beſynes ſholde not come to paſſe accordynge to our mynde.
                  we ſende vnto you by this our embaſſatour Mathew a croſſe, made of

the ſame ſelfe wood, on whych our ſauyour Ieſu Cryſte was crucyfyed at Hieruſalē. A pyece of this holy wood was brought vnto vs from Hieruſalem, of whyche we haue made .ii. croſſes, wherof the one ſtyll remayneth wyth vs, &amp; thother we ſende by our embaſſatour vnto you. The colour of the wood is black, and hangeth at a lyttell ſyluer rynge. Moreouer yf it pleaſe you eyther to mary your doughters with our ſons, or your ſons wyth our doughters, yt ſhall be very pleſaunt and profytable for both partes, and a great ſtablyſhement of the brotherly lege all redy enterd, whych I pray god longe to cōtinew. No more at this tyme but the helthe and grace of our redemer Ieſu Cryſt and of his bleſſed mother our ladye ſaynt Mary the vyrgyn, holde theyr hande ouer you, your ſonnes, your doughters, and all your hole houſholde. Amen.
                  Beſydes all this we certyfye you yf we lyſt to aſſemble our power that we haue ſtrength ynough to deſtroye (yf god be our helpe) all the enymyes

of our holy fayth. But as for our realmes and countres ſo be annexed and ioyned to gether, that on no parte we can breke out to the ſee. wherfore we haue no power on ye water, wherin (god be thanked) you of all nacyons are moſt myghty.
                  Ieſu Cryſte be your ayde, helpe, &amp; ſuccour, for the thynges that ye haue done in Inde / be ſurely more by goddes myght then mannis. If ſo be it you wold prepare &amp; ſet out a thouſande ſayle to ſe, we ſhall fynde vytayle, and all other thynges, plentyfully, neceſſarye for the furnyſhynge of your nauey.
               
            
            After that the moſte chryſtyned kynge emanuell by the interpretour had well vnderſtanden theſe letters, very deſyrous to heare of Criſten maters, gredy to knowe agayne, of the legate, how the maters and Cryſtes fayth ſtode amongeſt the Indyans / after certayne dayes, callynge to gether the nobles of his court, commaū
               ded that by certayne well lerned chryſten deuyns, whyche was there redy at hande, he ſhold be demaunded in

hys preſens, of euery poynt. And he anſwerynge by parcell mele declared all thynges, as hereafter in order foloweth.
            
               The confeſſyon of the fayth, ceremonyes, and manner of theyr relygyon, of the empyre of preſter Iohn̄.
               
                  IN this poynt, fyrſt of all, they beleue as we do, thre perſons and one god, in whyche one and moſte beſte father thei faithfulli truſt and byleue.
               2 Item that he of no ſubiecte mater at all, nor of nothynge erthly, but by a meruaylous meanes made both heuen and erth, &amp; lyke wyſe all thynges conteyned in them.
               3 Alſo that Ieſu Cryſte, that anoynted kynge, oure ſauyoure, the verye Meſſyas ſo often by prophetes promyſed, is the very ſonne of very god borne in Bethleem the cytty of Dauid (accordynge to ye prophecyes)

of Mary, whyche contynued a vyrgyne, both byfore the byrth and alſo euer after.
               4 Moreouer that the ſame Ieſu Cryſte for our ſynne at Hieruſalem byfore Pontius Pylate a Romayne there preſydent and gouernour of Iury, by an vniuſte iugement, both was condempned, ſuffered, died, and was buryed.
               5 Furthermore he incontenent after his deth deſcended to hell, &amp; theyr gates ſhaken and all to broken, the thyrde daye arroſe from deth to lyfe hauynge the vyctory of his enymyes and deth, and that after he retourned agayne, and meruaylouſly aſcended vp to heuen frō whens he came.
               6 Byſydes this, they faythfully cō
                  feſſe that after all this mortall lyfe, they loke for an vnyuerſall and endeles reſurreccyon of our body.
               7 Alſo that by the ſame fayth they loke for Cryſte to be iudge, who ſhall geue an vnyuerſall iudgement of good and euyll, in whyche eche man ſhall receyue a iuſte rewarde, accordynge to his deſerte in this worlde.
               
                  8 By whych iudgemēt geuē ones, good men ſhal haue eternall ioy with out ende, and euyll men euerlaſtyng payne vexacyon and ſhame.
               9 Therfore they as well as we, ſolemnely obſerue and dyligently kepe the .x. preceptes of Moyſes.
               10 Alſo they rekē as we do the .vii. dedely ſynnes.
               11 They haue alſo all ye bokes writen of Moyſes, &amp; fynally all the prophetes, wyth all ſuch other volumes of the olde lawe.
               12 The four euāgeliſtes haue they in great eſtymacyon, euen the ſelfe ſame that we haue, that is to wytte, ſaynt Mathew, ſaynt Marke, ſaynt Luke, and ſaynt Iohn̄.
               13 Of Poules epyſtles they lacke nothynge, whyche eche by name he there in preſence recyted.
               14 The crede made by thapoſtles and euery artycle of the ſame they well allowe.
               15 The pater noſter made by Criſt they ſo mych ſet by, that they preferre yt byfore all other prayers.
               16 The Aue Maria alſo they mich

vſe, in the honoure of the mother of god the virgyn our lady ſaynt Mary
               17 Theyr chyldrē the .vii. day after theyr byrth, both be baptyſed, and alſo after Moyſes law cyrcumcyſed. And that not for any reſpecte of meryte or truſt they haue in it, but onely for yt yt ſo hath remayned of an olde cuſtome frō theyr forefathers, and ſo to them left from hande to hande.
               18 All the people in the remēbraūce of the trewe and theyr ones receyued baptyme, yerely in feſte of the epyphanye wyth a meruaylouſe great gladnes and reioyſynge of mynde, openly a freſhe profeſſe the fayth of Cryſte, and be ſolempnely baptyſed agayne.
               19 In the remembraunce of our lordes maundy, euyn in maner as we vſe, they ſaye maſſe, but that not for any rewarde money or lucre, vnleſſe that percaſe ſome of a good relygyouſe mynde frely wythoute axynge geue theyr almoyſe.
               20 The bleſſed ſacrament of thauter they recounte for the hygheſt ſacrament, fyrmely wyth a ſyncer and

pure fayth, profeſſyng it to be the vndouted bodye and blood of our lorde Ieſu Chryſte / and accordynge vnto Chryſtes ordynaunce, receyuynge yt vnder both the formes.
               21 As for the ſacramentes of anoylynge and vnxyon, they confeſſe.
               22 Strayte ways as ſoone as they haue cōmitted any dedely ſynne, they get them a preſte to whome in ſecrete they confeſſe theyr fautes.
               23 They receyue payne for theyre treſpas (whyche in theyre vulgare tonge they call penaunce) lymyted at the dyſcrecyon of the confeſſour, whyche the party cōfeſſed fulfylleth with all dylygence.
               24 On faſtynge dayes (as often as they come) they abſteyne both from fleſhe and fyſhe, wythoute the receyuynge of collocyons or refeccyon.
               25 In ſtede of the lenton faſte, they faſte the ſeptuageſime. And that (as we may gathere of the tyme) bygynneth wyth our lent.
               26 As for ſondayes and other holy dayes, appoynted by theyr byſhoppes, in the remembraunce of god and

our lady and other ſaintes, they kepe wyth al reuerence.
               27 In the later weke of theyr lent, they vſe the memoryall of Cryſtes paſſyon euen as we do.
               28 They kepe ye palme ſondaye yerely euen aboute the ſame ſelfe tyme that we do, and as we do.
               29 And they vſe to burne tapers as we do, &amp; at the ſame tyme that we do.
               30 The go on comon proceſſyons, as the tyme or neceſſyte requyreth.
               31 Ones in ye yere they vſe to haue a ſolemne dyryge for all chryſten ſoules.
               32 They vſe to take aſhes, both in the maner we do, and alſo about the tyme that we do.
               33 There is there an infynyte nomber of monaſteryes, as well of womē as of men, lyuynge very ſtraytely in great abſtynence.
               34 Amongeſte theſe monaſteryes ſome there be, wherof eche hath in yt eyther vii. hundred viii. hundred or a thouſand monkes.
               35 In that realme is there a certayne montayne, that hath inhabytynge

here and there vppon yt .xii. thouſande monkes.
               36 All thoſe mōkꝭ as many as they be, get theyr lyuynge by theyr handy labour, nor in no wyſe may go to axe almoyſe houſe by houſe, in ſtretes, vyllage, countres, or townes. All maner of beggynge is vtterly forbydden them, vnleſſe that ſome of a good godly mynde gyue theym any thyng frely, then may they receyue yt, not as begged, but as frely gyuen.
               37 Here and there be preachers, whych preche to the people the fayth of Cryſte, and thoſe be preſtes or mō
                  kes, and that of the beſte lerned.
               38 Euery where be many hoſpytalles, wherunto all pore folke be gētylly welcomed and receyued.
               39 Theyr holy houſes, that is to wytte the temples of ſayntes, yf any malefactour fle thyther for ayde and helpe, yt ſhall ſuccour hym and ſerue hym. But this herein prouyded yet, that yf any happen to come thyther for murderynge of theyr neyghbour, they gyue hym ſo ſmall a porcyon to eate, that at the laſte he is compelled

to dye for hunger.
               40 If one dy, they make myche a do at his buryeng, euen as it is wyth vs, wyth prayers, croſſes, preſtes, &amp; ſuch other kynde of ceremonyes, and burye hym in the chyrche.
               41 Such as haue ben holy, &amp; men of good conuerſacyon in theyr lyfe, after they haue bene longe tyme dede and buryed, they make dylygēt ſerch of theyr vertuous lyuynge. whyche done, they recounte hym a ſaynt, that is to ſay (as the greke worde is) canonyſe hym.
               42 The houſbandes ſolempnely wyth a great company come to the chyrche doers, and mary onely but by wordes that they ſpeke of the preſent tyme.
               43 Of an olde cuſtome they haue, men may not mary any of theyr kyndred wythin the .vii. degree / wythin whych, no not theyr hygh patryarche in any wyſe eyther may or wyll preſume to dyſpenſe.
               44 In theyr chyrches and temples they haue and worſhyppe the ymages of god, oure bleſſed lady ſaynte

Mary the vyrgyn, wyth other holy ſayntes.
               45 They haue in theyr temples holy water, whyche they beleue good and effectuall agaynſt euyll and wycked ſpyrytes.
               46 Very many coſtly temples and belles they haue.
               47 The garmētes wherin they ſay maſſe in, vſe to be conſecrate.
               48 Chyefly they honoure the feaſte of ſaynt Iohn̄ Baptyſte.
               49 They begynne the yere at September.
               50 The pope of Rome they knowlege / but the cauſe why they do not theyr obedyence to hym (as other cryſten people do) is the euyll dyffycult waye.
               51 Saynt Bartholmew thapoſtel of Chryſt, preached fyrſte the goſpell and Chryſtes fayth vnto them.
            
            
               Of theyr patryarche, and of his offyce.
               
                  
                  THey haue but one chyefe preſte or byſſhoppe which they call a patryarche, that is to ſaye the chyefe of the faders. He only hath power on ſpyrytuall maters, that is to ſaye as well in eccleſiaſtycall offyces as dyſpenſynge wyth benefyces, wythoute the interrupcyon of any tēporall perſon / &amp; he lyueth contynually vnmaryed.
               2 This patryarche hath very gret poſſeſſyons / for the thryde parte of preſter Iohn̄s reueneus commeth to his parte, and that beſydes all the tythes of the hole realme.
               3 All the profytes hereof ys beſtowed onely vppon pore folke, the maryage of fatherleſſe chyldren, and pryſoners.
               4 when the patryarche dyeth, the emperour preſter Iohn̄ is the heyre of al his goodes. His ſucceſſour hath no maner a thynge left hym, beſydes the dignyte of ye patryarches chayre, and the cure of al his fold of ſhepe cō
                  mytted

to his charge.
               5 This patryarche is called the patryarche of Alexādry / and for this cauſe. For that where of olde there were onely foure through out al cryſtendome, of whyche Inde chanſed to haue the patryarche of Alexandry.
               6 This patriarche of an old vſage was wonte to be choſen at Hieruſalē onely, and that by the voyces of all good relygyous men of thempyre of preſter Iohn̄ that there were at the ſame ſeaſon dwellynge.
               7 This patryarche extendeth hys curſe or excōmunycacyon vpon ſuch as are obſtynate and rebellyous perſons / whyche in ſo farforth is dreded and feryd, that who ſo euer ſtande ſo accurſed dare not touch neither meat nor drynke tyll tyme he knowe hym ſelfe aſſoyled. For yf ſo be yt there be any ſo obſtynate a perſone that he careth not for the curſe, but that not wythſtandynge he leueth not from the cryme for whych he ſo was accurſed: his meate and drynke ſhall be taken from hym, and he ſo compelled to dye for famyne.
               
                  8 This patryarche ſhall not let or forbydde the people from the ſacramentes of the chyrche, for no maner of offence but onely for murder.
               9 The preſtes haue wyues / but when one is dede, they may not mary another.
               10 Baſtardes ſhall neuer be admitted to be preſtes.
               11 Neuer ſhall there be any admytted to the order of preſthed, but that before he ſhal be examined, by a well lerned company, whether he be mete for yt or no. If he be not mete, he ys reiected wyth ſhame ynough.
               12 The emperour him ſelf. Preſter Iohn̄, hath no maner powre on the clergy. For that is a thynge bylongeth onely to the patryarche.
               13 If any ſpyrytuall man committeth any abomynable cryme, hym the patryarche after his own dyſcrecyon ſuffereth to eate but certayne vnces of meate, &amp; ſo lyttel and lytell to dye for famyne. But none of them euen out of hande putteth he to deth, but onely murderers.
               14 That ſame patryarche geueth

playne and full remyſſyon and abſolucyon of ſynnes.
               15 Twelue hath he of his coūſayl, wyth whome he ordereth and gouerneth al ſpyrytuall maters.
            
            
               Of the realme and eſtate of themperour preſter Iohn̄.
               
                  AFter al this beyng further demaūded of the emperours realme and domynyon, he anſwered in this maner.
               1 Fyrſte he hath in his realmes very many cyties and townes.
               2 His nobles weare garmentes of ſylke, cloth of golde, veluet, ſatyn, damaſke, wyth ſuch other precyouſe thynges.
               3 The comen people were nothing but cloth.
               4 Dyuers kyndes of marchaundyſe hath he in his realmes, &amp; thoſe very precyouſe.
               5 He hath great plenty of mynys

of gold, ſyluer, and other metall.
               6 Money hath he none, but that is brought out of realmes nexte borderynge there about. They take golde &amp; ſyluer by weyght in ſtede of coyne.
               7 Great plenty of corne haue they, and that of dyuerſe colours, bothe blacke, whyte, redde, and gray. But as for theyr meale of all of thē is very whyte. Benys, peſyn, tarys, and all ſuche other codware, haue they ynough both plente &amp; alſo of diuers kyndes.
               8 There groweth great abundaūs of ſuger.
               9 Oxen, ſhepe, horſe, mulys, camelles, gotes, hogges, wyth ſuche other houſholde cattell beſydes byrdes they haue great plentye.
               10 Porke eate they none / not for ye that eyther theyr conſcyens or relygyon that forbyddeth, but bycauſe they fynd it not holſome for theyr bodyes.
               11 Themperours eſtate and powre is very great, for he hath vnder his domynyon thre ſkore chryſtened kynges. whych be kinges of great myghty kyngdomes. whoſe names the legate

there ſhewed openly.
               12 Beſydes theſe thre ſkore kynges, yet hath he .v. other Machomet kynges vnder hym.
               13 Moreouer he hath vnder his dominion meruaylous many gret men, as prynces, dukes, marquyſes, erles, barons, lordes of very great landes and reueneus.
               14 They obſerue &amp; ſtraytely kepe what ſo euer themperour commaundeth them.
               15 The Cronycles and noble actes of theyr prynces they kepe ſaufe, and what ſo euer is worthy remembraūce theyr ſecretary dylygently regeſters.
               16 The rytes, lawes, ſtatutes, and comen ordinaunces made for the peoples gouernaunce, they ſaufely kepe in wrytynge.
               17 Themperour hath euer .xii. men preſent wyth hym of his counſayll, whome he may comen wyth of all the maters of his realme.
               18 Through al the realmes and domynyons of his empyre, there be iudges appoynted, whych ſerue (accordynge to the trewth of ye mater) both

to heare cauſes and iudge them.
               19 No iudge maye iudge any man to deth but onely for murder.
               20 The emperour hath very great trybutes.
               21 The emperour hath as well of ye inhabytours as of other marchaunt ſtraungers, the .x. parte of theyr gaynes / theyr ſtocke ſaued hole.
               22 There be ſouldyours of a certayne relygyon, whyche euer go in whyte, wyth croſſes on theyr cote armour / alwaye redy for to warre for Cryſtes fayth, yf nede be.
               23 Of the inherytaūce of theyr fathers, one hath as mych as a nother, no reſpecte hadde to the age, whyther they be older or yonger.
               24 In all thoſe realmes &amp; prouynces, there be no Iewes, all though yt is well knowen that ones there were many. But when the people coulde not ſuffer or bere theyr naughtynes, ſodenly they ſet vppon them and vtterly deſtroyed them.
               25 Many fayres and ryche markettes haue they by reaſon of ye marchaū
                  tes that reſorte thyther.
               
                  26 The realmes, prouynces, and countres of preſter Iohn̄, ſtretcheth to both the partes of Nilus floode.
               27 The people knowe none nother but Erithreā, yt is to ſay the redde ſee.
            
            
               Of the order of the ſame empyre, and maner of the courte.
               1 THe emperours proper name is Dauid. His cōmon name preſter Iohn̄, kynge of the Ebeſſyns.
               2 His tytles be in this maner. Dauid kynge of kynges, kynge of the Ebeſſins, preſter Iohn̄, kynge of kynges vnto the Ebeſſyns and of all his prouynces, both nexte and alſo at the ende of the ſees. The kynge of Nilus flood, and iudge of ye gret Sodane, &amp; of the countrey of Cayre, and the ſee of Alexandrine. By the power of god and our redemer Ieſu Chryſte, &amp; by the powre of our ladye the vyrgyne ſaynt Mary.
               3 This emperour of an old cuſtome maryeth euer the kynges doughters that be vnder his domynyon.
               
                  4 The eldeſt ſonne euer ſuccedeth his father in his kyngdome.
               5 This ſonne of his is veryly well nuryſhed and brought vppe wythin his fathers courte / as for his other ſonnes (at leſt ways yf he haue any) be brought vppe lyke noble men, eyther vnder the kynges, or ellys ſome great prynces of the emperours domynyon.
               6 The inherytaunce of his empyre neuere deſcendeth to the doughters. But yf themperour happe to dye wythout iſſew male, then cōmeth yt to the nexte of his blood.
               7 Themperours wyues be had in great honoure and kepe a gret port.
               8 Themperour hath euer redy at hande a meruaylous great number, as well of horſemen as fotemen.
               9 The emperoure to thentent he wolde exercyſe his ſouldyours, in actes of warre, is euer for the moſte parte in the felde amongeſt theym. where they applye them ſelfe to fetys of armes.
               10 In the emperours courte the chamberlayn hath the chyefeſt rome.
               
                  11 Themperour hath for ſauegard of the body, euer at hande .xii. of the nobleſt of his realme. Eche of whome haue vnder hym .xii. thouſand fyghtynge men.
               12 Thoſe ſame .xii. noble men occupyes ye greteſt romes in the court.
               13 They kepe very dylygently in writyng pedygrees, names, &amp; ſurnames of theyr anſetours, wherby euery one may perfytely knowe his nacyon and ſtok.
               14 Themperours ſonnes &amp; doughthers be maryed vnto the ſonnes or doughters of other kynges vnder hym wyth great dowers geuen wyth them in maryage. And then all ye people come, and of theyr owne mocyon geue them gyftes.
               15 Themperoure what tyme neceſſyte ſo requyreth vſeth thobedyence and ſeruyce of his ſubiectes.
               16 The men chylderne of the kynges, that be vnder hym, be (to wynne theyre fathers good wylles) brought vppe in themperours courte.
               17 He admytteth and ſuffereth chalenges amonges his ſubiectes.
               
                  18 The name of the emperours preſter Iohn̄s mother yt nowe is, is Ellen, a very holy woman, and one that ſheweth a great example of chaſtyte, to whome for here eſpecial goodnes, and the nonage of her ſonne, is commytted all the hole order and rule of the realme.
               19 Of kynges, emperours, or the chryſten prynces of Europe, they neuer had knowledge but onely of the frenchmē whom they cal in theyr vulgare tonge Criſtyans. But by ye reaſon of certayne noble actes that were done few yeres paſſed by the Portyngales, agaynſt the Turkes, Perſys, Arabyens, and Indyās, the name of the kynge of Portyngale begonne to be well knowen and had in myche reuerēce &amp; reputacyon amongeſt them.
            
            
               
                  HEre haue you now ryght reuerēt father ye thynges I promyſed your holynes (at my beynge wyth you) of the legacy

of Inde. But yet to thentent you may geue the more credēce to the mater, I ſhall put ſomwhat to, that a very noble yonge man, and one of my famylyar acqueyntaūce, named George Lupe Dandrade (what time we were to gether about our prynces beſynes in the lowe countreys, and alſo hoſted both twayn in one houſe at Antwerpe) told me. On this wyſe was his tale.
               In the tyme of his beyng at Inde for certayne maters he had there of his prynce (where he remayned by the ſpace of certayne yeres) one a very valyant man Lupus Soarez, by the kynges commaūdement was the chyefe capitayne of the Portyngales warres, &amp; chyefe ruler of all the realmes, cyttes, townes, and caſtelles, that be vnder the kynge of Portyngales domynyon, euen frō Ethiope, thorough out the Chynas. Thys Lupe had prepared hym a meruaylouſe gret nauey, to ſayle as his aūcetours were wont to do from Cochine (now is Cochyne ye caſtel &amp; dwellyng place of the Portyngale captayns) &amp;

ſo intended to come to the ſee of Araby commenly called the redde ſee, agaynſte the Turke / whyche Turke nowe in ſtede of the Soldayne occupies the coūtrey. when he was arryued in a certayne Ile, called of the inhabytours Camara, that lyeth in that coſte / incontynēt he cauſed two ſhippes to be made redy, and toke vn to hym a certayne choſen Portyngales bothe famylyar and faythfull, amonges whome this George was one. This done he commaūded they ſholde caſte ouer to a nother Ile called Mazua, to the entent that when he were there ones, he wolde ſend out thre eſpyes vnto the great emperour of preſter Iohn̄, vnder the pretext of marchaūdyſe, &amp; that for two cauſes. One to be certyfyed of the legacye wherof Mathew before ſhewed vnto our kynge, and to knowe whether thoſe thynges were trew or falſe. Secondely that they very narrowly ſholde ſerche, what portes and what hauens were vnder the dominyon of Peſter Iohn̄. Of theſe .iii. ſpyes one was well lerned and very expert in

ſcrypture whoſe name was Iuſarte Viegas, a Baccaren borne. After they were ones ſaufe come home agayne bothe man &amp; ſhyppes to theyr capytayne, and had made an ende of theyr vyage / they ſhewed hym all, both that they hadde ſene there, and alſo harde of the inhabytours of that countrey / and further declared that they knewe for a ſuerty that the legacy of Mathew was trewe / and that the ſame Mathewe they ſayde was ſuche a one as we had ſene hym with our owne eyen ones embaſſatour before our kynge. The cauſe and maner of the legacye they ſay was ſych.
               After that Ellyn the mother of Dauid preſter Iohn̄, that then was a very wyſe and a dyſcrete gouernour of all his hole realme (for he was but a chylde) had lerned of certayne Portyngales whyche were come to her court, &amp; ſpecyally of one called Iohn̄ Clerke, all that euer we hadde done at Inde agaynſte the infydeles, ſhe ſendeth that Mathew in a ſecrete legacy vnto the moſt chriſtyned prynce Emanuell, the fyrſte of that name,

kynge of Portyngale / wyth whome ſhe ſendeth alſo a nother yonge man an Ebyſſyne borne an noble man, Iames by his name, of whome byfore in the deſcrypcyon of the legacy, we haue made mencyon. To theym ſhe gaue here letters of commendacyon dyrected to the hed ruler of that prouynce, vnder the domynyon of preſter Iohn̄, whoſe powre ſtretcheth to Mazua and the ſee of Araby, to pray hym to helpe them as ſecretely as he coulde with all ſuch thynges as they ſhold nede, makyng as though they were marchaūt men which came thether for marchaundyſe. This ruler (and who ſo euer happeneth to be in that offyce) is called in the Ebeſſyne tonge Baruagays. This Mathewe and his companyon the Ebyſſyne; through the letters of commendacy. on they had, were louīgly welcomed, where as they made mery a certayne ſpace, neuer tellynge no man theyre purpoſe, neyther what he wolde do there, or where when he thens departed he wolde become. But (to the entent

he myght brynge his purpoſe to paſſe wyth leſſe parell) fayned hym ſelfe a lether byer, and in the meane ſeaſon now and then bought certayn preſents whych pryuyly he ſent vnto quene Ellyn. And vnder this cloke, peruſed dyuers prouynces, menyng this, that eſcapynge ſaufe wythout hurte, through enmyes of the Portingales, at laſt myght come to Portyngale yt ſelfe, and ſo there do the thynges he come for. For other way then this was there not. Alwaye whether ſo euer he went or where ſo euer he became, he toke with hym this yonge man his felowe the Ebyſſyne, leuynge all his hole houſholde at Arquyke, whyche is a cytty nere the ſee coſte, appertaynyng to preſter Iohn̄, dyſtant about a myle from the yle of Mazua. wherin that Baruagais before named then abode. For it is euer the abydynge place of that offycer.
               But nowe yf percaſe any capcyous felowe wolde obiecte why of ſo many noble men, as there is no dout but there be in ſo great a court as preſter Iohn̄s is, there were not ſent in

that embaſſate, ſome oldermen, men of more grauyte, of greater experyēce and byſydes this Ebyſſyns borne, whyche myght haue borne a greater porte and maieſte before our prynce rather then theſe, of whome the one was farre frome the nobilyte ether of an Ebyſſyne or Indyane eyther, bycauſe beyng an Armenycane / and the other all though he was an Ebyſſyne and in ye kynges court brought vppe, yet but a yonge man, an wythoute the company waytyng on hym yt becometh a prynces embaſſatour to haue / and therby ſheweth not the dygnyte of a legate. But hereof may there be two cauſes alledged.
               The fyrſte, in all thoſe regyons (as great as they be) from the ſee of Araby, to the water of Gange, there be but two languages, that is to wit, Perſyke and Arabyke. whyche languages who ſo perfytely knoweth, may eaſely paſſe thorough all thoſe prouynces. Nowe in Preſter Iohn̄s courte be there very fewe or none nobles, Ebyſſyns borne, that can ſkyll of thoſe tonges. Fyrſte bycauſe they

haue lyttell cōpany or acquayntaūce wyth the out borderars. Secondely for that yt ſeldome cauſeth theym to go out of theyr owne countrey, as beynge contente wyth theyre countrey lawes. And for yt cauſe the ſame Mathew, ſkylled in both the tonges and in all the prouynces there about, for he hadde ofte ben in them / and ſeyng that at that tyme, all though he were an Armenyane, yet he was of the quenys counſayll, and very great about her, he was thoughte the metyſt for that meſſage / namely ſyns he hadde one ioyned wyth hym an Ebyſſyne borne, whyche both knewe the tonges and maners of many nacyons / ſo that yf nede ſhold requyre, he were mete to be ſent on a lyke embaſſat.
               The ſeconde cauſe is. The actes of warre of the Portyngales done wyth the Indyans, agaynſt the Turkes or Perſyes at that tyme was not ſo well knowen of the Ebyſſyns, that they thought it nedefull to vēter any old noble Ebyſſyne, &amp; ſpecyally ſyns they were vnexperte in ye tonges, in ſo farre and ſo dyffyculte a vyage, tyll

tyme they were farther certyfyed by ſome other. And therfore pleaſed to ſende that Mathew, an Armenycane borne, as moſte meate for that beſynes whyche not greatly accōpanyed, but as a marchaunt ſholde go and eſpye al to gether. And that it ſo was ment, the mater ſelfe ſhewed. For after ones all was exactely tryed by hym, there was then a nother embaſſatour ſent, both an old man, a noble man, an Ebiſſyne borne, and a preſte, connyng both in ſcrypture and Calday / on whome wayted a very great company of nobles of the Ebyſſyns, of themperours p̄ſter Iohn̄s courte. And this mā was ſent vnto the moſt myghty prīce one Iohn̄, ye thyrd king of Portyngale. For Emanuel that was his father departed almoſt .x. yeres ago. This legate wyth all his cō
                  pany at this preſent day is wyth our kynge, myche made on, and hadde in great reuerence. whome queſtyonleſſe they wold neuer haue ſent, hadde they not ben afore ſurely certyfyed of our maters by Mathew. But now we be a littell degreſſed therfore

let vs agayn returne to our purpoſe. This Mathew then vnder the pretexte of fayned marchaundyſe, after his beynge at many other cytyes, reſorted to Aden / whych is a cytye by ye ſee of Arabye vnder the Turkes domynyon, byelded euen as our cytyes be, very ryche, and very well fenſyd wyth fortreſſes. where after he hadde fallē in ſome familiare acqueyntaūce wyth certayne marchaunt men, and hadde ſerched all thynge to the vtter moſte, and fynyſhed the maters he came for, makynge hym ſelfe euer amōgeſt ye Turkes a Turke, for other wyſe coulde he neuer haue eſcaped &amp; done his beſyneſſe ſaufe without daū
                  ger, he returned to Arquique where before he had left his houſhold wyth his companyon the Ebyſſyne, &amp; thus he remoued, toke his houſhold again and ſo retourned to Aden, hopynge that from thens he myght ſayle wyth his warys and his houſholde to India. For why at the towne of Aden they are wonte to take ſhippynge towarde India. where when he was landed he ſold al his lether &amp; bought

other marchandyſe of Alexandrye to cary wyth hym to Indy, by whych he muſte nedes paſſe into Portyngale.
               Now was a ſhyppe redy goynge to Inde, and he redy wyth all his marchandyſe to go wyth that ſhyppe, whyle there ſpronge a certayne ſuſpycyon amonges the cetezyns of Aden, that he ſholde be a ſpye. wheruppon he was taryed and let that he coulde not take paſſage at that ſeaſon. But he as one of a great wyt and experyence, ſo clerely purged hym ſelfe of that ſuſpycyon, prouynge in dede he was a marchaūt man, and that there he ſoughte nothynge but marchaundyſe, that they gaue hym wyth hys houſholde free paſporte, to departe whether hym pleaſed. But now then beynge dyſmyſſed / he founde neuer a veſſel goynge toward Inde. Then he was fayn to hyer one, &amp; ſo he with all his company toke ſhyppyng, and came towarde Inde, to a certayn noble ryche cytye called Xaer. whych is dyſtant from Aden about a hundred myle, where lykewyſe he founde no ſhyppes goynge to Inde, bycauſe yt
                  
nowe yt was wynter, whyche there begynneth in Marche. And whyle yt laſteth no man may ſaile toward Inde, for the great ſtormes of wynde (whyche is a meruaylous thynge) yt contynually blows contrary oute of one quarter. But when the ſees ſerued hym, he ſayled from the cytye of Xaer vnto a towne called Fartaque, there in euery place faynynge hym ſelfe a marchaunt of Turkey. From whens he wente to a place called the inhabitours of Dabul / &amp; from thens to departe to the town of Goa. where thē wyntered the gret Alfonſus Dalbubarque a Portyngale, the chyefe capytayne of all India, predeceſſour vnto Lupus Soarez, whom we haue made mencyon of byfore, whych was he ye ſubdewed al that ſame Inde, Araby, Perſe, Malach, and the hole ſee of Ganges, and made all them ſubiectes to Portyngale. Dabull is dyſtant from Fartaque, whych is in the coſt of Inde .iiii. hundred myle, from Goa .xl. frō Dio .iii. ſcore great myle. Dio is a very ryche cytye, vnder the domynyon of Cambaie very well fenſed,

wyth gonnes and ſuche other ingens of warre, and very well walled.
               Furthermore he taried at Dabul from May to Decēber, and there occupied hym ſelfe about marchaūdyſe becauſe in all that tyme he could not take ſhyppynge. At laſte he gate hym a ſmale veſſell, and beganne to gete hym away. And by ye reaſon he ſhewed certayn of his frendes &amp; the mayſter of the ſhyppe that he wolde go vnto Portyngale wyth his marchaundyſe, by and by yt was ſhewed to certayne hed offycers of the towne, that there was a ſtraunger one vnknowē, whyche pryuyly wolde conuey hym ſelfe to Portyngale. wheruppon wottynge neuer what they ſhuld thynke of the mater, they kept him ſtyll with fayre wordes, and ſo let hym of hys paſſage for ye ſeaſon. After he ſaw this incontynēt by certayn marchaūt men whych were wonte to be cōuerſant in Inde with the Portyngales, whyche he before hadde made hys frendes, he wrote ſecretely vnto the capytayne Alfonſus Dalbuberque, certifyeng hym as diligētly as he could

how it ſtode with him. He as ſoone as he knew it ſent thither certain ſhyppꝭ and galleys ſome great ſome ſmale vnto hym. Silueſter Corzo was ye capitayn of them, where whē he was arryued, ſtrayt way he ſhewed the offycers of the town that he was ſent vnto them from ye great duke Alfonſus Dulbuberque to ſeke a certayn marchaunt man whyche he muſte nedes ſpeke wyth all, &amp; that the ſame Mathew was he whom he ſought / which knowen they gaue hym leue to ſpeke wyth hym and ſo delyuered hym into his handes. For this cauſe the Dabulenſes vſed this liberalyte towarde hī, for fere they ſhold ſeme our opē enimyes, for as mych as they take mych profyte by our Portyngales whyche vſe Goa &amp; Inde, &amp; yet in place &amp; time whē the may, ſecretly do vs diſpleaſe. This Mathew then cōuayde frō the citie of Dabull, cam with this noble yong man ye Ebyſſyne his felow, &amp; al his famyly, at ye laſt to Goa, where as we before recyted, ye noble capytayne Alfonſus then wintered wyth a gret number bothe of people &amp; nobles of

the Portyngales. There is bothe an ile &amp; alſo a citie of this name of Goa. The citye I ſay as it is very riche, ſo is yt alſo very habūdaūt of all thyng that ſeruyth for the fyndyng of men. In that dwelleth marchaunt men of all kyndes, Indians, Arabyes, Perſyās, wyth diuers of the realmes of Narſynga &amp; Cambaia. In thys yle be .iiii. great &amp; very well fenſed fortreſys, well māned wyth many hyered ſouldyers of the Portyngales. There inhabiteth the city, about .xv. hundred Portyngales. Theſe be cytezyns there, wyth theyr wyues, chyldren, and ſeruauntes, beſydes many other, as ſoudiours, &amp; marchauntes. Both that hole Ile the cytye &amp; the caſteles, be vnder the Portyngales. In the cytye be grāmer ſcoles kept, wher in is taught in comyn ſcoles both the latyne and the Portyngale tonge. wherby the inhabytours of thoſe partes, be as well ſkylled in both thoſe lāguages, as in the lāguage of theyr natyue coūtre, where they were brede and brought vp. The fayth of Cryſte is euery where receyued amongeſt

them. Many ſumptuous and coſtely temples &amp; houſes of relygyō be there as well of other as of ſaynt Fraūces order, where dayly is vſed diuine ſeruyce. Ouer ye hygheſt parte of a gate in the cytye, whyche they call ſaynte Mary da ſera, be kept &amp; had in great veneracyon &amp; honour, the bones of that capytayne Alfonſus Dalbuberque. But nowe after yt Mathew had arriued, from the town of Dabull in the hauen of Goa, the Capitayne Alfonſus cōmaunded hym to come vnto him. He denyed &amp; ſayd he wold not come out of the ſhyppes, alledgynge yt he was not the legate of any meane prince but of ye hygh mighty emꝑour of Inde Preſter Iohn̄ / &amp; hereūto added that it were not cōuenyēt nor metely that thembaſſatour of ſo hygh a myghty chryſtened emperour, ſhold be receyued to ſo noble a duke as Alfonſus is wythout dewe reuerence &amp; honour. Thē Alfonſus callyng to gether his clerkes, preſtes, &amp; all his nobilite yt were nigh at hand, goth forth (namely ſyns he was ye embaſſatour of thēperour Preſter Iohn̄s) to mete

hym wyth croſſes, and ſuch other ornamentes of the chyrche, the preſtes and clerkes ſyngynge this hymne: Te deum laudamus, within a fewe dayes after Alfonſus began to aſke hym of his legacy, to whome he anſwered, yt he was ſent from preſter Iohn̄ vnto the moſt Cryſtened prynce Emanuel kynge of Portīgale, &amp; that he ought onely to open the cauſe of hys embaſſate to no creature but vnto hym alone. whych when he hard the duke Alfonſus axed hym no further queſtyons. wythin a whyle after when he ſaw his time, this Mathew &amp; this noble yonge mā ye Ebyſſyne, with al his company makyng haſt toward Portyngale, Alfonſus very gentylly accōpanied him vnto ye hauen, where takyng ſhyppyng frō Goa they cam toward Portīgale. All this ſhewed vn me this George Lupe Dandrade, that he knewe of a ſuerty for trewth, for as myche (as we haue ſhewed you before) the great rular of Inde Lupꝰ Soarez had ſent him from the Ile of Camara, as a ſpye amonge the Ebyſſynes vnder the pretexte of marchaū
                  dyſe,

to ſerche out the trewth of that legacye. when he &amp; that noble yonge man the Ebyſſyne, wyth all his famyly came to Portyngale, my ſelfe (as I haue ſhewed your holynes byfore) was by, whome I both ſaw and ſpoke often wyth all. He was a man of mean ſtature, very whitly viſaged and ſomwhat ſallowe, wyth a ſyde &amp; hore here, wyth a longe whyte berde. whych a lyttell more at lēgth I haue ſhewed your holynes, to thentēt you with all other yt be deſyrous to know the very trewth ſhall not thynke yt be a lye or fayned.
            
            
               Of the people of Pilapes.
               
                  I Very well remembre me ryght reuerēt father howe you ſhewed me at my laſte beynge wyth you, that vnder your archbyſhopryke, was ye ſame wyld regyō of Scythyce other wiſe calleth Pilape where they neyther knowe god or Chryſte, nor aw haue they none amonges theym

for theym to lyue by. Surely a very myſerable caſe, &amp; a thynge nothynge chryſtenlike conſydered of your men. For yt was tolde me bothe of good men &amp; vertuous men alſo (and that for a ſuerty to) that your nobles (the more ſhame for theym) were in faute why thoſe people were no better then brute beſtes, nor came to chryſtendome. For ſo they fere they ſhall leſe a great parte of theyre pollynge and pyllynge and theyr accuſtomed rauenous roberye, thorough the whyche they pytyfully oppreſſe with inſacyable auaryce thoſe ſylly pore innocent people. And therfore I deſyred you then (&amp; yet agayne in Chryſtes name do) and that not I alone, but alſo as many as thynke as I do, that ſyns yt is your offyce (as beynge theyre herdman, and they cōmytted to you by god) you wold cauſe thoſe nobles of yours, to leue theyr couetous crueltye, and ſo in concluſyon to brynge thoſe ſymple ſoules to the knowlege of Cryſte, and ſo payenge theyr dew trybutes to theyr kynges, as other cryſten people do to theyre prynces.

Let thoſe nobles of yours take hede therfore what they do, that they compell not ſo great a folde of ſhepe in tyme to come, in the preſence of that iuſte iudge Ieſu Cryſte, to axe iudgement of that tyranny of theyrs. I deſyre your holynes to do that lyeth in you, whyche doyenge, ſe what glory and what rewarde you ſhall obtayne of god, what prays and laude byſydes of the worlde. No more to your holynes but thus fare you well. I ſuppoſe that I ſhalbe ſhortly at Portyngale with the kynges hyghnes or elles at Germany. But where ſo euer I become I ſhall be holly yours. I pray you I may be hertly recomēded vnto your brother Olaus the great Goth, a very ſpecyall frende and louer of myne.
            
            
               At Antwerpe out of the comyn houſes of our realme of Portyngale, in the Calendas of December, the yere of our god M.D.xxxi.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶Prynted by W. Raſtell in Fleteſtrete in ſaynte Brydys chyrch yarde. 1533 Cum priuilegio.
            
         
      
   

