
   
      
         
            Encouragements. For such as shall have intention to bee vnder-takers in the new plantation of Cape Briton, now New Galloway in America, by mee Lochinvar·
            Gordon, Robert, Sir, d. 1627?
         
         
            
               1625
            
         
         Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01932
            STC 12069
            ESTC S105760
            99841486
            99841486
            6072
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01932)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6072)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1101:09)
         
         
            
               
                  Encouragements. For such as shall have intention to bee vnder-takers in the new plantation of Cape Briton, now New Galloway in America, by mee Lochinvar·
                  Gordon, Robert, Sir, d. 1627?
               
               [36] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Wreittoun,
                  Edinburgh :
                  Anno Dom. 1625.
               
               
                  Lochinvar = Sir Robert Gordon.
                  Signatures: [A]²  B-E⁴.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Running title reads: Encouragements for New Galloway.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Cape Breton Island (N.S.) --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-05
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-08
            Simon CharlesSampled and proofread
         
            2005-08
            Simon CharlesText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ENCOVRAGEMENTS. For ſuch as shall have intention to bee Vnder-takers in the new plantation of CAPE BRITON, now New Galloway in AMERICA, BY MEE LOCHINVAR.
            
            Non nobis nati 
                  〈◊〉
                aliquid parentes, aliquid Patria, aliquid cognati poſtulant.
            
               DREAD GOD 1625
            
            EDINBVRGH, Printed by Iohn Wreittoun. Anno Dom. 1625.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL. SIR WILLIAM ALEXANDER of Menſtrie Knight. Maſter of Requeſtes for Scotland, and Lievetenant Generall to his Majeſtie in the Kingdome of NEW SCOTLAND.
            
            AND TO THE REMNANT THE NOBLEMEN, AND KNIGHTS BAROnets in Scotland
               ▪ Vnder-takers in the plantations of New Scotland in AMERICA.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE ADVENTVRERS, FAVOVrers, and well-willers of the enterpriſe for the inhabiting, and planting in Cape Briton, now New Galloway in America.
            
               
                  GEntle Reader,
            
            It hath beene the policie vniverſall, from the creation of the World vnto this time, of all civile States, the repleniſhing of the World with Colonies of their owne ſubjects. Adam and Eva did firſt beginne this pleaſant worke to plant the Earth to ſucceeding poſteritie. Noah, and his familie began againe the ſecond plantation. And the confuſion of tongues at Babel, made diviſion of States, ſcattering as manie Colonies over the face of the Earth after the Flood, as there was diverſitie of Languages: and their ſeede as it ſtill increaſed, hath ſtill planted new Countries, one after another; and ſo the Worlde to that eſtate whereinto it is.
            That the planting of Countries, and civilizing barbar
                  ••
               s and inhumane Nations, hath ever beene the worke of the greateſt Princes of the Earth, their ever-living actions hath teſtified; wherewith are filled both the records of divine Trueth, and the monuments of humane ſtate; and whoſe heroicke actions (wee

muſt not thinke) hath beene vndertaken vpon triviall motives, when as by that they did aſwell inlarge the limites of their Dominions, and enriche the revenues of their eſtates; as bridle ſedition at home, and ſettle ſecuritie againſt their enemies abroad.
            Theſe preceeding praiſe-worthie Fathers, and their memorable of spring were diligent to plant, that yet vnplanted to their after-livers; wherein ſhined thoſe worthie Founders of the great Monarchies and their virtues: the Hebrues, the Lacedomonians, Gothes, Graecians, Romanes, and the reſt from time to time in their ſeverall ages.
            But to leaue theſe remote times, let vs take a view within theſe 60. yeeres of the diſcoveries, and plantations in America, by the Engliſh, the French, the Spainard, the Portugale; by whoſe induſtrious paines are made knowne vnto vs alreadie their, ſo hudge tracts, kingdomes, and territories, peopled and vnpeopled, as vpon the hither ſide for the ſpace of 
                  •
               000. leagues at the leaſt, and for 3000. more on the backe ſide in the South Sea.
            Manie diſcourſes of the diſcoueries which hath beene there effected within theſe few yeeres are made of worthie Perſonages: ſuch as Columbus, Cortez, Pitzora, Soto, Magellanes, and manie others, who to the wonder of all ages hath ſucceſſivelie ſeconded one another in thoſe partes.
            Whole Decads are filled with diſcoveries there, and volumes with their actions of plantation: There wee ſee the renowned Drake, and memorable Candiſch twiſe about the round circumference of the whole Earth. Virginia to perpetrat the memorie of her honourable Knight Sr Walter Ralegh, Amadas, Arthur, Whyte, Grenuile, and Lane her firſt diſcoverers, and worthie Governours in her plantations. Sr Iohn Haukins in his Guinea. Iohn de Verrazano a Florentine, Iohn Rinault, Rene Landoniere, Dominique Gourgues in their Florida. The noble Cortez, and the other Spainards, and Portugalls in their golden Mynes of the 15. Provinces of new Mexico, Nueua Gallicia, Nueua Hiſpanna, Nueua Biſcaia, Cibola, Quivira, and to the Gulfe of California on the back ſide of America. The famous

               Cabot, Frobiſher, Davis, whoſe memories ſhall never die in the North-weſt parts: and many innumerable 
                  〈◊〉
                Worthies, whom all after-ages ſhall eternize for their vertues, whoſe actions I leave to bee ſearched as they are regiſtred in the monuments of their praiſe-worthie proceedings.
            The ſhining brightneſſe of theſe (Gentle Reader) and ſuch others, hath ſo beamed a path way to all poſteritie for imitation; as that the baſeſt minde that is, may bee induced to follow their footsteppes. And for my ſelfe, hauing from the ſource of that ever and over-flowing fountaine, that was ſtill a running to all, from our late Soveraigne of never-dying memorie King IAMES obtained a Patent of Cape Briton, which now, by his Royall direction is intituled New Galloway in America: I haue reſolved to follow the troden way of theſe others, whoſe happie ſucceſſe are ſo plainlie ſeene in ſuch honorable deſignes.
            And ſince I doe propone to my ſelfe the ſame ends, which are firſt for the glorie of my great and mightie GOD; next the ſervice of his 
                  〈◊〉
                my dread Soveraigne, and my native Countrie: and laſt the particular weale, and vtilitie of my ſelfe, and ſuch as ſhall bee generouſlie dispoſed adventurers with mee: Why ſhall it bee lawfull for others, and not for mee: and not as poſſible and as commodious for mee, as vnto others of my qualitie?
            The chiefe (then) and the fartheſt poynt that my intention ſhall ſeeke to arrive at; ſhall bee to remove that vnbeliefe, which is ſo grounded in the mindes of men, to diſcredite moſt noble and profitable endevoures with diſtruſt: and firſt, to ſhake off their colourable pretences of ignorance, and then, if they will not be perſwaded to make their ſelfe-willes inexcuſable; I ſhall make manifeſt the worthineſſe of the cauſe to the mindes of ſuch as are deſirous to bee ſettled in a certaintie. As for my ſelfe, I doe giue truſt to the relations of ſuch, whoſe wiſdomes (I know) are not ſo ſhallow, as eaſilie bee deceiued of others; nor conſciences ſo wretched, as by pretences to deceive others: and having the perſonall tryall of ſo honourable and ſufficient reporters, our owne Countrie-men, this naked contemplation, and idle knowledge can

not content mee: but knowing that the chiefe commendation of vertue conſiſteth in action, I haue reſolved a practiſe, and to trace the footſteppes of thoſe heroicke fore-runners, whoſe honourable actions ſhall ever live vpon Earth; whiles their Soules live in glorie in the Heavens, and ſhall increaſe heere, and multiplie; as their bodies in the grave ſhall putrifie.
            The inducements which hath incouraged mee to this enterpriſe, and to spend my time, and beſt abilities in theſe adventures, I ſhall heere ſette brieflie downe without any inlargment of made wordes, but in ſingle ſpeach, as beſt beſeeming a ſimple meaning; Intreating thee (Courteous Reader) that thou would with an affectioned mind conſider theſe my ſubſequent motives, wherewith I haue beene induced my ſelfe: ponder aright my endes: and then but weigh my willing and free Offers, which I doe make for the weale and furtherance of ſo worthie a Worke. Wee are not borne to our ſelves; but to help each others, and our abilities and meanes are not much vnlike at the first houre of our birth, and the last minute of our death: and it is our deades good or bad that all of vs haue to carrie vs to Heaven or Hell after this life. While wee are therefore heere, let vs imitate the vertues, and glories of our Predeceſſours, that heereafter worthilie wee may bee remembred as their Succeſſours,
            FARE-WELL.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE MOTIVES, which hath induced mee, and may happilie encourage ſuch as haue intention to bee Vnder-takers with Mee in the plantation of New GALLOWAY in AMERICA.
            
               MOTIVE I.
               
                  
                     motive 1
                  AS the chiefe and primarie end of mans creation is the Worſhippe of GOD; ſo ſhall the firſt, and ſpeciall motive of my proceeding be the advancement of his Glorie, and that by the propagation of the Goſpell of IESVS CHRIST amongſt an Heathen people, where Chriſtianitie hath not beene knowne, nor the worſhippe of the true GOD. Where can bee ſelected a more excellent ſubject, than to caſt downe the Altars of Devills, and to raiſe vp the Altar of CHRIST: to forbidde the Sacrifice of men, that they may offer vp the Sacrifices of contrite Spirites.
               Is it not a determined Trueth, that the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt ſhould bee preached to all the Worlde (Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but GODS Worde ſhall not paſſe away). And is it not as certaine a Concluſion amongſt all the Divines, that theſe are the latter Dayes, wherein we live, well knowne by the ſignes that were to come before, ſette downe by God himſelfe in his ſacred Worde, and for the moſt part alreadie manifeſted? And hath not Gods

all-ſeeing Providence begunne as firſt by diſcoverie, and next by plantation of ſo hudge and ſo waſte a tract, more commonlie, than properlie called the New Worlde; vnknowne but within this 60. yeeres, except by a glimpſe, to make appeare the progreſſe of his divine Providence, how hee will haue the ſeede of his worke to bee ſowne amongſt them; Then doth it not belonge vnto vs to proſecute his worke; and as by merchandizing and trade wee buy at them the pearles of the Earth; wee ought to communicate vnto them the pearles of Heaven.
               The time hath never beene ſo apparent as now, vnder our moſt gratious and Soveraigne Lord, King CHARLES, whoſe generous and gratious goodwill by encouragement to the ſame, hath manifeſted the ſame ſince hee receaved the Crowne, to bee the ſelected inſtrument to atchieue it.
               Then ſhould not that Heroicke, and illuſtrious diſpoſition in Him, whom wee ſee ſo prompt to bee ſtill in action, both incite, and invite to ſo noble deſignes all ſuch as would ſhunne the imputation of idleneſſe to imitate His foot-ſteppes.
               Is it vnlawfull for vs to come to them? No; it is the duetie of Chriſtianitie in vs, to behold the imprinted footſteppes of GODS glorie in everie Region vnder Heaven; and to them, againſt the Law of Nations, to violate a peaceable Stranger, or to deny vs harbour.
               Is it vnlawfull for vs to trade with them? No, vnleſſe Salomon ſhould bee condemned of ſending for Golde to Ophir; Abraham for making a league with Abimelech, and all Chriſtendome for having commerce with Turkes, and miſcreants.
               Nor neither is it vnlawfull that wee poſſeſſe part of their Lands, and dwell with them, and defend our ſelves from them, becauſe there is no other moderate, and mixt courſe, to bring them to converſion, but by daylie converſation, where wee may ſee the Life, and learne the Languages

each of others: and becauſe there is towne ſufficient in the Land, (as Sichem ſaid) for them, and vs; the extent of an 100. myles beeing ſcarce peopled with 500 inhabitants: and chieflie becauſe (as Pharaoh gaue Goſhen, to Iſrael, ere Ephron ſold his caue to Abraham) they have ſolde to our people their Lands for copper (which they more eſteme of, than money) to inherite and inhabite:, as Paſpehay and Powhatan, two our there greateſt Kinges to theſe our Colonies in Virginia; and chieflie (as it is written by Captaine Iohn Smith, a worthie actour in the buſineſſe) when Captaine Newport was deſired by Powhatan at Worowacomaco, to come from Iames towne in Virginia, where hee was, as a place vnwholeſome, and to take poſſeſſion of another whole Kingdome, which hee gave vnto him.
               If any ſcrupulous conſcience will impute, that yet wee can poſſeſſe no further limites, than was alloted by compoſition, and that fortitude without juſtice, is but the firebrand of iniquitie. Let him know that Plato defineth it to bee no injuſtice, to take a ſword out of the hand of a madde man. And Saint Auguſtine hath allowed, for a lawfull offenſiue warre that revengeth injuries, and wherein the whole Divines in Europe, although contraverting farre in other things, yet in this they all agree, that it is lawfull. That the Church of Rome allowe it. The Spaniard, and Portugalles large and ample territories and kingdomes in the 15. Provinces of Mexico, Nueua Hiſpanna, Nueua Gallicia, &amp;c. beare witneſſe. And for the Church of England, their Bermudes, Virginian, and New England conqueſſe and colonies affirme it. And the Church of Geneva in the yeere 1555. determined in a Synode (where Calvin was preſident) to ſende Peter Rochier, and William Quadrigarius, vnder a French Captaine to Braſilia, althogh they were ſupplanted by the Cardinall of Loraine, and the treacherie of their falſe Captaine.
               
                  
When therefore it is ſo ſweete a ſmelling Sacrifice to propagate the name of Ieſus Chriſt: if wee haue any graine of faith or zeale in Religion, let vs ſeeke to convert theſe poore Savages to knowe Chriſt, and humanitie. Let Religion bee the firſt aime of our hopes, and other thinges ſhall bee caſt vnto vs. Our Names ſhall bee regiſtred to poſteritie with a glorious Title; Theſe are the men whom GOD hath raiſed to augment the ſtate of their Countrie, and to propagate the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt.
               
               The ſame GOD that hath ordained three Kingdomes vnder the Scepter of our gratious King CHARLES, will not bee wanting to adde a fourth, if wee would diſſolve that froſtie ycieneſſe which chilleth our zeale, and maketh vs cold in the action.
            
            
               MOTIVE II.
               
                  
                     motive 2 AND next to the Worſhippe of my GOD, is the ſervice of my Prince, and native Countrie: which is the ſecond end that I haue propounded vnto my ſelfe, by inlarging theſe Dominions whereof I am a Subject: a duetie moſte proper to all the true and loyall Lieges, whenſoever by ſo lawfull and eaſie meanes it may bee atchieved.
               What is ſo truelie ſutable with honour and honeſtie, as to gaine to our native Mother-Countrie a Kingdome to attend her? Wherein can the taſte of true vertue, and magnanimitie bee more ſweete and pleaſant, than in planting, and building a foundation for thy poſteritie; gotte from the rude earth by Gods bleſſing, and thine owne induſtrie, without prejudice to any? What more conducing

to that myſticall bodie politicke, whereof thou art a member, than for to finde imployment for thoſe that are idle, becauſe they knowe not what to doe? Poſteritie ſhall remember thee for it, and remembring, ever honour that remembrance with praiſe.
               Conſider what was the beginninges, and endinges of the Monarchies of the Chaldeans, the Perſians, the Graecians and the Romans, but this one rule: what was it they would not doe for the Common-wealth or there mother Citie? for example: Rome, what made her ſuch a Monarcheſſe, but only the adventures of her youthe, not in ryots at home, but in dangers abroad? and their juſtice, and judgment, out of their own experience when they grewe aged. What was their ruine and hurt, but this: their exceſſe of idleneſſe, want of experience, hypocriticall ſeeming goodneſſe, &amp; growing onlie formall Temporiſts; ſo that what their Predeceſſours gotte in many yeeres, they loſt in few dayes: theſe by their paines and laboures became Lordes of the Worlde, they by their eaſe and vyces became ſlaves to their ſervants.
               Then, who would live at home idle (or think in him ſelfe any worth to live) onlie to eate, drinke, and ſleepe, and ſo to die? or by conſuming that careleſlie, which their predeceſſours hath got worthilie? or by vſing that miſerablie, that maintained vertue honeſtlie? or, for beeing deſcended noblie, pyne with the vaine vaunt of Kinred in penurie? or (to maintaine a ſillie ſhow of braverie) toyle out the heart, ſoule, and time baſelie, by ſhiftes, trickes, cardes, or dyce? or by relating newes of others actions, ſharke heere or there for a Dinner or Supper? deceiving his friends by faire promiſes and diſſimulation, in borrowing where hee never intendeth to pay? offending the Lawes, ſurfeting with exceſſe, burthening his Countrie, abuſing himſelfe, deſpairing in want, and then couſening his kinred? although it is ſeene what honoures

the World hath yet, and what affluence of all things; for ſuch as will ſeeke, and worthilie deſerue them. Heere were courſes for Gentle-men, (and ſuch as would bee ſo reputed) more ſuting their qualities, than begging from their Princes generous diſpoſition the labours of his other ſubjects.
               It woulde bee a Hiſtorie of a large volume to recite the adventures of the Spaniards and Portugalles, their conſtant reſolutions, with ſuch incomparable honour, ſo farre beyond beliefe in their diſcoveries, and plantations, as may well condemne vs of too much imbecillitie, floth, and negligence. And yet the authours of theſe new inventions were helde as ridiculous at that time: as now are others that doe but ſeeke to imitate their vnparalelled vertues.
               And though wee ſee daylie their mountaines of wealth (ſprung from the plants of their generous indevoures) yet is our incredulitie, and vntowardneſſe ſuch, and ſo great, that either ignorantlie wee beleeve nothing; or ſo curiouſlie conteſt, to prevent wee know not what future events; that ſo wee either neglect, or oppreſſe, or diſcourage both our ſelves, and others, that might both as eaſilie and would as willinglie attempt and embrace the like.
               Who ſeeth not, what is the greateſt good of the Spaniard, but theſe newe concluſions, in ſearching theſe vnknowne partes of this vnknowne Worlde: by which meanes hee diveth even into the verie ſecreetes of all his Neighboures, and the moſt part of the Worlde.
               And when the Portugalles and Spaniards had found the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, how manie did condemne them-ſelves that did not accept of that honeſt offer of noble Columbus, who vpon the neglect of England, to whom it was firſt offered; brought them to it: perſwading them-ſelves the Worlde had no ſuch places, as they had found: and yet ever ſince wee finde, they ſtill haue found newe

Lands, newe Nations, new trades, and ſtill daylie doe finde; both in Aſia, Africa, Terra incognita, and America: ſo that their is neither Souldiour, nor Mechanicke from the Lord, to the begger, but theſe parts affoord them all employment, and diſcharge their native Soyle of ſo manie thouſands of all ſorts, that elſe by their ſloath, pryde and imperfections, woulde longe ere this haue troubled their neighboures, or haue eaten the pryde of Spaine it ſelfe.
               And ſeeing further, for all they have, they ceaſe not ſtill to ſearch for that, which yet they neither haue, nor knowe not 
                     •
                   it is ſtrange that wee ſhoulde bee ſo dull, as not maintaine that which wee haue, and purſue that, which wee knowe.
               I am ſure that manie would take it in an evill part to be abridged of the titles and honours of their predeceſſours: when if but truelie they would judge themſelves: looke howe inferiour they are to their noble vertues, ſo much they are vnworthie of their honours, and livings: which never were ordained for ſhowes and ſhadowes, to maintaine idleneſſe and ſloath, but to make them more able to abound in honour by heroicall deedes of action, judgement, pietie and vertue.
               What was it they would not doe both in purſe and perſon for the good of the Common-weale? and may not this bee a motive for vs to ſet out ſuch as may bee ſpared of our kindred in ſuch generous deſignes. Religion aboue all things ſhould move (eſpeciallie the Cleargie) if wee were religious, to ſhowe our faith by our workes, in converting theſe poore ſavages to the knowledge of GOD. Honour might move the Gentrie, valiant and induſtrious; the hope and aſſurance of wealth, all: if wee were ſuch, as wee would ſeeme, and deſire to bee accompted.
               Or bee wee ſo farre inferiour to other Nations, or our Spirites ſo farre dejected from our ancient Predeceſſoures

or our minds ſo vpon ſpoyle, pyracie, or other villanieas to ſerve the Portugale, Spaniard, Dutch, French, or Turk, (as to the great hurte of Europe too manie doe) rather than our GOD, our King, our Countrie, and our ſelves? excuſing our idleneſſe, and our baſe complaints by want of imployment? when heere is ſuch choyce of all ſortes, and for all degrees in this plantation.
               So let theſe anſwere ſuch queſtionleſſe queſtions, that keepe vs backe from imitating the worthineſſe of their brave ſpirits, that advanced themſelves from poore Souldiers, to great Captaines, their poſteritie to great Lords, their King to bee one of the greateſt Potentates on Earth, and the fruits of their labours, his greatest glorie, power, riches and renowne.
            
            
               MOTIVE III.
               
                  
                     motive 3 AND as I haue ſpoken of two principall cauſes that hath induced mee; The third of my ends may happilie bee no leſſe forcible to encourage all ſuch, whoſe education, ſpirits and judgments, wants but onlie the purſe to proſecute the ſame with mee, and that is the private and particulare gaine, that may bee got by ſo lawfull and eaſie meanes: whereof it is more than admirable, that ſuch ſhould either bee ſo wilfullie ignorant, or ſo negligently careleſſe as not to bee moved to imbrace, and ſpeciallie, ſuch imployment as may ſearch out commodities, to live happilie, plentifullie, and at eaſe.
               Ought not everie man to regard, aſwell to inlarge his patrimonie, as that hee bee not chargeable to others, ſo

farre as hee may by his vertue and induſtrie, in a lawfull and honeſt manner attaine vnto. Is not a lawfull ſearch for ſuch commodities, to bee preferred to an idle ſloathfulneſſe? and an honorable policie in a lawfull plantation abroad, before vnlawfull monopolies, and wrangling ſuites of Law, by neighbour againſt neighbour at home, impoveriſhing thy ſelfe, and thy native Countrie, whereof thou oughteſt to bee a more profitable member?
               May not the fortunate ſucceſſe of the plantation of Ireland, ſo freſh and recent to all, whence ſo great commodities are brought both to England, and Scotland, and whereby the Countrie it ſelfe is enriched, and wee ſo benefited, bee inticements to induce vs to the like. The verturous, and generous Spirites of reſolute Gentlemen, vnder-takers of this plantation, haue raiſed their fortunes worthie of honour; and by his Majeſties favour, their vertues rewarded with the titles of Earles, Vice-Countes Lords, Barronets, and Knights, according to their qualities, and his Majeſties pleaſure. The meaner ſort, ſuch as artiſanes, labourers of the ground, the greater part whereof, were knowne to haue ſcarce a competent meanes to defraye the charges of their paſſage thither, now promoted to bee Gentlemen, and of great meanes. And why may not time produce as great effects to vertue, in others who ſhall follow her pathes with reſolution: where as good occaſions are are offered, in a climate more temperate, a Soyle more fertile, and farre exceeding in greater commodities?
               And laſt, to ſhake off the difficulties, and impedimentes that may bee objected: as the dangerouſneſſe of Sea, the barienneſſe of the Soyle, and the vnwholeſomeneſſe of the climate; all which diſcouragements might aſtoniſhe ſome with feare, and to thinke our expenſſes, and paines vnprofitable; when as our endes ſhall bee vnpoſſible.

I haue therefore heere taken a view that you may generallie knowe and learne, what the Countrie is, and her commodities: the temperature of the climate: nature of the natives: and the eaſineſſe of the paſſage; all which I ſhall briefly runne over; only to remove from before your feete the ſtumbling blocks of impoſſibilitie that may affright vs.
               The Countrie it is called by the name of Cape Briton, now New Galloway: new, not in reſpect of the diſcoverie thereof, which to the judgment of men of knowledge and vnderſtanding is not new, but old; for the much hath been written thereof, yet new, not olde, becauſe of our new vndertaking of that plantation. It is ſituated betwixt the degrees of 45. and 57. an Yland within the Sea, but vpon the maine, ſevered by the diſtance of foure leagues in ſome parts, of two or three at other parts: and at others, leſſe.
               The Yland is in length ſome 120. myles, and in breadth 80. myles or thereby: ſtanding South-eaſt, and North-weſt to New Scotland; vvhere the great river Canada ingorgeth her ſelfe in the maine Ocean. Harbours there bee exceeding good on all ſides, in moſt part vvhereof are ancorage for ſhippes of all burthen. Yles there be about over-grovvn vvith good timber of diverſe ſorts of vvood; all as yet not diſcovered, except the Yle Sablon, vvhich is full of vvoodes and vvilde beaſtes, but vvithout any people. The Land is vvatered by foure maine rivers, full of Salmond, and diverſe other ſortes of fiſhes. It hath plentie of ſpringes of ſvveete vvaters. Tovvards the North-eaſt, Mountanous: and tovvard the South-weſt Caimpainge: promiſing as rich entralles as anie other Kingdome to whom the Sunne is no nearer neighbour. The ground in it ſelf ſo fertile and good as may equalize any of the Kingdomes that lyeth in the hight of 45. 46. 47. Onlie this advantage I find in nature, that they haue above this: they are bewtified by the long labour &amp; diligence of induſtrious people &amp; airt: &amp; this is only as God made it, when he created the world, vncultured, planted &amp; manured by men of induſtry, judgmēt &amp; experience.
               
                  
The commodities which we ſhal reape from thence ſhall be great, for the Sea ſhall ſweeten our labours with her benefites, as the Land, and the Land aſwell as the Sea. The Sea ſhall reach vs vp her Whale, her turbot, her ſturgion, cod, haddocke, ſmall ling, makkerell, herring, mullet, pearch, Ecle, crab, lobſter, muskle, wilk, oyſter, and infinite others. Fiſh is the maine Staple, from whence is to be extracted, a preſent commoditie to produce the reſt: which howſoever it may ſeeme meane and baſe, yet it is the Myne, and the Sea is the ſource of theſe ſilvered ſtreames of all theſe vertues, which hath made the Hollanders, the miracle of induſtrie, &amp; patterne of perfection for theſe affaires: and the benefite of fiſhing, is that Primum mobile, that turneth all their Spheare to this hight of plentie, ſtrength, honour, and admiration.
               The ground it will yeeld vs an admired varietie; ſome wee ſhall haue that are merchantable, which, by the ſerving for ordinarie neceſſars of the planters &amp; inhabitants, may yeeld a ſuperplus ſufficient, by way of traffick and exchange with other nations, to enriche our ſelves the provyders; ſuch as flaxe, hempe, which the Soyle doth yeeld of it ſelf not planted. For pitch, tarre, rozen and turpentine, there bee theſe kind of trees there, which yeeld them aboundantlie. Saſſafras, called by the natives, winauk, a kind of wood of ſweet ſmell, and of rare vertues in Phyſick. The Vine, it groweth there wild. Oyle there may be there of two ſortes: one of walnuts; and another of berries, like the ackornes, which the natives vſe. Furres of manie and diverſe kinds; ſuch as the matterne, the otter. the black foxe, the luzernes, Deere skins, bevers, wildcat, and manie others. Sweet gummes of diverſe kinds, and many other Apothecarie drugges. Dyes of diverſe ſortes: ſuch as ſhoemake, for blacke: the ſeede of an hearbe called vaſebur, and a litle ſmall roote called chappacor, for red: &amp; for blew, the her be woad, a thing of great vent and vſe at home for Dyers, and many other commodities merchantable, which by planting may bee raiſed.
               
               
                  〈2… pages missing〉
               
               and in our coaſtings at home wee are ſubject vnto.
               And now laſt, it reſteth I ſpeake a worde of the nature of the people, in ſo farre as you maye knowe, how litle they are to bee feared, in reſpect of troubling our inhabiting and planting.
               They are a people ſo fewe, ſo poore, ſo baſe, ſo incivile, and ſo ſavage, as wanting both multitude, power, or ai
                     •••
                   to harme vs. They are cloathed with looſe mantles, made of Deere skinnes, caſten rounde about their middles, the reſt of their bodie all naked, of ſuch ſtature onelie as wee are heere, having no edge tooles, nor weapons of yron, nor ſteele to offende vs, neither knowe they how to make anie, nor howe to vſe them.
               Theſe weapons which they have, are onelie Bowes made of Hazell, and arrowes of reedes: flat edged truncheons alſo of vvood, about a yarde long: neither haue they anie thing to defende themſelves, but targes made of barkes, and ſome armour made of ſtickes vvickered together vvith threed. In number they are verie fewe, in twentie myles, ſcarce threeſcore people. Townes in the countrie are verie rare, and ſmall: containing fewe inhabitants: and hee is a Viroan, or great Lord, that hath the government of one towne. There houſes are litle, made of ſmall poles, and faſt at the toppes in round forme, in moſte parte covered with barkes. If there ſhoulde fall out anie Warres betwixt vs and them, what fight coulde there bee, wee having advantages againſt them, ſo manie manner of wayes: it maye bee eaſilie imagined, by our diſcipline, our ſtrange weapons, eſpeciallie, our Ordinance great, and ſmall. And by the experience that others hath had of them there, in places more populous than this of ours: where the taking of them-ſelves to their heeles, was their beſt defence againſt them.
               
                  
So ſeeing you maye perceive, what the Countrie is, and how ſituated? the aire how temperate, and wholeſome? the Soyle how fertile, and what affluence it doeth yeelde of commoditie? the natives how both ſo fewe, and ſo harmeleſſe? and the paſſage, howe ſo eaſie, and ſo frequentlie experimented? I hope there remaineth no cauſe, whereby the action ſhould bee miſliked.
               Thus referring my relation to your favourable conſtructions: the ſucceſſe of the action to Him, who is to bee acknowledged the Author and Governour, not onlie of this, but of all thinges elſe: and theſe my ſubſequent Offers, which I have freelie, and willinglie granted, as helpes, and furtherances for your encouragement to ſo good a Worke; yee maye pervſe, and onelie imbrace as you ſhall thinke your ſelves diſpoſed.
            
         
         
            
            
               
                  DREAD GOD 1625
               
            
            
               
THE OFFERS to bee granted to the Adventurers in the new plantation of CAPE BRITON, now called by the name of New Galloway in AMERICA, BY LOCHINVAR.
            
            
               ARTICLE 1.
               For Miniſters.
               
                  THAT the bleſſing of GOD may accompanie vs in our indevoures; without whoſe gracious, and mercifull aſſiſtance, wee can not have happie, nor proſperous ſucceſſe in our affaires. For the Miniſters of the Worde of God; ſuch as ſhall bee the factours of CHRIST for the gaine of Soules: and to propagate his Trueth: and enlighten thoſe that are captivate in Ethnicke darkneſſe: and for the vſe, and exerciſe of true Religion amongeſt our ſelves; I doe willinglie, and freelie graunt and offer as followeth,
                     1. Their paſſage from Scotland vnto the ſaid Land of New Galloway ſhall bee free vnto them, without payment of any fraught, either for themſelves,

their wiues, and children, if they anie haue, and their neceſſare houſhold ſtuffe: which all ſhall bee tranſported thither vnto them, into mine owne Shippes, and vpon mine owne charges.
                     2. They ſhall haue their entertainment of mee, their wiues, and children as ſaide is, in their whole paſſage on the waye thither.
                     3. For their maintenance, and their foreſaids beeing there: I ſhall giue them entertainment for the ſpace of the firſt three yeeres, in during the infancie of our Church there: and howe ſoone it ſhall pleaſe GOD that our number bee increaſed, that our Companies maye bee divided in Paroches, that then a competent meanes ſhall be alloted vnto each Miniſter in his ſeverall charge, as ſhall bee found expedient for their places.
                     4. For their aſſiſtance in ſuch things as belongeth vnto them in their callings: I ſhall haue a ſpeciall care to ſee, that ſuch reverence, and reſpect be had vnto them, as appertaineth vnto their place and calling: and ſhall ſee ſuch goode order, as by them ſhall bee ſette downe for reformation of life, and manners, duelie obeyed and performed, by cauſing the tranſgreſſours, and contemners of the ſame bee ſeverelie puniſhed.
                  
               
            
            
               ARTICLE II.
               THAT everie one of ſuch as ſhall bee vndertakers, ſhall giue his oath of alledgeance: and ſhall all conforme themſelves in Religion, according to his Majeſties

Lawes, and manner profeſſed within the Kingdome of Scotland.
               
            
            
               ARTICLE III.
               For Gentlemen, and others vndertakers: what I ſhall bee obliged to performe vnto them.
               ITEM, for the helpes, and furtherances of ſo generous, and well-diſpoſed vndertakers as ſhall willinglie vnder-goe the hazard, and imbrace the enterpryſe: I ſhall performe the particulars in everie point vnto them, as followeth,
                     1. For their paſſages: everie vnder-taker ſhall bee tranſported, himſelfe, his wife, children, &amp; ſervants, his whole houſhold ſtuffe, and their proviſion of victualles for their intertainment, ſuch as meale, malt, beefe, &amp;c. and ſuch as they ſhall pleaſe to provide to ſuſtaine them for a whole yeere: Together with as much cornes, as they ſhall bee able to ſowe vpon their Lands, the firſt yeere: and that all, and together paſſage free, into mine Shippes, from Scotland vnto the ſaid countrie of New Galloway.
                     
                     2. Beeing thither by GODS mercifull aſſiſtance, and providence tranſported, to bee eſtabliſhed and placed in the Land: each man according to his qualitie, as followeth: The landed Gentleman vndertaker, ſhall haue his Landes granted vnto him in fee, and heritage to himſelfe, and his ſucceſſours for ever, to bee holden of mee, my heires, and ſucceſſoures in New Galloway, in

manner as they holde their Lands in Scotland of our Soveraigne Lord, the King his Majeſtie, either by feaw, wairde, or blanſh, and ſhall grant the ſame vnto them in quantitie, according to everie one of their qualities and meanes. And for tennants, and farmorers, their landes ſhall bee granted vnto them in Lace, everie one of them to have three Life-rents, and a nyneteene yeere Tacke thereafter, conforme to their power, and meanes, and performance of the conditions of the rent after mentioned.
                     3. And further more that their helpes, and furtherances maye haue a competent time to eſtabliſhe them-ſelves in their eſtates, and that their meanes may the better increaſe: each vndertaker of the plantation of New Galloway ſhall bee free from the payment of any duetie for his Landes, for all and whole the ſpace of the firſt three yeeres.
                     4. For their aſſurance of a ſecuritie, and peaceable quietneſſe in the poſſeſſion of their Landes in New Galloway, whereof they bee vndertakers: I ſhall finde ſufficient caution, and ſuretie vnto each one of them within the Shyre where hee dwelleth in Scotland, that whatſoever his goods or geare thither tranſported, and placed vpon the ground of the ſaids Landes, ſhall bee taken from him by violence, of the natives, or forraine Nations, that the double thereof ſhall bee payed and refounded againe vnto him in Scotland, or to his heires, executours, or aſſignayes.
                     
                        
5. And for artiſanes and crafteſ-men, ſuch as Taylors, Shoe-makers, Smyths, Wrights, Websters, Wakers, Millers, &amp;c. their paſſages ſhall bee made free vnto them without the payment of anie fraught; and likewiſe the rents of their lands ſhall bee free vnto them, induring their owne lifetimes: and for their ſucceſſours, they ſhall bee kept in the caſe, and eſtate of tenants and farmorers, and ſhall haue their Laces of their Lands granted vnto them, as is ſet downe in the Article for Tennants.
                  
               
            
            
               ARTICLE IIII.
               What the Vnder-takers ſhall performe vnto mee.
               FOR the whole duetie of my Landes, charges, and expenſſes to beſtowed by mee in my ſhipping and other proviſion: I ſhall bee contented to receive from everie one of the ſaid vndertakers, the thirteenth parte of that increaſe, and commoditie, which their Lands ſhall bee made worthie vnto them in the ſaid plantation: And that I ſhall not require to bee payed vnto mee in moneyes, but only in ſuch commodities, as the Soyle ſhall affoord: ſuch as cornes, fiſhes, furres, &amp;c.
            
            
               AND laſt, I deſire that all ſuch, as ſhall imbrace the foreſaids offers, may come vnto mee before the firſt day of December next, and giue vp their names, and a note of ſuch things as they deſire to bee carried with them, whereby I may provide for them, conforme to my preceeding offers, and they received everie one, and placed according to the order as they firſt come: ſo that all thinges may bee duelie provyded, and had in readineſſe againſt the due time and ſeaſon of ſetting out.
               
               
                  〈2… pages missing〉
               
               ſenſe, and feeling out of mine owne experience, howe I ſee the eſtate of the Kingdome.
               Then (Worthie Countriemen) let vs lay theſe two things in the ballance, and judge vpon them: whether it is better for vs to goe there, where wee may haue to live in in a fruitfull Soyle, and wholeſome, in all commodities abounding to our contentments, beeing onlie a litle induſtrious, and painefull? than to live heere at home as Runnagates, vnanſwerable to GOD, the King, the Lawes, to all reaſon, and conſcience: to bee captivate as ſlaves, and caſt in loathſome Priſons, to ſatiſfie with our perſons, when our goods hath failed vs: and eſpeciallie, when wee haue wronged our beſt and kindeſt friendes, who out of their loves hath engaged themſelves, to be diſtreſſed, and impriſoned for vs, which ſhoulde bee a greater griefe vnto vs, than our owne impriſonments.
               And then ſhall wee diſdaine plantation: which to enterpriſe is ſo honourable; to proſecute ſo poſſible: to purchaſe ſo lawfull, and when attained, ſo profitable? No, whoſoever ſhall reaſon againſt the ſame, eſpecially ſuch as are in diſtreſſe, may well bee reputed, either the Baſtard of generoſitie, or the nurſling of ſimplicitie, or the abject of frugalitie: and ſhall either become for ever, the proſtitute of infamie, or conſecrated to perpetuall oblivion: and when hee is dead, his actions, his meanes, his name and all, ſhall die with himſelfe; and if hee ſhall ever happen to bee remembred, that remembrance ſhall onelie bee in ignominie, as the Wretch of his Countrie, the Curſe of his Kinred: and an vnthriſt for himſelfe.
               But I ſpeake not to ſuch a crew, whoſe baſeneſſe I knowe cannot climbe to ſurmount the meaneſt imagined difficultie, that may ariſe. I ſpeake to ſuch noble Spirites and generous mindes, in whom doeth ſhine the light of knowledge to diſcerne the differences betweene a baſe ſecuritie and honourable actions, vice and vertue, ſtupiditie,

and true worth: and who in end ſhall not miſſe to rejoyce in the enjoying the fruits of their labours in themſelves, and their names to bee honoured with a perpetuall remembrance.
               And if wee would ſtudie to bee remembred in our poſterities, heere is offered the occaſion to inſert vs in the bookes of memorie: for if wee would portion our ſecond children in a plantation, and ſuch as in nature wee are bound to helpe, and advance: both ſhall wee bee remembred in their ever-living ſucceſſions, throughout all enſueing ages: and they provyded in a competent beeing and meanes for them-ſelves, and theirs, and to bee thereafter proffitable for their King and Countrie: which is better, than either to be kept at home baſelie, &amp; ſhort of that which is beſeeming their birth, and qualitie: or to bee ſent to the ſervice of the Warres of forraine Princes, and to bee cutted away by the ſword, and then never more againe remembred: and for ſo ſmall meanes, as thereby yee can furniſh themſelves both in rayment, and foode.
               Imbrace then the honours of plantation. Doe wee dreame of difficulties? then knowe; that it is out of the greateſt difficulties, that ſpring the greateſt honours: &amp; it is that Knight-hood, which is gotten vnder the banner of a King, and in the Fieldes which is moſt honourable; and not that, which wee acquire by our moneyes; as the moſt part is now a-dayes. And that our actions may both renowne vs, and beget vs moneyes, wee may ſee in the examples that I haue ſette before your eyes, both of forraine nations, and of our own Countriemen, in their late plantations of Ireland, their eſtates now, their dignities, their honours, their credite, and their riches: and what they were knowne to haue beene before.
               But theſe I leave to your judgments: onelie now, to make an end, I muſt entreate thee (Noble and courteous
                  
                  Reader) to excuſe my freeneſſe in this my homelie diſcourſe, which I perſwade my ſelfe the generous minde will allowe of: and for the baſe, the ſimple and the vitious; I doe not care for their cenſure, onelie I wiſhe it were a ſpurre to drawe them to more vertue. As for the rudeneſſe of my ſpeach, I hope none will except, wherein I profeſſe no airt, if ſimplie I publiſh my good meaning and earneſt affection to ſo goode a Worke▪ And wherein their is defect in mee; I hope the purpoſe ſhall bee better inlarged by him, whoſe Pen is more than knowne to bee famous, the principall Actor in the buſineſſe, and to whom I principallie dedicate this my treatiſe: and to bee ſeconded by the vertues of theſe the Noblemen, and theſe worthilie honoured Gentle-men, the Knights Baronets, Vnder-takers oft o faire deſignes: ſo that nowe I ceaſe with my penne, but never with my Sword to doe them ſervice for the advancement of ſo good a Worke.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

