
   
      
         
            The state-mysteries of the Iesuites, by way of questions and answers. Faithfully extracted out of their owne writings by themselues published. And a catalogue prefixed of the authors names which are cited in this booke. Written for a premonition in these times both to the publike and particular. Translated out of French
            Mysteres des peres jesuites. English
            Rivet, André, 1572-1651.
         
         
            
               1623
            
         
         Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01948
            STC 12092
            ESTC S120862
            99856055
            99856055
            21571
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01948)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21571)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 959:3)
         
         
            
               
                  The state-mysteries of the Iesuites, by way of questions and answers. Faithfully extracted out of their owne writings by themselues published. And a catalogue prefixed of the authors names which are cited in this booke. Written for a premonition in these times both to the publike and particular. Translated out of French
                  Mysteres des peres jesuites. English
                  Rivet, André, 1572-1651.
                  Gosselin, Peter.
               
               [8], 54, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by G[eorge] E[ld] for Nicholas Bourne,
                  London :
                  1623.
               
               
                  A translation of: Rivet, André.  Les mysteres des peres jesuites.
                  Translator's dedication signed: Peter Gosselin.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Running title reads: The mysteries of the Iesuites.
                  Includes bibliography.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  A variant of the edition with Nathaniel Butter named as publisher in the imprint.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-10
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE STATE-MYSTERIES OF THE IESVITES, By way of Questions and Anſwers.
Faithfully extracted out of their owne Writings by themſelues publiſhed.
AND A Catalogue prefixed of the Authors names which are cited in this Booke.
Written for a Premonition in theſe times both to the Publike and Particular.
            Tranſlated out of French.
            REVEL. 3. 24. 25.
            
               Ʋnto you I ſay, who haue not knowne the depth of Satans, that which you haue already hold faſt till I come.
            LONDON, Printed by G. E. for Nicholas Bourne.
1623.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT VVORTHY, AND euery way moſt accompliſhed, Sr. Thomas Penyſtone Knight and Baronett, my euer-honored Maſter.
            
               SIR:
            
            
               ALthough wee haue ſeene in theſe our later dayes, and may euery day more and more perceiue in the affliction of Ioſeph, and in the pitifull and lamentable eſtate of a great many of the Reformed Churches of the world, the fearefull effects of the cruell and bloudy doctrine of thoſe, who vnder the ſweet name of Ieſus, preach and teach little elſe then fire, murther, and ſedition: Yet becauſe there are many, which eyther haue neuer heard of the damnable points theſe dangerous men doe

teach and maintaine, or hauing heard of them, will not at any hand beleeue, that ſuch holy-ſeeming Fathers haue in ſuch manner ſharpned their tongues like Serpents, &amp; that the venome of Aſpes is hidden vnder their lips; Therefore this Treatiſe (by the prouidence of God) fallen into my hands, diſcouering at large thoſe ſecret and abhominable poſitions of theirs, which no Rack, nor greateſt torments could euer yet extort out of any of them, I thought good to learne it to ſpeake the Engliſh Tongue, both to inſtruct them, which are not yet acquainted with their inacceſſible myſteries; as alſo to informe them better, which are ſo caried away by the blind loue of theſe perſons, as they will not be perſwaded that euer they haue been the Authors of thoſe wofull and miſerable Tragedies, newly acted vpon the Theaters of France and Germany: To the end that the truth being knowne, it may appeare in the face of all the world, what they are, who in ſtead of the wholſome milke and meate of the word of God, doe feed them, which are committed to their charge, with the poyſon of their deteſtable

blaſphemies, applying to their Inſtitutor many paſſages of the holy Scriptures, which are onely proper and appertaining to the Diuinity: with their impious and abhorred doctrine of depoſing and killing Kings, whereof there is in no other booke extant whatſoeuer, ſo much found briefly together; with their perfidous and peſtilent diſtinctions, for Princes to violate their faiths giuen vnto others, vpon that wicked Maxime of theirs, That faith is not to be kept with hereticks; with their pernitious Equiuocations, &amp; moſt leud mentall Reſeruations. In all which, and the reſt, the Author hath not belyed the Societie, for he hath cited all his affirmations out of their owne writings (iudging them like wicked ſeruants out of their owne mouthes) the quotations wherof, appearing in the margine, haue beene moſt punctually examined with the originals themſelues, by three learned Doctors of Oxford, who haue both reported them for faithfull, and the booke in generall moſt vſefull, and to that purpoſe for which the Author wrote it, which was, not ſo much for a Diſcouery, as for a Caueat to

all ſuch, who being not able to weigh their reaſons, are the eaſier to be abuſed by their diſſembling allurements: to which end alſo hauing now diuulged it, I preſent it in all humilitie vnto your noble Patronage, as a teſtimony of my dutie and thankfulneſſe for ſo many f
                  •
               uours and benefits receiued, ſince it pleaſed you to take me into your protection and ſeruice, after the miſerable diſſipation of the moſt part of the Reformed Churches of Normandy. So wiſhing you heauen vpon earth in this world, and eternall bliſſe in the life to come, I reſt euer in all ſubmiſſion,
            
               Your humble and truly-deuoted Seruant, PETER GOSSELIN.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE READER.
            
               THE Bookes which are cited in this Diſcourſe, are for the moſt part common, and haue beene diuers times printed in ſundry places: there is one cited in the beginning, which was firſt publiſhed in Spaniſh, and ſince tranſlated into Latine and French, wherein are contained three very excellent Sermons preached on the feaſt day of the Beatification of the glorious Patriarch bleſſed Ignatius, founder of the Society of Ieſus.
            
            
               By the Reuerent Doctor, Petrus de Ʋalderama, an Auguſtine Frier.
            
            
               The Reuerent Doctor Petrus Deza of the order of the Dominicans.
            
            
               The Reuerent Father Iacobus Rebuttoſa, of the ſame Oder.
            
            In this Diſcourſe I haue followed the edition of the French tranſlation made by Father Francis Solier a Ieſuite, imprinted at Poitiers by Anthony Meſnier, Printer to the King and the Vniuerſity, the yeare 1611.
            Now although the ſaid Sermons were compoſed by ſuch as were no Ieſuites; yet by tranſlating, publiſhing, and recommending them, they haue made them theirs; and engaged their credits for all that is ſaid in them concerning the founder and Society of the Ieſuites. For the other Bookes that are cited, here is a Liſt of them.
            
               Arturi de Eccleſia libri.
               Becaniſumma Theol.
               Bellarmini Controuerſiae.
               Idem contra Barclayum.
               
                  
Caniloci Theologici.
               Delrij diſquiſitiones Magica.
               Diſcipuli de tempore ſermones.
               Eudaem
                     ••…
                  -Iohannes Apol. pro Garneto.
               Eiuſdem Reſp. ad Anticot.
               Ignatij Epist. de virtute Obed.
               Maphau
                     •
                   de vitae Ignatij Loyolae.
               Marian. de Rege &amp; Regis Iuſtitutione.
               Poſſevini Bibliotheca ſelecta.
               Ribadeneira de vita Ignatij Loyolae.
               Suare
                     •
                  ii defenſio 
                     •
                  id. Cathol. contraſectam Anglicanam.
               Eiuſdem diſp. in Thomam.
               Sa Aphoriſmi confeſſariorum.
               Scribanij Amphitheatrum honoris.
               Sanctius in Iſayam.
               Toleti inſtructio Sacerdotum.
               
                  Ʋalentia in ſummam Thoma.
               Vaſquez in tertiam partem Thoma.
            
         
         
            
               Page 49. Line 17. for ſom any, reade ſo many.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE MYSTERIES OF THE IESVITES, by Queſtions and Anſwers.
            Where the Nouice demandeth, and the profeſſed Ieſuite anſwereth.
            
               NOVICE.
               
                  FATHER, being reſolued to vow my ſelfe to a religious life in your Societie, I entreat you would be pleaſed to giue me leaue, for my inſtruction, to aske you ſome Queſtions, to the end, that by your Anſwers I may not onely be confirmed in my reſolution my ſelfe, but alſo prepared to informe others, whereby they likewiſe may bee drawne to the ſame deuotion.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Speake on boldly, my Sonne, for no part of our myſteries ſhall be concealed from thee, prouided thou promiſe to receiue them at my hands vnder the ſeale of Confeſſion, and not to reueale any more thereof, then what we are contented to haue

publike, reſeruing in ſecret the Theory of many things, whoſe practice cannot be hid, and yet it may not eaſily be perceiued from whence they procced.
            
            
               NOVIE.
               I will carefully obſerue the ſilence, which I am ready to vow, and will neuer ſpeake word of any thing, but when you ſhall pleaſe to open my mouth, vnleſſe it be now, that for to learne of you, I make ſome demands. And firſt of all I beſeech you let me vnderſtand the originall of our Society: for ſome there be, and thoſe too among other religious Orders, that hold it to be but new.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               It is true indeed that it hath been renewed in our time, wherein it was neceſſary to inſtitute ſome new Orders, Bellarm. de Monach. l. 2. cap. 6.
                  
                  Becauſe that feruor which is found in the beginning of a new Order, exciteth many men to pietie, which by little and little waxing cold, it is needfull that new ſhould be raiſed, whereby that feruor may be entertained: But if wee regard the firſt originall of this Societie, it will appeare to be very ancient.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I pray you ſhew me how; for I ſhould be glad to be furniſhed with meanes to ſtop their mouthes which termes vs New-men.
               
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  So farr is our Society from being to be accounted new, that there is not any one ſo ancient; for it was before the Apoſtles time: and to proue it, The

Societie of Serm. de Valderama pag. 10.
                  Ieſus was founded euen at the very point of his admirable Conception, vniting in his diuine perſon his humanitie with his eternall nature: And that was the firſt ſocietie which God had with men, and the first Colledge thereof was the virginall womb of the Virgin.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I ſhould neuer haue dreamed of this Colledge, nor of ſo authenticall an originall of our Societie without your direction: But is it not ſpoken of in the Goſpell, or in the writings of the Apoſtles?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Yes. For S. 
                  1 Cor. 1. 9.Paul ſpeaketh of it in theſe words, in the firſt to the Corinthians, God is faithfull, by whom yee haue beene called to the ſocietie of his Sonne Ieſus. And S. 
                  1 Ioh. 1. 3.Iohn, To the end our ſocietie may be with the Father, and with his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. By which words it followeth, ſaith Father Arturus, Lib. 1. de Eccleſia.that the Societie of Ieſus hath beene euer ſince the time of the Apoſtles, and is not new, as Sadeel doth maliciouſly ſlander it. Neither is any credit to be giuen to 
                  Locor. Theol. lib. 4. cap. 2.
                  Melchior Canus Biſhop of Canary, ſaying, That that ſocietie being the Church of Chriſt, they which doe attribute that title vnto themſelues, are to conſider whether like vnto the Heretikes they doe not vainly boaſt, that the Church is no where abiding but with them. For you muſt obſerue my Friend, that this Canus was of the Order of the preaching Friers, of whom Father 
                  Praefat. ad lib. diſquiſ. Magic.Delrio writeth truly, That openly they carry themſelues as enemies and oppoſites to our Societie, and in ſecret by their deuices they traduce it, labouring all they can, both in Italy, Spaine, and throughout the

whole world, to make it to be enuied, and ſeeke not onely by themſelues, but by certaine lying Hiſtorians their inſtruments, to blemiſh it in what they may; and ſtriue with all their might, either to cauſe their bookes to be prohibited, or the reading of them to be ſuſpended, or at leaſtwiſe they charge them with ſome note of infamy: Whereupon it may be reaſonably concluded, that theſe men are not to be held eyther for competent Iudges, or witneſſes againſt them of our Societie, nor againſt any of their writings whatſoeuer, but are to be ranked in the number of our accuſers and aduerſaries.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               It is no maruell then if this Spaniſh Biſhop hath ſnarled ſo at our Societie: and without doubt from the ſame ſpirit proceedeth that which hee ſaith in another Locor. Theol. lib. 11. cap. 16.
                  place ſpeaking of fabulous Legends, wherewith he compareth certaine Hiſtories, which he calleth fables, publiſhed not long ſince by ſome that came from farre, vnto whom hee applyeth the Spaniſh prouerbe, De luengas vias, luengas mentiras, Great trauellers, great lyers. For I ſuſpected that thereby he meant that which is read in the Epiſtles of the Fathers of the Societie, ſent from the Eaſt-Indies.
               
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Thine opinion was not improbable. But to leaue theſe enuious fellowes, I will returne to the original of our Societie, which though it be as ancient as I haue deliuered, yet that muſt be vnderſtood onely of the firſt and fartheſt foundations thereof; for elſe it cannot be denyed, but that in many things it is of a new inſtitution; and alſo it doth acknowledge for

Inſtitutor an holy perſonage, that beganne his Order not aboue foureſcore yeares ſince; for Father Bellarmine in his Chronologie doth attribute the confirmation thereof to Paul the third, in the yeare 1540.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Who was the Inſtitutor of it?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               St. Ignatius Loyola borne in Biſcay, and a ſubiect of the Kings of Spaine.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               What life had he lead before?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Why he had beene a debauched Souldier, and borne armes at Pampelune againſt the French, where hee was maymed, with an hurt that he receiued on both his knees, whereof hee halted euer after, but in ſuch manner that it was hardly perceiued, as Father Maphaeus well obſerueth in his life.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I feare that the Heretickes will draw ſome bad conſequence from thence, and ſay that he is the father of a Societie, which halteth on both ſides, as ſometimes the 1 Kings 18. 21▪
                  Prophet Elias obiected to the Idolaters amongſt the Iſraelites.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               I make no queſtion but they will, but we muſt not regard what they ſay; howſoeuer, though we halt on both ſides, I am ſure we runne faſt enough to cut them out as much worke, as they can turne their hands vnto. But to returne to Saint Ignatius our Inſtitutor,

it was he that enflamed with zeale, firſt thought vpon the enrolling of ſo holy a Society.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               It ſeemeth alſo that his name taketh its ſignification from fire.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Thou art in the right, and thereupon I will diſcouer great myſteries vnto thee. Firſt of all: 
                  Serm. de Valderama pag. 10.
                  As the Pſalmiſt ſaith, According to thy name O Lord, ſo is thy prayſe throughout all the earth, thy right hand is full of iuſtice: As much thinke I may I ſay of Father Ignatius, which ſignifieth a Saint compoſed of fire, and that is one of the names proper to God, Our God is a conſuming fire: and on the other ſide I perceiued, that in his right hand he carrieth the name of Ieſus, who was our Sauiour and ſanctification.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Now I learne of you, that one may ſay as much of a man as of God without ſinning, which is a deepe point.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Thou ſayeſt true, my Sonne, and this I will adde further, 
                  Serm. de 
                        •
                     e
                     
                        •
                     a pag. 112.
                  That in theſe laſt times God hath ſpoken vnto vs by his Sonne Ignatius, whom he hath conſtituted heyre of all things, and in whom nothing is wanting, but onely that word whereby he made all ages.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Verily, though he did not make all ages by him, he hath renewed the world by him, and hath made

another age of it: And as Gen. 1. v. 2.
                  the Spirit of the Lord moued vpon the waters, before the world was formed, as it were ſitting vpon that confuſed maſſe, for to hatch it ſuch as it was at laſt: euen ſo is it true, as Father 
                     Pag. 74.
                  Valderama preached, That when Saint Ignatius plunged himſelfe in the water vp to the very chin in the heart of winter, for to diuert a young man from certaine filthy deſires, one might ſay, that Spiritus Domini ferebatur ſuper aquas, the Spirit of the Lord was carried vpon the waters.
               
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  This indeed is a pretty obſeruation, and there is no doubt, but that the coldneſſe of the waters was well warmed by the touching of his body: for as the ſame 
                  
                     Pag. 10.
                  Preacher ſaith, When he reſolued to quit the Souldiers life, the very houſe wherein he then was, moued, the wals ſhaked, the poſts and beames trembled, and all that were in it betooke themſelues to flight, and ranne out of doores as faſt as their legges could carry them: euen as when ſome ſtrange eruption of fire doth ſodainly burſt out with furious flames in ſome high mountaine; ſo when this interior fire began to be diſcouered in him, who before (young Souldier) was cold and frozen in the things of God, it lightned forth in ſuch ſort, that it cauſed a thouſand feares, a thouſand amazements, a thouſand firings of houſes &amp;c. there was neuer any Montgibel, or flaming mountaine that did the like.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I heard an Hereticke not long ſince make ſtrange Gloſſes vpon this. Heeſaid vpon occaſion of Father

                  Bellarmins reaſon that it was needfull to haue new Orders, becauſe the feruor of the old by little and little grew cold, how we held a good courſe that the like ſhould not arriue vnto ours: for beſides the care we prouidently take, that the great pot may be alwayes boyling, which is a perpetuall meane to preſerue the feruor of our mercinary Religion, we exerciſe the trade of incendaries in all places; and not contented with a thouſand firings of houſes, made by our Inſtitutor, we haue ſet all Chriſtendome on fire: neither is there any Kingdome, Commonwealth, City, or Prouince, which we haue not enflamed with warres and ſeditions; and therefore ſaid he, was our Father Ignatius moſt properly compared to a Montgibel, the very tunnell of Hell.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  For hearing theſe things, and repeating them againe, thou deſerueſt to be impriſoned in the chamber of meditations, there to faſt with bread and water, and be diſciplined twice a day, and after all that, be forced to haue recourſe vnto his Holineſſe for an Abſolution, as of a caſe reſerued. But becauſe I find thee docible, I will proceed in inſtructing thee, and ſeeke to cleare thee of all ſuch doubts, as theſe blaſphemies may happely haue left in thee: And firſt of all, for anſwer vnto thoſe which accuſe vs for the care we take of our pot, I muſt remember vnto thee the worthy diſcourſe which Father Deza made thereupon. The deſigne 
                     1 Serm. de Deza pag. 152.
                  
                  ſaith he, of theſe good Fathers, when as they ſeeke the commodity of their Colledges, is like the aduice which Ioſeph gaue to Pharaoh for the ſtoring vp of corne into his Garners againſt the

time of neceſsity and famine. The maruell is how theſe Fathers in ſuch hard and peruerſe times can poſsibly find the meanes to furniſh themſelues with all that they want. It is a miracle that men being ſo miſerable and pinching, yet ſhould not haue the power to deny theſe Fathers; a miracle like vnto that which God wrought vpon the Egyptians, in fauour of his people, when they lent vnto the Iſraelites whatſoeuer they asked, and God would haue them to carry it all away: ſuch is euen right the caſe of theſe good Fathers, for it is a ſigne that God hath a care of them, that they are his people, and that he tenderly loueth them, when they that are ſo neere and couetous take a pleaſure to furniſh them with all that they ſtand in need of.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I ſhould feare that many good Catholikes would be much offended with this ſpeach, when in recompence of their liberality they ſhall ſee themſelues compared to the Egyptians, which may indanger their affection to our Society.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Neuer feare it: for good Catholikes will not bee offended if any thing be derogated from them to magnifie ſo holy a Society. Now touching the other obiection of Montgibell, and incendiaries, whereof they accuſe vs, for anſwer I ſay, that thoſe Sophiſters take that literally, which wee meane ſpiritually.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I ſubmit my ſelfe in all humility to your expoſition.

But I intreat you to tell me why our Father Ignatius gaue the name of Ieſus to his Society.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  There be many reaſons for it. And the firſt is, 
                  Valderama pag. 10.
                  That as our Lord Ieſus, who being the Sauiour of our ſoules, from the time of his natiuity into the world, vnto his death, neuer dealt in other buſineſſe then that which concerned our ſaluation; ſo the life of our Ignatius was wholly beſtowed about the ſauing of ſoules. The life of Ieſus was manifeſted in his workes, and Ignatius was transformed into him, whoſe name the Societie beareth.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I thought there had beene none but Saint Francis, that had beene transformed in ſuch manner into Chriſt, that the one could not be knowne from the other, but by their difference of habit, as father Horat. Turcel. in Ieſuit. apud Poſſ.
                  Horace Turcelin hath daintily expreſſed it in theſe foure verſes.
               
                  Exue Franciſcum tunica laceroque cucullo,
                  Qui Franciſcus erat iam tibi Chriſtus erit:
                  Franciſci exuvijs, ſi qua licet, indue Chriſtum,
                  Iam Franciſcus erit qui modo Chriſtus erat.
               
               That is to ſay, take the frocke and the gowne from Saint Francis, and he ſhall be Chriſt: and put on the frocke and gowne on Chriſt, and he ſhall be Saint Francis: but now I learne that the ſame alſo may be ſaid of father Ignatius; take from him his cloake and his buckle, and he ſhall be Ieſus: or attire Ieſus like a Ieſuite, and he ſhall be Ignatius, ſeeing

                  Ignatius is transformed into him.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               No queſtion but it may be ſaid with as much reaſon, as that which father Gaſpar Sanctius, dedicating a Booke to St
                  ▪ 
                  Ignatius aſſureth, namely, that the iudgement of father Ignatius, Nihil omnino diſcrepat à Diuine, is in nothing different from the iudgement of God.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Is there no other reaſon why the name of Ieſus was giuen to our Societie?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Yes; and this it is, Father Ignatius going to Rome for to obtaine the approbation of his Order, and finding himſelfe much perplexed about that which might befall him there, Ieſus appeared vnto him carrying a Croſſe, and in the ſame viſion alſo God the Father was ſeene recommending our Society vnto his Sonne, who promiſed him in good Spaniſh termes, that he would be propitious and fauourable vnto him at Rome, as father Maphae. in vit. Loyala lib. 2. Et Rib lib. 2. cap. 20.
                  
                  Maphaeus and Ribadeneira relate. Theſe ſpeeches fortified him, and gaue him occaſion to name his Company the Society of Ieſus.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               The ſame Hereticke of whom I ſpake before, obiected vnto me, that that Ieſus which ſpake to our father Ignatius, was but an imaginary Ieſus, and that whereas the true Ieſus maketh interceſſion to his Father for the faithfull, the imaginary father of our Ignatius maketh interceſſion to his ſonne for vs; and whereas the true Ieſus promiſeth to bee propitious

vnto his in heauen, the imaginary promiſed to bee propitious to his at Rome. But to leaue theſe ſcoffers with their blaſphemies, did not Ieſus that appeared to father Ignatius performe his promiſe?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Doſt thou doubt of that? certainly the Apoſtles haue not more credit in heauen, then we haue vpon earth, eſpecially at Rome, where after this apparition, Serm. de Valderama. pag. 48.
                  
                  The Pope hauing well conſidered Ignatius hands, he found them all printed ouer with the name of Ieſus, whereupon he ſaid, Digitus Dei hic eſt, In theſe hands is the finger of God.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Indeed I haue beene told that this good Saint wrought great miracles as well as Moſes, of whom the Magicians of Egypt ſayd that which the Pope ſaid of Ignatius.
               
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  What ſayeſt thou, as well as Moyſes? Serm. de Valderama pag. 11.
                  It was no maruell if Moyſes wrought ſuch great miracles, for he did them by vertue of the ineffable name of God engraued in his rod: it was no maruell if the Apoſtles wrought ſuch miracles, ſeeing they alſo did them in the name of God: But that Ignatius, with his name written in paper, ſhould doe more miracles then Moyſes, and as many as the Apoſtles, &amp;c. is that which ſheweth ſo wonderfull vnto vs.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               What particular office hath father Ignatius? or

what part is there commonly aſſigned vnto him for the ſuccour of men? for I make no doubt, but as God hath aſſigned to euery orher Saint the cure of ſome one diſeaſe or other, as to St. Roch the plague, to St. Petronel the feuer, to St. Main the itch, ſo St. Ignatius hath ſome certaine one vnto which hee is maruellouſly aſſiſting.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Thou art in the right: 
                  Valderama. pag. 51.
                  Father Ignatius doth aſſuredly and moſt readily aſsiſt all women that are in labor: for this vigilant Paſtor doth alwayes accompanie the ſheepe that are great with young, for to helpe them to be deliuered, as it is written in Eſay, Foetas ipſe portabit, that is to ſay, he will looke to the Ewes, for to haue their wooll and their lambes.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Now here is a paſſage of Eſay moſt ſubtilely interpreted, and ſure none of the Ancients euer diſcerned that it was ſpoken of Ignatius, and of the care which he hath of women with child. But it is not ſtrange that Ignatius ſhould haue ſuch a care of good women, for the holy Virgin her ſelfe, accompanied with two Angels, made it not ſqueamiſh to goe and viſit a gentle Abbeſſe, that had ſuffered her ſelfe to be gotten with child, and for the preſeruation of her honor, commanded thoſe two Angels to deliuer her of her burthen, and to carry it to an Hermit to bring it vp, which in time became a Biſhop, as it is at large related in the Booke of the miracles of the Virgin Mary, printed certaine yeares ſince at Cum ſec. parte Serm. diſcip. de tempore. Apud Ioh. Albinum▪ 
                     1612.
                  
                  Mentz.
               
            
            
               
               IESVITE.
               
                  Father Ignatius taketh not that courſe, nor hath any need of Angels for the matter: 
                  Valderama. ib.For doe but onely lay the bleſſed Fathers ſignet vnto the patient, and ſhe will ſoone be rid of her paine. The onely ſight of his name hath giuen eyes to the blind, hands to the maimed, legs to the lame, hath conſumed the ſtone in the kidneyes, and very eaſily brought women to bed.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Why this indeed is the very finger of God. But doth he not caſt out deuils?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Valderama pag. 55.
                   It happened one night, that the deuill had almoſt ſtrangled him, and twice or thrice he beat him cruelly: but ſince he had a full reuenge of him: For it hath beene often ſeene by experience, that after many prayers haue beene made, many Saints inuoked, many and ſundry relickes applied, the last remedy hath beene the image of bleſſed Ignatius, laying it on the patient, or one of his ſignets, ſhewing it vnto him, and ſaying, Permerita B. Ignatii abi hinc Spiritus maligne, and preſently he departed.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Is not this good Saint dead?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Yes, that he is, and his body was laid in the earth, whence he is not yet riſen againe: 
                  Idem pag. 89.
                  But in his Sepulcher was heard moſt melodious ſinging: his Sepulcher

ſeemed a new heauen, the Angels made ſuch muſicke there, and for that effect they deſcended downe in ſquadrons from heauen. Now though no Angell euer appeared vnto him in his life time, yet the bleſſed Virgin, Saint Peter, the eternall Father, and his Sonne carrying his croſſe, appeared vnto him.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Why did no Angels appeare to him during his life?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Fol. id. ibid. It arriued vnto him at his death, as it arriueth vnto great Potentates of the earth: As long as Kings are in their Palaces and houſes of pleaſure, the Guard ſuffer none to enter but men of note, vnleſſe it be ſome neceſſary attendants: but when the King is dead, and that hee is laid on an hearſe in the great Hall of the Court, then euery one is admitted to come in. As long as Ignatius liued, there was none but Popes, as St. Peter; Empreſſes, as the Mother of God; or ſome Soueraigne Monarch, as God the Father, and his Sonne, which had the fauour to behold him: but as ſoone as he was dead, euery Courtier belonging to the eternall King was admitted, all the celeſtiall people ranne to ſee him, Angels, Archangels, Thrones, &amp;c.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               This indeed was admirable, and verily I doe not thinke that the like can be ſaid of any other Inſtitutor of an Order. But tell me, I pray you, was hee author of any rule more auſtere then others that went before him?
            
            
               
               IESVITE.
               
                  He deſired, 
                  Ignat. Ep. de virtute obedien. Sect. 3.
                  That we ſhould ſuffer our ſelues to be ſurmounted by other religious Orders, in watching, faſting, and other auſterities both in diet and habit, and hath exempted vs from ſinging day and night in the Quire as others doe: And that for great reaſons: He would not haue vs ſubiect to ſinging day and night, 
                  Valderama pag. 30. &amp; 31.
                  Becauſe as the Angell wraſtling with Iacob, ſaid vnto him, Let me goe, for behold the day appeareth; to make him conſider that he had many droues of ſundry kindes of cattle, that he had children in his traine, and was to prouide meat for ſome, and drinke for others; ſo that to a man which had ſuch a charge vpon him, it was fit the night ſhould be allowed free for contemplation: ſo it is not poſsible for vs to beſtow the day in the Quire, that are to furniſh the flocke with paſture and cleare water.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Here is a reaſon as cleare as water, and therefore I ſee that that was the cauſe, why he did not thinke it fit to charge vs with ſuch auſterity of watching, faſting, and diet, leſt by too much weakneſſe of body, we ſhould be made vncapable of the guiding and gouernment of ſo many Beasts, as are committed vnto vs.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               It is right. But in one thing hee would haue vs not to ſuffer our ſelues to be ſurmounted, but rather that we ſhould ſurmount all others, And that the true and lawfull poſterity of our Society ſhould thereby be distinguiſhed, as by their marke.
               
            
            
               
               NOVICE.
               What marke is that I pray you? for I very much deſire to carry it, though the heretickes ſhould hold it for a marke of the Beaſt.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Thou doeſt wiſely not to regard their prattle, nor that neither of ſome Politicians as bad as they, who hold that for ſottiſhneſſe, which we account the greateſt vertue of all, and that is, Ignat. de obed. virtute, Sect. 3
                  
                  the renunciation of all will, and all iudgement, for to depend wholly vpon the iudgement and will of another.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               If by that other you meane God, it is a great impietie to gainſay that we ſhould not altogether ſubiect our will to his will, and our iudgement to his iudgement; and I hold him for a manifeſt Hereticke that denyeth it.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Nay, now thou ſheweſt that thou art but a Nouice; it is not that which we blame in the Heretikes and Politicians, for they confeſſe as much as thou ſayeſt: but by another, wee meane our Superiours, whoſe will our Father 
                  Ibid. Sect. 1.
                  Ignatius would haue vs hold to be Diuine. And we are not to regard, 
                  Ibid. Sect. 3.
                  Whether this Superior hath wiſdome, or goodneſſe, or other gifts of God, that our obedience may not in any thing be diminiſhed: or whether he be not capable of great counſell, or whether he be not prudent: becauſe wee are to regard, that he holdeth the place of him which cannot be

deceiued, who will ſupply any defect he may haue of prudence and probitie. And it is to be noted, 
                  Ibid. Sect. 5.
                  That your obedience ſhall be imperfect, if it mount not to that degree, not onely to execute the action, which hee commandeth you exteriourly, but alſo that you transforme your will into the will of your ſuperiour, otherwiſe it will not merit the name of vertue. And therefore it is, that we reade how obedience is better then ſacrifice: the reaſon whereof is deliuered by S. Gregory, becauſe in ſacrifices the fleſh of a thing was offered, and by obedience one offereth his owne will, which is an excellent part of the ſoule.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I had thought till now that ſacrifice was not to be offered to any but onely vnto God, which was the cauſe why I beleeued that when you ſpake of renouncing all a mans will for to obey another, which is, as you teach me now, to ſacrifice ones owne will, it was not to be done to any but vnto God alone.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Therein thou wert miſtaken, not to regard in the perſon of thy Superiour, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, who is ſupreme wiſedome, immenſe goodnes, infinite charitie, that cannot be deceiued, neyther will deceiue thee. And this we muſt doe according to the inſtruction of S. Ibid. Sect. 16.
                  Ignatius, who would not haue vs queſtion 
                  
                     Sect. 12.whether he that commandeth vs, doth it well or ill, Recténe, an ſecus: for then 
                     Sect. 7.by obedience wee render our freewill vnto him, from whom we receiued it. Now, 
                  Tollet. inſtruc. ſacerd. l. 4. cap. 3. Sect. 4.
                  if (as Cardinal Tollet teacheth) a ſimple Countriman, that beleeueth his Biſhop, propounding ſome Hereticall doctrine vnto him in the articles of faith, meriteth
                  
in beleeuing it, although it be an error, becauſe hee is bound to beleeue vntill he knoweth that it is repugnant to the Church. Why ſhould not we yeeld as much to our Superiours; and why ſhould not we hope to merit, if we doe that which they command vs, without farther inquiry, euen when they command euill? It is they that ſhall anſwer for it.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I wholly ſubmit my ſelfe to beleeue you, that I may not loſe the fruit of obedience; and renounce mine owne vnderſtanding to approue this doctrine, which I would entreat you to declare me ſomewhat more particularly, in regard that therein conſiſteth our Proprium quarto modo, our principall marke.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  I will doe it in our Father Ignatius owne termes, who hath preſcribed vnto vs, for an article of faith, 
                  Ibid. Sect. 18.
                  How wee are to hold for moſt infallible, that whatſoeuer our Superiour commandeth, is the commandement and will of God, and by conſequent, that with all our heart, &amp; with all our conſent, wee labor to do all that the Superiour biddeth, out of a certaine blinde impetuoſitie of the will, deſirous to obey, without any enquiry at all; as wee imploy all our conſent to beleeue The Articles of our Faith, and as Abraham did, when God commanded him to offer his ſonne Iſaac.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               This being once granted, as needs it muſt, ſeeing the iudgement of our Father Ignatius is diuine, nothing ſhall be impoſſible to our Societie: and as

long as there are thoſe which haue vowed this obedience, ſo long ſhall wee haue men capable to execute the moſt difficult and hazardous enterpriſes. But be pleaſed, I pray, to tell mee whom wee are to take for our ſuperiours, which haue this power ouer vs.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Bleſſed Ignatius ſhall anſwer thee himſelfe; 
                  Ibid. Sect. 20.
                  That which I haue ſaid of obedience, equally appertaineth to priuate perſons towards their neareſt ſuperiours: as to Rectors of Colledges, and ſuch as are ordained for Preſidents in each place towards their Prouincials; to Prouincials, towards their Generall: to the Generall, towards him, whom God hath eſtabliſhed ouer him, namely his Vicar vpon earth.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               What are wee to beleeue of this Vicar, which is our holy Father the Pope?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               That he is the vniuerſall Monarch of the whole Church; her head, her ſpouſe, and conſequently aboue her. That hee is the fundamentall ſtone, of which Eſay ſpeaketh, ſaying; 
                     Eſay 28. 16.
                  I will ſend into Sion a ſtone, a tryed ſtone, a pretious corner ſtone, a ſure foundation, hee that beleeueth ſhall not make haſte. For although the Apoſtles 1 Pet. 2. 6.
                  S. Peter, and 
                     Rom. 9 33.
                  S. Paul haue applyed it to Chriſt, yet ſo it is, that it is ſpoken there of a foundation after a foundation, of the ſecond foundation, not of the firſt, as Cardinall Praeſat in lib. de ſum. Pontif. Item in eod. lib. per totum. &amp; de concil. lib. 2. 
                     
                        •
                     . 17
                  
                  Bellarmine learnedly obſerueth.
            
            
               
               NOVICE.
               Muſt it be vnderſtood that the holy Father is aboue the whole Church, both in ſpirituall and temporall things?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               It muſt: howbeit with this moderation, whereof we make vſe to content the ſcrupulous; that temporall things depend on him, ſo farre forth as they ſerue to ſpirituall, and that for the good of them the Pope Bellar. de pontif. lib. 5. cap. 6. §. Explicanda.
                  hath ſoueraigne power to diſpoſe of the temporall eſtates of all Chriſtians: Becauſe 
                  Ibid. cap. 7. §. Prima ratio.
                  the Ciuill power is ſubiect to the Spirituall, and euery ſuperiour may command his inferiour.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Doe you apply this to Kings and Kingdomes?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               It is to that vſe for which this doctrine chiefly ſerueth, and it needeth no further explication, ſeeing that ſo many effects haue ſufficiently declared the application thereof.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I, but yet I would deſire you to furniſh me with ſome Maximes for the eaſe of my memory, according as they haue beene regiſtred by the moſt approued Authors of our Societie.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  With all mine heart: And in the firſt place Cardinall 
                  Deſum. Pont. lib. 5. cap. 7. Sect. Item poteſtBellarmine ſhall teach thee, That the ſpirituall power may depoſe Princes, and place others in their

ſteads, when as it cannot otherwiſe conſerue its ſpirituall eſtate. And Father Suarez, Defen. 
                        •
                     id. Cath lib. 3. cap. 23. §. 10.
                  That the power of the Pope extendeth to the repreſsion of Kings by temper all paines, and by priuation of their Kingdomes when neceſsity requireth. Alſo, 
                  
                     Ibid. §. 18.That the Pope hath as much power ouer temporall Princes, yea ouer ſuch as are abſolute and ſoueraigne, as ouer the other faithfull or baptiſed Chriſtians, not onely to repreſſe them by cenſuring their faults, but alſo to puniſh them with temporall and corporall paines. Further, That this power is much more neceſſary for the repreſsion of Princes, then of ſubiects.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               This it may be is meant of hereticall Princes.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Indeed it is firſt meant of them. And if our Catholikes in England, and other places, had as much power as they haue right, they would not endure hereticall Princes, as they are conſtrained to doe, till ſuch time as opportunitie ſhall ſerue to free themſelues from them: for otherwiſe they are taught by vs, that 
                  Bellar. de ſum▪ Pont. lib. 5. cap. 7 Sect. Praeterea.to ſuffer an hereticall or infidell Prince, who laboureth to draw men vnto his Sect, is to expoſe Religion vnto euident perill, which Chriſtians ought not to doe. And Father 
                  
                     Vbiſupr. §. 21Suarez worthily proueth, That it appertaineth vnto the Pope to defend the ſubiects of an hereticall Prince, and that by his power he may depriue ſuch a Prince of his Kingdome, chaſe him out of it, &amp; abſolue his ſubiects from their oath of allegeance. And herewith agreeth Father Gregory of Valentia, writing 
                  Tom. 3. Diſp. in Thom. diſp. 1. 
                     
                        •
                     . 12. punct. 2.
                  That temporall domination and ſuperioritie ouer ſubiects, by the ſentence of the Pope may be taken

away from Heretikes: And the reaſon of it is, That if they may bee depriued of their liues, much more of their eſtates, and conſequently of all ſuperioritie ouer others; and that they which are excommunicated for Hereſie, incurre de facto the depriuation of politicke power, and that their ſubiects are not onely abſolued from their oath of allegeance, but are alſo forbidden to keep it: And that if the Iudge hath not yet pronounced the ſentence of Excommunication, this paine is neuertheleſſe incurred, if the crime of Hereſie be ſo notorious that it cannot be hid; and then it is lawfull for the ſubiect to deny obedience to his hereticall Lord, much leſſe is he bound thereunto.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Truly theſe are notable Maximes, inſomuch that although the Pope hath not pronounced expreſſe ſentence of Excommunication againſt the Kings of Great Britaine, of Denmarke, and others ſuch like, and though their ſubiects are not expreſly forbidden to obey them, yet now I learne of you, for to teach them vpon occaſion, that it is in their libertie, eyther to doe, or not to doe it, without ſcruple of conſcience.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               I haue giuen thee for it the very words of our Maſters.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               But doe they extend this power alſo againſt Catholike Kings and Princes.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               They doe: for Father Suarez conioyneth him

                  that is peruerſe in his manners, with the hereticall Prince. And Cardinall Bellarmine cleareth thee of all doubt, 
                  Vbiſup. Sect. Alterum.The Prince (ſaith he) when he is Catholike in faith and beleefe, but of ſuch euill manners, that he is hurtfull vnto Religion, or to the Church, may be remoued, and reduced to the ranke of other ſheepe, by the Paſtor of the Church.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               May this be done in any other caſe?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               The Bellar. lib. 5 cap. 7. Sect. Tertium.Pope may alſo command Kings to puniſh Heretickes and Schiſmatickes; and if they doe it not, he may conſtraine them by Excommunication. Now I taught thee before the conſequences of Excommunication, which wee haue ſufficiently demonſtrated in the proceedings againſt Henry the third King of France, concerning whom Charles Scribanius one of our principall Fathers at Antwerp, in his 
                  Amphith. honoris, cap. 12.
                  Amphitheater of Honor, thus refuted thoſe which found fault with the Popes euill-entreating him. If (ſaith he) a Denis, a Machanidas, an Ariſtotimus, monſters of ages, ſhould oppreſſe France, ſhall there be no high Biſhop found ſo hardy as to animate a Dion, a Timolcon, a Philopoemon, an Helematus? If more monſters held the Commonwealth in captiuitie, ſhall no Thraſibulus ſet to an helping hand? The violence of Tarquin in the bed of Collatine gaue a iuſt cauſe, and ſhall there none be met withall to depoſe and aboliſh out of France, a tyrant King, that oppreſſeth the liberty, &amp;c? Shall there not ſome ſword-man at leaſt riſe vp againſt this beaſt? No Pope that will deliuer ſo noble a Kingdome?
            
            
               
               NOVICE.
               It ſeemeth to me, that they of our Society which anſwered Anti-Coton, deny Charles Scribanius to be the Author of that Booke: and albeit Father Reſp. ad Antic. cap. 3. pag. 48.
                  
                  Eudaemono-Iohannes confeſſeth that our Society is much indebted to the Author, for defending it with ſo learned a volume, yet hee maintaineth, how Anti-Coton cannot proue his coniecture, that Scribanius was the Author of it, by any euidence.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Therein he was deceiued: for by the Index of the Bookes of our Societie, compoſed by Father Ribadeneira, hee ſhall finde that Charles Scribanius hath ſhewed what knowledge hee had in humane learning, by his bookes of the Amphitheater of Honor, againſt the accuſations of the Caluiniſts.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Are wee the ſubiects of Princes where wee were borne, or where we liue?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Of neyther: for wee are Clerkes.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Doth it neceſſarily follow, that if we be Clerkes, then wee are not their ſubiects?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Yes, very clearly: For it cannot be proued (ſaith our 
                  De Clericis. lib. 5. cap 30. Sect. Quarto obijciunt.Bellarmine) that the Kings of this age are lawfull

ſuperiors and Iudges of Clerkes, if by the ſame meane it be not proued, that children are aboue their fathers, ſheepe aboue their paſtor, things temporall aboue ſpirituall.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               But is it not to be vnderſtood of ſpirituall things only, that Clerks are not ſubiect to ſecular Princes?
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Not onely (ſaith the ſame 
                  De Clericis lib. 2. cap. 17. Sect. Ad primam
                  Author,) in ſpirituall things, but alſo in temporall, is the Prieſt to be gouerned by his Eccleſiaſticall ſuperior: and it cannot bee, that in temporall things hee ſhould acknowledge the ſecular Prince, becauſe no man can ſerue two Maſters. And as Father 
                  Defenſ. contra Ang. lib. 4. cap. 17. Sect. 16. &amp; 18.
                  Suarez writeth, The ciuill Lawes of Princes and Magiſtrates doe not oblige Clerks, neyther as touching the power of conſtraint, nor as touching the power of direction, by force of the laicall iuriſdiction, onely they oblige them by force of reaſon: nor can Kings oblige Clerkes to thoſe lawes particularly impoſed. Now wee vnderſtand obligation by force of reaſon, when the authoritie of the Canons or daineth, that ſuch lawes are to be obſerued by Clerkes: but they are free from the vertue and proper obligation of ſuch lawes. The ſame man 
                  
                     Ibid. lib. 4. cap. 9. Sect. 17. &amp; 18.
                  after hee hath proued that Clerkes were committed to Peter, draweth this neceſſary conſequence from thoſe words of our Sauiour, No man can ſerue two Masters, Mat. 6. that Clerkes are exempted from the temporall iuriſdiction of Princes, iure diuino: becauſe the ſame morall impotence noted in thoſe words, Hee ſhall hate the one, and loue the other; he ſhall cleaue to the one, &amp; deſpiſe the other, would be found, if Clerkes were ſubiects according to

the body, both to the pope and to the King. Whence he euidently concludeth, that Clerkes are abſolutely exempted from the temporall Iuriſdiction of princes, by reaſon that that Iuriſdiction is exerciſed towards ſubiects in regard of the body, and conſequently in regard of all things which are ordained for a conuenient conſeruation of the body: if Clerkes then be exempted from the iuriſdiction of Princes as touching their bodies, certainly they are exempted from their temporall Iuriſdiction.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Doth it not follow now of this, that ſo many Eccleſiaſticks as are made in a Kingdome or Commonwealth, ſo many ſubiects is the Prince depriued of?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Cardinall 
                  De Clericis lib. 1. cap. 38. Sect. Quarto obijciunt.Bellarmine teacheth, that as he which transferreth his dwelling into another towne, or prouince, ceaſeth to be the ſubiect of that prince vnder whoſe domination he was before, without doing him wrong: So Princes haue no reaſon to complaine, if they be depriued ſpite of their teeth, of the right which they had vpon Clerkes, before they were Clerkes, becauſe he vſeth but his owne right, that chooſeth an eſtate, which he thinketh moſt conuenient for him, although by accident it followeth thereupon, that the Prince be depriued of his ſubiect.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I would be loath that all Princes ſhould know this ſecret: for from thence I learne, that they haue a State within their State, no more depending on them, then that of France doth on that of England.
                  
And that their ſubiects without ſtirring out of their Countryes, there enioying their eſtates, may exempt themſelues from their ſubiection: and by other Maximes, that they may alſo make themſelues their ſuperiours, euen in temporall things, though indirectly.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Thou ſayeſt right, and vnderſtandeſt the caſe well. For iure ordinario, as Father 
                  Defenſ fid. contra Ang. lib. 3. cap. 17.
                  Suarez will teach thee, not onely the Pope, but the Biſhop likewiſe is the Kings ſuperior, and euery King is ſubiect to his Biſhop in ſpirituall things, if he be not exempted from it by the pope, and immediatly receiued vnder his protection and iuriſdiction. Now temporall ſubiection neceſſarily followeth ſpirituall, as wee haue declared before. For as the ſame man teacheth, 
                  Eiuſdem lib. cap. 23. Sect. 18. &amp; 20.
                  If the Church could not puniſh thoſe that are ſpiritually ſubiect, with temporall paines, they would ſoone contemne the ſpirituall: and that would fall out which is ſpoken of in the Prouerbs, chap. 29. verſ. 15. The child which is left to his owne will confoundeth his mother. Whence would enſue, that the ſtate of Chriſtendome would not be well ordered, nor had beene ſufficiently prouided for, if the Church had not power to conſtraine ſuch rebels, as will not obey her cenſures. And it muſt not be ſaid, that the vengeance of crimes appertaineth to ſecular Princes, and that it is enough that they haue this power, becauſe they themſelnes may offend, and haue need of correction. And further, becauſe this vengeance doth not of it ſelfe appertaine to the ciuill Magiſtrate, but ſo farre forth as the faults are contrary to ciuill ends, the peace of the Commonwealth,

and humane iuſtice: but to puniſh them as contrary to Religion, and the ſaluation of ſoules, that of it ſelfe appertaineth to the Eccleſiaſticall power, vnto which Principally appertaineth the faculty of vſing temporall paines for ſuch corrections: which power is much more neceſſary for the repreſsion of Princes, then of their Subiects.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               You teach mee great myſteries, which I ſhould not eaſily haue apprehended without your direction, and haue made mee to ſee, that they which will betake themſelues to our Order muſt ſubiect their vnderſtanding by the vow of blind obedience. But declare vnto me, I pray you, the ground of the exemption of Clerks from the ſubiection of Princes in the States where they were borne.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Why it is grounded vpon the very law of Nature it ſelfe, 
                  Bellarm. de Clericis lib. 1. cap. 29. Sect. Alterum.For the Eccleſiaſticall power, which is ſpirituall, is in conſequence by nature aboue the ſecular, and therefore when need requireth, can direct, iudge, and correct it: but there is no reaſon that permitteth the ſecular to direct, iudge, or correct the ſpirituall.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I but if the election, which one may make of an Eccleſiaſticall eſtate, doth not exempt the ſeruant from the ſubiection of his Lord, why ſhould the ſame eſtate depriue the King, Prince, or Commonwealth of their ſubiects?
            
            
               
               IESVITE.
               The Bellarm. de Cleric. lib. 1. cap. 30. Sect. quarto obijciunt.tie which is betweene the Lord and the ſeruant is all in all farre greater then that which is betweene the Prince and the Subiect: And that is the reaſon why clericature exempteth the Subiect from the ſubiection of the Prince, or from the ciuill power, yea though the ſuperior oppoſeth it, but not the ſeruant from the power of his Lord. Cardinall Bellarmin ſaith as much of the obligation betweene the debtor and the creditor.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               If it bee ſo, may a Clerke, whatſoeuer hee doth or vndertaketh, euen againſt the very perſons of Princes themſelues, be guilty of humane treaſon?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Father 
                  Aphoriſ Confeſſ. Tit. Clericus.Emanuel Sa hath ſatisfied this queſtion in few words: The rebellion, ſaith hee, of a Clerke againſt his Prince is not treaſon, becauſe he is not his ſubiect.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I thinke thoſe words were left out in the edition of Paris.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  They were indeed, becauſe at that time this matter was much ſtirred in by certaine Politicians, who a great coile about it; howbeit they continue ſtill in the editions of Antwerp and Cullen. But ſay hee had not written it, it followeth well enough from this Maxime, whereof we are agreed, that Clerkes are not the ſubiects of Princes, nor Princes, in regard of them, ſuperior powers. And then 
                  Suarez. Defenſ. fid. 
                        ••
                     b 4. cap. 15. Sect. 1. 9. &amp; 10.
                  It is a generall

rule, that Eccleſiaſticall perſons are exempted from the ſecular iuriſdiction, not onely in Eccleſiaſticall crimes, but alſo in ciuill, which cannot be denied, ſaith Father Suarez, without denying a principle of faith. And ſo generall, that it ſuffereth not, according to him, any exception of crime whatſoeuer. Now if it be obiected, That in ſome Kingdomes, certaine crimes of Clerkes are excepted, which the ciuill Magiſtrate may take knowledge of, as the crime of high treaſon, of coyning falſe money, &amp;c. That is not by common right, but by a particular priuiledge, which Kings haue receiued from the Pope; for there is no King nor ſecular Prince that can giue it.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               But the Apoſtles, and the firſt Miniſters of the Chriſtian Church, ſubiected themſelues to Kings and Princes, payd them tribute, and neuer went about to depoſe them.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  The times are to be diſtinguiſhed: 
                  Bellarm. de Pont lib. 
                        •
                     . cap. 7. Sect. Quod ſi.For if the Chriſtians did not in times past depoſe Nero, Diocleſian, Iulian the Apoſtata, Valens the Arrian, and ſuch like, it was becauſe they wanted temporall forces; for otherwiſe by right they might, ſeeing that the Apoſtle in the 1. to the Cor. chap. 6. commandeth that new Iudges be eſtabliſhed amongst the Chriſtian, to the end that the Chriſtians might not bee conſtrained to plead before a Iudge that was a perſecutor of Chriſt, ſo would he haue commanded new Kings and Princes to haue beene made for the ſame reaſon, if they had had power enough in their hands.
            
            
               
               NOVICE.
               But why did not they vſe cunning where power wanted?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               It Mariana de Reg. lib. 1. cap. 6.
                  was expedient then, that the foundations of the Church ſhould be laid in patience, and ſuffering of death; with ſo much the more miracle, that it grew the greater being oppreſſed, and diminiſhing in number, yet euery day encreaſed. Moreouer in thoſe times it was not expedient to doe all, that law and right permitted.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               What doe law and right permit according to the doctrine of our Society?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               In all memory of men, ſuch as haue vndertaken the killing of Tyrants, haue euer beene held in high eſtimation.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Whom meane you by tyrants that may be killed?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               The Theologians, ſaith Father 
                  Def▪ fid. lib. 6. cap. 3. Sect. 1.
                  Suarez, thus diſtinguiſh Tyrants; the firſt ſort is of thoſe, which by force &amp; iniuſtly, without all title, occupy a Kingdome, which truly are neither Kings nor Lords, but onely hold the place, and are as it were the ſhadowes of them. The other ſort is of thoſe, which though they be true Lords, and poſſeſſe the Kingdome with a iuſt title, yet as touching their cariage, and manner of gouernment, reigne tyrannically, namely, becauſe that either neglecting

the publike good, they conuert all to their owne particular commodity, or iniuſtly afflict their ſubiects with ſpoyling, killing, and peruerting, or iniuriouſly commit ſuch things, or the like, publikly and frequently.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               May one with a good conſcience kill both the one and other of theſe Tyrants?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Of the firſt ſort no man doubteth: 
                  Marian. de Reg lib. 1. cap. 6.
                  For all Theologians and Philoſophers agree that they may be killed, depriued of their liues, and Principalities, by any one whoſoeuer. For ſeeing that ſuch a one rightly carrieth the name of a Tyrant, and hath put on the humor of one, let him at any rate be taken away, and diſpoiled of the power which he hath vſurped by violence. So by good right Ahud hauing inſinuated himſelfe by preſents into the fauour of Eglon King of the Moabites, he killed him with the ſtab of a ponyard in his belly, and deliuered his Countrimen from a cruell ſeruitude. Father Suarez defendeth this opinion as the moſt common and receiued, 
                  Defenſ cathol▪ lib 6. cap. 4. Sect. 7.
                  That ſuch a Tyrant may be killed by any priuate perſon whatſoeuer, that is a member of the State, which ſuffereth vnder the tyranny, if otherwiſe it cannot be deliuered from it. And to that which Saint Auguſtin ſaith in the firſt Booke of The City of God, how it is not lawfull to kill any perſon without publike adminiſtration, he anſwereth learnedly; That a priuate man, which killeth ſuch a Tyrant, doth it not without publike adminiſtration, becauſe he doth it either by the authority of the Common-wealth, tacitely conſenting thereto; or he doth it by the authority

of God, who by the law of nature hath giuen vnto euery one power to defend himſelfe and his Commonwealth from the violence which is done them by ſuch a tyrant.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               But what ſay you of Kings and Princes that are lawfull, but yet adminiſter tyrannically as touching their cariage?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               The Vbi▪ ſup. Sect. 2
                  preſent queſtion regardeth chiefly ſuch a Prince, and the King of England (as Suarez ſaith) ſpake alſo of ſuch Princes, becauſe we hold them in the ranke of lawfull Princes. Father Mariana, hauing vſed all the ordinary precautions, wherewithall I will hereafter inſtruct thee, came at length to this, not to leaue that power of killing ſuch a Prince in the pleaſure of any priuate man whatſoeuer, Vnleſſe the common voyce of the people be ſuch, and that graue and vnderſtanding men haue beene conſulted with vpon it. For in that caſe he iudged, that it would bee good for humane affaires, if valiant and couragious men were found, that deſpiſing their owne proper ſafety and liues, would for the liberty of their Country, and ſauouring the publike wiſhes, deliuer it from the Tyrant.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Is this opinion approued?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               The ſtirre which our Aduerſaries made about it, eſpecially in France, where they inſiſted vpon thoſe words. as the cauſes of attempts vpon their Kings, and affirmed, that Mariana by graue and vnderſtanding

men conſulted with vpon it▪ meant Confeſſors, and eſpecially thoſe of our Society, giuing them all power ouer the liues of Kings, hath beene the cauſe that wee were conſtrained to qualifie that ſaying a little: and although Marianaes booke had paſſed for currant, and had beene publiſhed according to order by permiſſion of the ſuperiors, yet at the inſtance of the Fathers of our Society, which in France found themſelues in trouble about it, the Generall Apud Eudaem. in Reſ. ad Antic. cap. 1.
                  
                  Aquauiua made a De
                     •
                  ree, whereby hee forbad, but without naming Mariana, to teach eyther by word of mouth, or writing, that it was lawfull for any perſon whatſoeuer, vnder any praetext of tyranny that might be, to kill Kings, or to plot their death. Father Eudaemono-Iohannes writing againſt the Ibid. pag. 32.
                  Wolfe (as he calleth him) of Chicheſter, hath refuted this opinion of Mariana, howbeit with this excuſe of him, that hee wrote it not as an Oracle, but as a man that deliuered his opinion with doubt; neuertheleſſe hee ſaith, that all the reſt of the Ieſuites diſallowed it.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Teach mee then, I pray you, what others ſay that ſpeake beſt of it.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               I cannot doe it better then by the doctrine of Father Suarez, who anſwering the King of England vpon this matter, ſpake the moſt correctedly hee could. Hee Defenſ. fid. lib. 6. cap. 4. Sect. 2.
                  holdeth then this Maxime for reſolued, that the lawfull Prince ruling tyrannically, or for any crime whatſoeuer, cannot be killed by any priuate authority.
            
            
               
               NOVICE.
               Doth he meane this in any caſe whatſoeuer?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  There are but three caſes, which may be conſidered in it. Eyther Ibid. Sect. 5.
                  the little of iuſt vengeance and puniſhment, or the title of iuſt defence of himſelfe, or the title of iuſt defence of the Common-wealth. The firſt title appertaineth to no priuate man. As touching the title of a iuſt publike or particular defence, diſtinction muſt be vſed, and conſideration had, whether a man defendeth himſelfe or the Common-wealth: if himſelfe, whether it be his life, his members, ſome grieuous mutilation of his body, or his goods. For it is not lawfull to kill his King doing violence for his goods. But if there be queſtion of the defence of his owne life, which the King would take away from him by violence, then, ordinarily it is lawfull for the ſubiect to defend himſelfe, although the death of the Prince doth thereof enſue: becauſe the right of the conſeruation of a mans owne life is the greateſt of all others; and then the Prince is not in any neceſsity that obligeth the ſubiect to loſe his life for him, who voluntarily and iniuſtly thruſteth himſelfe into that perill.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               
                  But may not one from thence draw that conſequence, which Mariana maketh? If thou ſeeſt (ſaith hee) 
                  De Reg. lib. 1. cap. 6. pag. 51.
                  thy Mother, or thy-deareſt Wife vexed in thy preſence, and doſt not ſuccour them being able, ſhalt thou not be cruell, and incurre the reproach of cowardiſe and impiety? and wilt thou let thy Countrey

be vexed and tormented by a Tyrant at his pleaſure, vnto which we owe more then to our parents?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  The conſequence is good in the like caſe. For (ſaith Father 
                  Ibid. vbi ſupra lib. 6. cap. 4. Sect. 6.
                  Suarez) grant that the King doth actually ſet vpon the Citie for to ruine it iniuſtly, or to kill the Citizens, or ſome ſuch like thing, then it ſhall be lawfull to reſiſt the Prince, euen in killing him, if the defence cannot otherwaies be made. For if it be lawfull to doe it for a mans owne life, much more for the publike good, becauſe a City or Common-wealth doth then make a iuſt defenſiue warre againſt an iniuſt oppreſſor, though its owne proper King, and ſo euery Citizen as a member of the Common-wealth, and moued by it eyther expreſly or tacitely, may defend the Common-wealth in that conflict, in any manner that he can. But it is otherwiſe of a King that raigneth in peace, and that vexeth the Common-wealth, and is hurtfull vnto it by other meanes, for then there is no place for defence by force, or for plots againſt the life of the King; becauſe the Common-wealth doth not then ſuffer any actuall violence, which it were lawfull to repell with violence.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               What muſt be done then in this caſe, where the Prince otherwiſe lawfull, commeth to ſuch a paſſe, That hee ruineth the Common-wealth, ſpoyleth men of their goods, deſpiſeth Religion, and the publike Lawes, maketh a vertue of pride, and holdeth impietie againſt God to be the greateſt valor?
            
            
               
               IESVITE.
               
                  Thou knoweſt what Father 
                  De Reg. &amp; Re. Inſt. lib. 1. cap. 6. pag. 59. &amp; 6.
                  Mariana, from whom thou hadſt this queſtion, bringeth for anſwer thereunto, namely, That it is not to be diſſembled, but the ſureſt meane to remedy it, is the publike way of Aſſemblies, wherein by a common conſent may be deliberated what ſhall be done. The Prince ſhall firſt be admoniſhed, and if he reiect the medicine, and that there reſteth no farther hope of amendment, the ſentence being pronounced, it ſhall be lawfull for the Common-wealth to deny him obedience: and becauſe that warre will neceſſarily enſue thereupon, armes muſt be taken vp, money raiſed, and if otherwiſe it cannot be done, by the right of defence the Common-wealth, by its owne proper authoritie, or by a greater, may kill the Prince declared a publicke enemy.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               But is not this a priuate opinion of that Father, which is not to be followed.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  No: for if hee had not proceeded farther, none of ours would euer haue contradicted him. Father 
                  Def. fid. lib. 6. cap. 4. Sect. 15.
                  Suarez teacheth the ſame doctrine very amply, whereof behold here the firſt ground, which is, That if a lawfull King doth gouerne tyrannically, and that the King dome hath no other meane of defence, but by depoſing and expelling the King, the whole Common-wealth, by a common conſent of the Townes and principall perſons of the Kingdome, may depoſe the King, as well by vertue of the law of Nature, whereby

it is permitted to repell force with force, as becauſe that neceſſary caſe of the proper conſeruation of the common-wealth, is alwayes held to be excepted in that firſt accord, by which the Common-wealth transferred its power to the King.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Doth it follow hereupon that the Common-wealth hath power to put this King to death?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               That Ibid. Sect. 18.
                  ground being laid, we muſt ſay, that after the ſentence of condemnation, touching the depriuation of the Kingdome, giuen by a lawfull power: or (that which is all one) after a declaratory ſentence of the crime, which of right hath impoſed ſuch a paine, he which hath pronounced the ſentence, or he vnto whom he hath giuen commiſsion to execute it, may depriue the King of the Kingdome, euen by putting him to death, if otherwiſe he cannot, or if the iuſt ſentence doth alſo extend to that paine. Howbeit the depoſed King cannot be killed by any priuate perſon whatſoeuer, no nor be expelled by force, till he be commanded vnto it, or that the generall commiſsion be declared by ſentence, or of right. The firſt part euidently followeth vpon that precedent principle: for hee that may iuſtly condemne any one, may likewiſe execute the ſentence eyther by himſelfe, or by helps neceſſary thereunto: otherwiſe that power would be fruſtratory, in being able to decide the right, without the ability of an efficacious conſtraint. And as the miniſter of a King doth well to kill a man by the Kings commandement, becauſe that then he executeth the Kings power rather

then his owne: ſo when the Common-wealth may iuſtly depoſe the King, the miniſters thereof doe well to conſtraine the King, or to kill him, if it be neceſſary, becauſe then they doe it no longer by priuate, but by publike authority. And therefore Soto ſaid well, That although it be not lawfull for any priuate man whatſoeuer to kill him that is a Tyrant in his gouernment, yet when the ſentence is giuen, one may eſtabliſh for the miniſter of the execution thereof whomſoeuer one will.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               But what meaneth Mariana by that ſpeach, where he ſaith, By the authoritie of the Common-wealth, or of a greater: what is that greater?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  He meaneth that which we all hold for moſt certaine, namely, that that 
                  Ibid. Sect. 17.
                  
                  power appertaineth to the Pope, as to the ſuperior, hauing iuriſdiction to correct Kings: yea ſuch as are ſoueraigne as well as their ſubiects. Now though the Common-wealth or Kingdome conſidered in its owne nature, and as it was amongst the Gentiles, or as it is at this preſent amongst them, hath the power, as we haue ſaid, to defend it ſelfe from a tyrant King, and for that effect to depoſe him, if it be neceſſary: yet Chriſtian Kingdomes, as touching that point, haue ſome dependance on the ſoueraigne Biſhop. Firſt, becauſe the Pope may forbid a Kingdome to depoſe the King without his knowledge and aduice, and vnleſſe he hath firſt beene informed of the cauſe, &amp;c. Wherupon we read in Hiſtories, that alwayes in ſuch caſes Kingdomes haue conſulted with the Pope, or haue euen implored him to depoſe vnworthy or tyrant kings,

as we haue declared of Childeric King of France in the time of Pope Zacharie, &amp;c. Secondly, the Chriſtian kingdome dependeth alſo on the Pope in this, That the Pope may not onely counſell, or conſent, that the kingdome may depoſe the King, which is pernicious to it, but may alſo command and conſtraine it to doe it, when he iudgeth it neceſſary for the ſpirituall ſafety of the kingdome, but eſpecially to auoid hereſies and ſchiſmes.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               If the holy Father▪ hauing conſented to the depoſition of a King, or hauing ordained it, yet doth not declare himſelfe for the execution thereof, ſhall it bee lawfull for the firſt Prince, that will, to make warre vpon him, and inuade his kingdome?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               No. Ibid. Sect. 19.
                  But then his lawfull ſucceſſor, if he be a Catholike, hath that power; or if he neglect it, or that there be none; the Cominalty of the kingdome ſhall ſucceed him, prouided they be Catholikes, and if they craue aſſiſtance of other Princes, they may aſsiſt them: howbeit if the Pope giue other Kings power to inuade the kingdome, they may iuſtly doe it, becauſe then they ſhall neither want iuſt cauſe nor power.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               What ſhal I anſwer vnto thoſe, which alledge Dauid that would not kill Saul, but cauſed the Amalekite to be put to death for vaunting that he had ſlain him: which obiect the miſchiefes arriuing vnto the Common-weath by ſuch facts: which ſay that

the reuerence of ſubiects towards their Princes is in danger, if once they bee perſwaded that they may puniſh their faults; and that vnder ſuch pretexts the publike peace ſhall often be diſturbed by ſeditions and commotions, one part of the people arming themſelues againſt the other, &amp;c.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               So they diſpute which take the tyrants part, ſaith our 
                  De Rege lib. 1. pag. 57.
                  Mariana, but the aduocates for the people produce as many, and as great reaſons for them. For the Common-wealth, from whom the Royall power tooke its originall, may according to the neceſsity of the caſe call their King in queſtion, and if he reiect the remedy, they may deſpoile him of his kingdome: for they haue not transferred their right in ſuch manner to the Prince, but that they haue reſerued a greater power vnto themſelues. Cardinall 
                  De Concil. lib 2 cap. 16. &amp; 19.
                  Bellarmine teacheth the ſame, That in the kingdomes of men the power of the King commeth from the people, becauſe the people made the King, which otherwiſe had beene a priuate man like another. And that if he degenerate into a tyrant, albeit he be the head of the kingdome, he may notwithſtanding be depoſed by the people, who may elect another. He commendeth 
                  Recog. lib de La
                        •
                     cis §. Addo.
                  alſo that which Nauarrus ſaith, How the people neuer make ſuch a tranſport of their power to the King, that they doe not reſerue it in habitude, to re-aſſume it in certaine caſes.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               
                  What ſhall I anſwer vnto thoſe, which alledge the decree of the Councell of Conſtance, condemning this propoſition; That the tyrant may and ought to

be killed by any one of his ſubiects whatſoeuer, not onely by open force, but by ſecret practices and fraud.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               There be anſwers enough, for as Vbi ſupra. pag. 62.
                  
                  Mariana ſaith, I doe not find that Pope Martin the fifth approued that Decree, nor Eugenius or his ſucceſſors. But Father Suarez, without wronging the Councell, ſpeaketh thus to the King of England, Where doe you finde in the acts of the Councell of Conſtance, Princes excommunicated by the Pope, or degraded, or this other particle, By his ſubiects, or any other whatſoeuer? Seeing then that the addition of ſuch particles to the propoſition giueth it a diuerſe ſenſe, it is an illuſory inference to attribute ſuch a propoſition vnto that Councell.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               And what ſhall I anſwer if that be obiected vnto me, which Saint Paul ſaith, Let euery perſon be ſubiect to the higher powers?
               
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  That Saint Paul Suarez. vbi ſupra Sect. 20.
                  
                  neuer added, That euery one ſhould be ſubiect to powers excommunicated, or depoſed by the Pope; And that the one cannot be inferred from the other, ſeeing they are diuers things, nay meere contraries; for a depoſed King is no longer an higher power. And as Cardinall Bellarmine Contra Barclayum cap. 3.
                  
                  introduceth the Pope anſwering the people, which would continue in the obedience of the depoſed King; I doe not free thee either from the naturall, or diuine commandement, when I abſolue thee from the tye of obedience: for I doe not permit that thou ſhouldeſt▪ not obey

thy King, which were againſt the diuine Law, but I make him that was thy King not to be ſo any longer: as he that ſetteth a ſeruant at liberty, doth not agree that the ſeruant ſhould not be tyed to obey his Lord, which would be againſt the diuine Law, but he dealeth ſo, that he hath no Lord any longer to obey.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               It followeth then, that Iaques Clement, which killed Henry the third King of France, did not kill his King, but onely a priuate man, ſeeing the Pope had excommunicated him, and expoſed his Kingdome as a prey.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  The conſequence is neceſſary. Alſo 
                  De Reg. lib. 1. cap. 6. pag. 53. &amp; 54.
                  Mariana ſaith, That that young man of a ſimple ſpirit, and weake body, but in whom a greater vertue, Vis maior, had confirmed ſtrength and courage, got himſelfe no ſmall renowne by killing that King. That it was a memorable act: and he accuſeth them of barbarouſneſſe and cruelty, feritatis &amp; ſeuitiae, that thronging in gaue ſo many blowes to a man that was dead before: and he aſſureth, that in his face it might haue beene read, how ioyfull and glad he was, amidſt his blowes and wounds, that with his bloud he had bought the liberty of his Country. For hee had learned of Diuines, with whom he had conſulted, that the: Tyrant might iuſtly be killed.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Is it lawfull to kill the Tyrant with poyſon, or mortiferous hearbs?
            
            
               
               IESVITE.
               We Mariana de Reg lib. 1. cap. 7. per totum.know that it hath beene often done, nor are we to thinke, that any man, which is aſſured to kill him, neglecting a meane ſo fairely offered to diſpatch him, will ſtay the aduice of Diuines, and rather make vſe of ſteele, conſidering the danger that way is leſſe, the hope of impunity more, and the publike ioy much increaſed, the enemy being killed, and the author and architect of the publike liberty preſerued.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               The queſtion is not of that which men would do, but of that which may be iuſtly done.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               There be arguments on eyther ſide: For what difference is there, whether thou killeſt him with poiſon or with ſteele? There be many examples both ancient and moderne of enemies killed this way. Indeed it is a difficult thing to poyſon a Prince, but if a fit occaſion preſent it ſelfe, who is there, ſo ſharp-witted, or clear-ſighted, that can ſhew any difference betweene the one and the other death? I do not deny but that theſe arguments are of great force, howbeit I deny that one may iuſtly kill him with poyſon, whom, we haue ſaid, may be killed by fraud.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Why ſo?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Becauſe Chriſtians haue thought it to be an inhumane thing in preſenting men with poyſon, eyther in meat or drinke, to make them the inſtruments of their owne death, as if one ſhould conſtraine them to ſtab themſelues with their owne hands.
            
            
               
               NOVICE.
               Is there no way to remedy this, and in the meane time to make vſe of poyſon without ſcruple of conſcience?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  There is. And this is the moderation which I would bring vnto it. That he, whom we would haue killed, be not conſtrained to be the inſtrument himſelfe of ſending downe the poiſon into his owne bowels, but that it be applyed outwardly by another, without the help of him that is to be killed. Which may be done when the force of the poyſon is ſo great, that the robe, or ſeate whereupon one ſitteth being infected with it, hath the power to kill him; which I haue read hath beene vſed by ſome Moore Kings towards other Princes.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I find my ſelfe ſufficiently inſtructed herein. But calling to mind that which you decided heretofore, How the Pope may conſtraine Kings by excommunication to puniſh Heretickes and Schiſmaticks, I would pray you to tell me, whether it bee lawfull for a King to permit diuerſity of religions in a Kingdome, and if he hath permitted or tolerated it, whether he ought to continue it?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               The Common-wealth cannot ſubſiſt, where the Citizens doe not agree in religion. In one houſe the Wife doth neuer agree with a concubine, and in a City or Prouince it is not well done to tolerate a falſe religion with the true. For to what end ſerueth this profane liberty

whereby the people are brought to ſhake off all feare? vnleſſe it be, that religion being violated, the order of Prieſthood abaſed, and Churches ſpoyled, this fire gaining farther and farther, commeth at length to conſume euen the very Nobility it ſelfe.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               What muſt be done then?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Princes Mariana lib. 1. cap. 2. de Reg. in
                        ••
                     it.are to be admoniſhed and exhorted, That if they deſire to haue their affaires proſper, they muſt repreſſe hereſie at the beginning, and ſtifle the growing Fury in the cradle, to the end they may not too late repent their paſſed negligence: Let the Prince feare, leſt after the courſe of this life he be not condemned as culpable of for ſaking his charge, and ſo conſequently of a moſt grieuous crime, and infinite miſchiefes; and that he be not very iuſtly puniſhed for neglecting the publike and particular good.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               This being well vrged to Catholike Princes, they whom we hold for Heretickes, cannot thinke themſelues ſafe in a kingdome, whoſe Prince maketh account of ſuch admonitions.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  I will tell thee in few words what father 
                  Theol Schol. part. 2. Tom. 2. Tract. 1. cap. 16▪
                      q. 4.
                  Becan teacheth hereupon. Firſt, that liberty of Religion is altogether vnlawfull and repugnant to the Law of God. Secondly, that it is pernicious to the Common-wealth. Thirdly, that the Prince ought not to command, approue,

or introduce it, but rather by all meanes, if commodiouſly it may be done, impeach and extirpe it. Fourthly, if commodiouſly it cannot be done, but with great preiudice to the Common-wealth, he may tolerate it for a time. Laſtly, that if it be ſo tolerated, and that thereupon an accord be made, he muſt obſerue it.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               Doth not this laſt clauſe make well for thoſe, who haue their Kings perpetuall and irreuocable Edicts for it?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Firſt of all we ſay that this toleration ought not to be but for a time. Secondly, that though in words we giue the lie to ſuch as charge vs for ſaying, that faith is not to be kept with heretickes: yet in effect we haue alwayes reſerued two meanes for Catholike Princes and Common-wealths to break with them: becauſe whatſoeuer they doe, or promiſe, wee ſay, that 
                  Becanus vbi ſupra. q. 6.
                  they doe not grant▪ ſecurity vnto Hereticks, but onely againſt vniuſt violence, alwayes excepting iuſtice, and the execution of right: and by this meane was Iohn Hus and his companion caught: for whatſoeuer ſafe conduct was giuen him againſt vniuſt violence, that made nothing to ſaue him from the fire, which he had iuſtly merited. The other meane is, that we let Princes know, 
                  Becan Ibid.How when there are two Princes, whoſe iudgements and tribunals are different, and that the one is inferior to the other; the inferior, whatſoeuer he promiſeth, cannot hinder the ſuperior from the execution of his iuriſdiction, and therefore he is quit of his promiſe, becauſe he hath done all that he can. Now the Pope being the ſuperior of all Chriſtian
                  
                  Princes principally, he may, notwithſtanding any promiſe of theirs, exerciſe his iuriſdiction in their Kingdomes. And foraſmuch 
                  Suarez Deſen. fid. lib 4▪
                      cap. 22.
                  as Chriſtian kings not onely as touching their perſons, but alſo as touching their Royall power; not onely as men, but alſo as Kings, are vnder his power. It is then in him to direct them in the vſe of their power, and to command, forbid, or hinder them in any thing which he ſhall ſee conuenient for the ſpirituall good of the Church. And ſo, he may amend and correct the ciuill lawes, when they are not agreeable to good manners, make others, or command Princes to reuoke and reforme them. This being, there is no Edict can hold good, when oportunity ſerueth, and that Kings will obey the Pope, as they ought.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               It were an hard thing to draw this obedience from ſom any Kings, that haue ſuch ſeuerall and diuers intereſts, whereby they are gouerned in theſe matters; wherefore me thinkes it were good for that purpoſe, there were one onely King, which might be the Superiour of all the reſt of the whole world, as there is one Pope aboue all Biſhops. For thoſe two agreeing, wee ſhould haue a dainty harmonie, though not very pleaſing to the eares of the Heretickes.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Cardinall Bellarmine hath thus ſpoken of it, 
                  Bellar. de Pont. lib. 1. cap. 9.
                  Me thinkes it were very expedient, if it could be effected without iniuſtice and warres, that all Prouinces of the world were gouerned by one ſoueraigne King in politick matters: eſpecially if this ſoueraigne Monarch had vnder him, not Deputies and Vice-roys, but▪ true princes,

as the Pope hath vnder him▪ true Biſhops. We trauell with all our power to attaine hereunto.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               If this could once be brought about, to whom ſhould we giue our voyces for that vniuerſall Monarchy?
            
            
               IESVITE.
               Nay, now thou toucheſt a ſhrewd point I tell thee, and which is not fit to be diuulged, for feare leſt they, which ſhall ſee themſelues excluded, do mainly oppoſe it; and therefore it muſt be kept ſecret, as a moſt reſerued article. Howbeit for thine owne particular content, read the Preface of our good friend Henry Doerhangk profeſſor of the Spaniſh, Italian, and French Tongues at Cullen, vpon his Spaniſh Grammar, which will teach thee what hope thou art to haue in the matter: Looke here is the Booke printed by Peter Brachel, 1614. Read this clauſe.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               All the people of the earth doe ſee that the Name of God is called vpon by the Spaniards, that is to ſay, that God is in the middeſt of them, and is their protector, which is the reaſon why all men feare and tremble vnder them. And I doubt not, if they continue ſo conſtant and zealous to amplifie and defend true Religion and pietie, to obſerue both diuine and humane Lawes ſo ſtrictly, and to abſtaine from the moſt enormous ſinnes, but that by the bleſsing of God they ſhall poſſeſſe the Monarchy of the whole world, and ſubiect all countries, people and nations vnder the moſt ſweet and glorious yoake of Chriſt, and then ſhall they accompliſh that

which our Lord and Sauiour ſaid, And there ſhall be but one ſhepheard, and but one fold.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               This is a myſtery not to be publiſhed till the euent appeare, for which we labour ſo much. I haue many others beſides to impart vnto thee; but that ſhall be at another time: for now thou haſt enough to employ thy meditation vpon yet a good while, that ſo thou maiſt be made capable of the practice of theſe good inſtructions.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               
                  I thanke you, good Father: now I finde indeede that Father Deza did not mock, when in his Sermon he ſaid, that our Father Ignatius was that Angell, of whom S. Iohn ſpeaketh in the Apocalyps, chap. 10. verſ. 1. And I ſaw a mighty Angell come downe from heauen, clothed with a cloud, and a rainbow vpon his head, and his face was as the Sunne, and his feet as pillars of fire, &amp;c. For, by that which is ſaid, how he was clothed with a cloud, is meant, that he couered his high and generous enterpriſes and deſignes: which alſo repreſenteth the gouernment of our Societie, that manifeſt their effects by concealing the rules and manner thereof. And as in times paſt, a cloud couered the tabernacle of the Congregation, &amp; the glory of the Lord filled the Tabernacle, Exod. 40. 34. So God, who hath built this Tabernacle of ours here vpon earth, to the end ſo holy a thing might be reſpected as it deſerueth, hath ordained that its manner of gouernment ſhould be ſo ſecret, as no man ſhould be able to pierce into it. Lo, that which is meant by, amictum nube. I ſhall
                  
                  neuer forget this dainty Allegory, which will teach me to obſerue ſecrecy, eſpecially in Confeſſions, though it ſhould concerne the liues of Kings, whatſoeuer the Heretickes ſay of that ſame ſentence of Father Binet. How it were better all kings ſhould periſh, then that the ſeale of Confeſsion ſhould be violated. And that which our father 
                  Apol. pro Garneto cap. 13.
                  Eudaemono-Iohannes teacheth, How there can be no miſchiefe ſo great, for the auoyding whereof a Confeſsion is to be diſcloſed. In ſome caſe, ſaith 
                  De paenit. diſp. 33. Sect. 1.
                  Suarez, it is not lawfull, no not for any end, were it euen to preſerue a whole State from a great temporall or ſpirituall miſchiefe. In like manner Cardinall Tolet, The obligation of the ſeale is ſo great, that for no cauſe, no not for to ſaue his owne life, nor for the ſafety of the whole State, may the Confeſſor reueale the confeſsion of the penitent. lib. 3. cap. 16. Inſt. Sacer.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               This I aſſure thee is a very good inſtruction, my Sonne, and of great importance: But becauſe it may happen ſometimes that thou maiſt be called before a Iudge, or a Tyrant, who may demand of thee, whether thou knoweſt any thing of that which thou haſt heard in Confeſſion, in which caſe thou maiſt boldly anſwer without lying, that thou knoweſt nothing, becauſe his demand is vniuſt, and that to ſuch a demand anſwer muſt be made, not to that which is demanded, but to that which ought to bee demanded. And then againe, thou knoweſt it as God, not as man. But if he ſhould preſſe thee further, and demand of thee formally if thou haſt heard it in confeſſion, then thou canſt not ſay thou haſt not heard it, for ſo thou ſhouldeſt lye: neyther art thou

likewiſe to anſwer that thou wilt not tell, nor to reprehend him that makes thee that demand, for thereby the Confeſſion may come to be ſuſpected. What ſhalt thou doe then? Thou muſt deny that thou haſt heard it in confeſſion, but meaning in thy minde, for to tell you, or euer to ſpeake of it: By which meanes thou maiſt eſcape. This is the doctrine of Equiuocations and Reſeruations, whereof another day I will make thee a more ample diſcourſe. Onely I will aduertiſe thee, according to father Vaſq. in 3. part. Thom. Tom. 4. Quaeſt. 93. art. 4.
                  
                  Vaſquez, from whom I haue drawne moſt of that aforeſaid, how thou art not to be abaſhed if thou art told, that which indeed is true, namely that none of the ancient Doctors euer thought of this anſwer, vpon occaſion of ſuch difficulties, and that they all beleeued, that if the matter be denyed, eyther before a Iudge, or any other body, it is a lye: and they neuer found out any other meane but not to anſwer at all: which is no maruell, becauſe in thoſe times this doctrine was not knowne, but is come to light ſince by continuall diſputations.
               
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I will not faile to make vſe of this inſtruction for the concealment of Conſeſſions.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Thou maiſt alſo make vſe of it in other things▪ and teach it vnto others, according as father 
                  Lib 4. de inſt. Sa
                        •
                     er. cap. 21.
                  Tolet decideth it. It is lawfull ſomtimes to vſe Equiuocations, and deceiue him that heareth you; not alwayes, but when the Iudge calleth you to ſweare contrary to iuſtice, then it is lawfull for you to ſweare according to your owne meaning, againſt that of the Iudge: As if he ſhould ask you, did you that? you may anſwer▪ I did it not, meaning

to your ſelf, for to tell you, or at that time, or ſome ſuch thing. And if the husband asketh his wife whether ſhe haue committed adultery, ſhe may anſwer, that ſhe hath not, although ſhe hath, meaning to reueale it vnto him. If any one be conſtrained to ſweare that he will take ſuch a woman to wife, he may ſweare he will, meaning to himſelfe, if afterwards he thinketh good ſo to doe. In like manner he that is in the hands of theeues, or he that is vniuſtly detained, may promiſe mony, but meaning to himſelfe, that he will pay it, if it pleaſeth him; or promiſe to returne againe if he be let goe, and yet not performe though he haue ſworne it, if firſt hee haue vſed equiuocation.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I will endeuor to make a commodious vſe of theſe good precepts, and as a precious treaſure will keepe what you haue taught me, attending till you thinke me capable of the reſt, at ſuch time as you ſhall ſee how I haue profited in this, wherein you haue inſtructed me already, vpon which I will goe and meditate very diligently.
            
            
               IESVITE.
               
                  Doe ſo, and giuing vp thy ſelfe wholly to Father Ignatius, deuoutly pray him, 
                  Gaſpar Sanc. Epiſt. dedic▪ ad Ignat. Loyol. Comment. in Eſayam.That being the leaſt of his, and the moſt vnworthy of thoſe which are the companions of Ieſus in this religious warfare, he wil be pleaſed to imbrace, entertaine, and aſsiſt thee, &amp; that alſo he will often commend thee to Ieſus thy head, &amp; ſtandardbearer, vnder whoſe Colours thou fighteſt, and with whō he hath continuall familiarity &amp; communication.
            
            
               NOVICE.
               I humbly thanke you for this aduertiſement, good Father, and ſo God be with you.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

