
   
      
         
            Eglogs epytaphes, and sonettes. Newly written by Barnabe Googe: 1563. 15. Marche
            Googe, Barnabe, 1540-1594.
         
         
            
               1563
            
         
         Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01909
            STC 12048
            ESTC S106441
            99842157
            99842157
            6787
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01909)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6787)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 344:05)
         
         
            
               
                  Eglogs epytaphes, and sonettes. Newly written by Barnabe Googe: 1563. 15. Marche
                  Googe, Barnabe, 1540-1594.
                  Blundeston, Laurence.
               
               [178] p. : ill.  
               
                  By Thomas Colwell, for Raffe Newbery, dwelyng in Fleetstrete a litle aboue the Conduit in the late shop of Thomas Bartelet,
                  Imprynted at London :
                  [1563]
               
               
                  Edited by Laurence Blundeston, whose name appears in the heading of the preface.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A B⁴; ² A-B C (C8+"c3") D⁴ E-K.
                  With a final colophon and errata leaf.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-08
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2005-10
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Eglogs Epytaphes, and Sonettes. Newly written by Barnabe Googe: 1563. 15. Marche.
            ¶Imprynted at London, by Thomas Colwell, for Raffe Newbery, dwelyng in Fleet ſtrete a litle aboue the Conduit in the late ſhop of Thomas Bartelet.
         
         
            
            
            ¶ Alexander Neuyll.
            THe Moūtaines hie the bluſtryng wīds The fluds: ye Rocks wtſtād
            The Cities ſtrong, the Cānons ſhot, &amp; threatning Cheiftains hād.
            The Caſtels houge by long beſeyge, and dredfull battrye brooke,
            Bothe fyre, &amp; flames, and thundryng
                  •
                thumps and euery deadly ſtroke,
            With feruent broylyng furious rage, doth beate, and 
                  •
               ryue to ground
            The long defenced wals by force, and throughly them confound.
            Ryght ſo thy Muſe (Oh worthy Googe.) thy pleaſaunt frain
                  •
               d ſtyle.
            Diſcouerd lyes to momiſh Mouthes Reprochfull tongs and vyle
            Diffaming minds. Regard them not. preas thou for hygher prayſe.
            Submit thy ſelfe to perſons graue, whoſe Iudgement ryght alwayes
            
               By Reaſon rulde doth ryghtly iudge, whom Fancies none can charme,
            Which in the moſt Incōſtant brains, are chyefly wont to ſwarme.
            Whom no deſyre of fylthy gayne, whom lucre none can moue
            From truth to ſtray. Such mē eſteam, Such ſuch embrace and loue.
            On ſuch men ſtay thy tender years, ſuch Patrons ſeeke to chuſe.
            Which taught by Tyme, &amp; practiſde Proofe vprighteſt iudgement vſe.
            But as for thoſe Crabſnowted beſtes thoſe ragyng feends of Hell.
            Whoſe vile, malicious, hatefull mindes, wt boylyng Rancour ſwell.
            Which puft with Pryde, enflamd wt ſpight, &amp; drownd in deape diſdain:
            Lyke Momus monſtrous broode outright euen of a ielows Brayn
            With curious, cāckard, carping mouthes, moſt famous dedes diffame,
            Defacing thoſe whoſe labours great, Deſerue immortall name.
            
               Such crabfaced, cākerd, carliſh chuffs within whoſe hatefull breſtes,
            Suche Malice bydes, ſuche Rancour broyles, ſuch endles Enuy reſts
            Eſteame thou not. No preiudice to th
                  •
               e: nor yet opreſt,
            Thy famous wrytyngs are by them. Thou lyueſt and euer ſhalt.
            Not all the ſlaundryng tonges aliue, may purchaſe blame or fault
            Vnto to thy name (O worthy Goog
                     •
                  .) No tyme, no fyrye flame
            Not all the furies frettyng Force, Thy doynges may dyffame.
            Let them in broyle of burning ſpight, continuall Toyle ſuſtayne
            Let thē fele ſcourging Plags of mind Let euer duryng payne,
            Spred through their poiſoned vaines. Let Care wt payſe of dedly waight:
            Oppreſſe theyr vyle infected Harts, with ſtynging Malyce fraight.
            Let them deſtroy them ſelvs in Time. In Rancour let them boyle.
            
               Let mortall hate, let pynching gryefe, let flamyng torments broyle,
            Within theyr greuous vexed breſts, for euermore to dwell
            Let them fele Enuies curſed force. (conſumyng Feend of Hell.)
            Defye them all. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and ſquynteyd Monſters ryght
            They are. In fyne leue Sow to ſwill and Chuff to canckerd Spyght.
            But thou procede in vertuous dedes, and as thou haſte begon,
            Go forward ſtyll to aduaūce thy fame Lyfes Race halfe ryghtly ron
            Farre eaſyer tis for to obtain, the Type of true Renowne.
            Like Labours haue ben recompenſt with an immortall Crowne.
            By this doth famouſe Chaucer lyue, by this a thouſande moore
            Of later yeares. By this alone the olde renowmed Stoore
            Of Auncient Poets lyue. By this theyr Praiſe aloft doth mownt.
            
               Vnto the Skyes: and equall is with Stars aboue. Accownt
            Thy ſelfe then worthy of the lyke, yf that thou doſte proceade
            By famous deds thy Fame to enhaūce and name abroade to ſpreade.
            With Courage ſtout thā through the thikſt thou needſt not for to feare·
            Not he that ſayth, but he that doth, ought Gloryes Garlande weare.
            Thus ſhalt yu ſtyll augment thy name, and wyn the hyghe Renowne,
            And preſent Prayſe, in preſent Lyfe, and after Death a Crowne
            Of Honour, that for euer laſts. immortall Fame in fyne.
            To whoſe reward, thy faithfull Frend doth wholly the reſygne.
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            
            
               
                  B. Googe.
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶To the ryght worſhipfull M. William Louelace, Eſquier, Reader of Grayes Inne: (Barnabe Googe) wyſſheth health.
            
               HOwe lothe I haue ben, beyng of long tyme earneſtlye requyred, to ſuffer theſe tryfles of mine to cōe to light: It is not vnknowen to a greate nombre of my famyliar acquaintaunce. Who both dayly &amp; hourely moued me therunto, and lytell of long tyme preuayled therin. For I both conſydered and wayed with my ſelfe, the groſenes of my Style: whiche thus cōmytted to the gaſynge

ſhewe of euery eye ſhuld forth with diſcloſe ye manifeſt foly of the Writer, and alſo I feared and miſtruſted the diſdaynfull myndes of a nombre both ſcornefull and carpynge Correctours, whoſe Heades are euer buſyed in tauntyng Iudgementes. Leaſt they ſhuld otherwyſe interprete my doyngs than in deade I meant them. Theſe two ſo great miſchiefes vtterly diſwaded me from the folowynge of my frendes perſwaſions, and wylled me rather to condem thē to continuall darkenes, wherby no Inconuenience could happen: than to endaunger my ſelfe in gyuynge them to lyght, to the diſdaynfull doome of any offended mynde. Notwithſtandynge all the dylygence that I


coulde vſe in the Suppreſſion therof coulde not ſuffiſe for I my ſelfe beyng at that tyme oute of the Realme, lytell fearynge any ſuche thynge to happen. A verye Frende of myne, bearynge as it ſemed better wyll to my doynges than reſpectyng the hazarde of my name, commytted them all togyther vnpolyſhed to the handes of the Prynter. In whoſe handes durynge his abſence from the Cytie, tyll his returne of late they remayned. At whiche tyme, he declared the matter wholly vnto me: ſhewynge me, that beynge ſo farre paſt, &amp; Paper prouyded for the Impreſſion therof: It coulde not withoute great hynderaunce of the poore Printer

be nowe reuoked. His ſodayne tale made me at ye fyrſt, vtterly amazed, and dou
                  •
               ting a great while, what was beſt to be done: at the lengthe agreyng both with Neceſſytie and his Counſell, I ſayde with Martiall. I
                     •
                  am edpo
                     ••
                  ras tu
                     ••
                  oreſſe domi. And calling to mynde to whom I myght chieflye cōmyt the fruytes of my ſmiling muſe: ſodaynly was caſt before my eyes the perfect vewe of your frendly mynd (gentle Maiſter Louelace) Vnto whō for the nombred heapes of ſundrye Frendſhyps, accoūtynge my ſelfe as boūde, I haue thought beſt to gyue them, (not doubtyng) but that they ſhalbe as well taken, as I do p
                  •
               eſently meane them.
            Deſyry
                  ••
               e 
                  〈◊〉
                herein, as all ſuche as ſhall 
                  〈◊〉
                them eſpeciallye to

beare with the vnpleaſaunt forme of my to haſtely fynyſhed Dreame, the greater part wherof with lytle aduyſe I lately ended, bycauſe the beginnyng of it, as a ſenſeles 
                  •
               ead ſeparated frō the body was gyuen with the reſt to be prynted. And thus deſyrynge but for recompence the frendly receyuyng of my ſlender Gyfte, I ende: wyſhyng vnto you good Mayſter Louelace in this life the happye enioyeng of proſperous yeares: and hereafter the bleſſed eſtate of neuer ceaſynge Ioye.
            
               ¶Yours aſſuredly Barnabe Googe.
               
            
         
         
            
            
               
                  Daphnes. Amintas.
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶ L. Blundeſton to the Reader.
            TO creepe into thy fauoure (good Reader) with a longe paynted Preamble in prayſe of this Auctor, I account it as vain. The Sōne Beames gyues light ſufficient. To moue thy Affection with fore promyſed pleaſure in reading the voh
                  •
               me, I think it as Booteles. Gold is of ſelf force and vertue to draw the deſire. But wt flowers of Rethorique fyrſt to delyght the, or wt Pythy Reaſons to wynne thy good wyll and frendlye Reporte for this my attempte: yf ſuche tropes &amp; ſignes were flowing in me to perſwade wel thy fauour, or ſo muche Diſcreſcion wantynge

in the to necglecte my good meanyng, I wold eyther enforce my ſelf to vse a better kynde of perſwaſion or els withdrawe my good wyll from the Sentence of ſo carpynge and ſlender a Iudgement: but as I haue felte no 
                  •
               luddes of the one, ſo lykewyſe I ſee no Ebbes of the other, that if I weare no more barraygne of the fyrſte, then fearefull of the laſte: I woulde be then no more ſparynge to horde vp my Treaſure from the: then I truſt to fynde the thankfull now in takyng this Preſent frō me, which not onely to ſhewe my good wyll, (as my Preface diſcourſeth more largely) by preſeruynge the worthy Fame, and Memorye of my deare frende M. Googe in his abſence

I haue preſumed more bouldely to hazard ye prynting heareof, though this maye ſuffyce to excuſe well my enterpryſe, but alſo to ſtyrre vp thy Pleaſure and further thy proffit by readyng theſe his workes, whiche here I haue Puplyſhed: openly vnto thee. And ſo (beyng vnſtored my ſelffe) I ſeake to ſateſfie thy learned or willyng deſyre with other mens trauaeiles. But wheare the power fayleth the will may ſuffyce, the gyuer, not the gyft is to be regarded: preferre Colonus Radyſhe roote before the Courtiers barbed horſe.
            Accept my goodwyll and way not the valew, ſo ſhalt thou bynd me if power (as it is vnlykely, maye aunſwere hearafter my meanynge, to gratefie thee with the whole fruits

of myne owne indeuour and ſo ſhalt thou encourage others to make the partaker of the like or farre greater Iewels who yet doubtyng thy vnthankefull receyte nigardly keape them to their own vſe &amp; priuat commoditie. whear as beynge aſſured of the contrarye by thy frendly report of other mens trauayles, they coulde parhappes be eaſely entreated more frely to lend them abroad to thy greater auayle and furtherraunce. Thus therfore to thy good or euill taking I put foorth this paterne for others to follow in weightyer matters or els to beware by other mens harms, in keaping their names vnreproued by ſylence.
            
               ¶From my Chambre, the .xxvii. of Maye. 1562.
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶The Preface of L. Blundeſton.
            
               Th
                     •
                   Sen
                     •
                  es dull of my appailed muſ
                     •
                  
               
               Foreweryed with the trauayle of my brayne
               
                  
                     •
                  n ſtannyng of the argued Bookes di
                     ••
                  uſe,
               And darke for me the glimeryng ſyght 
                     •
                  o 
                     •
                  uyne,
               Deb
                     •••
                  e 
                     •
                  t long what excerſyce to vſe,
               To fyle the edgeles partes of Wyt agayn
                     •
                  
               
               To clenſe the 
                     ••
                  eade from ſleapy humours ſlyme.
               To rouſe the Hart from drowſye Dreames ī 
                  
                     •
                  ime
            
            
               The mind deſyres to brek frō thoughtful denne
               And time requyres the painted felds to vewe.
               The Eye procures to pleaſe the Fancie then
               With f
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  dish ſights of diuers colours newe.
               The ſmelling likes the ſauour ſwete of them.
               The Eare agrees the pleaſaunt laye anewe
               Of Byrds to here. Thus theſe do all contryue,
               With this diſporte the Spirits to reuyue.
            
            
               But Fancie then, by ſerche of ſelfe denyſe,
               Renouncyng thus to ſpende the pleaſaunt Maye
               So vainly out with ſport of fruteles Pryce
               Found out at length, this practyſe for thy playe,
               
                  To penne in Verſe, the toy
                     •
                  s of her de
                     •
                  iſ
                     •
                  ,
               To pas this tyme of Pentecoſte awaye
               Whoſe ydle dayes ſhe w
                     •
                  ld u
                     •
                  e thus to ſpende?
               And publiſh forth her doings in the ende.
            
            
               Quod Reaſon no, (and brake her tale begon,
               Wilt thou preſume, lyk
                     •
                   Bayarde blynd to preſſe,
               Into the throng, of all the lookers on
               Whoſe vewyng eyes, will wey thy wiſdom 
                     •
                  eſſe.
               To ſe the threde of all thy work
                     •
                  s yll ſpon
               Drawen out at length, vnto the comon g
                     •
                  ſſe,
               Then i
                     •
                   thou ſhuldſt kepe to thy ſelfe thy clewe
               Where none thy works beſydes thy ſelf may vew
            
            
               With this roſe vp, from out her Seate behynde,
               Dame Memorye, and Reaſon thus beſought.
               Since Lady chiefe of vs thou art aſſygnde
               To rule and temper all my ſecrete thought
               And to reſtrane affections Fancie blynde,
               Let me entreate if I may perce the ought,
               For to preſent a Solace very fytte
               Our Sences dull with chaunged Muſe to whet.
            
            
               Lo here the Eye a Paper buntche doth ſe
               Of fyled worke of Googes flowing Heade,
               Lefte here behynde, when hence he paſt from me,
               In all the ſtormes that Winter blaſtes beſpreade
               Through ſwellyng Seas &amp; loftye moūtains hye
               Of Pyrenet the pathes vnknowen to treade.
               
                  Whoſe great good wyll I kepe, and in his plate
               His Verſes craue to repreſent his face.
            
            
               Vnfolde the truſſe therfore and yf the Muſe
               Be ſ
                     •
                  tted ſo with this graue Study paſt
               In ſo ſhort ſpace, or if we ſeke to chuſe
               To prynt our actes in ſafetie at the laſt
               Ceaſe of a whyle this Labor and peruſe
               Theſe Papers left of ſuche delyghting taſte
               And put in prynt theſe workes of worthy Skyll
               So ſhall we ſhowe the fruytes, of our good wyll.
            
            
               This Fancie lykte, imagynyng aryght
               Of her owne Ioye in hearyng of his Verſe
               And pleaſaunt Style, moſt pythyly endyght
               whoſe Fame forth blowen, his deds could wel reherſe
               But for to paynt my name in open ſight
               with others Stuffe, this wold ſhe fayne reuerſe,
               And thinkes I ſhould in others Plumes ſo ſhow
               My ſelfe, to be a ſeconde Eſops Crowe.
            
            
               But after when the Eye had vewed trhe Lyne.
               That Googe had pend and left behynde with me,
               when Memorye could all the e
                     •
                  fect refygne,
               To Reaſons Skyll. to weye them as they lye.
               with long reherſe of tryed Fayth by tyme
               Then Fancie ſoone her Pryde, began to plye
               And all receyued muche pleaſure to the Mynde
               More profytte farre then Fancye had aſſygnde.
            
            
               
               And Fancie thus her ſelfe with bluſhyng face,
               Condemned by Dame Reaſons dome deuyne
               To ſe thalluryng Style the cumly grace,
               The ſappye Sence of this his paſſyng Ryme,
               So farre ſurmountynge her Inuention baſe,
               And hearyng of his frendlynes in ſyne
               whiche Memorye her Storehouſe held full faſt
                     •
                  
               
               Allowed well theyr Iudgements at the laſte.
            
            
               Since euerye Sence did wonted ſtrength reune,
               The Blud congeld, recourſed to his place
               The wyts benomd brought to theyr propre quue
               The Hart oppreſt with old delighting grace,
               Vnburdend nowe and puft with pleaſure newe
               By takyng of this Booke the vewyng gaſe
               They all at ons Good wyll nowe calde dyon,
               To wreſt her ſelfe to quyght theſe works ad on.
            
            
               Thus puſhte I forth ſtrayghte to the Printet
                     •
                   hande
               Theſe Eglogs, Souets, Epytaphes of men
               Vnto the Readers Eyes for to be ſkande,
               with Prayſes ſuche as is due vnto them
               who abſent nowe theyr Mayſter maye cōmende,
               And feade his Fame what ſoeuer f
                     •
                  yleth him,
               Gyue Googe therfore his owne deſerued Fame,
               Giue Blundeſton leaue to wyſh wel to his nam
                     ••
                  
               
            
            ¶Finis.
         
      
      
         
            
            Egloga prima.
            Daphnes. Amintas.
            SYth Phebus now begins to flame,
            O frende Amintas deare:
            And placed hath his gorgeous globe in midſte of all the Spheare
            And frō yt place doth caſt his Beames; where (they that fratres defyne)
            Lyes poynt (doo ſaye) that termed is, ryght Equinoctial lyne.
            wheras the Rain doth cauſe to ſpring, eche herbe and floure in fyelde
            A
                  •
               d forceth ground (y• ſpoyld of grene Old lye,) newe grene to yelde.
            Let ſhepherds vs yelde alſo tales, as beſt becōmes the tyme:
            Suche tales as Winter ſtormes haue ſtayde in countrey Phets Ryme.
            Begyn to ſynge Amintas thou, for why? thy wyt is beſt:
            And many a laged ſawe lies hyd within thine aged breſt.
            
               Ofte haue I heard, of Shephards old, thy fame reported true,
            No Herdman liues: but knowes the praiſe, to olde Amintas due:
            B
                  •
               gyn therfore, and I gyue care, for talke doth me delyght,
            Go Boye: go dryue the Beaſts to fede whyle he his mynde reſyght.
            
               
                  Amin.
               Thy prayſes Da
                     ••
                  nes are to great, and more for me than meete:
            Nor euer I, ſuche ſaged ſawes, coulde ſynge in Verſes ſweete.
            And now, to talke of ſpring time tales my heares to hoare, do growe
            Suche tales as theſe, I tolde in, tyme, when youthfull yeares dyd flowe.
            But ſynce, I can not the denye, thy Fathers loue doth bynde:
            In ſymple Songe I wyll adreſſe my ſelfe, to ſhowe my mynde.
            Longe haſt thou Daphnes me requyred the ſtate of Loue to tell,
            For in my youth, I knewe the force, and paſſions all, full well.
            
               Nowe Loue therfore I wyll defyne and what it is declare,
            which way poore ſouls it doth entrap and howe it them doth ſnare.
            My Boie, remoue my beaſts frō hens and dryue them farther downe,
            Vpon the Hylles, let them go feade, that ioyne to yender towne,
            O Cupyde kynge of fyerye Loue, ayde thou my ſyngynge Verſe,
            And teache me heare the cauſe &amp; caſe, Of Louers to reherſe,
            Direct my tong, in trothe to treade, with Furye fyll my brayne,
            That I may able be to tell, the cauſe of Louers payne.
            Opinions diuers coulde I ſhowe, but chiefeſt of them all,
            I wyll declare: and for the reſt, with ſilence leaue I ſhall.
            A ſeruent Humour, (ſome do iudge) within the Head doth lye,
            Whiche yſſuyng forth with poyſoned beames doth rou frō eye to eye:
            
               And taking place abrode in heads, a whyle doth fyrmely reſt:
            Till Phrenſie framde in Fancie fond▪ diſcends from hed, to breſt.
            
               
                  Plato.
               And poiſon ſtrong, frō eies outdrawn do
                  •
               h perce the wretched harte,
            And all infectes the bloud aboute, and boyles in euery parte:
            Thus: whē the beames, infected hath, the wofull Louers blud:
            Then Sences al, do ſtrayght decaye, oppreſt with Furyes flud.
            Then Lybertie withdrawes her ſelf, and Bondage beares the ſwaye,
            Affection blynd then leades the hart, and Wyt, is wownde awaye.
            O Daphn
                     •
                  s then, the paines appeare, and tormentes all of hell.
            Then ſekes, the ſelye wounded ſoule, the flames for to expell.
            But all to late, alas he ſtryues, for Fancie beares the ſtroke
            And he, muſt toyle (no helpe there is) in ſlauyſſhe ſeruyle yoke.
            
               His blud corrupted all within, doth boyle in euery vayne,
            Than ſekes he howe to ſewe for ſalue that maye redreſſe his payne.
            And when the face, he doth beholde by whiche he ſhulde haue ayde,
            And ſees no helpe, thē lookes he long, a
                  •
               d trembleth all afrayde.
            And muſeth at the framed ſhape, that hath his lyfe in handes:
            Nowe faſt he flies, aboute the flames, nowe ſtyll amaſed ſtandes:
            Yet Hope relieues, his hurtful Heate and Wyll doth Payne make lyght,
            And al the griefes, that then he feeles doth Preſence ſtyll requyght.
            But when the Lyght abſented is, and Beames in hart remayne,
            Then flames the Fyre freſh agayne, and newe begyns his Payne.
            Then longe he lookes, his loſſe to ſe, then ſobbes, and ſyghes abounde,
            Then mourneth he, to mys the marke that erſt to ſoone he founde.
            
               Then ſhadefull places oute he lookes, and all alone he lyues,
            Erylynge Ioye, and myrth from him, hymſelfe to waylynge gyues,
            And ſtyll his minde theron doth muſe and ſtyll, therof he prates,
            O Daphnes here I ſwere to the, no griefe to Louers ſtate.
            Yf he but ones beholde the place, where he was wont to mete,
            The pleaſaunt forme yt hym enflamd, and ioyfull Countnaunce ſwete.
            The place (a wonderous thing I tell) his gryefe augmenteth newe,
            Yet ſtyll he ſekes the place to ſe, that moſte he ſhulde eſc
                  •
               ewe.
            Yf but the name rehearſed be, (a thynge more ſtraunge to heare)
            Then Colour cōmes and goes in haſt then quaketh he for feare,
            The verye name, hath ſuche a force, that it can daſe the mynde,
            And make the man amaſde to ſtande, what force hath Loue to bynde?
            
               Affection none to this is lyke, it doth ſurmownt them all,
            Of grei
                  •
               fes, the greateſt greif no doubt is to be Venus thrall,
            And therfore, Daphnes nowe beware, for thou art yonge, and fre,
            Take heade of vewynge faces longe, for loſſe of Lybertye,
            I ſhall not nede (I thynke) to byd the, to deteſt the Cryme,
            Of wycked loue, that Ioue did vſe, In Ganimedes tyme,
                  Iupiter.
               
            
            For rather wolde I (thoo it be muche) that thou ſhuldeſt ſeake the fyre,
            Of lawfull Loue, that I haue tolde, than burne wyth ſuche deſyre,
            And thus an end, I weryed am, my wynde is olde, and faynt,
            Suche matters I, do leaue to ſuche, as finer farre can paint,
            Fetche in the Gote: that goes aſtraye, and dryue hym to the folde,
            My yeares be great I wyl be gone, for ſpryngtyme nyghts be colde.
            
               
               
                  Daphnes
               Great thankes to the, for this thy tale Amintas here I gyue:
            But neuer can I make amendes to the whilſte I do lyue.
            Yet for thy paynes (no recompenc
                  •
               ) a ſmall rewarde haue here.
            A whiſtle framed longe ago, wherwith my father deare
            His ioyfull beaſts, was wont to kepe. No Pype for tune ſo ſwete
            Might ſhepharde euer yet po
                  •
               ſes. (a thynge for the full mete.)
            Finis Eglogae primoe.
         
         
            Egloga ſecunda.
            Dametas.
            MY beaſts, go fede vpon ye plaine, and let your herdman lye,
            Thou ſeeſt her mind, &amp; fearſt yu nowe, Dametas for to dye?
            
               Why ſtayeſt yu thus? why doſte yu ſtay
                  •
                thy lyfe to longe doth laſte:
            Accounte this flud, thy fatall graue, ſyth time of hope is paſte.
            What meanſt thou thus to linger on? thy life wolde fayne departe,
            Alas: the wounde doth feſter ſtyll, of curſed Cupids darte.
            No ſalue but this, can helpe thy ſore, no thynge can moue her minde
            She hath decreed, that thou ſhalt dye, no helpe there is to finde.
            Nowe ſyth there is, no other helpe, nor ought but this to try
                  •
               ,
            Thou ſeeſt her mind: why fearſte thou than? Dametas for to dye.
            Long haſt thou ſerued, &amp; ſerued true, but all alas, in vayne,
            For ſhe thy ſeruyce, nought eſtemes, but deales the griefe for gayne.
            For thy good wyll, (a gay rewarde) Diſdayne, for Loue ſhe gyues,
            Thou loueſt her while thy life doth laſt, ſhe hates the, wile ſhe liues.
            
               Thou flamſte, when as yu ſeeſt her face with Heate of hye deſyre,
            She flames agayne, but how? (alas) with depe diſdaynfull Ite.
            The greateſt pleaſure is to the, to ſe her voyde of Payne,
            The greatest gryefe to her agayne, to ſe thy Health remayne.
            Thou couetſte euer her to fynde, ſhe ſekes from the to flye,
            Thou ſeeſt her mynd, why fearſt thou than? Dametas for to dye?
            Doſte thou accounte it beſt to kepe, thy lyfe in ſorowes ſtyll?
            Or thynkſte thou beſt it now to lyue, Contrarye to her wyll?
            Thynkſte thou thy lyfe for to retaine? when ſhe is not content,
            Canſte thou addicte: thy ſelfe to lyue? and ſhe to murder bent.
            Doſte thou entende agayne, to ſewe for mercye at her handes?
            As ſoone thou mayſt go plow ye rocks, and reape vpon the Sandes.
            
               Draw nere O mighty Herd of beaſts ſyth no man els is bye,
            Your Herdman longe that hathe you kept, Dametas nowe muſt dye.
            Reſolue your Brutiſſhe eies to teares and all togyther crye,
            Bewayle the wofull ende of Loue, Dametas nowe muſt dye.
            My pleaſaunt Songs, nowe ſhall you here no more on Mountaines hye,
            I leaue you all, I muſt be gone. Dametas nowe muſt dye:
            To Titirus I you reſyne, in Paſture good to lye,
            For Titirus ſhall kepe you thoughe, Dametas nowe muſt dye.
            O curſed Cauſe, that hath me ſlayne, My trothe alas to trye,
            O Shephardes all, be Wytneſſes, Dametas here doth dye.
            Finis Eglogae ſecundoe.
         
         
            
            Egloga tertia.
            Menalcas. Coridon.
            A Pleaſaunt wether Coridon, and lytte to kepe the fyelde,
            This moone hath brought▪ hearſt yu the birds what ioyful tunes they yeld,
            Loe: how the luſtie lambes do courſe, whom ſpring time heate doth pricke
            Beholde againe, the aged Yewes, with bouncinge leapes do kicke,
            Amonſt thē all, what ayles thy rāme, to halte ſo muche behynde,
            Some ſore miſchaūce, hath him be 
                  •
               aln or els ſome griefe of minde,
            For wonte he was, of ſtomacke ſtoute and courage hye to be,
            And looked proude, amongſt ye flocke, and none ſo ſtoute as he.
            
               
                  Cor.
               A great miſhap, and griefe of mynde, is him be falne of late,
            Which cauſeth him, againſt his wyll, to loſe his olde eſtate.
            
               A luſtie flocke hath Titirus, that him Dametas gaue,
            
               Dametas he, that Martir died, whoſe ſoule the heaues haue,
            And in this flocke, full many Yewes of pleaſaunte forme do goe,
            with thē a mighty Rāme doth ronne, that workes all Woers woe.
            My Rāme, whē he the pleaſaūt dames had vewed rounde aboute,
            Choſe groūde of battayle, with his foe and thought to fyght it oute.
            But all to weake, (alas) he was, althoughe his harte was good,
            For when his enemye him espied, he rāne with cruell moode.
            And with his croked weapon ſmote, him ſore vpon the ſyde,
            A blowe of force, that ſtayde not there but to the legges dyd glyde.
            And almoſte laamd the woer quyte. (ſuche happes in loue there be:)
            This is the cauſe, of all his griefe and waylynge that you ſe.
            
               
               
                  Men.
               Well Coridon let hym go halte, and let vs both go lye,
            In yonder buſſhe of Iuniper, the Beaſts ſhall fede hereby.
            A pleaſaunt place here is to talke: good Coridon begyn,
            And let vs knowe the Townes eſtate, that thou remaynest in.
            
               
                  Cor.
               The Townes eſtate? Menalcas oh thou makſte my harte to grone,
            For Vice hath euery place poſſeſſe, and Vertue thence is flowne.
            Pryde beares her ſelfe, as Goddeſſe chiefe and boaſtes aboue ye Skye,
            And Lowlynes an abiecte lyes, with Gentlenes her bye,
            Wyt is not ioynde with Symplenes, as ſhe was wont to be,
            But ſekes the ayde of Arrogance, and craftye Polycie.
            Nobylitie begyns to fade, and Carters vp do ſprynge,
            Then whiche, no greater plague can hap, nor more pernicious thynge.
            
               
               Menalcas I haue knowen my ſelfe, within this thyrtye yeare,
            Of Lordes and Auncient Gentelmen a hundreth dwellynge theare,
            Of whom we Shephardes had reliefe ſuche Gentlenes of mynde,
            Was placed in theyr noble Hartes, as none is nowe to fynde.
            But Hawtynes and proude Diſdayne hath nowe the chiefe Eſtate,
            For ſyr Iohn Straw, &amp; ſyr Iohn Cur, wyll not degenerate.
            And yet, they dare account thē ſelues to be of Noble bludde.
            But Fiſſhe bred vp, in durtye Pooles, wyll euer ſtynke of mudde.
            I promyſſe the Menalcas here, I wolde not them enuye.
            Yf any ſpot of Gentlenes, in them I myght eſpye.
            For yf theyr Natures gentell be, thoughe byrth be neuer ſo baſe,
            Of Gentelmen (for mete it is) they ought haue name and place:
            
               But whē by byrth, they baſe are bred, and churliſſhe harte retaine,
            Though place of gentlem
                  •
               n thei haue yet churles they do remayne.
            A prouerbe olde, hath ofte ben hard
                  •
                and nowe full true is tryed:
            An Ape, wyll euer be an Ape, thoughe purple garments hyde.
            For ſeldom, wyll the maſtye courſe, the Hare or els the Deare:
            But ſtyll, accordynge to his kynde. wyll holde, the hogge by theare.
            Vnfitte are dunghill knights to ſerue the towne, with Speare in fielde:
            Nor ſtrange it ſemes, (a ſudain Chop) to leape from whyp, to ſhielde.
            The chiefeſt man, in all our towne, that beares the greateſt ſwaye,
            Is Coridon no kynne to me, a Neteherd thother daye
            This Coridon come from the Carte, In honour chiefe doth ſytte,
            And gouernes vs: becauſe he hath, a Crabbed, Clowniſh wytte.
            
               Nowe ſe the Churlyſh Crueltye, that in hys harte remayns.
            The ſelye Sheape y• Shephards good, haue foſterd vp wyth Paynes,
            And browght awaye, from Stynkyng dales on pleaſant Hylles to feade:
            O Cruell Clowniſh Coridon, O curſed Carliſh Seade:
            The ſimple Shepe, conſtrayned he, theyr Paſture ſwete to leaue,
            And to theyr old corrupted Graſſe. enforceth them to cleaue.
            Such Shepe, as wold not them obaye but in theyr Paſture byde.
            with (cruell flames,) they did cōſume and vex on euery ſyde.
            And wt the ſhepe, y• Shephardes good, (O hatefull Hounds of Hell,)
            They did torment. and dryue thē out, in Places farre to dwell.
            There dyed Daphnes for his Shepe, the chiefeſt of them all.
            And fayre Alexis flamde in Fyre, who neuer peryſſhe ſhall.
            
               O Shephards wayle, for Daphnes deth, Alexis hap lament,
            And curs the force of cruell hartes, that them to death haue ſent.
            I, ſynce I ſawe ſuche ſynfull ſyghts, dyd neuer lyke the Towne,
            But thought it beſt to take my ſheepe, and dwell vpon the downe.
            Wheras I lyue, a pleaſaunt lyfe, and free from cruell handes,
            I wolde not leaue, the pleſaunt fyelde for all the Townyſh Landes.
            For ſyth that Pryde, is placed thus, and Vice ſet vp ſo hye:
            And Crueltie doth rage ſo ſore, and men lyue all awrye:
            Thynkſte yu? y• God, wil long forbere, his ſcourge, and plague to ſende?
            To ſuche as hym do ſtyll deſpyſe and neuer ſeke to mende?
            Let them be ſure he wyll reuenge. when they thynke leaſte vpon.
            But looke a ſtormy ſhowre doth ryſe, whiche wyll fall heare anone.
            
               
               Menalcas beſt we nowe departe, my Cottage vs ſhall keepe,
            For there is rowme for the, and me, and eke for all our ſheepe:
            Som Cheſtnuts haue I there in ſtore with Cheeſe and pleaſaunt whaye,
            God ſends me Vittayles for my nede, and I ſynge Care awaye.
            ¶Finis Egloge tertie.
         
         
            Egloga quarta.
            Melibeus Palemon.
            O God, that guyds ye golden Globe, wher ſhinyng ſhapes do dwel
            O thou ye throweſt the thūder thumps from Heauens hye, to Hell,
            what wonders workes thy worthynes what meruayles doſte thou frame?
            What ſecrete ſyghts be Subiect ſene vnto thy holy name?
            A ſymple Shepharde ſlayne of late, by foolyſſhe force of Loue,
            
               That had not Grace ſuch fancies fond and Flames for to remoue,
            Appeared late, before myne eies, (Alas I feare to ſpeake,)
            Not as he here was wont to lyue, whyle Gryefe hym none did breake.
            But all in Blacke, he clothed came an vgly ſyght to ſe:
            As they that for theyr due Deſartes. with Paynes tormented be,
            My ſhepe for feare amaſed ran, and fled from Hyll to Dale,
            And I alone remayned there, with countenaunce wan and pale.
            O Lorde (quoth I,) what meanes this thyng is this Alexis ſpryght?
            Or is it Daphnes ſoule that ſhowes? to me this dredfull ſyght.
            Or comes ſome Feend of Hell abrode? with feare men to torment?
            
               Megera this? or 
                  
                     •
                  iſiphon? Or is Alecto ſent?
            what ſoeuer thou art, yt thus doſt com! Ghooſt, Hagge, or Fende of Hell:
            
               I the cōmaunde by hym that lyues, thy name and caſe to tell.
            With this, a ſtynkyng ſmoke I ſawe, from out his mouth to flye,
            And wt that ſame, his voyce did ſound. None of them all am I.
            But ons thy frende (O oldibe
                     •
                  ) Dametas was my name,
            
               Dametas I, that ſlewe my ſelfe, by force of foolyſſhe flame.
            
               Dametas I, that dotynge dyed, In fyre of vnkynde Loue:
            
               Dametas I, whom Deiop
                     •
                  y, dyd cauſe ſuche ende to proue,
            The ſame Dametas here I com, by lyceus vnto the:
            For to declare the wofull ſtate, that happens now to me.
            (O Melibe
                     •
                  
               ) take hede of Loue, of me Example take,
            That ſlewe my ſelfe, and liue in Hell, for Deiopeias ſake.
            I thought that Deth ſhuld me releaſe from paynes and dolefull woe,
            
               But nowe (alas) the trothe is tryed, I fynde it nothynge ſoe,
            For looke what Payne &amp; gryefe I felt when I lyued heare afore:
            With thoſe I nowe tormented ant, and with ten thouſand more.
            I meane not that I burne in loue, ſuche foolyſh toyes begon,
            But Gryefes in nombre haue I lyke and many more vpon.
            O curſed Loue, (what ſhulde I ſaye,) that brought me fyrſte to Payne,
            Well, myght I ones deſpyſe thy lore, but nowe (alas) in vayne.
            With fond Affection, I dyd flame, whiche nowe I moſte repent,
            But all to late (alas) I wayle, ſyth hope of Grace is ſpent.
            The fickle fadynge forme, and face, that ones ſo muche I fowght,
            Hath made me loſe the Skyes aboue, and me to Hell hath browght.
            Why had I Reaſon delt to me? and coulde not Reaſon vſe.
            
               Why gaue I, Brydle to my wyll? when I myght well refuſe.
            A wycked Wyll, in dede it was, that blynded ſo my ſyght,
            That made me on ſuch fadyng Duſte, to ſet my whole Delyght.
            A fonde Affection lead me then, When I for God dyd place,
            A Creature, cauſe of all my Care, a fleſſh ye fletynge face,
            A woman Waue of Wretchednes, a Paterne pylde of Pryde,
            A Mate of Myſchiefe and Diſtreſſe, for whom (a Foole) I dyed.
            Thus whyle he ſpake, I ſawe me thought of Hell an vglye Fende,
            With lothſome Clawes, hym for to cloſe and forced him there to ende.
            And with this ſame, (O M
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  bey,) farewell, farewell (quoth he.)
            Eſchewe the Blaſe of feruent flames, Example take of me.
            My Harte with this began to rent, and all amaſde I ſtoode.
            
               O lord (quoth I) what flames be theſe what Rage, what Furyes woode?
            Doth Loue procure, to wretched men what Bondage doth it brynge?
            Paine here: &amp; Paine in lyfe to come. (O dolefull, dredefull thynge.)
            I quake to heare, this Storye tolde, and Melibei I fainte,
            For ſure I thought Dametas had, ben placed lyke a Saynte.
            I thought that cruel Charons Boate, had myſte of hym her frayght,
            And through his deth, he mounted had to ſtarres and Heauens ſtrayght.
            Howe valiantly dyd he deſpyſe, his lyfe in Bondage ledde?
            And ſekyng Deth with courage hye, from Loue and Ladye fledde.
            And is he thus rewarded nowe? The ground be curſed than,
            That foſterde vp, ſo fayre a face that loſte ſo good a Man.
            ¶Finis Egloge quarte.
         
         
            
            Egloga quinta.
            Mopſus. Agon.
            SOm doleful thing there is at hand thy countenaunce doth declare,
            Thy face good Agon voide of blud thine eies amaſed ſtare:
            I ſe thy teares, howe they do ſtill, diſcloſe thy ſecrete mynde,
            Hath Fortune fr
                  •
               wned late on the? Hath Cupide ben vnkinde.
            A pyteous thinge to be bewaylde a deſperate Acte of Loue,
                  Agon.
               
            
            (O Deſtenies) ſuche cruell broyles, Howe haue you power to moue?
            Here lyued a Ladye fayre of late, that Claudia men dyd call:
            Of goodly forme, yea ſuche a one, as farre ſurmounted all.
            The ſtately Dames, yt in this Courte, to ſhowe them ſelues do lye,
            There was not one in all the Crewe: that coulde come Claudia nye.
            
               A worthy Knyght dyd loue her longe, and for her ſake dyd feale,
            The panges of Loue. that happen ſtyl by frownyng Fortunes wheale,
            He had a Page, Valeri
                     ••
                  
                named, whom ſo muche he dyd truſte,
            That all the ſecrets of his Hart, to hym declare he muſte.
            And made hym all the onely meanes, to ſue for his redreſſe,
            And to entreate for grace to her, that cauſed his diſtreſſe.
            She whan as fyrſt ſhe ſaw his page was ſtrayght with hym in Loue,
            That nothynge coulde Valeri
                     ••
                  
                fare, from Claudias mynde remoue.
            By hym was Fauſtus often harde, by hym his ſutes toke place,
            By hym he often dyd aſpyre, to ſe his Ladyes face.
            This paſſed well, tyll at the length, Vale
                     ••
                  us ſore dyd ſewe▪
            
            With many teares beſechynge her, his Mayſters gryefe to rewe.
            
               And tolde her that yf ſhe wolde not releaſe, his Mayſters payne,
            He neuer wolde attempte her more, nor ſe her ones agayne.
            She then with maſed countnaunce there and teares ye guſhing fell,
            Aſtonyed anſwerde thus, loe nowe, alas I ſe to well.
            Howe longe I haue deceyued ben, by the Valerius heare,
            I neuer yet beleued before, nor tyll this tyme dyd feare,
            That thou dydſte for thy Mayſter li
                  •
               e but onely for my ſake.
            And for my ſyght, I euer thought, thou dydſte thy trauayle take.
            But nowe I ſe the contrarye, thou nothynge carſte for me,
            Synce fyrſt thou knewſte, the fyerye flames that I haue felte by the.
            O Lorde howe yll, thou doſte requyte that I for the haue done,
            I curſe the time, that frendſhyp fyrſt, to ſhowe, I haue begon.
            
               O lorde I the beſeche let me, in tyme reuenged be:
            And let hym knowe that he hath ſynd, in this miſuſynge me.
            I can not thynke, but Fortune once, ſhall the rewarde for all,
            And vengeaunce due for thy deſerts, in tyme ſhall on the fall.
            And tell thy maiſter Fauſtus nowe, yf he wolde haue me lyue:
            That neuer more he sewe to me, this aunſwere laſte I gyue:
            And thou o Traytour vyle, and enmye to my lyfe,
            Abſent thy ſelfe from out my ſyght, procure no greater ſtryfe,
            Synce yt theſe teares, had neuer force to moue thy ſtoneye harte,
            Let neuer theſe my weryed eyes, ſe the no more. Departe.
            This ſayde, in haſte ſhe hieth in, and there doth vengeaunce call,
            And ſtrake her ſelf, with cruel knyfe, and bluddye downe doth fall.
            
               This dolfull chaūce, whā 
               Pauſtus heard lamentynge lowde he cryes,
            And teares his heare and doth accuſe, the vniuſt and cruell Skies.
            And in this ragynge moode awaye, he ſtealeth oute alone,
            And gone he is: no mā knowes w
                  •
               ere eche man doth for hym mone.
            
               Valerius whan he doth perceyue, his Mayſter to be gone:
            He weepes &amp; wailes, in piteous plight and forth he ronnes anone.
            No Man knowes where, he is becom, ſome ſaye the wooddes he tooke,
            Intendynge there to ende his lyfe, on no Man more to looke:
            The Courte lamentes, the Princeſſe eke her ſelfe doth weepe for woe,
            Loe, Fauſtus fled, and Claudia deade.
            
               Valerius vanyſſhed ſoe.
            ¶Finis Egloge quinte.
         
         
            
            Egloga ſexta.
            Felix. Fauſtus.
            
               
                  Felix.
               O Fauſtus, whom aboue the reſt, of Shephardes here that kepe,
            Vpon theſe holts, ye nōbre great of waightye fleeſed ſhepe:
            I euer haue eſtemde: and coūted eke, the chiefeſt Frende of all,
            What great miſhap, what ſcourge of minde or griefe hath the befall?
            That hath the brought ī ſuch a plight farre from thy wonted guyſe?
            What meanes this coūtenaūce all beſprēt wt teres? theſe wretched eies
            This mournynge looke, this Veſture ſad this wrethe of Wyllow tree,
            (Vnhappy man) why doſte thou wepe what chaunce hath altered the?
            Tell tell, me ſoone, I am thy frende, Diſcloſe to me thy gryefe,
            Be not afrayde, for frendes do ſerue, to gyue theyr Frendes relyefe.
            
               The wofull cauſe of all my hurte, good Felix longe agoe,
                  Fauſtus.
               
            
            Thou knewſt full well: I nede not now by wordes to double woe,
            Synce that (alas) all hope is paſt ſynce gryefe, and I am one,
            And ſynce the Ladye of my lyfe, (my faute) I haue forgone,
            What woldſt yu haue me do (oh frend?) to Ioye? in ſuche dyſtres?
            Naye pleaſures quyte I baniſh here, and yelde to Heuynes,
            Let gryefes torment me euermore, let neuer Cares awaye.
            Let neuer Fortune turne her wheale to gyue me blyſfull daye.
            Loue hath me ſcourged: I am content lament not thou my ſtate.
            Let ſpyght on me take vengeaunce nowe let me be torne with hate.
            Let her enioye, her happye lyfe, a Flowre of golden hewe,
            That cloſeth when the Son doth ſet, and ſpreads with Phebus newe.
                  A Marygolde.
               
            
            
               Syth frō my Garlande now is falne, this famouſe Flowre ſwete:
            Let Wyllows wynde aboute my hed, (a Wrethe for Wretches mete)
            
               
                  Felix.
               Fye Fauſtus, let not Fancie fonde, in the beare ſuche a ſwaye,
            Expell Affections from thy mynde, and dryue them quyght awaye.
            Embrace thine Auncient Lybertie, let Bondage vyle be fled:
            Let Reaſon rule, thy craſed Brayne, place Wyt, in Folies ſteade.
            Synce ſhe is gone, what remedye? why ſhuldeſt thou ſo lament?
            Wilt thou deſtroy thy ſelf with tears and ſhe to pleaſures bent?
            Gyue eare to me, and I wyll ſhowe the remedies for Loue
            That I haue learned longe agoe: and in my youth dyd proue.
            Such remedies as ſoone ſhall quenche the flames of Cupids Fyre,
            Suche remedies as ſhall delaye, the Rage of fonde Deſyre.
            
               For Fauſtus yf thou folow ſtyll, the blynded God to pleaſe,
            And wylt not seke, by Reaſons Rule, to purchaſe thyne owne eaſe,
            Long canſt thou not thy frends enioy but byd them all farewell.
            And leaue thy lyfe, and giue thy ſoule to depeſt fluds of Hell.
            Leaue of therfore, betymes and let Affection beare no ſwaye,
            And now at fyrſt the Fyre quench before it further ſtraye,
            Eche thyng is eaſely made to obaye, whyle it is yong and grene,
            The tender twyg, that now doth bend at length refuseth cleane.
            The feruent Fyre, that flamyng fyrſt, may lytell water drenche,
            When as it hath obtayned tyme, whole Ryuers can not quenche:
            Forſake the Town, (my Fauſtus deare) and dwell, vpon this playne,
            And tyme ſhall heale, thy feſtryng woūd &amp; Abſence banyſh Payne.
            
               Aboue all thynges fly Idlenes, For this doth dowble ſtrength,
            To Louers flams, &amp; makes thē rage, tyl all be loſt at length,
            Here in thes felds, are pleaſaūt things to occupye thy brayn,
            Be hold: how ſpryng reuyues agayn, that winter late had ſlayne,
            Behold: the pleſaunt Hylles adournd, with dyuers colours fayre,
            Geue eare to Scillas luſty ſonges, reioyſynge in the ayr,
            What pleaſure cāſt thou more deſyre, then here is for to ſe:
            Thy luſty yewes, with many a lam, Lo: whear they wayt on the,
            Thynke not vpon that curſed face, that makes the thus her ſlaue
            But well regard the pleaſaunt lyfe, that here thou ſeeſt me haue,
            Whan I long tyme a go, did feale, the flames of Cupids fyre,
            Theſe meanes Lo than I practiſed, to cure my fond deſyre.
            
               I fyrſt wayed with my ſelfe, How fond a thyng it ſeamd,
            To let my heart lye there in chaynes, where I was nought eſteamd.
            And how with flames I burnt for her, that paſſed nought for me,
            And how, theſe eyes encreaſt my harmes that fyrſt her face did ſe,
            With penſyfe heart full fraight with thoughts, I fled frō thence away,
            And though that Loue bad tourne my ſteppes, yet wold I neuer ſtay,
            But from that foule infectyue ayer, wher firſt I tooke my ſore,
            I hyed in haſt, and ſhund the place, to ſe for euer more.
            Eache letter that I had receyued from her, I caſt away,
            And tokens all, I threw them down, to my no ſmall dyſmay.
            Then buſyed I my ſelfe in thyngs that myght me moſte delyght,
            And ſought the chiefſt means I could, to helpe my weryed ſpryght.
            
               Somtyme I wold behold the fyelds, and Hylles that thou doſte ſe,
            Somtime I wold betraye the Byrds, that lyght on lymed tree,
            Eſpecially in Shepſtare tyme, when thicke in flocks they flye,
            One wold I take, and to her Leg, a lymed Lyne wold tye,
            And where ye ſlock flew thickeſt, there I wold her caſt awaye,
            She ſtrayght vnto the reſt wold hye, amongſt her Mates to playe.
            And preaſyng in the mydſte of them, with Lyne and Lyme, and all,
            With cleuyng wyngs, entangled faſt they downe togyther fall.
            Somtyme I wold the lytel Fyſh: with bayted Hooke beguyle:
            Somtyme the craftye Fore I wold, deceyue for all his wyle:
            Somtyme the Wolfe, I wold purſue, ſomtyme the fomyng Boore:
            And whan with labour all the daye, my weryed Lyms were ſoore.
            
               Thā reſt &amp; ſlepe I ſtraightway ſought no Dreames dyd me afraye:
            Tormented nought with care, I paſt the lyngryng nyght awaye.
            And thus I cleane forgot: in tyme, the dotyng Dayes I ſawe,
            And freed my ſelf, to my great Ioye, from Yoke of Louers Lawe.
            More of this ſame, I wyll the tell, the next tyme here we mete,
            And ſtrōger Medycines wyll I gyue, to purge that Venym ſwete.
            Beholde the Daye is ſlypt awaye, and Starres do faſt appeare,
            Loe where Calicto Virgin ones, doth ſhyne in Skies ſo cleare.
            Loe where olde Ceph
                     •
                  us walks about, with twynyng Serpent bye,
            We wyll no lenger heare abyde, But hence wyll homwarde hye.
            Finis Eglogae ſextoe.
         
         
            
            
            Egloga ſeptima.
            Siluanus. Sirenus. Seluagla.
            
               SIrenus Shephard good and thou, that haſt yll lucke in loue,
            The cauſe of al my hurt by whom my ſutes could neuer proue.
            God neuer let that I ſhuld ſeeke, to be reuenged of the,
            For whan I might haue ben with caſe, yet wold not ſuffer me.
            The Loue that I Duerda bare, on the to showe my Spyte:
            On the in whom my Ladye fayre, had once her whole delyght,
            If thy myſhaps do not me greue, my miſchiefes neuer ende,
            Thynke not sirenus that bycauſe, Diana was thy frend,
            I beare the worſer wyl aſſure thy ſelf ſo baſe my loue neuer ſemde
            That onely I shuld fauour her. but all that she estemde.
            
               
               
                  Siren.
               Thou eyther art siluanus borne, Example for to gyue,
            To vs that know not how, whan Fortune frownes to lyue,
            Or els hath Nature placed in the ſo ſtrong and ſtoute a mynde.
            Suffyſynge not, thyne yls alone to beare, but meanes to fynde,
            That may the Griefes of others help, I ſe thou art ſo bent,
            That Fortune can the not amaſe, for all her myſciefes ment,
            I promys the siluanus heare, tyme playne in the doth ſhow,
            How dayly ſhe diſ
                  •
               ouers things, that erſt dyd men not know.
            I can not beare the Gryefes I feale, my force is all to faynt,
            I neuer could as thou canſt ſtynt, the teares of my complaynt.
            
               Diana hath procured the paynes, that I ſhall neuer ende,
            When fyrſt ſhe falſt her troth to me, ſhe kyld a faythfull frende.
            
               I meruayle how ſhe could ſo ſoone, put the out of her mind,
                  Siluan.
               
            
            I well remembre ſynce thou wentſ
                  •
               e alone I dyd her fynd.
            In place that ſorow ſemde to ſhape, where no man ſtood her nye,
            But onely (I vnhappy wretche,) that herd her wofull crye,
            And this with teares alowde ſhe ſayd, O wretche in yll tyme borne.
            What chaūce haſt thou? that thus thou haſt Sirenus ſwete forlorne.
            Gyue ouer pleaſures now, Let neuer Ioye the pleaſe,
            Seke all the cruell meanes thou canſt that may thy hart dyſeaſe.
            Whan thou doſte hym forget I wyſh, all miſchifes on the lyght,
            And after death, the Fendes of Hell, torment thy lyuyng ſpryght.
            What man wold here beleue? that ſhe that thus could ſpeake,
                  Siren.
               
            
            In ſo ſhorte tyme as I haue bene awaye. wolde promys breake.
            
               O ſtedfaſtnes and Conſtancy, how ſeldome are you founde:
            In womens harts to haue your ſeats, Or long abydyng ground?
            Who looke how much more earneſt they, at fyrſt theyr hearts do ſet,
            So much more ſooner euer more, where late they loued, forget:
            Full well could euer I beleue, all women gylty of this:
            Saue her alone, in whom I iudge, neuer nature wrought amis:
            But ſins her maryage how ſhe ſpeeds Siluanus I pray the tell?
            
               
                  Siluan.
               Some ſay ſhe lykes it very ill, and I beleue it well:
            For Delius he that hath her now, although he welthy be,
            Is but a lout and hath in hym, no hanſome qualytie:
            For as for all, ſuche ſhynges wherin, we Shepeheardes haue delyght,
            As in Quaiting, Leaping, Singing or to ſound a Bagpype ryght:
            
               In all theſe thinges he is but an Aſſe, and nothynge do he can,
            They ſaye tys quallities but tuſh, Its ryches makes a man:
            What woman is that y• cōmeth here, Siluanus canſt thou tell?
                  Siren.
               
            
            Its one hath ſped as well in Loue, as we, I knowe her well:
                  Siluan.
               
            
            She is one of fayre Guerdas frendes, who keeps her beaſts below,
            Not far from hence bi her thou maiſt, Dianas State wel know.
            She loued hear a Shephearde cald, Alanius longe a go:
            Who fauers one yſmenia now, the cause of al her wo:
            No place ſo fyt for the as this, Lo heare Siluanus ſtands,
                  Siluag.
               
            
            Who hath receaued lyke luck to thine at cruel Fortunes hands,
            This company beſemes the well, Fayr Shepheards both good deane,
            To the Seluagina eke of Hope, whom Loue hath ſpoyled cleane:
                  Silua.
               
            
            
               A thouſande better dayes I wyſh, than thou haſt had before,
            
               
                  Seluag.
               At length may better Fortune fall, For worſe can not be more.
            To truſte the fayned words of men, Loe, thus poore womens ſpeeds,
            
               
                  Siluan.
               And men do ſmarte not through your words but your vnconſtant deeds.
            For you whan earneſtlyeſt you loue, no thyng can chaunce ſo lyght.
            But yf a toye com in your Brayne, your mynde is altered quyght.
            If we but ones, abſent our ſelues, the ſhorteſt tyme we maye,
            So muche vnconſtant is your minds Loue ſoreth ſtrayght awaye,
            Example take Sire
                     •
                  us here, whom once Diana lovd,
            As all we know, and looke how ſoone her mynd is now removd:
            No, no, there is not one of you, that conſtant can remayne:
            
               
                  Siluag.
               You iudge but of malicious hart, and of a Ialouſe brayne.
            
               All thyngs you do your ſelues eſteme, and men muſt beare no blame.
            Of your diſſemblyng noughty deeds, we women beare the ſhame.
            Fayre Dameſell yf you can perceyue Siluanus true doth ſaye
                  Siren.
               
            
            There is not one amongſt you all, but doth from reaſon ſtraye.
            What is the cauſe that women thus? in theyr vnconſtancye,
            Do caſt a man from hyeſt hap, to deepeſt myſerye?
            Its nothyng els, I you aſſure, but that you know not well,
            What thing is loue, &amp; what you haue, in hand you can not tell.
            Your ſymple wyts are all to weake, Vnfayned loue to know,
            And therof doth forgetfulnes, in you ſo ſhortly grow.
            
               Si
                     •
                  enus iudge not ſo of vs, our wyts be not ſo baſe,
                  S
                        •
                     luag.
               
            
            But that we know as well as you, whats what in euery caſe.
            
               And women eke, there are ynow that could yf they were brought
            Teache men to lyue, &amp; more to loue, yf loue myght well be tought,
            And for all this, yet do I thynke, no thyng can worſer be.
            Than womens ſtate. it is the worſt, I thynke of eche degree.
            For yf they ſhow but gentle words you thynke for loue they dye.
            And yf they ſpeake not whan you liſt, than ſtrayght you ſay, they are hye.
            And that they ar, diſdainfull Dames, and yf they chaunce to talke.
            Thā cownt you thē for chatring Pies whoſe tongs muſt alwayes walke.
            And yf perhaps they do forbeare, and Sylence chaunce to keepe,
            Than tuſh, ſhe is not for company, ſhe is but a ſymple ſheepe.
            And yf they beare good wyll to one, thē ſtrayght they are iudged nought
            And yf yll name to ſhun they leaue, Vnconſtant they are thought.
            
               Who nowe can pleaſe theſe Ialouſe heads, the faute is all in you,
            For women neuer wold chaūge theyr minds yf men wold ſtyll be true,
            To this, I well could anſwere you, but tyme doth byd me ſtaye,
                  Siren.
               
            
            And women muſt the laſt worde haue no man may ſay them naye.
            Paſſe ouer this, and let vs here, what lucke you haue had in loue,
            And ſhowe yf euer loue of man, your conſtaunt hart could moue.
            No fytter place can be than this, here maye you ſafely reſt,
            Thus ſyttyng here, declare at large, the ſecretes of your breſt.
            Naye: lenger here we maye not byde, but home we muſt awaye,
                  Siluag.
               
            
            Loe how the Son denies his Beames depriuyng vs of daye.
            Finis Egloge ſeptime.
         
         
            
            Egloga octaua.
            Coridon. Cornix:
            NOw ragethe Titan fyerce aboue his Beames on earth do beate.
            Whoſe hote reflection, maks vs an ouer feruent heate:
            With fyery Dog, he forward flames feale hote Agues vp he dryues:
            And ſends them downe, with boylyng blud to ſhorten Myſers lyues.
            Loe, how the beaſts, lyes vnder trees how all thyng ſeekes the ſhade,
            O bleſſed God, that ſome defence, for euery hurte haſt made,
            Beholde this pleaſaunte Brodeleaued Be
                  •
               ch &amp; ſpringing foūtain cleare,
            Heare ſhade ynough, here water cold com Cornix reſt we here,
            And let vs ſongs begyn to ſyng, our purs and harts be lyght.
            We fere not we, the tomblyng world we breake no ſleaps by nyght.
            
               Both place and tyme my Coridon exhorteth me to ſynge,
                  Cornix:
               
            
            Not of the wretched Louers lyues, but of the immortall kynge.
            Who gyues vs paſture for our beaſts and bleſſeth our encreaſe:
            By whom, while other cark and toyle we lyue at home with eaſe.
            Who keepes vs down, from climyng hye wher honour breeds debate,
            And here hath graunted vs to lyue in ſymple Shephards ſtate,
            A lyfe that ſure doth fare exceade, eche other kynd of lyfe:
            O happy ſtate, that doth content, How farre be we from ſtryfe?
            Of hym therfore, me lyſt to ſynge, and of no wanton toyes,
            For hym to loue, and hym to prayſe, ſurmounts all other Ioyes.
            O Shephards leaue Cupidoes Camp, the ende wherof is vyle,
            Remoue Dame Venus from your eies and harken here a whyle.
            
               A God there is, that guyds the Globe, and framde the fyckle Spheare,
            And placed hath, the Starres aboue, that we do gaſe on here,
            By whō we lyue, (vnthākful beaſts) by whom we haue our health,
            By whom we gayne our happy ſtates by whom we get our wealth.
            A God: that ſends vs that we nede, a God: that vs defends.
            A God: from whom the Angels hye, on mortall men attends.
            A God: of ſuche a Clemencie, that who ſo hym doth loue
            Shall here be ſure to reſt a whyle, and alwayes reſt aboue.
            But we, for hym do lytell care, His Heaſts we nought eſteme,
            But hunt for thyngs that he doth hate moſt pleaſaunt thoſe do ſeme,
            (Vnthankfull myſers) what do we? what meane we thus to ſtraye?
            From ſuche a God, ſo mercyfull, to walke a worſer waye?
            
               Maye nought his benefyts procure? maye nought his mercyes moue?
            Maye nothynge bynde, but nedes we must? gyue hate to hym for loue?
            O happy (ten tymes) is the man, (a Byrde full rare to fynde)
            That loueth God with all his hart, and kepes his lawes in mynde.
            He ſhalbe bleſt in all his works, and ſafe in euery tyme,
            He ſhall ſwete quietnes enioye, whyle other ſmarte for Cryme.
            The threatnyng chaūces of the world ſhall neuer hym annoye,
            Whē Fortune frowns on fooliſh men he ſhalbe ſure to ioye.
            For why? the Aungels of the Lorde, ſhall hym defende alwayes,
            And ſet hym free, at euery harmes, and hurts at all aſſayes.
            Euen he that kept the Prophet ſafe, from mouthes of Lyons wylde,
                  Dauid.
               
            
            And he that once preſerued in Flags, the ſely ſuckyng Chylde,
                  Moses.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Elias.
               The God that fed, by Rauens Byll, the Teacher of his worde,
            Shall 
                  •
               ym (no doubt) in ſafetie kepe▪ from Famyn, Fyre, and Sworde.
            Not he, whom Poets old haue faynd, to lyue in Heauen hye,
            
               
                  Iupiter.
               Embracyng Boyes: (O fylthy thyng) in beaſtly Lecherye.
            
               
                  Iuno.
               Nor Iu
                     ••
                  
                ſhe: (that wrinkled Iade,) that Quene of Skyes is calde,
            
               
                  Saturn.
               Nor ſoleyn Sat
                     ••
                  n Churlyſh Chuffe▪ with Scalpe of Cancre bald.
            
               
                  Mars.
               Nor fumyng Foole, with fyery face, that moues the fyghters mynd.
            
               
                  Venus.
               
               
                  Cupido.
               Nor Venus ſhe: (that wanton wench) that guyds the Shoter blynd.
            Can the defende: as God wyll do, for they were ſynfull fooles,
            
               
                  N
                        •
                     merus.
               Whō fyrſt ye blynd hye wytted Grek
                  •
                brought in to wyſe mens Scooles.
            No none of theſe, but God alone, ou
                  •
               ht worſh
                  •
               p for to 
                  •
               aue,
            For they for all theyr Honour ones, reſt ye tin ſtynkyng Graue.
            
               Heare haſt thou heard, the happy ſtate of them that lyue in feare,
            Of God▪ &amp; loue hym beſt: now lyſt, his foes reward to heare,
            And fyrſt know thou that euery man, that from this God doth goe,
            And folows luſt, hym he acountes, to be his deadly foe,
            This myghty Kyng of whom we talk, as he is mercyfull,
            And ſuffers long, reuengyng ſlow, So when we be thus dull,
            That we wyl not perceaue in tyme, the goodnes of his grace,
            His fauour ſtraight, he doth withdraw and tournes a way his face.
            And to him ſelfe then doth he ſay, How long ſhall I permit
            Theſe ſtubburne beaſtes, for to rebell? and ſhall I loue them yet,
            That hate me thus? or haue I nede theyr louynge mynds to craue?
            I aſke no more but onely loue, and that I can not haue.
            
               Well, wel, I wil not care for them, that thus do me dyſpyſe,
            Let them go lyue, euen as they lyſt, I turne awaye myne eyes.
            When God hath thus ſayd to him ſelf, Then doth the braynleſſe foole,
            Caſt Brydle of, and out he runnes, neglectynge vertues Scoole,
            Then doth the Deuyl geue him lyne, and let him rune at large,
            And Pleaſure makes his Mariner, to row in vyces Barge,
            Then vp the Sayles of wilfulnes, he hoyſes hie in haſt,
            And fond Affection blowes hym forth, a wynd that Pluto plaſt,
            Then cuttes he ſwyft, the ſeas of ſin, and through the Chanell deape,
            With Ioyful mynd, he fleets a pace, whom Pleaſure bryngs a ſleape,
            Then who ſo happy thinks hym ſelfe? who dreames of ioy but he?
            Tuſh, tuſh, ſayth he: to thynk of God, Inage ſuffiſeth me,
            
               Now wil I paſſe my pleaſaunt youth, Such toyes becomes this age,
            And God ſhall followe me ſayth he, I wyll not be his page,
            I wyll be prowd, and looke a loft, I wyll my body decke,
            With coſtly clothes, aboue my ſtate who then dare gyue me che
                  •
               ke?
            Garments ſom time, ſo gard a knaue, that he dare mate a Knyght,
                  Coridon.
               
            
            Yet haue I ſene a Ne
                     •
                  
                in hemp, For Checking often lyght.
            The Peacocks plume ſhal not me pas that nature finely framde
                  Cornix.
               
            
            For coulord ſylkes ſhal ſet me fourth, that nature ſhalbe ſhamde,
            My Sworde ſhal get me valiant fame, I wyll be Mars out ryght,
            And Mars you know, muſt Venus haue, to recreate his ſpryght.
            I wyll oppreſſe the ſymple knaue, ſhall Saues be ſawſy now?
            Nay: I wyll teache the nedy Dogges, with Cappe to crowche, &amp; bow.
            
               Thus fareth he, and thus he lyues, no whyt eſtemyng God,
            In health, in ioy, and luſtynes, free from the ſmartyng Rod,
            But in the mioſt of all his myrth, whyle he ſu
                  •
               pecteth leaſt,
            His happy chaunce, begyns to chaūge and else his fl
                  •
               etynge feaſt,
            For d
                  •
               ath (that old deuouryng Wolf) whom goo
                  •
                men nothyng feare,
            Coms ſaylyng faſt, t
                  •
                Galley blacke, and whan he ſpy
                  •
               s hym neare.
            Doth boorde hym ſtrayght, &amp; grapels faſt and than begy
                  •
               s the fyght.
            In ryot leaps, as Captayne chiefe, and from the Mayn maſt ryght,
            He downward com
                  •
               , and ſurfet than, aſſayleth by and by,
            Then vyle diſeaſes forward ſhoues, with paynes and gryefe therby,
            Lyfe ſtands aloft, and fyghteth hard, but pleaſure all agaſte.
            Doth leaue his ore, and out he flyes then death approcheth faſt.
            
               And giues the charge ſo ſore, ye needs muſt lyfe begyn to flye,
            Thē farewell all. The wretched man with Caryen Corſe doth lye,
            Whō Deth hymſelf flyngs ouer bord, amyd the Seas of ſyn,
            The place wher late, he ſwetly ſwam now lyes he drowned in.
            Contynuall torment hym awaytes, (a Monſter vyle to tell)
            That was begot of Due Deſert, and raygneth now in Hell,
            With gredy mouth he alwayes fe
                  •
               ds vpon the Syndrownd ſoule,
            Whoſe gredy Pawes, do neuer ceas, in ſynfull fluds to prowle.
            Loe. 
                  •
                his the ende, of euery ſuche as here lyues luſtylye
            Necglectyng God thou ſeeſt. in vyce, 
                  •
               o lyue. in ſyn do dye.
            What ſhuld I ſpeke of al theyr harms blud that happens them in lyfe?
            Theyr Cōſcience prickt, theyr barren theyr toyle, theyr grief, theyr ſtryfe,
            
               With miſchiefes heaped many a one, which they do neuer trye,
            That Lou
                  •
                &amp; Feare the myghty God, that rules and raynes on hye,
            To long it we are, to make diſcourſe, and Phebus downe deſcends,
            And in the Clowdes his beames doth hyde which tempeſt ſure portends,
            Looke how the beaſtes begin to ſling, and caſt theyr heades on hye,
            The Hear on ſhew mountes aboue the Clouds ye Crowes ech wher do cry
            All this ſhowes rayn, tyme byds vs go com Coridon awaye,
            Take vp thy Staffe, fetch ī thy beaſts let vs go whyle we maye.
            
               
                  Coridon:
               
               Cornix agreed, go thou before, you curſed Bull of myne
            I muſt go dryue: he neuer bydes, among my Fathers Kyne.
            Finis Egluge octaue.
         
         
            
            ¶An Epytaphe of the Lorde Sheffeldes death.
            WHen Brutyſh broyle, and rage of war in Clownyſh harts began
            When Tigres ſtoute, in Tāners bonde vnmuſled all they ran,
            The Noble Sheffeyld Lord by byrth and of a courage good,
            By clubbiſh hāds, of crabbed Clowns there ſpent his Noble blud.
            His noble byrth auayled not, his honor all was vayne,
            Amyd the preaſe, of Maſt ye Curres, the valyant Lorde was ſlayue.
            And after ſuche a ſorte (O ruth,) that who can teares ſuppreſſe.
            To thynke ye Dunghyll Dogs ſhuld dawnt the Floure of worthynes.
            Whyle as the rauenyng Wolues he prayed his gylteles lyfe to ſaue.
            A bluddy Butcher byg and blunt, a vyle vnweldy knaue
            
               With beaſtly blow of boyſterous byll at hym (O Lorde) let dryue,
            And cleſte his head, and ſayd therwith ſhalt thou be lefte alyue?
            O Lorde that I had preſent ben, and Hectors force withall,
            Before that from his Carlyſh hands, the cruell Byll dyd fall.
            Then ſhulde that peaſaunt vyle haue felt the clap vpon his Crowne,
            That ſhuld haue dazed his dogged hart from dryuyng Lordes adowne.
            Then ſhuld my hands haue ſaued thy lyfe good Lord whō deare I loued
            Then ſhuld my hart in doutfull caſe, full well to the ben proued,
            But all in vayne thy death I wayle, thy Corps in earth doth lye.
            Thy kyng and Countrey for to ſerue thou dydſte not feare to dye.
            Farewel good Lord, thy deth bewayle all ſuche as well the knewe,
            And euerye man laments thy caſe: and Googe thy death doth rewe.
         
         
            
            ¶An Epytaphe of M. Shelley ſlayne at Muſſelbroughe.
            VVan Mars had moued mortall hate and forced ſumyſh heate
            And hye Bellona had decreed, to ſyt with Sworde in Seate,
            The Scottes vntrue with fyghtynge hande, theyr promys to denye,
            Aſſembled faſt, &amp; England thought, the trothe with them to trye.
            Choſe Muſclebroughe theyr fyghtynge place amyd those barrayne fyelds
            Theyr breche of fayth, there not to try with trothe, but trotheles Shyeldes
            In battayle braue, and Armye ſtrong Encamped ſoore they laye,
            Ten Scottes to one (a dredeful thyng a dolfull fyghtyng daye.)
            That Englyſh men were all agaſte, with quakyng ſtaues in hande.
            To ſe theyr enemyes lye ſo neare, and death with them to ſtande.
            
               No other remedye there was, but fyght it out or flye.
            And who ſhuld fyrſt the Onſet gyue, was ſure therin to dye.
            Thus al diſmayde, and wrapt in feare with doutfull mynde they ſtande,
            If beſt it be, with flyght of foote, to ſtryue or fyght of hande.
            Tyll at the length, a Captayn ſtoute. with hawtye mynde gan ſpeake.
            O Towards all, and maydly men of Courage faynt and weake,
            Vnworthye com of Brutus race, is this your manhode gon,
            And is there none you Daſtardes all. that dare them ſet vpon.
            Then Shelley all inflamed with heate with heate of valyaunt mynde,
            No Towardes we, nor maydly men, ne yet of Daſtards kynde,
            I wold you wyſte dyd euer com, but dare be bolde to trye,
            Our manhode heare, thoughe nought appeare but deth to all mens eye
            
               And with these wordes (O noble hart) no longer there he ſtayde,
            But forth before them all he ſprang as one no whyt diſmayed
            With charged ſtaffe on fomyng horſe his Spurres with heeles he ſtrykes,
            And forewarde ronnes with ſwyftye race, among the mortall Pykes
            And in this race with famous ende, to do his Countrey good,
            Gaue Onſet fyrſt vpon his Foes, and loſt his vitall blud.
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            ¶An Epytaphe of Maiſter Thomas Phayre.
            THe hawtye verſe, ye 
               Maro wrote made Rome to wonder mu
                  •
               he
            And meruayle none for why the Style and waightynes was ſuche,
            
               That all men iudged Parnaſſus Mownt had clefte her ſelfe in twayne,
            And brought forth one, that ſeemd to drop from out Minerua
                     •
                  s brayne.
            But wonder more, maye Bryttayne great wher Phayre dyd floryſh late,
            And barreyne tong with ſwete accord reduced to ſuche eſtate:
            That Virgils verſe hath greater grace in forrayne foote obtaynde,
            Than in his own. who whilſt he lyued eche other Poets ſtayned·
            The Noble H. Hawarde once, that raught eternall fame,
            With mighty Style, did bryng a pece of Virgils worke in frame,
            And Grimaold gaue the lyke attempt, and D
                     •
                  uglas wan the Ball,
            whoſe famouſe wyt in Scottyſh ryme had made an ende of all.
            But all theſe ſame dyd Phayre excell, I dare preſume to wryte,
            As muche as doth Appoll
                     •
                  es Beames, the dymmeſt Starre in lyght.
            
               The enuyous fates (O pytie great, had great diſdayne to ſe,
            That vs amongſt there ſhuld remayn ſo fyne a wyt as he,
            And in the mydſt of all his toyle, dyd force hym hence to wende,
            And leaue a Worke vnperfyt ſo, that neuer man ſhall ende.
         
         
            ¶An Epytaphe of the Death of Nicolas Grimaold.
            BEholde this fletyng world how al things fade
            Howe euery thyng doth paſſe and we are awaye,
            Eche ſtate of lyfe, by comon courſe and trade,
            Abydes no tyme, but hath a paſſyng daye.
            For looke as lyfe, that pleaſaūt Dame hath brought,
            
               Tht pelaſaunt yeares, and dayes of luſtynes,
            So Death our Foe, conſumeth all to nought,
            Enuyeng thefe, with Darte doth vs oppreſſe,
            And that whiche is, the greateſt gryfe of all,
            The gredye Grype, doth no eſtate reſpect,
            But wher he comes, he makes them down to fall,
            Ne ſtayes he at, the hie ſharpe wytted ſect.
            For yf that wytt, or worthy Eloquens,
            Or learnyng deape, coulde moue hym to forbeare,
            O Grima
                     •
                  ld then, thou hadſte not yet gon hence
            But heare hadeſt ſene, full many an aged yeare.
            Ne had the Muſes loſte ſo fyne a Floure,
            
               Nor had Minerua wept to leaue the ſo,
            If wyſdome myght haue fled the fatall howre,
            Thou hadſte not yet ben ſuffred for to go,
            A thouſande doltyſh Geeſe we myght haue ſparde,
            A thouſande wytles heads, death might haue found
            And taken them, for whom no man had carde,
            And layde them lowe, in deepe obliuious grounde,
            But Fortune fauours Fooles as old men ſaye
            And lets them lyue, and take the wyſe awaye.
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            
            ¶To Mayſter Alexander Nowell.
            THe Muſes ioye, and well they may to ſe,
            So well theyr laboure com to good ſucceſſe,
            That they ſuſtayned long agoe in the,
            
               Minerua ſmyles, Phebus can do no leſſe,
            But ouer all, they chyefly do reioyſe,
            That leauyng thyngs, which are but fond and vayne,
            Thou dyddeſt chuſe, (O good and happy choyſe)
            In ſacred Scoles, thy luckye yeares to trayne,
            By whiche thou haſt obtaynde (O happy thyng)
            To learne to lyue, whyle other wander wyde,
            
               And by thy lyfe, to pleaſe the immortall kyng,
            Then whiche ſo good, nothyng can be applyed,
            Lawe gyues the gayne, and Phyſycke fyls the Purſe,
            Promotions hye, gyues Artes to many one,
            But this is it, by whiche we ſcape the Curſe,
            And haue the blys of God, when we be gone.
            Is this but onely Scriptures for to reade?
            No, no. Not talke, but lyfe gyues this in deade.
         
         
            ¶To Doctor Bale.
            GOod aged Bale: that with thy hoary heares
            Doſte yet perſyſte, to turne the paynefull Booke,
            
               O happye man, that haſt obtaynde ſuche yeares,
            And leavſt not yet, on Papers pale to looke,
            Gyue ouer now to beate thy weryed brayns,
            And reſt thy Pen that long hath laboured soore
            For aged men vnfyt ſure is ſuche paine,
            And the beſeems to laboure now no more,
            But thou I thynke Don Platoes part will playe
            With Booke in hand, to haue thy dyeng daye.
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            ¶To M. Edwarde Cobham.
            OLde Socrates, whoſe wyſdome dyd excell,
            And paſt the reache, of wyſeſt in his tyme,
            
               Surmounted all, that on the earth dyd dwell,
            That Craggye Hyls, of vertue hye dyd clyme,
            That Socrates, my Cobham dyd allowe,
            Eche man in youth, hym ſelfe in Glaſſe to vew,
            And wyld them oft, to vſe the ſame, but how?
            Not to delyght, in forme of fadyng hew.
            Nor to be proude therof, as many be,
            But for to ſtryue, by beautie of the mynde,
            For to adourne, the beautie he doth ſe.
            If warlyke forme, Dame Nature hym aſſygnde,
            By vertuous lyfe, than coūtenaūce for to get,
            That ſhall deface, the fayreſt of them all,
            
               Suche Beautie as no age nor yeares wyll fret:
            That flyes with fame, whan fyckle forme doth fayle,
            Thus muche I ſaye, that here to the preſent,
            My wordes a Glaſſe for the to looke vpon.
            To the whom God, in tender yeares hath lent,
            A towardenes, that maye be muſed vpon,
            Suche towardenes, as in more grauer yeares,
            Doth ſure a hope, of greater thyngs pretende,
            Thy noble mynde, that to thy frendes appeare,
            Doth ſhowe the blud, wherof thou doſte deſcende,
            The gentlenes, thou vſeſt vnto all ſuche,
            As ſmallye haue deſerued good wyll of the,
            
               Doth ſhowe the grace, thou haſt that ſure is muche,
            As euer yet, in any I dyd ſe,
            Thy wyt as rype, as Nature well can gyue,
            Declares a greater hope than all the reſt,
            That ſhall remayne, to the whilſt thou doſte lyue,
            In deſperate yls, a Medycyne euer preſt.
            The good behauyour, of thy ſelfe in place
            Wherſoeuer that thou chaunceſt for to lyght,
            So much both beautie, mynde and wyt doth grace
            As well can be requyred of any wyght.
            What reſteth now? but onely God to prayſe,
            Of whom thou haſt receaued theſe Gyftes of thyns,
            
               So ſhalt thou long, lyue heare with happye dayes,
            And after Death, the ſtarrye Skyes ſhalt clyme,
            Let noughtye men, ſaye what they lyſt to the,
            Trade thou thy ſelfe, in ſeruyng hym aboue,
            No ſweter ſeruyce can deuyſed be,
            Whom yf thou fearſt, and faythfully doſte loue,
            Be ſure no thyng, on earth ſhall the annoye,
            Be ſure he wyll, the from eche harme defende,
            Be ſure thou ſhalt, long tyme thy lyfe enioye,
            And after many yeares to haue a bleſſed ende.
            ¶Finis.
         
         
            
            ¶Of Edwardes of the Chappell.
            DEuyne Camenes that wt your ſacred food,
            Haue fed and foſterde vp from tender yeares,
            A happye man, that in your fauour ſtoode
            
               Edvvards in Courte that can not fynde his feares
            Your names be bleſt, that in this preſent age
            So fyne a head, by Arte haue framed out
            Whom ſome hereafter helpt by Poets rage,
            Perchaunce maye matche, but none ſhall paſſe (no doubt)
            O Plautus yf thou wert alyue agayne,
            That Comedies ſo fynely dydſte endyte.
            
               Or Terence thou that with thy pleſaunt brayne,
            The hearers mynde on ſtage dydſt much delyght.
            What wold you ſay ſyrs if you ſhould beholde,
            As I haue done the doyngs of this man?
            No word at all, to ſweare I durſt be bolde,
            But burne with teares, that which with myrth began,
            I meane your bookes, by which you gate your name,
            To be forgot, you wolde commit to flame.
            Alas I wolde Edvvards more tell thy prayſe,
            But at thy name my muſe amaſed ſtayes.
         
         
            
            To L. Blundeſton.
            SOme men be counted wyſe that well can talke:
            And ſome becauſe they can eche man begyle.
            Some for becauſe they know well cheſe from chalke,
            And can be ſure, weepe who so lyſt to ſmyle.
            But (Blundſton) hym I call the wyſeſt wyght,
            Whom God gyues grace to rule affections ryght·
         
         
            The Aunſwere of L. Blundeſton to the ſame.
            AFfections seekes hygh honours frayle eſtate,
            Affections doth the golden meane reproue.
            Affections tourns the frendly hart to hate,
            
               Affections breede with out diſcretion Loue,
            Both wyſe and happye (Googe) he maye be hyght,
            Whom God gyues grace, to rule affections ryght.
         
         
            ¶To Alexander Neuell.
            THe lytell Fyſh, that in the ſtreme doth fleet
            With brode forth ſtretched Fyns for his diſporte
            When as he ſpyes, the Fyſſhes bayte ſo ſwete.
            In haſte he hyes, fearynge to com to ſhorte.
            But all to ſoone (alas) his gredy mynde,
            By raſh attempt, doth bryng hym to his bane,
            for where he thought a great relyefe to fynde,
            
               By hydden hooke, the ſymple fole is tane.
            So fareth man, that wanders here and theare,
            Thynkyng no hurt to happen hym therbye,
            He ronnes amayne, to gaſe on Beauties cheare,
            Takes all for golde that glyſters in the eye,
            And neuer leaues to feade by lookyng long,
            On Beauties Bayte, where Bondage lyes enwrapt,
            Bondage that makes hym ſynge an other ſong,
            And makes hym curſe the bayte that hym entrapte.
            
               Neuell to the, that loueſt their wanton lookes,
            Feade on the bayte, but pet beware the Hookes.
         
         
            
            Alexander Neuells Anſwere to the ſame.
            IT is not curſed Cupids Dart:
            Nor Venus cancred Spyght,
            It is not vengea
                  •
               ce of the Gods
            That wretched harts doth ſmyght,
            With reſtleſſe rage of carefull Loue.
            No, No, thy Force alone
            
               Aff
                     •
                  ct
                     •
                  on fond, doth ſtyr theſe flames.
            Thou cauſeſt vs to mone
            And waile, &amp; curs our wretched ſtats.
            Our thryſe vnhappy plights,
            Our ſighes, &amp; powdred ſobs wt tears,
            Our greuous gronyng Sprights,
            Thy hateful Malice doth procure:
            O Fancye flamyng Feend
            Of Hel. For thou in outwarde ſhape,
            And colour of a frende
            Doſt by thy Snares &amp; ſlymed Hooks
            entrap the wounded Harts:
            From whence theſe Hellike torments ſpryng,
            &amp; euer greauyng Smarts.
            
               Whence 
                  •
               ripe of minde, wt chaunged chere
            Whēce face be ſmeard wt teares.
            Whēce thouſād miſchiefs more, wher wt
            
            ſuche Myſers liues outweares.
            Our gaſyng eyes on Bewties bayt
            do worke out endles bane.
            Our eyes I ſay doo woorke our woo,
            Our eyes procure our paine.
            Theſe are the Traps to vexed mynds
            Here Gyns and Snares do lye.
            Here fyre &amp; flames by Fancie framde,
            In breſt doo broyle and frye.
            O Goo
                     •
                  e the Bayte ſone ſpyed is,
            Soone vewd their wanton lookes.
            Wheron to feede, and yet to ſhun,
            The priuy lurkyng hookes,
            Their pain, Their toile, Their labour is
            There There lyes endles ſtrife.
            O happye than that Man account,
            Whoſe well directed Lyfe
            Can fly thoſe yls, which fancy ſtirs,
            And lyue from Bondage free.
            A Phoenix ryght on yearth (no doubte)
            A Byrde full rare to ſee.
         
         
            
            ¶To M. Henrye Cobham of the moſt bleſſed ſtate of Lyfe.
            THe happyeſt lyfe that here we haue,
            My Cobham yf I ſhall deſyne,
            The goodlyeſt ſtate, twyxte byrth and graue,
            Moſt gracious dayes and ſweteſt tyme.
            The fayreſt face, of fadynge Lyfe,
            Race ryghtlyeſt ronne, in ruthfull wayes,
            The ſafeſt meanes to ſhun all ſtryfe:
            The ſureſt Staffe, in fyekle Dayes:
            I take not I as ſome do take,
            To gape and gawne, for Honoures hye,
            
               But Court and 
                  〈◊〉
                to forſake,
            And lyue at home, full quyetlye,
            I well do mynde, what he once ſayde,
            Who had, Courte not in any caſe,
            For Vertue is, in Courtes decayed,
            And Vyce with States, hath chyefeſt place,
            Not Courte but Countreye I do iudge,
            Is it wheare lyes, the happyeſt lyfe,
            In Countreye growes, no gratynge grudge,
            In Countreye ſtandes not ſturdye ſtryfe,
            In Countreye, Bacchus hath no place,
            In Countreye Venus hath defecte,
            
               In Countreye Thra
                     ••
                  
                hath no grace,
            In Countreye fewe of G
                     •
                  atoes Secte.
            But theſe ſame foure and many moe,
            In Courte, thou ſhalt be ſure to fynde,
            For they haue vowed, not thence to goe,
            Bycauſe in Courte, dwels ydle mynde.
            In Countreye mayſte thou ſafelye reſt,
            And flye all theſe, yf that thou lyſte,
            The Countrey 
                  •
               herfore, iudge I b
                  •
               ſt,
            Where godly lyfe, doth vyce reſyſte,
            Where vertuous exercyſe with ioye,
            Doth ſpende the yeares that are to run,
            
               Where Vyces fewe, maye the annoye,
            This lyfe is beſt whan all is done.
         
         
            ¶To Alexander Neuell of the bleſſed Sate of him that feeles not the force of Cupids flames.
            AS ofte as I remembre with my ſelf,
            The Fancies fonde, that flame by foolyſh Loue,
            And marke the Furyes fell, the blynded elfe
            And Venus ſhe that raynes ſo ſore aboue,
            As ofte as I do ſe the wofull ſtate,
            Of Louers all, and eake their myſerye,
            The ones deſyryng mynde the others hate,
            
               Trothe with the one, with the other Trecherye,
            So ofte ſaye I, that bleſſed is the wyght,
            Yea Neuell bleſt, and double bleſt agayne,
            That can by reaſon rule his mynde a ryght,
            And take ſuche foolyſh fadynge toyes for vayne.
         
         
            ¶Alexander Neuells Awnſwere to the ſame.
            THe plūged mind in fluds of griefs
            The Sences drowned quyght,
            The Hart oppreſt. The fleſh conſumed
            The chaūged ſtate outright.
            The Body dryed by broylyng blaſe,
            Of preuy ſchorchyng Flame.
            The doulfull Face. The coūtnaūce ſad
            The drowping Courage tame.
            The Scaldyng ſyghes. The greuous groones
            The burning rage of fyre
            
               The erneſt ſute, The fruitles Toyle.
            The deepe and hot Deſyre,
            The Braynes quight bruſd &amp; cruſht wt Cares.
            The euer duryng ſoore.
            The very paynes of Hell it ſelf,
            with thouſande miſchyefes moore,
            Which wounded Harts enflamd with Loue
            with Gryefe do ouerflow,
            And works theyr endles plage &amp; ſpight
            Tyll Death from thence do growe.
            All theſe conclude him bleſt (my Googe)
            and trible bleſt agayne,
            That taught bi tract of Time can take
            Such fadyng Toyes for vayne.
         
         
            ¶To Mayſtreſſe A.
            SYnce I ſo long haue lyved in pain and burnt for loue of the,
            (O cruel hart) doſte thou no more eſteame the Loue of me,
            Regardſt thou not, the health of hym? that the, aboue the reſt
            
               Of Creatures all, and next to God, hath deareſt in his breſt.
            Is pytie placed from the ſo farre is gentlenes exylde?
            Haſt thou ben foſtred in the Caues, of Wolues or Lyons wylde?
            Haſt thou ben ſo? why then no force, the leſſe I meruayle I,
            Suche as the Dāme, ſuche is the yong experyence trewe doth trye.
            Syth thou art of ſo fyerce a mynde, why dyd not God then place
            In the, with ſuche a Tygers Harte, a fowle yll fauerde face?
            Sure for no other ende but that, he lykes no Louers trade,
            And the therfore a ragynge Fende, an Angels face hathe made.
            Suche one as thou, was Go
                     •
                  gon ones as auncient Poets tell,
            Who with her Beautie maz
                  •
               d men, and nowe doth raygne in H
                  •
               ll.
            But mercye yet, of the I craue, yf ought in the remayne,
            
               And let me not ſo long the force, of flamyng fyre ſuſtayne,
            Let pytie ioynde with beautie be, ſo ſhall I not dyſdayne.
            My blud, my hart, my lyfe to ſpende with toyle, with ſtryfe, and payne,
            To do the good, my breath to looſe, yf nede ſhall ſo requyre,
            But for my ſeruyce and my paynes thou gyueſt me hate for hyre.
            Well now take this for ende of all, I loue and thou doſte hate,
            Thou lyueſt in pleaſures happely. and I in wretched ſtaie.
            Paynes can not laſt for euermore, but tyme and ende wyll trye,
            And tyme ſhall tell me in my age, How youth led me awrye.
            Thy face that me tormented ſo, in tyme ſhall ſure decaye,
            And all that I do lyke or loue, ſhall vanyſh quyte awaye,
            Thy face in tyme ſhall wrynckled be, at whiche I ſhall be glad,
            
               To ſee thy forme transformed thus, that made me once ſo ſad,
            Than ſhall I blame my foly moch and thanke the mightyeſt kyng
            That hath me ſaued tyll ſuch a daye, to ſe ſo fonde a thyng.
            And tyll that tyme I wyll keepe cloſe my flames and let them blaſe,
            All ſecretly within my breſt, no man on me ſhall gaſe.
            I wyll not treſpaſſe ſynfully, for God ſhall geue me grace
            To ſe the tyme wherin I ſhall neglecte thy folyſh face,
            And tyll that tyme adieu to thee, God keepe thee far from me,
            And ſende thee in that place to dwell, that I ſhall neuer ſee.
         
         
            
            ¶To George Holmeden of a ronnynge Heade.
            THe greateſt vyce that happens vnto men,
            And yet a vyce, that many comon haue,
            As aunci
                  •
               nt Wryters waye with ſobre Pen,
            Who gaue theyr doome, by force of wyſdom graue,
            The ſoreſt mayme, the greateſt euyll ſure,
            The vyleſt plague that Students can ſuſtayne,
            And that whiche moſte doth ygnoraunce procure.
            My Holmeden is to haue a ronnyng Brayne,
            For who is he that leades more reſtles lyfe,
            Or who can euer lyue more yll beſtead?
         
         
            
            ¶ The Harte abſent.
            SWete muſe tell me, wher is my hart becom.
            For well I feele, it is from hence a way,
            My Sences all, doth ſorrow ſo benumme:
            That abſent thus, I can not lyue a Day.
            I know for troth, there is a ſpecyall Place.
            Wher as it moſt, deſyreth for to bee:
            For Oft it leaues, me thus in Dolfull caſe,
            And hether cōmes, at length a gayne to me?
            Woldeſt thou ſo fayne, be tolde where is thy Hart
                  •
               
            
            Sir Foole in place, wher as it ſhuld not be:
            Tyed vp ſo faſt, that it can neuer ſtarte?
            
               Tyll Wyſdom get, agayne thy Lybertye:
            In place wher thou, as ſafe maiſt dwel ſwet daw?
            As may the harte, ly by the Lyons paw:
            And wher for thee, as much be ſure they paſſe:
            As dyd the maſter, ons for Eſops Aſſe.
         
         
            ¶ To Alexander Neuell.
            IF thou canſt baniſh Idlenes,
            
               Cupidoes Bowe is broke,
                  Guld.
               
            
            And well thou mayſt dyſpyſe hys bronds clean void of flame &amp; ſmoke
            What moued the kynge Agiſtus ons, to Loue with vyle exceſſe:
            The cauſe at hād doth ſtreight apeare he lyued in Idlenes.
            Finis.
         
         
            
            ¶The Aunſwere of A. Neuell to the ſame.
            THe lack of labour mayms yt mind,
            And wyt &amp; Reaſon quyght exiles.
            And Reaſon fled. Flames Fancy blind.
            And Fancy ſhe forthwith beguyles
            The Senſles wight: that ſwiftly ſails
            Through deepeſt fluds of vyle exces.
            Thus vice aboūds. Thus vertu quails
            By meanes of drowſy Idlenes.
         
         
            ¶To Mayſtreſſe D.
            NOt from the hye Cytherion Hyll nor from that Ladies throne
            Frō whēs flies forth ye winged boy yt makes ſome ſore to grone.
            But nearer hence this token coms, from out the Dongeon deepe,
            Where neuer Plutto yet dyd raygne nor Proſerpyne dyd ſleepe.
            
               Wheras thy faithful Seruaunt liues. whom duetie moues aryght,
            To wayle that he ſo long doth lacke, his owne deare Mayſtres ſyght.
         
         
            ¶ Out of an olde Poet.
            FYe Fye, I lothe to ſpeake wylt thou my luſt,
            Compell me nowe, to doo ſo foule an acte.
            Nay rather God, with Flame conſume to duſt.
            My carry on vyle, then I perfourme this facte
            Let rather thoughtes, that long, haue weryed me:
            Or ſycknes ſuche as Fancy fonde hath brought,
            O gapyng Hell, dryne me now downe to the,
            Let boylyng ſyghes, conſume me all to nought.
            
               ONs muſynge as I ſat, and Candle burnynge bye,
            When all were huſht I myght diſcern a ſymple ſelye Flye.
            ¶That flewe before myne eyes, with free reioyſynge Hart,
            And here &amp; there, with wings did play as voyde of payne and ſmart,
            ¶Somtyme by me ſhe ſat, when ſhe had playde her fyll,
            And euer when ſhe reſted had aboute ſhe flyttered ſtyll.
            ¶When I perceyud her well, reioyſyng in her place,
            O happy Flye quoth I, and eake, O worme in happy caſe.
            ¶Whiche two of vs is beſt? I that haue reaſon? no:
            But thou that reaſon art without and therwith voyde of woe.
            ¶ I lyue and ſo doſte thou, but I lyue all in payne,
            And Subiect am to her alas, that makes my Gryefe her gayne.
            
               WHen I do heare thy name, alas my hart doth ryſe:
            And ſeekes fourthwith to ſe the ſalue that moſt contētes myne eys.
            But when I ſe thy Face, that hath procured my payne,
            Then boyles my blud in euery part, and beates in euery vayne?
            Thy voice when I do heare, then collour comes and goes,
            Some tyme as pale as Earth I looke, ſome tyme as red as Roſe.
            If thy ſweete Face do ſmyle, then who ſo well as I?
            If thou but caſt a ſcornefull looke, then out alas I dye.
            But ſtyll I lyue in payne, my fortune wylleth ſo,
            That I ſhuld burne &amp; thou yet know, no whytt of all my wo.
            
               VNhappye tonge, why dydſte thou not cōſent
            When fyrſt myne eyes dyd vewe that Princely face,
            To ſhow good wyll, that hart oppreſt than ment.
            And whylſt tyme was, to ſewe for preſent grace.
            O fayntyng Hart, why dydſt thou then conceale?
            Thyne inwarde Fyers, that flamde in euery vayne,
            Whan pytie and gentlenes, were bent to heale.
            Why dydſt thou not, declare thy ragyng payne?
            When well thou mightſt haue moued her gentle mynde,
            Why dydſte thou than, kepe backe thy wofull playn?
            Thou knewſte full well, redres is hard to fynde,
            Whan in thy owne affayres, thy corage faynts.
            
               But ſynce ſhe is gon, bewaile thy grief no moore
            Synce thou thy ſelfe, wart Cauſer of the Soore.
         
         
            ¶Oculi augent dolorem. Out of ſyght, out of mynd.
            
               THe oftener ſene, the more I luſt,
               The more I luſt, the more I ſmart
               The more I ſmart, the more I truſt,
               The more I truſt, the heauyer hart,
               The heuy hart, breedes myne vnreſt,
               Thy abſence therfore, lyke I beſt.
            
            
               The rarer ſene, the leſſe in mynde,
               The leſſe in mynde, the leſſer payne,
               The leſſer payne, leſſe gryefe I fynd,
               The leſſer gryefe, tthe greater gayne,
               The greater gayne, the meryer I,
               Therfore I wyſh thy ſyght to flye.
            
            
               The further of, the more I ioye.
               The more I ioye, the happyer lyfe,
               
                  The happyer lyfe, leſſe hurts annoye
               The leſſer hurts, pleaſure moſt ryfe,
               Suche pleaſures ryfe, ſhall I obtayne
               Whē Diſtaūce doth depart vs twaine
               ¶Finis.
            
            
               ACcuſe not God, yf fancie fond, do moue thy foolyſh brayne,
               To wayle for loue, for thou thy ſelfe, art cauſe of all thy payne.
               ¶Finis.
            
            
               TWo Lynes ſhall tell the Gryefs that I by Loue ſuſtayne.
               I burne, I flame, I faynt, I fryſe, of Hell I feele the payne.
            
         
         
            ¶Of the vnfortunate choyſe of his Valentyne.
            THe Paynes that all the Furyes fell can caſt frō Lymbo lake,
            Eche Torment of thoſe Helliſh brains wher crawleth mani a ſnake,
            Eche miſchiefe that therrin doth lye eche ſmart that may be founde,
            
               Flye frō thoſe feendiſh clawe
                  •
                a whyle with flames breake vp the grounde,
            Lyght here vpon this curſed hand, make here your dwellyng place,
            And plague the part, ye durſt preſume his Mayſter to diſgrace.
            Whiche thruſt amongſt a nombre of: ſo many princely names,
            And wher thy Maiſtres had her place amongſt the chiefeſt Dames,
            Durſte thus preſume to leue her there and drawe a ſtraunger wyght,
            And by thyne owne vnhappy draught torment my pauled Spryght.
         
         
            ¶The vncertayntie of Lyfe.
            NO vayner thing ther can be foūd amyd this vale of ſtryfe,
            As Auncient men reporte haue made then truſte vncertayne lyfe.
            This trwe we dayly fynde, by proofes of many yeares,
            
               As anſwered well, vnto thy vertuous fame,
            The gentlenes that at thy handes I founde
            In ſtaungers houſe, all vnaquaynted I,
            Good S. hath my Hart to the ſo bounde,
            That from the can it not be forced to flye,
            In pledge wherof, my ſeruyce here I gyue
            Yf thou ſo wylte, to ſerue the whylſt I lyue.
         
         
            ¶Of Money.
            GYue Money me, take Frendſhyp who ſo lyſt,
            For Frends are gon come once Aduerſytie,
            When Money yet remayneth ſafe in Cheſt,
            
               That quickely can the bryng from myſerye,
            Fayre face ſhowe frendes, when ryches do habounde,
            Come tyme of proofe, farewell they muſt awaye,
            Beleue me well, they are not to be founde.
            If God but ſende the once a lowrynge daye.
            Golde neuer ſtarts aſyde, but in dyſtres,
            Fyndes wayes enoughe, to eaſe thyne heuynes.
         
         
            ¶Goyng towardes Spayne.
            FArewell thou fertyll ſoyle, that Brutus fyrſt out founde,
            Whē he pooreſoule, was driuen clean frō out his Coūtrey groūd.
            That Northward layſt thy luſty ſides amyd the ragyng Seas.
            
               Whoſe welthy Land doth foſter vpp, thy people all in eaſe,
            While others ſcrape &amp; carke abroad, theyr ſymple foode to gett,
            And ſelye Soules take all for good, that cōmeth to the Net.
            Which they with painfull paynes dopych, in barrain burning Realmes:
            While we haue all with out reſtreint among thy welthy ſtreames.
            O bleſt of God thou Pleaſaunt Ile, where welth her ſelf doth dwell:
            Wherin my tender yeares I paſt, I byd thee now farewell.
            For Fancy dryues me forth abrode, and byds me take delyght,
            In leuyng thee and raungyng far, to ſe ſome ſtraunger ſyght.
            And ſayth I was not framed heare, to lyue at home with eas:
            But paſſynge foorth for knowledge ſake to cut the fomyng ſeas.
         
         
            
            ¶At Bonyuall in Fraunce.
            O Fond affectyon, wounder of my Hart,
            When wylt thou Ceaſe, to breed my reſtles payne,
            When comes the end, of this my Cruell ſmart:
            When ſhall my force, beate backe thy force agayne.
            When ſhall I ſaye, this reſtles rage of myne:
            By Reaſon ruld, is banyſht quyte a way,
            And I eſcaped, theſe cruell bondes of thyne:
            O flamynge ſeend, that ſeakeſt my decaye.
            Safe thynkyng I, 
                  
                     •
                  haribdis Rage to flye,
            On Scyll a Rocke, in Bonyuall I dye.
         
         
            
            ¶ Commynge home warde out of Spayne.
            O Ragyng Seas, and myghty Neptunes rayn
                  •
               
               ▪
            
            In monſtrous Hylles, that throweſt thy ſelfe ſo hye,
            That wyth thy ſludes, doeſt beate the ſhores of Spayne:
            And breake the Clyues, that dare thy force enuie.
            Ceaſe now thy rage, and laye thyne Ire a ſyde,
            And thou that haſt, the gouernaunce of all,
            O myghty God, graunt Wether Wynd and Tyde,
            Tyll in my Countreye Coaſt, our Anker fall.
         
         
            
            ¶To L. Blundeſton of Ingratitude.
            THe lytell Byrde, the tender Marlyon,
            That vſeth ofte vpon the Larke to praye,
            With great reproche, doth ſtayne the mynde of man
            If all be true, that Wryters of her ſaye.
            For ſhe a Creature, maymde of Reaſons parte,
            And framde to lyue accordynge to her kynde,
            Doth ſeme to foſter Reaſon in her Hart
            And to aſpyre vnto Deuyner mynde.
            When Hungers rage ſhe hath exyled quyte,
            And ſupped well as falleth for her ſtate.
            
               The ſelye Larke, doth take by force of flyght,
            And hyes to tree, where as ſhe lodged late,
            And on the tremblyng Byrde all nyght ſhe ſtondes,
            To keepe her feete, from force of nyppynge colde,
            The amazed Wretche, within her ēnemyes handes,
            And cloſed faſt, within the claſpyng holde.
            Awayteth Death, with drowſye drowpyng Hart,
            And all the nyght with feare drawes on her lyfe,
            The gentle Byrde, whan darkenes doth departe
            Doth not depryue, the ſelye ſoule of lyfe,
            Nor fylles with her her hungred egre breſt
            But wayeng well, the ſeruyce ſhe hath done.
            
               To ſpyll the Blud, her Nature doth deteſt,
            And from ſo great a Cryme, her ſelfe doth ſhun.
            She lets her go and more with ſtedfaſt eyes.
            Beholds whiche way ſhe takes with mazed flyght,
            And in thoſe partes that Daye ſhe neuer flyes
            Leaſte on that Byrde agayne ſhe chaunce to lyght.
            Loe, Blundſton heare how kyndenes doth habounde,
            In ſelye Soules where Reaſon is exylde,
            This Byrde alone ſuffyſeth to confounde,
            The Brutyſh myndes of men that are defyled,
            With that great Vice, that vyle and haynous Cryme
            Ingratitude (whiche ſome vnkyndenes call.)
            
               That Poyſon ſtrong that ſpryngeth ſtyll with tyme,
            Tyll at the length, it hath infected all.
         
         
            ¶The Aunſwere of L. Blundeſton to the ſame.
            THis Mirrour left of this thy Byrde I fynde,
            Hath not ſuche force, to enter in the Hert,
            To roote away, Vnthankefulnes of minde,
            As others haue, the Vertues to peruert, (ſo prone we are to Vice:)
            The Tenche by kynd, hath Salue for euery Soore,
            And heales the maymed Pike in his dyſtreſſe,
            
               The Churlyſh Pike fo Gentlenes therfore,
            In his rewarde, doth Crueltie expreſſe.
            His murdring mynde, his fylthy ſpotted fayth,
            When hungre prickes to fyll his gredye Iawes,
            He grypes his poore Chyrurgion vnto death.
            Who late to hym of lyfe was onely cauſe.
            Thy Merlians haue fewe Ayryes in our ground
            But Pikes haue Spawnes good ſtoore in euery Pound
         
         
            ¶To the Tune of Appelles.
            
               THe ruſhyng Ryuers that do run
               The valeys ſweet adourned new
               That leans their ſides againſt ye Sun
               wt Flours freſh of ſūdry hew,
               
                  Both Aſhe and Elme, and Oke ſo hye,
               Do all lament my wofull crye.
            
            
               while winter blak, wt hydious ſtormes
               Doth ſpoil ye groūd of Sōmers grene,
               while ſpringtime ſweet ye leaf returns
               That late on tree could not be ſene,
               while ſōmer burns while harueſt raīs
               Stil ſtyl do rage my reſtles paynes.
            
            
               No ende I find in all my ſmart,
               But endles torment I ſuſtayne
               Synce fyrſt alas, my wofull Hart
               By ſight of the was forſt to playne,
               Synce that I loſt my Lybertie,
               Synce that thou madſte a Slaue of me
            
            
               My Hart that once abroade was free
               Thy Beautie hath in durance brought
               Ons reaſon rulde and guyded me,
               And now is wyt cōſumde wt thought
               Ons I reioyſed aboue the Skye,
               And now for the I alas I dye.
            
            
               
               Ons I reioyſed in Companye,
               And now my chief and whole delyght
               Is from my frendes awaye to flye
               And keepe alone my weryed ſpryght
               Thy face deuyne and my deſyre,
               Frō fleſh hath me tranſformed to fyre.
            
            
               O Nature thou that fyrſt dyd frame,
               My Ladyes heare of pureſt Golde
               Her face of Cryſtall to the ſame.
               Her lippes of precious Rubyes molde
               Her necke of Alablaſter whyte
               Surmountyng far eche other Wight
            
            
               Why dydſt thou not that tyme deuiſe
               Why dydſt thou not foreſe before?
               The miſchyefe that therof doth ryſe,
               And grief on grief doth heap with ſtor
               To make her Hart of War alone,
               And not of Flynt and Marble Stone.
            
            
               O Lady ſhowe thy fauour yet,
               Let not thy Seruaunt dye for the
               Where Rygour rulde, let Mercye ſyt
               
                  Let Pytie Conquere Crueltie,
               Let not Diſdain, a Feend of Hell,
               Poſſes the place, wher Grace ſhuld dwell.
            
         
         
            ¶Cupido Conquered.
            THe ſweeteſt time of al the yeare it was when as the Sonne,
            Had newly entred Gemini, and warmynge heate begun:
            Whan euery tre was clothed greene, and flowers fayre dyd ſhow,
            And when the whyt and blowmynge May on Hawthorns thicke did grow,
            Whan ſore I longd to ſeeke a broade, to ſe ſome Pleaſaunt ſyght,
            A mid my woes and heauye happes, that myght my Mynde delyght,
            Care wold not let me byde within, but forſt me foorth to go:
            And bad me ſeeke ſume preſent helpe, for to relyue my wo.
            
               Than forward went I foorth in haſte, to vew the garnyſht trees?
            What tyme the Son was moūted vp, twirt nyne and ten degrees.
            From Flowers flew ſweete ayers abroad, delighting much my brayn,
            With ſyght &amp; ſmels ga
                  •
                
               
                  •
               orow fade, and Ioy returne agayne.
            So that in mynde I much reioyce, to feele my ſelf ſo lyght:
            For gorgyous ſyghtes &amp; odours ſweet had new reuyued my ſpryght.
            Beſyde the pleaſaunt Harmonye, that ſyngyng Byrdes did make:
            Bad me pul vpp my Hart agayne, and ſorrow ſone forſake.
            For though (quoth Reaſon.) ſhe be gon on whom thy Lyfe dependes,
            Yet fond it is to carke and care where there is none amendes.
            Thus foorth I went, &amp; in the grooues I raunged heare and theare,
            Wheras I hard ſuche pleaſaūt tunes as Heauen had ben neare.
            
               I thynke that if Amphion hadde, ben preſent ther to playe,
            Or if Sir Orph
                     •
                  us myght haue hel
                  •
               , his Harp, that preſent day.
            Or if Apoll
                     •
                  
                with his Lute, had ſtryuen to excell,
            None of them all, by Muſycke ſholde, haue borne away the Bell.
            I rather iudge the thracian wold, his Harpe wherwi
                  •
               h he played,
            Haue caſt a way as one whom Ire, had vtterly diſmayed.
            Such paſſyng tunes of ſundry Byrds, I neuer herd before,
            The further I went in the Woods. the noyſe reſounded more.
            O happy Byrdes quoth I what lyfe, is this that you do leade,
            How far from Care and myſery, how far from Feare and dread:
            With what reioyſynge melodie, paſſ
                  •
                you this fadyng Lyfe,
            While Man vnhappieſt creatur liues In wretched toyle and ſtryfe.
            
               Styll foorth I went and wonderd at, this pleſaunt Harmony.
            And gaſed at theſe lytle Fooles, that made ſuche Melody:
            Tyll at the length I gan to ſpye, a ſtately Lawrell tree,
            So plaſt and ſett in ſuch a guyſe, That as it ſeamed to me,
            Dame Nature ſtroue to ſhew her ſelf in plantyng ſuch a thyng,
            For Euen out beſyde the rocke, a fountayne cleane did ſpryng,
            Where in the water I beheld, reſembled wonderous trew,
            The Whyte &amp; Greene of al the trees, adourned late of new.
            And how in order eake they ſtood, a goodly ſyght to ſe,
            And there I might diſcerne the Byrds that ſonge in euery tree.
            To moue the Byll &amp; ſhake the wings in vteryng Muſicke ſweete
            And heare and thear, to flye to feade, and efteſones theare to meete.
            
               Great pleaſure had I there to byde, and ſtare vpon the Spryng,
            For why me thought it dyd ſurmount, eache other kynde of thyng.
            Now was the Son got vp aloft, and raught the mydle Lyne,
            And in the Well, the Golden Gloobe, with flamyng Beames dyd ſhyne,
            Wherof the Bryghtnes was ſo great that I might not endure,
            Lenger to looke within the Spryng, whoſe waters were ſo pure.
            Vnwyllyng went I thence away, and vnderneth the tree,
            I laid me down whoſe braūches brode dyd keepe the Son from me.
            Thynkyng to reſt me there a whyle, tyll fallyng ſome degrees▪
            
            Syr Phebus ſhuld haue hyd hym ſelf, behynde the ſhadowyng trees,
            And thē for to haue vewd the Spring, and marked euery place,
            And ſeene yf there I could haue ſpied the weepyng Biblis face.
            
               For ſure I thynke, it was the place, wherein Narciſſus dyed,
            Or els the Well, to which was turnd poore Biblis whyle ſhe cryed.
            But whether it was werynes, with labour that I tooke,
            Or Fume y• frō the Spryng dyd ryſe, wherin I late dyd looke.
            Or yf it were the ſweete accorde that ſyngyng Byrdes dyd keepe,
            Or what it was, I knowe no whit but I fell faſt a ſleepe.
            I thynke the woddy Nimphes agreed that I ſhuld haue this chaūce,
            And that it was theyr pleaſure ſo, to ſhowe me thyngs in traunce.
            Whilſte I lay thus in ſlumbre deepe. I myght perceyue to ſtande,
            A Perſon clothed all in whyte, that held a Rod in hande.
            Whiche was me thought of Maſſey Gold, I knew it very weale,
            For that was it, made Argos ſleepe, whyle he dyd Io ſteale.
            
               When I perceaued by his attyre, that it was Mercuri.
            
            My Hart at fyrſt began to faynt, yet at the length quo
                  •
               h I
            Thou Goddeſſe Son, why ſtandſte y• there what buſines now wt thee,
            What meaneſt yu in thy flying weed, For to appeare to me,
            And therwithall my thought I ſtaied, and could no farther ſpeake,
            For Feare did force my ſpech to fayle, and Courage wared weake.
            Which whan the sone of Maia ſawe, he tooke me by the hand,
            Looke vp quoth he be not affrayed: but boldly by me ſtand.
            The Muſes all of Helicon, haue fent me now to thee:
            Whō thou doeſt ſerue &amp; whoſe yu ſekſt For euer more to be.
            And thankes to the by me they ſende, Bycauſe thou tookeſt payne,
            In theyr Affaires (a thankeles thyng) 
                  〈…〉
                
               
                  ••
               ayne.
            
               Deſyring thee not for to ſtaye, for Momus ill report,
            But endyng that thou haſt begun, to ſpyte the Canckred ſorte.
            And thynk not thou, that thou art he, that canſt eſcape Diſdayne.
            The day ſhall come when thankfull men, ſhall well accept thy Paine,
            But rather lay before thyne eyes, the hie attemptes of thoſe,
            Whoſe ſtatly ſtyle wt painfull proofe, theyr worthy wytes diſcloſe,
            Marke him that thundred out ye deeds grace, Of olde Anchifes ſun,
            Whoſe English verſe gyues Maroes In all that he hath done,
            Whoſe death the Muſes ſorrow much, that lacke of aged dayes,
            Amongeſt the cōmon Brytons old, ſhould hynder Virgils prayſe.
            Mark him y• hath wel framde a Glaſſe▪ for ſtates to looke vpon,
            Whoſe labour ſhews the ends of thē, that lyued long a gone.
            
               Marke hym that ſhowes ye Tragedies thyne owne famylyar Frende,
            By whom ye Spaniards hawty Style in Englyſh Verſe is pende.
            Marke these same three, &amp; other moe, whoſe doyngs well are knowne,
            Whoſe fayre attempts in euery place The flying fame hath blowne,
            Haſt thou not harde, thy ſelfe in place full ofte and many a tyme,
            Lo here the Auctor loſeth grace, Loe here a doltyſh Ryme,
            Now ſyth that they haue this reward who paſſe the euen as farre,
            As in the nyght Diana doth, Excell the dimmeſt Starre.
            Take thou no ſcorne at euyll tongs, what neadst thou to diſdayne?
            Syth they whō none can well amend haue lyke fruyte of theyr payne.
            Moreouer yet the Ladyes nyne, haue all cōmaunded me,
            Bycauſe they know, the blynded God hath ſome thyng pearced the.
            
               To leade the foorth, a thyng to ſee, yf all thyngs happen ryght,
            Whiche ſhall gyue the occaſion good, with ioyfull mynde to wryght.
            To this, I wold haue anſwered fayne and theare began to ſpeake,
            But as my words were cōmyng forth my purpoſe he dyd breake.
            Come on (quoth he,) none Aunſwere now we may no lenger ſtaye.
            But frame thy selfe, to flye abroade, for hence we muſt awaye.
            And here withall, on both my ſydes, two wyngs me thought dyd growe,
            Of mighty breadth, away went he, and after hym I flowe.
            And euer as we mounted vp, I lookte vpon my wyngs,
            And prowde I was, me thought to ſee ſuche vnacquaynted thyngs.
            Tyll foorth we flewe, my Guyde &amp; I, with mowntyng flyght apace,
            Beholdyng Ryuers, woods, &amp; Hylles and many a goodly place.
            
               Till at the length me thought I might a Gorgyous Caſtell ſpye,
            Thear downe began my guyd to fall, and downward eake fell I,
            Lo heare the place where yu muſt light Gan Mercury to ſaye,
            Farwell and note what thou dooſt ſe, for I must hence away.
            And with this ſame a way flewe he, and left me there alone,
            Wher as with Feare a maſde I ſtood, and thus began to moue.
            Alas where am I now become, what Curſed Chaunce hath blown,
            Me from the place where I was bred, to Countreis heare vnknown.
            What ment that fell vnhappy Feend, that Maía brought to lyght,
            To bring me from my Hartes deſyre, to ſee thys dolefull ſyght.
            Vnhappy Wretche, I wolde I hadde, his Perſon heare in hand,
            Then ſhuld I wreak mine Ire of him, that brought me to this Land.
            
               But all to late alas I wyſh, for words auayle not nowe,
            Tis beſt to learne, what place it is, and yet I knowe not howe.
            Alas that here were P
                     •
                  h
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  me, with Compaſſe Globe in hande,
            Whose Arte ſhuld ſhowe me true the place &amp; Clymate where I ſtande,
            Well yet what soeuer chaūce theron what soeuer Realme it be,
            You Caſtell wyll I vyſyte ſure, hap what hap wyll to me.
            Thus much me thought alone I ſpoke▪ and then I forewarde went,
            And curſed eke an hundred folde, them that me thyther ſent.
            Thus to the Ca
                  •
               tell, ſtrayght I came, whiche when I vewde aboute,
            And ſawe the workmanſhyp therof full gorgeouſlye ſet oute.
            I entred in, with fearefull Harte, muche doutyng howe to ſpeede,
            But euer hope of happye chaunce, my heauye Hart 
                  •
               yd fee
                  •
               e.
            
               Wyde was the Courte &amp; large within the walles were rayſed hye,
            And all engraued with Storyes fayre of coſtlye Imagrye.
            There myght I ſe, wt wondrous Arte, the Picture porturde playne,
            Of olde Orion Hunter good, whom Scorpions vyle had ſlayne.
            And by hym ſtoode his Borſpeare and his other Inſtruments,
            His Net, his Darte, his Courſar, and his Hunters reſtyng Tents.
            And vnder hym was wrytten fayre, in Letters all of Golde,
            Here lies he ſlain, wt Scorpions ſting, vnhappy wretche that wolde,
            Haue forced the Ladye of this forte with ſtayne of Royaltie.
            To haue conſented to his wyll, in fylthye Lecherye.
            Wherfore beware that enters here, what ſoeuer man thou art?
            Accounte thy ſelfe but loſt, yf that thou bearſte a lecherous Hart.
            
               Whē I had vewd theſe wrytten lines and markde the Storye well,
            I ioyed muche, for why I knew, Dìana there dyd dwell.
            
               Diana ſhe that Goddeſſe is, of Virgyns ſacred mynde,
            By whom Orion Hunter wylde, his Fatall ende dyd fynde.
            Next vnto hym, I myght beholde, Acteon wofull wyght,
            In what a maner, all to torne, his cruell Dogs hym dyght.
            There might be ſeene, theyr gredye mouths wt Maiſters blud embrued,
            And all his owne vnhappye men, that faſt theyr Lorde purſued.
            And many Storyes more there war engraued: to long to tell.
            What fearefull haps to many men, for luſt vncleane befell.
            Thus as I ſtoode with muſyng mind beholdyng all thyngs theare,
            In ruſheth at the Gate behynde a Poſt with heauy cheare.
            
               〈2 pages missing〉
            
            
               Aboue them all I myght beholde, as placed before the reſt,
            
               Hipolitus whom Phedraes ſpyte? moſt Cruelly had dreſt.
            
               Hipolitus the vnſpotted Pearle: of pure Virginitie,
            Whoſe noble Hart culd not agre, to ſtepdames vyllany.
            Next vnto hym ſat Continence, and next was Labour placed?
            Of bodie bygge and ſtrong he was, and ſomwhat Crabtre faced.
            Next hym was placed Abſtinence, a leane vnwyldy wyght,
            Whoſe Diet thyn had baniſht cleane, all fond and vayne delyght.
            A Thouſād more me thought ther war whoſe names I did not know,
            And yf I did to longe it were, in Verſes them to ſhow.
            Down of his knees the meſſenger, before them al doth fall,
            And vnto chaſt Diana thear, for ſuccour thus doth call.
            
               O Goddeſſe chiefe of Chaſtitie, and Sacred Virgins mynd:
            Let Pitie from your noble Hart: redreſſe for Miſers fynd.
            Let not our weryed Hartes ſuſtaine, ſuche wrongfull Tyranye?
            Quench quickly now the fyrie flames of open Iniurye.
            This ſayd for Feare he ſtaied awhyle, and than began agayne,
            A myghty Prynce (quoth he) is com, with great vnruly trayne.
            All armed well at euery poynt, (a dredefull ſyght to ſe:)
            And euery man in feates of armes, ryght skylfull all they be.
            The Captaine chyfe in Charyot ryde with pompe and ſtately Pryde:
            With Bow in hand of gliſtring gold, and Quyuer by his ſyde.
            Wher many a ſhaft full ſharp doth ly: and many a mortall Darte,
            That hath wt poyſoned force deſtroid, Full many a yealdyng Harte.
            
               He entred hath within your Realme, and taken many a Forte,
            Hath ſakte them all, and ſpoyled them quyte &amp; ſlayne a wondrous forte.
            In ſtraungeſt guyſe, for where he ſhoots the woūde doth feſter ſtyll
            And all the Surgians that we haue can not remoue the yll,
            In lytell tyme the gryefe ſo ſore, doth growe in euery parte,
            Diſtraynyng through the venomed vaines doth ſo torment the Hart.
            That ſome to ryd them ſelues therof in fluds full deepe they leape,
            And drown thē ſelues ſom downward falles from Houſes hye by heape,
            Some Anker caſt on croſſed Beames to ryd them ſelues from ſtryfe,
            And hang them ſelues full thycke on trees to ende a wretched lyfe.
            And they whoſe fearefull mynds dare not thus make an ende of wo,
            With greuous flames, conſumynge long theyr lyfe at length forgo.
            
               Loe here the Sōme of all I haue, this Tygre vs anoyes,
            And cruellye hath ſpoyled vs, of all our wonted ioyes.
            Whom yf your Grace, do not repuls, and fynde ſome preſent ſtaye,
            Vndoubtedly he wyll wyn this Realme, and take vs all awaye.
            At this, the Ladyes all amazde for feare dyd looke full pale,
            And all beheld with mazed eyes, the Wretche that tolde the tale.
            Tyll at the length Hìpolitus of Hart and courage hye,
            Nothyng abaſhde, with ſodain newes began thus to replye.
            Caſte fere away, fayre Dames (quoth he) diſmaye your ſelues no more,
            I know by whō this miſchief ſpryngs and know a helpe therfore.
            It is not ſuche a dredefull Wyght, as he doth here reporte,
            That entred is within theſe partes, and plagues the ſymple ſorte.
            
               Nor is his force ſo great to feare, I know it I full well:
            It is the ſcornfull blynded Boy, that neare to vs doth dwell.
            Whom Mars long tyme a go begott, of that Laſciuious dame:
            That Linckt in Chaines for Lechery, receaued an open ſhame.
            A diſobedient blynded Foole, that durſt preſume to turne:
            His dartes agaynſt his mother ons, and cauſd her ſore to burne.
            An auncient foo: to all this Court, Of long tyme he hath ben:
            And hath attempted euermore, by this: Renowne to wyn.
            His cruell Hart, of Pitie voyed, doth ſpare no kynd of age:
            But tender youth and dotyng age, he ſtrykes in furyous rage.
            And laughes to scorne the ſely ſoules that he hath wounded ſo,
            No Fine appoynted of theyr ils, no end of al theyr wo.
            
               But ſyns he hath preſumed thus, to entre heare in Place,
            And heare to threten Conqueſts thus, agaynſt Dianaes Grace,
            Let him beſure his loftie Mynde, this deade ſhall ſoone repent,
            If that your grace do here agre, with Fre and full concent.
            To make me Cheftain of this Charge and whom I lyſt to choſe,
            If Prisoner heare I bryng hym not, Let me myne Honour loſe.
            And there he ceaſde with ioyfull looks the Ladyes ſmyled all,
            And thorough his wordes they hoaped ſoone to ſe Cupidoes fall.
            With heauenly voice Diana thear, as chyefe aboue the reſt:
            This wiſe her words began to frame, From out her ſacred breſt.
            My good Hipolitus quoth ſhe, whoſe true and faythfull mynd:
            In doubtfull daunger often I, do alwayes redy fynd.
            
               For to reuenge the cankred rage, of all my ſpytfull foes,
            Thou be frō whoſe vn
                  ••
               otted hart, the fluddes of vertue flowes.
            whoſe ſeruiſe long hath ben aproued, within this court of myne,
            Reſtrayne this boyes vnruly rage, by valyant means of thyne,
            I geue the leaue &amp; thee appoint, my cheyf Lieutenant here,
            Chuſe whom yu wilt take whom yu lyſt, thou nedeſt no whit to feare.
            With this he roſe from out his place, and lokynge round a bout:
            Choſe Abſtinence and Cont
                     •••••
                  , with Labour Captayne ſtout.
            And with theſe thre he tooke his leaue of all the Ladyes there,
            Who doubtyng of his ſafe returne, let fall full many a teare.
            He lefte them theare in heauynes, and made no more delaye,
            But outward went &amp; toward ye Cāpe, he tooke the neareſt way.
            
               With this the Queenes commyſſion ſtraight was ſent abroad in haſte,
            To rayſe vp ſouldiars round about, and with theyr Captayne plaſte.
            To bring them foorth &amp; marching on, Hipolitus to meet.
            Than ſounded Trumpetes al a broad, and Drumes in euery ſtreat.
            And ſouldiears good lyke ſwarmes of Bees theyr Captains preaſe about
            All armed braue in Corſletes white, they march with courage ſtout.
            And forwarde ſhoue, till at the length where as theyr marſhall lyes,
            They fynd the place the ioifull ſoūds, Do mount aboue the ſkyes.
            
               Hipolitus receaued them all, with woordes of pleſaunt cheare,
            And placith them in good aray, bycauſe the camp was neare.
            Three Battails big of them he frams, and of the Rereward ſtrong,
            Hath Labour charge who ſteppeth foorth, before the ſtatlye thronge:
            
               And Captayn of the reare ward next, was placed abſtinens.
            And Ioind to him for Policie, was Captayne Continence:
            The Battayle mayne Hipolitus, him ſelfe did chuſe to guyd.
            And in the formeſt front therof, on Courſer fayre doth ryde:
            The Trumpets ſound march on apace, and Dromes the ſame do ſtryke.
            Then forward moues ye Army great, In order Martiall lyke.
            I cam behynde (me thought) and beſt, it ſeamed then to me:
            To vew the dynt of dreedfull ſword, and feyghter none to be.
            Thie Spies were ſent abroad to vew, the place where Cupíde lay:
            A longeſt a Ryuer fayre and broad, they ſpye a pleaſaunt way,
            Which waye they tooke and paſſynge foorth, at length apeares a plaine:
            Both large &amp; vaſt wher
                  •
                lyes ye rowt, of Cruell Cupides trayne.
            
               Thus told the ſpyes we onward hye, and ſtrayght in ſyght we haue,
            The ferfull ſhow of all our Foes, and dredfull army braue.
            The firſt y• marched frō 
               Cupides Camp was drowſy Idlenes.
            
            The chyefeſt frend that loue had then, the next was vyle Exc
                     •
                  s.
            
            A Lubbour great, miſhapen moſt, of all that thear I ſaw,
            As much I thynk in quantitie, as hores ſyxe can draw.
            A myghty face both broad and flat, and all with Rubies ſet:
            Muche noſed lyke a Turky Cocke, with teth as blacke as Get.
            A Belye▪ byg, full truſt with guts, and Peſtels two, lyke Poſtes,
            A knaue full ſquare in euery poynt, a Prynce of dronken Doſtes.
            Vpon a Camell couched hye, for Horſe coulde none hym beare,
            A mighty Staffe in hande he had, his Foes a farre to feare.
            
               Behynde them all, the blynded God, doth com in Charyot fayre,
            With ragyng flames flong rounde about he peſtres all the ayre.
            And af
                  •
               er hym, for tryumphe leades a thouſande wounded Harts,
            That gush abrode hot ſtreams of blud new perſed with his Dartes,
            The army redy for to meete and all at poynt to fyght,
            
               Hipolitu
                     •
                  
                with luſty cheare and with a noble Spryght.
            His Souldiers to encourage. Thus his wordes begyns to place.
            My valyaunt frends and Subiects all of Chaſt Dianaes Grace.
            whoſe noble Harts were neuer ſtaind with ſpot of Daſtards mynd,
            Behold our enemyes here at hande, behold you coward blynd.
            Of lytle force, comparde with you howe in a fond araye,
            They ſtragle out no ordre dewe, obſerued in theyr waye.
            
               Behold what goodly Guyds they haue to gouerne them withall,
            That neuer knew what fighting ment but lyue to Venus thrall.
            Marke hym that guyds the rerewarde there that vyle deformed Churle,
            Whoſe foggy Mates, with paunches ſyde do thycke aboute him whurle.
            And he that formoſt hether coms loe what a handſome Squyre,
            Sure full vnapt to kepe the felde, more fyt to ſyt by the fyre.
            In fyne lo Victorye at hande with hye tryumphant Crowne,
            Bent for to spoyle our Foes of Fame, and caſt theyr Glorye downe.
            Fyght therfore now courageouſlye, and ryd your frendes of feare,
            Declare your Manhod valyauntly, and let your Harts appeare.
            With this the ſounde begyns to moūt and noyſe hye to ryſe,
            And warlyke tunes begyn to daſh, them ſelues agaynſt the Skyes.
            
               The Canons Cracke, begins to roor
                  •
                and Darts full thycke they flye
            And couerd thycke, the armyes both, and framde a Counter Skye.
            And now the Battayls both be ioynde with ſtroke of Hande to trye.
            The quarell iuſt and for to fynde, where Victory
                     •
                  
                doth lye,
            The Souldyers all of Idl
                     •
                  nes, where Labour coms, do fall,
            And wounded ſore, by force of hym, all bathde in blud, they ſprall.
            Hym ſelfe alone with Idl
                     •
                  nes nowe hande to hande doth fyght
            And after many a mortall wounde, deſtroyes the ſelye wyght.
            Then ioynes with him Syr A
                     •
                  ſtinence with ayde &amp; ſuccours newe,
            And both vpon the greſye Hoaſte, of Glottonye they flewe.
            The Captayn doth aduaunce hymſelf with Abſtinence to meete,
            The vnweldy Creature ſmitten there is tombled vnder feete.
            
               Than Fancie flyes Incontinence and all C
                     •
                  pidoes frendes.
            Beholdynge Fortune thus to frowne, by flyght them ſelfe defendes.
            
               Cupido whan he ſees hymſelfe, thus ſpoylde of all his ayde,
            The chyef Supporters of his Courte, ſo ſodaynly decayde.
            Bad turne his Charyottes than with haſte and faſt away he flyes,
            Amongſt the chaſte Hipolitus on ſwyftye Courſer hyes,
            Than all with Ioye they after run, downe thycke the enemyes fall,
            The blinded boy, for ſuccour ſtraight to V
                     •
                  nus hye doth call,
            But all his cryes auayleth not, his Foes hym faſt purſewe,
            The dryuer of his Charyot ſoone, Hip
                     •
                  litus there ſlewe.
            And down frō Horſe, the wretche doth fall. The horſes ſpoyld of guyde,
            A Souldier ſtoute of Reasons bande, is wylled there to ryde.
            
               Who turyng Raynes another waye reſtrayns hym of his flyght,
            His Honours loſt and taken thus, Cupide in dolfull plyght.
            Theſe wordes with tremblyng voyce began ſyth Fortune thus quoth he,
            Hath giuen her doome from doubtfull breſt &amp; turnd her Grace from me.
            Syth that the moſt miſfortune nowe, that euer I could fynd,
            Hath chaunced to me and Myſer I, by Deſtenyes aſſygnde.
            Am Captyue heare, conſydre yet, what Fortune myght haue wrought
            And made a Canquerer of me, and you in Bondage brought.
            Conſydre yet the wofull plyght, wher in you had remaynd,
            If that the Gods my happy ſtate, had not ſo ſore diſdaynd,
            And by your Gryef, than meſure mine ſhowe mercye in this caſe,
            That Conquerour cōmended is, who gyues to pytie place.
            
               The cruell mynd diſprayſed is, In euery kynd of ſtate,
            No man to hauty lyues on earth, but ons may fynd his mate.
            Theſe wordes Hipolitus I ſpeake, to bread no farther ſtryfe,
            I ſpeake not this of malyce heare, my fute is for my lyfe.
            Syth Fortune thus hath fauord you, graunt thys my ſmall requeſt,
            And let me lyue yf mercy dwell, within your Noble breſt,
            By this tyme Morphens had diſperſt the drowſy Clowd of ſleape,
            And frō my braynes the quyet traūce, began full faſt to Creape.
            And dounward fell. I wakd therwith and lokyng round a bout,
            Long tyme I muſed where I was, my mynd was ſtyl in doubt.
            Tyll at the length I vewde the tree, and place where as I ſat,
            And well beheld the pleaſaūt Spryng that late I wondred at.
            
               
that late I wondred at,
            I ſawe beſyde the Golden Globe, of Phebus ſhynyng bryght,
            That Weſtwarde halfe, dyd hyde his face approchyng faſt the nyght.
            Eche Byrde began to ſhrowd hymſelf in tree to take his reſt
            And ceaſte the pleasaunt tunes yt late proceaded from theyr Breaſte.
            I homewarde went, and left them all, and reſtles all that nyght,
            I musynge laye, tormented thus, with fond lamentyng spryght.
            When Phebus roſe to paſſe the tyme, and paſſe my gryefe awaye
            I toke my Pen and pend the Dreame that made my Muſes ſtaye.
            ¶Finis.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶Imprynted at London in S. Brydes Churchyarde, by Thomas 
               
                  〈◊〉
               , for Raufe Nevvbery.
            And are to be ſold at his ſhop in Fleeteſtrete, a lytle aboue the Conduit.
            1563. 15 Die Menſis March.
         
         
            
            ¶Faultes eſcaped in the Pryntynge.
            ¶In ye .5. Eglog, for Agon rede Egon. ¶In the .6. Eglog for Calicto, reade Caliſto. ¶In ye .7. Eglog, for Duerda and Guerda, reade Diana, For Siluanus reade Siluan. For Seluagina, reade Seluagia.
            ¶In the .2. Epytaphe, for ſoore, reade ſure. ¶In. H. the .2. Page, &amp; .15. lyne, for in, reade on. H. v. Page .1. lyne, for fo, reade for .4. lyne, for Cruelty, rede cruellye. ¶In. K .5. Page .12. lyne, for hores, reade Horses.
             ¶Reade theſe .8. Lynes at the ende of the Sonet. Ons muſyng. &amp;c.
            ¶Thou lyueſt, but feelſt no gryefe, no Loue doth the torment,
            A happye thynge for me it were, If God were ſo content.
            That thou with Pen, wert placed here and I ſat in thy place,
            Then I ſhuld Ioye as thou doſt nowe and thou ſhuldſt wayle thy caſe.
            
         
      
   

