
   
      
         
            The man for heaven A sermon preached at the court to his Majesties houshold, anno Domini, 1637. By Iohn Gore, rector of Wendenlofts, and preacher of S. Peters in Cornhill, London.
            Gore, John, Rector of Wendenlofts, Essex.
         
         
            
               1639
            
         
         Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01937
            STC 12073
            ESTC S103329
            99839086
            99839086
            3482
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01937)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3482)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1547:05)
         
         
            
               
                  The man for heaven A sermon preached at the court to his Majesties houshold, anno Domini, 1637. By Iohn Gore, rector of Wendenlofts, and preacher of S. Peters in Cornhill, London.
                  Gore, John, Rector of Wendenlofts, Essex.
               
               [4], 23, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by R. Bishop, for Thomas Alchorn, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Green Dragon in Pauls Church-yard,
                  London :
                  1639.
               
               
                  With a preliminary imprimatur leaf.
                  Reissued as part of his "Certayn sermons", 1639.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            Imprimatur.
            
               THOMAS WYKES.
               
                  Octob. 9. 1638.
            
         
         
            
            THE MAN FOR HEAVEN.
            A Sermon Preached at the Court to his Majeſties Houſhold, Anno Domini, 1637.
            By IOHN GORE, Rector of Wendenlofts, and Preacher of S. Peters in Cornhill, LONDON.
            LONDON, Printed by R. Biſhop, for Thomas Alchorn, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Green Dragon in Pauls Church-yard▪ 1639.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            The Man for Heaven.
            
               PHILIP. 3. 20.
               Our converſation is in Heaven, from whence alſo wee looke for the Saviour, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.
            
            
               YEE Honourable and Honoured Courtiers, here is a Text of Scripture fit for perſons of your rank and quality. A text that will learn you ſo to demean your ſelves, ſo to order your Converſation in this World, that after you have been Courtiers on Earth, you may be Courtiers in Heaven; after you have converſed with men, you may converſe with God; after you have ſerved and attended our gracious King and Queene below, you may be preferred and taken up by the Angels of Heaven to accompany and attend the King of Glory above.

Certainly, if there be an 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                an Heaven upon Earth, an Eſtate of Majeſty, Height and Glory; Heare it is, and you are thoſe that are advanced, and enſtated in it; Let mee only adviſe you (as a poore unworthy Meſſenger of Chriſt) to take heed and beware of Capernaums Doome, Mat. 11. 23. And thou Capernaum which art exalted to Heaven ſhalt be thrown down to Hell; Oh pray to God that ye may eſcape that wofull praecipitium, that diſmal, that dolefull, that deadly Down-fall: Rather (as Salomon ſaith) let your way be upward, direct your ſteps and courſes to Heaven-wards, and labour every day to ariſe in your care, in your zeale, in your devotions to God, that you may come neerer to Heaven at night, than you were in the morning; that ſo even while you live and converſe on Earth, you may be truly and rightly ſaid to have your converſation in Heaven. For ſo ſpeakes my Text of ſome, and God grant it may bee ſpoken of us all, that Our converſation is in Heaven, from whence alſo we looke for the Saviour, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.
            
            In which words there are two generall parts to be obſerved: Firſt, the excellency of the Saints (they have their converſation in Heaven.) Secondly, the expectation of ſinners, (from thence alſo we looke for the Saviour, &amp;c.) Firſt, what is meant by converſation. Secondly, how we that live and converſe on earth, can bee ſaid in proper ſence to have our converſation in Heaven.
            The firſt of theſe may be conſidered in foure circumſtances,
            
               
1. That a mans converſation is Res continuata, a conſtant, a ſetled, continued thing. It is not one or two, or ſome few particular actions that do denominate a mans converſation, but the generall courſe and current of his life; which if it be rightly ordered, as it ought to bee, then it is termed an Honeſt Converſation, 2 Peter 2. 12. (Have your converſation honeſt among the Gentiles.) if otherwiſe it be idly and unprofitably miſpent, then it is termed a vaine converſation: 1 Pet. 1. 18. (yee are redeemed from your vaine converſation.) That which brings a man no profit, no credit, no comfort in the end, that's a vaine converſation: And God forbid that any Chriſtians converſation ſhould be ſo vaine. This we know, that as there is no man ſo bad but he may do ſome particular actions that are right and good; as God ſaid of Abimelech, Gen. 20. I know thou haſt done this thing in the integrity of thy heart: that one thing he did well, though his converſation went another way; ſo on the contrary, there is no man ſo good, but he may do ſome particular actions that are vile and bad; as tis ſaid of David, he was upright in all things, ſave only in the matter of Vriah; In that one thing hee failed exceedingly, though the whole ſtreame of his life and converſation went right to God-ward.
            It is with a Chriſtian in this world, as with a Ship that goes to Sea, They are bound for ſuch a Coaſt, that way they ſayle, and thither they direct their voyage; now there may come many a contrary ſtorm that may turne them cleane back, or

drive them quite another way: which for the preſent is a great trouble and griefe unto them, but as ſoone as ever the ſtorme is over, and the Sea is calme, they hale and toyle and never are at reſt, till they have recovered themſelves, and are gotten into the right way againe. So fares it with a Chriſtian ſoule, ſuch a one is bound for Heaven, that's his home, that's his harbour, that's the Heaven where he would be; now there may come, and daily there doth come many a croſſe, many a corruption, many a pleaſing, or unpleaſing temptation that turnes him cleane another way, into the way of ſinne and wickedneſſe, or turnes him clean back from the way of Grace and goodneſſe; which for the preſent (like the diviſions of Ruben, Iudg. 5.) muſt needs cauſe great ſighings and thoughts of heart; and indeed hee is never at quiet in his mind, nor at peace in his conſcience, till by the mercy of God he have recovered himſelfe by repentance, and come back to his old comfort and converſation againe. So the meaning of the Text is this; that it is not enough for a man to look to Heaven at ſome particular times, as in the time of ſickneſſe, of ſorrow, of extreme adverſity; (as the manner of the world is) for then the wickedeſt man that is, will peradventure have an eye to Heaven.
            Iuſt as you ſee a Hog, that never looks to Heaven, till he be over-turned, and caſt upon his back, then he looks to Heaven, and cryes; whereas if you do but let him looſe, that he gets upon his

leggs againe, hee returnes with his ſnowt to the earth, and looks to Heaven no more; ſo fares it (I feare me) with many a carnall man, that ſeldom or never looks to Heaven, till hee bee overturned in his credit, overthrown in his eſtate, or caſt upon his back on the bed of ſickneſſe and death; then he liſis up his eyes to thoſe Hils from whence commeth his help, (as David ſpeaketh:) whereupon if God do but ſet him at liberty, and reſtore him to his health, that he get upon his legs againe, hee returnes like a Hog to his old ſwiniſh diſpoſition, &amp; looks no more after Heaven, till he be caſtdown again into the like diſtreſſe. Thus it is, but thus it ſhould not be: If you deſire to have comfort from Heaven in your ſickneſſe, let your converſation be there in your health; and that not for a fit or a brunt, but in a conſtant, &amp; ſetled, and continued courſe of life; that like as it is ſaid of God, Deut. 11. 12. that his eyes are upon the land, from the beginning of the yeare, to the end thereof; ſo let thine eyes be upon God from the beginning of the day, of the weeke, of the yeare, even to the end and conſummation of thy life. You know what our Saviour ſaid to thoſe Jews which beleeved on him, Iohn 8. 31. Si manſerit is in me, If ye abide in mee, then are ye my Diſciples indeed. They that only come to Chriſt, and make profeſſion of Chriſtianity for a time, and then like Demas fall away, and embrace this preſent World; theſe are but diſciples in name only, like Labans Images, that were called Gods, when they were but blocks:

Thoſe and none but thoſe are diſciples in deed and in truth, that do as their maſter did, of whom it is ſaid, Philip. 2. 8. that Hee humbled himſelfe, and became obedient unto the death: He was not only obedient in his death, ſubmitting himſelfe to all the cruelty, all the infamy, all the extremity of pain and ſhame that God or man could lay upon him; but He was obedient unto death; that is, (as Beza expounds it) unto his Dying day, from the beginning of his Incarnation, to the very end of his diſſolution: Here's the Load-ſtar that wee muſt all bee guided by▪ let us beare the ſame mind, and hold the ſame reſolution, that our Saviour did, to become obedient to the death, (or as Iob ſpeaketh, Cap. 27. 5.) not to leave our innocency till wee die; then may we take it as an undoubted evidence and aſſurance to our ſoules, that wee, even wee our ſelves are of the number of thoſe bleſſed Saints that have their converſation in the Heavens. This is the firſt circumſtance to bee conſidered, that a mans converſation is Res continuata, not a ſudden or a momentarie, but a conſtant and continued thing.
            2. A mans converſation is Res manifeſta, an open and a manifeſt thing: the Conſcience of a man, that is ſecret, knowne only to God; but his converſation that is evident and apparent to the word. So the meaning of the Text is, that it is not enough for a man to have a care of his conſcience inwardly towards God, but he muſt have as great

a care of his converſation outwardly to the World. That like as it is ſaid of our Saviour, Luke 9. 53. They knew what hee was by his face, becauſe (ſaith the Text) his face was as though hee would go to Ieruſalem: So ſhould a good Chriſtian be known by his face (that is) by his outward carriage and converſation to bee one that is going to Jeruſalem that is above; If thou beeſt ſuch a one, let it be thy principall care to lead thy life in ſuch a way as God doth beſt accept, in the way of Godlineſſe and honeſty, in the way of temperance and ſobriety, in the way of truth and ſincerity; that the World may ſee by thy life, that as thou doſt live and move in God, ſo thou doſt alſo live and move to God. As Alexander once gave order that the Grecians and Barbarians ſhould bee no longer diſtinguiſhed by their garments; but (ſaith hee) let the Greciens be known by their vertues▪ and the Barbarians by their vices: thus ſhould a Chriſtian bee diſtinguiſhed from a carnall man, not by his habit, but by his heart, not by his eſtate and condition, but by his wiſdome and converſation, being ſuch (as St. Paul ſpeaketh) as becometh the Goſpell, Philip. 1. 27. The works of the fleſh are manifeſt (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) and ſo ſhould the works of the ſpirit bee alſo. As it is ſaid of the Kings daughter, Pſal. 45. 13. She is all glorious within, and her cloathing alſo is of wrought Gold: ſo ſhould every Chriſtian ſoule, which is the Spouſe of Chriſt, and the daughter of the King of Heaven, bee all glorious, or rather

indeed all gracious and all vertuous, both within and without: And as it is ſaid of the Arke of God, Exod. 37. that it was over-laied with pure Gold both within and without: ſo ſhould every Chriſtian pray, that he may have a good conſcience as the overlaying of gold within, and a good converſation, as the overlaying of gold without; providing things honeſt, not only in the ſight of God, but alſo in the ſight of men, Rom. 12. 17. And this is the ſecond circumſtance to bee conſidered in our converſation; namely, that it is or ought to bee Res manifeſta, a manifeſt thing.
            3. A mans converſation is Res familiaris, a friendly, or a familiar thing; You know there is no one thing that breeds ſo much entireneſſe, ſo much familiarity and acquaintance among all ſorts of perſons, as living, and loving, and converſing together: So the only way to bring a man into an humble familiarity and acquaintance with his God, is to bee converſant in holy duties, and to have his converſation in the Heavens. It is the phraſe of Iob, (and I do not remember that I find it any where but in that book) Iob 22. 21. Acquaint thy ſelfe with God, and thereby good ſhall come unto thee. Aſueſce cum Deo, (that is) Accuſtome and inure thy ſelfe to walke with God, as Enoch did; to talke with God, as Moſes did; to ſeeke the face of God, as David did: make nor thy ſelfe a ſtranger to God now, leſt he know thee not, leſt hee own thee not, at the later

day, when thou and all the world will bee glad to claim acquaintance of Him. But ſome may ſay; What am I, or what is my fathers houſe, that I ſhould dare to thinke of being acquainted, with ſo great a Majeſty, as is the Lord? that is too familiar a word: I anſwer, according to the common proverb; volenti nonfit injuria, That which is an injury to our thinking, is no injury to him that is willing and deſirous of it. Now you ſhall obſerve that all the perſons in the Bleſſed Trinity, are ſo farre from taking ill at our hands, that they do even deſire and wiſh for ſinfull mans ſocietie. God the Father he deſires it, Eſay 1. 18. Come (ſaith God) let us reaſon together, let us parley, let us confer, let us be familiar (as it were) and renew our old decayed acquaintance, which hath ſlept ſo long, and been ſo unkindly laid aſide. In the originall it is, Adeſte, &amp; increpemus, come let us chide together; as one friend chides another for being ſtrange and aloofe, &amp; taking diſtaſte without a cauſe: And this is it, makes God to chide us as he doth, partly by word of mouth, in the Miniſtry of his Word; and partly by Act and Deed, by ſending his reall Judgements into the World to plague us for ſinne; which David calleth Increpationem Domini, the chiding of God, Pſal. 18. 15. and all for our averſeneſſe, and aloofeneſſe in this kind, that wee will not come at him to renew our acquaintance with him, by a ſound and ſerious humiliation, as his mercy, and our dutie

doth require. God the Sonne, Hee deſires our acquaintance likewiſe, as you may read, Iohn 5. 39. Yee ſearch the Scriptures (ſaith Chriſt) and in them ye looke to have eternall life, and yet ye will not come to mee that yee might have life. We deale juſt with our Saviour, as one ſaid of his Friend or Father, Si bene eſſem ſine te, nunquam venirem ad te; If I could bee well without thee, I would never come at thee: It is our illneſſe, and our weakneſſe, our lameneſſe, and our ſickneſſe, that makes us to repaire unto Chriſt, or elſe (I am afraid) wee would ſeldome or never come at him. As for the Holy Ghoſt, David cals him a Loving Spirit, Pſal. 143. 10. a Spirit that loves the company and the conduct of a poore ſinner (let thy loving Spirit lead mee into the land of Righteouſneſſe;) it is not only a leading Spirit, but a loving Spirit; a Spirit that loves to lead us, and to carry us into all truth, into all goodneſſe, and to guide our ſinfull feet into the way of peace; wee read of divers that were condemned in Scripture, for having to doe with Familiar Spirits, and juſtly, for what graceleſſe wretches were they that durſt bee familiar with thoſe evill ſpirits that were the mortall enemies of their ſoules; that durſt to harbour thoſe helliſh Serpents in their boſomes, that ſtung their Soules to death eternall: And oh, what a bleſſed and a happy thing it were, if we were but halfe ſo deſirous of the familiaritie

and acquaintance of the Good Spirit, as they were of the evill ones; then as Iob ſpeakes in the place fore-named, Inde proventus erit bonus, thereby good ſhall come unto thee: Good to thy eſtate, thou ſhalt proſper by it; Good to thy children, they ſhall flouriſh by it; Good to thy name, thou ſhalt have credit and reputation by it; Good to thy body, thou ſhalt have health and protection by it; but ſpeciall good ſhall come to thy Soule, thou ſhalt have mercy, and peace, and ſalvation by it: Thou ſhalt have his good Word to inſtruct thee, his good Angels to guard thee, his good Spirit to comfort thee, and above all his good Kingdom to receive thee. Therefore, if thou loveſt thy ſelfe, and tendereſt thy owne good, let thy converſation with God, bee Res familiaris, a free, a frequent, and a familiar thing.
            Laſtly, if wee take the originall word 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                in the native and proper ſenſe, as it ſignifies the traffiquing and trading that one Merchant or one Citizen hath with another, then it affords us this conſideration; That to converſe or to have commerce with God, is Res queſt uoſa, the gainfuleſt trade, and the richeſt marchandiſe under Heaven. For if wee beleeve the Apoſtle; Godlineſſe is no vile commodity, but exceeding gainfull, yea gaine it ſelfe, yea and great gaine too; (if not to the purſe, yet to the Conſcience; if not to the eſtate, yet to the

ſoule it is) for it hath the promiſes not only of the life that now is, but of that which is to come. There bee many that ſay (ſaith David, Pſal. 4. 6.) Who will ſhew us any good? It is not the ſaying of one man, or of ſome men, but of many and of moſt men, who will ſhew us any Good; all their deſire is to liſten and inquire who can tell them of any good purchaſe, any good bargaine, any good fortune that may concerne them, or come to their hands; let the party that ſhewes it bee who hee will, if hee ſhewes any good wee love him, wee thank him for it: Behold here is one (Saint Paul by name) that ſhewes us Summum Bonum, the Greateſt Good, the trueſt and ſureſt Gaine that is to be had in all the Chriſtian World: and that is to keep a Factory in Heaven (as it were) by the meanes and mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, to deale betwixt God and our own Soules in a ſecret and a ſacred commerce, to exchange our Prayers for his Favours, our duties for his Mercies, and ſo to drive a Spirituall trade in the City of God; And this will bring us into ſuch a way of profit, that wee ſhall gaine Wiſdome and Grace, and Comfort and Credit in this life, and a Crowne of Eternall Glory in the life to come, and now judge your ſelves whether to have our converſation in Heaven bee not Res quaeſtuoſa, a gainfull thing.
            I come now to the ſecond generall propoſition

of my Text, which is this: How wee that live and converſe upon Earth, can bee ſaid in proper ſenſe to have our Converſation in the Heavens? I ſhall anſwer it foure waies.
            1. Per Elevationem, By lifting up our hearts and minds, and Soules to God. Wee read, Levit. 11. 21. that thoſe Reptilia, thoſe Fowls or other Creatures that crept on all foure, were Abomination in Moſes Law, the people might not eat nor touch them; but thoſe that had legges and wings to leape withall, and to lift up themſelves from the Earth toward Heaven, thoſe were cleane in Gods account. This was certainely a ſymbolicall type to ſignifie unto us, that thoſe Chriſtians that are alwayes creeping (as it were) and crawling and groveling upon the Earth, alwayes minding earthly things, and ſetting their hearts upon the muck of this World, they are uncleane and Abomination to the Lord: But they that have the legges and wings of Faith and fervent Prayer, to leape (as it were) from the Earth, and to lift up themſelves towards Heaven in their ejaculations and devotions to God, they are thoſe whom God accepts. An Angell once cried, Revel. 8. 13. Woe, woe, woe to the inhabitants of the Earth. Inhabitantibus, non Accolis (ſaith a Father) not to the ſojourners and ſtrangers of the Earth (as all good Chriſtians are, whoſe Home is

Heaven, and the Earth but a place of their pilgrimage for a time.) But the woes are to the ſetled Inhabitants of the Earth, who ſo fixe their hearts on the Earth, that they make it their Heaven; like that Cardinall that would not change his part in Paris for his part in Paradiſe: or like the Children of Reuben and Gad, Numb. 32. 3. that deſired to make their ſtay on this ſide Jordan, and let their brethren if they liſted paſſe over into the Land of promiſe; for their owne parts, they liked well of the place where they were, and did not deſire to remove, becauſe it was a place fit for their Cattell. In like ſort, they that make more account of their cattell, than they doe of their conſcience; and doe more eſteeme the pleaſures and profits of a life temporall, than the incomprehenſible joyes of the life eternall; they that ſo love the Earth, that by their good wills they would not leave it for Heaven: Woe bee to them three wayes: firſt, woe to them in life; ſecondly, woe to them in death; thirdly, woe to them after death: or thus, woe to their bodies, woe to their ſoules, and woe to both body and ſoule together in that woefull place of torment. In a word, therefore if we deſire to eſcape this threfold woe, and that it may bee well with us both here and hereafter; let us doe by our af
                  •
               ections, as Husband-men do

by their corne, if it lie low in a damp room, it is in danger to putrifie, and corrupt, and ſtink; therefore they convey it and carry it up into ſome higher room that is farther from the Earth, and neerer to Heaven, and there it is ſafe. Such a damp place is this ſinfull World, therfore if thou wouldſt preſerve thy affections from ſtench and corruption, carry them up on high, liſt them up to Heaven by divine contemplations, and by a divine converſation, and then they are out of danger. We ſhould frame our affections in forme of a ſhip, which is cloſe downwards, and open upwards, in an hearty deſire of a Heavenly condition. One ſaith well, It is with Men, as it is with the Moone: When the Moone decreaſeth, it is cloſe above, and open below; Contrarily, when it increaſeth, it is open above, and cloſe below: So if our minds, (as Nature hath framed our hearts) bee cloſe downwards, uſing the World, as if wee uſed it not, and enlarged upwards in ſeeking and ſighing after the things that bee above; then tis a happy ſigne of our increaſe in grace and favour with God, and an infallible evidence to our ſoules, that though our abode bee below on Earth, yet our converſation is above in Heaven.
            2. Per Anticipationem, you that deſire to have Heaven hereafter, muſt begin your heaven here, by Anticipation; and that three waies:

firſt, take direction from Heaven in all your wayes and actions; doe as ſhip-men doe at Sea, becauſe they have no common Road, nor beaten Path to ſayle by, they take their direction from the ſtarres, and guide themſelves by the Heavens; ſo becauſe in this World (which is as briniſh with ſinne, as the Sea is with ſalt; and as dangerous to the Soule, as the Sea is to the ſhip) there is no common Road (as I may ſay) no beaten path to Heaven, ſo few there bee that goe that way; let every one that deſires to walke ſafely, take heed of walking raſhly, and following the luſts, devices, and deſires of his own heart, but let him looke up to Heaven for direction, and deſire God to be his guide and conduct; ſaying and praying in the words of the Prophet David, Pſal. 48. 14. Thou O. God art my God for ever, oh bee thou my guide unto the day of death. Secondly, learne the language of Heaven while yee are here; as one that is to travell into a forraine Country, will if hee can poſſible learne ſome part of the language of that countrey before-hand, that he may not be altogether to ſeeke when hee comes into a ſtrange place: So if Heaven bee (as I hope it is) the Countrey and the Kingdome that yee all deſire to live in; bee carefull then while yee are here to inure your ſelves to the language of Heaven ere ye come

there, (that is) to bleſſe God, and praiſe him, and ſpeake good of his Name: for as terrene, and ſordid and baſe diſcourſe is the language of the World, and lying, and lewd and profane diſcourſe is the language of Hell: So pious, and profitable, and divine diſcourſe, that ſavoureth and relliſheth of the Grace and good Spirit of God, that's the language of Heaven: learne that. Thirdly, labour to get a Temper and a diſpoſition fit for Heaven; As God hath given the fowles a Temper fit to live in the ayre, and fiſhes a Temper fit for the water; and creeping things a Temper fit for the Earth; ſo deſire of God to frame thy heart to an Heavenly diſpoſition, and to give thee a Temper fit for Heaven.
            Certainly Carnall Men miſtake Heaven, taking it to bee only a place of Reſt, but not a place of righteouſneſſe; a place of happineſſe, but not a place of holineſſe; ſo that if a Carnall man ſhould bee admitted to peepe into Heaven to ſee what is there adoing, to ſee how the Glorified Soules and Spirits are alwayes lauding and magnifying their God and Saviour, alwayes taken up with Holy and Heavenly exerciſes and employments; hee would loath no place ſo much as Heaven, as being no wayes agreeable, but altogether contrary to his temper and diſpoſition: He that is weary of one Sabbath here, how will

hee brooke an eternity of Sabbath hereafter: if the Foot-men have ty
                     •
                  ed him (as Ieremy ſpeakes in another caſe, Ierem. 12. 5. how will hee doe to hold▪ pace with the Horſe-men: Hee that thinkes too much of that little holineſſe that God requires in his Saints on Earth, how will hee comply with that excellency of holineſſe that is in the Saints, and bleſſed Soules in Heaven. In a word then, as wee all hope to have Carnem Angeliſicatam (as Tertullian ſpeakes) to have Angell-like bodies hereafter; ſo let us labour and pray that we may have Animas Angeliſicatas, Angell-like Soules while wee are here; that wee may wholly addict and give our minds to doe Gods will on Earth as it is done in Heaven, that we may begin our Heaven here in Grace, and perfect it hereafter for ever in Glory.
            3 A man that lives on Earth, may bee ſaid to have his converſation in Heaven, Per Charitatem, by holy Charity, which is nothing elſe but a divine love to God, and to all Goodneſſe. Hee that is a truly Charitable man on Earth, is in ultima &amp; proxima diſpoſitione, in the laſt, and likeſt, and neereſt diſpoſition to the Glorified Saints in Heaven: For this wee know, that moſt of thoſe other vertues wherein men excell on Earth, do faile and ceaſe when the Soule returnes to Heaven; Our Faith, that ſhall ceaſe, for wee ſhall then

ſee the beatificall face of God, and the bleſſed reward of the Godly, which we now beleeve unſeene.
            Our Hope, that ſhall ceaſe; for wee ſhall then enjoy the good things wee hoped for: no more need of Anchour when wee are paſt the Sea of this world, and landed upon the ſhoare of Heaven. So likewiſe Patience ſhall ceaſe, for there ſhall be no more pain; and Continency, for there ſhall be no more temptations; and Mercy, for there ſhall bee no more objects of miſery: Only Charity, that remaynes and abides, and accompanies the ſoule into the kingdom of Chriſt, and of God; that's a Grace that is begun on earth, and never ceaſeth in Heaven; it is a celeſtiall, a heavenly quality, whether it bee in men or women; in perſons of noble, or of meaner rank. It is true, all have not meanes alike to expreſſe their charity to thoſe that are poore and needy; therefore you muſt know, that Charity is twofold; there is the outward charity of the hand, and the inward charity of the heart; this later is that which God requireth equally of all, both rich and poore. It is like that Tribute of the Sanctuary Exod. 30. 15. wherein there was an equall Rate ſet for the Ranſome of their lives, that the poore paid as much as the Rich: ſo a poore man may have as Charitable an heart, as a Rich man,

though God have ſtraitned him in his means that he cannot have ſo charitable an hand: you ſee 1. Cor. 13. that Charity which the Apoſtle ſo magnifies, and extolls above all other gifts, is only this inward Charity (Charity envieth not, is not eaſily provoked, ſeeketh not her own, but hopeth all things, beleeveth all things, indureth all things &amp;c.;) all this reflects upon the heart, and therein a poore man may abound, as well as a rich; In a word then, if God have clipt thy wings, and cut ſhort thy eſtate, that thou canſt not have a charitable hand; yet howſoever retaine a charitable heart, and what thou wanteſt in ſubſtance make up in prayer. This is the third way, whereby a man that lives on earth may be truly ſaid to have his converſation in heaven.
            4. The fourth and laſt way, is, per Claritatem, by brightneſſe and ſhining in Grace, and good works; Heaven is a ſhining place, full of ſplendour, luſture and glory, and ſuch are all the ſoules that dwell therein. The Prophet tell us Dan. 12. 3. they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the firmament, and they that turne many to Righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as the ſtars for evermore. The firmament that ſhines by day, and the ſtars they ſhine by night; the meaning is, that they which are truly vertuous and wiſe, eruditi &amp; erudientes, the practiſers, and the teachers of wiſdome; they that are wiſe themſelves,

and they that make others wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the Firmament in the day-time of their life, and as the Starres in the night when they are dead and gone; they ſhall ſhine in Grace here, and in Glory hereafter. Though for a time they bee over-clouded (as it were) with Croſſes and Corruptions, which darkens and obſcures the luſtre that is in them; yet the time will come that all theſe Clouds, theſe Croſſes, and Corruptions ſhall bee blowne away, and they ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the Kingdome of their Father. When Moſes converſed with God, his face ſhined, Exod. 34. there's no good man that converſeth with God, but his face ſhines too, that is, hee hath a venerable aſpect, inſomuch as they that will not imitate him, cannot but honour him: Iohn was a burning and a ſhining light (ſaith the Goſpell, Iohn 5. 35.) burning with zeale inwardly to God, ſhining by a good life outwardly to the World. You that deſire to ſhine in Heaven muſt begin your ſhining here on Earth: Let your light ſo ſhine, (ſaith our Saviour) that men may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven. True Faith is in the heart, like a candle in a lanterne, which muſt not, nay cannot be altogether hid, but diſcovers it ſelfe by its own ſhining light.
            
               
Aſtronomers obſerve that the Galaxia, or the Milky way (as they call it) is a Glorious Circle, and poſſeſſeth a great part of Heaven, and yet is all of ſo little Starres, as have no name nor knowledge taken of them by Aſtrologers. So no doubt, there are many Saints in Heaven, that ſhine as the Starres in the Kingdome of God, that were none of thoſe great magnitudes, that the World ſhould take notice of them; but good and bleſſed Soules that have honeſtly performed the duties of their inferiour calling, and behaved▪ themſelves ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this World; and ſo glimmered in a poore eſtate, like a Diamond that gliſters in the duſt. In a word, as wee all beleeve and hope that God will one day change our vile bodies (as the Apoſtle rightly calls them) and make them like unto the Glorious of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour; ſo let us now deſire and beg of God to change our vile Soules, that they may in ſome meaſure bee like the pure and precious Soule of our deare Ieſus; that all the fogges and fumes of our unſavoury noyſome luſts may bee diſperſed and done away, that wee may ſo ſhine on Earth, by a godly life and converſation, that wee may bee rewarded with ſhining in Heaven, in a ſtate of immortallity and incorruption.

Which GOD of his mercy Grant, for JESUS CHRIST his ſake, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, bee given and aſcribed all honour, praiſe, and glory; bee done and performed all ſervice, obedience and duty, from this time forth for ever-more,
            Amen.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

