
   
      
         
            Here begynneth a lytell prosses or matter called the Chauc̃e of the dolorous louer newely cõpyled or made by Crystofer  Goodwyn the yere of our Lorde God, a. M.ccccc.xx.
            Goodwin, Christopher.
         
         
            
               1520
            
         
         Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01907
            STC 12046
            ESTC S3995
            34382691
            ocm 34382691
            29054
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01907)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29054)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1896:8)
         
         
            
               
                  Here begynneth a lytell prosses or matter called the Chauc̃e of the dolorous louer newely cõpyled or made by Crystofer  Goodwyn the yere of our Lorde God, a. M.ccccc.xx.
                  Goodwin, Christopher.
               
               [14] p. : ill.  
               
                  By Wynkyn de Worde,
                  Imprynted at London in Flete strete at the sygne of the Sonne :
                  [1520?]
               
               
                  Imprint from colophon; date of publication from STC (2nd ed.).
                  Title page contains wood-cut illustration.
                  Imperfect: stained and with print show-through.
                  Signatures: A⁴, B³.
                  Reproduction of original in: British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2000-00
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2001-00
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2001-06
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2001-00
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Text and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2001-11
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
            
            ¶Here begynneth a lytell prosses or matter called the chaūce of the dolorous louer newely cōpyled or made by Crystofer Goodwyn The yere of our Lorde god, a, M. ccccc. xx.
            
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶The prologue of the auctour.
            
               Upon a certayne tyme as it befell
               I was all pensyfe and thoughtfull in my herte
               For sondry thynges whiche I knewe full well
               Coude not be remedyed as touchynge my parte
               Wherfore I ymagynynge from me to astarte
               Suche thoughtes &amp; fātasies comynge thrugh ydeues
               And euen so I began this lytell mater or prosses
            
            
               For as I haue redde in bokes and in storyes olde
               Of all vyces the chefe rote of Idelnes
               And yf it be as wyse men haue tolde
               Whiche veryfyenge of the same playnly dyde expres
               That of all synnes Slouthe is chefe maystres
               Into the whiche lest I sholde fall I made for fere
               This treatyse callyd ye chaunce of the dolorous louer
            
            
               Not for no prasynge but my spyrytes to wake
               Whiche at that tyme were full rude and dull
               And so I you requyer that you wyll it take
               Whiche that dothe entende for to rede it full
               Or it to here and so I trust that you wyll
               That slouthe to auoyde whiche enemy is to vertue
               Thys werke I toke in honde that after dothe ensewe
            
            ¶Thus endeth the prologue.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶Here foweth a lytell treatyse called The chaunce of the dolorous louer.
            
               AS it fortuned me for passe
               Thrughe straunge countres my solace to take.
               Whan the feldes were resplendent and couered with grasse
               And with swete herbes and floures delycate
               And byrdes melodyously syngynge on euery busshe or stake
               I mene in the pleasaunt tyme of Autom
               Whiche nexte vnto vere may haue the chefe rome
            
            
               And thus as I rode my selfe all alone
               Musynge of thynges that were in tymes past
               By the space of thre dayes and than aboute none
               My waye I dyde lose by rydynge ouer fast
               Than I was full sory yet at the last
               A pleasaunt way I founde I thanke god of his grace
               In whiche I entred and rode in an esye pace
            
            
               For my Journayes whiche I had the dayes afore
               And also the wayes that I had reden wronge
               Had made me full wery and also faynte and sore
               That ferther on my hors I coude not endure longe
               Wherfore I thought me to rest &amp; wt yt I herde asonge
               Nere by whiche was so melodyous and swete
               That all my werynes I dyde all forgete
            
            
               
               ¶To knowe what it myght be I had grete purpose
               Wherfore thyderwarde full fast I dyde me hye
               And then before me I sawe a grene close
               Enuyronned with grete trees &amp; hedges full strongly
               Yet not withstandynge I entred pryuely
               In at the gate wiche open then I founde
               And there I tyed my horse &amp; lyghted on the grounde.
            
            
               ¶And whan I within this close entred was
               Beynge nothynge rounde but of compas quadrant
               I behelde it well in euery corner and place
               Sayenge to my selfe that suche another skant
               Coulde not be founde of floures so habundaunt
               As was this lytell close whiche before truely
               I herde the songe that was songe so swetely
            
            
               ¶And in beholdynge this felde rounde aboute
               Ryght agaynst me then dyde I espye
               A waye whiche as this close wente out
               Also in another place truely
               I sawe a byrde whiche sange full hye
               Upon foure floures castynge so swete a sauour
               yt they quyckened my spyrytes wt theyr doulcet odour
            
            
               ¶And euer this byrde full plesauntly dyde synge
               With her sugered notes very lowde and shyll
               That all aboute ye place her Iocoūde voyce dyd rynge
               Whom dylygently to here I stode full softe and styll
               And to vnderstonde I fyxed my mynde and wyll
               The dytte of her songe whyche was so certayne
               God sende euery true louer his lady to optayne
            
            
               
               ¶Than to this swete byrde or auys I 
                     〈◊◊◊〉
                   nere
               And as I wente I stombled on a busshe
               And almost had a fall and with a ragged bryere
               I was constrayned to make a grete russhe
               Wher with she was a ferde and sodaynly dyde flusshe
               And wolde no longer tary but with all her myght
               Frō thens I wyst not whyther fast she toke her flyght
            
            
               ¶Than I was full sory whan I sawe her gone
               Not withstondynge I knewe there was no remedy
               And streyght vnto the place I walked all alone
               From whiche a lytell before I dyde se her flye
               And whan I was this foresayd place by
               I wyst not well wheder I dyde wake or slepe
               So grete a swetnes in to my stomake dyde bete
            
            
               ¶And whā I was reuyued &amp; come to my selfe agayne
               I behelde ye meruaylous facyon of this foresayd place
               Whiche was square and also lowe and playne
               Compassed rounde about with hye herbes and gras
               So that no man myght se in but at one space
               Whiche was opyn wherin to entre I dyde purpose
               Thynkynge there my selfe for to repose
            
            
               ¶And whan I had entred in this lytell gardyn grene
               Whiche full smothe and lowe was with herbes
               In all my lyfe I had neuer sene
               An arbour that was so pleasant I wys
               Wherin stode in the myddes
               Of this sayd place foure delycyous floures
               Castynge meruaylous swete &amp; delycyous sauoures
            
            
               
               ¶
                     〈◊◊〉
                   whiche I wente &amp; downe by them dyd lye
               And ouer this as I lay ryght well I dyde beholde
               What herbes and floures they were yf I coude dyscry
               Then of all theyr names I might rede as I wolde
               The fyrst letters whiche were of beten golde
               Syngulerly set on euery floure aboue
               Growyng after the maner of a goodly trewe loue
            
            
               The fyrste floure to my thynkynge was of a crymsyn pure
               Hauynge an A wryten hym vpon
               Whiche stode for ȳe fyrst letter of his name I was right sure
               Yet what floure it was I lay musynge longe
               And whan I had all studyed yet knewe I none
               Name that it had wherfore I was right sore
               For it passed all other in swetenes and beaute
            
            
               ¶The seconde floure was a vyolet full swete
               That had on hym wryten of hys name the fyrst lettre
               Whiche was an. U. bothe fayre and grete
               In all the worlde coude not be a better
               The .iij. herbe orfloure whiche myght none be swetter
               Was Isope of sauour bothe good and holsome
               Whiche had for his name an I vpon hym wryten
            
            
               ¶The souerayne herbe sauge was the fourte
               Whiche all other herbes in vertue dothe excell
               As in olde tyme wyse men dyde reporte
               Whiche had wryten vpon hym an. S. as I you tell
               For the fyrste letter of his name meruaylously well
               And than full well I knewe these herbes amonge
               Sate this lytell byrde or auys syngynge of her songe
            
            
               
               ¶All these foure floures so swete and delectable
               Grewe lyke a trewe loue as I before dyde tell
               Hauynge this golde lettres without ony fable
               Eche one his owne whiche I to geder dyde spell
               And whan I had set them to gyder than I knewe wel
               That it was the name of my true loue
               Whome specyally I desyryd nexte god aboue
            
            
               And thus whan I had rede the name of my lady dere
               From wome I was departed not longe afore
               Sodaynly was chaunged all my mery chere
               And my herte began to be full heuy and sore
               With greuous grones and syghes more and wore
               So that in fayth it was no grete wondre
               Though in a hundrede peaces it had brast a sondre
            
            
               ¶From her the departynge to me so greuous was
               Whome to the sayd floures full well lyken I myght
               She is so goodly and beautefull of face
               So curteys so gentyll so amyable and so bryght
               That in the wyde worlde suche another wyhgt
               Coude not be founde so full of grace and goodnes
               As is this myne owne swete lady and maystres
            
            
               ¶And whan I had ben a longe tyme in this heuynes
               The absence of my loue ryght peteously be waylynge
               It came to my mynde my sorowes to releys
               Some balade to make whiche that I myght synge
               And thus I began ryght dolorously wenynge
               By cause of her the syghte I had lost
               Whome in this worlde I desyre moost
            
         
         
            
            
               
                  ¶Here after foloweth the balade of the dolorous louer.
               
            
            
               O Myserable creature wrapped all in wo
               Full well may I complayne both morne &amp; wepe
               Syth my louely lady I am departed fro
               That was so gentell so goodly fayre and swete
               So dulcet a byrde or auys a man cannot gete
               Wherfore I maye saye alas my mortall payne.
               From her the departynge full nyghe hath me slayne.
            
            
               
               ¶Sle me it wyll ye and that ryght shortely
               Without that I maye within a lytell space
               Haue of her a lyghte or elles ryght gladly
               Wolde I dye euen in this same place
               And neuer to se no body more in the face
               Wherfore I beseche dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght of my true loue
            
            
               ¶Alas vnfortunate man what thynge dyd I mene
               Frome her whā I departed whome I so moche set by
               Has nowe out of her fauoure clene
               I shall be caste than may I bothe sobbe and cry
               And also to be sorowfull euer tyll I dye
               Wherfore alas my mortall payne
               Frome her to departe full nyghe hathe me slayne
            
            
               ¶O rubycunde ruby and perle moost oryent
               O gyloffer gentyll and swete floure delyce
               O daynty dyamounde and moost respendent
               O doulset blossome of a full grete pryce
               O swete maystres aboue all creatueres mooste wyse
               Wherfore I beseche dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght of you my true loue
            
            
               ¶In vertue to Magulon I maye you well acounte
               In wysdome to lady Florypes ye do insewe
               In mekenes Gryselde ye do surmounte
               In stedfastnes to Clerymounde that lady true
               In beaute to the lady Eglantyne I maye deme you
               And euer alas my mortall payne
               Frome you the departynge full nyghe hath me slayne
            
            
               
               ¶Also foure letters ye haue in your name
               In tokenynge of loue ye sholde be true
               Of whiche these floures haue the same
               That be so swete and full of vertue
               Wherfore to theym I may well lyken you
               And yet I beseche dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght of my true loue
            
            
               ¶This floure vnknowen and vyolet in swetenes
               This Isope so holsome thys sage so souerayn a thȳge
               You passe and excell thrughe your goones
               Also to this byrde or auys that hereafore dyde synge
               With your dulcet voyece ye maye be lykened my dere swetynge
               But euer alas my mortall payne
               Frome you ye departynge well nyghe hathe me slayne
            
            
               ¶Alas dere lady ye be myne onely hope
               My Ioye my herte and the substaunce of my lyfe
               My payne my sorowe and also my dethe god wote
               Agaynst whiche I can make no maner of stryfe
               Nor other remedy I knowe but styll morne &amp; syghe
               And yet I beseche dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght of my true loue
            
            
               ¶That I myght to your goodly parsone declare
               How faythefull I haue ben how stedfast and how true
               But alas I fere that ye be voyde and bare
               Of pyte and compassyon whiche I full sore may rewe
               For then my wo and sorowe shall renewe
               Wherfore alas my mortall payne
               From you the departynge well neyghe hath me slayne
            
            
               
               ¶Alas I trowe a Iewe on me wolde take cōpassyon
               Knowynge my faythfulnes and my louynge herte
               Whicheuer to her I have borne wt all my hole entēcion
               And styll purpose to do and neuer for to reuerte
               From her my mynde thoughe she vntrewe astarte
               And yet I beseche dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght of her whome I do loue
            
            
               Alas to call her vntrue I am gretely to blame
               Seynge that as yet I neuer shewed my mynde
               Unto her goodnes alas I durste not for shame
               Wherfore I am yet in good hope yt I shall her fynde
               To me her owne true seruaūte bothe louynge &amp; kynde
               And yet alas my mortall payne
               Frome her the departynge full nyghe hathe me slayne
            
            
               ¶She is so gentell so louely and so meke
               So fayre so swete so good to more and les
               That whā I on her thȳke I wene my herte shal breke
               For the loue of her I am in so grete dystres
               Whiche is myne owne dere lady and maystres
               Wherfore I beseche dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght of my true loue
            
            
               ¶Of all her goodnes what sholde I more endyght
               The halfe wherof it wolde not well suffyse
               For to be declared is an hole seuvn nyght
               If styll therat syt I sholde and neuer fer to ryse
               She is so beautefull so curtyes and so wyse
               Whefore alas my mortall payne
               Frome her the departynge full nyghe hath me slayne
            
            
               
               ¶Alas at this tyme I maye no more synge
               I feble my herte so fele and so sore
               With lamentacyons and contynuall wepynge
               Whiche doth in dure euer more and more
               Wherfore adue the best that euer was bore
               Alwaye besechynge dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght of my trewe loue
            
            
               ¶Adue my swetynge adue my darlynge dere
               Adue my helthe and solas with paynes smarte
               Adue the goodlyest that euer lyfe dyde bere
               Adue for whome I am bothe pale and swarte
               Yet crystes dere blessynge have swete herte
               But euer alas my mortall payne
               Frome you the departynge full nyghe hath me slayne
            
            
               ¶Adue adue my lyfe so swete
               Adue my dethe so sherpe and stronge
               Adue fayre byrde and auys so dulset
               Adue for euer I cannot endure longe
               Wherfore this is the last of my songe
               yet or I dye I beseche dame venus aboue
               To sende me agayne the syght or my true loue
            
            ¶There endeth the balade of the dolorous louer &amp; foweth of the aduenture that happened vnto hym shewed by vysyon in his slepe
         
         
            
               
               ¶And thus whan I had of this balade made an ende
               I began ryght strongely to sobbe syghe and wepe
               Besechynge dame venus some conforte me to sende
               And from all parelles my dere herte for to kepe
               And then for pure werynes I fell in a lytell slepe
               And as I slepte me thought the foresayd auys
               To me dyde come and bad me aryse
            
            
               ¶Saynge o thou slouthfull man &amp; full of ydylnes
               Wenest thou with slouggynge thy lady to optayne
               Or by alone complaynynge her sorowes to redres
               Nay nay it must be througe grete labour and payne
               And here thou doost but spende thy tyme in vayne
               Wherfore I the counsayle that shortly to her thou go
               Elles thy mynde &amp; purpose shalte thou neuer come to
            
            
               And be nothynge agast to shewe to her playne
               All thy mynde and wyll requyrynge her of grace
               And when she knoweth yt trouth then wyll she agayne
               Some conforte the gyue &amp; that within shorte space
               Otherwyse loke neuer thy wyll to brynge to passe
               Farewell for I go hens and loke thou take good hede
               Unto to my forsayd wordes yf thou purpose to spede
            
            
               ¶Than out of my slepe sodaynly I made abrayde
               And loked rounde aboute but nothynge I coude aspy
               And than I remembred what ye byrde to me had sayd
               And in my secrete mynde I prynted it surely
               Sayenge yt I wolde do after it for me thought truely
               It was the best counsayll I that herde my lyfe dayes
               Wherfore I concluded to ryse and go my wayes
            
            
               
               ¶And whan I was by I wente a full softe pace
               Unto my horse whome I lefte behynde
               Whan I wente the songe to here and in the same place
               Where as I hym lefte I dyde hym fynde
               Uppon whome I lyght all thoughtfull in my mynde
               And rode for the on my way besechynge our lorde Iesu
               To kepe my lady and me and all louers that be true
            
            AMEN
         
         
            ¶Lenuoy of the auctour.
            
               ¶Go forthe lytell quayre with full due reuerence
               Unto the prynces of beauty souerayne
               And the humbly submyt vnto her magnyfycence
               Requyrynge her to take not in dysdayne
               This lytell werke whiche with grete labour &amp; payne
               Her goodnes to declare I toke on honde to make
               Though I vnworthy were suche thȳges to vnder take
            
            
               Wherfore I beseche all you that shall ouer rede
               This lytell proses to haue me in no skornynge
               Nor me to dysprayse thoughe I so rudely enterprysed
               suche maters to take in honde to me nothȳge ꝑtainȳge
               But where as is amys there to be amendynge
               Thus I you pray with my hole affeccyon
               Whiche entendeth to rede or thys dytte to loke uppon
            
            Finis.
         
      
      
         
            ¶Imprynted at London in Flete strete at the sygne of the Sonne by Wynkyn de Worde.
         
      
   

