
   
      
         
            The strange discovery a tragi-comedy. Written by I.G. Gent.
            J. G. (John Gough), fl. 1640.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01989
            STC 12133
            ESTC S103348
            99839104
            99839104
            3500
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01989)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3500)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 959:04)
         
         
            
               
                  The strange discovery a tragi-comedy. Written by I.G. Gent.
                  J. G. (John Gough), fl. 1640.
                  Heliodorus, of Emesa.
               
               [88] p.   
               
                  Printed by E[dward] G[riffin] for William Leake, and are to be sold at his shop in Chancery-lane, joyning to the Roles,
                  London :
                  1640.
               
               
                  I.G. = John Gough.
                  Based on Heliodorus.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: [A]¹ B-M⁴ (-M4, =[A]1).
                  A variant of the edition with "I. Gough" on the title page.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-08
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2005-10
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE STRANGE DISCOVERY: A Tragi-Comedy.
            Written By J. G. Gent.
            LONDON, Printed by E. G. for William Leake, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Chancery-lane, joyning to the Roles. 1640.
         
      
      
         
            
            The Prologue.
            HOw's this, The ſtrange diſcovery, may ſome ſay,
            Tis likely we ſhall ſee ſome glorious Play
            Of Chriſtopher Columbus, and his brother,
            Whoſe navigable paines did firſt diſcover
            
               
                  America.
               That unknowne world, thinking the far fetch'd ſceane,
            To be Peru, and th' Indies, but to w
                  •
               ane
            Your expectations from this gold
                  •
               n dreame,
            Our Author bad me tell you, that the ſcope
            Of his intend
                  •
               d travell's Aethiope,
            
            There he begins, there ends, but as he paſſes
            To and againe, toucheth at many places,
            As Egypts fertile ſoile and learned Greece,
            
            Y
                  •
               t as h
                  •
               roicke Jaſon ſought the fleece
            In divers coaſts, but in the ſtately Ile
            Of Colchos gate it by Medeas guile,
            So he in Aethiopia ſ
                  •
               tteth downe
            The period of his plot, which but a frowne
            Of yours will ruinate, your gracious eyes,
            Raiſe to the height of Jaſons enterpriſe.
            The Hiſtory is candid, crown'd with praiſe,
            So let the play be too, our Poet prayes.
         
         
            The perſons of the Play.
            
               
                  HYdaſpes, King of Aethiopia.
               
               
                  P
                        •
                     rſina, his Queene.
               
                  Cariclea, their daughter.
               
                  Syfimethres, a Gymnoſophiſt Embaſſadour for the King,
               
                  Caricles, Apollos Prieſt.
               
                  Calaſiris, Iſis Prieſt.
               
                  Ariſtippus, a Citizen of Athens.
               
               
                  D
                        •
                     meneta, his wife.
               
                  Cnemon, Ariſtippus ſonne.
               
                  Thisbe, Demenetas maid.
               
                  Arſinoe, a Courtezan.
               
                  Nebulo, Caricles man.
               
                  Nebulona, his wife.
               
                  Theagines, a Theſſalian Captaine.
               
                  Arſace, wife to the Deputy of Aegypt.
               
               
                  Cibile, her Chamberlaine, nurſe, and bawd.
               
                  Aura, Cibiles mayd.
               4 Iudges, Magiſtrates of Perſia.
               
            
            Beſides meſſengers and attendance.
         
         
            
            THE STRANGE DISCOVERY, A Trage-Comedie.
            
               
                  Actus primi Scena prima.
                  Enter Caricles, ſometimes Apollos Prieſt at Delphos in the habit of a Pilgrim.
                  
                     Caric.
                     
                        WHat courſe ſhall aged Carcles now take
                     After his weary travells? ſhall I here
                     Reſolve to lay my bones, and Egypt make
                     The finall period of my pilgrimage?
                     No, I muſt bid Catadupíce adieu
                     So famous for theſe ſluces of faire Nile,
                     
                     And ſince the ſurfeit which I tooke of ſorrow
                     For my deare daughters ſad untimely death,
                     Is well digeſted in this breaſt of mine,
                     And change of aire hath wrought a change of mind;
                     I am reſolv'd to ſtately Greece to wend
                     And breath my laſt breath where I breath'd my firſt,
                     'Tis ſo determin'd;— Enter Nebulo his man.
                     
                     Honeſt Nebulo,
                     
                     My man draw neare, I'm in a humour now
                     To change ſome words with thee;—ſo oftentimes— aſide.
                     
                     We ſee wiſe men for recreations ſake,
                     
                        Conſult with Fooles, and honeſt men with Knaves.— aſide
                     
                     What courſe doth thy fond braine adviſe me to?
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     To no other but to a home courſe Sir, I muſt tell you plainly, I like not theſe extravagant ones you take of travelling the world thus; I'm ſure I have paid deare for thoſe idle humours of yours, witneſſe my body, brought to a meere Anatomie by travell and faſting; me thinkes, a wiſe man, as you are, ſhould not have ſuch wandring thoughts in his mind: well Maſter, reſolve to leave this place, and returne to Delphos our native habitation, or I ſhall ſoone reſolve to leave you, and goe there without you. O the ſmoake of mine owne poore chimney at home, and the beloved ſmoke of my wife, would both ſmell to my noſe now ſo comfortable, as a perfume made of Arabia ſpices; adiew, I can ſtay no longer from pretty Nebulona without the laſh of her juſt diſpleaſure; I come my chickin, I come, be ready to receive me, I know thou languiſheſt all this while for want of my company.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Nay prethee ſtay a little longer and heare me; wilt thou leave me now at laſt, and fruſtrate the good opinion I have alwaies had of thy ſimple plainneſſe and conſtant ſervice? have patience awhile, and I will accompany thee in thy journey; as for thy wife Nebulona (if that trouble thee) I ſhall rectifie her in the truth of al thy actions. Who knockes there? go
                           •
                         ſee, and bring me word before you grant entrance Nebulo.
                     
                     Exit, &amp; redit Nebulo.
                     Who is it now?
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     A very ſweet fac'd Gentleman, ſo ſooty as the Divell himſelfe, I believe ſome Embaſſadour ſent from Pluto and the fiends.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     What e'r he be admit him.
                  
                  Enter Siſimethres, Legate of Aethiopia.
                  
                     Siſimet.
                     God ſave you reverend Father.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Welcome Sir,
                     Although I have not ſeene your face before
                     That I can well remember.
                  
                  
                     Siſimet.
                     May be ſo.
                     But I have ſeene you often in this towne
                     Walking the ſtreets, and read the character
                           •
                        
                     
                     
                        Of gravity and wiſdome ciphered in
                     Your aged face, wherein I thinke my judgement
                     Nothing deceives me; and I doe ſuppoſe
                     You are an aliene here as well as I,
                     No naturall Egyptian.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I confeſſe
                     I am a ſtranger borne, and ſhould be glad
                     To know your name, your countrey and your buſineſſe.
                  
                  
                     Siſimet.
                     I ſhall obey you, for my countrey, firſt
                     'Tis Aethiopia underneath the line,
                     My name Siſimethres imployed now
                     As Legate from my ſoveraigne King Hydaſpes,
                     
                     Unto the Deputy here, to forbid him
                     To meddle with the mines, out of whoſe bowells
                     The Smaragds digged were, which appertaine
                     To none but to the crowne of Aethiopia:
                     
                     Now Sir you know me, be not ſcrupulous
                     To let me underſtand ſo much of you,
                     Something doth prompt me ſtrangely, that you have
                     Some neer relation to the gods, or elſe
                     My Genius doth deceive me.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Underſtand then,
                     You doe not erre in your imagination,
                     I am a Grecian borne, and ſometimes Prieſt
                     Unto Apollo in that ſacred City
                     Of Delphos, which Parnaſſus lofty tops,
                     As with a wall, encompaſſeth about,
                     And ſweet Caſtalius pleaſant ſprings refreſh,
                     There was I borne and bred, and exercis'd
                     The office I was call'd to by the gods.
                  
                  
                     Siſimet.
                     Most venerable Prieſt, and holy Father,
                     Let me beſeech you tell me what miſchance
                     Drove you from thence to theſe remoter parts?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     The great misfortune that I had at home.
                  
                  
                     Siſim.
                     I wonder at it, pray relate the manner.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     When you have heard my ſtory to the end,
                     Your wonder will forſake you.
                  
                  
                     Siſimet.
                     Then reſolve me
                  
                  
                     
                     Caric.
                     Upon your better knowledge and acquaintance
                     I ſh
                           •
                        ll, till when excuſe me.
                  
                  
                     Siſim.
                     I'll not preſſe you
                     Beyond good manners; Sir, I ſaw you buy
                     Some herbs and roots that grow in India
                     
                     And Aethiopia for your uſe laſt day;
                     If ſo you pleaſe, I can produce you ſuch
                     As ne'r were better.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Pray Sir let me ſee them,
                     Syſimethres take from under his arme a little bagge, and ſhewes Caricles precious ſtones in ſtead of roots.
                     You muſt for theſe, good Sir, ſeeke other chapmen,
                     The Margaritas, the Smaragds, Hiacinths,
                     Are for a Princes uſe, and not for mine:
                     Each one alone is ranſome for a King,
                     My whole eſtate cannot buy one of them.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     But though you cannot buy them, you can take them (I trow) if freely given you, can you not?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     'Tis true, I can receive them, but I marvell
                     Why you ſhould mocke me thus?
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     I mocke you not
                     By all the Gods, but meane uprightly in't,
                     I will not onely give you theſe, but if
                     You will be pleaſ'd to take it at my hands
                     Beſtow a richer gift, to which compar'd,
                     Theſe are but droſſe and rubbiſh.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Ha ha ha.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Why laugh you Sir?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Is't not a matter which
                     Deſerveth laughter, when you promiſe things
                     Of ſuch a priſe, and yet aſſure me more;
                     You cannot meane uprightly.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Ttruſt me, but ſweare
                     That you will uſe this gift as I ſhall teach you,
                     And I'll performe my promiſe of the other.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     Accept it Sir, if you be wiſe; 'tis not good, nor religious to refuſe any mans courteſie.
                  
                  
                     
                     Caric.
                     You tempt me ſhrewdly Sir.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Let me prevaile,
                     And bind me ſtill your ſervant.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     You have won me
                     To what you would.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Then take an oath, and ſweare
                     To follow my directions, ſo confirme it.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     By great Apollo, then whoſe Miniſter
                     I was at Delphos, I ſhall not digreſſe
                     From what you ſhall inſtruct me touching this.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     It is ſufficient, and I build upon
                     Your faith, your truſt and your religion;
                     Here fellow, take this bag, and keepe it for
                     Your honoured Maſter.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     But more honoured bag,
                     Would I might keepe thee for my ſelfe, I then
                     Should make an Idoll of thee — aſide.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     What's your pleaſure,
                     That I ſhould doe in lieu of this reward?
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     I cannot now acquaint you, for ſome reaſons
                     Beſt knowne unto my ſelfe, give me your hand
                     To meet me without faile tomorow morning
                     At Iſis Temple, thence I ſhall conduct you
                     Unto my lodging, and in ſecret tell
                     The ſumme of my requeſt.
                  
                  
                     Carie.
                     I ſhall not faile you.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Adieu, untill we meet— Exit Syſimethres.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     
                        Apollo keepe thee
                     In his ſafe cuſtodie. I marvell much
                     Whence this unlook'd for kindneſſe ſhould proceed,
                     I'll ſee the iſſue on't, what e'r betide me,
                     It may be that the gods have pre-ordain'd
                     I ſhall once more be happy, and in lieu
                     Of all my paſſed ſorrowes, reape the fruit
                     Of long expected comfort, ſure my mind
                     Is much illuminated with the thought
                     Of ſome good fortune, and refreſh'd as if
                     The ſpirit of Pitho were infuſ'd into me
                     
                        By heavenly inſpiration; I'll obey
                     My Genius, for oftentimes the gods by ſignes
                     Will have that mortalls underſtand their mindes. Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus primi  Scena ſecunda.
                  Enter Demeneta, and young Cnemon her ſonne in Law.
                  
                     Demen.
                     MY pretty boy, how doſt thou? where haſt thou beene ſo long abſent from my imbraces; come hither, let mee ſolace my ſelfe a little with thee, let mee kiſſe thee my ſweet heart, my heire, my owne life.
                  
                  
                     
                        Cnem:
                     Had ever any one a kinder ſtepmother— aſide. Mother, you make too much of mee, I am not able to deſerve your love in ſo high a ſtraine, my duty cannot countervaile it.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     How prettily hee ſpeakes, I cannot chuſe but kiſſe thee for it.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     What a cloſe and hot kiſſe was that? I like not this behaviour, would I were delivered hence, pleaſe you give mee leave to goe about my exerciſes?
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     What exerciſes?
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     My bookes and ſtudies at the Schoole, I ſhall be ſhent elſe by my Tutor.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Come, thou ſhalt not leave me.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Will you have me prove a truant then?
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     No, but a ſtudent in a better art; haſt thou ever read Ovid de arte amandi, or Ovids amorous Epiſtles?
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Never.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     O, I would have thee ſtudy that booke above all other, there are very good rules, and worth the obſervation truly, if thou erreſt in any thing therein written, I will be thy Miſtreſſe to inſtruct thee, follow my rudiments good ſonne.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     But I have heard 'tis a ribaldrous booke, and corrupteth youth to all wantonneſſe.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     That is but a fantaſie, a mere untruth; it was made by the Poet for youthfull recreation and paſtime, none but Stoicall old men will invey againſt them, who envie that in others which they cannot enjoy in themſelves.
                  
                  
                     
                     Cnem.
                     I underſtand not your Philoſophie.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Would thou didſt, and wert well entred in my book
                           •
                         and ſcience; but where is thy father and my husband Ariſtippus?
                     
                     Enter Ariſtippus.
                     O, my deare husband, where have you lingred ſo long; you are too blame indeed to leave me ſo ſolitary, I muſt chide you for it, truly, had you tarried never ſo little longer, I ſhould have died for ſorrow.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     My ſweet wife Demeneta, I have a jewell of thee, thy extreme love to me is confirmed in thy affection to my ſonne Cnemon, vertuous woman.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     I love him I muſt confeſſe, as well as if he were mine owne ſonne, or better.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     I know thou doſt my love; never was a man happier in his choice, I thinke.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     
                        Cnemon, ſit on my lap pretty boy.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     No, I know my duty better.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     I will have it ſo; the very picture of his father.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Pray mother excuſe me, this is no fit place for me.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     There is not a prettier or wittier boy in Athens, but 'tis no wonder, that old men beget alwaies the fineſt children, 'tis moſt commonly ſeene.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     I know your vertue, and therefore will diſpute with you a little upon this ſubject, and aske you this queſtion: how could you, a young woman, affect me an old man?
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     How could I not Sir; your wiſdome, ſtayedneſſe and underſtanding were ſuch motives to my affection, as I would not change my old man for the youthfull'ſt cavalere of all Greece; I hope for all your age, to have a hopefull off-ſpring from you, ſuch another as Cnemon, you can doe it i'faith, old Ariſtippus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     My girle, how thou doſt revive my decayed ſpirits to heare thee talke thus! I will ſtraine hard for this, but I will anſwer thy expectation.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     Thankes ſweet husband, let me hang upon your necke, pretty gravity, how well it becomes him, who could chuſe but love ſuch a man intirely; pox upon ſmooth faces,

and young luſty gallants, there's more trouble with them a bed, when a gentlewoman would ſleep and take her reſt; they are alwaies diſturbing of her, when by a man of ſome yeeres and experience we may lie as quiet as we will; would all women were of my opinion, we ſhould cut the combes then of theſe luſtie gameſters.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Indeed young men are very inconſtant in their love, and changing from one unto another, whereas an old man perſeveres to the end in his devotions.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     True, true, my love, your words are oracles,
                     Were I now as I ſeeme, how ſhould I wrong
                     Youth, beautie, nature, and rebell againſt them — aſide.
                     
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     My deareſt love, though loth, I am inforc'd
                     To leave you for ſome houres, the ſtate of Athens
                     
                     Sent for me, to repaire unto the Senate
                     At ten a clocke about affaires of weight,
                     'Tis now about the time; farewell my ſweeteſt.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     You ſhall not goe, come, come, you doe not love me,
                     Elſe could you not be ſo unkind my deare,
                     To kill your loving wife with your departure.
                     I doubt I ſhall not live till your returne.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Come prethee, leave this off, and be aſſur'd
                     I will not ſtay two houres.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     On that aſſurance
                     I doe diſmiſſe you, but if you exceed
                     The time, you're like to find me turn'd a coarſe;
                     ſticke to your promiſe.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     I'll not faile you ſweet.— Exit Ariſtippus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Where goe you Cnemon?
                     
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     No where, but to waite
                     Upon my Father to the Senate-houſe,
                     And inſtantly returne.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     See that you doe,
                     And you ſhall not repent it, Exit Cnemon.
                     
                     I muſt gaine him
                     Unto my will by faire and gentle meanes,
                     By promiſes and gifts, by ſweet allurements
                     And ſtrong inticing words, by pleaſing him
                     
                        With what he likes beſt, this will take his youth
                     (I make no doubt) and bring me to his bed.
                     I burne for love of him and muſt be quench'd,
                     Old Ariſtippus I have fool'd and made
                     Believe I love him, but it is not ſo.
                     I have brought him to my owne lure ſo th
                           ••
                        
                     
                     He ſtoops unto my beauty; now if I
                     Can but enjoy my Cnemon, I am then
                     Miſtris of my deſigne, and a chiefe Artiſt
                     In this ſweet trade; let fooles burne in their fire
                     Of modeſt love, i'le on to my deſire. Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus primi, Scena tertia.
                  Enter Caricles, Syſimethres and Nebulo.
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Prethee honeſt friend
                     Shall I intreat thee to go forth and bid
                     The pretty girle without in the next room
                           •
                        
                     
                     To come here to me.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     Yes ſir that I ſhall,
                     I love to be imploy'd a meſſenger
                     To pretty mayds, is ſhe ſo beautifull▪
                     
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     O wondrous faire and beautifull.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     I'le then
                     Uſher her ſafely in, and kiſſe her too.
                  
                  Exit Nebulo, enters againe with Cariclea.
                  
                     Syſim.
                     See here the ſecond gift I meane to give you:
                     More pretious then the firſt, you told me ſir
                     You had a daughter once, but rap'd by death.
                     Here is another for you, uſe her well.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I am amaz'd to ſee ſo rare a beauty,
                     Such an Angel-like creature.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Ceaſe your wonder;
                     The mother of this beautious girle which here
                     Standeth before us for a certaine cauſe
                     Which you ſhall learne hereafter, laid her forth
                     Clad in ſuch weeds as commonly is us'd
                     For ſuch a purpoſe, ſo committing her
                     
                        To fortunes doubtfull chance, but I by hap
                     Finding her tooke her up, for tis not lawfull
                     That we neglect a ſoule when once it hath
                     Entred a humane body, (being a precept
                     Amongſt the wiſe men with us, to be whoſe
                     Unlearned ſcholler I was once judg'd worthy)
                     Be
                           •
                        ides even in the infants eyes appear'd,
                     Something which bred both wonder and delight.
                     With her I found this bag of precious ſtones
                     Whi
                           •
                        h I gave you of late, and a ſilke cloth
                     Wrought full with letters in her mother tongue,
                     Wherein contayned was her whole eſtate;
                     Her mother as I gheſſe procur'd the ſame,
                     Which a
                           •
                        ter I had read, I knew from whence
                     and what ſhee was, and 
                           •
                        herefore carryed her
                     Into the Land farre diſtant from the City
                     Delivering her to certaine honeſt ſhepheards
                     To bring her up, with charge that they ſhould not
                     Reveale her unto any; for thoſe things
                     That were found with her I detain'd with me,
                     Leaſt for them ſhe might suffer any danger,
                     And thus at firſt this matter was kept cloſe.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     But what befell her after pray goe one.
                     In proceſſe then of time this princelie maid
                     Growing and as ſhe grew encreaſing ſtill
                     More faire then any women elſe beſides
                     (For beautie ſurelie cannot 
                           •
                        e conceald
                     Though under ground but would from thence appeare)
                     I fearing leaſt her fortune ſhould be knowne
                     And I brought unto danger, ſu'd to be
                     Sent in embaſſage to the Deputie
                     Of Egipt and abtained it, therefore come I
                     And bring her with me, full of zealous care
                     To ſet her buſines right and in good order.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Leave that to me.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     But chiefly unto me,
                     I'le be her guardion too.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     What will you have me doe concerning her?
                     
                        Direct me, and i'le punctualle obſerve it.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     As touching her, firſt I commend her to you,
                     (And to the gods who hitherto have kept her,)
                     On ſuch conditions as by oath you'r bound
                     To ſee perform'd, that is that you will uſe her
                     As a free woman ought to be, and give her
                     In marriage to a free man, as you doe
                     Recevie her at my hand, or rather of
                     Her mother who hath left her to your charge:
                     I hope you will performe all things according
                     Unto your oath, and anſwer the opinion
                     I have of your good manners, which I finde
                     By ſome few dayes experience to be
                     Greekiſh indead; this much I had to ſay
                     Before I executed my commiſſion
                     Concerning my embaſſage, other ſecrets
                     Belonging to the maid, i'le tell you them
                     To morrow in more ample manner, if
                     You pleaſe to meet me about Iſis temple.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Expect me there then; but I cannot brooke
                     So long a time to ſee the Virgin mask'd
                     In ſo obſcure a manner.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Now I cannot
                     Stay to diſcover what I know of her;
                     The Deputie of Egypt hath appointed
                     This day for hearing of me: farewell both. Exit Syſim.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Can you ſpeake Greeke my pretty ſweet heart, can
                     you?ſhe ſmiles upon him but ſaies nothing.
                     
                     No, can you ſpeake Egyptian? neither ſweet?
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     I'le undertake to teach her both the tongues
                     So I may be her tutor. ſhe frownes upon him.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Nebulo
                     Thou ſeeſt I have another daughte
                           •
                         
                        
                           •
                        ow,
                     She ſhall be called faire Cariclea
                     
                     Deriv'd from Caricles which is my name.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     Would I had ſuch a daughter too, ſhe ſhould not
                     Have then ſo courſe a name, all men ſhould call her.
                     The pretty Nebuletta; Nebulo,
                     
                     
                        Then Nebulona, then neate Nebuletta,
                     
                     A ſumptuous pedegree, how ſweet it runnes!
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Thy houſe would flouriſh then, were ſhe thy daughter.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     Above the clouds, the gods would lodge themſelves
                     Beneath my roofe, and powre downe plenty on me
                     In golden ſhowers to reſt in Danaes lap.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     What growne ſo high conceited Nebulo?
                     
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     Something inſpir'd my braine, I know not what ſir,
                     But now i'm come unto my ſelfe againe,
                     'Twas but a toy that tooke me.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I believe it,
                     Many ſuch toyes doe take thee in the head:
                     Get me a maske, I muſt convey this damzell
                     Muffled home to my houſe.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     She need not be
                     Aſham'd to ſhew her face, it may procure her
                     A husband by the way for ought you know;
                     You ſhall but wrong her much in doing ſo.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Sirrah away, diſpute no more, but doe it.
                  
                  Exit &amp; redit with a maske, they muffle her.
                  
                     Nebul.
                     'Tis pitty faith methinkes to uſe her thus,
                     'Tis ſuch a pretty thing.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Come you muſt goe
                     With me my daughter deare where you ſhall be
                     Uſ'd and reſpected as my native child:
                     When I have underſtood (harke Nebulo
                     
                     Her's newes for thee) by good Syſimethres
                     
                     My daughters fur
                           •
                        her ſtate, we'll hye forthwith
                     To Greece and Delphos, and put on againe
                     My firſt religious habit; to your ſhrines
                     Ye gods we'll offer ſanctified minds. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus primi, Scena quarta.
                  Enter Demeneta and Thisbe her mayd.
                  
                     Demen.
                     When ſaweſt thou Cnemon, Thisbe?
                     
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Know you not
                     That Pallas high feaſt call'd Quinquatria
                     
                        This day was celebrated here in Athens,
                     
                     One with a ſhip by land, (as is the manner)
                     Was conſecrated, Cnemon was imployd,
                     Clad in his robes, and on his head a crowne,
                     To ſing the uſuall hymne due to her praiſe
                     I ſaw him buſie in the ceremonies.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Is this the day? by Iove I knew it not,
                     Elſe had I beene ſpectator of the ſight,
                     Chiefly to ſee my Cnemon in his office,
                     Could I be angry with him, I ſhould chide him
                     For not acquainting me.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     He did it neatly;
                     I would not for my maiden-head have miſs'd
                     So rare a ſight, not for ten maiden-heads.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Are all the rites and ceremonies done?
                     I faine would ſee yet the concluſion.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Miſtreſſe, tis to late; ſee Cnemon there return'd in all his robes.
                  
                  Enter Cnemon in his robes crowned, Demeneta runnes to him and takes him in her armes.
                  
                     Dem.
                     My young Hippolitus, and my deare Theſeus,
                     
                     Welcome, O welcome to me.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Heavens defend me
                     From this lewd Phaedra— aſide. Mother what dee meane
                     To burne me thus with kiſſes?
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Burthen thee
                     With bliſſes too I can, my pretty boy,
                     If thou wilt love thy mother.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     In what nature
                     Require you that? if as it ought to be,
                     That children love their Parents, I agree.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     As 
                           Ʋenus with Anchiſes ſported once
                     In Ida grove, ſo let mee ſport with thee;
                     Doſt underſtand me now?
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     You are too bold,
                     Too impudent.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Nay, prethee doe not frowne,
                     This night I muſt enjoy thee, and thou me,
                     
                        Thy fathers abſence doth invite us to it;
                     I will maintaine thee like a Princes ſonne,
                     Glittering in gold, and our ſweet furtive ſports
                     Keepe from the ſunne and knowledge of the gods,
                     No one ſhall know it.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Hence inceſtuous woman,
                     Think'ſt thou to make me wrong my fathers bed,
                     And to commit an act ſo foule as inceſt?
                     Tempt me no more; by heaven, by earth and all
                     Th'immortall gods, I'le die a thouſand deaths
                     Ere thinke a thought on't, much leſſe yeeld unto it,
                     Your damned wit, nor quaint inticing words
                     Shall not prevaile, my hate exceeds my love.
                  
                  Exit Cnemon in a rag3.
                  
                     Demen.
                     Am I deſpiſed thus, and my hot love
                     Requited with diſdaine, as cold as ice,
                     By ſuch a youngling? he ſhall know the difference
                     Betweene a womans favours and her frownes,
                     And curſe too late his fooliſh modeſty:
                     Goe Thisbe to the Caſtle, tell my husband
                     I am not well, intreat him to come to me
                     With all the ſpeed he can.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     I ſhall ſweet Miſtreſſe.— Exit Thisbe.
                     
                  
                  Demeneta a lies down upon the bed, faining her ſelfe ſicke.
                  
                     Dem.
                     What raging fires ſtill burne me? how I am
                     Divided in my ſelfe tweene love and hate,
                     two mighty paſſions combatting together?
                     Love would prevaile, if reaſon might be judge,
                     But love is too unreaſonably harſh:
                     Hate therefore execute thy proper function,
                     Enflame my breaſt with rage and high diſdaine
                     Againſt this brat that gave me the repulſe,
                     Inſpire my ſtudy in his Tragedie.
                  
                  Enter Ariſtippus and Thisbe.
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     How fares my ſweet heart, that ſhe keepes her bed?
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Deare husband, very ſicke and in ill caſe.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     The gods forbid, that ſound doth ſtrike me dead;
                     What ailes my deareſt wife? tell me the cauſe
                     
                        Of this your ſudden ſickneſſe.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Nothing Sir,
                     I know no cauſe at all.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Come, come, you muſt not
                     Conceale your griefe, but lay it ope unto me,
                     I doe beſeech my love.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Since you are ſo
                     Importunate to know it, underſtand
                     The goodly young man, ſonne unto us both
                     (To you by nature, but to me by love)
                     Whom I (the gods know) held as deare unto me
                     As you, when he perceiv'd by certaine tokens
                     I was with child by you (which thing I kept
                     Hid from your knowledge till I knew my ſelfe
                     The certainty) and waiting for your abſence,
                     When I in wonted manner councell'd him
                     To leave his whores, and to avoid his cups
                     (Which things I knew he lov'd, but would not tell you,
                     Leſt I ſhould run into the ill ſuſpition
                     Of ſtepmother) whileſt I in gentle manner
                     Told him theſe things, I will not ſpeake the worſt,
                     Nor in what ſort he did revile us both,
                     But laſt of all, he ſpurn'd me on the belly,
                     Which hath procur'd this my diſeaſe and paine.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     O villaine, I will ſcurge him even to death;
                     
                        Thisbe, goe call him hither. Exit Thisbe,
                     
                  
                  Then preſently enters Cnemon, Ariſtippus falls preſently a buffetting of him without ſpeaking a word, then calls his ſervants and ſcurgeth him with rods.
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Deare father, I beſeech you let me know
                     The cauſe of this your anger and my ſtripes
                     So cruelly laid on mee.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Oh cleanly diſſembler,
                     Thou wouldſt indeed know thy owne fault from me.
                  
                  Hee beats him afreſh.
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Yet now at length, Sir, let me underſtand
                     What I have done, that thus provokes your wrath,
                     The gods doe know my innocence.
                  
                  
                     
                     Ariſt.
                     Baſe wretch,
                     Thy innocence; would ſhe belie thee thinkſt thou,
                     That lov'd thee better than her ſelfe? away,
                     Get out of my ſight, I will not heare thee ſpeak. Exit Cnemon.
                     
                     My deareſt Demeneta, cheere your ſelfe,
                     Strive to forget the paine.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     I'm in bad plight,
                     So that I doe not onely feare the life
                     Of that I goe with, but mine owne, beſides,
                     Theſe accidents are dangerous to women;
                     Yet, Sir, it griev'd me that you tooke ſo ſharpe
                     A puniſhment of Cnemon, for all this
                     I cannot chuſe but love him.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     That's thy vertue,
                     But baniſh him thy thoughts as I will doe,
                     Hence forth as moſt unworthy of our love;
                     Come ſweet, you ſhall remove from hence into
                     A fitter roome, I'le ſend a Doctor to you. Exit Ariſtippus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     You doe miſtake my pulſe, whoſe veines doe ſwell
                     With rage and furie, and ſhall live in paine,
                     Untill I be reveng'd.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     My Miſtreſſe knowes
                     How to deceive old Dotards with falſe ſhewes. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus primi  Scena quinta.
                  Enter Nebulo ſolus, frisking for joy.
                  
                     Nebul.
                     WEe ſhall fall downe the river Nile to night, and hoiſe ſaile for Greece, brave newes, comfortable newes, my heart capers within me for joy, that I ſhall ſee my countrey againe; my Maſter is ſore troubled for blacke Syſimethres his conſtrained flight, which hath defeited their appointed meeting and conference touching Caricleas fortunes, but haſte our journey the ſooner, there's my comfort. I left him curſing the Deputy, and invoking the god Apollos wrath to plague him for diſmiſſing the Embaſſadour ſo ſuddenly, with ſuch deadly threatenings to depart the Kingdome. Alas, poore maid, I pity thee, that by this meanes thou ſhalt not be able to

knowe who begot thee nor who brought thee forth, but all's one, thou wilt ſoone learne to be begotten, and to bring forth by inſtinct of nature and thy owne experience. Catadupice adiew adiew, adiew gentlemen; when you ſee us next, twill be in Delphos; away, away, away, merrylie, merrily.
                  
                  Exit.
                  Finis actus primi.
               
            
            
               
                  Actus ſecundi, Scena prima.
                  Enter Calaſiris Iſis prieſt at Memphis.
                  Am I the goodeſſe Iſis prieſt, and burne
                  In theſe unlawfull fires? ſhall Rhodopis
                  
                  With her 
                        Ʋenerious charmes ſubdue my heart,
                  And make me breake that temperance of life
                  Which I have hitherto preſerv'd unſpotted?
                  What ſhall I doe? I cannot ſtand the puſh
                  Of theſe ſtrong paſſions, yet I am reſolv'd
                  Nere to commit the act, nor ſo to ſtaine
                  My prieſthood with diſhonour; Iſis temple
                  And ſecret places ſhall not be defil'd
                  By Calaſiris, no i'le rather banniſh
                  My ſelfe from ſight of curſed Rodopis,
                  
                  Leaſt ſtaying here I ſhould be forc'd to doe
                  So vile a deed; I am reſolv'd to leave
                  This ſtatelie City Memphis ſuddenly,
                  I'le give it out, my iourney is for Thebes
                  
                  To ſee my eldeſt ſonne call'd Thiamis.
                  
                  VVith this pretence I ſhall unqueſtion'd goe,
                  But there's a City ſacred to Apollo
                  
                  In Greece hight Delphos, there i'le bend my courſe
                  (For tis a Colledge where wiſe men reſort
                  Free from the concourſe of the common people)
                  To viſit my old friend prieſt Caricles.
                  
                  When whoriſh beautie and vaine pride diſplay
                  Their gaudie colours, wiſe men ſhun the way. Exit.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Actus ſecundi, Scena ſecunda.
                  Enter Demeneta and Thisbe.
                  
                     Dem.
                     
                        Thisbe my wench, thou muſt be ſecret unto all my commands.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     As your owne heart could wiſh, as your truſty cabinet.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     I am confident of thee; thou know'ſt how I lov'd that proud boy Cnemon, what proffers I made him, what favours I beſtow'd upon him, and all to winne him to my imbraces, yet how ſcornfully and ſcurvily he refuſed me, with what diſdaine he left me; I am now reſolv'd no longer to ſollicite my love but to execute my revenge; I have devis'd a dainty plot againſt him, which will take according as I would wiſh, follow thou my directions.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     I will not digreſſe a haires breadth miſtris.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     Then thus I ſchoole thee, make a ſhew that thou lov'ſt Cnemon exceedingly, entice him to thee with beckes and amorous glances, he'll ſoone be caught with theſe baites, eſpecially having heretofore long nibled upon thy beauty; frequent his bed often, be not aſham'd, it ſhall be for thy great advancement, and whereas thou art now a bondmaid, thou ſhalt be made free forever.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     I am your creature in all things, eſpecially in matters of this nature.
                  
                  
                     Dem.
                     When thou haſt done this which I command thee, I will inſtruct thee farther.
                  
                  Exit Demeneta. Manet Thisbe a little.
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     I waite your pleaſure. I muſt give Cnemon good countenance, well, I muſt entice the young man, well, I muſt lie with him too, very well; faith theſe are no harſh commands, it ſhall never grieve me to be imployd in ſuch worke, would my miſtris had no harder labour for me, this is a taske of pleaſure; I have a warrant now for what I ſhall doe; I durſt not yeild to C
                              ••
                           mon before when he attempted me, now let him come with his ſtouteſt artillery, I will ſtand the charge valiantly.
                     Enter Cnemon.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Faire Thisbe are you here? why now I like you,
                     
                        You ſmile upon me, and your countenance
                     Darts amorous glances which before caſt frownes,
                     Now you appeare like 
                           Ʋenus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Courteous Cnemon,
                     
                     Although at firſt I did deny your ſuit,
                     Impute it not to want of love, but place
                     And oportunity, beſides the doubt
                     And danger which the action brings with it
                     If once diſcover'd, made me to commit
                     So groſſe an errour.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Will you be reform'd
                     Upon mature counſell?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     You ſhall ſee
                     I will not be refractory to ought
                     You ſhall adviſe me, I doe know your mind,
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Come with me then and learne to kiſſe and ſmile,
                     You know the backe way to my chamber ſweet.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     I do, and will attend you, there wee'l meet. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus ſecundi, Scena tertia.
                  Enter Caricles and Calaſiris.
                  
                     Caric.
                     Welcome to Greece my worthy friend and brother,
                     And in the fitteſt time, becauſe I ſhall
                     Need your aſſiſtance in the perfecting
                     A buſineſſe which concernes me, you are wiſe
                     And can perſwade, when reaſon is your theame.
                  
                  
                     Cala.
                     What I can doe, our long acquaintance ſir
                     And brotherhood in travell and vocation,
                     VVils me to render it unto your ſervice;
                     VVherein can I be uſefull to my friend?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     In this, you know laſt night I did relate
                     
                        Cariclaes ſtory, how I did receive her
                     And brought her from your Egypt here to Greece,
                     
                     where in a ſhort time ſhe hath learn'd our tongu
                           •
                        ,
                     And ſo farre paſſeth ſhe all other beauties
                     That ſhe attracteth all mens eyes to gaze
                     VVith admiration on her, as well ſtrangers
                     
                        As Greekes, ſo that where e'r ſhee be converſant,
                     Either at home, or in the Temples, or
                     At publique exerciſes, all mens eyes
                     Are fix'd upon her with as great devotion
                     As if ſhe were the image of ſome goddeſſe
                     Lately created; that which grieves me, is
                     She loathes to heare of marriage, and reſolves
                     To live a maiden ſtill, and ſo becomming
                     
                        Dianas ſervant, for the moſt part doth
                     Apply her ſelfe to hunting and to ſhooting;
                     I had a great deſire to marry her
                     Unto my ſiſters ſonne, a fine young man,
                     Well manner'd, and faire ſpoken; but I cannot,
                     Either by prayer or promiſe, or by force
                     Of argument perſwade her thereunto:
                     In this I crave your helpe, deare Calaſiris,
                     
                     Uſe ſome point of your wiſedome to perſwade her
                     To know her nature, that ſhe is a woman,
                     And that ſhe would not ſo degenerate
                     From all thoſe of her ſex; this I beſeech you
                     To doe for great Apollos ſake, and all
                     Your countrey gods.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     In this point, Caricles,
                     
                     I'le doe my beſt indeavour. Enter Nebulo.
                     
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     Maſter, come
                     Away for ſhame, the captaine of the Aenians
                     
                     Embaſſage ſtayeth for you at the gate
                     For to begin the ſacrifice.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Pray Sir,
                     What are thoſe Aenians? what their holy meſſage?
                     What ſacrifice make they?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     They are the nobleſt
                     Of all Theſſalia, this ſame ſacrifice
                     They ſend to Pirrhus, ſtout Achilles ſonne,
                     Every fourth yeere (at ſuch time as the feaſt
                     
                        Agen is kept unto Apollo here)
                     For here was Pirrhus maſſacred before
                     
                        Apollos altars by enrag'd Oreſtes,
                     
                     
                        This meſſage is more honourably done
                     Than any of the reſt, becauſe they ſay
                     The Captaine is ſprung from Achilles line.
                     Indeed, ſuch is the beauty of his perſon
                     And brave majeſticke carriage, as confirmes
                     He is ſome goddeſſe ſonne.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     I faine would ſee him.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     You ſhall, and his brave order'd ſacrifice,
                     
                        Cariclea too, my daughter, muſt be there
                     To day by cuſtome, at the funerall pompe
                     Of Neoptolemus, but you have ſeene her
                     Before.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Yes, and done ſacrifice together.
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     Come, you muſt goe unto the Temple with us
                     To helpe me in this ceremonious worke.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Lead on, I'le follow, if I'm prompted right,
                     Strange things will happen after this rare ſight Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus ſecundi Scena quarta.
                  Enter Cnemon and Thisbe.
                  
                     Cnem.
                     
                        Thisbe my love, we muſt act cloſely, and with great circumſpection, leſt we be diſcovered by the miſchievous Demeneta, who (as thou ſay'ſt) hates me more now than ſhe lov'd me before.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     You talke ſimply Cnemon, if you count it a dangerous matter for me being a bond-maid, bought with money, to be taken a bed with you; what puniſhment thinke you her worthy, who is a free-woman, and lawfully married to a husband, yet playeth falſe, and beareth a man too many.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     I judge her worthy of death, but who is the perſon, prethee?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Your vertuous ſtepmother, my Miſtreſſe Demeneta, now you may be reveng'd upon her by diſcovering it to your father Ariſtippus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     I can ſcarce believe it.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     To confirme my report (if you pleaſe) I will delive
                           •
                         the adulterer unto you in the very act.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     You ſhall doe me a courteſie then.
                  
                  
                     
                     Thiſ.
                     VVith all my heart, not onely for your ſake who have been injured by her before, but for mine owne alſo, who, for that ſhe hath me in jealouſie, am uſed of her very extreamely, wherefore if thou be a man apprehend him.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Elſe let me die in ſcorne and infamie,
                     Ile kill them both, for ne're ſhall it be ſaid,
                     That Cnemon knew his fathers bed defil'd
                     And durſt not be reveng'd, aſſiſt my hand
                     Infernall furies, Thisbe lead the way
                     That I may doe the deed ere ſee the day. Exeunt
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus Secundi, Scena quinta.
                  Enter Ariſtippus and Demeneta.
                  
                     Demen.
                     'Tis late 'ith night, ſweet husband, let's to bed,
                     I cannot have too much of your imbraces,
                     The envious day will interrupt our ſport,
                     Me thinks we married were but yeſterday.
                  
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     Conceiv'ſt thou ſo, that doth proceed from love,
                     But I am old, and thou a ſprightly laſſe.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     You wrong your ſelfe, you are a luſty man,
                     For were you old the dull effects of age
                     Would then appeare, but I have had experience
                     Of your performance, Cnemon, I believe,
                     Your ſonne is not ſo active in his trade.
                  
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     If it be ſo, then ſure the youthfull heat
                     Of thy faire body hath infuſed life
                     Into my withered vaines, more powerfull then
                     Medeas charmes, when ſhe ſtir'd up freſh blood
                     In the decayed body of old Aeſon.
                     
                  
                  Enter Cnemon with his ſword drawne followed by Thisbe, a candle carried before, he comes haſtily to the bed.
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Where is the villaine, the moſt worthy lover
                     Of this chaſte dame?
                  
                  his father leapes out of the bed, and falls on his knees before him.
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     My ſonne, have pitty on thy fathers age,
                     Spaire his white haires, take not away his life
                     That gave thee thine, and brought thee up with care,
                     
                        We doe confeſſe we wrong'd thee, yet the fault
                     Was not ſo great that it ſhould merit death;
                     Aſſwage thy fury, and put up thy ſword,
                     Imbrue not in thy fathers blood thy hands.
                  
                  Cnemon in amaze lookes round about him for Thisby, who had conveyed her ſelfe away, and being thus aſtoniſhed, his ſword fell out of his hand, which Demeneta ſtraightwaies tooke up.
                  
                     Dem.
                     Did I not tell you this before, ſweet heart,
                     To looke unto this princoks pride and hate
                     Who would no doubt, if time had ſerv'd his turne,
                     Attempt ſome miſchiefe to deſtroy us both.
                  
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     You told me ſo indeed, but I believ'd not;
                     Now I do finde it true, which to prevent
                     I'le raiſe my houſe and bind him faſt, to morrow
                     I'le carry him before the people to
                     Be judg'd for his offence; let nature goe
                     In parents, when ſonnes prove unnaturall ſo. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus secundi, Scena sexta.
                  Enter Nebulo and Nebulona.
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     
                        Nebulona my pretty chickin, how faires thy body? didſt thou not thinke me loſt long agoe?
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     I gave you for dead in good faith, and was in the humour once to marry another man?
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Why ſure thou wert not, thou doſt but jeſt I know.
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     Truely I was, nor could you blame me for it if I had; is it not a torture, thinke you, for a woman, to ſtay ſeven yeeres without her husbands company?
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Methinkes my browes begin Acteon-like to bud already, they are very knotty, I pray God thou haſt not graft ſomething there, I begin to ſuſpect it ſhrewdly by diverſe ſignes and tokens, how comes your belly ſo high wife?
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     'Tis nothing but a timpany I am ſometimes troubled with.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     I do believe thee, how long is it ſince you perceiv'd it to grow upon you?
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     About two moneths ſince, the Doctor tells me I

ſhal be free of it very ſpeedily.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     He is a foole, I am a better Doctor then he, thou ſhalt goe with it this foureteene weekes yet or thereabouts; come you are a whore, and have abus'd my honeſt bed; Ile have you before the Justices to be puniſh'd for thy offence.
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     Spare me prethee gentle Nebulo, and hearken to my counſell a little, ſince thou art a cuckold (as I doe not deny it) chooſe whether thou wilt weare the hornes in thy forehead, and ſo all men ſee them, or put them into thy pocket, and no man ſee them, I leave it to thy owne diſcretion.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Why then I am a cuckold it ſeemes?
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     I cannot ſay againſt it truely, and ſpeake the truth, if I ſhould, this marke of thy fortune here deepely ſtamped would bewray me, be not ſo fooliſh now as Vulcan was, to make a proclamation of thy forked order.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Did 
                           Ʋulcan do ſo?
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Yes, but afterwards he repented it for he forg'd an artificiall net, with which he caught his wife Venus and Mars a bed together in carnall copulation, then called all the gods and goddeſſes to be ſpectators of his owne ſhame.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     But what ſaid they when they ſaw it?
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     They commended Mars, but condemned 
                           Ʋulcan for being the publiſher of his owne diſgrace.
                  
                  
                     Nebul.
                     But twas a ſhame for Mars to be caught ſo.
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     The gods wiſh'd every one of them if that were a ſhame, to be ſhamed in the ſame manner.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     but how did Venus 
                        
                           •
                        ake this?
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     In ſcorne of the ſmith, and in revenge of this trick hath made his head as hard as his anvile.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Thou haſt devis'd a pretty ſtory in thy owne defence, i'ſt beſt to follow thy counſell, and ſay nothing, or ſtirre this bad thing and make it ſtinke the more?
                  
                  
                     Nebulona.
                     You may do what you pleaſe, but I have told you the beſt courſe.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Let it be ſo then; I have travelled well I trow, and to good purpoſe, at may returne home to father a child, of which I did not beget ſo much as the leaſt finger or the leaſt toe; if this be the fruits of travelling, God keepe me from it

hence forward, and all good folkes beſides; come Nebulona we are friends, do ſo no more, and all is forgotten.
                  
                  
                     Nebulon.
                     Not, if you ſtay at home and warme my bed,
                     But if you leave me, then have at your head. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus ſecundi, Scena ſeptima.
                  
                     Enter the ſacrifice to the tombe of Pirrhus in the manner of a Hecatombe led in by the Theſſalians, who had each of them a white garment knit about them, theſe were entertayned by ſo many virgins of Theſſalia ſtanding in a ring with their haire looſe about their eares; the maydes were divided into two companies, thoſe who were in the firſt carryed flowers and fruite, the other carried in backets other fine knackes and perfumes, at the ſound of muſicke and a ſong made fit and agreeable to the muſicke, they danced, the ſong was made in praiſe of Thetis.
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              The Song.
                              O Nereus god in ſurging ſeas, we praiſe thy 
                                    Thetis.
                                  daughter deare,
                              Whom Peleus at commandement of Jove did make his pheere:
                              Thou art the goddeſſe we adore in Sea a glimpſing ſtarre,
                              Who ſtout Achilles didſt bring forth a very Mars in warre,
                              And Captaine good unto the Greekes, thy glory ſcales the skies;
                              To thee did thy red-headed wife cauſe Pirrhus rough to riſe,
                              The Trojans utter overthrow, but ſtay to Greekiſh hoſt,
                              Be thou good Pirrhus unto us a favourable ghoſt,
                              Who here in grave intombed lieſt in Phoebus ſacred ground,
                              Bow downe thy eare to th' holy hymnes that we to thee do ſound,
                              
                                 And this our City ſuffer not in any feare to be,
                              Of thee and Thetis is our ſong, Thetis all haile to thee.
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     The ſong ended, enters Theagines Captaine of the Theſſalians, very richly apparelled, followed by many gallants, who guarding him as he went, at laſt encompaſſed him round about; the maides overcome with the beauty of Theagines could not moderate their paſſions but began to caſt flowers and fruit upon him, with that enters Cariclea moſt ſumptuouſly adorned according to the manner, her haire was neither all bound up, nor all loo
                           •
                        e, but the moſt part thereof that grew behind, hanged over her ſhoulders; that which grew from the crowne of her head downe to her forehead, being of a yellow colour, was crowned with a garland of young Laurell; in her left hand ſhee bare a guilded Bow and a Quiver of arrowes hanged on her right ſhoulder, and in her other ha
                           •
                        d ſhe bare a taper burning: after the young men had gone three times about Neoptolem is ſepulture in their bravery, the women cryed out pittiouſly, &amp; the men made a ſtrange noiſe, with that Theagines ſpeakes to Caricles.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Moſt ſacred Prieſt of this high Deity
                     We make requeſt unto you to begin
                     This ſacri
                           •
                        ice to Neoptolemus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     The ſacrifice indeed belongs to me,
                     But you 
                           •
                        ir, as the Captaine o
                           •
                         this charge,
                     And ſacred meſſ
                           •
                        ge, ought to take the taper
                     Of her there, who of all thoſe ceremonies
                     Is p
                           •
                        eſedent, and burne the alter of;
                     This is the order and our Countrey f
                           •
                        ſhion.
                  
                  
                     Theagnes takes the taper with a great deale of reverence from the hand of Cariclea, and ſets fire to the Alter, b
                           •
                        t firſt he was in a maze at the exceeding beauty of Cariclea, and ſhe as much taken with his, then they both ſmiled a little and bluſh'd and then became pale againe: in concluſion he f
                           •
                        ll in love with her, and ſhe with him.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     So burnes my heart as doth this Alter here,
                     
                        The taper that did ſet my heart a fire
                     Was faire Caricleas beauty. aside.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cariclea.
                     How my ſoule
                     Could ſacrifice to faire Theagines.
                        aside.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     Great god of Delphos in whoſe ſacred temple
                     We celebrate theſe funerall obſequies
                     Of great Achilles ſonne, vouchſafe to ſend
                     A happy ômen which may crowne this worke
                     Of our devotion offered at thy Altar.
                  
                  The Oracle ſpeakes touching Theagines and Cariclea.
                  
                  
                     Ye men of Delphos ſing of her, and her rare beauties praiſe,
                     Who now in grace begins to grow, but fame ſhall end her daies,
                     Who leaving theſe my temples here, and ſailing ſurging ſtreames
                     Shall come at length to contries ſcorch'd with Phoebus burning beames,
                     Where they as recompences due that vertues rare doe gaine
                     In time to come ere it be long White miters ſhall obtaine.
                  
                  After this anſwer of the god Apollo, the pompe is broken up, and Exeunt.
                  
               
               
                  Actus ſecundi, Scena octava.
                  Enter the iudges and people of Athens, then Ariſtippus And Demeneta with Cnemon bound.
                  
                     1 Iudg.
                     
                     
                        Cnemon ſtand forth, who doth accuſe him here?
                  
                  Ariſtippus ſteps forth, and ſtrewing aſhes on his head, ſaith:
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     I brought not up my ſonne ye men of Athens
                     
                     To ſee him come unto this end, but rather
                     To be a ſtaffe to ſtay my age upon;
                     As ſoone as he was borne his education
                     VVas good and civill, when he did attaine
                     
                        To riper yeeres, I ſet him to our ſchooles
                     And Academies there to ſtudy arts,
                     And Mathematicke ſciences, beſides,
                     According to the lawes of this our City,
                     Made him free deniſon, yet notwithſtanding
                     He hath not onely caſt behind his backe
                     Theſe favours of my love, but diverſely
                     Both injur'd me, and beaten this good woman,
                     Who by our lawes is now my ſecond wife;
                     And not content herewith, one night he came
                     Unto us with a drawne ſword in his hand
                     (When we in bed ſuſpected no ſuch thing)
                     In mind to kill us both, and was no farther
                     From being a paracide but that by chance
                     His ſword by ſudden feare fell out his hand,
                     Which Demeneta my good wife tooke up:
                     Therefore I flee to you moſt learned Judges,
                     And though I might by law of this our Senate
                     Slay him with my owne hands, yet I appeale
                     Unto your juſtice, and commit my cauſe
                     To your grave cenſures, counting it more fit
                     To puniſh this my ſonne by publike lawe
                     Then private bloodſhed.
                  
                  With that Ariſtippus weepes, Demeneta faining teares alſo.
                  
                     Demen.
                     
                        Cnemon, i'me ſorry for thee pretty boy,
                     In an ill hower wert thou brought to the world;
                     Unhappy creature.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Grave and learned ſenate
                     Vouchſafe to heare me ſpeake.
                  
                  
                     2 Iudg.
                     
                     We will not heare thee,
                     But anſwer to this queſtion we propound,
                     Came you unto your father with a ſword
                     Drawne in your hand, or no?
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     I not deny
                     But I came with a drawne ſword in my hand,
                     But I will tell you how, pleaſe you to heare me.
                  
                  
                     3 Iudg.
                     
                     He hath confeſſ'd ynough, he ought not ſpeake more for himſelfe.
                  
                  
                     
                     1 Iudg.
                     
                     Let us proceed to ſentence.
                  
                  
                     2 Iudg.
                     
                     I judge him worthy to be ſton'd to death.
                  
                  
                     3 Iudg.
                     
                     I to be hang'd.
                  
                  
                     4 Iudg.
                     
                     This is my ſentence, fathers,
                     That he be caſt headlong into the dungeon.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     O cruell ſtepmother, and moſt unkind,
                     For thy curs'd ſake am I ſo ill intreated
                     Againſt all equity and juſtice too,
                     Thou kil'ſt me contrary to courſe of Law.
                  
                  
                     1. Iudg.
                     
                     Your ſentence is too hard and too ſevere,
                     Let him not die, but be for ever baniſh'd.
                  
                  
                     2 Iudg.
                     
                     Let him be ſton'd.
                  
                  
                     3. Iudg.
                     
                     Nay hang'd.
                  
                  
                     4. Iudg.
                     
                     nay caſt into
                     The dungeon.
                  
                  
                     1. Iudg.
                     
                     ſince we differ conſcript fathers,
                     In our opinions, I doe thinke it fit
                     It be referr'd unto the peoples voyces.
                  
                  
                     2. Iudg.
                     
                     I doe aſſent unto it.
                  
                  
                     3 Iudg.
                     
                     So do I.
                  
                  
                     4. Iudg.
                     
                     And I.
                  
                  
                     1. Iudg.
                     
                     Then people give your voices, ſhall young Cnemon
                     
                     Die or be baniſh'd!
                  
                  
                     The people.
                     baniſh'd, baniſh'd, baniſh'd.
                  
                  
                     1. Iudg.
                     
                     Then Cnemon, this muſt be thy puniſhment,
                     Perpetuall exile from thy native land
                     Never to be revok'd, which if infring'd
                     By thy preſumption, then expect to have
                     No mercie from the ſenate, but a grave.
                     Breake up the Court. Exeunt,
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus ſecundi, Scena nona.
                  Enter Caricles, and Calaſiris.
                  
                     Caric.
                     Saw you my onely joy, and the ſole honour
                     Of Delphos, faire Cariclea my daughter?
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     This was not ſir the firſt time that I ſaw her
                     As often as the people made reſort
                     
                        Unto the temple I was preſent with her,
                     And more, we have done ſacrifice together,
                     And when ſhe doubted any point depending,
                     On divine matters, or on humane learning;
                     She would have me inſtruct her in the truth.
                  
                  
                     
                        C
                              •
                           ric.
                     
                     How did you like her at the ſacrifice?
                     Did ſhe ſet forth that brave ſight any thing?
                  
                  
                     Calaſiris.
                     You aſke me a ſtrang queſtion Caricles,
                     
                     As if you doubted, whether the bright moone
                     Did paſſe the leſſer ſtarres.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     The people praiſ'd
                     
                        Theagines the young Theſſalian captaine,
                     Attributing the ſecond place to him.
                  
                  
                     Calaſires.
                     Yea, and the third too, but they all acknowledge
                     Your daughter carryed it away, and was
                     The verie eye of the ſolemnitie.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Come will you goe with me to viſite her
                     I doubt the concourſe of ſo great a troope
                     Hath preiudic'd her reſt.
                  
                  
                     Calaſir.
                     though my affaires
                     Call me another way, yet il'e diſpence
                     VVith them how great ſo ever and important
                     To waite on you and her exeunt
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus ſecundi, Scena decima.
                  Enter Cariclea love ſicke, ſhe lyeth upon her bed
                  
                     Cariclea.
                     O cruell power of love! why doſt thou triumph
                     In lovers reſtles paines? what glorie can
                     Be added to thy deitie in ſeeking
                     The overthrow of my poore libertie?
                     Take here this tribute of my teares, theſe ſighes,
                     Sent from a gentle heart, convaey them hence
                     That they may meet Theagnies, and flow
                     With his as from one fountaine, from one head.
                  
                  To her enters Caricles and Calaſiris, Caricles embraceth her
                  
                     Caric.
                     What ailes my ſweet, my deare Carcilea,
                     
                     Tell me my daughter.
                  
                  
                     
                     Cariclea.
                     Nothing but my head
                     Doth ake a little, and I faine would ſleepe.
                  
                  Cariclea faines her ſelfe aſleepe.
                  
                     Caric.
                     What ſhould this meane good Calaſiris thinke you,
                     VVhat diſeaſe hath ſhe tane?
                  
                  
                     Calaſir.
                     You need not marvell
                     At this, for I believe ſome enuious eye
                     Hath over look'd her.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I muſt laugh at this,
                     Then you beleive as commonlie men doe,
                     That there is witch craft
                  
                  
                     Calaſiris.
                     Yes as I beleive
                     That anything is true, and for this cauſe,
                     The emptie aire that is about us round
                     On everie ſide, entring in by our eyes,
                     Our mouth, our eares our noſtrills, all our pores,
                     Carrying ſuch outward qualities with it
                     As tis indew'd with, doth ingraffe a like
                     Infection in the man who hath receiv'd it;
                     As when a man hath enviouſly beheld
                     Something that's excellent forthwith the aire
                     Is filled with that poiſonous qualitie,
                     VVhich entreth into that is neere at hand,
                     This ſame aire being a ſlender ſuble thing
                     Pierceth even to the bones and very marrow,
                     And by that cauſe hath envie beene the meanes
                     Or that diſeaſe, which by a propper name
                     VVe call bewitching.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Your wiſe reaſons beare
                     Some probility I muſt confeſſe.
                  
                  
                     Cala.
                     Conſider Caricles how many have
                     Gotten the plague, although they never touch'd
                     Nor ſaw, nor eate, nor lay wi
                           •
                        h the deſeas'd,
                     B
                           •
                        t being with them in the ſelfeſame aire,
                     Let love be argument and proofe of this,
                     VVho taketh its beginning from the object
                     Or what it ſees, and ſo as if it were
                     Some privy paſſage by the eyes hath entrance
                     
                        Into the heart, and this is probable,
                     For ſeeing of all other pores and ſences
                     The ſight is capable of moſt mutations,
                     And ſo the hotteſt, it muſt needs receive
                     Such like infections as are round about it,
                     And with a hot ſpirit entertaine loves changes,
                     As for examples ſake, I will produce
                     Out of the holie bookes ſome reaſons for it
                     Gathered from natures ſole conſideration;
                     You know the bird Charadrius doth heale
                     Thoſe perſons whoſe diſeaſe is the kings evill,
                     Which bird doth flie away aſſoone as any
                     Diſeaſed with this griefe hath ſpied her,
                     And turnes her taile to him, and ſhuttes her eyes
                     Not (as ſome ſay) becauſe ſhe would not help them
                     But that by looking on them ſhe by nature
                     Drawes that diſeaſe unto her, therefore wiſelie
                     Declineth ſuch a ſight as preſent perill,
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     You have diſcuſs'd this doubt right ſagelie Sir,
                     I would my daughter once might feele and finde
                     What love doth meane, I would not then conceive
                     That ſhe were ſick, but in her perfect health,
                     But nothing leſſe then this is to be thought
                     Hath happened to her, who contemnes all love,
                     But rather ſeemes to be bewitch'd indeed;
                     Deere Calaſiris for our friendſhips ſake
                     Shew ſome point of your wiſedome to diſſolve
                     This witchchraft, and if poſſible to bring her
                     Into a good opinion of my nephew.
                  
                  Enter Nebulo with a baſtinado in his hand.
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Sirs what dee meane to make ſuch tarriance? Theagines hath made ſuch a feaſt, and all the good cheere will be eaten before you come, for ſhame come away, there are none of the gheſtes wanting but you who are the principall, if you will be ſuch fooles to miſſe it, you may, but i'le not follow your fooliſh example.
                  
                  
                     Calaſiris.
                     This fellow cals us rather 
                           •
                        o a battle
                     Then to a banket.
                  
                  
                     
                     Caric.
                     'Tis his ruſtieke manner;
                     O what a lo
                           •
                        ty fellow Bacchus is
                     When he is well waſh'd! but come let us goe
                     Leaſt with his cudgell honeſt Nebulo
                     
                     Doe drive us forward.
                  
                  
                     Nebulo.
                     Well firs you may jeſt,
                     But I meane earneſt if I miſſe the feaſt.
                  
                  Exeunt.
                  Finis actus ſecundi.
               
            
            
               
                  Actus tertii, Scena prima.
                  Enter Ariſtippus ſolus in a melancholy humour.
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     How have I plai'd the foole and rob'd my ſelfe
                     In haſtie paſſion of my onelie ſonne;
                     Repentance when it comes too late doth argue
                     An inconſiderate iudgment; O my Cnemon
                     
                     Would thou hadſt kill'd me ere I baniſh'd thee,
                     For death is better ſure then baniſhment;
                     Nere ſhall I ſee my boy, well for this fault
                     I will do penance, penance on my ſelfe;
                     
                        Athens adiew and all the Citie pleaſures
                     Forſake me quite; my ſolitarie manour
                     Farre in the countrey where no people comes
                     Shall be my habitation day and night
                     Where I will eate my heart out. Exit Ariſtippus.
                     
                  
                  Enter Demeneta and Thisbe.
                  
                     Demen.
                     Oh my Cnemon,
                     
                     My prettie boy, more deere then my owne life,
                     How I lament thy chance and my miſhap.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Comfort your ſelfe deere miſtris I beſeech you.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     Peace foole, my griefe is more then can be cur'd
                     By any words of comfort, no man knowes
                     What a ſharpe corſive it was to my heart,
                     More fervent is my love now he is abſent.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Fie, fie, forget him, thinke upon his pride
                     And high diſdaine againſt you, thinke he doth
                     Deſerve this puniſhment and greater too.
                  
                  
                     
                     Demen.
                     How readie thou art Thisbe to doe miſchiefe,
                     Thou art the fire brand that haſt kindled this
                     Combuſtion in my heart, thou haſt not beene
                     A helpe unto me, but a hinderance
                     In the fruition of my love, by thee
                     And by thy meanes I h
                           •
                        ve loſt my onely joy,
                     And yet for all this thou doſt ſtill incenſe me
                     To run on in this way; moſt wicked wretch.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Well I perceive your mind, ſhe thinkes to make me
                     Support the fury of her franticke fits,
                     But I ſhall overreach you ſure in wit,
                     And lay the ſaddle on the right horſe backe, aſide.
                     
                     Why do you thus accuſe your truſty ſervant?
                     You know I did but what I was commanded,
                     Nor ere did any thing without your warrant,
                     If this thing happen'd not as you would have it,
                     Aſcribe it not to any fault in me,
                     But r
                           •
                        ther, as you juſtly may, to fortune;
                     If you will have me yet deviſe ſome way
                     To remedy your preſent griefe and ſorrow,
                     You ſhall perceive how ready my good will
                     Shall be at your commands.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     What remedy
                     Can poſſibly be found, ſince he that can
                     Eaſe me, and none but he, is ſeparated
                     At ſuch a diſtance from me? and beſides
                     Th'unhop'd for lenity of thoſe which gave
                     Sentence againſt him hath deſtroyd my hopes.
                     I would he had ſuffered death, for then in me
                     H
                           •
                        d quenched beene the flames of burning love.
                     Hope that is paſt removes griefe from the heart,
                     And when deſpaire poſſeſſeth troubled minds
                     They in
                           •
                        ermit all ſorrow building on
                     Th'impoſſibility of their enjoying;
                     But as it is methinkes I ſee and heare
                     
                        Cnemon complayning of my cruelty,
                     And how by unjuſt guiles I did enſnare him;
                     Sometimes me thinks he comes to me as if
                     
                        I ſhould enjoy him, othertimes I bend
                     My courſe to him where ere he lives remote;
                     Theſe things enflame me, theſe things make me mad,
                     But O ye gods, I have as I deſerve;
                     Why did I not with good will ſeeke to win him
                     Rather then by deceit and craft compell him?
                     Why did I not moſt humbly ſue unto him
                     Rather then wrong him like an enemy?
                     It may be at the firſt he did deny me
                     For maiden modeſty, and feare to foule
                     His fathers ſheets, but had I perſever'd
                     Unto the end, he might have beene allur'd
                     To condeſcend by faire meanes to my will;
                     But O my Thisbe tell me, tell me quickly
                     What remedy is that thou wouldſt deviſe
                     For me and ſaiſt is eaſie?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Miſtris this:
                     All men ſuppoſe that Cnemon is departed
                     The towne of Athens and the territory
                     As he was judg'd to doe, but I know well
                     (Who have ſearch'd all things meerely for your ſake)
                     That he remaines here ſtill in ſecret manner
                     With one Arſinoe whom I thinke you know,
                     Shee playes well on the Virginals, with her
                     He lyeth every night, for this faire maid
                     Won with his love, and pitying his diſtreſſe
                     Receiv'd him in, and promiſeth as ſoone
                     As all things are provided for her journey,
                     To goe away with him.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     O happy wench,
                     Happy Arſinoe is thy deſtiny,
                     Though baniſhment or death with ſuch a partner;
                     But what doe theſe thinges ought aduantage me?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Much, i'le pretend I am in love with Cnemon,
                     
                     And will deſire for old acquaintance ſake,
                     
                        Arſinoe would be pleaſ'd to ſuffer me
                     In ſtead of her to lie with him one night,
                     Which if I can obtaine, it ſhall be yours,
                     
                        You ſhall enjoy him in Arſinoes ſtead,
                     And ile provide before he go to bed
                     He ſhall have wine ſufficient, leaſt our plot
                     Should be diſcover'd; if you have your wiſh,
                     Reſt then contented to give o're your love,
                     For in moſt natures it is eaſily ſeene
                     That ſuch love whoſe beginning's violent
                     After the firſt experiment decayes
                     And waxeth cold, but graunt it burne a freſh
                     Within your boſome (which ye gods forbid)
                     Tis but to make a new voiage, &amp; ſeeke out
                     A new way to atchieve it.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     I approve,
                     And praiſe thy rare inuention deereſt Thiſbe;
                     Faile not to put this plot in execution,
                     And I ſhall well reward thee.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Feare it not,
                     I crave but three dayes to bring this about.
                  
                  
                     Demen.
                     Tis granted; if thy wit can worke my pleaſure,
                     How I ſhall love my Thiſbe beyond meaſure!Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus tertii, Scena ſecunda.
                  Enter the banquet, after Theag. Caric. &amp; Calaſi. with attendance.
                  
                     Theag.
                     Welcome my honoured friends, and holy fathers
                     To my poore Table here, pleaſe you to ſit
                     And eate of what the gods have ſent us.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Sir,
                     Superabundant are your cates and dainties,
                     Faire Cleopatra that luxurious Queene
                     Might revell here, and be contented too,
                     We that are Prieſts uſe to ſuch dainty fare
                     Whoſe lives are ſquar'd by rules of temperance.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     We will not cauſe you breake thoſe rules, nor ſwerve
                     From your religious order, but ſometimes
                     A little Wine will much enflame your zeale
                     To holy duties, reverend Caricles
                     
                     I muſt begin to you. drinkes to him.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Caric.
                     
                        Theagines, I muſt returne you thanks.
                     Theagines on a ſudden falls into muſing, ſighes, and changeth his countenance ſometimes red, ſometimes pale, and gapes withall, as if he were not well.
                     
                     What meaneth this variety? I thinke
                     Some envious eye hath look'd upon him too,
                     Methinkes Cariclea and Theagenes
                     
                     Haave one diſeaſe. — 
                           ſoftly to Calaſires
                     
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     By Iſis that they have
                     One and the ſame diſeaſe, thus it appeares:
                     Since he next to your daughter was the faireſt
                     Of all the ſhew at that brave ſacrifice.
                  
                  Theagenes begins to recollect himſelfe.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Sirs, pardon my ſtupidity and dulneſſe,
                     A little fit of paſſion did poſſeſſe me,
                     But now tis paſt, here worthy Calaſiris,
                     
                     I drinke a health to the faire preſident
                     Of our late funerall pomp.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Excuſe me Sir,
                     I drinke no healths, yet thanke your courteous proffer.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Refuſe Caricleas health?
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     Sir, be not angry,
                     This man ne'r drinketh wine, nor eats the fleſh
                     Of any living thing.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     That's ſtrange, how comes it?
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     He's an Aegyptian, borne at holy Memphis,
                     
                     And Iſis Prieſt, whoſe cuſtome is t'abſtaine
                     From wine and fleſh as things unlawfull.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Then
                     Bring me ſome water, wiſe and reverend man,
                     Pardon my ignorance which knew it not;
                     Now Sir to you in your owne element,
                     And let this table make a laſting league
                     Of amity betweene us.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Let it be ſo,
                     Worthy Theagenes, for I doe much
                     Deſire that combination.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Ere you goe
                     
                        Pleaſe you to ſee a dance in armour, call'd
                     Pyrricha, which we uſe in Theſſalie.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     What pleaſeth you doth pleaſe us.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Sound muſicke then.
                  
                  
                     The Theſſalian youths with Theagenes their Captaine, dance Pyrricha in armour, with a gracefull dexterity, which ended, the Prieſts take their leaves, and bid Theagenes adieu.
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     Thanks for our worthy entertainment Sir.
                  
                  Theagenes embraceth Calaſiris very often, and at parting whiſpereth him ſomething in the eare.—Exeunt all.
                  
               
               
                  Actus tertii  Scena tertia.
                  Enter Calaſiris ſolus.
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     'Twas not a dreame or ſuch like fantaſie,
                     As oftentimes invades and creepes into
                     The mindes of men, when Morpheus ſhuts their eyes,
                     That tooke me laſt night napping in my bed:
                     No, twas no dreame, but a true apparition.
                     I ſaw Apollo, and Diana both
                     Appeare before me, and with them they brought
                     
                        Theagenes and faire Cariclea,
                     
                     
                        Apollo gave me him, Diana her,
                     With this command, goe take theſe young folkes with thee,
                     And haſte thee home unto thy native countrey,
                     Tis time, for ſo the Deſtinies command,
                     Love them as if they were thy naturall children,
                     And when thou comſt to Egypt, leade them further,
                     Where it ſhall pleaſe us gods to give direction;
                     With that they vaniſh'd, and a token gave
                     That it was not a dreame, or a falſe viſion:
                     Immortall powers, your heſts I will obey,
                     If you vouchſafe to point me out the way. one knockes.
                     
                     Who's there?
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     'Tis I, Theagenes your friend.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     
                        Theagenes, the 'brave Theſſalian Captaine,
                     Moſt welcome Sir, what busineſſe was of force
                     To make you ſtirre ſo earely?
                  
                  
                     
                     Theag.
                     Reverend Father,
                     A ſtirring one which keeps my thoughts awake,
                     And baniſheth ſweet ſlumber from mine eyes,
                     Hath made me breake your morning meditations,
                     And though I ſuffer beyond thought of man,
                     Yet bluſh I to reveale my griefe for ſhame.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Come, come, I know your griefe, although you are
                     Aſham'd to tell it me, I know it well,
                     For nothing from my wiſedome can be hid,
                     And from the knowledge of the gods my ſon.
                     Calaſiris caſteth ſome account upon his finger, as if he would propheſie.
                     
                     Young man, thou art in love, nay, ſtart not backe,
                     Thou art in love with faire Cariclea.
                     
                  
                  Theagines embraceth him about the necke.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Thy propheſie is true, I am in love
                     With faire Cariclea, ſave me learned man;
                     For without helpe I cannot live a day,
                     So much this miſchiefe workes upon my heart;
                     I never till now knew the effects of love,
                     Nor ere ſaw woman that I thought deſerv'd
                     To be beloved, before Caricleas beauty
                     Made me a ſlave to Cupids cruelty.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Weepe not Theagines, be of good cheere;
                     For ſince you have recourſe to me for helpe,
                     My wiſedome ſhall prevaile above her ſtrength,
                     Although ſhee be perverſe, and eaſily
                     Will not be drawne to love, I'le try all meanes
                     For your ſake whom I love, and uſe all art
                     I can to breake her nature, be but bold,
                     And doe as I ſhall ſhew you.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     With my ſoule,
                     And if you doe this, I am yours, and all
                     I have at your command.— one knockes.
                     
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Who's there, be gone
                     
                        Theagines, to morrow morne I'le meet you
                     In great Apollos Temple and talke more.— Exit Theagines.
                     
                     Enter Nebulo.
                     O, is it you Sir Nebulo, what newes
                     
                        Bringſt thou I prethee?
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     What dee take me for, a newes Carrier? I would you ſhould know it, I am none ſuch, I have not to doe with other mens buſineſſe nor their wives, I would they had not to doe with mine, but tis no mater for once, there is promiſed a reformation, I hope all will be amended, let it paſſe; but to the point now.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     I, to the point Nebulo by all meanes.
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     And then to the buſineſſe afterward.
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     Why, didſt thou not meane the buſineſſe when thou mention'dſt the point? is it not all one in the ſenſe? I conceive it ſo, elſe thou art more learned than I am.
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     No, tis not all one, the point is one thing, and the buſines another, we muſt firſt handle the point, before we come to the buſineſſe; for your better underſtanding, I will make it plainer.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Thou art a very learned Doctor ſure, in matters of this nature.
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     I hope ſo, yet my wife hath gone beyond me I'le beſworne, by many degrees.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     But Nebulo, prethee what wouldſt thou have with me? how doth thy Maſter, and my good friend Caricles?
                     
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     In health, but doggedly out of tune, hee will be with you preſently, ſo much he bid me tell you, and ſomething elſe, but I have forgott
                           •
                        n it, ſo much buſineſſe I have to thinke of.
                  
                  Enter Caricles.
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     My deareſt friend and brother, welcome to me,
                     Why doe you looke with ſuch a ſullen cheere?
                     Methinks you're very ſ
                           •
                        d and melancholy.
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     I am indeed, and I have reaſon for it.
                     I come to crave your counſell what to doe,
                     But firſt depart and leave us Nebulo.
                     
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     Wherefore I pray? well, there will be a ſweet counſell now I am excluded, I ſhould be loth to change heads with either of them for all my hornes.— Exit Nebulo.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caricles.
                     My daughter, Sir, ſince yeſterday, the race
                     Was run in armour tweene Theagenes
                     
                     And ſtout Ormenes, hath beene wondrous ſicke,
                     And the laſt night did never ſleepe one winke.
                  
                  
                     
                     Calaſiris.
                     Who won the garland Sir?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Theagines,
                     
                        Cariclea as the cuſtome is did hold
                     The prize, and he receiv'd it at her hand,
                     She ſtill growes worſe and worſe, deere Calaſiris,
                     
                     Imploy your ſkill and wiſedome to reſtore her,
                     I know tis eaſie for you if you pleaſe
                     To heale her, who, you ſay, is but bewitch'd,
                     For I believe tis not impoſſible
                     For holie Prieſtes to bring to paſſe ſtrange things.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Let's goe then if you pleaſe unto the maid,
                     And by recommendation ſtrive to make
                     Me more familiarlie acquainted with her,
                     That ſhe the bolder may ſuſtaine my cure.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Content, Apollo graunt a good ſucceſſe
                     Unto thy worke, and Aeſculapius. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus tertii, Scena quarta.
                  Enter Ariſtippus and Thisbe.
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Maſter I doubt not but my ſudden comming
                     Appeareth ſtrange as being unexpected,
                     The cauſe whereof I will relate unto you
                     Without more circumſtance, or vaine preambl
                           ••
                        ;
                     I come here to accuſe my ſelfe unto you;
                     And to receive ſuch puniſhment as your
                     Diſcretion ſhall thinke fit for my offence;
                     By me ſir you have partly loſt your ſonne,
                     I doe confeſſe I was an acceſſary,
                     Though much againſt my will; when I perceiv'd
                     My miſtris liv'd not well, but wrong'd your bed,
                     Not onely provident to ſhun the danger
                     Might light upon my ſelfe for keeping counſell
                     (If it ſhould come to light by any other)
                     But chiefly ſorrowfull for your miſ-hap,
                     Who ſhould in recompence of all your kindneſſe
                     Vnto your wife, reape ſuch diſgrace from her,
                     I came one night to my yong maſter Cnemon,
                     
                     (My ſelfe not daring to acquaint you with it)
                     
                        And told him there was one who us'd to play
                     The lecher with my miſtris, he enrag'd,
                     Thinking that then they were in bed together,
                     Tooke ſuddenly his ſword into his hand,
                     And notwithſtanding that I told them then
                     They were not at their ſport, he would not heare me,
                     But thinking that I had repented of
                     Bewraying it, ran like a mad man forth
                     Unto your bed-ſide with intent to kill
                     Th'adulterer, what followed ſir you know:
                     Now to confirme that this I ſay is true,
                     If ſo you pleaſe, this night ile ſhew your wife
                     My miſtris Demeneta with her friend
                     A bed together in a neighbours houſe
                     Without the City.
                  
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     If thou canſt doe this,
                     Ile make thee free, and pardon all thy faults,
                     For I ſuppoſe I ſhould revive againe
                     So I reveng'd were on my enemy;
                     I had ſuch a ſuſpition in my head
                     That ſhe was falſe, but kept it to my ſelfe,
                     Becauſe I wanted cleere proofes to convince her,
                     But what muſt I doe Thisbe, tell me wench?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     You know the garden where the monument
                     Of Epicures doth ſtand, there come a little
                     Before the night and ſtay for me; adiew. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus tertii, Scena quinta.
                  Enter Arſinoe and Thisbe.
                  
                     Arſ.
                     My old acquaintance welcome, welcome Thisbe.
                     
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Thanks good Arſinoe, will you teach me now
                     A leſſon on the Virginals?
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     You jeere me,
                     I faine would learne of you: but prethee tell me
                     What buſineſſe brought thee hither?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     I will tell thee,
                     You know Feledemus the dauncer
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     Yes.
                  
                  
                     
                     Thiſ.
                     We too muſt daunce la volta here to night,
                     Let's have a chamber and a bed made ready
                     Sweet ſiſter, for I've promis'd him this night
                     He ſhall come firſt, and I will follow after,
                     Aſſoone as I to bed have brought my miſtris.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     All things ſhall be according to thy wiſh,
                     My better halfe.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     But when he comes I pray you
                     Be out the way, for he is very ſhame-fac'd
                     As being a novice in this art.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     Is he
                     Not entred yet?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Not yet I can aſſure yee,
                     His flower is yet to ſpend and ſtrength of youth.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     That flower thou ſoone wilt crop, and waſt the ſeed.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     In time I may, at night expect me ſiſter.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     Ile waite you home.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     If this my plot doe hit
                     Nere was the like devis'd by womans wit. Exeunt.
                     
                  
                  Enter Demeneta, and Thiſbe againe with a candle.
                  
                     Thisbe.
                     Come miſtris, let me make you unreadie inſtantlie, all that I promiſed you is done, I will goe fetch young Cnemon unto you who is making merrie here by, and returne ſuddenlie, lye downe, take your pleaſure and ſay nothing. Exit Thiſbe.
                     
                  
                  Enter Thisbe followed by Ariſtippus.
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Bind the adulterer faſt maſter.
                     With that ſhe ran to the doore and made it give ſo great a craſh as ſhe could, crying out in this manner:
                     O wonderfull thing, the villaine is fled, take heed ſir that you be not againe deceived.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Peace be of good cheere, I have this wicked and miſchievous woman which I moſt deſired.
                     O thou much hated of the gods, I have thee
                     And all thy ſhame about thee, come thou ſhalt
                     With me unto the City, to receive
                     What puniſhment the lawes allot to ſuch
                     As live unchaſt, and wrong their husbands bed,
                     Which is no leſſe then death.
                  
                  
                     
                     Ariſtippus dragges her along, but ſhe pulling herſelfe out of the old mans hands, fell ſuddenlie of purpoſe into a pit made in the ſtage, and ſo ended her life.
                  
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     See Thiſbe, is ſhe dead?
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Oh yes, her necke
                     Is broaken ſir.
                  
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     Then hath thy puniſhment
                     Prevented what the law ſhould have inflicted;
                     Ile to the people and declare this matter,
                     And with my friends conſult what meanes to uſe
                     For to call home my ſonne from baniſhment,
                     Whoſe truth and innocence doth open lie
                     By this unheard of ſtrange diſcovery. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus tertii, Scena ſexta.
                  
                     Enter Cariclea, ſhe lieth downe upon the bed indiſpos'd, her kinsfolk
                           •
                         weeping about her, then enter Caricles and Calaſiris.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     My child, my daughter deare, tell me thy father
                     The cauſe of thy diſeaſe, have a good heart,
                     This wiſe man Calaſiris is requeſted
                     By me to finde ſome remedy to cure thee,
                     And he can well performe it as a man
                     Of heavenly knowledge, and a ſacred prieſt.
                     My moſt endeered friend, you ſhall doe well
                     To ſuffer him to exerciſe his art
                     And holy ſpels for your recovery,
                     For I perceive thou art ore-look'd my child.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Sir tis my duty to obey your will
                     In all things you command me.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Then depart
                     Deare Caricles, and all the reſt avoyd
                     The roome, we muſt be private here together,
                     Fetch me a little Laurell and a ſtoole
                     Having three feet, ſome fire and frankincenſe,
                     And let no man diſturbe us till I call.
                     It ſhall be done forthwith, heavens crowne your worke.
                  
                  Exeunt all but Cariclea, and Calaſiris.
                  
                     
                     Calaſiris begins to burne frankincenſe, to mumble with his lips, to lay lawrell upon her from top to toe, to gape &amp; make ſtrange geſtures, while Cariclea, wagged her head oft and ſmiled.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Father you are deceived in my griefe,
                     You cannot gheſſe at it for all your art.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Nay daughter ſay not ſo, but cheere your ſelfe,
                     For what doth vex you is a malady
                     Common, and eaſie to be cur'd by me;
                     Thou wert o're-look'd not onely at the pompe
                     Of Pirrhus funerall rites, but at the race
                     In armour too when you were overſeer,
                     And gave the prize unto the conquerour;
                     
                        Theagenes was he that overlook'd you,
                     Whoſe want on eye was alwaies fixt upon
                     Your ſplendant beauty object of his ſight.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Whether he daign'd to looke on me or no
                     
                        Apollo have him in his cuſtody;
                     But whence is he, and what's his pedegree?
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     He's a Theſſalian borne, and as you hear'd
                     Deſcended from Achilles, who although
                     He have bewitch'd you with an envious eye,
                     He ſuffers more than you by the reflex
                     Of your Sun-burning eyes upon his heart.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Why do you wrongfully accuſe the man
                     Of witchcraft, who hath done no harme at all,
                     There's no ſuch matter, tis ſome other ſickneſſe.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Then tell me daughter, and conceale it not
                     If you deſire to find a remedy,
                     I am no ſtranger to you but your friend,
                     and old acquaintance of your loving father,
                     I am of your profeſſion too, a prieſt,
                     I'le keepe your counſell, and be bound by oath
                     To helpe you what I can; all griefes are cur'd
                     In the beginning, but if left alone
                     At length they grow incurable; declare
                     Your minde at full.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I love Theagines.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Calaſiri
                              •
                           .
                     
                     I knew ſo much before, he loves you too,
                     
                        I'le be your faithfull friend and true aſſiſtant.
                  
                  Enter Caricles, with Aceſtinus a ſkilfull phyſitian.
                  
                     Caric.
                     Deere friend what have you done? what newes have
                     You to tell me that is good?
                  
                  
                     Calaſir.
                     All ſhall be well
                     
                        Cariclea ſhall be heal'd to morrow morne
                     Of her infirmitie, I now will leave you
                     To proſecute my buſines for her health.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Adiew deere friend, the gods reward thy paine.
                     Heere Aceſtinus, lies the ſicklie patient Exit Calaſiris.
                     
                     You are well read in phyſicke, feele her pulſe
                     And give your wiſe opinion.
                  
                  
                     
                        Ac
                              •
                           ſtin.
                     
                     faireſt maid
                     Where doth your paine lie moſt?
                  
                  
                     She turn'd her face from him, and repeated with a loud voice this verſe of Homer,
                  Achilles is the braveſt man of all the Greekiſh rout.
                  
                     
                        Ac
                              •
                           ſt.
                     
                     Her ſtate of heart I finde Prieſt Caricles,
                     
                     My labour is in vaine, no phyſicke can
                     Reſtore her to her health.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     The gods forbid,
                     Why ſay you ſo, muſt my deare daughter die
                     Without all hope of her recovery?
                  
                  
                     
                        Ac
                              •
                           ſt.
                     
                     Peace make not ſuch adoe, but here me ſpeake.
                     Our art ſir, doth extend no further then He drawes Caricles aſide.
                     
                     To cure diſtempered bodies, if the mind
                     Diſeaſed be without the bodies ſickneſſe,
                     We have no helpe for that, the maids diſeaſe
                     L
                           •
                        es in the mind, her bodie's in good ſtate,
                     No humours doe abound there, no headach,
                     No fever burnes her, all is free within.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     What then ſhould be the cauſe of theſe her fits,
                     Utter what y
                           •
                        u perceive doth trouble her,
                     I doe beſeech you, ſkilfull Aceſtinus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Aceſtin.
                     Tis love doth trouble her, which who knowes not
                     Is an affection and griefe of the heart,
                     Doe you not ſee her eyes ſwolne in her head
                     Rouling one every ſide, her viſage pale,
                     
                        Her halfe diſtraction, how ſhe uttereth
                     What ere comes in her minde, and ſleepes but little;
                     In briefe I doe perceive that ſhe hath loſt
                     The moiſture of her body, and indeed
                     Juſt amplitude thereof, my counſell is
                     You finde her out a man and that with ſpeed. Exit Aceſtinus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     A man, heavens grant ſhe be enclin'd that way,
                     Then Calaſiris hath plaid well his part;
                     How fares my daughter now, what ſickneſſe haſt thou?
                     Shall I ſend for more Doctors yet?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Tis needleſſe,
                     Send none to me but Calaſiris onely,
                     He hath the art to eaſe me, and none elſe.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Ile ſend him to thee, ſleepe Cariclea,
                     
                     Untill he come: if Alcamenes love
                     Poſſeſſe her heart, thanks to the gods above. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus tertii, Scena ſeptima.
                  Enter at one doore Theagines, at another Calaſiris.
                  
                     Theag.
                     My worthy friend moſt opportunely met.
                  
                  
                     Calaſi.
                     What, beautifull Theagines!
                     
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     How can he
                     Be beautifull that pleaſeth not Cariclea?
                     
                  
                  
                     Calaſir.
                     No more, you make me angrie thus to doubt
                     My skill by which ſhe is entrap'd in love,
                     And longs to ſee you.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     What is that you ſay?
                     Doth faire Cariclea wiſh to ſee me father?
                     Why doe you then detaine me here, and not
                     Conduct me to her?Theagines offers to run forth, Calaſiris catcheth him by the cloake, and holds him faſt.
                     
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Nay ſir ſtay a while,
                     Though you are very nimble of your feet,
                     You muſt not thinke this matter muſt be handled
                     As if it were a prize for every man
                     That liſt to get it, take my counſell firſt;
                     Know you not that her father Caricles
                     
                     Is the chiefe man in Delphos? that the lawes
                     Give preſent death to ſuch as ſteale a maid
                     
                        Without their friends conſent? be wiſe my ſonne.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     The matter were not great although I dy'd
                     After I had enjoyed Cariclea,
                     
                     Death for her ſake is life, but Calaſiris
                     
                     If you thinke good, let us demand her of
                     Old Caricles her father for my wife,
                     I doe ſuppoſe my blood is high ynough
                     To be commixt with his.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     We ſhall not ſpeed,
                     Not that he thinkes you any way unworthy,
                     But 'cauſe ſhe's promis'd to his ſiſters ſonne
                     By him in marriage.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     O ye gods above,
                     It cannot be, nor ſhall it by your leaves,
                     
                        Theagenes, and none but he ſhall wed
                     
                        Cariclea, who ere preſumes to touch
                     My goddeſſe but my ſelfe, ſhall ſure repent it,
                     This hand is not benum'd, nor this ſword blunt
                     But it can take revenge.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     It ſhall not need,
                     
                        Theagines be patient, be but rul'd
                     By me, and we will bring all things to paſſe
                     According to your wiſh; now leave me here
                     Alone to project on your good, be carefull
                     You be not ſeene oft-times to talke with me,
                     But when you come, come private and alone
                     To ſhun ſuſpition.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Farewell reverend Father. Exit Theagenes.
                     
                     Enter Caricles.
                     So efficacious is your wiſdome ſir,
                     So forceable our friendſhip, as it hath wrought
                     That effect I wiſh'd upon my daughter,
                     
                        Cariclea is in love and quite ſubdu'd
                     By ſtrong affection, who before was ſtubborne
                     Unto ſo ſweet a yoake.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     I knew my charmes
                     Were of ſufficient force to doe the feate,
                     But can you tell aſwell what man ſhe loves
                     
                        As that ſhe is in love?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     No by Apollo,
                     
                     Would Alcamenes were the man ſhe lov'd
                     My ſiſters ſonne, I have indeavour'd it
                     All that I can to make her fancy him.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Tis beſt you bring him to her, and ſo try
                     The aime of her affection, mutuall ſight
                     Of lovers kindleth ſparkes which elſe would die
                     Rak'd up in aſhes of forgetfulneſſe.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Ile take your counſell.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     And returne with newes
                     How you have ſped.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Ile give you a relation. Exit Caricles.
                     
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     I muſt convey them hence, this taske is laid
                     Upon me by the gods, but where I know not.
                     The Oracle is myſticall and darke,
                     I cannot well interpret what it meanes,
                     We muſt begin our voyage by ſea it ſeemes,
                     As may be gathered by the Oracle
                     Where it is ſaid, and ſayling ſurging ſtreames
                     
                        Shall come at length to countries ſcorch'd with Phoebus burning beames.
                     
                     If I could by any meanes get the Faſcia now, which was laid out with Cariclea, wherein Caricles ſaid he h
                           •
                        ard all the maide eſtate was notified, I ſhould be inſtructed more particularly what I ought to doe, and whether the Ladies of deſtiny would ſend us. Enter Caricles.
                     
                     Now brother what ſucceſſe?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Oh wofull newes,
                     My daughter ſeemes diſtracted, ſuch a ſtrange
                     Infirmity doth ſeiſe her, when I brought
                     My nephew Alcamenes to her fight
                     Freſhly apparel'd, as if Gorgons head
                     Appear'd, or ſome more fearefull thing, ſhe cri'd
                     With a loud voice, and turn'd her countenance
                     From him and me, withall ſhe put her hand
                     Unto her throat, threatning to kill her ſelfe
                     And bound it with an oth, if we departed
                     
                        Not ſuddenlie the chamber, which we did
                     In Leſſe time then ſhe ſpake it, leaſt ſhe ſhould
                     Put that in execution which ſhe ſaid;
                     Now Calaſiris once againe I come
                     Moſt humbly to beſeech you that you will not
                     Suffer the maid to periſh, nor her father
                     Be fr
                           •
                        ſtrate o
                           •
                         his purpoſe.
                  
                  
                     Calaſiris.
                     Caricles,
                     Tis true your daughter is diſtract in mind,
                     For ſhe is moved wich the multitude,
                     Wh
                           •
                        ch I have b
                           •
                        rth
                           ••
                        'd her of purpoſe with,
                     They are not of the leaſt but ſuch as ſhould
                     Force he
                           •
                         to doe what ſhe abhorred moſt
                     Aſwell by nature as decree of minde,
                     But I ſuppoſe ſome god doth take in hand
                     To hin
                           •
                        er this deſigne and ſtrive to croſſe
                     My miniſters, therefore tis requiſite
                     And time you ſhew me that ſame Faſcia
                     You ſaid was found with faire Cariclea
                     
                     Amongſt her coſtlie iewells, for I feare
                     Leaſt that it be enchaunted ſtuffe and wrought
                     With ſuch things as doe now exaſperate
                     Her minde, by reaſon that ſome enemie
                     Aſſoone as ſhe was borne had this ordain'd
                     To keepe her from all love and thought of marriage
                     That she might die, and leaue behind noe iſſue.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Tis probable; it may be ſo indeed.
                     Come goe with me, and I will ſhew you all
                     What in the Faſcia is contain'd and written,
                     I underſtand it not, character
                     Is Aethiopian, and the letters are
                     Not common, but ſuch as the princes uſe
                     Of Aegypt in their holie buſineſſes.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     I underſtand the Aethiopian tongu
                           •
                        ,
                     Which unto thee I muſt interpret wrong.
                  
                  Exeunt.
                  Finis Actus tertii.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Actus quarti, Scena prima.
                  Enter Calaſiris, Theagines and Cariclea.
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Come let's away my children, let's away,
                     Why do we linger here? the gods commands
                     Muſt be obeyd, all things are ready for
                     Our ſecret flight, a ſhip for Memphis bound
                     Waites us without, the wind comes gently from
                     Th'adjoyning ſhore, and ſtayes to ſwell the ſailes
                     With pride till you imbarke, ſee here the Faſcia,
                     
                     Which by a ſlie deviſe from Caricles
                     
                     I have obtain'd, nothing doth hinder us
                     To meet this long wiſh'd opportunity,
                     If you have got your jewels, deereſt jewell,
                     From your ſuppoſed father.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Calaſiris.
                     I have them all, but how gat you I pray
                     The Faſcia from old Caricles, for when
                     He had receiv'd me from Syſimethres,
                     
                     Who brought me up, he brought me here to Greece
                     
                     I know not how, and tooke the Faſcia from me,
                     Which in a cheſt he did preſerve and keepe.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     How I came by it you ſhall know hereafter,
                     But can you tell me what it doth containe?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     How ſhould I as being never told by any?
                     Beſides although I oftentimes had ſeene it,
                     I could not underſtand the character,
                     Pray ſir, interpret what it doth containe.
                  
                  
                     Cala.
                     It doth declare your parents and your Countrey,
                     And all your fortunes, thus I read it to you
                     
                        Verbatim as it ſtands, give your attentions.
                  
                  
                     
                        The Faſcia.
                        
                           Perſina Queene of the Aethiopians to her daughter, onely in ſorrow by what name ſoever ſhe ſhall be called, doth write in haſte this lamentation contayned herein, as her laſt gift.
                        My daughter, the ſunne being authour of our ſto
                              •
                           ke, is witneſſe that for no miſ-deed, I have caſt thee forth, and concealed thee from

thy father Hydaſpes ſight, yet I would have my ſelfe excuſed to thee, if thou happen to live, and to him that ſhall finde thee if the gods procure any, and therefore I declare the cauſe of thy expoſition, after king Hydaſpes had beene married to me ten yeeres, and we had never a child, we happened one time to reſt us after dinner in a gallerie where hung rare pictures and images, amongſt which were thoſe of Perſeus and Andromeda portrayed as when he firſt redeem'd her from the rocke, at this time your father lay with me, ſwearing that by a dreame he was command
                              •
                           d ſo to doe, and I by and by perceived my ſelfe to be with child: but thou wert borne white which colour is ſtrange among the Aethiopians. I knewe the reaſon, becauſe I looked ſted faſtlie upon the picture of Andromeda naked, and by that meanes, conceived a thing like to her, yet I de
                              •
                           ermined to rid my ſelfe of ſhamefull death (counting it certaine that thy colour would procure me to be accuſed of adulterie, and that none would believe me when I told them the cauſe) and to commit thee to the unſtablenes of fortune, which is a great deale rather to be wiſhed for then preſent death, or to be called a baſtard: and telling my huſband that thou wert ſtraight dead, I have privilie layd thee forth with the greateſt riches that I had for a reward to him that ſhall find thee and take thee up: above all thinges remember that thou ſeeke among thy jewels for a certaine ring, which thy father gave me when we were firſt made ſure, in the hoope whereof is a princelie poſie, the ſtone is a Pantarbe of ſecret vertue, conſecrated in the place where it is ſet. The gods preſerve thee my deereſt daughter, and grant us a happy meeting.
                     
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     A ſtrange but bleſt diſcoverie haſt thou made
                     Of faire Caricleas royall pedegree
                     (Right reverend father) which before lay buried
                     Deepe in the obſcure vault of ignorance.
                     Now princelie virgin raiſe thy glorious head
                     Above the clouds, and give thy conquering beautie
                     Command to pull the thunderer from his ſeate
                     To ſerve thee here on earth or in Olympus
                     
                     Where thou ſhalt pleaſe to dwell, and reſt not here,
                     Let Mars be fetter'd, Mercurie a ſlave,
                     And bright Apollo dazled with the ſight
                     
                        Of beames more ſplendant then his owne, fall downe
                     And worſhip thy appearance, offering thee
                     His throne to ſit upon.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     Theagenes,
                     Fie, be not ſuch a vaine Idolater
                     The gods may plague you for it.
                  
                  
                     Theagines.
                     plague me for
                     Adoring queene Caricles deity?
                     They are unjuſt then, for themſelves commit
                     The ſame Idolatry aſwell as I.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     That's but your ſuperſtitious jealouſie.
                     Thinke you the gods will rivall you, or love
                     A mortall Virgin? fie 'tis blaſphemy.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     They have done ſo, or elſe the Poets lie,
                     Witneſſe Europas bull, and Laedas ſwans
                     Faire Danaes ſhower, and Daphnes transformation;
                     If their poore beauties had that operation
                     To worke ſuch ſtrange effects in heavenly powers,
                     How much more force, nay violence thinke you
                     Hath hers, to whoſe compard, theirs are like glaſſe
                     To ſparkling diamonds.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     My deareſt friend,
                     Forbeare theſe candid raptures of your wit,
                     Not my deſert, and enter into thought
                     Of what concernes us moſt.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Agreed my goddeſſe.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     No more diſpute then, but forthwith to ſea.
                     
                        Delphos adiew, the fates call us away. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quarti, Scena ſecunda.
                  Enter Arſace and her old baud Cibile.
                  
                     Arſa.
                     So ſweet a man as thy deſcription makes him?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Nothing inferiour Madame, but beyond it;
                     His body is a Temple ſtately built,
                     Where 
                           Ʋenus comes and offers turtle doves
                     To gaine his liking.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Such a majeſty
                     Accompanying that ſweetneſſe too?
                  
                  
                     
                     Cib.
                     As if
                     They wedded were together, hand in hand
                     Walking in ſo delectable a manſion.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     So active and broad ſhoulder'd as thou ſaiſt,
                     So tall and portly?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Every way provided
                     To ſatisfie your pleaſure.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Thou haſt kindled
                     A fire within me; but what Countrey ownes
                     This wonder of a man? when landed he
                     At Memphis ſhore? who brought him, canſt thou tell?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     He came with Calaſiris from ſome parts
                     Of Greece, as I am given to underſtand,
                     And landed here laſt night.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Where doth he lodge?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     In Calaſiris houſe without the Temple.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Thou muſt deviſe ſome way to bring him to me,
                     And lodge him in our palace, for I have
                     An itching humour to enjoy the man.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Let me alone, I am your Ingineer
                     To worke your pleaſure.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     But who is the maid
                     Thou ſaiſt did beare him company, and was
                     So neere his boſome?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     I ſuppoſe ſhe is
                     Hi
                           •
                         ſiſter or his wife.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Is ſhe faire as he?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     I never ſaw one fairer, ſuch a beauty
                     As would have made Iove ſtoope, and ſhaken off
                     His Eagles borrowed ſhape, to force a kiſſe
                     From her Nectorious hand.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Thou mak'ſt me jealous
                     With praiſes of my rivall.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Let not that
                     Trouble your thoughts, he cannot be ſo fooliſh,
                     That when ſo great a happineſſe ſhall be
                     Offer'd unto him as the love and liking
                     Of faire Arſace Oromdates wife,
                     
                        
                        Egypts great Deputy, but reverently
                     Kneele downe, and worſhip ſuch a change in love.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     If thou canſt bring, deare nurſe, this thing to paſſe,
                     Thou ſhalt at once cure two diſeaſes in me,
                     Fell love and jealouſie.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     I doubt it not;
                     What mad man but will be content to change
                     His Braſſe for Gold, his Copper for rich pearle?
                     Both which he ſhall enjoy, enjoying you.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     O what a ſugred time have I to uſe
                     My ſweet diſports now that the Deputy
                     My husband is imployed in the warre
                     Againſt Hydaſpes King of Aethiopia
                     
                     About the Smaragd mines, pray heaven they end not
                     Before my pleaſures period.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Never feare it.
                     You ſhall have time ynough to bathe in bliſſe.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     See Cibile who knocks there. one knocks.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Calaſiris
                     And the faire parties.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Heavens! conduct them in.
                  
                  Enter Calaſiris, Theagines and Cariclea.
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     All haile unto the Palace of my Prince,
                     Madame it may ſeem ſtrange unto your Highneſſe,
                     That I preſume to bring theſe ſtrangers with me
                     To kiſſe you Princely hands; I make no doubt
                     But when you ſhall be well informed of
                     Their birth and breeding, it wil plead my pardon.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     What need this complement? you'r welcome ſir,
                     So are your friends, when did you ever know me
                     Unkind to ſtrangers, or inhoſpitable
                     To ſuch as theſe▪ whoſe outward lookes declare
                     Their inward minds, and ſpeake their noble parts?
                     So elegant a grace and ſtately beauty,
                     As ſhineth in their countenances cannot
                     Proceed but from ſome Princely pedegree,
                     Pray 
                           •
                        r ſpeake whence you are?
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Moſt beautious Lady,
                     
                        Pleaſe you to underſtand, we are of Greece,
                     
                     Deſcended of a Noble family,
                     Which ne're produced yet unworthy branches,
                     Let it ſuffice (I doe beſeech your Grace)
                     We open it no further; we have beene
                     Rob'd on the ſea by pyrates, but redeem'd
                     By Noble Calaſiris, and brought here
                     To Memphis ſtately City.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Is this Lady
                     Your ſiſter, or your wife?
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     My ſiſter Madame,
                     Toſt equally with me by fortunes blaſts.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     but now thoſe ſtormes are paſt, and you are in
                     A quiet harbour: pleaſant calmes appeare.
                     Sir, I muſt rob you of your gheſts.
                  
                  
                     Calaſ.
                     I durſt not
                     Deny you Madame, though I muſt confeſſe
                     I ſhould to any other.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Cibile,
                     Prepare their lodging neere our owne, and let
                     No coſtly furniture be wanting there,
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     It ſhall be done with ſpeed.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     My noble gheſts,
                     I know not if you would retire alone
                     Into your private chambers, travell doth
                     Require repoſe, pleaſe you to follow me,
                     Ile be your glad conductor.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     O I feare
                     This kindneſſe is ſome love plot on my deare. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quarti, Scena tertia.
                  Enter Thisbe ſola.
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     What ſly evaſion to put off thy guilt
                     Is left thee now poore Thisbe? what device
                     To ſhun the ſevere juſtice of the Law?
                     All will be now diſcover'd, and my plots
                     Returne upon my ſelfe, the heavens are juſt
                     In ſending Cnemon home from baniſhment
                     
                        To puniſh me in cheering of himſelfe,
                     Canſt thou behold his face, or ſpeake one word
                     In thy defence, when he ſtands forth t'accuſe thee
                     Before the people? O what ſhame, what curſes
                     Breath'd from a generall mouth will weigh thee downe
                     Even to Avernus gulph; I feele the weight
                     Of my offences poiſed in the ſcale
                     Of ſad deſpaire; O thou incendiary
                     Of all this miſchiefe, ſaith my guilty thoughts,
                     Thou murthereſſe of thy miſtris, hie thee hence
                     To the infernall ſhades, where never light
                     Appeares, but gloomy darkneſſe covers all
                     Under her ſable mantle, there finde out
                     Medea, Clitemneſtra, Paſiphe,
                     Long ſince condemn'd for murther to this place,
                     Companions of thy ſhame; why lingreſt thou
                     Upon the earth? is not thy ſinne compleat.
                     And ripe for hell? yes, yes, I know it is,
                     I know it is, my ſad deſpairing thoughts,
                     Ile follow your ſuggeſtions, gentle violl
                     Reſerv'd for ſuch a uſe, this kiſſe from thee
                     Shall croſſe the ſentence of the Lawes decree. She drinks poyſon.
                     
                  
                  Enter Ariſtippus and Cnemon.
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Hold, hold thy hand, drinke not the poiſon downe▪
                     
                     Thou deſperate woman.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Not to gaine a crowne,
                     Tis done, and paſt prevention.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     
                        Thiſbe yet
                     Make thy confeſſion, and ſubſcribe thy hand,
                     That innocent Cnemon die not.
                  
                  
                     Thiſ.
                     Write it then. Cnemon writes.
                     
                     I Thiſbe doe confeſſe yong Cnemon was
                     Unjuſtly baniſh'd, I and Demeneta
                     
                     Did forge that plot againſt him, for the which
                     We have our condigne puniſhment.
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     Tis done, now put your hand to't ſhe ſignes it.
                     
                     Dying Thisbe.
                        ſhe dies.
                     
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Sonne tis ynough to cleare thee of all things
                     
                        Can be objected; i'le forthwith declare
                     This matter to the people, and produce
                     
                        Thiſbes confeſſion, ſtrengthned with her han
                           •
                        ,
                     Come with me Cnemon.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cnem.
                     See the wretched ſtate
                     O
                           •
                         falſe accuſers, and their po
                           •
                        ſonous fate. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quarti, Scena quarta.
                  
                     Enter Theagines and Cariclea, to them preſentlie Cibil
                           •
                        .
                  
                  
                     Cibile.
                     My children great Arſace recommends
                     Her love unto you, who hath ſeat me here
                     To ſerve you in all things that you command,
                     I'm proud to be imployed in your ſervice
                     Who am a Gr
                              •
                           cian too, and borne in Leſbos:
                     
                     Moſt be
                           •
                        utifull yong man cheere up thy ſelfe,
                     I bring thee joyfull newes, Arſace loves thee,
                     
                        Arſace ſhe whoſe favour kings have kneel'd for,
                     Doth kneel
                           •
                         to thee petitioning thy love
                     With rich oblatio
                           •
                        s both of pearle and gold.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     O heavens, my propheſie is too too true,
                     My iealousie foreſaw this.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Tell Arſace
                     
                     My ſiſter and my ſelfe both kiſſe her hands
                     And doe returne her humble thanks for all
                     Her noble fauours, but that ſhe doth love me
                     I thinke it ſtrange, whoſe huſband is a man
                     So farre beyond my ranke as put in ballance
                     With worthles me, it would not brooke the triall.
                     We know you are her hands, her eyes, her eares,
                     Her minde, her all, for countries ſake perſwade her
                     (I doe beſeech you) to remove her thoughts
                     Upon ſome worthier perſon; all that we
                     Deſire is one
                           •
                        y this, that ſhe would pleaſe
                     To ſend us backe againe to Calaſiris,
                     
                     And never bring ſtrange baniſh'd, reſtleſſe lives
                     Unto ſo high and excellent a fortune.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     My ſonne be rul'd by me, be not ſo fooliſh
                     To ſhun this happineſſe that courts thee now,
                     
                        Imbrace it, leaſt hereafter thou repent
                     Thy over-ſight; thou ſhalt have rule and riches,
                     Dalliance, and all the fruits of flouriſhing youth,
                     If thou but condeſcend unto her will;
                     But if thou doſt deny, know that ſhe hath
                     A high and Princely ſtomack, which nere brooks,
                     Affronts of ſuch a nature.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Tempt me not,
                     But tell your miſtris I deſpiſe her luſt
                     As much as prize her love, you ſhall obligue us
                     Unto you in a bond of love and kindneſſe
                     To get us leave from her hence to depart
                     To ſeeke our fortunes.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Obſtinate young man,
                     That wilt not ſee thy good, Lady perſwade
                     Your brother to ſome reaſon, you may hap
                     To worke upon his nature, and prevaile;
                     I leave you to your ſelves. Exit Cibile.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Theagines,
                     This is no honest dealing, I perceive;
                     Was it for this ſhe ſent us from her table
                     Such curious viands, and ſuch coſtly cates?
                     Was it for this ſhe did adorne our chambers
                     With ſtately hangings wrought with ſundry colours,
                     Which came from Sidon and faire Lidia?
                     Was this her wicked end? would that we were
                     A hundred leagues from this accurſed place,
                     Or that we never had beheld her face. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quarti, Scena quinta.
                  Enter Arſace and Cibile.
                  
                     Arſ.
                     But will he not be wonne?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Not all the art
                     I have can worke him to it.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     Doe my favours
                     Make no impreſſion in him?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Yes of thankes,
                     No otherwiſe, he craves leave to depart,
                     
                        A ſigne he doth not like his entertainment.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     
                        
                           •
                        hou mak'ſt my hot blood cold within my vaines
                     As if an ague ceaz'd me; how depart,
                     Ere he get o
                           •
                        t my power, I am reſolv'd
                     T'enjoy him, or deſtroy him.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     A right courſe
                     Yo
                           •
                        r wit hath found out miſtris, my adviſe
                     Is this, that once more you ſollicit him
                     By faire intreaty and perſwaſive meanes
                     To win him that way, but if he ſtand out
                     And ſtubbornly refuſe to grant your ſuit,
                     Let him be ti'd unto cold fare hard lodging,
                     And give him up unto your Eunuches hands
                     To be ſcourg'd and tormented, for yong men
                     Reg
                           •
                        rd not when they are intreated faire,
                     But when enforced, then they ſtoope and yield.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Tis well advis'd, but how can I endure
                     To ſee that body bleed?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Madame you are
                     Too pityfull, if that an eye-ſore be
                     To ſee him ſcourg'd, you may refrain
                           •
                         the ſight,
                     I know twill mollifie his haughty ſtomacke
                     To your deſire.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Firſt try all meanes, before
                     You put this laſt deviſe in execution;
                     But Cibile what cauſe or colour have we
                     To hold them priſoners, or detaine them here
                     Againſt their wills?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     We'l give it out, they came
                     As ſpies from King Hyd
                              •
                           sp
                              •
                           s army hither,
                     To view the ſtrength of Memphis.
                     
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Excellent.
                     How ſhall we handle faire Cariclea
                     
                     His beautious ſiſter?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Siſter, I believe
                     Shee is his miſtris rather, for ſuch dalliance
                     As I have ſeene betweene them argueth love
                     Of a more fervent nature; I have come,
                     
                        And found them kiſſing with ſuch ardency,
                     As if they faine would have their ſoules to meet,
                     And at their mouths ſalute.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     O ſtrange diſcovery!
                     If this be true, hence may proceed the cauſe
                     Of my repulſe and his unkind deniall;
                     Sift out this buſineſſe further, and obſerve
                     Their lookes, their geſtures, give an eare unto
                     Their privateſt diſcourſe, for this concernes
                     My buſineſſe mainely; if Cariclea prove
                     A barre to my deſires, we muſt remove her.
                     Goe preſently and know the young mans mind,
                     If he will yield yet, but if he refuſe,
                     Let Euphrates the Eunuch puniſh him
                     With yrons to pull downe his lofty heart.
                     So farre I'm gone, purſuing my deſire,
                     Hell ſhall not make me now backe to retire. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quarti, Scena ſexta.
                  Enter two Iudges, then Ariſtippus and Cnemon.
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Although I doe not doubt moſt learned Judges,
                     That your grave judgements would acquit my ſonne
                     Without more proofes then by the ſequele of
                     This buſineſſe doth appeare, yet to the end
                     To make his innocence the more perſpicuous
                     Which hath ſo long ſtriv'd to breake through this cloud
                     Of falſhood and deceit, I here have brought you
                     
                        Thisbes confeſſion, and her hand ſubſcrib'd
                     For confirmation of it, pleaſe you ſee
                     What it containes. the Iudges read it.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Iudg.
                     
                     When did ſhe write this?
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Preſently upon
                     Her poiſonous draught, her conſcience prompting her
                     Unto ſo good an action.
                  
                  
                     2 Iudg.
                     
                     Was't voluntarily done without conſtraint?
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Yes, for what force hath power to worke upon
                     The ſetled reſolution of a perſon
                     Whom death is ready for to ſeiſe upon?
                     
                        I
                           •
                         came free from her, the confeſſion was
                     Her owne invention, and the hand her owne.
                  
                  
                     1 Iudg.
                     
                     But will you ſweare to t
                           •
                        is?
                  
                  
                     Ariſtip.
                     I will, and ſafely.
                     By all the gods tis true, elſe let me be
                     Strucke with their thunder for my perjury.
                  
                  
                     2 Iudg.
                     
                     It is ynough, we doe acquit your ſonne,
                     Long may he live the comfort of your age;
                     So now diſmiſſe the people, it is done.
                  
                  
                     Ariſt.
                     Thus innocence ſhines cleerer then the ſun. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quarti, Scena ſeptima.
                  
                     Enter Arſace and Cibil
                           •
                        .
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     Now will he bend or breake, yeeld or endure
                     More puniſhment? how doe his fetters pleaſe him?
                     How doth he beare his ſtripes?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     With patience
                     And manly fortitude beyond beliefe,
                     Takes glory in his ſufferings, and becomes
                     More unrelenting now then heretofore.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     What a ſtrange nature hath this ſavage man,
                     Will nothing worke upon it? cannot love
                     Perſwade him, nor the force of puniſhment
                     Compell him to humanity? ſome Tigreſſe
                     Or ſhe Wolfe in the foreſt was his nurſe.
                     Is there no hope he will relent in time?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Our labour's loſt in the attempting it,
                     He hath Cariclea ſtill before his eyes,
                     Lodgeth her in his heart, his mouth expreſs'd it;
                     I heard him to exclaime thus, deare Cariclea,
                     
                     My love, my life, my heart, thy onely name
                     Makes me deſpiſe my torments, and in thee
                     I'm comforted what ever fall to me;
                     Whereby I'm confident ſhe is his wife,
                     Or ſecret miſtris, wherefore if you pleaſe,
                     Lets (as the proverbe ſaith) caſt our laſt anckor,
                     And ſeeke ſome meanes to rid her of her life,
                     For when he knows ſhe's dead, tis very likely
                     
                        He'll change his minde, when hope of love is gone.
                  
                  
                     Arſace.
                     Thy counſell pleaſeth me, and i'le command
                     This ſtoppe to be removed preſentlie.
                  
                  
                     Cibile.
                     How, will you doe it without courſe of Law
                     Or orde
                           •
                        lie proceeding, who will doe
                     In this pointe your commandment? for although
                     All things are ſubject to you, yet the laws
                     Are free, and will not let you kill without
                     The judgment of the Perſian magiſtrates;
                     Beſides we ſhould be carefull how we did
                     Accuſe the maid, leaſt we ſhould not be able
                     To pro
                           •
                        e what we doe lay unto her charge.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     How then ſhall we contrive it?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     D
                           •
                        intily,
                     By a more ſure and farre more ſafe a way,
                     By a ſtrong ſubtle cuppe of deadlie poiſon,
                     The plot is layd alreadie, and the potion
                     P
                           •
                        epar'd, I ſtay but onely for the patient
                     T'adminiſter it.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     Is any gone to call her?
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     Yes, Aura madame.
                  
                  
                     Arſ.
                     Well i'le leave you then,
                     Strong phyſick's beſt for ſtubborn natur'd men. Exit Arſace.
                     
                  
                  Enter Cariclea, with Aura weeping, and ſervants.
                  
                     Cib.
                     Why doe you weep, ſweet heart? 'twill mar your be
                           •
                        uty,
                     Your brother ſhall not long be kept in priſon;
                     Be not ſo fooliſh to conſume and pine
                     Away for ſorrow, know Theagines
                     
                     This night ſhall be releas'd, and come unto thee,
                     Therefore be merry; 'twas his fooliſh fault
                     And diſobedience to my miſtris ſervice
                     Made him to be committed; nicety
                     Is naught in yong folkes, but all is forgotten,
                     (Partly at my requeſt) and liberty
                     Granted unto him, this was the occaſion
                     I ſent for you, that you might be partaker
                     Of this glad newes, therefore rouſe up your ſelfe,
                     And now at length eate ſomething; Aura lay
                     
                        The table, I have made ſome meate, I hope
                     Will comfort your weake ſtomacke, ſure you are
                     Too blame to faſt ſo long.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     But is this true
                     That you have told me? you ſo often have
                     Deceiv'd me with untruths as I ſcarce dare
                     To credit any thing you ſay unto me.
                  
                  
                     Cib.
                     By all the gods tis true, which if it be not,
                     Let me be poiſon'd at this table heere
                     And be a ſad example; more this day
                     Your buſines all ſhall be diſpatch'd, ſo that
                     You ſhall not need to take more care heereafter,
                     If by refrayning from your meate you doe not
                     Deſtroy your health and die, pray eate a little.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     On confidence that this is true I will.
                  
                  they ſit downe and eate.
                  
                     Cib.
                     Aura give me ſome wine, Cariclea health
                     Remember good Theagines.
                     
                  
                  Aura miſtaks and gives the poiſon'd cupp to Cibile, ſhe drinks, but powres halfe of it on the ground when ſhe taſted what it was, looking cruellie upon Aura, the poiſon ſuddenlie workes and ſhe begins to fall, Cariclea ſupportes her.
                  
                     Cib.
                     I will not have thy helpe, falſe wretch, I will not th'aſt poiſon'd me, beare witneſſe all heere preſent
                     That ſee me die, I lay my death on none
                     But her and this queane Aura, ſo informe
                     
                        Arſace that ſhe may revenge my death. ſhe dies.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     See heere the iuſtice of the heavens diſplaid
                     To mortall view in this ſtrange accident;
                     This cup, this poiſonous cup was meant to me
                     By wicked Cibile, but yet it fell
                     By ſome miſtake to her owne lot to drinke it.
                     
                        Arſaces ſervants binde Cariclea and Aura.
                     
                     What doe you meane to binde me a weake maid,
                     I'le goe without conſtraint where you will lead me
                     If't be before Arſace, though I die
                     I care not ſo Theagenes be by. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Actus quinti, Scena prima.
                  Enter Hydaſpes and Syſimethres, with attendance.
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Thus farre have we march'd by the bankes of Nile,
                     
                     And conquer'd Philae, and the Smaragd mines,
                     Thus farre hath fortune favourd our attempts,
                     And ſterne Bellona ſet our conquering feet
                     Deepe in the boſome of th' Egyptian Land;
                     Are we not now reveng'd Syſimethres
                     
                     For thy uncivill barbarous entertainement,
                     When we imploy'd thee our Embaſſadour
                     To Oroondates Deputy of Egypt?
                     
                     How thinke you, doe they not repent the wrongs
                     And diſreſpect they gave thee, contrary
                     Unto the lawes of Nations? doe they not
                     Wiſh that they had ſurrender'd to our Crowne
                     Thoſe lands we juſtly challeng'd for our owne?
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     I thinke they doe, and curſe their arrogance
                     That hath brought home the warres unto their dores;
                     It cannot chooſe but vex their very ſoules
                     To ſee ſo fruitfull and ſo faire a ſoyle,
                     Their native Country, over-runne and ſpoyl'd
                     By the incurſions of a hoſtile army.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Tis fit they ſuffer for their uſurpation;
                     But where lurkes Oroondates ſince his flight
                     In our laſt battaile, no newes yet of him?
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Fame gives it out, he is within this towne
                     Of Syene with the remnant of his army.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Will not the Towne yet come to compoſition?
                     Will it hold out yet longer notwithſtanding
                     Our water-workes to drowne them?
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Royall ſir,
                     As ſoone as we had cut the banks of Nile
                     
                     And let the river in upon the towne,
                     Th'inhabitants began to ſee and feele
                     Their miſery, for ſuddenly the water
                     Encompaſſed faire Syene round about
                     
                        That it became an Iland, and by ſinking
                     Into the earth below the walls foundation,
                     The weight above began to ſhake as if
                     It would have fallen downe in every place;
                     Then ſuddenly aroſe a piteous cry
                     Amongſt the people of the towne, imploring
                     The gods aſſiſtance, and the Deputy
                     It ſeemes by this extreamity conſtrained
                     Firſt cauſed letters tyed to a ſtone
                     As meſſengers to be ſhot to our campe
                     Out of a ſling, and archers from their bowes
                     Sent their ſwift winged arrows to ſpeak for them,
                     But both fell ſhort and periſh'd in the water;
                     At laſt when we by ſignes perceiv'd their mindes,
                     As holding up their hands in token of
                     Submiſſion, and ſometimes behinde their backes,
                     In token they were ready to receive
                     Bandes ſo they might finde mercie, we ſent out
                     Some bootes to talke with them, who brought us word
                     They would ſurrender to your royall hands
                     The towne of Syene, if you would be pleaſ'd
                     To grant ſome poore conditions.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     What a
                           •
                        e they?
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Firſt Oroondates makes requeſt that he
                     And all his ſouldiers without interruption
                     May march forth as beſt ſuiteth their profeſſion,
                     With all their martiall habiliments
                     And armes about them, next to be convoy'd to
                     
                        Elyphantina with your royall guard;
                     Elſe he would rather die then live to be
                     Condemned as a traitor to his king,
                     For yielding up the City and betraying
                     The armie, and beſides be put to death
                     With rackes and tortures.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     What a foole is he
                     To make his owne conditions, or to argue
                     Of ſuch a matter? doth he not conceive
                     He is not in his owne power, but in ours,
                     
                        To live or die, why what a madnes is it
                     For conquered men to argue of conditions?
                     But tis not noble to deſtroy a number
                     For one mans folly, goe Syſimethres,
                     
                     Take heere our ſeale and ſigne their articles,
                     F
                           •
                        r pitty workes upon a noble ſpirit. Exit Syſimethres.
                     
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     If I could entertaine ambitious ſparkes
                     Within my royall breaſt, or never enter
                     Into examination with my ſelfe
                     Of right or wrong, (as many politicians
                     And proud uſurpers doe not) what ſhould let me
                     From adding this large kingdome to my owne,
                     Stretching my Empire to the mouth of Nile;
                     But iuſtice ſets downe limits to my thoughts,
                     Boundes my ambition in, ſo that I dare not
                     Advance one foote beyond it, ſacred goddeſſe,
                     Divine Aſtrea, though all kings rebell
                     And pay no reverence to thy deitie,
                     
                        Hydaſpes ſhall adore thee, and his might
                     ſhall never be more potent then his right. Exit.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quinti, Scena ſecunda.
                  Enter the Perſian magiſtrates as judges with Arſace, then enters Caricles with Aura bound, they ſit.
                  
                     1 Magiſt.
                     
                     Is this faire maid the priſoner?
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Faire without, but foule within.
                  
                  
                     2 Magiſt.
                     
                     Tis pitty vice ſhould beare
                     A ſemblance of faire vertue, or be maſk'd
                     Under ſo ſweet a vaile,
                     Sure by her lookes
                  
                  
                     3 Magiſt.
                     
                     I ſhould not judge her guiltie.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     That's a rule
                     Deceives us, for the choiceſt fruites of all
                     Ofttimes have rotten cores, and underneath
                     The faireſt Howers lurke moſt the fouleſt ſnakes.
                     That cannot hold,
                     Bring forth the priſoners;
                     You are accus'd for poyſoning Cibile,
                     
                     
                        How doe you anſwer this?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Who's my accuſer?
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     My ſelfe, and theſe my ſervants, who were preſent
                     When the old woman dy'd, and heard her name
                     Thee, a
                           •
                        d that other guilty of her death;
                     Canſt thou deny the fact?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Ile anſwer thee
                     Proud dame, if my Theagines live yet,
                     I ſay, I am not guilty of this murther,
                     But if by thy moſt damnable attempts
                     His purer ſoule hath left the earthly priſon
                     Of his faire body, I declare my ſelfe
                     Guilty of this and whatſoever elſe
                     Thy malice can invent, I was the woman
                     That poiſon'd then thy nurſe, who train'd thee up
                     To all thoſe goodly vertues of thy mind;
                     I doe deſire to ſuffer, kill me ſtraight
                     That I may meet my lover, who ſo ſtoutly
                     Reſiſted thy foule luſt, and lewd enticements,
                     Chooſing to die rather then condeſcend.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Baſe queane, how durſt thou take unto thy ſelfe
                     Such liberty of ſpeech? judicious sirs.
                     And magiſtrates of Perſia, underſtand
                     That this ſhe ſaith is falſe touching my honour;
                     I take the gods to witneſſe that when firſt
                     This woman and her friend came to the Palace,
                     I entertain'd them as became the ſtate
                     Of greater perſons, and ſo long continued
                     My favours to them till by open proofe
                     I found they came as ſpies to Memphis ſent
                     From King Hydaſpes army, then indeed
                     I did begin to draw backe my affection,
                     Many more things inciting me to doe it
                     Which I forbeare to ſpeake of, but in briefe
                     Although I lov'd this maid ſo as to make her
                     My boſom-friend, and my moſt deare companion,
                     She hath repaid me as you ſee, and poiſon'd
                     My truſty woman, is't not to be doubted
                     
                        Her purpoſe ſtretch'd yet further, even to me?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I doe confeſſe yet once againe, I poiſon'd
                     Thy nurſe, and would have done ſo much to thee
                     Had I not beene prevented.
                  
                  
                     Aura.
                     O Cariclea,
                     
                     Unhappy maid, why doſt thou wrongfully
                     Accuſe thy ſelfe, and draw on death upon thee?
                     Heare me right grave and moſt impartiall Judges,
                     There is no fault in her, I onely, I
                     Gave Cibile the poiſon by miſtake,
                     Which was prepared for this vertuous mayd
                     By that old beldame, this is true, or elſe
                     Ye gods hurle downe your thunder on my head.
                  
                  
                     2 Magi.
                     
                     But how came this miſtake? make it more plaine.
                  
                  
                     Aura.
                     Old Cibile my miſtris did prepare
                     This cup for faire Cariclea, I was forc'd
                     To have a hand in't too; when I ſhould give
                     The poiſon'd cup unto Cariclea,
                     
                     And Cibile the other, I know not
                     Whither being troubled with ſo ſtrange a deed
                     Or haſtily cal'd on by Cibil
                              •
                           ,
                     
                     I chang'd the cups, and poiſon'd the old woman.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     This is a forg'd deviſe, believe it not,
                     This woman is a traitor, and conſpires
                     With them in all their plots, as privie to them.
                  
                  
                     3.
                     If ſhe that cals herſelfe Cariclea.
                     
                     Be guiltleſſe of this buſineſſe, what ſhould make her
                     To caſt herſelfe into the jawes of death
                     By her ſo free confeſſion of the fact?
                  
                  
                     Aura.
                     Sir I believe ſhe's weary of her life,
                     And being in deſperation e're to ſee
                     Much leſſe t'enjoy her husband, without whom
                     Life ſeemes a burthen haſtens on her death.
                  
                  
                     1.
                     Madame you muſt produce ſome witneſſes,
                     Or we ſhall cleere the priſoners.
                  
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Here are five
                     Will be depos'd they heard Cibile charge
                     Theſe two here with her death.
                  
                  
                     
                     2.
                     What ſay you friends.
                     Dare you ſweare this?
                  
                  
                     
                        All 5.
                     We dare and will, by Iſis,
                     
                     And all the gods tis ſo.
                  
                  
                     3.
                     Then we muſt paſſe
                     Sentence according to the law, which moſt
                     Depends on witneſſes, your doome is death,
                     Carry theſe two forthwith unto the fire,
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     O ſunne, and earth, and all you bleſſed creatures
                     That are above or underneath this round
                     Terreſtriall ball, you that doe take revenge
                     On ſuch as worke impiety, beare witneſſe
                     I die an innocent, and willingly
                     Submit my ſelfe to death, for to avoyd
                     Th' intollerable griefes that burthen me;
                     Vouchſafe to take me gently to your hands,
                     And ſpeedily inflict your puniſhments
                     Upon this whore Arſace, who hath plotted
                     This miſchiefe to no other end and purpoſe
                     But to take from me my Theagines.
                        Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quinti, Scena tertia.
                  Enter Caricles ſolus, Nebulo liſtning.
                  
                     Caric.
                     
                        Cariclea rap'd, O gods how can it be;
                     Where is your juſtice then? where our reward
                     For ſerving at your altars, when you ſuffer
                     Your ſacred temples to be rob'd and ſpoyld
                     Of its chiefe jewell, and my life, Cariclea?
                     O ſacriledge unheard of! can you ſleepe
                     And winke at this? or is your anger to me
                     Implacable, and therefore to torment
                     My heart the more, you ſeeme not to regard it?
                     Was't not ynough, O cruell powers, to kill
                     My daughter at her Nuptiall, and my wife
                     For griefe thereof, but to augment my ſorrow
                     Beyond the bounds of reaſon, give conſent
                     Unto Caricleas rape, who was my joy,
                     My onely comfort, heart, yea life and all?
                     
                        Well I will once more put on pilgrimes weedes.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     Ha, what was that? a dreadfull ſound me thought
                     More pilgrimages? ſtay but liſten yet.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     And goe in queſt of thee throughout the world,
                     Firſt to Theſſalia, where that thiefe was borne
                     That ſtole thee hence, then unto Memphis City
                     Where Calaſiris that falſe prieſt remaines.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     I am confirm'd in horror, tis too true
                     He'll travell once againe, but ſoft attend.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     And if I finde thee not, ile travell further,
                     Even to the utmoſt bounds of Aethiopia,
                     
                     Where I ſuppoſe thy parents live and raigne.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     To Aethiopia, what ſtrange land is that
                     (I marvell) oh, oh now I doe remember
                     
                        Syſimethres was borne there as he ſaid; Nebulo diſcovers himſelfe.
                     
                     We ſhall be blacke a divels if we goe there.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     What Nebulo, my truſty friend and ſervant,
                     Prepare thy ſelfe to accompany thy maſter.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     Where ſir, unto the temple of Apollo?
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Beyond the ſeas I meane.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     Beyond the ſeas;
                     He's mad I thinke, or hath ſome worſe diſeaſe. aſide.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I heare you ſir, it ſeemes your growne a Poet
                     You rime ſo well.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     I care not who doth know it.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Raptures ſtill flow upon thee more and more,
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     But this bad newes of yours doth vex me ſore,
                     That you will croſſe the ſeas, the bare conceit,
                     Will keepe me ſeven daies without taſte of meat.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Why that is profitable, ſaves thy purſe.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     But hurts my body ſir, and that is worſe.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Why th'art a ſecond Ovid, all he ſaies
                     Doth flow in verſe.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     Then I ſhall weare the Bayes.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     But Nebulo no more of this, you are content to accompany me this journey, are you not?
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     Good ſir, do not 
                           •
                        rge me to it; you know how willing I ſhould be to wait upon ye, did not one thing croſſe it.
                  
                  
                     
                     Caric.
                     What's that thy wife?
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     You have hit the marke, tis dangerous (I can tell yee) for me to goe abroad and leave her at home▪ I had woefull experience on't after our laſt peregrination.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     What did ſhe make thee a cuckould in thy abſence?
                  
                  
                     Neb.
                     I know not, but ſhe dub'd me knight of the forked order.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Why that honour is for terme of thy Life man; thy ſtaying at home cannot take it away, nor thy going abroad adde unto it.
                  
                  
                     Nebu.
                     No, doe they not riſe by degrees? I ſuppose yes, as in this manner, from Knight to Lord, from Lord to Earle, from Earle to Duke of the forked order, and ſo forward: but my ambition is not to climbe ſo high, therefore i'le ſtay at home and prevent that promotion.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     fie, prevent thy honour?
                  
                  
                     Nebu
                     My Nebulona will heape ynough ſuch honours on my head, If I follow your counſell, but I tell you againe I am not ambitious ſo to be promoted, yet notwithſtanding, ſo well I love you, that rather then you ſhall goe alone, i'le once more adventure my fortune.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Spoken like a right honeſt man, come let's away then withall expedition.
                     
                        Delphos and Greece farewell, your prieſts hard fate
                     Denyes him ſtill t'enjoy a ſetled ſtate. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quinti, Scena quarta.
                  Enter Theagines, Cariclea, and Aura.
                  
                     Theag.
                     And haſt thou ſcap'd the fire my deereſt love?
                     Miraculous deliverance! let me heare
                     The manner on't related.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Thus it was,
                     After we were condemned to be burnt
                     By foule Arſaces slanderous report
                     For poiſoning Cibile, a blazing fire
                     Was made, and we two caſt into the ſame,
                     And whereas it was thought by everie one
                     The fierceneſſe of the flame would ſoone conſume us,
                     It prov'd cleane contrarie, for we ſtood in
                     
                        The middſt of it untouch'd, for everie ſide
                     It gave us way, and never ſing'd our cloaths,
                     Although Arſace with a threatning voice
                     Commanded the tormentors to lay on
                     More wood and reed, yet all prevailed not,
                     For no hurt would approach us, which the whore
                     
                        Arſace ſeeing, preſently declar'd
                     Before the people with an open voice
                     That we were witches; though good Calaſiris
                     
                     Did what he could to free us from her hands,
                     We by her guard were apprehended, and
                     Brought here againe to thee my deare, for which
                     I'm glad that we may ſuffer both together.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     I have not heard a ſtranger miracle,
                     This doth proceed from favour of the god
                           •
                        ,
                     And their unbounded juſtice.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     It ſhould ſeeme ſo,
                     But ſtill to be toſt on the angry ſeas
                     Of rigid fortune and ne're ſee an end
                     Of our ſad miſeries, ſhould rather argue
                     Their hate and fierce diſpleaſure, if th
                           ••
                        e be not
                     Some ſecret and more hidden myſtery.
                     We mortals underſtand not, which r
                           •
                        ſtore
                           •
                         u
                           •
                        ,
                     After our ſufferings when all hope is fled,
                     Unto a happier ſtate and peacefull being.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Oh ſweet, let not the ſence of miſery,
                     Make you offend the gods thus, but be patient.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Twas a raſhly ſpoken, and I doe repent it,
                     My deare Theagines; now I remember
                     A dreame I had laſt night, but had forgotten
                     Till now to tell it you, thi
                           •
                         was the verſe.
                     
                        By vertue of Pantarbe let feare of fire removed be:
                        An eaſie thing to Perſaetis, though elſe right ſtrange to ſee.
                     
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     The gods are good to us, for I likewiſe
                     Am made a Poet by remembring now
                     An anſwer which laſt night ſome ſpirit gave m
                           •
                        
                     
                     Who ſeem'd to ſay this,
                     
                        
                        To morrow ſhalt thou with the maid eſcape Arſaces hand,
                        And ſoone be brought with her into the Aethiopian land.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     That Oracle hath but a ſad conſtru
                           •
                        tion,
                     Which thus I dare interpret, Aethiopia
                     
                     Is meant that land that is beneath the ground,
                     That with the maid is meant with Proſerpine,
                     
                     And the eſcaping of Arſaces band
                     Doth ſignifie the ſoule and bodies parting.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Still how you erre! calamity hath made you
                     Forget your ſelfe, and alwaies doubt the worſt,
                     Turning all things to a ſiniſter ſenſe,
                     The Oracle is plaine, you are the maid
                     The gods do point at, whom I shall convey
                     Out of Arſaces power into your Land
                     Of Aethiopia, but how this ſhall be
                     Effected, unto us doth not appeare,
                     Yet it is credible the gods can doe it;
                     We muſt leave th
                           •
                        t unto their ſecret workings.
                     Now what your verſe ſhould meane I cannot gheſſe,
                     Which doth containe ſo many contrarieties,
                     For Pantarbe, in its true ſignification,
                     Is taken for all fearefull, yet it would not
                     Have you to feare the fire.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I doe believe
                     This ring preſerv'd us both from force of fire,
                     Wherein is ſet a pretious ſtone calld Pantarbe,
                     And round about ſome holy letters written;
                     My Faſcia, if you doe remember well,
                     Did mention ſuch a one among my jewels;
                     And to be briefe, I thinke that ſtone containes
                     Some heavenly vertue which withſtandeth fire.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     But then, how was't that Aura periſh'd not?
                     She had no Pantarbe to defend her.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     No
                     But I ſtill held her alwaies in my hand
                     Whereon my ring was.
                  
                  
                     
                     Theag.
                     This is probable;
                     But now what other Pantarbe have we left
                     To ſhun the next daies danger, for Arſace
                     
                     Will not end here, but practiſe ſtill new miſchiefe.
                  
                  
                     Aura.
                     Deſpaire not, but rely upon the promiſe
                     The gods made you laſt night.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Diſtreſſed Aura,
                     
                     What wilt thou doe?
                  
                  
                     Aur.
                     Run on, in the ſame fortune
                     That you doe, be it life or be it death.
                  
                  With that enters an Officer from the Campe of Oroondates, to fetch Theagenes and Cariclea.
                  
                     Officer.
                     Be not afraid, I come not to deſtroy you
                     As you ſuppoſe, but to deliver you
                     From hence; my Lord and Generall Oroondates
                     
                     Hath ſent me hither from the campe, to bring you
                     Unto him, for the fame of your rare beauty
                     And vertue in reſiſting his wifes lewdneſſe,
                     Hath wrought ſo much upon his diſpoſition
                     As he deſires your preſence, come with me,
                     Delay breeds danger, I have fifty horſe
                     Shall ſafe convoy us to the camp, the way
                     Is cleere.
                  
                  
                     Theag.
                     Lead on then, we are bound to obey. Exeunt.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus quinti, Scena quinta.
                  Enter Arſace ſola.
                  
                     Arſa.
                     Ye ſterne Eumenides, and direfull powers
                     Of the infernall kingdomes, muſter all
                     Your troops together by a generall ſummon,
                     For I doe cite you to the court of hell,
                     My grievances beget this invocation;
                     Have I ſo long ſerv'd you, and bent my thoughts
                     To your low centre? have my actions beene
                     As lewd as you would wiſh them, and as blacke
                     As you your ſelves, and could you ſuffer me
                     To faile in this atchievement of my luſt?
                     So much your inſtigation? is this juſtice?
                     
                        Juſtice that is a word not knowne in hell;
                     Is this injuſtice? no, then are you rebels
                     To your owne lawes, I doe inſiſt on this:
                     What other doctrine preach your miniſters
                     But foule inj
                           •
                        ſtice, rapes, impieties,
                     Adulteries, murthers, ſlaunders, ignominies,
                     Falſe accuſations and the like, all which
                     My life hath practis'd? yet ye puniſh me
                     With juſtice ne're till now heard in your courts:
                     You thought it juſt Cariclea ſhould eſcape
                     The poiſon'd cup, and afterward the fire,
                     You thought it juſt Theagines and ſhe
                     Should ſcape my hands, and Oroondates know
                     All my proceedings, curſed fates of mine!
                     Wretched Arſace, wilt thou live and feele
                     Thy puniſhment augmented by thy ſhame?
                     Shall the lawes triumph o're Arſaces will?
                     Or Oroondates ſay he was reveng'd
                     Upon the high and royall blood of Persia
                     
                     For wrong I did him? no, ſince I have fail'd
                     In my deſire, theſe fa
                           •
                        es I will withſtand,
                     And die by none but by this Perſi
                           •
                        n hand.
                  
                  She fals upon a ſword, and kils her ſelfe.
               
               
                  Actus quinti, Scena ultima.
                  Enter Hydaſpes, Perſina his Queene, Syſimethres with attendance.
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     
                        Perſina welcome to our campe, how durſt
                     Our faireſt Queene adventure forth to ſee
                     The angry face of Mars? this is no object
                     For Ladies eyes, dame 
                           Ʋenus ſport's more proper.
                  
                  
                     Perſ.
                     Where you are ſir, there is my object fixt,
                     Whether at home or here, all's one to me,
                     Beſides, where Mars is, there will Venus be.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     This was a favour we expected not;
                     I muſt imbrace thee; O Syſimethres,
                     
                     What is there wanting in the curious modell
                     Of this rare Architecture, built by nature,
                     That mortall or immortall eye can ſee
                     
                        To adde more beautie to it then it hath?
                     Nothing, I know you'll grant it, then what pitty
                     Thinke you it is, ſo beautifull a frame
                     And building ſhould containe within it's wombe
                     No living creature, no inhabitant
                     That might ſupport it's ruines, but ſtand rather
                     For proſpect then for benefit?
                  
                  
                     Pers.
                     this pointes
                     At my unfruitfull wombe. aſide.
                     
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     I graunt it ſir,
                     But if the gods have order'd that this houſe
                     So ſtatelie built by them, this temple rather
                     Shall be reſerv'd for their immortall uſes,
                     And have forbid that any mortall ſeed
                     Shall dwell therein: it argueth in you
                     Sinne and impietie ſo to repine
                     At their decrees and ſecret operations. Enter a gentleman attendant.
                     
                  
                  
                     Gent.
                     Sir the fore-riders of your royall army
                     Have tane two priſoners the moſt beautifull'ſt
                     That ere were ſeene, a young man and a maid,
                     They waite without attending what's your pleaſure.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Let them be brought forthwith into our preſence,
                     They may be found a fitting ſacrifice
                     And an oblation to be offered
                     Unto our gods for this our victorie,
                     Being the firſt fruites of the warres.
                     Enter Theagines, Cariclea, Aura and Bogoas the officer of Oroondates lead in priſoners.
                     Yee gods The king raiſeth himſelfe from his throne, And ſits downe againe in a ſtudie.
                     
                     Be mercifull unto me!
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     What doth aile
                     Your royall majeſtie, that you remayne
                     In ſuch a ſtudious meditation?
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     I had a dreame laſt night Syſimethres,
                     
                     That did preſent unto my fantaſie
                     A beautious virgin, ſuch as is this maid
                     Telling me that ſhe was my naturall daughter:
                     But whence are you, and of what countrey borne?
                  
                  
                     
                     Theag.
                     Great King, I am her brother, ſhe my ſiſter,
                     Both borne in Greece.
                     
                  
                  
                     Hydaſ.
                     O noble Greece, that ſtill
                     Produceſt what is good, and at this time
                     Haſt given us ſuch faire offerings to preſent
                     Unto our gods; but O thou beautious maid,
                     Why doſt thou hold thy peace, and anſwereſt not
                     Unto my queſtion?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     At the ſacred altars
                     Of the immortall gods (to whom we are
                     Reſerv'd for ſacrifices) you ſhall know
                     Me and my parents.
                  
                  
                     Perſ.
                     O ſir, what a mayd
                     Have you appointed to be ſacrific'd?
                     Ne're have mine eyes beheld a fairer creature;
                     With what a ſtout and an undaunted courage
                     Beares ſhe her fortune? I am mov'd with pity
                     At her ſo flowring age, O had my daughter
                     I bare unto you liv'd, ſhe would have beene
                     Almoſt as old as ſhe, I doe beſeech you
                     Spare her, and let her ſerve me at my table,
                     For I am prompted ſtrangely by my Genius
                     Unto commiſeration.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſ.
                     So am I,
                     Beyond imagination, but you know
                     The Law requires the firſt fruits of the warre
                     Should be the gods oblation, to the Sunne
                     Therefore we'll offer him, ſhe to the Moone,
                     The gods muſt be obey'd, the lawes fulfil'd.
                  
                  They all offer to rise, Cariclea fals at the feet of Syſimethres.
                  
                     Caric.
                     Wiſe, grave, and learned ſir, be pleas'd to ſtay
                     A little longer, for I have a cauſe
                     Of conſequence to plead before the King
                     And Queene Perſina, which concernes them too
                     Aſwell as me, this matter doth require
                     A ſpeedy judgment, and I heare that you
                     Give ſentence on ſuch noble perſonager;
                     Therefore judge you this plea of life and death,
                     And know it is not juſt to off
                           •
                        r me
                     Unto the gods.
                  
                  
                     
                     Syſim.
                     Vouchſafe to heare, moſt gracious Soveraigne,
                     This ſtrange appeale, and what this maid requireth.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     What judgement may this be? or what have I
                     To doe with her? by what meanes ſhould I come
                     Into her danger?
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Pleaſe you to attend,
                     She will declare it.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſ.
                     But take heed that this
                     You doe, be no true judgment, but plaine wrong,
                     If I that am a King muſt ſtand to plead
                     My cauſe with any priſoner whatſoever.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Juſtice and equity ner'e lookes into
                     The perſon, but the cauſe, and he ſpeeds beſt
                     That brings beſt reaſons.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     But the Law permits
                     You onely to determine controverſies
                     Betweene the King and ſubjects, not with ſtrangers.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Wiſe and diſcreet men doe not meaſure things
                     By the appearance, but by equity.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Well let her ſpeake, ſince good Syſimethres
                     
                     Will have it ſo, but it is manifeſt,
                     She will ſay nothing to the purpoſe, but
                     Some forg'd deviſe to ſhun the ſtroke of death.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     O Sunne, thou founder of my anceſtros
                     High pedegree, and all ye other gods.
                     Ye noble men that here are met together
                     Aſſiſt me in this place, and be a witneſſ
                           •
                        
                     
                     That what I ſay is true, and by firme proofes
                     It ſhall appeare: doe you command, O King,
                     Strangers or your owne ſubjects to be offer'd?
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Strangers.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Then it is fit and neceſſary,
                     You ſeeke out ſuch, I am no ſtranger borne,
                     But of this countrey, and your ſubject too.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Thou lieſt.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     You ſeeme to wonder at ſmall things,
                     But there are greater undiſcover'd yet,
                     I am not onely of this Country borne,
                     
                        But of the royall blood.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     This woman's mad,
                     Away I'le heare no more ſuch lunacie.
                  
                  Hydaſpes turnes from her in anger.
                  
                     Caric.
                     My royall father, I beſeech you know
                     Your onelie daughter and deſpiſe her not.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     
                        Syſimethres and grave Gymnoſophiſts,
                     
                     How long ſhall ſhe abuſe my patience?
                     This mayd's diſtracted, and the feare of death
                     Makes her ſpeake any thing how falſe ſoever,
                     How bould and impudent; I know I had
                     Sometimes a daughter, but ſhe dy'd aſſoone
                     As ſhe was borne, this is a falſe impoſtor,
                     Wherefore away with her, and let's delay
                     The ſacrifice no longer.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     none ſhall dare
                     To take me hence, unleſſe the judges pleaſe
                     So to command, for you are not to judge
                     In your owne cauſe although a King, but muſt
                     Be ſubject to the law aſwell as others
                     Which priviledgeth you perchance to kill
                     Strangers, but neither this law, nor the law
                     Of nature doth allow you to deſtroy
                     Your naturall children, for the gods to day
                     Shall by a ſtrange diſcoverie make you know
                     I am your daughter, though you now diſclaime me.
                     All controverſies in the law depend
                     One theſe two pointes eſpeciallie, that is
                     Firme proofe by writings, and ſure confirmation
                     By witneſſes, both which I can produce
                     To prove I am your child, my witneſſe ſhall not
                     Be common neither, but the judge himſelfe,
                     And heer's a writing ſhall declare both mine
                     And your eſtate.
                  
                  She gives the Faſcia to the Queene, ſhe knowes it and is amazed.
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     What meaneth this Perſina, that thy blood
                     Thus comes and goes, and that thy countenance
                     Weares ſuch an alteration? is there ought
                     
                        Contayned in this writing troubleth thee?
                  
                  
                     Perſ.
                     O King, my Lord and huſband, I have nothing
                     To ſay unto it; but take heed, and read it
                     Your ſelfe, the ſame ſhall teach you well and truelie.
                  
                  Hydaſpes reads it to the end, then gives it to Syſimet: and the reſt.
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     
                        Perſina doe you owne this character
                     As your owne hand, and know the birth to be
                     Legitimate and true?
                  
                  
                     Perſ.
                     By Sunne and Moone I sweare it.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Although you tould me that my daughter dy'd.
                     I yet believe ſhe was expoſed forth
                     As heere is mention'd but who was the man
                     That tooke her up and carryed her to Aegypt,
                     
                     How ſhall I know that he was taken with her,
                     Or this is ſhe, or whether the expoſed
                     Be dead or no, beſides whether ſome man
                     When he hap'd to finde this might his good luck
                     Abuſe, and make her play this famed part,
                     Mocking the great deſire we have of iſſue
                     By the ſuborning of ſome changelinge and
                     Colouring the truth with this deviſed Faſcia.
                     
                     All theſe doubts muſt be cleer'd ere I believe.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     I can reſolve you in the firſt, for I
                     Was he that tooke her up, and carried her
                     With me to Aegypt, when you ſent me thither
                     Embaſſadour (you know we may not lye
                     Who are Gymnoſophiſts) I know this Faſcia,
                     Written with Aethiopias royall letters.
                     Therefore you need not doubt that it is forg'd.
                     Beſides tis ſigned with Perſinas hand;
                     But there are other tokens that I gave
                     To him that did receive you at my hands
                     Can you produce them?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Yes, loe heere they are She ſhewes Siſimet: and the queene her jewels.
                     
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     What are they? doe you know them?
                  
                  
                     Perſ.
                     Yes with wonder.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Theſe jewells were my mothers, but this ringe
                     Was yours, I thinke you know the Pantarbe well.
                  
                  
                     
                     Hydaſp.
                     I doe and all the reſt, but whether you
                     Came by them as my daughter, that I know not,
                     You might have got them by ſome other meanes,
                     For to omit all other needles queſtions,
                     Your colour's ſtrange and the like never ſeene
                     In Aethiopia.
                     
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     She was alſo white
                     That I brought up, and with this virgins age
                     Doth correſpond the terme of yeeres when ſhe
                     Was forth expoſed being ſeuenteene yeeres,
                     So old ſeemes this faire mayd.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Syſimethres
                     In my opinion you have ſhow'd your ſelfe
                     An advocate in this cauſe, not a judge,
                     Beware leaſt while you ſtrive to cleere this doubt,
                     I may ſuſpect Perſina hath beene falſe,
                     For how iſt poſſible that ſuch a thing
                     Sould be in nature, we two being black
                     To have an iſſue white? this is againſt
                     All humane ſence, and reaſon naturall.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     The Faſcia tells you how this came to paſſe,
                  
                  
                     Perſina
                     in the act of generation
                     Contemplatively eying the faire picture
                     Of beautifull Andromeda, and firing
                     A ſtrong imagination thereupon,
                     Conceived in her wombe the very figure
                     Of Perſeus Miſtris when ſhe was bound faſt
                     Unto the rocke, and he redeem'd her thence,
                     For proofe let that ſame picture be preſented,
                     And then compare them, you ſhall finde the ſubſtance
                     And ſhadow nothing different but in life.
                  
                  
                     Enter a Gentl
                           •
                        man attendant.
                  
                  
                     Gent.
                     Sir there's a ſtrange prieſt newlie come from Greece
                     
                     Deſires he may be heard touching this matter,
                     Who can informe you of the truth of thinges.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     admit him ſtreight. Enter Caricles with the gentleman.
                     
                     Grave Sir can you declare
                     Ought of this matter, doe you know this mayd
                     
                        And that young man?
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     I know them both great King;
                     That maid which ſhall be found to be your daughte
                           •
                        
                     
                     I nouriſh'd from a child; one of this countrey
                     Gave her to me in Aegypt, and with her
                     Rich coſtlie jewells, and a Faſcia,
                     Wherein was written her high pedegree;
                     With her I went to Greece my native countrey,
                     And being prieſt unto Apollo there,
                     When I was buſie in the rites and cuſtomes
                     Belonging to my office, This Theſſalian,
                     Who vaunts himſelfe borne of Achilles line,
                     Stole her from Delphos, and I underſtand
                     Paſſ'd many daungers with her; I forgive him
                     And crave you would be pleaſ'd to doe ſo too;
                     For ſince the gods by diverſe ſignes and tokens
                     Have unto us reveild their ſacred willes,
                     And made it plaine by ſtrange diſcoveries,
                     Strive not to croſſe their workings.
                  
                  Cariclea fals at Caricles feete.
                  
                     Caric.
                     O my Father,
                     As deare unto me as thoſe that begat me,
                     Take what revenge you pleaſe, lo here I ſtand
                     T'abide your ſentence.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     O how largely am I 
                           Embraceth her and weepe
                                 •
                               for joy.
                        
                     
                     Rewarded for my travell! tis ynough.
                     I have beheld thy face yet once againe.
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     What Caricles, doe you not know your friend?
                     Have you forgot the Aethiopian Legat?ſalutes him.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     No, no, I have not good Syſimethres,
                     
                     But doe congratulate our happy meeting.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     We have heard and ſeene ynough, I'm yet unmov'd;
                     Bring in the picture of Andromeda.
                     
                  
                  Enter the picture of Andromeda, the King for joy and admiration could not ſpeake, the people give a great ſhout.
                  
                     Syſim.
                     One point is wanting yet, ſtrip up your ſleeve
                     Faire maid, there was a blacke ſpot 'boue your elbow.
                     It is no ſhame to ſhew a naked arme
                     
                        Before your parents for to prove your birth.
                  
                  She ſhowes there a mole, the Queene runs and embraceth her.
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     You ſtrive to waſh me white an Aethiopian
                     In hin
                           •
                        ering this ſacrifice, you ſhall
                     Doe one aſwell as tother, for although
                     I now believe ſhe is my naturall daughter
                     Sprung from my loynes (as I have seene it prov'd
                     By many arguments) yet I ſo much
                     Feare juſtice and the gods, and owe ſuch love
                     Unto my country, as i'le lay aſide
                     All naturall reſpects, and all regard
                     To the succeſſion of my blood, and offer
                     My daughter to the gods for your behoofe,
                     (As Agamemnon did his Iphigene)
                     Regarding more the publique benefit
                     Then my owne private profit and reſpect.
                  
                  
                     All the people.
                     Save the blood-royall, ſave her whom the gods
                     Will have preſerv'd, appeaſe the Sunne and Moone
                     With a more lawfull ſacrifice.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Well ſince
                     You'l have it s
                           •
                        , though loath I am content;
                     And now I turne to thee my daughter deere
                     With armefuls of my love; but what is he
                     That was tane with thee, whom you cal'd your brother?
                     I trow he ſhall not too be prov'd my ſonne.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     In that ſir pardon me, I did abuſe you,
                     He's not my brother, but neceſſity
                     Compell'd me to diſſemble, what he is
                     Himſelfe can boldly tell you.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſp.
                     Whatſoe're
                     He be, he's deſtin'd to be ſacrificed,
                     Some women too muſt beare him company.
                     This mayd that waites on you ſhall ſerve the turn.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     If he be ſacrific'd, Ile be that woman,
                     Death muſt not part us two.
                  
                  
                     
                        Hyd
                              •
                           ſp.
                     
                     The gods forbid,
                     Why ſay you ſo?
                  
                  
                     
                        Ca
                              •
                           ic.
                     
                     Becauſe tis fore-decreed
                     
                        I muſt both live and die with that yong man.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſ.
                     I praiſe your courteſie and gentle nature
                     Unto this Grecian ſtranger, who hath beene
                     Companion of your journey, but we cannot
                     Breake ſo the cuſtome of our Country, as
                     To ſave his life.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Then I muſt periſh with him,
                     For know, O king, (perchance I may not dare
                     To call you father) it is cruelty
                     To ſpare my body, and deſtroy my heart,
                     He is my heart, my love, my life, and all,
                     My husband by the deſtinies appointed,
                     And it is ſinne t'oppoſe the gods decrees.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſ.
                     What will you counſell me to doe herein,
                     
                        Syſimethres and thou moſt reverend Prieſt,
                     I will be guided by your wiſdomes wholly
                     In this affaire,
                  
                  
                     Syſim.
                     Through the exerciſe of joy
                     The wiſeſt men, oft-times we ſee are blinded.
                     For at the firſt, great King you might perceive
                     The gods lik'd not this ſacrifice which was
                     Ordained, who have every way declar'd
                     
                        Cariclea your daughter, and brought hither
                     Out of the midſt of Greece this reverend man,
                     Who brought her up, to fortifie your faith.
                     Moreover it is plaine by many ſignes
                     And ſecret revelations that the gods
                     Have fore-decreed this couple man and wife,
                     And to that end have freed them from ſo many
                     And imminent dangers, therefore let us ſuffer
                     Theſe divine miracles to sinke into
                     Our underſtandings, and from this time forward
                     Doe ſacrifices more acceptable
                     Unto the gods, who are not pleaſed with
                     Humane oblations, but the blood of beaſts.
                  
                  
                     Hydaſ.
                     Since things are thus appointed by the will
                     And pleaſure of the gods, ſince this faire couple
                     Have beene preſerv'd by fate from many dangers
                     
                        By Land and Sea, and as ſhould ſeeme reſerv'd
                     For Hymens inſtigation, ile no longer
                     Reſiſt the will of heaven, heavens ſend you joy, puts their hands together.
                     
                     And a moſt plenteous off-ſpring to ſucceed you,
                     This is our firme decree, which we'll confirme
                     By ſacrifice, and worſhipping the gods.
                     O Sunne and Moone, whoſe ſacred deities
                     We moſt adore, ſince it is falne out thus
                     By your decrees, that young Theagines
                     
                     And faire Cariclea are made man and wife,
                     Accept their offerings, and vouchſafe to take them
                     Into the order of your holy Prieſthood.
                     
                        Theagines, I doe reſigne unto thee
                     My office, be thou Prieſt unto the Sunne,
                     Weare this white Miter. 
                           Tak
                                 •
                              s his Miter and puts it on Theagines his head.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Perſ.
                     And Cariclea thou
                     Weare this of mine, which conſecrateth thee
                     Prieſt of the Moone, adore her Deity.
                  
                  
                     Caric.
                     Now is the god Apollos Oracle
                     Of Delphos verified, which ſaid of them
                     That leaving Greece, and ſailing ſurging ſtreames
                     They ſhould arrive at Countries ſcorch'd with Phoebus burning beames,
                     Where they as recompences due that vertues rare doe gaine,
                     In time to come ere it be long white Miters ſhould obtaine.
                  
                  Exeunt omnes.
                  FINIS.
                  
               
            
         
      
   

