
   
      
         
            Enōtikon or A sermon of the vnion of Great Brittannie, in antiquitie of language, name, religion, and kingdome: preached by Iohn Gordoun Deane of Sarum, the 28 day of October 1604, in presence of the the Kings Maiestie at Whitehall
            Gordon, John, 1544-1619.
         
         
            
               1604
            
         
         Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01920
            STC 12059
            ESTC S103340
            99839097
            99839097
            3493
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01920)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3493)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1139:9)
         
         
            
               
                  Enōtikon or A sermon of the vnion of Great Brittannie, in antiquitie of language, name, religion, and kingdome: preached by Iohn Gordoun Deane of Sarum, the 28 day of October 1604, in presence of the the Kings Maiestie at Whitehall
                  Gordon, John, 1544-1619.
               
               [2], 52 p.   
               
                  [Printed by Eliot's Court Press] impensis Georgii Bishop,
                  Londini :
                  1604.
               
               
                  First word of title in Greek characters.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Running title reads: A sermon tending to vnion.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
               Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625 --  Sermons.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-07
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2005-07
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ΕΝΩΤΙΚΟΝ

OR
A SERMON OF
the Vnion of Great Brittannie,
in antiquitie of language,
name, religion, and
Kingdome:
            Preached by IOHN GORDOVN Deane of
SARVM, the 28 day of October 1604,
in preſence of the Kings Maieſtie
at WHITEHALL.
            LONDINI
Impenſis GEORGII BISHOP.
1604,
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ΕΝΩΤΙΚΟΝ

OR
A Sermon of the Vnion of
Great Britannie.
            
               MATTH. 12. verſ. 25.
               Euery Kingdome diuided againſt it ſelfe (or in the ſelfe)
ſhall be brought to nought (or deſolate;) and euerie
citie or houſe diuided againſt it ſelfe (or in it ſelfe)
ſhall not ſtand.
            
            
               CHriſt Ieſus the eternall Sonne of
the eternall Father,Diuiſion bringeth deſtruction, Vnion preſeruation. doth deliuer
vnto vs in this text, a moſt wholeſome
and profitable doctrine, into
the which he ſheweth to all eſtates
of euery Societie of man in the
world, That Diuiſion is the ouerthrow,
deſtruction, and deſolation
of all eſtates whatſoeuer; whereby we are taught,
That the contrary vertue to Diuiſion (which is Vnion)
hath beene, is, and ſhall be to the end of the world the
cauſe of the preſeruation and keeping of all ſpirituall
and temporall felicitie and happineſſe in the ſocietie of
mankinde in this earth.
            
               
In theſe three words,All eſtates of ſocietie are contained in three words. 
               Kingdome, 
                     〈◊〉
                  , Houſe, are
comprehended all men of whatſoeuer eſtate, qualitie
or condition they be. Chriſt in this doctrine doth proceed
à generaliori ad ſpecialius, a ſummo ad infimum,
from the more generall to the more ſpeciall, from the
higheſt to the loweſt. This word Kingdome doth containe
in it Cities; and Citie, houſes; and Houſe, man
and woman: on the other part, by that order of doctrine
which doth proceed ab imo ad ſummum, from the
loweſt to the higheſt, which is the order Architectonicke
of building. By the vnion of man and woman is
made the loweſt degree of ſocietie, which is here called
a Houſe; by the vnion and coniunction of many
houſes, doth proceed the ſecond degree and eſtate of
mankinde, which is called Citie; and laſt, by the vnion
of many cities doth come the third and loweſt degree
of ſocietie, which is comprehended vnder the
word Kingdome.
            In the expoſition of this text we meane (God willing)
to gather ſome wholeſome and fruitfull doctrine
of the myſticall ſignification of theſe three words out
of the auncient originall Hebrew language.The myſticall ſignification of the Hebrew words, man and woman. Theſe
words then that ſignifie all the eſtates and conditions
of the ſocietie of mankinde, in the originall language
haue a certaine hid doctrine, which doth expreſſe and
ſignifie that which is moſt wholſome and profitable to
the felicitie and happineſſe of all men. We muſt firſt
beginne at the words that ſignifie man and woman,
by whoſe vnion a houſe is made. The Hebrew word
that ſignifieth man,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                is Iſch, in the which word are three
letters vnited to ſignifie one thing. The firſt, Aleph,
               
ſignifieth learning, knowledge, and a conductor. The
ſecond, Iod, ſignifieth God, becauſe by the ancient Hebrewes
he is called Macom,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               a place, that doth containe
and comprehend all things created inferiour to himſelfe.
The third, Schin, doth ſignifie ſecond. Which
three letters vnited in the word Iſch, which is man,
doth ſet before our eyes a wholſome doctrine for the
inſtruction of all men that will follow the ſame; to wit,
that the knowledge of God doth make man a ſecond
God,Strom. 7. and the image of God, as Clemens Alexandrinus
teacheth vs: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
God dwelleth in the middle of man, that
is, in his ſoule and minde; euen as the letter Iod which
ſignifieth God, is in the middeſt of the Hebrew word
Iſch, that ſignifieth man. The word that ſignifieth
woman in Hebrew is Iſchah;
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                which is made by the
growing or augmenting of the letter He, to the foreſayd
word Iſch, that ſignifieth man. This letter He, ſignifieth
reſpiration of life, which doth ſerue to be a memoriall,
that the woman tooke life from God, by making
her out of man. This letter alſo ſignifieth her inclination
towards man; for this letter affixed to the
word Iſch, that ſignifieth man, doth denote motum ad
aliquid, a motion from one thing to another, as from
God to man, the woman being created by God to
adhere to man. This bleſſed coniunction of man and
woman in the holie bond of marriage doth make a
houſe.
            The Hebrew word Beth that ſignifieth houſe doth
conſiſt of three letters.The mysticall ſignification of the word houſe. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                The firſt, Beth, doth ſignifie the

forme of the materiall and earthly houſe, in the which
man and woman doe dwell: the ſecond Iod, ſignifieth
God (as ſaid is) the third Tau ſignifieth a mark or ſigne.
For in the 9. of the propheſie of Ezechiel it is called the
marke of ſaluation and preſeruation of the people from
death and deſtruction:
                  
                     •
                  zechiel. cap. 9. as the blood of the paſchall
Lambe was ſprinkled on the houſe poſts of the Iſraelits
to be a ſigne that when God ſent his deſtroying Angell
to kill all the firſt borne of the reſt of the people,
their firſt borne ſhould be ſaued, and preſerued; which
marke was a figure of Chriſt his blood that ſaueth all
true beleeuers, from the deſtroying Angell and death
eternall. Of this myſticall ſignification of theſe three
letters vnited in one word, we are taught that God his
true knowledge and worſhip ſignified by the letter Iod,
being in the middle of the houſe ioyned with the mark
of the letter Tau, which is a ſigne of ſaluation contrary
and againſt the deſtroying Angell, that that houſe is
preſerued &amp; kept ſafe againſt ſinne, and Satans machinations.
This much for the myſticall interpretation of
the Hebrew letters in the word Beth that ſignifieth
houſe. Note alſo that this word Houſe is here figuratiuely
taken for man and woman, dwelling within one
a houſe. Which is continens pro contento, that is, when
the container is taken for the thing contained.
            The ſecond word whereby is ſignified the ſecond
degree of the ſocietie of mankind,
                  
                     •
                  he myſticall 
                     ••
                  gnification of 
                     〈◊〉
                   word Citie 
                     〈◊〉
                   Hebrew. is the Hebrew word
Gnir, which doth conſiſt of three letters, hauing in them
a myſticall ſignification,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                ſhewing vs by what meanes
all cities are to be conſerued from this diuiſion whereof
Chriſt ſpeaketh in this Text. The firſt Hebrew letter

is Gnain which ſignifieth the eye: the ſecond is Iod,
which as we heard before ſignifieth God: the third is
Reſch, which ſignifieth the head: whereby we collect
the ſignification of the whole word to be this. That
God being in the eyes and heads of the Citizens, ſhall
be the onely meanes to preſerue and defend that Citie
from diuiſion, which doth bring foorth, as our Text
ſaith, a miſerable deſolation.
            The third Hebrew word whereby is ſignified the
moſt high and generall degree or eſtate of the ſocietie
of mankind,The myſticall ſignification of the Hebrew word Melech a King. is the word Kingdome, which doth come
from King, which in the Hebrew language is called
Melech;
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                and conſiſteth of three letters alſo: the firſt
is Mem which ſignifieth water, and is of the duall number,
becauſe that there are ſuperior and inferior waters,
which in their myſticall ſignification doe denote and
ſignifie ſpirituall and temporall Life. As Chriſt in the
Goſpell of Iohn calleth himſelfe and his doctrine the
water of life:Iohn. 4. 10. the ſecond is Lamed, which ſignifieth
knowledge and doctrine: the third is Caph which ſignifieth
the hand, and is figuratiuely taken for ſtrength
and force of armes, and for the hand of Iuſtice: the vnion
or coniunction of theſe three letters in the Hebrew
word Melech, which by interpretation is called King,
doth teach vs what is required in this moſt excellent
office of a King, to wit, that he be a fountaine or water
of life and felicitie to his ſubiects, by maintaining the
water of life, which is true religion: that he retaine true
doctrine and learning within his kingdome. For the
adminiſtration of iuſtice, and preſeruation of his people:
that he haue in his hand the ſword of iuſtice which

is here ſignified by a mighty hand or a hand of force.
That he may be able to reſiſt the violence of forraine
enemies, and puniſh the rebellious murtherers and oppreſſors
in the Land. Alſo the word Melech doth ſignifie
in Hebrew, counſell, and in the Greeke tongue it is
called 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , that is to ſay, a King is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the foundation
of the people. Wherby we learne that the coū
               ſell
and wiſedome of a King is the foundation of the
whole eſtate of his ſubiects, who hereby are preſerued
from all diuiſions, factions, and diſſentions, whereof
commeth deſolation as Chriſt teacheth vs in this Text.
The Poet Homer calleth Kings 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               enutriti a Ioue
nouriſhed by God, admoniſhing therby that as a child
doth participate of the nature of his nurce: Euen ſo
Kings ſhould participate the nature of God, who is
their nource. This participation of Kings with God is
effectuated by exerciſing themſelues in God his word,
and ruling their kingdome according as they are inſtructed
by God his law. As it is written in Deut.
            The word diuiſion in the originall language is called
Peleg,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   The myſticall ſignification of the word, diuiſion, in Hebrew which word doth conſiſt of three letters:
the firſt, Phe, ſignifieth the mouth; the ſecond, Lamed,
learning and knowledge: the third Gimel, retribution,
By the which three letters conioyned in one word is
miſtically contained the cauſes and effects of Diuiſion.
For by the mouth is ſignified all ſeducing, deceiuing, or
beguiling with the mouth, whether by lying, falſe perſwading,
or poyſonable flattering by knowledge and
learning is ſignified the wicked abuſe of learning, in imploying
the ſame to ſow diuiſion amongſt men: by retribution
is ſignified, the vengeance that men exerciſe

ſeth one againſt another by diuiſion, diſcord, and diſſention.
By the which myſticall interpretation we are
inſtructed of the whole nature of diuiſion to this end,
that we may ſee how dangerous a plague diuiſion is,
whereby euery one of vs may learne to auoide the
ſame. Of all this we gather that Diuiſion is the ſeparation
and partition of things that ware before vnited;
where alſo we collect that Vnion doth goe before Diuiſion,
and that the one is contrarie to the other. The
phraſe and manner of ſpeaking of Chriſts maternall
language (which was the language of Ieruſalem) doth
expreſſe in this Text the inward operation of diuiſion,
with greater force and efficacie then the Greeke language.
For where the Greeke text ſaith (diuided 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
againſt it ſelfe) the Syriack hath Gnal napſcheh againſt
his own ſoule.
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                Signifying thereby that the fountaine
of diuiſion is rooted in the ſoule, hart, and minde
of man, whereby we are taught that vnion which is
contrarie to diuiſion, muſt begin in the hart and ſoule
of man. Therefore let all men that loue God, who is
the God of vnion, and enemy to diuiſion, gratiouſly diſpoſe
their ſoules, harts, and mindes to the performance
and accompliſhment of this bleſſed Vnion of this Iland.
            The word Vnion in the originall language is Achad
and doth conſiſt of three letters:The myſticall ſignification of the word Vnion in Hebrew. the firſt is Aleph, which
(as is ſaid) ſignifieth knowledge, learning, or a conducter:
the ſecond,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               Cheth, ſignifieth breathing or life: the third
Daleth, ſignifieth a doore, of the which three letters conioyned
in the Hebrew word, Achad, Vnion, we are
taught that Vnion is the doore whereby we enter by
knowledge to life and eternall felicitie.
            
               
I haue ſet before your eies this doctrine of the myſticall
ſignification of the Hebrew letters, that are contained
in theſe words Man, Woman, Citie, kingdome, diuiſion,
and vnion, to this end that the perſons which are
to treate of this great worke of vnion in the vniting of
the Iland of Great Brittannie in one kingdome in the
members, as God hath vnited them alreadie in one
head, may make their profit thereof and apply the ſame
to their harts.
            And becauſe I haue heretofore ſhewed you,Man is a type of a little world and of a little kingdome that the
beginning of all ſocietie in this earth, is by the Vnion
and coniunction of man and woman together, I will
(by God his grace) repreſent vnto you the image of a
kingdome both in the outward and inward man. For
this effect we ſhall marke that man is called by the Philoſophers

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                that is,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . a little world. Becauſe the
harmonie of all the Elements is found in the edifice and
building of the man in the coniunction of the which,
mans preſeruation doth ſtand, as by their diuiſion his
deſtruction enſueth. And ſeeing the world is made of
many kingdomes,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                we may alſo call Man 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                a
little kingdome, as before we heard he was called a little
world.
            In this little kingdome of the outward man,The Image of a kingdome in the outward man. the head
is the King, and ſoueraigne gouernour of the whole
body, becauſe by the head, there doth come nouriſhment
and foode to the body: And as in a kingdome
there be many, members, that is, ſubiects, vnder one
King: euen ſo in this kingdome of the outward man
there be many members, as the armes, hands, legges,
and feete, which are as officers, and vnder-gouernours,

to the head their King. By whoſe adminiſtration the
head diſtributeth equallie to all his members food and
nouriſhment. Let vs apply this ſimilitude of 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
in the outward man to our ſelues: ſeing the whole people
of this Iland is alreadie Vnited vnder one head, and
ſeeing the armes, hands, legges, and feete are tyed to
the obedience of this their head. And that the head and
the members are ipſo iure, &amp; ipſo facto, by law and by
the deede it ſelfe Vnited. Let no man be ſo vnreaſonable
to ſeparate them, for in ſo doing they do but throwe
ſtones againſt the heauen. For how can the armes,
hands, legges, and feete ſerue the head in the nouriſhing
of the whole body, if they were onely vnited in the
head and diuided amongſt themſelues? If the hands and
armes were diuided one from another, and ſeparated
from the whole body, it were then impoſſible &amp; againſt
nature that this body could be nouriſhed, by the worke
and induſtrie of the hands: and againe, if the feet were
diuided from the head, and the reſt of the body, and the
one from the other, the head muſt needes fall to the
ground. Therefore let not the hands deny the ſeruice
due to their head, which conſiſteth in preparing and
adminiſtrating foode to vphold and nouriſh the head,
and the whole body. The force of both the armes, and
hands doth come from the head to the body, and from
the head to the armes. Let not the feete, and legges deny
their ſeruice in carying of their body, becauſe from
thence commeth their nouriſhment and foode. But let
vs apply this doctrine more particularly to our ſelues.
The head of this Iland, the Kings Maiestie, hath vnited
in his Royall perſon the armes, hands and legs of

this body, which is this kingdome of Great Brittannie,
to wit, the South and the North in one obedience, and
ſeruice, whoſe ſtrength and nouriſhment doth flow
from this head as from a fountaine: So hauing this
conſideration before you, iudge and ponder with your
ſelues what a miſerable and dangerous eſtate it were,
that one of the armes, hands, or feete ſhould draw to it
ſelfe, the whole foode which commeth from the head,
and not to ſuffer his fellow to be participant thereof.
Therefore let not the armes of the South, I meane the
Officers, and great Gouernors in the South, attribute to
themſelues onely, the whole ſuſtenance and nouriſhment
that doth come from the head, that is to ſay, preferments,
offices, and dignities as well Eccleſiaſticall as
Temporall, excluding from thence the fellow arme of
the North, which is the other arme of this body: and
on the other part let not the arme of the North, which
is the other arme of this body, withdraw from his fellow
the offices, preferments, and dignities that proceed
from the head, which equally ſhould pertaine to them
both. But according to the diſpoſition of nature in this

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                or little kingdome. Let both the armes be
equally participant of the benefits, that come from
their head. Thus much concerning a perfect and ſtable
Vnion betwixt the members and the head, and of the
Vnion of the members amongſt themſelues.
            We come now to the Image of a kingdome,The Image of a kingdome in the inward man. which
is repreſented vnto vs in the inward man. Honorius a very
faithfull Chriſtian Emperour, inſtructing his ſonne
Arcadius (who ſucceeded to his Father into that great
huge Monarchie of the whole world,) deſcribed the

forme of that kingdome,Claud. Paneg. Conſ. 4. Hon. which is within man. As Claudianus
the Poet doth record in a very elegant panegyrike
of the fourth Conſulſhip, of this foreſaid Honorius.
Wherein he doth teach vs that this inward kingdome
of the inwardman doth conſiſt of Mens, which in the
Greeke language is called 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , that is, the wit, vnderſtanding
or minde of man, hauing within it 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Ratio,
reason, which by him is called ſyncera Mens, and alluding
to the allegorie of the auncient Greeke Poets, he
imagineth that this mind filled with wit, &amp; vnderſtanding
was ſtollen out of heauen, and placed within the
outward man by Prometheus; which doth ſignifie the
vnſpeakeable prouidence of God in the creation of
man to his owne Image, which is this diuine mind, wit,
vnderſtanding, ſoule and reaſon infuſed by God his
ſpirit into the inward man. The wit, and reaſon of the
mind beareth the Image of a King in the inward man.
And as Claudianus ſayeth in the perſon of Honorius,
The maker of man, to wit, Prometheus (as is ſayd)
—hanc alta capitis fundauit in arce mandatricem operum: proſpecturam
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   labori.
            
            He did place this ſpiritual king of the inward man in
his head, as in a throne out of the which he ruleth and
diſpoſeth all the actions of man, prouideth and foreſeeth
to keepe his ſubiects which are Ira, Metus, Cupido,
anger, feare, couetouſneſſe, in good order and temperature;
of the which it will pleaſe you heare Claudianus
words as followeth.
            
               Illas inferius collo, praecepta
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   summae
               Paſſuras Dominae, digna ſtatione locauit.
            
            
               
That is the maker of man, did place the ſubiects of
this King of the inward man, in theſe parts of the body
which are vnder the head and necke, as in a fit ſtation,
ward, or ſtanding place to obey the commaundement
of their ſoueraigne Lord, the firſt of theſe ſubiects named
Ira, anger, hath his ſeate in the hart which is full
of heat: the ſecond Metus, feare hath his ſeate in the
lungs or lights: the third Cupido, deſire, couetouſneſſe,
hath his ſeate in Iecore, in the Liuer. Let vs draw this
example of the image of the kingdome, in the inward
man to our ſelues, in this vnion of great Britannie,
which great worke is now in hand, for euen as Mens
or Ratio is the king, who ruleth, and keepeth in order
his ſubiects, to wit, Ira, metus, cupido, euen ſo the king
and head of this Iland muſt keepe his ſubiects in the
South and in the North, that are as diuers of nature as
Ira, metus, cupido, in good order &amp; temperature, leaſt
that not being ruled, and ouerruled by their King, they
fall into a lamentable diuiſion, whereupon will follow
according to Chriſts words in this text, a moſt miſerable
deſolation (from the which I pray the Lord deliuer
vs) So that I conclude if we be vnited vnder one head
and one king, we muſt be vnited amongſt our ſelues, or
els be diſobedient to Reaſon our King: This if we do, all
the members of one body ſhall agree in a harmonie amongſt
themſelues, and be participant euerie one of
his fellowes benefits, in ſo much that the heate of the
hart, wherein wrath and anger dwelleth muſt participate
of the moiſt and cold of the lights, that is, the furie
of wrath and anger muſt be ruled, and brideled by
the feare of god, and of the king his Lieutenant heere

on earth, which otherwiſe getting looſe bridle raines,
would cut the whole kingdome by diuiſion in pieces:
Alſo the reſpiration and breathing of the lights muſt
temperate, and moderate the ardent heat of deſire
and couetouſneſſe that is in the liuer. So that ye may
ſee the three inward parts of man, which are ſubiect to
their king reaſon, muſt communicate one with another
all their offices and commodities, otherwiſe the ſubiects
of the kingdome of the inward man could not
keepe themſelues in the obedience of Reaſon their
king.
            
            Of this we learne, that by the figure and type of this
kingdome of the inward man the whole people and
ſubiects of this Iland ſhould conſider, that if they will
follow the law of their king reaſon (which they muſt
needes doe, or els they cannot remaine vnited with
their ſoueraigne king, whoſe kingdome is ruled by reaſon)
it behoueth them all to make euery one participant
of an others helpe, and aide, in communicating
mutually one to his neighbour, and fellow the emoluments,
and preferments on both the ſides. For when
the heat of the hart is withdrawen from the cold moiſtneſſe
of the lungs and humiditie of the liuer: or when
the lights, and the liuer doe withdraw their refreſhing
from the heart, then the kingdome of the inward man
is brought to confuſion, and deſolation, by the diuiſion
of the ſubiects in withdrawing the commodities
one from another which ſhould be common to both.
Ye ſee now what I meane; that if the people of the
South withdrawe the commoditie of their heat from
the North; and on the other part, if theſe of the North

withdraw the refreſhing of the heat of the South:
There is no doubt, I ſay, but if ſuch diuiſion were ſuffered
by Reaſon our king, it would bring forth ere it
were long ſuch a diſtemperature amongſt his ſubiects,
that in the end in place of vnion, there ſhould be nothing
but miſerable deſolation and confuſion, which is
the fruite of Diuiſion, ſpoken of in our text.
            Now let vs come to the opening of the matter contained
in our text, hauing alreadie amply enough ſpoken
of the myſticall doctrine, collecting the ſame out
of the literall ſenſe.
                  
                     •
                  lu
                     •
                   ſorts of kingdomes. Chriſt in theſe words (euery kingdome)
doth teach vs, that there is diuerſitie of kingdomes,
to wit, the kingdome of God in heauen, the
kingdome of Satan in hell, and the kingdome of men
in earth. And againe the kingdome of men may be ſubdeuided
into the kingdome of God &amp; the kingdome of
Satan amongſt men. This kingdome of God is compoſed
and made of the elect number of true beleeuers,
which are predeſtinated and preordained to life euerlaſting
before the foundation of the world was laied.
The kingdome of Satan, in earth is made of the whole
number of the reprobate (who are ſet downe more
particularly by S. Paul in the 13 to the Rom. and in the
5. cap. to the Galat. verſ. 19.) as adulterers, all vncleane
perſons, Idolaters, all contentious and ſeditious perſons,
murtherers, drunkards, gluttons &amp;c. and in a
word all other wicked offendours, who as S. Paul teacheth
vs ſhall neuer enter into the kingdome of
God.
            The kingdome of God in heauen doth conſiſt of
Archangels,
               The kingdome of God in heauen. 
               Angels, Cherubins, Seraphins, Vertues,

Thrones, and all other ſorts of ſpirits called by S. Paul

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                miniſtring ſpirits, who doe praiſe
and worſhip continually their Creator with hymnes,
and ſpirituall ſongs, ſurpaſſing the intelligence of man
in this earth, liuing in an incomprehenſible and vnſpeakeable
felicitie and happineſſe in an inacceſſable
light, who are guided by the euerlaſting wiſdome, and
prouidence of the eternall, omnipotent, and onelie
good God.
            This celeſtiall kingdome was from the beginning
eſtabliſhed in vnion: But Satan who was created in all
perfection, and for his brightneſſe (by the auncient Fathers)
called Lucifer, did fall away from his Creator,
&amp; drew with him innumerable legions of Angels, and
in ſo doing, by his apoſtaſie &amp; defection from God, did
make a diuiſion amongſt the Angels in the kingdome
of heauen. For the which he was throwen downe from
that heauenly habitation, to the bottomleſſe pit of hell,
prepared for him and his Angels before the beginning
of the world, as we may read in the Goſpell of Saint
Matthew,Matth. 25. 41. where they are tyed with chaines of eternall
darkneſſe,2. Peter. 2. 4. as Saint Peter,Iud. v. 6. and Saint Iude doe teach vs:
from this originall diuiſion made by Satan in the beginning
in the kingdome of heauen, came an eternall
and endleſſe deſolation vpon him and all the reſt of the
Angels of iniquitie, according as it is here ſaid in our
Text: Euery kingdome, &amp;c. Although Satan will admit
no diuiſion, in his owne kingdome, as we are taught in
this Chapter; yet he is the very fountaine, &amp; welſpring
of all diuiſions, both in the kingdome of God and man,
from the beginning of the world to the end thereof.
            
               
For the better vnderſtanding of this word Diuiſion
which is in my Text,Three kinds of Diuiſion. you muſt know there be three
kinds of Diuiſion, viz. a diuiſion betwixt God and
man: a diuiſion betwixt man and man, and a diuiſion
betwixt countrey and countrey. The diuiſion betwixt
God and man doth come by Idolatrie, and ſinne: the
diuiſion betwixt man and man, is partly by diuerſitie
in Religion, and partly by ambition, in hunting after
dignities, honours, and preferments, of which alſo doth
come the diuiſion of countries and lands.
            As we haue ſhewed you how many kindes of Diuiſion
there be,Sundry ſorts of Deſolation. now it followeth to ſhew how many
kindes there be of Deſolation. There is a deſolation of
mens goods, which doth fall out by robbing, ſtealing,
forraing, ſpoyling, burning ſhip wrake, and all other
meanes that may be to the preiudice of mens goods.
There is a ſecond deſolation of mans body, which doth
fall out, by plagues, peſtilence, or by the ſword in ciuill
or forraine warres: There is a third deſolation of mans
ſoule, which doth fall out by Idolatrie, apoſtaſie and
blaſphemie; of the which all other ſinnes doe proceede.
            Hauing ſhewed you what Diuiſion and deſolation is,
and their kinds, I purpoſe (by God his grace) for the
better expoſition of my Text, to ſet ſummarily before
your eyes, as in a painted table, the moſt notable examples
of the Diviſion of Kingdoms, Cities, and houſes
in all ages: together with their deſolation which doe
follow on the other, as the effect the cauſe: Moreouer
we ſhall ſee, that diuiſion is a puniſhment and a curſe
of God laid on mankind: as by the contrarie Vnion
is a great bleſſing of God amongſt all eſtates and conditions

of men, which we ſhall doe to this end, that laying
before you the good fruits of Vnion, and the miſeries
and calamities that doe flow from diuiſion of
kingdomes, countries, and houſes, that all theſe things
may ſerue, for your inſtructions who haue now in hand
the conſideration of the bleſſed Vnion of this Iland of
Great Britannie into one kingdome, which is alreadie
vnited in our head our dread Soueraigne the King his
Maieſtie.
            The firſt diuiſion that euer we read of after the creation
of the world,The first Diuiſion inuented by Sathan. was inuented by Satan that old Serpent,
by the which there came a miſerable deſolation
vpon all mankind. For ſoone after the creation of Man
and woman, who was created in an angelicall nature,
Vnited with God, and hauing the viſible communication
of Gods preſence, was placed in a habitation of vnſpeakable
ioy and felicitie: But Satan vpon hatred and
enuie did ſeduce and deceiue the womans mind by lying,
and falſe perſwaſions, and by the woman the man,
with a conceite of vaine glory, that they thought to be
like God in knowledge: ſo being thus waies ſeduced by
Satan, they brake and violated Gods commandement;
of the which came the firſt diuiſion betwixt God and
man, and after the diuiſion followed a miſerable and lamentable
deſolation vpon the whole race of mankind
which dayly in our owne perſons by dolefull experience
we find to be true. For being created immortall
they became ſubiect both to the death of the ſoule, and
the death of the body, and were caſt out of that place
of vnſpeakable ioy and felicitie, which in the originall
language is called Gan-heden a Garden of pleaſure into

to a moſt barren and infertile ſoile, wherein he ſhould
labour hardly and purchaſe his bread by the ſwet of his
face, till he returne againe to the earth. Vpon the other
part, God who is the fountaine of charitie, loue, and
Vnion, yea charitie it ſelfe, did begin his kingdome alſo
amongſt men, whereby at the time preordinate in
his incomprehenſible prouidence, he ſhould ouerthrow
the kingdome of Satan. God, I ſay, did begin this
his kingdome in the very fall of man, in that bleſſed
promiſe, which he made to Man, when he ſaid, that the
ſeede of the woman ſhould bruſe and deſtroy the head
of the Serpent.Gen. 3. 15.
            
            The firſt example of the beginning of the kingdome
of Satan in this earth by diuiſion,Deſolation came by Diuiſion in Adams houſe, and in his poſteritie. is in his practizing
of the diuiſion of the houſe of Adam. Who hauing
two ſonnes, Satan eſtabliſhed his kingdome amongſt
men in the perſon of Cain. For Cains hart being puffed
vp with arrogancie and pride, by reaſon of his birth-right
(whereby he pretended preeminence aboue his
brother Abell, both in the fauour of God, and in regard
of religion) he offred vp a Sacrifice to God, which
was reiected, becauſe he offered the ſame with an euill
mind. But Abell the ſecond brother, hauing his hart
filled with loue, and humilitie, did offer a Sacrifice to
God which was willingly accepted, becauſe he did offer
it with faith, as Saint Paul doth teach vs in the 11.
Cap. to the Hebrewes. Of this Satan taketh occaſion,
to ingender in the hart of the elder brother an immortall
inanimitie, and hatred againſt the yonger, ſo
that by theſe meanes, Satan ſeduced Cain to murder his
brother traiterouſly (as he himſelfe was a murtherer

from the beginning.) This murther made a diuiſion in
the houſe of Adam, which was the cauſe of a miſerable
and pitifull deſolation that came to paſſe by ſucceſſion
of time, in the drowning of the whole world by
the deluge.
            But God on the other part, hauing a care of his promiſe
of the bleſſed ſeede, did renue his kingdome amongſt
men, in the perſon of Seth, Enos, Enoch, and
ſundry others, who were the true and faithfull worſhippers
of God, that bleſſed ſeede that was promiſed, in
whom the ruine of man with God, did conſiſt. Yet
notwithſtanding Satan continuing in his practiſes of
diuiſion againſt mankind, being deſirous to bring them
all to lamentable deſolation and confuſion, did ſeduce
the progenie of godly Seth, and Enos, whom the Text
calleth the ſonnes of God, by the bewitching beautie
of the daughters of men, to wit, the daughters of the
Cainites, who were an Idolatrous &amp; wicked people: of
this vngodly mixtion, the generations of wicked Idolatrous
and blood thirſtie men, did ſo multiply, that we
reade in Geneſis the whole race of mankinde was corrupted,Geneſ. 6. 11.
by falling away from God; which diuiſion
brought in by Satan betwixt God and man, was the
cauſe of miſerable deſolation. For God for the puniſhment
of ſuch wickedneſſe did deſtroy the whole world
except Noe, his wife, their three Sonnes, and their
wiues, being eight perſons onely that did find fauour in
the ſight of God. We ſee by this example, that it is
moſt true which is here ſpoken by Chriſt, that Euery
kingdome, &amp;c. For here we ſee how Satan in this firſt
age, did practiſe a generall deſolation in the whole race

of mankind, by the diuiſion which he brought into the
houſe of Adam.
            
            Out of this doctrine there may be collected a wholſome
inſtruction, and warning to all the ſubiects of this
Iland of Great Britannie. But more ſpecially this doctrine
doth appertain, for the inſtruction of theſe, whom
God and his Lieutenant hath aſſembled at this time, to
treate of the performance of this godly worke, of the
Vnion of this Iland in one kingdome. For euen as the
firſt age which was before the deluge, did deſcend of
one Father, and was diuided by diſcord amongſt bretheren,
and afterward by this diuiſion brought to ſmall
deſolation and deſtruction: So the firſt Inhabitants of
this little world, of great Britannie, (who are called by
Virgill, diuiſi toto orbe Britanni,) were in the beginning
borne of one Father, but amongſt themſelues by bretheren
diuided, who could not liue together in loue
and amitie: of this diuiſion, which hath beene for
many yeers, many deſolations did fall out, in the whole
Iſland by ſundry cruell, &amp; bloody wars: yet in our daies
God hath ſhewed his mercy wonderfully towards vs
in vniting vs al vnder one head. Wherby we are taught
alſo, that as the diuerſitie of heads, and Kings in this
Iſland made the diuerſitie of kingdomes: Euen ſo the
ſingularitie of one King, and one head, maketh the ſingularitie
of one kingdome: ſo that this whole Iſland is
vnited ipſo iure, &amp; ipſo facto in that ſame vnited eſtate,
in the which it was before the firſt diuiſion thereof, into
diuers kingdomes. Therefore let euery man thinke,
that it is, both agreeable with law, and reaſon, that
we be no more two kingdomes, but one, ſeeing we all

confeſſe to haue onely one head, and one King.
            The order of this matter doth lead vs to ſet downe
before you,Diuiſion of 
                     •••
                  
                  guages, and diuerſitie of 
                     ••
                  
                  uernours did bring forth diuiſion of lands and countreys. the beginning of the diuiſion of countreies
and lands, betwixt people and people, of the which diuiſion,
the whole multitude of kingdomes according
to the diuerſitie of languages did proceed in the beginning
of the renewed world, as we read in the hiſtorie
of Geneſ.Gen. 10. For Noah and his three ſonnes, Sem, Ham,
and Iaphet did diuide the whole habitable world amongſt
their poſteritie. After the confuſion of languages,
which did fall out a hundred yeares after the deluge.
The auncient Greeke authors, whom Epiphanius
did follow in his Anchorato, did moſt conſtantlie
hold, that the whole Orient, which commonly is called
Aſia, did fall by lot to the eldeſt brother Sem, and
to his poſteritie: the whole South called Africa to
Cham, and his poſteritie: the whole North and occident
commonly called Europa, to Iaphet and his poſteritie:
we haue the teſtimonie of this alſo in thoſe
auncient Greeke hiſtories, and poeſies, which Horace
did follow, in the which he calleth the poſteritie of
Iaphet, Audax Iapeti genus.
            In this generall diuiſion of the whole world we may
obſerue, that the gouernours and captaines of theſe
people, which firſt did inhabite any land, gaue the firſt
names to that land or kingdome that they did inhabite.
Of the which names there remaine as yet to our daies
ſome ſignes, markes, and remembrances of their firſt
impoſition; as for example, the countrey of Thracia,
gat the name from Thyras one of Iaphets ſonnes; the
country of the Grecians, was called Ionia from Iauan,

one of Iaphets children, who by the Grecians was called
Ion, et inde Iones: The countrey of Moſchouia,
whoſe people to our age are called Muſchouits, did
take the name from Meſchet, another of Iaphets ſons.
In the 10. cap. of Geneſ. after that Moſes hath named
Iaphets poſteritie, he ſaith, that the Iſles of the Gentiles
were deuided likewiſe by Iaphets ſonnes according
to their families, and languages, and although the
names of the gouernours, and people, who firſt did inhabite
the ilands of the Gentiles, are not expreſſed in
the Bible: yet we find them expreſſed by that moſt renowned
Doctor Epiphanius in his Anchorato, who
after he had named and ſpoken of Iaphets poſteritie
and progenie, he doth name in the end of his Catalogue,
Britanni, Scoti, Hiſpani: Inſulae verò ipſorum,
Brittannia, Sicilia, Rhodus, &amp;c. ſo that we ſee heere
that this Iland of great Brittannie, is firſt named amongſt
all the Ilands of the world, by all appearance
at that time, as the greateſt.
            Whereby we may collect,The antiquitie of the name of Brittannia in the firſt diuiſion of countreys. that this name of Britannia,
or Brettania commeth from the name of ſuch
a one of the poſteritie of Iaphet, that did firſt deuide
the Iſles of the Gentiles, vnto whom by lot this Iland
did fall. Therefore it is moſt certaine that as the reſt of
the names of the kingdomes of Europe, did take their
originall name out of the Hebrew language from the
ſonnes of Iaphet: euen ſo wee muſt ſeeke the Etymologie
of Britannia, out of the Hebrew language,
which is Brit-an-iah,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                and doth conſiſt of three words.
Brit ſignifieth, foedus, a couenant; an, ibi, there: iah
Dei, of God. Which three being conioyned in one,

doe ſignifie, that there is the couenant of God, that is,
in this Iland the couenant of God was to be eſtabliſhed.
            The proper names of men,Proper names of men and places propheticall or memoriall. and places in the renued
world was propheticall, for they did contain myſtically
within them prophecies of things that were to fall out
afterward: or elſe they were impoſed for a memoriall of
notable things already come to paſſe. As for example,
the name of Abram which is made of the Hebrew
word,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               Ab Pater, Father, &amp; Ram, excelſus, high, that is to
ſay, a high Father, was altered, &amp; changed by God himſelfe,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
               
in adding thereto one other word hamon, which
ſignifieth a multitude, and ſo ioyning all theſe three
words together, per ſynaereſin, he was called Abraham,
pater excelſus multitudinis, a high Father of a multitude,
in which name was contained a prophecie: into
the which change of his name God did make a promiſe
to him, that a multitude of Kings, and people ſhould
come of him: for this ſame cauſe God changed the
name Sarai,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                which ſignifieth a particular Lady into a
more general name Sarah,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                which ſignifieth a great and
generall Lady, becauſe a great number of Queenes and
Ladies were to come of her. In like manner, Iacob did
impoſe a newe name to the place where God did appeare
to him,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                and called it Bethel the houſe of God,
which before was named Luz, that is, a Nutte tree, to
be a perpetuall memoriall, that in that place God and
his Angels did appeare to him aſcending and deſcending
a Ladder. In the ſame manner alſo, Iacobs name was
changed by God,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                and was called Iſrael, that is, a prince
to God, to be a continuall memoriall of his wreſtling

with the Angell, who bare the figure of a man. For the
Text ſayeth, Strenue egit cum Deo &amp; cum hominibus,
that is, he played the part of a valiant wreſtler, both
with God and man. And Iacob named that place Peniel,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Gen. 32. 30.
               the face of God, becauſe in that place he ſaw the
face of God vnder the ſhape of a man Euen ſo we may
ſay, and that not without reaſon, that the name of Britan-iah,
is a propheticall name from the beginning, foreſhewing
that the couenant of God ſhould be eſtabliſhed
in this Iland, at the appointed time by God. The
couenant betwixt God and man, doth conſiſt in the
true worſhip, and adoration of the onely increated
God, which is moſt plainly ſet downe to vs in the new
Teſtament of the Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus.
            As the generall name of the whole Iland doth containe
vnder it ſelfe,The ſignification of the auncient names, Anglia, Scotia, Wallia, and Hibernia. all the people that dwell therein:
Euen ſo the ſignifications of all the names of theſe people
are contained within the ſignificatiō of the generall
name Brit-an-iah. The people of this Iland, are diuided
into foure ſundry countries, according to the diuiſion of
the earth, and the places where they dwell. For Angli
doe inhabite the South Eaſt ſide: Scoti the North Eaſt:
Walli the South Weſt: and Hiberni or Heberni, &amp; Hebrides
Inſulae, the North weſt. And frō the people, the
places of their habitation are called Anglia, Scotia,
Wallia, Hibernia. Vndoubtedly all theſe foure names
haue their auncient originall from Iaphets poſteritie, as
Epiphanius, and others doe write: So that we may gather
that the etymologie of their names is to be ſearched
out of the Hebrew language, whoſe ſignification
hath a great correſpondence, with the generall name

               Brit-an-iah. And therefore it is fit they be knowne. Angli,
Saxones, &amp; Viti were the three ancient nations,
that came out of Sueuia, and Germania into great Britannie
as Beda doth witneſſe,Beda lib. 1. cap. 15. and diuers other Hiſtoriographers;
from thence the name of Anglia did come,
who in their owne countrey were called Angles before
they came into South Brittannie, as Balaeus writeth.
And therfore we muſt not ſeek the Etymology of England
neither from Hengist, neither any Queene named
Angla, neither from angulo, or angelo: but we muſt
ſearch the deriuation of Anglia, out of the originall
language, ſeeing we may ſee clearely, they are deſcended
of the poſteritie of Iaphet.
               An-gli-iah. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                Wherefore An-gli-iah
in Hebrew is ibi Reuelatio Dei, there is the Reuelation
of God: Scotia, is alſo a moſt ancient kingdome in this
Iland. For in the booke of collections out of Ioſeph
Bon-gorion, written in Hebrew, Veſpaſianus ſpeaking
to Nero, doth make mention of Scotia, ſo doth Flauius
Ioſephus in an Oration which he had to the people of
Ieruſalem,Hegeſippus. lib. 5. cap. 15. which Hegeſippus doth teſtifie. Quid attexam
Brittannias interfuſo mari a toto orbe diuiſas, &amp; a
Romanis in orbem terrarum redact as tremit hos Scotia,
quae terris nihil debet. Of this name alſo Epiphanius
beareth record, when hereckoned the poſteritie of Iaphet,
as I ſhewed you before: and therefore we muſt in
like maner ſeeke the deriuation of Scotia, out of the Hebrew,
which is,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                Skot-iah quies Dei, the rest or peace of
God. Hiberni or Heberni are deſcended alſo of Iaphets
poſterity.
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                And therefore in Hebrew Heber-nin-iah and
by a contraction Hebernia, is, Tranſitio filij Dei, the paſſing
ouer of the Sonne of God. Euen ſo Wallia doth come

from Gallia, from whence Walli had their progenie,
who as yet doe ſpeake the old language (which was
in Gallia before the Romane conqueſt) and in this Wallia
were the old auncient ſchooles of the Gentilique religion
of the Druides. The name then of Wallia or Gallia,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
               
               Galli-iah in the originall is, flumen Dei, Gods Riuer:
or reuelatio Dei, the Reuelation of God. So that ye may
ſee all theſe names are propheticall, and doe foretell
that the couenant of God ſignified by the generall
name Brit-an-iah ſhould make this happy and bleſſed
Vnion in one Religion, and one Kingdome.
            The prophecie of all theſe names was accompliſhed
immediatly after Chriſt his aſcention,The accompliſhment of the propheticall name of Britannia. and the ſending
downe of the holy Ghoſt vpon his Apoſtles, and Diſciples.Theodor. de Cur. gree Serm. de leg.
For we read in Theodoretus, Metaphraſtes, and
Nicephorus, that S. Paul, S. Peter, Ioſeph of Arimathaea,
and Simon Zelotes did preach the Euangell of Chriſt
in Brittannie,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c. that is, the new couenant betwixt God
and man: at which time this ſaid Iland of great Britannie
did beare the ſame name of Gods couenant as it
doth now. All Hiſtoriographers, and Chronologiſts of
whatſoeuer profeſſion, doe beare witneſſe that about
80. yeares after Chriſt, Britanni omnium gentium primi
publicè fidem Christi receperunt. The Britaines before
all nations firſt publikely receaued the Faith of
Chriſt; I muſt confeſſe there was Faith and Religion
before receaued in Ieruſalem, in Aſia, in Rome, France,
&amp; Spaine: but it was not ſo publikely embraced, in any
place, by Kings and ſuperior Magiſtrates: as it was
then receaued by Lucius, King of Britannie, and by all
his people. Tertulian alſo, who liued 200. yeeres after

Chriſt,Tertul. ad Iud. in his writings againſt the Iewes alleadgeth
to them, that the whole world had receaued Chriſt his
Faith, yea and amongſt the reſt ſpeaking of the Britaines
he ſaith. Britannorum loca Romanis inacceſſa,
Christo ſeſe ſubdiderunt. Origen who liued about the
ſame time, doth witneſſe the ſame.
            Alſo this propheſie that is contained myſticallie in
the name of Britannie hath thrice come to paſſe in this
Iland. Firſt, as is ſaid, it was accompliſhed in the preaching
of Chriſts Apoſtles, and their Diſciples: Secondly,
in the time of Conſtantinus Magnus by the vnion
of the kingdome of the whole world with Chriſts
kingdome: Thirdly, this propheſie is accompliſhed in
our daies (as we ſhall heare more amply hereafter) in
vs and our poſteritie. For before our daies the couenant
of God hath beene broken, and violated in this
Iland, by the operation of Satan, who transforming
himſelfe into an Angell of light, in taking vpon him
the pretext of Chriſts true religion, did change the
worſhip of Chriſt, into the worſhip of Chriſts images,
made by the handes of man, of gold and ſiluer, which
he made to be worſhipped, as Chriſt himſelfe. As
Thomas Aquinas, and the reſt of that ſort, do teach.
Quòd Chriſtus, &amp; imago Chriſti eadem adoratione adorari
debeant. That Chriſt and his image ſhould be
worſhipped with one and the ſelfe ſame adoration.
            Moreouer that old enemie of mankind, Satan, did
make our predeceſſors to breake Gods couenant by ſeducing
them to worſhip, &amp; erect a ſtrange God in this
earth: which was a new created God made of a wafer
cake, by tranſſubſtantiating the ſubſtance thereof into

the ſubſtance of the humane nature of Chriſt pretending
Chriſt, God, and man, reallie to be contained
vnder the outward forme thereof, which they called
by the name of God, Creator, and adored him as the
true God, both contrary to the Scriptures, and the
auncient doctrine of the Trinitie, by the which no
thing is to be adored extra 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               conſubſtantialitatē
Patris, that is not vnited in conſubſtantialitie with God
the father, which vnion cannot be performed in the Imaginarie
tranſſubſtantiation of this wafer cake, neither
yet can it be vnited with the deitie of Chriſt, as
Cardinall Bellarminus doth confeſſe; ſo that ye ſee,
how the couenant of God was broken in this Iland, by
the worſhipping of a ſtrange, and new God, who was
not incarnate or borne of the bleſſed Virgin Marie,
not vnited with the deitie in the Virgins wombe.
            Of all theſe we note,The reſtitution of the auncient name of Britannie, is a teſtimonie of the Vnion of language, kingdome, and religion. that God hauing reſtored againe
in this Iland the true worſhip of the only vncreated
God, excluding from this true worſhip all falſe adoration
of viſible, and created things, and reſtoring
againe in this Iland the true couenant of God; of this
we note, that ſeeing the couenant of God is reſtored
in this Iland, the name alſo of great Britannie,
which doth ſignifie the couenant of God, both by the
law of God, and the law of man, ſhould be reſtored in
the ſame, as it was before. Therefore I take the reſtitution
of this auncient name of great Britannie, by the
Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie to haue come, by the
very motion, and inſtigation of Gods holy ſpirit, to
this end; that it may be a perpetuall memoriall, and teſtimonie,
that God hath reſtored his true couenant of

eternall life, which he hath promiſed to all thoſe that do
worſhip him faithfully and truely. Let euerie one of vs
bleſſe, and praiſe God, for the reſtoring of the ſame.
Let all the ſubiects of this Iland thinke, that it is a great
glory to them to be called Britannes, that is to ſay, the
people of Gods couenant, which after the name of
Chriſtian is the moſt glorious and honorable name,
that any man in the world may enioy.
            I thinke I ſhould not diſcharge my duety, if in this
place, I did forget to ſhew you the King his Maieſties
great and laudable modeſtie, which he hath obſerued
in reſtoring of this auncient name, in ſo much that laying
a ſide all priuiledges, and prerogatiues due to other
Kings, in ſuch like caſes. For when the whole kingdomes
of the Orient were vnited to the Aſſyrians, they
tooke their names from their ſoueraigne King: And
when the Monarchie was tranſlated to the Perſians,
that ſecond Monarchie receaued the name of the Perſians:
and likewiſe in the third, and fourth Monarchie,
the people embraced the name and title of thoſe that
were their Kings and Princes. So that by the Kings
M. prerogatiue and priuiledge, ſeeing that the South
part is fallen to his royall perſon, both by the lawe of
God, and nature; the name of the former kingdome
might haue beene impoſed to this kingdome, which is
laſt fallen in his power: We ſee alſo that the name of
Scoti is inſert, by Epiphanius in the Catologue of thoſe
countries, that were diſtributed to the poſteritie of Iaphet:
whereof we may note the antiquitie thereof. So
that all men may ſee, that looke with an indifferent
eye, the great modeſtie, the good conſideration, and

louing kindnes that hath accompanied his Maieſtie in
this great worke, inſomuch that he hath not vſed his
owne prerogatiue in bringing in a new name in this
kingdome of the South: But he hath onely reſtored
the ancient name of great Britannie, both to the South
and the North. To the end that he might extirpat the
very ſeede of diuiſion, which hath beene theſe many
yeeres deeply rooted amongſt vs: But now (God be
praiſed) by the embracing of this godly Vnion, both in
the head, in the members, and in name, all matters of
diuiſion, and contention, are to be buried in the graue
of obliuion. For by this name of Britannie, which is
as much as Gods couenant we are vnited both in the
corporall, and ſpirituall kingdom.
            But let vs returne backe to the diuiſion of Countries.The first diuiſion of countries, and languages.
And firſt let vs make our profit of the diuiſion of countries,
and lands amongſt Noahs poſteritie. The cauſe of
this diuiſion was, for that the ſpace of a hundred yeers,
or thereabout after Noah, the whole race of mankinde,
did dwell together, as in one countrey without any diuiſion.
But Satan who watcheth day and night to eſtabliſh
his kingdome by diuiſion of countries amongſt
men, did ingender a deſire of vaine glory in their harts,
that they were about to build a tower which ſhould
reach to heauen; all this was attempted by them, vt
acquirerent ſibi nomen,
               Gen. 11. 4. That thereby they might purchaſe
themſelues a name. But God did puniſh this their
vaine glory, by the diuiſion and confuſion of their
tongues, being all before vnius labij of one lippe, and
of one language. This diuiſion of tongues, was the
cauſe that the heads and gouernors of families, that

were of one language, did ſeparate and diuide the
whole earth amongſt them, as we ſaid before; where
by the way we haue to obſerue that diuiſion of languages
was ſent vpon mankind as one of Gods curſes; for
there is nothing more forceable to maintaine Vnion
and peace amongſt men, then conformitie in language:
as on the other part we ſee diuerſitie of tongues doth
ingender hatred and enuy amongſt the nations of the
whole world.
            This being conſidered,Diuiſion of languages a curſe of God. it followeth that diuiſion
of lands, in ſundry countries, is a rod and puniſhment
of God, which being conioyned with the diuiſion
of tongues hath begotten ſundry fearefull and cruell
warres betwixt countrey and countrey, nation and nation.
Therefore ſeeing diuiſion of languages is a curſe
of God, it followeth neceſſarily that the Vnion of diuers
Kingdomes, in one language, and one Kingdome,
is a ſpeciall bleſſing of God. Wherefore briefly we intend
to bring in for all your inſtructions ſome examples,
out of the foure Monarchies, where we ſhall ſee,
as in a glaſſe, how theſe two doe follow, the one vpon
the other.
            In the firſt Monarchie of the Aſſyrians,Examples ſhewing Vnion to be a bleſſing of God. the Aſſyrian
language was then a common language vſed in the
whole Monarchie, and from thence came to the Iewes
by the captiuitie of Babylon, and to this day all the
Chriſtians of Aſia doe vſe it in their diuine ſeruice:
And it is euidently knowen that the Monarchie of the
Greekes did ſpread the Greeke tongue throughout
all Aſia, and Egypt, yea and it did remaine in the beginning
of the Romane Monarchie, when all men ſtudied

to the vnderſtanding of the Greeke language, and
the Romanes hauing obtained the vniuerſall Empire,
did eſtabliſh therein their owne language: Euen ſo,
when Chriſt came into the world, to eſtabliſh his kingdome
by the preaching of the Goſpell, he ſent downe
vpon his Diſciples, the knowledge of all tongues,
which was a ſpirituall Vnion of them. And therefore
God conuerted the curſe, that came by the diuerſitie of
language, into a great bleſſing, by giuing his Apoſtles
the gift of the vnderſtanding of all tongues: So God
did begin the Vnion of this Iland, by the Vnion of one
language in both theſe nations, which came to paſſe by
a conqueſt. Yet God would not performe this Vnion
of theſe two kingdomes by conqueſt, which is a kind
of violent Vnion; but in the time appointed by his incomprehenſible
wiſdome hath vnited vs not by a violent,
but a free and voluntary Vnion. So that long
after the Vnion of the language of the South and
the North, he did vnite vs in the couenant of God,
which is ſignified by our generall name Brit-an-iah:
and afterward vnited vs vnder one ſoueraigne head
and King. The which Vnion of one language, one Religion,
and one King, maketh the Vnion of the two
countries, ipſo iure naturali. For as we haue prooued,
that the firſt diuiſion of lands, did come from the diuerſitie
of languages, as alſo the diuerſitie of chuſing
Kings to gouerne ſundry people according to the diuerſitie
of their languages: Euen ſo, by the generall
rule, deficiente cauſa, deficit effectus; the cauſe of the
diuiſion of kingdomes being taken away, the effect
and diuiſion of them ſhould be taken away, ipſo iure,

&amp; ipſo facto. For ſo they returne to be one nation, one
people, and one land, as they were before the diuiſion.
            By this it is moſt euidently ſhewed to vs, that our
great Britaine being in our daies vnited in one language,
in one religion, and vnder one head, one King
and ſupreame gouernour, we cannot by any law, be any
more two nations, or two kingdomes, but only one.
            The ſecond example of the Vnion of ſundry Countries,Vnion of kingdomes a bleſſing of God.
Kingdomes, and Lands, being before diuided, is
manifeſt in the poſteritie of Abraham. For the Land
that was promiſed by God to the Iſraelites, which
ſince was called Paleſtina, was diuided into diuers Kings,
and Kingdomes (as the hiſtorie of the Bible doth teach
vs:) all theſe diuided Kings and kingdomes were vnited
by God in one kingdome of the Iſraelites in the perſon
of Dauid, and Salomon, in the time of which Vnion
was the moſt happy eſtate of any kingdome we
read of before that age: So that we may gather, ſeeing
the cauſe of this Vnion of many kingdomes was the
vnitie, and ſingularitie of the head; euen ſo the like Vnion
and ſingularitie of the head in our great Britaine,
doth vnite ipſo iure, &amp; ipſo facto, the kingdomes that
were ſeuerall and ſeparated before.
            Therefore let no man imagine that we are two
kingdomes, or two nations, but vnus grex, vnum ouile,
ſub vno paſtore,
               Homer. 
               ac vno Rege: as Homer did call the King,

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                the Paſtour and Sheapheard of the people.
In this bleſſed Vnion of many kingdomes in the perſon
of Dauid, and of his ſonne Salomon, was eſtabliſhed
the kingdome of God in earth, which was ioyned with
the vnited eſtate of the temporall and worldly kingdome.

For the temple of Ieruſalem was builded for the
exerciſe of the true worſhip of God; But Satan continuing
in his accuſtomed malicious practiſes, did caſt
in the ſeede of diuiſion: firſt by diuiſion of Religion,
and of the ſpirituall kingdome, and then by the diuiſions
of earthly, and temporall kingdomes; by the which
diuiſions in the ſpace of 300. yeeres, or thereabout, the
whole kingdome of the Iſraelites was brought to a lamentable
deſolation, according to the doctrine of
Chriſt Ieſus in our Text.An example that diuiſion of kingdomes, is a curſe of God, and that for Idolatrie.
            
            Satan to eſtabliſh his kingdome in the middle of the
people of God, did deceaue the wiſe Salomon, by the
filthie loue, and deſire of forraine women: afterward
he ſeduced him to erect Idols, and falſe Gods in the
high places of that holy Land, retaining neuertheleſſe
the temple of Ieruſalem, &amp; the true Sacrifice, worſhip,
and adoration of God: by the which maintenance of
true Religion on the one part, and falſe Religion on the
other, there did proceede a diuiſion ſo odious vnto
God, that for this cauſe, he did poure foorth his curſes
and maledictions vpon the poſteritie of Salomon, and
rent away the ten Tribes, and parts of the kingdome of
the holy land from Roboam his ſonne, which he gaue
to Ieroboam his ſeruant: leauing onely to Roboam the
two Tribes which did remaine. By this we learne, how
diſpleaſant this diuiſion of Religion made by Salomon
was to God, and what a miſerable deſolation it did
bring, by ſucceſſion of time vpon his poſteritie.
            Let this puniſhment,The application of the diuiſion that was in Salomons kingdome. which was laid by God on
Salomon be an example to all the Kings and Princes of
our daies, by whom God hath builded his Temple in

the ſpirituall Ieruſalem, that is to ſay, the preaching of
the true worſhip and adoration of the increated God,
that they be not by any meanes ſeduced, by the deſire
and couetouſneſſe of the riches of that falſe God,
which is made of a wafer cake, to be erected, ſet vp, and
maintained in high places, houſes, and caſtels, which
do pertaine to men of high places in the Countreies and
kingdomes where they dwell. For vndoubtedly as God
in euery place, and in all ages is like vnto himſelfe: euen
ſo ſhall he be to the end of the world, to all the
Monarches, Kings, Princes, ſoueraigne gouernours, and
to all Republicks, that doe commit ſuch an offence as
Salomon did, which came to paſſe by a diuiſion of falſe
and true religion that was ſuffered by Salomon.
            
            I pray the eternall God to extermine and aboliſh all
the remnants &amp; reliques of Idolatrie, which as yet are
excerciſed, &amp; tolerated in the high places of this Iland:
and let vs all call to God in the contrition &amp; humilitie
of our harts, that that ſame good God, who moued
his Maieſties heart to renew all theſe lawes, that ſerue
to extinguiſh all Idolatrie (which his Maieſtie doth deteſt
as much as any man liuing) would alſo mooue and
touch the hearts of all his ſubiects, who are in the high
places of the land, that they may follow the godly example
of their Soueraigne Prince and King, and that
they may put in effect the ſaying of the Poet, Regis ad
exemplum totus componitur orbis: that following the
example of their King in louing the true religion,
and hating falſe worſhip and Idolatrie: euery one of
them according to their place and eſtate, may be carefull
to purge and clenſe this whole Iland from the ſpirituall

plague, and peſtilence of Idolatrie, that doth to
much increaſe in many places of this Kingdome▪
                ſo that
if God put not to his helping hand, it is to be feared,
and there is to great appearance that this foule infection
of Idolatry ſhall extend it ſelfe vniuerſally through
the whole countrey, that it will not be contented with
the high and ſecret places: but wil come to the valleies,
townes, cities, and Churches; which without all doubt,
if it be ſuffered, will bring that miſerable, and fearefull
deſolation, whereof Chriſt doth ſpeake in our text.
            
               Satan by the diuiſion of the earthly Kingdome betwixt
Roboam and Ieroboam did practiſe a lamentable
diuiſion in the ſpirituall Kingdome of God,
               Diuiſion of kingdomes bringeth diuiſion of religion. whereby he
did eſtabliſh his kingdome of abhominable Idolatrie:
Againe we ſee that the old ſerpent hath alwaies taken
occaſion to eſtabliſh his Kingdome, (in the which is exerciſed
falſe religion) by the diuiſion of the earthlie
Kingdome: as he did in the firſt world, by the diuiſion
of the houſe and poſteritie of Adam, and as he did in
the age following, by the diuiſion of languages, lands,
Countreies, and kingdomes, as yee haue heard before.
And for this effect Satan did ſeduce Ieroboams heart,
that he might ſhew himſelfe ingrate to God, who had
beene ſo beneficiall vnto him, in making him King of
the greateſt part of his Maiſters kingdome; and to moue
him to ſuch a falling away from God, did caſt in his
heart this worldly conſideration, to witte, that if he
ſhould ſuffer his people to remaine vnited with the two
Tribes of Iudah, and Beniamin, which did appertaine
to Roboam, and ſo to continue in the exerciſe of true religion
in the temple of Ieruſalem, would be the cauſe

to reunite them, as they were before in one Kingdome.
            This wicked minde of Ieroboam did diſtract him
from God,The example of Ieroboam. and tooke away that true confidence which
he ſhould haue had in him, which was this. That as
God did foretell by his Prophets that he was to giue
him theſe ten Tribes, euen ſo he was to conſerue them,
to him and his poſteritie vpon this condition, that he
would remaine conſtant in God his true worſhip, and
Religion: out of this all Monarches &amp; Kings haue their
leſſon, who haue receaued from God this their high
preferment, that they ſhould take heede, leaſt ſuch vngodly
cogitations enter into their harts, as did into Ieroboams,
which the diuell infuſed into his hart, by lying,
and falſe imaginations: The onely true meanes of keeping,
maintaining, and preſeruing of a Kings royall
eſtate, is, to be conſtant in defending the true worſhip
of God.Dan. cap. 2. 21. Who as Daniel doth teach vs, dat regnum
cui voluerit, &amp; transfert regnum à quo voluerit, giueth
a kingdome to whom it pleaſeth him, and doth
transferre and take away kingdomes, as pleaſeth him.
            Satan in drawing men from the true Religion in diuiding,Worldly commodities cauſe of Diuiſion in Religion.
and ſeparating them from the kingdome of
God vnto the kingdome of darkneſſe, doth proceede
and worke by degrees. For firſt he drew away Ieroboam
the King from God, by his deceitfull counſell; next he
ſeduced the people of the ten Tribes by worldly and
earthly commodities, to ioyne with their King in this
apoſtaſie and falling away from God: perſwading them
that it was a great vexation of body, and chargeable
expences, and conſumption of their goods, to goe ſo
farre as vp to Ieruſalem to offer their ſacrifices, and ſo

to auoide ſuch a tedious trauell to their perſons, and
ſuch a great waſt and ſpending of their goods, he perſwaded
them, that it was better to build Temples and
Altars, and inſtitute ſacrifices at home in their owne
countries neere their owne Cities and houſes. In this
reſpect and regard of worldly commodities, there came
a lamentable diuiſion in Religion amongſt the Elect
people of God, which made the greateſt part of them,
to be Idolaters, by worſhipping of two golden calues,
which were erected by their new King, the one being
ſet vp in Bethel, &amp; the other in Dan; in the which places
they did build temples, as Ioſeph doth write; frō whence
we learne, that the diuiſion of the earthly kingdome
was the meane by the which Satan did practiſe the diuiſion
of the kingdome of God, by ſeparating the greateſt
part of this people from the true Church of God.
            After this diuiſion of the kingdome in the Elect
people of God,An example of Deſolation comming by Diuiſion. within the ſpace of 240. yeeres, there
did fall out a miſerable deſolation vpon the Iſraelites,
according to the doctrine of Chriſt in our Text. For
God raiſed vp cruell warres againſt the Iſraelites, and
in the end they were all caried away into a miſerable
captiuitie in the countrey of the Aſſyrians,
               2. King. 17. 24. and another
people of the ſaid countrey called Cuthians were planted
in their Cities, houſes, and lands.
            That this example may ſerue for our inſtruction:
Firſt let vs be thankful to God who hath vnited the people
of this Iland in the true Religion,The Vnion of language, Religion, &amp; kingdome in great Britannie. and worſhip of
the onely God, Creator of all things, excluding the
falſe adoration of things inferiour to God, or created
by God: Secondly, let vs be thankfull to God that he

hath vnited vs vnder one head and King, taking away
from vs the dangers that diuerſitie of Kings ordinarily
doth bring foorth, to wit, diuiſion of Religion, and aduancing
of Idolatrie. All theſe conſiderations ſhould
inſtigate vs, to put to our helping hands to the performance
of the Vnion of the members of this Iland, that
is, the South and the North; and for this effect, let vs beware
that the pretext of worldly commodities doe not
make any ſeparation or diuiſion amongſt vs, as we ſee
Satan did amongſt the people of Iſrael, which only fell
out for worldly reſpects. Let not the people of the
South challenge to thēſelues the great riches, &amp; fertility
of their country to be a colour, whereby they ſhould
not ioyn in vnion with the people of the North, becauſe
their riches are not ſo great, or their ſoile ſo fertill. Let
not their riches be a meane whereby they ſhould pretend
any preheminence aboue them, either in offices,
or preferments temporall, or ſpirituall, or in dignities
of honour: On the other part, let not the ſubiects of
the North deſire, or hunt after any preheminence in honour,
dignitie, offices, or preferments, either temporall,
or Eccleſiaſticall, becauſe that the King his Maieſtie,
our common head, was borne and bred, and had his
beginning in the North, or becauſe the Nobilitie of the
North may claime to haue ſome preheminence by the
antiquitie of their houſes, aboue the South. But let vs
all thinke with our ſelues, that as our head and Soueraigne
Lord is made of a bleſſed commixtion of the
bloud royall of the South and the North: Euen ſo, let
all the ſubiects of the South &amp; the North thinke themſelues
mingled together, and vnited in their head and

               King: So that all men of worth, and merit, be equally
participant of the honours, dignities, preferments, and
offices of great Britannie, according to their talents,
places, and merits, laying aſide the place of their birth,
whether it be South, or North. This equalitie is the only
meane to eſtabliſh this bleſſed worke of the Vnion in
the members, as God hath eſtabliſhed the ſame already
in the head, which will take away from amongſt vs all
ſeede of diſcord.
            The order of this matter which we haue in hand,Vnion of kingdomes in the 1. Monarchie, was the beginning of true Religion, amongst the Gentils.
doth lead vs to ſet before your eyes, that the vnited
eſtate of Kingdomes, hath beene alwaies the moſt bleſſed
and happy eſtate amongſt men, and that as well in
reſpect of worldly commodities, as in regard of the
propagation and maintenance of true Religion; which
we may eaſily gather by the Vnion of the kingdomes
of the world vnder the foure Monarchies: as on the
other part we may ſee the miſerable and fearefull eſtate
of all men, that are ſubiect to diuiſion, in the diuiſion
of the Monarchies in ſundry kingdomes, as it did fall
out, whereby the true worſhip of God and Religion
was troubled and oppreſſed, and the falſe worſhip of
Idolatrie augmented and maintained by the diuiſion
of kingdomes before vnited.
            After that the kingdome of Iudah was ouerthrowen
by Nabuchadnetzar King of the Aſſyrians, the Temple of
God deſtroyed, &amp; the whole people led into captiuitie
to Babylon, God did begin to eſtabliſh his Kingdome in
that captiuitie, and the calling of the Gentils, which
was a figure and a type of the eternall kingdome of
God, that he was to eſtabliſh by his eternall ſonne, ouer

all the nations, and people of the world. Of which
kingdome Daniel did ſpeake in the interpretation of
the Viſion of that great Image,
               Dan. 2. which did appeare to
Nabuchadnetzar, which was a repreſentation of the
mutation of all Monarchies, and Kingdomes to the end
of the world; of the which kingdomes we ſhall ſpeake
according to the order of their eſtabliſhment.
            We reade in Daniel,
               Dan. 4. 31. how Nabuchadnetzar was called
to the true Religion from the Idolatrie of the Gentils,
               The Vnion of Kingdomes in the 2. Monarchie, was a meane to call the Gentils.
by the miracles which were wrought by Daniel;
but Belthazar his ſonne, for falling away from the true
Religion, to the prophanation of the golden, and ſiluer
veſſels, that were dedicated to God his ſeruice in the
firſt Temple of Ieruſalem,
               Dan. 5. was depriued of the Monarchie.
For it was tranſlated from him to the Medes and
Perſians. We reade in Eſdras and Nehemias how Darius
and Syrus were conuerted to the true Religion,
and adoration of the only increated God, how they did
reſtore the people of God to their owne countrey, and
how they gaue great wealth and riches to build the ſecond
Temple, which was a figure of the eſtabliſhing
of Chriſt his kingdom.
            In like manner when God did tranſlate the Monarchie
from the Perſians to Alexander and his ſucceſſors,By the Vnion of kingdomes in the 3. Monarchie, true Religion eſtabliſhed.
we doe learne by the hiſtorie of Flauius Ioſephus, that
Alexander himſelfe did maintaine the Prieſthoode,
and Temple of Ieruſalem,Ioſeph. antiq. lib. 11. cap. vlt. being in his voyage to war
againſt Darius, &amp; by the way beſieging Tyrus, he gaue
a command to the high Prieſt, &amp; Senate of Ieruſalem,
that they ſhould furniſh his army with all things neceſſary
for their ſiege. But being refuſed by them, after the

winning of Tyrus, he went to Ieruſalem with an intention
to deſtroy the ſame; but when he did ſee the high
Prieſt, and his brethren clothed with their clothes dedicated
to the Sacrifice of the true God, who came to
receaue him in a peaceable manner, he did humble
himſelfe in all reuerence before the Prieſt, &amp; gaue him
all the externall adoration, which was ordinarie due to
Kings, Prieſts, &amp; Prophets, &amp; being asked of his chiefe
Captaines why he did ſo: he anſwered, that before his
expedition in warre, there was a God that did appeare
to him, clothed after the faſhion of this high Prieſt,
who did call him to the kingdome of all Aſia, and did
promiſe the ſame to him.
            This was the cauſe that mooued Alexander to enter
into the Temple of Ieruſalem,Ibidem. and Sacrifice to the
true God of Iſrael, which was a preparatiue of the
eſtabliſhing the Vniuerſall kingdome of Chriſt, by calling
all nations in the world to the true Religion, and
worſhip of the onely true God, from gentiliſme, Idolatry,
and worſhip of a multitude of falſe Gods. After his
death the Monarchy was diuided into foure parts, during
the which diuiſion of kingdomes before vnited,
the Church of God did ſuffer great troubles: Yet God
did maintaine hir for a time, by Ptolomaeus one of Alexanders
ſucceſſors, who did much good to the Iſraelites,
and was the Author of tranſlating the Bible into
the Greeke language, which was a meane to inſtruct
the Gentiles in the true knowledge of God, and of his
religion; which as I haue ſaid already, was a preparatiue
to the eſtabliſhing of Chriſt his kingdom amongſt all
the nations of the world. The diuiſion of the Monarchie,

and kingdome of the Greekes brought by ſucceſſion
of time, a miſerable deſolation, according to the
doctrine of our Text, which was a preparing before
hand of the tranſlation of the Grecian Monarchie, to
the Romanes.
            The Romane Monarchie did grow to her perfection,Chriſt himſelfe made choiſe of the vnited ſtate of the 4. Monarchie, to ioyne his vniuerſall kingdome with the kingdome of men vpon earth
in the perſon of Augustus Caeſar, and did indure
partly in perfection, partly in her decaying age, for the
ſpace of ſeauen hundreth yeeres or there about: But in
her declining age, great diuiſions did fall out by ciuill
warres, which did bring foorth a great deſolation, and
diſſolution; of the which there did riſe a multitude of
other Kings and kingdomes, according to the prophecie
of Daniel:
               Dan. 7. 7. during the perfection of this Monarchie
Chriſt did eſtabliſh his eternall kingdome, which was
the calling of all the nations of the Gentiles from
their Idolatrie foretold by the Prophet.
            Chriſt amongſt all eſtates of the world, did make
choiſe of this vnited eſtate of all kingdomes vnder one
King, &amp; Monarche to begin his ſpirituall kingdom here
amongſt men. Whereby we are taught that the onely
ſon of God did loue the condition of the Vnion of many
kings in one, as being an Image of his heauenly
kingdome, aboue all other eſtates. For the choiſe of
Chriſts birth &amp; Incarnation vnder the eſtate of Vnion,
was a propheſie of the Vnion of Chriſts vniuerſal kingdome
which was to be ioyned with the earthly Monarchie.
The beginning of the foundation of Chriſts kingdome
was in the age of a generall peace eſtabliſhed by
Auguſtus, who as we learne by the Romane hiſtories,
Toto arbe pacato Ianum cluſit. did cloſe the Temple of

               Ianus, the whole world being at peace.
            We will lay before your eyes briefly,The wonderfull bleſſing of God ſhewed on great Britannie, in the Vnion of religion, and all the kingdoms thereof, in a Monarchie, in the perſon of a Britain Emperour. the eſtate, and
progreſſe of this bleſſed vnion of the worldly Monarchie,
with the ſpirituall kingdome of God, and ſhew
you alſo what a great benefit God hath powred foorth
vpon this Iland of great Brittannie, in chooſing it to be
the holy place, wherein this admirable vnion of God
and man is conioined in the perſon of a Britaine King,
vniting the temporall and ſpirituall Monarchie in one.
We are taught by Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories and others,
that Chriſt Ieſus the eternall ſon of his eternall father,
after his crucifying, and aſcenſion by ſending of his Apoſtles
through the world, did propagate the true religion
and adoration of the increated God in the whole
Romane Monarchie for the ſpace of fiftie yeares: But
Satan who was, and as yet is, a vigilant watchman, a
carefull ſearcher, and a buſie Biſhop did not forget his
diuelliſh attempts. For knowing that the preaching of
the Euangell would deſtroy his Temple, which was
full of Gentilique Idolatrie,Euſeb. in Eccleſ. hiſt. he did raiſe vp Nero, &amp; many
of his ſucceſſors,Sulp. Seuer. &amp; alij. to excerciſe many bloody and cruell
perſecutions againſt Chriſts owne Apoſtles and
Diſciples, for the ſpace of three hundred yeares or therabout.
Hoping by ſuch cruell murdering of Gods holy
Saints to aboliſh the true adoration and religion of
Chriſt, and to maintaine the temples of his Idols and
falſe Gods. But that is true, which antiquitie doth
ſay, Sanguis Martyrum eſt ſemen Euangelij. The blood
of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Goſpell. So that in
this caſe Satan was fruſtrated of his wicked expectation
that he had to deſtroy the true religion by the ſhedding

of the pretious blood, euen as he was deceiued when
he ſeduced the people of the Iewes to crucify the Lord
of glory. For if Satan had knowen, that the crucifying
of Chriſt Ieſus, and the ſhedding of the bloud of that
immaculat Lambe ſhould tend to the ſaluation of mankind,
and of his revnion with God, he would not then
haue inſtigated the Iewes to crucifie the Lord of glory;
and if he had knowen that the bloudſhed of ſo manie
holie Martyrs which were killed, for the ſpace of three
hundred yeeres after Chriſt, by the Romane Emperors,
and their lieutenants; if he had imagined, that all theſe
things did more eſtabliſh, and confirme Chriſts Goſpell,
then they did hinder the paſſage thereof, he would
haue left of to haue procured ſo many perſecutions againſt
the Chriſtians.
            All theſe perſecutions being ended,God did vnite great Britaine in one kingdome, and one true religion by the mariage of Conſtantius Chlorus, and Helena. God did conciliat
a marriage, betwixt Conſtantius Chlorus, (who had to
his part of the Romane Monarchie, Germanie, France,
Spaine, and great Brittaine) and Helena daughter to
Coilus or Coelus, who was King ouer that part of Brittaine,
that did reſiſt the Romans; by the which mariage
Conſtantinus Magnus their ſonne was borne in this Iland,
who after the death of his father that died at
Yorke,Euſeb, in vit. Conſt. &amp; Bal. cent. did enter into the full poſſeſſion of this Iland of
great Brittannie,Eutrop. lib. 9. Gallic. in Panig. and ſo it was wholy vnited in his perſon,
where he did eſtabliſh the true Chriſtian religion
and the true worſhip of the onely vncreated God.
From thence he did take his iourney by Fraunce, to
Rome, where he ouerthrew in battell Maxentius that
great perſecutor of the Chriſtians. And hauing eſtabliſhed
there, and in the whole occident the kingdome

of Chriſt, he went to the Orient, where he did likewiſe
ouerthrow in battel Licinius;
               Euſeb. lib. de vita Conſtantini. the which Licinius after
he had been long a Chriſtian did returne to gentiliſme,
and became a perſecutor;Balaeus. And ſo by all theſe victories
this Britaine King became Emperour, King, and Monarche
of the whole world, who did make Lawes for
the aboliſhing of Gentiliſme, and eſtabliſhing of Chriſtian
Religion.
            We doe learne by this hiſtorie, how the propheticall
ſignification of the name Britannia, was fulfilled in
Conſtantinus daies, in whoſe perſon, both the temporall
kingdome of the whole world, and the ſpirituall kingdome
of the true Religion of God, was vnited. Of this
we collect, that the reſtoring of this auncient and glorious
name of Great Britannie into one kingdome, vnder
our newe Conſtantinus, is to be embraced by all men
with great congratulation and gladneſſe.
            Secondly,The Vnion of great Britannie in one kingdome, and one true Religion, by the meanes of a ſecond mariage. we doe learne of this hiſtorie, that as
God did firſt procure the bleſſed Vnion of this Iland,
by the mariage of Conſtantius, and Helena; Euen ſo,
that ſame good God, who is euer like himſelfe, did
bring foorth three moſt happy Vnions within theſe
hundred yeeres, or there about, by a mariage betwixt
King Henry the ſeauenth, and Queene Elizabeth heire
of Yorke. The firſt Vnion was of the two houſes of
Lancaſter, and Yorke; the ſecond Vnion did conſiſt in
the vniting of all the people of this Iland in the true
Religion and worſhip of God, and aboliſhing of Gentiliſme,
which was brought in vnder the pretence of
Chriſtian Religion; the third vnion was the vniting of
England, and Scotland together in the perſon of our

gratious Soueraigne, who is deſcended Lineally from
King Henry the ſeauenth. For it is notoriouſly knowen
that by that happie mariage of King Henry the ſeuenth,
heire of Lancaſter, and Elizabeth heire of Yorke, the
cruell wars which were for many yeeres, betwixt theſe
two houſes, were extinguiſhed; and the Vnion in their
royall progeny eſtabliſhed: out of which mariage came
King Henry the eight, (who did begin to aboliſh Idolatrie
in this Iland,) King Edward the ſixt who did eſtabliſh
true Religion, and Queene Elizabeth of happie
memory, who did embrace all the daies of her life the
true auncient Chriſtian Religion: vnto whom lineally
our Kings Maieſtie ſucceeded, in whoſe Royall perſon
is made the revnion of this Iland in one kingdome,
as it was before in Conſtantinus Magnus daies.
            Let vs all then call to memorie three great bleſſings,Three bleſſings vpon Great Britanny aboue all other nations, which doe come by meanes of Vnion.
which God hath powred foorth vpon vs. The firſt is a
publike embracing of Chriſtian Religion, begun by
King Lucius and all his people, and aboliſhing of Gentiliſme,
and Idolatrie, wherein God did preferre this
Iland before all the nations of the world. The ſecond
bleſſing is, that God raiſed vp in this Iland Conſtantinus
Magnus a Britaine Emperour, in whoſe raigne
God did vnite the earthly kingdome with the ſpirituall.
The third bleſſing is this laſt admirable Vnion of
the South and the North in one kingdome, vnder one
King and gouernour, in the true Religion and worſhip
of God, by the which Vnion this Iland is in the moſt
happy eſtate of all the kingdomes of the world. God
giue vs all thankefull harts to acknowledge the ſame.
            I will entreate all the ſubiects of Great Britaine, to

lay before their eyes, the bleſſed eſtate of the Vnion of
this Iland, in one language, one true Religion, and in
one temporall kingdome: And on the other part, looke
what was the miſerable and lamentable eſtate of this
Iland, during the ſpace that it was diuided into many
earthly kingdomes, and holding vnder the ſpirituall
captiuitie of the Idolatrie of ſpirituall Babylon. And
for this cauſe remember the hiſtory of the diuiſion, and
ciuill warres of the Romane Monarchie, how they did
draw their ſouldiers and warriours out of this Iland,
and marke, at that ſame time, what a deſolate and miſerable
eſtate both the ſpirituall and temporall kingdome
did fall into. For the North Britaines did riſe
vp in warre againſt the South Britaines, who for their
aide and helpe had refuge to the Saxons, who did profeſſe
Gentiliſme and Paganiſme.
            But the Saxons hauing deliuered the South Britaines
from the oppreſſion of the North,
               The miſeries and calamities that did fall out in Britannie by the diuiſion thereof into ſundry kingdomes. did thruſt out the
Southerne people out of their poſſeſſions, lands, houſes,
and Countrey: ſo that a great number of them, did flie
into little Britannie in France, and the remnant went to
the Weſterne part called Wales. I might ſhew you alſo
how that the South was deuided into ſeauen Kingdomes,Bed. Hiſt. Ang. lib. 1. cap. 15.
at what time there were moſt cruell warres exerciſed
amongſt themſelues: how that afterward they
were afflicted by the Danes, and how during the diuiſion
of kingdomes in all theſe ages, all learning, all
true Religion, and all pietie was baniſhed, yea almoſt
extinguiſhed: and by the contrary, all barbaritie by violence
and bloodſhed, all Gentiliſme, and Idolatrie did
abound; I might ſhew you, how all theſe things did

raigne in this Iland during the deuided eſtate of this
kingdome, but time will not ſuffer me.
            Let the conſideration of felicitie,An exhortation to the performance of this happy Vnion. (which doth flow
from Vnion) on the one ſide; of miſery and calamitie
(which doth come by diuiſion,) on the other ſide,
worke mightily in the harts of all theſe, whom God and
his Lieutenant hath choſen at this time, out of the
South and North, to entreate of this Vnion whereof I
haue now ſpoken. And that they may learne what a
dangerous thing it is, to leaue any little ſeede of any
former diuiſion; we are to take heede of Satans lying
deceptions, who is a buſie watchman ſeeking by all
meanes to throw in ſome ſeede of diuiſion amongſt
men, to hinder &amp; ſtay the good worke of God; as mens
particular commodities, &amp; preferments, which are not
of ſuch waight or importance in reſpect of this happie
Vnion: Therefore, Tollantur à nobis nomina diuiſionis,
Let all the names of diuiſion or diſcord be taken from
amongſt vs. Let vs alſo learne by theſe hiſtories of the
Vnion, and diuiſion of kingdomes, a very ſure rule (as
I ſhewed you a little before) that the diuiſion of countries
in diuerſe kingdomes doth come from the head
Gouernours, who by deuiding of one kingdome made
many kingdomes, as we ſee in the firſt diuiſion of the
world, and ſpecially in the diuiſion of the kingdome
of the Iſraelites; In the third Monarchie of the Greekes
amongſt the foure ſucceſſours of Alexander; In the
diſſolution of the Romane Empire into the Orient and
the Occident: In the ſubdiuiſion of the kingdome of
Carolus Magnus, in the Occident; In the ſubdiuiſion of
Spaine, into many kingdomes. In the diuiſion of this

               Iland, into many kingdomes. So that the cauſe of diuiſion
ceaſing by the Vnion of kingdomes, the people
was vnited ipſo iure &amp; ipſo facto, as Fraunce was
(during the firſt race of Kings called Meroninges) deuided
amongſt foure brethren into foure Kingdomes:
but ſo ſoone as all thoſe foure fell in one Kings hands,
they were all vnited ipso facto, in one, ratione capitis,
by reaſon of their head. Likewiſe, we haue an example
in Spaine, and in South Britannie, when the ſeauen
kingdomes did fall in one Princes gouernment,
they were all ſeauen vnited ipſo facto, ratione capitis,
by reaſon of the head: Euen ſo, pari iure the South
and North, being vnited vnder one King, it followeth
neceſſarily that the Kingdomes are vnited amongſt
themſelues: ſo that by the Law of God and man our
Great Britannie is no more two kingdomes, but one
onely; He that oppoſeth himſelfe againſt this holy
Vnion, doth offend his God, make little regard of his
Prince and King, and hurteth the welfare and happy
ſtate of this whole Iland.
            Let all men remember by the foreſaid examples,
that the Vnion of kingdomes hath beene alwaies the
furtherance and ſtanding of true Religion; but diuiſion
of kingdomes hath beene the ouerthrow of true
Religion, and aduancing of Idolatrie; let all thoſe that
loue God, perſeuerance in true Religion, proſperitie
of their naturall King, and ſtanding of the Commonwealth
of this Iland, (which is the common mother of
vs all) be carefull of the performance of Gods worke,
and put to their helping hand for the furtherance thereof.
And let all reaſonable and godly men conſider, how

God on his part hath taken away from vs, all the cauſes
of diuiſion, as diuerſitie of Language, Religion, Gouernours,
and Kings, and hath vnited vs in one Language,
in one Religion, and vnder one head and King.
If we then caſt in any lets or impediments on our ſide;
or if we inuent any new ſubiect of diuiſion betwixt the
South and the North, we ſhall be like vnto thoſe that
doe diuide, teare, and cut in peeces their owne bowels,
deuoure their owne children, and put fire in their owne
houſes.
            Let all men therefore examine their owne harts and
minds,The Concluſion. whether they feele any inward motion within
them to further and aduance this good woorke. If they
doe, let them beleeue certainly, that ſuch a motion doth
come from God; and by the contrary, if any man find
any euill motion in his hart that tendeth to the hinderance
of this good worke, let him beleeue that this motion
commeth by the Diuels ſuggeſtion. Let vs all pray
to God as well in our priuate houſes, as in our publike
aſſemblies, that God would performe this his owne
worke, wherein doth conſiſt the eſtabliſhing of his true
worſhip and Religion in this Iland, and the extinguiſhing
of all falſe Idolatrie; Let vs auoyde all euill motions,
inuentions of men, impediments or hinderance
whatſoeuer that Satan may caſt in mens minds to trouble
this his holy worke, to ſtay the building of Gods
houſe; let all men be aſſured that God will powre
downe his bleſſings vpon all thoſe, that ſhall further
this worke, and will ſend his curſe and puniſhment
on all them and their poſteritie that ſhall let or
ſtay the progreſſe of the ſame holy Vnion. We will

ende here, praying all in the vnitie of our harts and
ſoules, that the eternall Vnion of all the ſubiects harts
in this Ilan
                     •
                  
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                be an Image of the Vnion of Chriſts
Elect members in hi
                  •
                their head, who is the fountaine
of all 
                  〈…〉
                with the Father in the Vnion
of the 
                  〈…〉
               , three perſons in one Deitie, be
all hon
                  •••
                praise, and glory, now and for
euer, Amen. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
            
         
      
   

