
   
      
         
            A good speed to Virginia
            Gray, Robert, 16th/17th cent.
         
         
            
               1609
            
         
         Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02059
            STC 12204
            ESTC S105839
            99841565
            99841565
            6158
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02059)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6158)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 725:20)
         
         
            
               
                  A good speed to Virginia
                  Gray, Robert, 16th/17th cent.
               
               [32] p.   
               
                  Printed by Felix Kyngston for VVilliam Welbie, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Greyhound in Pauls Churchyard,
                  London :
                  1609.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: R.G., i.e. Robert Gray.
                  Signatures: A-D⁴.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Virginia --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-12
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-12
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A GOOD SPEED to Virginia.
            ESAY 42. 4.
            He ſhall not faile nor be diſcouraged till he haue ſet iudgement in the earth, and the Jles ſhall wait for his law.
            
               LONDON Printed by FELIX KYNGSTON for VVilliam Welbie, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Greyhound in Pauls Churchyard. 1609.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT NOBLE AND HONORABLE EARLES, BARONS and Lords, and to the Right Worſhipfull Knights, Merchants and Gentlemen, Aduenturers for the plantation of Virginea, all happie and proſperous ſucceſſe, which may either augment your glorie, or increaſe your wealth, or purchaſe your eternitie.
            
               TIme the deuourer of his own brood conſumes both man and his memorie. It is not braſſe nor marble that can perpetuate immortalitie of name vpon the earth. Many in the world haue erected faire and goodly monuments, whoſe memorie together with their monuments is long ſince defaced and periſhed. The name, memorie and actions of thoſe men doe only liue in the records of eternitie,

which haue emploied their beſt endeuours in ſuch vertuous and honourable enterpriſes, as haue aduanced the glorie of God, and inlarged the glorie and wealth of their countrie. It is not the houſe of Salomon, called the Forreſt of Lebanon, that continues his name and memorie vpon the earth at this day, but his wiſedome, iuſtice, magnificence and power, yet doe and for euer ſhall eternize him. A right ſure foundation therefore haue you (my Lords and the reſt of the moſt worthie Aduenturers for 
                  Ʋirginia) laid for the immortalitie of your names and memory, which, for the aduancement of Gods glorie, the renowne of his Maieſtie, and the good of your Countrie, haue vndertaken ſo honorable a proiect, as all poſterities ſhal bleſſe you, and vphold your names and memories ſo long as the Sunne and Moone endureth: whereas they which preferre their money before vertue, their pleaſure before honour, and their ſenſuall ſecuritie before heroical! aduentures, ſhall periſh with their money, die with their pleaſures, and be buried in euerlaſting

forgetfulnes. The diſpoſer of al humane actions diſpoſe your purpoſes, bleſſe your Nauie as hee did the ſhips of Salomon which went to Ophie, and brought him home in one yeere ſix hundred threeſcore and ſix talents of gold. The preſeruer of al men preſerue your perſons from all perils both by ſea and land; make your goings out like an hoſt of men triumphing for the victorie, and your commings in like an armie diuiding the ſpoile. And as God hath made you inſtruments for the inlarging of his Church militant heere vpon earth; ſo when the period of your life ſhall be finiſhed, the ſame God make you members of his Church triumphant in Heauen.
            Amen.
            
               From mine houſe at the Northend of Sithes lane London, April 28. Anno 1609.
               
               Your Honours and Worſhips in all affectionate well wiſhing,
R. G.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            GOOD SPEEDE TO Virginia.
            
               Ioſuah. 17. 14.
               
                  Then the children of Ioſeph ſpake vnto Ioſhua, ſaying, why haſt thou giuē me but one lot, and one portion to inherite, ſeeing I am a great people?
                  Ioſhua then anſwered, if thou beeſt much people, get thee vp to the wood, and cut trees for thy ſelfe in the land of the Perizzites, &amp; of the Giants, if mount Ephraim be too narrow for thee.
                  Then the children of Ioſeph ſaid, the Mountaine will not be inough for vs, and all the Canaanites that dwell in the low countrey, haue Charcts of Iron as well as they in Bethſhean, and in the townes of the ſame, as they in the valley of Iſrael.
                  And Ioſhua ſpake vnto the houſe of Ioſeph, to Ephraim, and Manaſſes, ſaying, Thou art a great people, and haſt great power, and ſhalt not haue one lot.
                  Therefore the Mountain ſhal be thine, for it is a wood, and thou ſhalt cut it downe, and the endes of it ſhall be thine, &amp; thou ſhalt caſt out the Canaanites thogh they haue Iron Charets, and though they be ſtrong.
               
            
            
               THe heauens ſaith Dauid, euen the heauens are the Lords, &amp; ſo is the earth, but he hath giuen it to the children of men. Pſa. 113. 16. Yet notwithſtāding the fatherly prouidēce, &amp; large bountie of God towards man, ſo improuident and irreſpectiue is man, that he had rather liue like a drone, and féede vppon the fruites of other mens labors, wherunto God hath not entituled him, then looke

out and flie abroad, like the Bée to gather the pleaſures and riches of the earth, which God hath giuen him to enioy: whece vpon it comes to paſſe, that although the Lord hath giuen the earth to the children of men, yet this earth which is mans fee-ſimple by deede of gift frō God, is the greater part of it poſſeſſed &amp; wrongfully vſurped by wild beaſts, and vnreaſonable creatures, or by brutiſh ſauages, which by reaſon of their godles ignorance, &amp; blaſphemous Idolatrie, are worſe then thoſe beaſts which are of moſt wilde &amp; ſauage nature. As Ahab therfore ſometimes ſaid to his ſeruants, 1. King. 22. 13. Know ye not that Ramoth Gilead was ours, and we ſtay &amp; take it not out of the hands of the King of Aram? So may man ſay to himſelfe: The earth was mine, God gaue it me, and my poſteritie, by the name of the children of men, and yet I ſtay &amp; take it not out of the hands of beaſts, and brutiſh ſauages, which haue no intereſt in it, becauſe they participate rather of the nature of beaſts then men.
            The Chriſtian part of the world did plainly bewray this improuident and irreſpectiue neglect of Gods prouidence and bountie. When Chriſtopher Columbus made proffer to the Kings of England, Portugall, and Spaine, to inueſt them with the moſt precious and richeſt veynes of the whole earth, neuer knowne before: but this offer was not onely reiected, but the man himſelf, who deſerues euer to be renowned, was (of vs Engliſh eſpecially) ſcorned &amp; accoūted for an idle Nouelliſt. Some thinke it was becauſe of his poore apparell, and ſimple lookes, but ſurely it is rather to be imputed to the improuidency &amp; imprudencie of our Nation, which hath alwayes bred ſuch diffidence in vs, that we cōceit no new report, bee it neuer ſo likely, nor beléeue any thing be it neuer ſo probable, before we ſée the effects. This hath alwayes béene reported of the Engliſh, by

thoſe that haue obſerued the nature of nations: Bodin. lib. 5. de Repub. cap. 1. reporteth, that the Engliſh were alwayes accounted more warlike, valorous, and couragious, then the French, but the French went alwayes beyond them in prudence, and pollicie. And to expreſſe the ſame, he vſeth the words of Ennius. Bellipotentes ſunt magis quam ſapients potentes. And it may be that this might be reported of vs Engliſh, in thoſe times when our Country was not peſteced with multitude, nor ouercharged with ſwarmes of people, for peace and plentie breed ſecuritie in men: neither is it neceſſarie for anie man to beléeue reports, though probable, nor to follow ſtrange proiects be they neuer ſo likely, ſo long as he hath home inbred hopes to relie vpon, and aſſured certainties to ſatiſfie his future expectation.
            In thoſe dayes this Kingdome was not ſo populous as now it is, Ciuell warres at home, and forreine wars abroad, did cut off the ouer-ſpreading branches of our people. Our coūtry thē yéelded vnto all that were in it a ſurpluſſage of all neceſſities: it yeelded preferment in due correſpondencie, for al degrees &amp; ſorts of men. The commons of our Country lay free and open for the poore Commons to inioy, for there was roome enough in the land for euery man, ſo that no mā néeded to encroch or incloſe from another, whereby it is manifeſt, that in thoſe dayes we had no great néed to follow ſtrange reports, or to ſeeke wilde aduentures, for ſéeing we had not onely ſufficiencie, but an ouerflowing meaſure proportioned to euerie man. Religion and pietie taught vs, that ſéeing our lot was fallen vnto vs in a faire ground, and that we had a goodly heritage, rather to be content with our own, then either politikèly or ambitiouſly to vndertake vncouth enterpriſes, vnto which neceſſitie did no way vrge vs.
            
               
But nowe God hath proſpered vs with the bleſſings of the wombe, &amp; with the bleſſings of the breſts, the ſword deuoureth not abroad, neither is there any feare in our ſtreets at home; ſo that we are now for multitude as the thouſand of Manaſſes, and as the ten thouſads of Ephraim, the Prince of peace hath ioyned the wood of Iſrael and Iudah in one troe. And therefore we may iuſtly ſay, as the children of Iſrael ſay here to Ioſhua, we are a great people, and the lande is too narrow for vs: ſo that whatſoeuer we haue béene, now it behooues vs to be both prudent and politicke, and not to deride and reiect good profers of profitable and gainefull expectation, but rather to imbrace euery occaſion which hath any probabilitie in it of future hopes: And ſeeing there is neither preferment nor employment for all within the liſts of our countrey, we might iuſtly be accounted as in former times, both imprudent and improuident, if we will yet ſit with our armes foulded in our boſomes, and not rather ſéeke after ſuch aduentures whereby the glory of God may be aduanced, the territories of our kingdome inlarged, our people both preferred and employed abroad, our wants ſupplyed at home, his Maieſties cuſtomes wonderfully augmented, and the honour and renown of our Nation ſpred and propagated to the ends of the world. Many examples might be produced to mooue vs hereunto, but becauſe they were the practiſes of rude and barharous people, they are no exemplarie preſidents for chriſtians: but foraſmuch as euery example approued in the ſcripture, is a precept, I thought good to handle this conference betwéene the tribe of Ioſeph a family in the Iſrael of God, &amp; Ioſhua a faithfull and godly Prince ouer the whole commonwealth of Gods Iſrael: which to my ſéeming, is much like that plot which we haue now in hand for Virginia; for here the

people of Ephraim and of the halfe tribe of Manaſſes, are a great people, and ſo are we: and by reaſon of the multitude of their people, the land is too narrow for them; and ſo ſtands our caſe, whereupon they repaire to 
                  〈◊〉
                to haue his warrant and direction to inlarge their 
                  •••
               oers, and ſo haue many of our Noble men of honorable minds, worthy knights, rich marchants, &amp; diuerſe other of the beſt diſpoſitiō, ſolicited our Ioſhua, and mightie Monarch, that moſt religious &amp; renowned King Iames, that by his Maieſties leaue, they might vndertake the plantation of Virginia. Laſtly, as Ioſhua not onely giues leaue, but alſo a bleſſing to the childrē of Ioſeph in their enterpriſes, ſo hath our gratious Soueraigne granted his frée Charter to our people, for ye vndertaking of their intended enterpriſe and aduenture, ſo that from this example, there is both ſufficient warrant for our King to graunt his chacter for the plantation of Virginia, and ſufficient warrant alſo for our people to vndertake the ſame. And therefore for the better ſatiſfying of ſome, and for the encoraging of all fortes of people concerning this proiect for Virginia, let vs more fully examine the particulars of this diſcourſe betweene the children of Ioſeph and Ioſhua. Firſt we gather from the text, that the cauſe why the children of Ioſeph deſired to inlarge their borders, was the multitude and greatneſſe whereunto they were growne. God had bleſſed them according to the propheſie of Iacob, Gen. 48. 19. So yt the portion which was firſt thought to be roomie and large inough for them, is now too narrowe and little for them. What ſhould they do in this caſe? ſhould they prouide and eſtabliſh lawes to hinder the increaſe of their people, as we reade of Hyppodamus, ſometimes a law-giuer among ye Mileſ
                  •
               ans; whoſe example in gouernmēt, Ariſtotle in his 7. booke of Politicks and 16. chapter, and

Plato in his 
                  •
               . booke Delegibus, haue drawne into precept and rule of policie? ſhould they decree againſt building and execting houſes, luniting a certaine number and no more for euery familie in their tribe, as P
                     ••
                  do amongſt the Corinthians ſometimes did, and 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  ••
               ey of Paris of late enacted, taking order that old an
                  •
                anciēt houſes ſhould be repayred, but no new edifices erected. Anno. 1548? ſhould they haue peſtered themſelues with Inmates, and one houſhold haue receiued into it two or three families? They put none of theſe in practiſe, but with one conſent they repaire to the Magiſtrate, they complaine that their lot is not large inough, &amp; theyſhew the reaſon, becauſe they are a great people.
            There is nothing more daungerous for the eſtate of common-wealths, then when the people do increaſe to a greater multitude and number then may inſtly paralell with the largeneſſe of the place and countrey: for hereupon comes oppreſſion, and diuerſe kinde of wrongs, mutinies, ſedition, commotion, &amp; rebellion, ſcarcitie, dearth, pouertie, and ſundrie ſorts of calamities, which either bréed the cōuerſion, or euerſion, of cities and common-wealths. For euen as bloud though it be the beſt humour in the body, yet if it abound in greater quantitie then the ſtate of the body will beare, doth indanger the bodie, &amp; oftentimes deſtroyes it: ſo although the honour of the king be in the multitude of people, Pro. 14. 28. yet when this multitude of people increaſeth to ouer great a number, the common-wealth ſtands ſubiect to many perillous inconueniences, for which cauſe many Natiōs perceyuing their people to increaſe aboue a due and proportionable number, they haue ſent their ouerflowing multitudes abroad into other countreyes and prouinces, to the ends they might preſerue their owne in greater peace and proſperitie: ſo we ſee ye huſbandman deale with his groūds

when they are ouercharged with cattell, he remooues them from one ground to another, and ſo he prouideth 
                  •
               ell both for his cattel and for his ground: and ſo doth the maiſter of the bée-garden, when he ſoes a hiue peſteted with multitudes of bées, he driues ye hiue, &amp; ſo reapeth 
                  •
                greater gaine by his ware and honie.
            And herupon many ſtateſ-men haue thought nothing more profitable for populous common-wealths, then to haue forreigne and externe warres, to the ende that thereby the ſuperfluous braunches might be cut off. This was the cauſe why Scipio when he had conquered Carthage, would not haue it vtterly ruinated, leaſt ſaith he, the Romains hauing no warres abroad, mooue ciuill warres amongſt themſelues at home: others ſéeing the multitude of their people increaſe, haue planted Colonies with them, others haue baniſhed them into remote countries: and the children of Ioſeph here being peſtered with multitude come to Ioſhua to be directed and relieued. This ſhould teach vs of this kingdome and countrey, prudence and prouidence, the Lord hath bleſſed vs, and we are growne to be a great people, ſo that one lot is not ſufficient for vs: Our multitudes like too much bloud in the body, infect our countrey with plague and pouertie, our land hath brought foorth, but it hath not milke ſufficient in the breaſt thereof to nouriſh all thoſe children which it hath brought forth, it affordeth neither employment nor preferment for thoſe that depend vpon it: And hereupon it is, that many ſeruiceable men giue themſelues to lewd courſes, as to robbing by the high way, theft, &amp; coſoning, ſharking vpon the land, piracie vpon the Sea, and ſo are cut off by ſhamefull and vntimely death: others liue prophanely, riotouſly, and idely, to the great diſhonour of Almightie God, the detriment of the commonwealth. Now our caſe ſtanding

thus it behooueth euerie one to deuiſe a remedie for this miſery: When there was no bread in Chanaā, Iacob and his familie ſought into Egypt for corne to relieue themſelues. And Iacob ſéeing his ſonnes deſtitute of counſel in that extremity, did ſharply reprehēd them for ye diſſolute managing of their preſent ſtate, ſaying: Why gaze ye one vpo another? Behold, I haue heard there is food in Egypt, get ye down thither, and buy vs food thence, that we may liue. Euen ſo may it be ſaid to a companie of people in this land, which doe nothing but gaze one vpon another, deſtitute of counſell, aduiſe, and meanes, how to prouide iuſtly and honeſtly for their maintenaunce. They heare of honourable proiects abroade, they heare of employment and preſerment, they heare of plentie and abundance of many good things, of which a fruitful country largely makes offer vnto them: they heare of gaine and profite both to them and their poſteritie, they heare many honourable men, many worthie wiſe men, many valiaunt and couragious men, many rich and wealthie men, aduenture their perſons, their mony, their ſhips, towards the accompliſhing of ſo godly and memorable a dſigne, and yet they ſit ſtill folowing their intemperauncie, incontinencie, and other their luxurious and riotous courſes, to the high diſhonour of almightie God, to the great hurt of the common-wealth, and to their own euerlaſting ſhame and ignomie. If an honourable death were ſet before a vertuous minde, it would chuſe rather to die heroically, then liue opprobriouſly. What then ſhall we thinke of thoſe perſons, who hauing an honourable life ſet before them, doe yet chuſe rather to liue in idleneſſe, diſhoneſtie &amp; obſcenitie? ſurely they are of degenerate and dunghill minder, neither are they worthy to be nouriſhed in the boſome of a wel gouerned common-wealth. It was for euer a

blemiſh to the honour and credit of Vliſſes, becauſe hée feigned himſelfe mad, and ſowed ſalt in ſreed of corne in his field, onely that by ſuch a ſhift he might kéepe himſelfe at home, and not go with the Grecians to the ſiege of Troy. So let perpetuall ſhame and diſhonour attend vpon all thoſe, which doting vpon their wealth, or ſuffeting vpon their pleaſures, finde delaies and deuiſe ſhifts, either to ſaue their purſes, or their perſons, from ſuch honourable and profitable deſignments, as offer probable likelyhoods of future good to this our countrey or common-wealth.
            Thus we haue heard the dutie of the people which is prudently and prouidently to conſult with the magiſtrates, concerning the diſburdening, and diſcharging of ſuch vnneceſſarie multitudes as peſter a commonwealth, and alſo to further ſuch enterpriſes either with their purſes or their perſons as make to the ſame ende. Now yt in next place, we are to note the direction of Ioſua, vpon the aforeſaide complaint of the children of Ioſeph, which is to enlarge their territories, and dilate their borders, by deſtroying Gods enemies the Perizzites, and Giants, which inhabited the valleyes, bordering vpon mount Ephraim, which were moſt abominable Idolaters, and had no knowledge of the true and onely God: from whence we may learne, how odious thoſe people are, in the ſight of God, which hauing no knowledge of him and his worſhip, giue that honour to the inſenſible and vnreaſonable creature, which is onely due to the omnipotent and almightie Creator. For this cauſe hath almightie God, ouerthrowne the mightieſt Monarchies in the world, for this cauſe did hée diſperſe his owne Iſrael among the Nations, &amp; neuer vouchſafed them to returne againe into their owne land. Dauid by way of prophecie, doth promiſe a bleſſing to thoſe

that ſhall take the children of the Idolatrous Babilonians and daſh them againſt the ſtones, and they that haue taken armes againſt ſuch people, are ſaid to fight the Lords battells. Saul had his kingdome rent from him and his poſteritie, becauſe he ſpared Agag, that Idolatrous king of the Amalechites, whom God would not haue ſpared: ſo acceptable a ſeruice is it to deſtroy Idolaters whom God hateth, but foraſmuch as God doth not delight in bloud, but rather that a ſinner ſhould conuert and liue, agréeable vnto which, is that ſpeech of our Sauiour Chriſt in the Goſpell, There is ioy in heauen ouer one ſinner that repenteth. It is far more commendable, and out of doubt more acceptable vnto God, to reclaime an Idolater, vnles we haue a ſpeciall commaundement of God to the contrarie, as Saul had then to deſtroy him, to win him to the faith, then to depriue him of life, and to bring him to the knowledge of God, &amp; whom he hath ſent Chriſt Ieſus: rather then to kill them in their ignorance, and ſo to bring them into daunger both of bodie and ſoule, for they that turne many vnto righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres for euermore. Dan. 12. 3. Paul calls thoſe whom he had won to the faith of Chriſt, his crowne, his ioy, his glorie. 1. Theſſa. 2. 19. 20. As though they were the matter of his ioy, of his crowne, and of his glorie. Happie therefore is he that hath an hand in turning any vnto God. And he that will finde delaie whereby ſo gratious a worke may be hindered, is not with God, but againſt God, for aſmuch as he hinders the building vp of the kingdome of God.
            And ſurely ſo deſirous is man of ciuill ſocietie by nature, that he eaſily yéelds to diſcipline and gouernment,

if he ſée any reaſonable motiue to induce him to the ſame. For we reade of certaine people in Affrica, inhabiting the mountaine Magnan, which offentimes do conſtraine ſtraungers which trauell that way, to take the gouernment of them, and to impoſe lawes vnto them, whereby they may be iuſtly and orderly gouerned: and many Nations willingly ſubmitted themſelues to the ſubiection of the Romanes, being allured thereunto by Iuſtice, equitie, clemencie, and vpright dealing of the Romaine captaines: for it is not the nature of men, but the education of men, which make them barbarous and vnciuill, and therefore chaunge the education of men, and you ſhall ſée that their nature will be greatly rectified and corrected: ſéeing therefore men by nature ſo eaſily yéelde to diſcipline and gouernment vpon any reaſonable ſhewe of bettering their fortunes, it is euerie mans dutie to trauell both by ſea and land, and to venture either with his perſon or with his purſe, to bring the barbarous and ſauage people to a ciuill and Chriſtian kinde of gouernment, vnder which they may learne how to liue holily, iuſtly, and ſoberly in this world, and to apprehend the meanes to ſaue their ſoules in the world to come, rather then to deſtroy them, or vtterly to roote them out: for a wiſe man, but much more a Chrtſtian, ought to trie all meanes before they vndertake warre: di
               
                  •
               aſtation and depopulation ought to be the laſt thing which Chriſtians ſhould put in practiſe, yet foraſmuch as euerie example in the ſcripture as I ſaide is a precept, we are warranted by this direction of Ioſhua, to deſtroy wilfull and conuicted Idolaters, rather then to let them liue, if by no other meanes they can be reclaimed.
            
               
The report goeth, that in Virginia the people are ſauage and incredibly rude, they worſhip the diuell, offer their young children in ſacrifice vnto him, wander vp and downe like beaſts, and in manners and conditions, differ very litle from beaſts, hauing no Art, nor ſciēce, nor trade, to imploy themſelues, or giue themſelues vnto, yet by nature louing and, gentle, and deſirous to imbrace a better condition. Oh how happy were that man which could reduce this people from brutiſhnes, to ciuilitie, to religion, to Chriſtianitie, to the ſauing of their ſoules: happy is that man and bleſt of God, whom God hath endued, either with meanes or will to attempt this buſines, but farre be it from the nature of the Engliſh, to exerciſe any bloudie crueltie amongſt theſe people: farre be it from the hearts of the Engliſh, to giue them occaſion, that the holy name of God, ſhould be diſhonoured among the Infidels, or that in the plantation of that continent, they ſhould giue any cauſe to the world, to ſay that they ſought the wealth of that countrie aboue or before the glorie of God, and the propagation of his kingdome. I remember the practiſe of Chriſtopher Collombus, which he vſed amongſt the weſt Indians, to perſwade them to receiue his Spaniardes to ſocietie and commerce, which was, he obſerued that they were ſuperſtitiouſly giuen to worſhip the Moone, &amp; by the ſkill he had in Aſtronomie, he foreſaw that within thrée daies the Moone ſhould be eclipſed: wherupon he called them together, and told them, that he had often vſed his beſt meanes, to bring them to a ciuill, and friendly conuerſe with ſtrangers, but they would not harken vnto him, and therefore in the preſence of

them all, he called vpon the Moone to reuenge ſuch a 
                  •
               acha
                  •
               ous people, which denied ſtrāgers ſo conuerſe, and commerce with them: within three dayes after the Moone was much darkened by reaſon of the Eclipſe, which when the Indians ſaw, they thought the Moone to be angrie with them, &amp; fearing ſome plague would proceede from her diſpleaſure, they were eaſily induced to doe whatſoeuer Columbus would haue them. In like maner ſhould all men vſe their wits in the firſt place, and weapons ſhould alwayes be the laſt meanes in all our proiects. And therefore although the children of Ioſeph haue an expreſſe commaundement here in this place, to deſtroy thoſe Idolaters, and poſſeſſe their land, yet foraſmuch as we haue no precept but by example, we muſt firſt trie all means before weapons, and when we take them into our hands, neceſſitie of preſeruing our owne liues, muſt rather moue vs to deſtroy the enemyes of God, then either ambition, or gréedineſſe of gaine, or crueltie, or anie priuate reſpect whatſoeuer.
            Now the third thing which we are to obſerue in this entercourſe of wordes betweene the children of Ioſeph, and Ioſua, is the delayes which the people vſe, and the excuſes which they feigne, which ſeeme to import an impoſſibilitie, in the vndertaking of Ioſuas direction. And their delayes are, that the Chanaanites were ſtrong and well prouided of warlike munition, both for their owne defence, and alſo for the defence of thoſe which would vndertake to ſupplant or inuade them, they had yron Charets, &amp; ſuch like muniments of warre, ſo that it ſtoode not with wiſedome to make an inuaſion, with likelihoode to make a conqueſt of them. This is the nature of muddy and earthly ſpirits, to find delayes, and forge excuſes in matters of leaſt difficultie: Man ſayeth, A Lion is without, I ſhall be

ſlaine in the ſtreete. Prou. 22. 13. What ſlanders did the ten ſpies bring vpon the land of Canaan? which ſlā
               ders the I ſraelites made good groūds for their retiring back into Egypt, &amp; thought them lawfull excuſes for them to murmur againſt Moſes &amp; Aaron, Han
                     •
                  ba had much ado to bring his Carthagenians into Italy, they alledged the tediouſneſſe of the voiage; and the inacceſſible paſſage of ye 
               Alpes. We read of Caligula, ſometimes Emperor of Rome, that he on a time condemned a certain Citizens ſon of Rome to be executed, &amp; he ſent for his father to ſee his ſonnes execution. The father to excuſe his abſence, feined himſelfe to be ſick, whervpon the Emperor ſent him his horſlitter, &amp; by that meanes tooke away from him all colour of excuſe. This perplexed father had good cauſe to find delayes to keep him at home: but they that forge cauils, to withdraw themſelues from ſuch attempts whereby God may be honored, the maieſtie and royaltie of their King aduauced, the common wealth enriched, and poſtrecitie prouided for, would not be drawne to theſe attempts in Caligulaes horſlitter, for that is too eaſie meanes to draw on ſuch backward ſpirits, neither would I haue them puniſhed for their delayes, as Tu
                     •
                  lus Hoſtilius ſometimes puniſhed Metius Sufferius for his delayes: but I would ſome Diomedes would find out a meanes to drawe them on to this enterpriſe, by diſcouering their driftes and excuſes; for all that they can alleags for their backewardneſſe, is moſt idle and friuolous.
            The firſt obiection is, by what right or warrant we can enter into the land of theſe Sauages, take away their rightfull in hexitance from them, and plant our ſelues in their places, being vnwronged or vnprouoked by them. Some affirme, and it is likely to be true, that theſe Sauages haue no particular proprietis in

any part or parcell of that Countrey, but only a generall recidencis there, as wild beaſts haue in the forreſt, for they range and wander vp and downe the Countrey, without any law or gouernment, being led only by their owne luſts and ſenſualitie, there is not meum Ortuum amongeſt them: ſo that if the whole lande ſhould bee taken from them, there is not a man that can complaine of any particular wrong done vnto him.
            But the anſwer to the foreſaid obiectiō is, that there is no intendment to take away from them by force that rightfull inheritaunce which they haue in that Countrey, for they are willing to entertaine vs, and haue offered to yeelde into our handes on reaſonable conditions, more lande then we ſhall bée able this long time to plant and manure: and out of all queſtion vppon eaſie compoſition with them, wee may haue as much of their Countrey yeelded vnto vs, by lawfull graunt from them, as wée can or will deſire, ſo that wée goe to liue peaceablie among them, and not to ſupplant them: wee deſire not, neither doe wee intend to take anie thing from them, ex pacto &amp; iure foederis: but to compound with them for that wee ſhall haue of them: and ſurelie except ſucceſſion and election, there cannot bee a more lawfull entrance to a kingdome then this of ours.
            Moreouer, all Polititians doe with one conſent, holde and maintaine, that a Chriſtian King may lawfullie make warre vppon barbarous and Sauage people, and ſuch as liue vnder no lawfull or warrantable gouernment, and may make a conqueſt of them, ſo that the warre bee vndertaken to this ende, to reclaime and reduce thoſe Sauages from their barbarous kinde of life,

and from their brutiſh and ferine manners, to huinanitie, pietie, and honeſtie. Lip. lib. 5. pol. ca. 8. Caſman. in pol. cap. 8. Ke
                     •
                  kerm. lib. 7. pol. pag. 124. And Lipſius alledgeth Saint Auguſtine for proofe hereof, whoſe wordes are theſe: Qui licentia iniquitatis eripitur, vtiliter vincitur. Thoſe people are vanquiſhed to their vnſpeakeable profite and gaine, which by conqueſt are abridged of the libertie of ſinne &amp; impietie. And the ſame Saint Auguſtine hath an other golden ſaying to this purpoſe. Apud veros Dei cultores etiam illa bella peccata non ſunt qua non cupiditate &amp; crudelitate ſed pacis ſtudio geruntur, vt mali coerceantur, &amp; boni ſubleuentur: Amongeſt the true worſhippers of GOD, euen that warre is lawfull which is vndertaken, not for couetouſneſſe and crueltie, but for peace and vnities ſake: ſo that lewde and wicked men may thereby be ſuppreſſed and good men maintained and relieued: whereby we ſee, that both in the opinion of Polititians, and alſo by the iudgement of Auguſtine himſelfe, we might lawfully make warre vppon the Sauages of Virginia our proiect, hauing the endes aforeſaid. And therefore let euerie man that is or will be an aduenturer in this plantation, examine his whole heart, and if hée finde that hée is drawne to partake in this buſineſſe, to drawe the Sauages from their barbarous kinde of life, to a moreciuill, honeſt, and Chriſtian kinde of life, let him not doubt of the lawfulneſſe of it, but let him chéerefully and liberally put his helping hand to this buſineſſe.
            Secondly, they reaſon of the future euents by thoſe that are alreadie paſt. And ſéeing it is aboue twentie yeares agee ſince this attempt was begun, and yet no good hath come of it, nor little hope of any, they holde it an vnaduiſed courſe to ſet the ſame attempt

on foote againe: which obiection of theirs is very ſufficientlie anſwered in that booke intituled Noua Britannia. And indeed moſt childiſh is this obiection, for neither was the end of the firſt attempt the ſame, with the end of this, nor the meanes, nor the managing of the meanes of this attempt ſemblable with the former, and therefore in all likelihood the euent of this cannot be iudged by the euent of the former.
            Their ſecond obiection is, that this age will ſee no profit of this plantatiō. Which obiection admit it were true, yet it is too brutiſh, and bewraies their neglect and incurious reſpect of poſteritie: we are not borne like beaſts for our ielues, and the time preſent only, but beſides manie other things which may challenge an intereſt and right in vs: poſteritie and the age yet enſuing haue not the leaſt part in our life &amp; labours. What benefit or comfort ſhould we haue enioyed in the things of this world, if our forefathers had not prouided better for vs, and bin more carefully reſpectiue of poſteritie then for themſelues? We ſow, we ſet, we plant, we build, not ſo much for our ſelues as for poſteritie; we practiſe the workes of Godlines in this life, yet ſhall we not ſee the end of our hope before wee inioy it in the world to come: It is a bleſſed thing to be bleſſed of poſteritie. It was the reioycing of the Uirgin Marie, that from thenceforth all generations ſhould call her bleſſed. They that do not prouide for eternitie, can haue no aſſured hope of eternitie, and they which onely are for themſelues, ſhall die in themſelues, and ſhall not haue a name among poſteritie, their rootes ſhall bee dried vp beneath, and aboue ſhall their branch bee cut downe, their remembrance ſhall periſh from the earth, and they ſhal haue no name in the ſtreete, Iob 18. 16. 17. But the remembrance which a good man leaues behind him, is like the compoſition of the perfume that is made by the Art of the Apothecary; it is ſweet as honie in all mouthes, and as muſicke at a banket of wine: let it not grieue thee therefore to plant and

build for poſteritie, for the memorie of the iuſt ſhall bée bleſſed, but the name of the wicked ſhall rot. Prou. 10. 7.
            Others obiect the continuall charges which will prooue in their opinion very heauie and burdenſome to thoſe that ſhall vndertake the ſaid Plantation. Theſe like the dog in the manger, neither eate hay themſelues, neither will they ſuffer the Oxe yt would. They neuer think any charges too much that may any way increaſe their owne priuate eſtate. They haue thouſands to beſtow about the ingroſſing of a commoditie, or vpon a morgage, or to take their Neighbours houſe ouer his head, or to lend vpon vſurie: but if it come to a publicke good, they grone vnder the leaſt burden of charges that can bee required of them. Theſe men would bee vſed like ſponges, they muſt be ſqueaſed, ſeeing they drnuke vp all, and will yeeld to nothing, though it concerne the common good neuer ſo greatly. But it is demonſtratiuely prooued in Noua Britannia, that the charges about this Plantation will be nothing, in compariſon of the benefit that will grow thereof. And what notable thing I pray you can be brought to paſſe without charges? The things of this world are appointed vnto man with ſuch conditions as there may no profit accrew vnto him without paine, nor no gaine without charge: Hiel will build Iericho, though the foundation of it coſt him his eldeſt ſonne, &amp; the ſetting vp of the gates coſt him his youngeſt ſonne: Haman wil haue his wicked deſire vpon the Jewes, though it coſt him ten thouſand talents; So little doe the wicked reſpect charges about the effecting of their malicious, or vaine glorious attempts, condemning thoſe that profeſſe pietie and religion, which for ſauing charges, neglect, and often times ſuffer moſt honorable and profitable protects to faile and fall to the ground. Without queſtion kee that ſaues his mony, where Gods glory is to bee aduanced, Chriſtian religion propagated and planted, the good of the Commonwealth increaſed, and the glorious renowne of the King inlarged, s ſubiect to the curſe of Simon

Magus, his monie and he are in danger to periſh together. Let none therefore find delaies, or faine excuſes to withhold them from this imployment for Virginia, ſeeing euery oppoſition againſt it is an oppoſition againſt God, the King, the Church, and the Commonwealth.
            Now in the laſt place let vs heare the anſwere of Ioſhua to the excuſes of the children of Ioſeph, and his anſwere is an exhortation, that in ſtead of delaies they would vſe Art and induſtrie in this enterpriſe which they were to vndertake: Art in cutting downe the trees and making the Countrie champion: Induſtrie by taking paines to conquer and caſt out thoſe Idolatrous Cananites, &amp; to plant themſelues in their places. From whence we are to gather, that for this preſent buſineſſe of plantation in Virginia, there muſt bee ſpeciall choice and care had of ſuch perſons as ſhall be ſent thither. Nature hath emptied her ſelfe in beſtowing her richeſt treaſures vpon that Countrie; ſo that if Art and induſtrie be vſed, as helpes to Nature, it is likely to prooue the happieſt attempt that euer was vndertaken by the Engliſh. And foraſmuch as of all humane Artes Political gouernment is the chiefeſt, there muſt be a ſpeciall care in the Magiſtrate how to carry himſelfe in his place and order: for herein conſiſts the verie maine matter of the ſucceſſe of this buſineſſe. As therefore the Magiſtrate hath the eminencie of dignitie conferred vpon him by his Prince, ſo muſt he furniſh himſelfe with eminencie of vertue: for he ſhal the better containe others within the bounds and limits of honeſtie and godlineſſe, if he firſt be able to containe himſelfe. Mala anima male imperat, Plato: 1. de legibus. A Magiſtrate therefore muſt haue a good conſcience towards God, and he muſt alſo haue a louing affection towards thoſe ouer whom hee hath the gouernment. Concerning the conſcience that a Magiſtrate muſt carrie towards God, he muſt ſo watch ouer himſelſe, that at no time he burſt ſoorth into any notorious vice, nor ſuffer himſelfe to be ſtained with the imputation of any

enormious crime; for the vices of men are holden ſo much the greater, by how much greater the Maieſtie is of the partie delinquent: the blemiſhes of Princes are deformities, and diminitiue ſins in thē, are ſins of the higheſt nature. Again, he that is in place of gouernment muſt know that his example preualles much with thoſe yt are vnder his gouernment, ſo that he ſhall rule his ſubiects better by his good example of life, then by all the lawes and ſtatutes that hee can make. Laſtly, a Magiſtrate muſt know that the moderne times doe not onely behold him, but that he is ſubiect alſo to the view of ſucceeding poſteritie; and therefore Tacitus doth aduiſe Princes, lib. 4. Ann. to beware by all meanes that they giue no occaſion to Chroniclers to publiſh their leaud and wicked actions. Concerning his looing affection towards his ſubiects, his firſt care muſt be that he alwaies ſeeke the publike good of his ſubiects aboue his owne priuate profit: to which purpoſe the Emperour Adrian was wont to ſay; Ita ſe rempublicam geſturum vt ſciret populi rem eſſe, non propriam. The example of Alexander the Great is moſt memorable for this purpoſe, who leading his ſouldiers through the drie and w
                  ••
                places of India, had almoſt loſt his whole armie for water. At the laſt one of his ſouldiers found out the riuer Oxus, &amp; brought the King water to quench his thirſt: but the King powred the water vpon the ground before all his ſouldiers, and would not drinke it, ſpeaking theſe words: Ego bibam? &amp; reliqui ſitient? and when he and his whole armie came to the riuer, hee would not drinke before all his ſouldiers had quenched their thirſt: giuing thereby all Princes to vnderſtand, that they ſhould prouide for the good of their people before their owne good. Thus in conſcience towards God, and in affection towards his ſubiects ought a Prince to ſtand affected. And if he ſtand ſo affected he will puniſh ſuch as are vild and vitious, and he will aduance ſuch as are veriuous and well diſpoſed; he will incourage the painfull and induſtrious,

and he will correct the idle and diſſolute; he will eſtabliſh true religion, and he will repreſſe hereſies and ſchiſmes; he wil reiceue the weake and impotent, and he wil ſuppreſſe the mutinous and inſolent; ſo that God will giue a bleſſing, &amp; al things wil proſper vnder his gouernment.
            And for as much as no policie can ſtand long without religion, a chiefe care muſt be had of ſufficient, honeſt, &amp; ſober minded Miniſters to teach and inſtruct the people both by their life and doctrine in their dutie to God, and obedience to their rulers. When the T
                  ••
               be of Dan went to plant themſelues in La
                  •
               ſh, they tooke a Leuite with them to bee a father and a Prieſt vnto them: Micah thought that the Lord would be better vnto him becauſe he had a Leuite in his houſe. Neither do I euer reade of any that euer attained vnto any gouernment of what religion ſoeuer they were, but their firſt care was to prouide fit perſons which might teach the people religion and diuine worſhip; and therefore if this p
                  •
               antatio
                  •
                ſhould bee vndertaken without this care, there were ſmall hope of any good ſucceſſe to come thereof. And as the Miniſter being a ſubiect muſt yeeld his obedience to the Magiſtrate, ſo 
                  〈◊〉
                Magiſtrate muſt bee carefull to yeeld him countenance to keepe him from neglect, and maintenance to incourage him in his miniſtery. And it muſt be ſpecially foreſeene of the Miniſters that they reſiſt Poperie; for as it doth infect the mind with errour, ſo it doth infect the manners of men with diſloyaltie and treachery: and laſtly they muſt labour to preſerue the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace; for if they 
                  •
               nce 
                  •
               arre, or diſſent among themſelues, they open a gappe to ſchiſme and contempt of religion. Policie thus eſtabliſhing religion, and religion guiding policie; prouiſion muſt be made of men furniſhed with Arts and trades moſt neceſſarie for this buſines: Artificers and tradeſmen muſt be nouriſhed and cheriſhed, for without Artificers and tradeſmen a common-wealth cannot flouriſh nor endure: and therefore the Magiſtrate muſt ſpecially

regard them and reſpect them, and they muſt ſo carrie themſelues that they may be reſpected and cheriſhed of the Magiſtrate. It is required at their hands that they be faithfull, painefull, and honeſt in their callings; for if they be thus qualified, the countrie itſelfe will make them rich. Euery trade hath his myſtery, which is for the moſt part grounded vpon deceit and fraud: but ſeeing the beginning of a common wealth is now attempted, the foundation muſt not bee laid vpon fraud and deceit, for there can no good end be expected of an euill beginning. It is requ
                  •
               red likewiſe that they be painefull in their trades, or elſe the commonwealth can haue little vſe or comfort of them. And here our Engliſh tradeſmen and Artificers are to be aduiſed that they be warie in taking the Sauages to bee apprentices to teach them their trade, ſeeing there be meanes of imployment ſufficient beſides to ſet many thouſands on worke; and therefore not neceſſarie as yet to inſtruct them in our trades and myſteries.
            Beſides all this, induſtrie muſt be alſo added to helpe Arte and Nature, ſo that ſuch as haue no proſeſſed artes and trades, muſt painefully im
                  •••
               y themſelues in ſome labour or other, to the furthering of this Plantation: a Drone will in ſhort ſpace deuoure more hony than the Bée can gather in along time, and therefore the Magiſtrate muſt correct with al ſharpeneſſe of diſcipline, thoſe vnthriftie and vnprofitable Drones, which liue idly: for there is a law giuen to the ſonnes of Adam to labour, and to the daughters of Eue, with the ſweate of their browes to get their liuing, and therefore it is an Euangelicall precept that they which will not labour muſt not eate. In Iobs time there was a very ſtrict order taken for ſuch as liued idely, Iob 30. 5. They were chaſed forth from among men, and euery one ſhowted at them as at a theefe: and ſurely ſuch an order muſt bee taken with thoſe that will not liue painefully in Virginia, the rather becauſe meate and drinke, and ſuch other neceſſarie

ſupplies of liueliehoode will be very precious there a while: and therefore order had more néede be taken, that ſuch prouiſion be not conſumed by vnſeruiceable loytering companions.
            Laſtly, all degrées and ſorts of people which haue prepared themſelues for this Plantation muſt be admoniſhed to preſerue vnitie, loue and concord amongſt themſelues: for by concord ſmall things increaſe and growe to great things, but by diſcord great things ſoone come to nothing. Ageſilaus being demaunded why the Citie of Sparta was not compaſſed about with walles for the better defence and ſafety of the Citie, he ſhewed vnto the demandant, the Citizens and Souldiers of Sparta, all of them liuing and agréeing together in firme concord and vnitie; theſe, ſaith Ageſilaus, are the walles of Sparta: and out of queſtion ſo it is; concord and good agréement amongſt coinhabitants is a more ſure defence than walles or Caſtles, or any other warlike munition whatſoeuer. Therefore if any mutinous or ſeditious perſon dare aduenture to mooue any matter which may tend to the breach of concord and vnitie, he is preſently to be ſuppreſſed as a moſt d
                  ••
               gerous enemy to the ſtate and gouernement there eſtabliſhed. Now all theſe particulars being already not onely concluded vpon, but alſo prouided for by the godly care of the counſell and Aouenturers of Virginia: I haue preſumed onely to aduiſe, being 
                  ••
               t o
                  •
                
               
                  •
               oubt that they will be as carefully performed, as they at? already wiſely and religiouſly determined. And thus far haue I preſumed in my loue to the Aduenturers, and liking to the enterpriſe, 
                  •
               o deale in this buſineſſe, praying as much good ſucceſſe to them and it, as their owne hearts can deſire hoping to ſée their expectation ſatiſfied, and the glory of England as much increaſed by this their honorable attempt, as euer was the Romane Empire by the enterpriſes of her greateſt Emperours, ſorrowing with my ſelfe that I am not able neither in perſon nor purſe to be a partaker in the buſineſſe.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

