
   
      
         
            A moste true and marueilous straunge wonder, the lyke hath seldom ben seene, of. XVII. monstrous fishes, taken in Suffolke, at Downham brydge, within a myle of Ipswiche The .XI. daye of October. in the yeare of our Lorde God. M.D.LX.VIII.
            Granger, Timothy.
         
         
            
               1568
            
         
         Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02040
            STC 12186
            ESTC S121789
            99856954
            99856954
            22603
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02040)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22603)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 385:1)
         
         
            
               
                  A moste true and marueilous straunge wonder, the lyke hath seldom ben seene, of. XVII. monstrous fishes, taken in Suffolke, at Downham brydge, within a myle of Ipswiche The .XI. daye of October. in the yeare of our Lorde God. M.D.LX.VIII.
                  Granger, Timothy.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcut)  
               
                  In Fleetestreate, at the signe of S. Iohn Euangelist by Thomas Colwell,
                  Imprynted at London :
                  [1568]
               
               
                  Signed: Quod. Timothie Granger.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  Trimmed.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Whales --  England --  Ipswich --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-08
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2003-08
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            A Moste true and marueilous straunge wonder, the lyke hath
seldom ben seene, of .XUII. Monstrous fisshes, taken in Suffolke, at Downam brydge, within a myle
of Ipswiche. The .XI. daye of October. In the yeare of our Lorde God. M.D.LX.UIII.

            
            FYrste you shall vnderstande, that the begynners first Uenterers
to take these fishes, was Nycholas Gibbins, and Ihon Carnaby,
with theyr men: after came Iohn Baker, and Robert Haulley wt 
theyr men, being all Saylers &amp; Shipmen dwelling in Ipswiche,
with other, besydes manye of the countrey ther about, whyche when they
harde of it, came thyther to helpe, and see the taking of them.
            ¶Also, of these .xvii. fyshes, there was a male, and a female, that was
more howge and monstrous then the other .xv. For the least of these .ii.
fisshes, were .xxvii. foote longe: and as bigge in the middle eche of them,
as .iii. Buttes of Malmezie, and of a marueylous great strength, as it is
well known to dyuers in Ipswich &amp; other places, beside those men aboue
named. For they tyed one of these fysshes to a boat, to brynge hit to Ipswich
wharfe, and being so tied to the boat, swam awaye wyth the boat &amp;
all the men that weare in it, toward the sea a maruaylous swyft pace, for
all that they could do: this was when the tyde came in, for they had made
prouision before, whē the water was loo, to tie great roapes about theyr
tayles and finnes with small boates, and by such meanes as they could.
(And as I sayd before) the tyde commyng in &amp; the fyshe hauinge water,
swam away with the boat so fast toward the sea, that if ther had not byn
rescue of other boates and such vessels as they had thear, that boat and
all they in it, had ben lost and vtterlie cast away. But as God wold haue
it, by the helpe of thother boates or vessels, tieng the fishe also. Brought
him by force to a conuenient place, and tied him fast to a tree with strong
Cable roapes, and so vsyng theym one by one, founde meanes to brynge
theim to Ipswych wharfe. Wher they were layd with great labour and
trouble, besyde breaking of theyr wyndlace &amp; a great Cable roape, wyth
halyng them vp, they weare of suche maruaylous greatnes, strength and
wayght. Som of them laye vpon the wharfe .ii. dayes and a nyght before
they weare dead, and yet they strooke them wyth Axes &amp; other weapons
to kyll them. The ryuer wherin they weare taken was coloured red, wt 
the blood that issued from theyr woundes, whyle they weare a takyng, y•
water beinge so deepe that a H
                  •
               y might well ryde thear in. Thear was
also .iii. Butchers a hole day cutting out one of these fysshes, and as manye
to carye it awaye with hand barous to the town ware house, and the
Butchers were fayne to put on bootes to stand in to cut it out, it was so
deepe &amp; full of garbyge? this fishe was a mans heyght in thicknes, from
the top of the backe to the bone: and his bones as harde as stones, that the
Butchers mard al theyr Axes they occupied about them. The other .xv.
fisshes were .xxiiii. foote longe, and som of them .xxi. foote, and byg according
to theyr length. But the .ii. biggist, male and female, was .xxvii.
foote long, and as byg in the middle as .iii. Buttes of malmsie. Hauinge
a round snout. His mouth wyde, gapinge aboue a yeard broad. And had
xliiii. teeth, one beinge wayed &amp; waith a pound &amp; a halfe, viii. inches &amp; a
half long, and aboue .vi. inches in compas about, yet none of the biggest.
Also a great long tung, a marueylous byg head, &amp; is a yeard betweene the
eies, Upon theyr heds were holes, as big that a man might put in both his
fistes at once, out of the which they did spoute a great quantitie of water
whyle they were a takinge, that they had almoste dround .ii. boates men
and all, with spoutynge of water: for the water wold assende vppwarde
from the fisshes, as hie as any house, and so fall doun &amp; weet all them that
were within theyr reache moste cruellie. Also they were white beneath
the eyes a hand broad, theyr eies blacke, and no bigger then the eyes of a
Calfe. Theyr backes as blacke as ynke, so smoth &amp; bryght y• one myght
haue seene his face on it, as in a dim Glasse. Theyr bellies as whyte as
mylke. And vpon their backes they had eche of them one great blacke Fin
growing, and sum of them were a yeard and a halfe long, verie thycke, &amp;
strong, and .ii. great blacke ones vnderneath the fore part of his bellye.
Also the male, one of the .ii. biggest had a yerde, that when it was out, was
more then .iii. quarters of a yearde long, and as byg toward his bodye as
a mans arme sleeue &amp; all, by the elboe. His tayle was .iii. yeardes long,
and .ii. yerdes broad verye thycke &amp; blacke, &amp; wonderfull stronge: for .x.
tall men stood vppon his tayle, &amp; he liftng his tayle vp, ouer thrue theym
all. Also when he had lifted vp his tayle it was of such monstrous waight
strength, and bygnes, that when it fell the verye grund wold rynge, and
shake therwith. Thys fyshe was cut out in peeces, and geuen away to
diuers in the towne that did eate of it, and was verye good meate, eyther
rosted or bakt, (so much of it as was kept sweete) and the meate of them
bakt tasted lyke red Deere. And as they cut it out it was wayed by peeces,
so that the verye boddye of this one fishe, wayed .LII. hondred the
bare carckas, besyde many lytle peecis that was geuen away vnwaied to
crauers that stood by, &amp; besydes a Carte loade of garbyge that came oute
of his bellye, so that all together was aboue threescore hondred and od.
            If the men of Ipswych had knowne so muche betyme whyle they were
sweete, as they haue sence, they might haue made .ii.C. marche more of
them then is now made. But now they bee barreld vpp to make Oyle of,
and will not bee sold for a great peece of monney.
            ¶And this you maye see, the perfect and true discripcion, of these
straunge fishes, wherin is to be noted, the straung and marueylous
handye workes of the Lord, blessed be God in all his giftes, &amp; holye
in all his workes, the Lordes name bee praysed, in them, and for
them, for euer and euer. So be it.
            
               Quod. Timothie Granger.
            
         
      
      
         
            Imprynted at London in Fleetestreate▪ at the signe
of S. Iohn Euangelist by Thomas Colwell.
         
      
   

