
   
      
         
            An answere to maister Smyth seruaunt to the kynges most royall maiestye, and clerke of the Quenes graces councell though most unworthy / [by me a poore man ... W.G.]
            Gray, William.
         
         
            
               1540
            
         
         Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02062
            STC 12206A.3
            ESTC S2985
            29632447
            ocm 29632447
            28045
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02062)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28045)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1861:7)
         
         
            
               
                  An answere to maister Smyth seruaunt to the kynges most royall maiestye, and clerke of the Quenes graces councell though most unworthy / [by me a poore man ... W.G.]
                  Gray, William.
               
               1 sheet ([2] p.).   
               
                  Imprinted at London by me Rychard Bankes/cum priuilegio ad imprimandum solum. And to be solde in Pater noster rowe by John Turke/at the sygne of the Rose,
                  [London] :
                  [1540]
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Includes marginal notes in Latin.
                  Statement of responsibility found at end of p. [2].
                  Publication date from STC (2nd ed.).
                  Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Smyth, Thomas, --  servaunt to the Quenes most excellent Majestie.
               Ballads, English.
               Broadsides --  London (England) --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-07
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-10
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2004-10
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            An answere to maister Smyth seruaunt to the kynges most royall maiestye. And clerke of the Quenes graces counsell / though most vnworthy.
            ¶ Whether ye trolle in or els trolle out
            ye trolle vntruly / loke better about.
            
               
                  WHere as of late two thinges ye parused
               Concerning the treason of Thomas Crumwell
               Vndoutedly both your wyt and your syght were confused
               Lackyng a medecyne / blyndnesse to expell
               Put on your spectacles and marke it well
               Than shall you se / and say / maugre your hart
               That trolle in / hath played a true subiectes part
            
            
               
                  ❧ For where as trolle a way (as ye say) tolde trouth
               Declaring the offences / wherin Crumwell offended
               It was not the thyng / wherwith troll in was wroth
               For in that poynt / Troll in / Troll away commended
               But this was the mater / wherfore they contended
               Trolle away / vnder pretence of trollyng against treason
               Practised proude popery / as appereth by reason.
            
            
               ☞ And ye supporting the same / your pen runneth at large
               Boldly as blynde bayerd / ye write in his defence
               And in your myscheuous maner / ye lay falsly to my charge
               Sayeng / who that craftely coloureth any others offence
               Of lykelyhode in his owne hert / hath the same pretence
               But here ye speke of lykelyhode / and so blyndly go by gesse
               your fondnesse is the folyssher / and my faute is the lesse.
            
            
               ¶ An horse beyng nothing galled / of force ye may make to kycke
               With spurryng and with prickinge / more than reason wolde requyre
               But if the horse were lustye / coragious and also quycke
               ye might be the fyrst perchaunce / that might lye in the myre
               As wyse as ye / haue ben drowned in their owne desyre
               Many a man / anothers mischefe / of malyce wyll prepare
               And yet him selfe the fyrst / that is caught in the snare.
            
            
               ¶ Bycause of making stryfe (ye say) ye wyll take neither parte
               But here ye breke promyse / for agaynst all reason and right
                     Ve illi per qem scandalū uenit, Luce, xvij.
                  
               
               Speking with your mouth / that you thinke not with your harte
               Agaynst trolle in / ye take trolle awayes parte / with all your myght
               Thus all thinges lyghtly that ye make / amonge them selues do fyght
               Wherfore whatsoeuer ye write or saye / gretly it shall not skyll
               For if ye speke any thing wysely / I thinke it be agaynst your wyll.
            
            
               ¶ But blyndly haue ye sclaundred me / good maister Thomas Smyth
               Scraping togither scriptures / your madnesse to mayntayne
               Truly your rude rowsty reason / being so farre from the pyth
               Had nede of suche a cloke / to kepe it from the rayne
               For all the worlde may perceyue / how falsly ye forge and fayne
               Yet styll you affyrme your falshed / as though ye knew thinges presysely
               Christes blessyng on your hert / forsoth ye haue done full wysely.
            
            
               ¶ Ye rumble amonge the scryptures / as one that were halfe mad
               Wrestyng and writhyng them / accordyng to your owne purpose
               Facyonyng and framyng them / to your sayenges good and bad
               Lyke as the holy Papystes / were wont to paynt their popysshe glose
               Do ye take the holy scripture to be lyke a shypmans hose?
               Nay nay / although a shypmans hose / wyll serue all sortes of legges
               yet Christes holy scrypture / wyll serue no rotten dregges.
            
            
               
               ☞ Counsell with some tayler / whan that ye wryte nexte
               Take measure of diuinyte / before ye cut the facyon
               So shall ye square your scryptures / and the better trym your texte
               And than shall men of lernyng / commende your operacyon
               But howe shulde he be connyng / that knoweth not his occupacyon
               Howe shuld a cobler cut a core / or a smyth tast good wyne
               Or how shulde you scarsely a clerke / be nowe a good deuyne?
            
            
               
                  ❧ What lyuyng man (excepte it were you) beynge in his right wyttes
               Wolde write as ye haue written / and all not worth a myte
               I thinke it be some peuysshe pange / that cometh ouer your hert by fyttes
               Vnder the coloure of charyte / to worke your cruell spyte
               If men wolde marke your madnesse / and beholde your deuelyssh delyte
               Shuld se how ye wrest ye scriptures to your sayēg / not worth .ii. chippes
               And ioyne them all togither / as iust as Germans lyppes.
            
            
               ¶ Whan ye haue spytte your poyson / and sayde euen the worst ye can
               Than come ye in with charite / wyllyng all stryfe to cease
               But surely good maister Smyth / ye speke lyke a mery man
               Moche lyke a comen pyke quarell / that stryfe wolde encrease
               Continually cryeng in frayes / holde / kepe the kynges pease
               But those be prety peace makers / in dede for euery daye
               That styll bestowe mo strokes / than they that began the fraye.
            
            
               ☞ What wyse man wolde not laugh / for to here you bragge and boste
               Of your name / your seruyce / of your offyce and all this gere
               
                  
                     Qui se laudat stercore coronabit,
                  As though ye were prymrose perelesse / and a ruler of the roste
               By the declaryng wherof / ye thinke to put pore men in fere
               But your braggyng and your bostyng / shall neyther be here nor there
               As longe as I may indifferently / be suffred to vse my pen
               ye shall neuer be able to face me out / with a carde of ten.
            
            
               
                  ❧ A wyse man wolde haue praysed god / and than prayed for the kyng
               The which of their gret goodnesse / to your offyce dyd you call
               And not to haue bragged therof / and than put it out in printyng
               For ye stande not yet so sure / but it is possyble ye may fall
               And though your offyce be great / I trust your power be but small
               Or els parchaūce ye wold quickly thurst a poore man amōg the thornes
               But god almyghty prouydeth well to sende a shrewde cow short hornes.
            
            
               ¶ Christ preserue the kynges most noble grace / &amp; sende him longe lyfe
               Euen Henry the eight (next vnder god) of this church / the hed supreme
               Christ preserue &amp; kepe quene Katheryn / his most lawfull wyfe
               Christ preserue Prince Edwarde / the very right heyre of this realme
               Christ styll ensence their noble counsell / with the influence of heauen
               Christ for his tendre mercy / amende all thing that is a mys
               Christ sende maister Smyth more charite / whan his good pleasure is.
            
            ¶ Amen.
            
               W.G.
            
            
               ☞ By me a poore man whose herte if ye knewe
               Wolde be the kynges seruaunt as fayne as you.
            
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London by me Rychard Bankes / Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum. And be to be solde in Pater noster rowe by John̄ Turke / at the sygne of the Rose.
         
      
   

