
   
      
         
            The castel of memorie wherein is conteyned the restoring, augmenting, and conseruing of the memorye and remembraunce, with the safest remedies, and best preceptes therevnto in any wise apperteyning: made by Gulielmus Gratarolus Bergomatis Doctor of Artes and Phisike. Englished by Willyam Fulvvod. The contentes whereof appeare in the page next folovvynge.
            De memoria reparanda. English
            Gratarolo, Guglielmo, 1516?-1568?
         
         
            
               1562
            
         
         Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02045
            STC 12191
            ESTC S117976
            99853185
            99853185
            18554
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02045)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18554)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1238:12)
         
         
            
               
                  The castel of memorie wherein is conteyned the restoring, augmenting, and conseruing of the memorye and remembraunce, with the safest remedies, and best preceptes therevnto in any wise apperteyning: made by Gulielmus Gratarolus Bergomatis Doctor of Artes and Phisike. Englished by Willyam Fulvvod. The contentes whereof appeare in the page next folovvynge.
                  De memoria reparanda. English
                  Gratarolo, Guglielmo, 1516?-1568?
                  Fulwood, William.
               
               [128] p.   
               
                  By Rouland Hall dwellynge in Gutter lane, at the signe of the half Egle &amp; the Keye,
                  Printed at Londo[n] :
                  1562.
               
               
                  Translation of: De memoria reparanda.
                  Signatures: A-H.
                  Running title reads: The castell of memory.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Memory --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-12
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-12
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
            
            THE CASTEL OF Memorie: wherein is conteyned the reſtoring, augmenting, and conſeruing of the Memorye and Remembraunce,with the ſafeſt remedies, and beſt preceptes therevnto in any wiſe apperteyning: Made by Guliolmus Gratarolus Bergomatis Doctor of Artes and Phiſi\ke.
            Engliſhed by Willyam Fulwod.
            
            The Contentes whereof appeare in the Page next folowynge.
            
               AFTER DARKNES LIGHT.
               POST TENEBRAS LVX
            
            Printed at Londō by Rouland Hall dwellynge in Gutter lane, at the ſigne of the half Egle &amp; the Keye. 1562.
         
         
            
            THE CONTENTES.
            
               The j. Chapter declareth what Memory is where it floriſheth, how profitable and neceſſary it is, &amp;c.
               The ij. conteineth the chiefe cauſes, where by the Memorie is hurte, with theyr ſygnes and cures.
               The iij. ſhevveth the principall endomages of the Memorie in what ſort ſoeuer they be.
               The iiij. telleth lykewiſe the perticular helpes of the Memorye.
               The v. cōprehendeth certayne beſt approued and choſen medicinable compounded remedies, and preſeruatiues greatly encreaſyng the Memorie.
               The vj. expreſſeth Philoſophicall Iudgementes, Rules, and Preceptes of Remembraunce.
               The vij. Chap. entreateth in fewe wordes of locall or artificiall Memory.
               Laſt of all is 
                     •
                  ut a 
                     •••…
                  fe Epilogue of the foreſayde thynges.
            
         
         
            
            
               To the right honorable, the Lorde Robert Dudley, Maiſter of the Queenes Maieſties horſe; and Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter: Willyam Fulwod hartely wiſheth long lyfe, with encreaſe of godlye honour and eternal felicitie.
            
               SIth noble Maximilian, king of Boemia: Defended hath this worthy worke in Latin toung (I ſaic).
            
               Sith that alſo the godly prince
               Edward, our late good king:
               In French the ſame accepted hath
               as a right nedefull thing.
            
            
               I thought therfore my duty was,
               (moſt honorable Lorde):
               Soure worthy captain now to chuſe
               who with benigne accorde.
            
            
               
               In Engliſh wold vouchſafe to ſaue,
               this Caſtle from decay:
               Protecting it from enuious toungs
               that runne at large alway.
            
            
               But whom might I rather elect,
               my Patrone now to bee:
               Then one who doth moſt mē excell,
               in perfect clemencie?
            
            
               In feruent zeale to godlynes,
               In fauour of the iuſt:
               In forwardnes to all good works,
               the truth this tell needs muſt.
            
            
               A note of highe Nobility,
               a vertuous one in deed:
               Whoſe good report hath cauſed me,
               thus boldly to proceed.
            
            
               Right happy ſure may be yt realme,
               and praiſe to god extend:
               Wherin ſuch prudēt peeres do rule, Exod. 18. Deut. 1.
               
               as Moſes doth commend.
            
            
               
               Yea bleſt it is of God the lorde,
               that hath ſuch worthy ſtates:
               Who righteouſnes rightly exaltes,
               and wickednes abates.
            
            
               Theſe golden giftes of godly grace,
               thus planted in your breſt:
               Haue forced me to flie for ayde,
               where plenty is expreſt.
            
            
               Receue therfore (o worthy Lorde),
               an humble harte and true:
               Protect alſo the Patronage,
               which I ſubmitte to you.
            
            
               And graūt yt theſe my labors ſmall,
               may paſſe vnder your name:
               Sith that this worke deſcēded hath,
               from Princes of great fame.
            
            
               For though that all Forgetfulnes,
               be baniſht from you quyte:
               Yet hope I that this Treatiſe ſhall,
               you honor much delyte.
            
            
               
               Conſidering well the worthines,
               of perfect Memory:
               And what effect it furniſheth,
               in all affayres. for why?
            
            
               Lyke as Obliuion is the loſſe,
               of high renoumed actes:
               And cauſeth many worthy wightes,
               forgo both fame and factes.
            
            
               Lyke as it is an eatyng moth
               and ſore corrupting ruſt:
               Abaſyng things of noble ſtate,
               no better then to duſt.
            
            
               Lyke as it is a Chaos great,
               confuſedly compact:
               Wherin al things both good &amp; had,
               haue true proporcion lackt.
            
            
               So Memorie doth ſtill preſerue,
               eche thing in his degree:
               And rendreth vnto euery one,
               his doughty dignitie.
            
            
               
               So doth it pourge ech mans eſtate,
               and ſkoureth it full bright:
               Wherby appeares as in a glaſſe
               his liuely ſhining light.
            
            
               So doth it geue and attribute,
               to good thinges good report:
               To bad lykewiſe as they deſerue,
               in iuſt and equall ſort.
            
            
               How can yt Iudge iuſte iudgement geue,
               except he call to mynde: Iudge.
               
               The matters hanging diuerſly,
               the truth thereby to fynde.
            
            
               Howe ſhall the Preacher wel recite
               his matters orderlie: Preacher.
               
               If that he be forgetfull of,
               his places what they bee?
            
            
               How can yt Captayn well conduct,
               his ſoldiers in array: Captayn.
               
               Or els preuent his ennemyes,
               yf Memory be away?
            
            
               
               How ſhal the Marchant ſafely kepe, Marchant.
               
               his recknings from decay:
               If his Remēbrance ſhuld him fayle,
               though writīg beare great ſway?
            
            
               How can yt Lawyer plead his cauſe,
               before the iuſtyce ſeat: Lawyer.
               
               If he his clyents matters ſhall,
               at any tyme forgeat?
            
            
               How ſhall the Huſbandanā prouide,
               all ſeaſons to obſerue: Huſbandman.
               
               If he do not remember well,
               or any wiſe doe ſwerue?
            
            
               How needfull then is Memorye,
               to rule a publike weale:
               In things deuyne &amp; eke prophane?
               God graunt it neuer fayle.
            
            
               Or how can it at any tyme,
               be ſpared in the fielde?
               That is ſo requyſite at home,
               and ſtrong defending ſhielde.
            
            
               
               A good wit ſone may learne things,
               and vnderſtand the ſame:
               But them ſtill to retayne and keep
               in ſuch order and frame,
            
            
               That nothing be wanting therof,
               when iuſt occaſion ſhall
               Procure rehearſall of ſuch thinges,
               as did to vs befall
            
            
               Is thoffice of the Memorie,
               the greateſt gifte that can
               Here in this world by any meanes,
               come vnto mortall man.
            
            
               For what helps it good bokes to read
               or noble ſtoryes large:
               Except a perfect Memorye,
               doe take therof the charge?
            
            
               What profits is moſt worthy thīges
               to ſee, or els to heare:
               If that the ſame come in at thone,
               and out at thother eare?
            
            
               
               Why? then the matter is ſo playn,
               that need (a perfect ground):
               Doth vs compell to ſay no leſſe,
               when truth is truly found.
            
            
               Therfore I breifly thus conclude,
               take Memorye away.
               What is a man? what can be doe?
               or els what can he ſay?
            
            
               Reſtore the ſame to him againe
               in full integrytie:
               It will him ſone reduce in dede,
               to all felicytie.
            
            
               Wherin god graūt your honor may
               longe here with vs endure:
               And afterwards in heauens hie,
               emong the Angels pure.
            
            Amen.
            
               Your honors moſt humble Willyam Fulwod.
            
         
         
            
            
               The Tranſlator to the Reader earneſtlye deſyreth grace, mercy, and peace.
            
               AMongeſt other there bee twoo ſeuerall cauſes (good Reader) whiche inſtigated me to enterpriſe and publiſhe the tranſlation hereof. Partly, becauſe of myne own exerciſe and commoditie. But chiefely and eſpecially, for the common vtilitie and profite of my natiue countrey. The aduauncement and benefite whereof euery man is bound bothe by nature &amp; conſcience to ſtudy for all meanes poſſible

to the vttermoſt of his power: and for that purpoſe to diſtribute accordynge to the greatnes or ſmalnes of the talent miniſtred &amp; lent vnto Math. 35. Luck. 19. him: to the end that the ſame (be it neuer ſo lytle) yf it maye in anye wiſe profite, doe not remaine in him as dead and fruſtrate: but rather that it be beſtowed forthe to encreaſe and fructifie. Conſideryng in deede that (as Plato ſayeth) Non ſolum nobis ſumus; ortuſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
                
               Plato. 
               noſtri partem patrīa vendicat, partem parentes, partem amici.
            
            Accept therefore in good part (gentle Reader) my labours ſuche as they be: wherein yf thou ſhalte fynde any thing either not eaſye to be come

by, or obſcure and darke to thyne vnderſtandynge (as perchaunce in artificiall Memorie): thou muſt diligentlye and circumſpectly often pervſe the ſame, whiche if at the length thou canſt not vnderſtande, doe not therefore opprobriouſlye contemne it, but rather aſke counſell at ſome other, for Non cuiuis homini contingit adire Corynthum. or elles repare to eaſyer and playner, wherof there is in this treatiſe greate abundaunce to the ſame effect what ſoeuer it be: for I haue not preſumed to leſſen myne Authour, and therefore reporte me fauourablye. In whiche doynge thou ſhalte ſtyll encorage

and prouoke me to further paynes, I truſte to thy furtheraunce, and the glorye of almightye God the Father, the Sonne, and the Ghoſt: to whome be laude and praiſe worlde without ende.
            Amen.
            
               This. xx. of Nouember. 1562.
               
               Lege &amp; perlegé: Ne quid temeré.
            
         
         
            
            The Bookes verdicte.
            
               A Caſtell ſtronge I doe preſent,
               well furniſhed and ſure:
               Munited eke with armoure bent,
               For euer to endure.
            
            
               Vhich hitherto longe tyme hath bene,
               In (limbo patrum) hidd.
               But now at laſt may here be ſene,
               from daungers men to ridd:
            
            
               Procuringe them a perfect ſtate, Sapi. 6. 8. &amp;. 18.
               
               And ſafe ſecurity,
               Whereby they may fynde out the gate,
               Of wiſedomes lore. For why?
            
            
               He that hath loſt his Memorie,
               By me may it renewe:
               And he that will it amplifie.
               Shall fynde inſtructions trewe,
            
            
               
               And he that will ſtill kepe the ſame,
               That it ſhall not decaye:
               By me muſt learne: the way to frame:
               And my precepes obaye.
            
            
               Lo here ye ſee my full effecte:
               And that I doe entend:
               The ſecrettes therof to detect.
               That therby wittes may mend.
            
            Then Iudge me, As I am worthie.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               What Memorie is, where it floriſheth, how profitable and neceſſary it is.
               The firſt Chapter.
               
                  MEmorie is by the A definition of memorie. whiche the mynde repeateth things yt are paſt. Or it is a ſtedfaſt perceſuyng in the mynde of the diſpoſition of thinges and wordes. Or as (Ariſtotle ſuppoſeth) it is an imagination, that remaineth of ſuch Ariſtotle. thinges as the ſenſe had conceyued. Alſo by yt ſentence of Plato, Memorie is a ſenſe &amp; a ſafetie (or ſafe reteining Plato. of things): for yt ſoule obtaineth by the office of the ſenſes whatſoeuer thinges chaunce vnder the ſenſe, and therefore it is the beginninge of an opinion. But by the mynde it ſelfe it conſidereth intellectuall thynges, &amp; ſo is it become intelligence. Yet yt
                  
Memorie being loſt, it is renued againe by remembraunce: for whereas forgetfulnes or the loſſe of Memorie is double, to wit, perpetuall and temporall (or for a tyme), in this verely remembraunce worketh, of the which it ſhalbe ſpoken hereafter in his place. Neither is inuention or imaginatiō of yt one part of the ſoule or braine, and Memorie of the othe
                     •…
                   but they are in one ſame ſubiecte thing and the functions of the ſame part of the ſoule, and either of them is of ye hole brayne, in whoſe hole body yt ſoule (being yt principal parte of vnderſtanding) is diſperſed: yet haue auncient Writers (not withoute a cauſe) ſaide that diuers partes of the head and braine be occupied of theſe functions of the ſoule: Memorie The ſeate of the Memorie, is in the hinder part of the head. therefore hath his ſeate in the hinder part of the head in the thyrde Ventricle, whiche is alſo called Puppis. It would be long and altogether

ſuperfluous here (where I ſtudye breuitie) to deſcribe the Anatomie of the whole braine, the whiche is to be ſeene in the bookes of manyé, eſpecially of the learned yea and dilligent Andrea Veſalius. Yet will I briefely Andrea veſalius. ſpeake ſomwhat making nerer vnto our matter. There be three operations of the ſoule in the braine, fantaſie The ſculo hath. 3. operations. (or imagination), reaſonyng (or iudgement), and Memorie (or remembraunce). The two firſt haue their operation in the two greater Ventricles of the braine, and the thyrde is erxerciſed in thirde and leſſer Ventricle. In the concauities or holownes of the brayne is frequented The ſpirite is exerciſed in the concauities of the braine a liuelye, ſmall, pure, and moſte cleane ſpirite, and ſuche a one is caried to the Memorie: the which ſurely hath neede of thè clearenes and ſubtilitie of the ſpirite. For if ſo be that that waye be not opened by the whiche the ſpirite paſſeth to the hinder

part (or Puppis) of the braine, the man remembreth nothing: and contrariwiſe they that haue a ſwifte openinge of that waye, are wiſe, and anſwere ſpedely, as are diuers cholericke perſons: and they that haue that openinge ſlowe, are dull and ſlack to learne and to aunſwere, and ſuch are for the moſt parte flematick or melancholicke, vſynge groſſe and much meates and drincks. Certeinlye there be fewe founde that are indewed with a good witte and an excellent Memorie of Nature: for becauſe that witte betokeneth a ſubtile and ſofte ſubſtaunce of the braine, and Memorie a permanent ſubſtaunce. Alſo Galenus ſaith in Galenus chap 12. Artis Medicio. his .xii. Chapter, Artis medicinalis, that witte declareth a ſubtile ſubſtaunce of the braine: and the dulnes of vnderſtandinge, a groſſe ſubſtaunce, &amp;c. The ſpirite ſeruynge for this office, doth flee vpwarde from

the heart thorough the ſynowes to the head, and is nouriſhed with an outwarde compaſſing ayre, &amp; obtayneth a longe continuaunce. And to be ſhort, al Philoſophers do accorde, that Memorie is moſt of ſtrength by the good temperature of the organe or ſeate, in the whiche the ſoule doth exerciſe this office. And it ſhalbe a token that they haue a good Memorie, whoſe hinder part of the head is great and longe: and they a weake Memorie, whoſe hinder parte of the head is as it were playne and equall with the necke. It is alſo to be knowen that it cauſeth wiſedome by the goodnes of the ſpirites: and thoſe are good ſpirites, whiche be tempered with clearenes mouing and ſubtilitie. Plato in Theaeteto ſaieth, that Plato in Theaeteto. the ſoule is not well at eaſe in a body that is thicke or muddye, or that hath the fleſhe to ſofte, or harde.
               And vntemperatneſſe chaungeth

many wayes: For ſometyme a body ſhall bringe it oute of the mothers wombe ſo ſtronge and violent, that not onelye the Memorie, but alſo the reaſon ſhalbe hurte, in ſuche ſorte yt euen foliſhnes ſhall happen therewithall: the whiche amongeſt the other ſignes that it hath, is the cauſe Intēperatnes is the cauſe that the eares be great. Ariſtotle. 1. De animaliū natura. that the eares are verye great and erected, as Ariſtotle reciteth in hys firſte De animalium natura: Who ſo chaunceth to be borne when the Moone doth encounter the Sunne, wandering through Aries and Scorpio ſhall haue his brayne ſo afflicted, that beinge ſomewhat growen in yeres, a melancholicke paſſion ſhall beginne to ſpring. Alſo this vntemperatues of the brayne commeth manye tymes of ill nouriſhement, ſometyme of the vnwholſome ayre that is aboute vs: For it is an olde ſayinge, there as the ayre is dryer, there alſo for the moſt part the wits

be ſharper, and the ſoule wiſer and prompter: euen ſo a thicke &amp; groſſe element cauſeth the wittes to be duller. Of the ſame diet is reaſon, as alſo Galenus ſaieth in his booke Galenus Quod animi mores, &amp;c. 
                  Quod animi mores, &amp;c. The Memorie alſo is weakened of chaunce, of being ſtriken, of ſickennes and diuers other lyke accidentes, whereof there maye be had manye examples aſwell in Thucidides in his ſeconde Thucidides. 2. boke belli Pelop. booke belli Pelop. as in others: a certeine perſon beinge ſtriken with a ſtone, forgat onely his learninge, being fallen from a hye houſe, loſte the remembraunce of his mother, kinſfolkes and neighbours: alſo Meſſala Meſſala Coruinus. Coruinus the Orator forgat his owne name. Beholde therefore how Memorie is the chief goodnes of man. Seneca. fraile this moſt precious treaſure of man is. Memorie (as Seneca witneſſeth) is the principall commoditie and profit that mans nature can receyue: for it is an eaſie matter for

ſtudious perſons to read many thinges, and it is not difficile for a good and an exerciſed wit to vnderſtande the ſame: but to heape them together, and to conſcrue them in the coffre or ſecrete of the Memorie in ſuche ſorte that thei ſlippe not away, is the moſt neceſſarye and principall Plinius. 7. boke. 24. Chap. goodnes of mans lyfe. As Plinius reherſeth in his .vii. booke, the .xxiiii. Chapter. Cyrus king of the Perſians called all his ſouldiours name Cirus king of the perfians, by name. Mithridates alſo who was king of two and twenty nations, did vnderſtande and anſwere ſo manye Mithridates king of 22 nations. languages without an Interpretor: there wanteth no examples of the excellentnes of Memorie, whiche men haue had almoſt in all tymes. They therefore whyche haue not ſo excellent a Memorye, muſte by labor get the ſame, withoute the whiche a man ſhall ſcarce attayne vnto anye perfectiō: for it chaūceth many times

that ſomuch the more that a man excelleth in Memorie, he alſo ſomuche the more floriſheth in wiſdom, except it be ſome ſluggiſhe or idle perſonne. And yt Poetes not wtout a cauſe haue feyned wiſdome to be yt doughter of Wiſedome is the doughter of Memorye. Memory: &amp; of her it is rightly writtē.
               
                  By painefull vſe begot I was,
                  a worthy wyght and cleare:
                  By Memorye brought forth no leſſe,
                  who is my mother deare.
               
               Diuers aged perſōs vſing this practiſe, &amp; applieng thēſelues to ſtudy haue in fewe monethes proceded learned. Therefore we will declare in this worke, by what meanes it maye be gotten, encreaſed and kepte. For it is manifeſt by dyuers learned men, as alſo by Cicero, that Memorye hath a certayne cunning or practiſe and that Cicero. it procedeth not altogether of nature: ſo therefore we will firſt teache by what kynde of lyuynge and by what medecines it maye be gotten

and eſtabliſhed, expreſſing briefe, excellent, and (by vſe) approued preceptes. Afterwardes, we will breifly entreat of artificiall Memory, which of it ſelfe is naturall, but it is confirmed by certayne preceptes, and conſiſteth in obſeruations, places, and Images (or figures).
            
            
               THE SECONDE CHAPTER containeth the cheife cauſes whereby the Memorie is hurte, with their fignes and cures.
               THere be two principal cauſes Coldenes and moiſtnes are cō
                     traryes to the Memorye. which hurte the Memorye, to witte, coldnes and moyſtnes: the whiche coldenes is either alone, or els ioyned with moyſtnes, we wil omitte to ſpeake of the corruption whiche commeth of ouer muche heat and drynes. Yet coldenes hurtethe more then moyſtenes: for coldenes doth confound the nature, &amp; worketh not in it but as an vnder rulinge inſtrument.

And moiſtnes is contrary to the retentyue, the whiche is comforted with a proportioned drines: for ſuperfluous drynes is hurtfull eſpecially to the apprehenſion, whileſt it The natur of coldnes is to repreſſe, and the nature of heat is to moue. hindereth that formes or likeneſſes can not be receiued and ſetled in the ſame. It is the nature of coldenes to ceaſſe, and of heat to moue: therefore coldenes hindereth the mouinge neceſſarie to the Memory. And moiſtenes hindereth the retayning thereof. To be breife, ſeing that forgetfulnes Forgetfulnes is the doghter of coldenes. Paulus Aegineta. is the doughter of coldenes, as Paulus Aegineta, and others doe teſtifie, it is to be ſaid &amp; affirmed, that coldenes more hurteth the Memorie, then moyſtenes. For the figure or kynde of coldnes which congeleth humors and ſpirites, can not be conceaued. The ſlepings alſo of ſuch whoſe Memorie or vnderſtading periſheth, are to be obſerued, to witt whether they be vehement or moderate ſlepers, or

altogether not ſlepie, but haue it according to the courſe of nature. And ſo ſhall you fynde vntemperatenes the vanquiſher: and ſhall knowe alſo that moyſtnes &amp; drines be the contraries: moiſtnes, becauſe of ouer much ſlepe: drynes, becauſe of ouer muche watchinge: and that of the meane of theſe twoo, equalitie, and the good proportion of humours procedeth. Moreouer it is to be conſidered, whether any thinge be voyded out of the noſtrells or mouthe that commethe from the head, or whether thoſe places be altogether drye or but partly: the knowledge of whiche precedent cauſes and ſhowes will geue to vnderſtand the diſpoſition of the head, whereby mai be miniſtred a fitte remedye according to the diſpoſition of the perſonne. They that haue greate The fignes of moiſtenes. Moyſtenes of the brayne, are verye deſyrous of muche ſleepe, whoſe mouthes are full of ſpittle, and their

Noſtrells and eyes frequented with fleame: all their Motions are dulle. Suche kynde of people doe remember thinges preſent and lately done: but being done long agone, they doe either neuer, or with great paine remember them. For ſuche is the nature of moyſtenes of the brayne that it eaſelye receyuethe what imprintings or infixions it liſteth and with like eaſenes loſeth them againe.
               Wheras drines ruleth or reigneth, The fignes of drines. whiche is contrary to moiſtenes, it is knowen by the contrarie ſignes: the head ſhalbe geuē to watchinges and lightnes: and ſeldome doth the noſe, the roufe of the mouthe, and the eies expell ſuch ſuperfluities: the eyes are holowe: they ſone become balde: the eares abound with earwaxe. And as concerninge that it appertayneth to the Memorie: preſent thinges are wc more difficultie receiued or infixed then things paſt, and being receiued

they doe longer abyde: whereof it cō
                  meth to paſſe, that we haue a better Memory &amp; vtterance, of olde things, then of newe. Ancient men may herin be an example vnto vs, who will orderly recyte feates done from the beginninge of their age: but preſent thinges they eyther doe not remember, or els doe confounde them in vtterig. And this happeneth vnto aged men: becauſe that the ſtate or diſpoſinge procedeth of frequented actes: wherby it commeth to paſſe that extreme olde men doe well remember auncient thinges: becauſe they haue often pondered either them or yt like. But they doe yll remember newe thinges: becauſe that the imprinting of them in theyr Memorie is not eaſye by reaſon of the hardnes of the inſtrument of vnderſtanding.
               Where as Coldenes ruleth, there The fignes of coldnes. the face is white, the eyes are feeble, the veynes can not eaſely be perceyued:

they be geuen to muche flepe, thoſe partes that belonge to the head ſhalbe but litle warme, nor ruddye, the minde ſhalbe aſtonyed, the head troubled with gyddineſſe, and ſhall bring things to remembraunce with muche a doe. Thys qualitye (as we haue ſaid before) is very hurtful, and dothe diminiſhe the powers of the minde, and maketh them dull: for as it is the propertie of heat to moue, ſo is it the nature of coldenes to hinder the mouing: and take this for a generall rule, that the braine of a liuinge body is warmer with a ſomers aire, then otherwyſe, as alſo Galenus ſaith in his booke De vſu partium.
               
               But when Heate flouriſheth in the The fignes of heate. brayne it is eaſelye knowen by theſe fignes: for ſuche partes as are about the heade, are warmer and redder, then thoſe that be farre of: you ſhall perceiue the eyes to be more rolling, and the veynes more apparante: As

ſone as they be borne their heares growe fourth, and are blacke, harde, and curled: they are contented wyth ſmalle and ſhorte ſleepes, they haue quyckenes of motyons and remembraunce. But if the heat doe encreaſe and become vnnaturall, they ſhalbe very vigilent. This ouer much heat doth boile the liuely ſpirites, and conſumeth them into ſmokes and vapoures, and burneth yt iuyces which be apte to ingender ſpirites wherby they be deſtytute of a good or ſalfe Memorye.
               But if the two qualities be Ioyned together, you ſhall knowe theyr ſignes by as greate a proportion, as theſe qualities be great, or lytle. And the iudgement of the foreſaid things ſhall not be difficulte, as if that heat and drynes were without temperature, there ſhalbe a permixtion of yt ſence, or a freneſie accordinge to the greate or ſmall degrees of the qualities.

And therfore it is manifeſt that the Memorie may be kept, encreaſed and ererciſed by the ſcyence or practiſe Memorie maye be holpen by phiſicke. of Phiſicke, ſeing that by ſicknes it may be diminiſhed, hindered, and loſte.
               Therfore as concerning yt meanes to cure it, firſte of all the feedinge or The meanes to cure the diſſeaſes. kynde of lyuing muſt be altered according to the varietie of the cauſes, as we will herafter ſhowe. But firſt it is to be noted, that the forgetfulnes which cometh of nature cannot eaſely be taken awaye, nor yt whiche commeth of a hote and dry cauſe, the reſt of the bodye remaininge ſounde and perfecte. This alſo chauncethe ſome times, that the Memorie maye be diminiſhed or loſte by an vnaccuſtomed waye: &amp; then it is to be feared of a worſe ſickenes, (except it be ſpedelyremedyed) to witte of the Lethargie, falling ſicknes, Apoplexie, Palſey, and other ſuche kinde of diſſeaſes

the which are engendxed of fleame in the brayne, for the whiche recourſe muſt be had to the Phiſitions. Alſo if the Memorie be periſhed by extrome age, it is not in vaine to be laboured to be gotten againe by remedies: but onely muſte be contented with a conuenient kind of liuing or feeding, and muſt haue miniſtred ſucking moiſte &amp; reſtoratiue meates and linctuaries, and ſuche as maytake away the drynes.
               If the hurting of the Memory come by vehement purgations and other vnmeſurable emptines, or of drynes it muſt onely be remedied by good &amp; nouriſhing meates: for yt body being ſtrengthened, &amp; yt forces and powers gotte again, the Memorie is reſtored and fortified. Therfore meats being Obſeruations belonging to the Memorye. ful of good iuyce do help much, which be eaſelye concocted &amp; bigeſtid in the ventricle: the wine muſt be red, ripe &amp; alaied with water the exerciſe muſt

be moderate &amp; withoute wearines: the head muſt be lightly rubbed: they muſt ſlepe long; they muſte lye ſofte: they muſt vſe bathes of warme water: they muſt avoide ſweatinges: the head being ſhauen there muſt be powred on Epithemata or Fomētations of the decoction of flowers of Camomill, Melilote, Linſede, hufked Barley, &amp; Milke newly milked: it muſt be anointed in wt oyle of Lilies, or of Almondes, oyle of Dialtea, (in yt French Guimauues), &amp; with freſh Butter. Let them take cōſerue of Borage, Bewgloſſe, Orenge pilles preſerued, and ſuche lyke.
               If the annoiance of yt Memory come Other obſeruations. of a colde vntemperature of yt braine alone wtout ſubſtance, let coldnes beſet againſt heat, &amp; likewiſe drynes againſt moiſtnes, but neuertheles moderatly for in heat &amp; naturall drynes the proportiō ought to be moſt equal to the ende, yt nothinge be to muche:

becauſe that a naturail heat is not a pure heat, but cōpounded, in yt which there is a proportiō of moſt equalitie. For all kynde of heate cauſeth not a good Memory, nor al kinde of drynes but yt which is of a temperate proportion, and floweth not into an immoderate vntemperatnes, which hath yt power to take away ye acte of it owne vertue. Therfore it is to be takē hed
                     •
                   leſt the brayne be made to hote, or to Note. dry. And he that hath a tēperate head let him take hede that he meddle not with any medicines. They therefore that haue the Memorie corrupted by vnmeaſurable heat &amp; drines (yt which being ioyned together doe oftē cauſe freneſies &amp; dotings) muſt haue Oxirhodinum, powred vpon their heades, &amp; it ſhalbe eaſey to heale the reſt with ſuche things as doe coole, &amp; moiſten. And if the hurte come of ouer muche heate ioyned with ouer muche drynes, (the whiche chaunceth comonly

tyther becauſe of longe ſickeneſſes, or of exceſſyue labours of the bodye, or of fyerce ſorowefull and carneſt affections of the mynde, by the which the forces and powers of nature are greatly opened or weried &amp; the liuely ſpirits diſſolued and waſted) moiſtning and meanely warminge medicines hauing ſtrength together, ſhalbe very defencible and neceſſarie.
               But when the qualities ſhall doe Other obſeruations for the Memorye. harme not alone by thēſelues, but yt there ſhalbe alſo great aboundaunce of humours we muſt beginne wt euacuations &amp; pourginges in prouiding before a concoction or digeſtiō, if nede be. The abundance of bloude requireth yt cutting (or opening) of a vaine which muſt be done wt the councel of a lerned Phiſition: &amp; let the veyne vp on the ſhoulder be opened, the which is called Cephalica, if the head only be burthened: if yt whole body be geued, the inward or middle veines muſt be

opened. If a yelowe or fleamy choler abound, by the aduiſe of the phiſitiō, it may be purged with medicines yt driue out choler, as with Rubarde, Manna Caſia, iuyes of Roſes, electuarye of Roſes, ſyrupe of Roſes reſoluatiue or laxatyue, Tamerindi, or with golden Pittes &amp; ſuche like. If it be a blacke choler or melancolye, it muſt likewiſe be remedied by conuenient aides miniſtred by experte phiſitions as wt the ſteeping or 
                     ••••…
                  or of Sene of Epithimum, of Veratrū, in them that be ſtronger. Diaſene, Pilles Indie, &amp;c.
               But if the cauſe be (the whiche in a Moe obſeruations. maner chaneeth alwaies) colde and moiſte, theſe meanes ſhall ſerue to cure it: &amp; firſt as touchīg their liuing let thē abide aſmuch as is poſſible, in a light &amp; cleare aire not windy: for the winds do hurt much. And let them auoide to eate any thing that encreaſeth fleame, as all colde things, and

likewiſe vapourous, as oynions, and aboue al things yt fulnes &amp; lothſomenes of meates, or rawnes, &amp; muche drinke, let thē forbeare much eating of fruites, meates of hard digeſting, waſhing of thēſelues with to hote or to colde water &amp; to much drinking of water or wine. Therfore meates yt 
                  Meates permitted to the pacient. haue good nouriſhment, &amp; ingender warme &amp; liuely bloud, are very helping &amp; neceſſary: as wethers muttō, yt floſhe of Goates, Eapons, Feſantes, Partriges, whoſe egges are of a ſinguler power in this behalf, pigiōs turtle doues, litle ſparrowes, larkes thruſſhes or throſtles, &amp; O w
                     •…
                  elles: being dreſſed wt Hiſope, ſauerie, thime, maioram, Roſemary, Cloues, maces Ginger, Peper, Cinamom, Iuniper beries, chiefly in winter. Let thē eate Meates for bidden the pacient. no kind of liuing thing that is newly brought forth, becauſe their fleſhe is ſlimy &amp; clammy: nor yt braines of any thing becauſe they be fleamatike, except

the braines of a Henne, for they be peculiarly &amp; chiefly praiſed.
               Let thē alſo forbeare Marow (which is in bones) Cranes fleſhe, Fyſhe, eſpecially if it be clammye and nouriſhed in diches or holes, colde pot Herbes, Milke, Cheeſe, eſpecially much, or noughtie: fruites moiſte &amp; not ripe or oftē, but ſometimes they may eate ſharper or tarter meates, cheifly in yt winter, as Garlike, Peniroiall or Calamint, Capers being watered, muſtard is praiſed of Pithagoras: thei muſt Pithagoras eate little &amp; eſpecially at ſupper: they muſt drinke no water except it be ſod with Hony, or Cinamom or ſome other pleaſant ſpices. They muſte abſteine Moderate vſe of wine allowed. from ouer much ſlepe, and not to ſlepe in the day time, nor vpon the noddle of the head, nor vpon to much fulneſſe of meate: let them alſo take beede of ouer greate watchinges, for it weakeneth the ſpirite, and reſolueth it and ſtuffeth the head.

Let their exerciſe bee walkynge abrode, Certaine exerciſe. and that before meales, with the rubbyng of the parts of the head (but hauyng firſte bene conueniently purged) with courſe clothes, and of the feete and handes, but moderatly, and the whole body muſte be rubbed firſte, then afterwarde the head, and let the rubbyng beginne at the legges, in rubbynge by lytle and lytle the vpper partes, that the ſubſtaunce may be drawen downewarde. Let them not remain aboute pooles, fluddes, and moiſt ſokye places, let them auoyde ſouthe wyndes and rainy weather, let them dwell in lightſome and hie houſe, let their head be annoynted with helpinge and conuenient oyles (as it ſhalbe alſo deciared hereafter). Let them take heede of to muche frequenting of the act of generation, and al thinges that make feeble the braine, for the principall being weakened, that

which ſpringeth thereof muſt nedes be hurte. Let the body be kept cleare without ſuperfluities. If therefore the fleume be colde and groſſe, it muſt be attenuated, concocted and Sundry me dicines, remedies, and oyntmentes. prepared to be voyded forthe, with Ox
                     ••…
                  ll compounde or ſquilliticke or made De quinque radicibus, of Stichas, of Radiſhe rootes, with Roſe honnye, as neede ſhall require, and with conuenient waters or decoctions. And to bryng forthe the prepared ſubſtaunce or matter they muſte haue miniſtred vnto them Pilles or Cochies, or of the confection called Hiera Galeni, in puttyng to a lytle of the oyle of Caſtoreum, and of a Nutmygge. Let there be alſo added vnto it a prepared Colorynthis or Coloquintida (a kynde of wylde Gourdes) according to the diſcretion of the Phiſition then preſent: or let there be geuen them Hiera magna, wyth Nutmigs, or Hiera Rufi, of ye which

Aetius in his thyrde booke maketh Aetius in his 3. boke. mencion: alſo Yeralogadii, and other things which helpe the payne of the head that commeth of fleume: then after let ther be made Gargariſmes Fomentations, Oyntmentes, lytle Bagges, and ſuche lyke: the Gargariſme maye be made thus.
               Take Calamus aromaticus, Penyroyal or Calamint, Hyſope, Thyme of euery one a hand full, let them be ſodde in water euen to the halfe of the iuſt quantitie, and to fyue vnces ſtrained through a Colander, put an vnce and a halfe of Scilliticke Oximell, and mingle halfe an vnce of Koſe honny, and let it be gargaled warme in a morning faſtynge. Alſo if there nede a Gliſter, let it be made accordinge to the diſeaſes that haue reſpect to the head: neſynges or ſternutations may be prouoked, as with Pepper, Struthion or Condiſi, Elleborus albus, Lyngwort or neeſyng pouder,

Flourdeluce, and ſuche lyke: or of theſe, with Turpentine, and with a Gumme called Ladanum, let there be made ſneeſyng medecines. Moreouer yf the fleume procede further, good odours or Apophlegmatiſmi (medecines that purge fleume and ſpittle) do much belp: Cubebes maſticated or chewed, doe ſucour by al meanes: applye to their eares oyle of Caſtoreum, oyle of Lauander, oyle of Spike. If ſo be yt either there be not ſo great aboundance of ſuch humors in the body, or that the pacient be not of ſo great ſtrengthes, we muſt firſt dryue the fleume oute of the whole body by an eaſie purgation, and becauſe it ſhall rather ſuffre yt powers and forces to remaine in the members &amp; parts of the body then to take them awaye, therfore let it be in this maner. Take Aloes waſſhed wyth the iuyce of Thyme or Maioram or wyth their waters one Dramme,

Trochiſces of Agaricke two drammes, A dramme is the .
                        〈◊〉
                     . Parte of an vnce. Maſticke, Cubebe, Nutmygs, of eche of them ſixe graines, with pleaſaunt wyne let there be made twelue Pilles, of the whiche ſeuen muſt be taken in the morning with the ſirupe of Stichas: and the reſt three dayes after, two houres after ſupper: afterwardes they muſte be ſtrengthened with comfortinge electuaryes, ſuch as folowe o
                     •
                   the lyke. But ouerpaſſīg alſo yt pur
                     •…
                  g locals as aboue, if it be nedeful. Againe for the purgatiō theſe pilles alſo do properlye agree. Take of male Frankenſcence, of fyne Myrrhe, of Ginger, euery of them a dramme and a halfe, of the pouder of a Houpe or Lapwinges heade .ii. drammes, of Galyngalle twoo ſcruples, of A Scruple is the third parte of a dramme. Hiera maior one Dramme and a halfe, of oyle of Caſtoreum, of Colocynthys, of either of them half a ſcruple, dreeſſe theym wyth good

Turpentine or with Syrope of Stichas, and let there be made paſt (or dowe) and miniſter vnto them but a fewe Pilles, and thoſe great: vpon a lyght ſupper goynge to bedwarde: alſo ſuche thyngs as do diſſolue may be taken awaye, that they may onely nouriſhe: theſe are moſt chiefe and ſinguler in this cauſe, and do principallye helpe the Memorie. Afterwardes to ſtrengthen the Pacient let there be made ſuche an electuaryc Strengtheninges for the paciēt. or in lyke maner.
               Take of conſerue of Roſemary flowers, of Baulme gentle, of eche of them an vnce, of Helycompane preſerued, of greene Ginger, either of them halfe an vnce, of Orenge pilles preſerued ſixe drammes, of Diatrionpipereon, of Diambar either of them halfe an vnce, with a lytle Aquavite diſtilled together wyth good wyne in glaſſe veſſelles, or with Baulme water, or with the

flowers of Lilium conuallium: mingle them together: and let the Pacient take a dramme or twaine in the mornynge two houres before hys meate, and halfe a dramme at bedde tyme. Nucha (called alſo ſpinalis medulla) is a ſubſtaunce procedyng from the brayne, alonge the backe.
               
               It is alſo to be noted that the Nucha is colder then the brayne, and therefore it endureth and ſuffereth colde thinges better then warme, and for that cauſe it muſt be remembred, leſte the cauſers of coldenes, whiche come from without doe not fall vpon the hinder part of the head. And therefore ſuche medecines as cauſe warmenes as well withoute as wtin the body are to be miniſtred. Other remedies &amp; oyntmentes. Thyme, Penyroyall, (or Calamunt) Organie (or wylde Maioram) or ſuche lyke of this kynde muſte be ſodden in Vinegre and layed to the Noſtrelles of the Pacient: annoynt the roufe of the mouth with verye 
                     〈◊〉
                   or ſharpe medecines. Alſo in

the ſommer tyme annoynt the out ſyde of the head with warme Oyle, as wt Oyle of Rue, Oyle of Dill, &amp;c. And in the Winter tyme wyth the Oyle of Flowerdeluce, in the which there ſhalbe ſodden commen Sauory or buſh Calamint, Pepper, Bay berries, in puttyng to a lytle Vinegre for to make it perce. Alſo Oyle of Caſtoreum ſhalbe verye good to anoynt the hynder parte of the head withall: or ſuche an oyntment as foloweth.
               Take oyle of Tyles, of Caſtoreū either of them halfe an vnce, of the rootes of Acorus or greate Galingale, of Phu or Valerian, either of them a ſcruple, of Pellitorie, of Rue or Herbe grace, either of them half a ſcruple, with as much waxe as ſhal ſuffice. Let there be made an oyntment, with the whiche the head being ſhauen ſhalbe annoynted: and therevpon let there be layed a lytle

bagge within the which there muſte be of the flowers of Roſemarye, of Baulme gentle, of Lauander, ech of them half a handfull, of the flowers of an Elder tree a handful, of Stichas iij. drammes, of Nutmygges, of Lignum Aloes, of Maces, ech of them a ſcruple, beinge beaten together let them be put into a ſilke bagge.
               Another ointment greatly helping the diminution of the Memorye and forgetfulnes.
               ¶ Take oyle of Elder flowers an vnce, oyle of Been .ii. vnces, oyle of Euforbium, oyle of Caſtoreum, either of them halfe an vnce, Vinegre .iii. drammes, mingle them together, &amp; let the place be anoynted therwithal. Alſo oyle of philoſophers (ſo called of Meſue. 
                  Meſue) being anoynted vpon the hinder part of the heade, dothe wonderfully repare the Memorye.
               Another oyntment.
               ¶ Take yt rootes of Rew, Bugloſſe

                     〈1 page missing〉
                  
                  
Phu or Valerian with the rootes eche of them .iiij. vnces, of oyle of Caſtoreum of ij. or .iij. yeares olde, of the ſeede of Aſhe kayes which is lyke to a byrdes tounge, either of them two dragmes: let them be made into pouder and mingled together: then take of the iuyce of Eufragia or Eybryght, of Clarie, of Veruen, ech of thē .iiij. vnces, of the pithe of Anacardum an Vnce, of the olde Greaſe of a male. Beare aſmuch as ſhal nede, let there be made a moiſte oyntment, and put it in a copper or tinne veſſell, that it may remaine moiſte, for els it is nothing worthe, and therwithal anoint the hinder part of yt head. But if you will ſonner helpe it, or that the pacient haue a colder head and that it be in a colde tyme, then let the noſtrells within be anoynted with this odoriferous ointment. Take oile of ſwets Spike an vnce, Cloues a ſcruple, Am bergriſe halfe a ſcruple, Muſke fyue

graines, white Waxe aſmuch as nedeth: alſo a droppe of the ſame, before the puttig in of ye wax, being powred warme into the eares is verye good. Meſue .2. deſcriptione Antid
                        •
                      tarii.
               
               A plaiſter alſo of Muſtarde (of the which Meſue ſpeaketh in the ſecond deſcription of the boke of Medicines) is very expedient being laid to ye cold afflicted hinder part of the head: or els oyle of Muſtard ſeed
                     •
                  .
               Alſo ye aforſaid medecines, aſwell as thoſe yt folowe (without anye former purgatiō) are very good for them that are vexed wt coldenes alone without great 
                     ••••…
                  es. And beſides theſe before reherſed there be other yt helpe in wardlye, as righte Acorus preſerued which I ſuppoſe to be Calamus aromaticus or Galyngalle,) Sugre, flowers of Betonnye, Roſemarye, Lauander, Spikenarde, Baulme Gentle, in puttynge to longe Peper, Cloues, Cinamom, Nutmeges and ſuch like odoriferous things.

Alſo Ginger preſerned the quantitie of a filberde nut doth help much eſpecially in a cold and moiſt ventricle, as it is almoſt in all or in yt greater part of them that are troubled with ſuche cauſe &amp; diſſeaſe, for it doth amend the Memory beinge taken in yt morning (not in warme ſeaſōs) foure howers before meate.
               This alſo doth not a litle help.
               ¶ Take Frakenſence, Ciperus, lōg Peper, Saffron, Mirrhe, of ech alike, mingle them wt Hony, and of yt ſame take euery day a dramme at the howers aforſaid, &amp; ſpecially in yt mornig.
               Another for yt ſame purpoſe cheifly working in aged perſones.
               ¶ Take of ye hony of Anacardum, of whit Frākenſence, of Ciperus, of right Acorus, ech alike .ij. parts, of round &amp; lōg Peper either alike .i. part, of Mirobalanū cepulū, ceruleum, either alike .ij. partes, of Cummin .i. part, of Hony aſmuch as ſhal ſerue, let there

be miniſtred .ij. dragmes euery morning: Diambar alſo is very good.
               Alſo a confection of Anacardū doth profit much yf it be wel made, &amp; vſed vi. monthes after, for it ſharpneth the witte &amp; ſence and purifieth the vnder ſtanding, it calleth againe yt mind, it healeth the lethargie &amp; goute, it helpeth much yt diſſeaſe of the hentricle &amp; the bealy coming by coldnes, but it is to be geuē to them yt be aſtonined, &amp; yt haue a very colde &amp; reumy head. And it is thus made: takeof Mirobalanū empeliticū, belezicū, of white &amp; long Peper, ech of thē xij. drammes, of Ginger, of yt hony of Anacardū, ei ther of thē an vnce, of oile of Caſtoreum, of Stirax or Storax, of Cloues ech of thē v. drammes, of the flowers of Camomil, of Bay beries, of Ciperus, ech of thē iij. drammes, of Hony aſmuch as ſhall ſuffice, mingle them after the maner of an electuary. Let a ſcruple of it be miniſtred at nyght,

or the biggenes of a ſmall or filberde nutte, that is halfe a Dramme, with warme wyne of the decoctyon of Anyſe and Fenell ſeedes: it maye alſo be taken in the morning.
               But let theim that take it refraine from fleumatyke meates, from anger, from lecherye and dronckenes.
               And before that Anacards be put into anye compounde Medecynes, they muſte be dreſſed in thys maner that foloweth.
               Take Anacards and beate theym verye well in a Morter and then put them in moſte ſtronge Vinaigre by the ſpace of ſeuen dayes, then ſeeth theym wythe a ſofte fyer in the ſame Vynaygre tyll there remaine but the thyrde parte of the Vinaygre: then ſtrayne the Groundes thereof whyche remayne in the botome of the veſſell, after that the Vinaygre is firſte lyghtelye ſtrayned or powred oute, and thoſe groundes

beynge putte through the ſtrainer or Colander, occupye theym in medecynes: for alſo the fruytes of Anacrds are not putte in medecynes to be taken at the mouth, excepte they be firſte dreſſed in this or like maner.
               Yf ſo be you wyll make Honny of. Anacardum, you muſte putte wythe the ſame Anacardum ſo ſodoen in Vynaygre, aſmuche claryfyed Honnye, and lette theym boyle bothe together tyll they be thycke, and ſo ſhall youe haue Honnye of Anacardum, the whiche hathe a wounderfull operatyon in the foreſayde dyſſeaſes, yf you geue thereof a Drammo or two in the mornyng,
               In Sycylya whyleſte the Anacardij be newe they are putte into puryfyed Honny, and doe remaine long therin, and ſuch is called Honny

of Anacardum, and it is vſed with out the fruites thereof, and is putte in electuaries. If ther be ij. drammes geuen of yt Hony, it reneweth yt Memory of it owne property.
               Alſo Acorus (yt is Galingale) is an approued thing, being nouriſhed and ſodden in Hony &amp; reſerued as yt nuts &amp; rootes are conſerued: likewiſe long Peper nouriſhed &amp; ſodden in Hony &amp; preſerued, for they do kepe &amp; encreaſe the Memorye: at euery time receyue a Dramme.
               Another proued 
                     •…
                  forme of a pouder.
               ¶ Take Frākenſence a dragme, Cyperus, Peper, Saffrō, Mirrhe, ech of them ij. drammes, let thē be beaten fine, &amp; driuen through a ſearce, and ſo make it into a pouder, of the whiche the paciente ſhall receyue euerye mornyng when he riſeth a dramme or at euenynge when he goethe to bedde.
               Another proued.
               
                  
¶ Take Cummyn, Pepper either of them two drammes, whyte Sugar thre drammes: let thē be beaten &amp; reduced into pouder, take therof a dramme euery day in the mornyng.
               Another likewiſe proued.
               ¶ Take whyte Frankenfence a dramme, longe or whyte Pepper a ſcruple, make them into pouder, which muſte be dronke earely in the morninge all at one draughte, and that manye dayes, with three vnces of Honny water, or of Cinamon and Cloues moderatly decocted.
               Another as good and certaine.
               ¶ Take Cummyn fyue drammes, newe Pepper one dramme, righte Acorus or Galingale, Cyperus, black Myrobalanum, of ech of them two drammes, Honny of Anacardū, (wherof we ſpake before) one dramme, common Honny thre vnces and a halfe: let ſuche of them as maye be punned, be punned together, and incorporated

with Honny, and preferued in a boxe: and rereyue thereof euery morning two drammes.
            
            
               
                  ❧ The thyrd Chapter ſheweth the principall endomages of the Memorie in what ſort ſoeuer they be.
               IT behoueth to auoyde vniuerſally rawnes or vndigeſſions, as moſt daungerous and hurtefull both to the reaſon, and alſo to the whole bodye.
               It is verye ill to drynke muche Wyne eſpeciallye to them that be ſtronge: for it doth vehemently moyſten Exceſsiue vſe of wine in forbiddē
                   the head, and there is almoſte nothing that ſo ſoone bringeth forgetfulnes, as doeth ſuperfluous moyſtenes.
               The exceſſiue outwarde coldenes hurteth the Memorie, and chiefly in the night when the head is vncouered. To goe through Myer in

cold tymes, and bare footed doeth aboue the reſte, hurte and coole the brayne, and weakeneth the eyes.
               Alſo to muche heate doth ſometymes greatlye trouble the reaſon and hurte the Memorie.
               You muſte forbeare the eatinge of fuminge meates and drynkes, as Garlyke, Leekes, Oynions, alſo Cheeſe and Peaſon: Brothes, Potage, and all ouer moyſte thynges are to be refrayned, eſpeciallye at night: alſo all ill chewinge or eating is noughte.
               To drynke after meate (whyles the meates be digeſtynge, interruptynge the ſame) namelye after ſupper, is verye hurtfull both to the Memorie and the brayne.
               Ouer muche reſte dothe weaken the heate: reteyneth and aggrauateth the ſuperfluities, and therefore hurteth the Memorie.
               
                  
It is verye noyſome to ſlepe vpon meate, to witte before that the meate be deſcended into the bottom of the Ventricle: therefore take your ſlepe two houres after: hauyng your head lying hie &amp; wel couered, but not ſuperfluouſly, becauſe that to muche couerynge doeth either weaken the head in reſoluynge: or els doth ſtuffe it in drawing.
               Frequented venerye doth hurte either with a full ſtomarke or a hungry, or after the whiche no ſlepe doth folowe, or nere vnto the Eclipſe of the Moone, or with anye other then their owne ſpouſe.
               To ſleepe hoſed and ſhoed eſpecially with foule ſockes, doth hinder the Memorie, becauſe of the reflection of ye vapours: feebleth the ſyght, and cauſeth the body to waxe whote and burne.
               Herbes eaten rawe, doe verye muche hurte the Memorie: lykewiſe

Nuttes, Filberds, &amp; Cheſtnuttes.
               Alſo to ſee or heare thinges that pleaſe not the mynde: and ſuch lyke Simptomata or griefes of the minde.
               Feare doth oppreſſe the Memorie, or endurynge ſadnes: alſo a penſiue care of houſholde buſyneſſe is hurtfull.
               Alſo immoderate ſleepe and violent vomiting.
               Vinegre and all ſharpe thinges doe the lyke: but if Vinegre be vſed of fattē and fleumaticke perſonnes let it be made of ſtronge Wyne, and let it be warme, and vſed ſeldome &amp; that with Cynamon: and put Calamus aromaticus or Galingale into the Vinegre veſſell, Penyroyall or Calamint: There be ſome ſaye that the bones of Cockes beinge ſucked, do breede the Lethargie.
            
            
               
                  ❧ The fourth Chap. telleth likewiſe the perticular helpes of the Memorie.
               
                  
THe fruites that bynde or reſtraine of Nature or arte, in keepinge fumes or vapours from ryſyng, beynge moderately taken after meates, doe greatlye helpe the Memorie.
               The moderate eating or refection of temperate meate and drynke, as of Hennes and Patriges, and eſpecially of the braynes, doth not only comfort the Memorie, but alſo the whole bodye: for lyke as Cacochimia (that is euill nouriſhing meates) do hurte the workynges of the ſoule: ſo Euchimia (that is good nouriſhynge meates) do keepe them ſafe, &amp; chiefly in youth. And therefore a highe witte doth ſeldome ſpringe oute of a meane or ſimple ſtorke, except there chaunce a liberall education.
               Moderate and conuenient exerciſe before meate, doth not only profit the Memorie, but likewiſe the other functiōs of the body, alſo let the

mouing be long, and the exerciſe laborious, according to the ſtrength of the body, that it may reſolue the ſuperfluities and let it be in fayre and drye places: and (if it be poſſible) let all the parts of the body be exerciſed.
               A conuenient and due expulſion of ſuperfluities by the entrailes, by the roufe of the mouth, by the mouth, by the eares, by the vrine, by the rubbyng of the head with a combe, is very expedient to the memoratiue vertue, yf the exerciſe be done before ſleepe and after.
               An often callinge to mynde of The Memorye muſte be exerciſed. things ſeene or hard, doth ſtrengthē and confirme the Memorie: for there is nothyng that is ſo ſoone encreaſed by diligence, or diminiſhed by necgligence, as Memorie it ſelfe is: becauſe except it be throughlye tylled and exerciſed with a continuall meditation, it is ſoone corrupted by fluggiſhenes.
               
                  
A temperate gladnes, and an he neſt delectation, eſpecially in the meditation of ſciences, doeth not onely augment the Memorie, but alſo the intellectiue vertue, and all the other vertues of the body.
               To waſhe ones feete often in warme water wherein hath bene boyled Baulme gentle, Baye leaues, Camomile, and ſuche lyke, is verye good for the Memorie, ye head and the eyes.
               To waſhe ones head euerye tenth daye with Lee, in the whyche there hath a whyle ſodden Camomile or Aſarum, Baulme gentle, Sage, ſwete Maioram, or Maioram gentle, Baye leaues, or ſuche lyke, and Roſes in the Sommer, doth coroborat and fortifie the Memorie, as it ſhall alſo be more plainlye ſpoken of in the Chapter folowing.
               To ſtande after meales, or to walke ſoftly vp &amp; downe, by meanes

whereof the meate maye deſcende to the botome of the ventricle, is very expedient for the good digeſtion of the meates.
               To take Coriander after meate, being well dreſſed with Sugre, doth let the vapoures from aſcending to yt heade, and helpeth the Memorie: alſo Diacotoneon doth the ſame.
               To chewe Maſticke with a lytle Ginger being faſting, doth purge the heade from moiſte fleumatike humors without any greif or paine, and the Memorie being ſo hindred is ther with cōforted, Galingale beinge put to the noſtrells dothe ſtrengthen the colde brayne.
               Take the whiteſt Frankenſence beate it into pouder, put it in pure and ſymple colde water, and drincke it at the encreaſe of the Moone, at the ſpringe of the daye, at noone, and at the Sunne ſettinge: and it wyll cauſe a good Memorye, a ſharppe

witte, and drye the brayne and the ventricle.
               Symeon Sethi affirmeth that the Simeon Sethi. Galle of a Partrige being anoynted once in a moneth, vppon the vaynes of the temples, ſo that it doe perce thorowe, is verye profitable to confirme the Memorie.
               Baulme gentle eſtabliſheth the Memorie, quickneth the witte, and in what faſhion ſoeuer it be eaten maketh a mā ſtudious and dilligent the whiche vertue alſo Creſſes doc bringe to paſſe in them that be colde and olde, wherof it is come into a cō
                  mon prouerbe, Ede naſturtium, Eate Creſſes. Baulme gentle alſo beſides this bringeth quietnes to the minde in cauſinge a pleaſant ſleepe to come to the heade: It is alſo ſayde that the fleſhe of A Turtle Doue dothe encreaſe the witte.
               The braynes of a Henne dothe helpe the witte and the Memorye,

in ſuche ſorte that it hathe broughte ſome agayne to their wittes, that beganne to dote.
               The ſeede of Orminum or houſholde Clarye dothe wonderfullye ayde the reſtoringe of the Memorye, yf it be taken in poulder with ſome meate or drinke. And the ſcrapinges of Yuorie dothe remedye forgetfulnes, if a little thereof be taken in the morning in a litle wine.
               Alſo a Grayne of whyte Frankenſence when you goe to bedde, dothe greatlye helpe the clammye or glewed ſubſtaunce: for it dryeth vp the moyſtenes of the heade and the Ventricle, and ſo eaſethe the Memorye. Vſe thys after a purgaryon twyſe or thryſe in a weeke, yf there be much moiſtnes.
               Twoo Drammes in wayghte of the confectyon of Ple
                     •
                  eſar
                  
                     •
                  hotycum taken when youe

goe to ſleepe, or Myrobalanum Cepulum preſerued and well chewed beynge taken in the mornynge fowre howres before meate once in a weeke, dothe wounderfullye reſtore the Memorye eſpecially yf it be hurte of a moiſte cauſe. For Myrohalani cepuli, preſerued doe ſtrengthen the vnderſtandynge and in a maner conſerue you the. So doe paſſula.
               
               It is good to take twiſe or thryſe in a weeke preſerued Ginger, the bygnes of a ſmall nut or litle cheſte nut, for it helpeth muche an emptye ſtomacke. The confection of Diambar hath the ſame effect
               Remember that in a moyſte ſubſtaunce or cauſe there procede fyrſte purginges. For a moyſte ſubſtance is for the moſte parte the cauſe of the weakenes of the Memorie, as it is alredy declared.
            
            
               
               
                  ❧ The fifte chapter comprehendeth certaine beſt approued and choſen medicinable compounded remedies, and preſeruatiues greatly encreaſing the Memorye.
               
                  ¶ A Medecine wonderfully helping the Memorie, and lethargie or forgetfulnes: it comforteth the ventricle and all the members weakened by fleume and coldenes.
                  Take Ginger, Galingale Maſtike Cūmin, Organny, ech of thē vi. drammes, Nutmige, Calamus Aromaticus, Aſarum or Fole foote, Carpeſium, yt is Cubebe, Lignū aloes, Mace, Percely ſeede, Ammios eche of theym .ij. drammes, whyte Frākenſence, Cloues, Cardamomum or graines, Zedoaria, Piretrum or Pellitorye, Caſtoreum, lōg &amp; blacke Peper, Coſtum or Cocus, Ciperus, eche of them .iij. dragmes dry Mintes half an vnce: let theym all be punned and beaten to pouder, and with a ſufficiente

quantytye of Penydes and of puryfyed Honnye, let there be made a linctuarye: The whiche and the reſte alſo you muſte vſe, chieflye in colde wether or not ouer hote, &amp; that a good ſpace betwene.
               
               
                  
                     ❧ Pilles that are good for a languiſhing brayne eſpecially in aged and colde folkes.
                  Take ſwete Amber or elect Ambargriſe one Dramme, Lignum Aloes halfe a ſcruple, Cubebe twoo ſcruples: with the pureſt and ſweteſt wyne make .xv. Pilles, and miniſter a cople of them before ſupper.
               
               
                  ¶ Catapotia, or Pilles very effectuall to the Memorie.
                  Take Cubebes, buſhe Calamint, Nutmiges, Cloues, eche of theym a dragme and a halfe, pure Frankenſence,

fine Mirrhe, orientall Ambargriſe, ech of them a dramme &amp; a halfe Muſke .v. graines: with Maiorā water make Pilles, &amp; geue one at bedde time, and two at Sunne riſing fyue howers before meat, in Somer by a monthes ſpace, in the ſpringe and in harueſt ſeldomer.
               
               
                  ¶ An odoriferous or ſwete ſwellinge Apple for the Memorie
                  Take the rootes of Floure de luce, the ſeedes of Seſclis or Oſiar, that is, Syler montanum or wylde Cummyn, Stichas, eche of theym two Drammes, Nuttmygge half a Dramme, Minte a Dramme, Ambergriſe, Frankenſence, buſhe Calaminte, Storax, Lignum Aloes eche of theym halfe a Dramme, Ladanum as muche as ſhall ſuffyce, make thereof an Apple by arte: the whiche notwithſtanding in winter

muſt be made of warmer things, and in ſommer of colder.
               
               
                  A moſte proued Experiment for the witte and Memorie, which is ſaid to be of Ariſtotle,
                  Take Beares Greaſſe or fatte Ariſtolle. whiche he hathe in the righte ſhoulder or ſklyſe, and put the ſame in the ſayde Beares bladder together with his vrine or water and let them ſtand together eight dayes: than pul it out and take the iuyce of Orminum or houſholde Clarie, Cybrighte, Veruene, Bugloſſe, Phu or Valerian, Aloes, of eche a lyke quantitye, and mingle theym together wyth the ſayde fatte ſturringe theym vppon the fyer wyth a wodden ſkliſe, till it come to a thycke oyntment of ye which take when you will the quantytye

of a lytle Beane, and anoynt the forehead, and the temples rubbyng them a lytle whyle, and you ſhall remember the thynges that you haue harde.
               
               
                  ¶ A comfortynge Water or Lees for the waſhyng of a cold and moyſt head, alſo it helpeth the Memorſe, and it muſt be of the Aſhes of Twigges, or of an Oke, then after let theſe thinges boyle in it.
                  Take righte Acorus, Stichas, Baye leaues, Roſemary, Iua or Chamapithys, Sage, eche of them a handfull: with this waſhe the head: and after the waſhynge bathe the foreparte of the head with a lytle Aqua vite, and ſprinckle it with the pouder folowynge.
                  Take Penyroyall, buſhe Calamint, Cloues, Sandarake, Mace, Stichas, drye Mynte, Maioram, of

eche fyue drammes: mingle them and make thereof a fyne pouder, and after the ſprincklynge laye it vppon hempe towe. Alſo at other tymes when you goe to bedde put of the ſame pouder vpon the hinder parte of the head, the head alſo beinge vnwaſhed, for it dryeth. &amp;c.
               
               
                  ¶ Another Lee for to comfort the head and Memorie.
                  Take walle Yuye, Roſemarye Baye leaues, Stichas, Marubium or Horehounde, or Betony, and let them boyle in the Lee, and therewith you ſhall waſhe your head. Cipres nuttes haue almoſte the ſame operation being often vſed. And that you mai haue Sope wt the ſame Lee.
                  Take Venice or Frenche Sope two pounde, Calamus aromaticus thre drammes, Maioram, Thyme, Stichas arabica, Nigella, Cloues,

Cardamomum, eche of them two drammes, mingle thereto the rootes of drye and ſweete Flouredeluce an vnce, and then mingle it with Sope fynely cut or ſcrapped in being well heated, &amp; make lumpes or pilles in maner of a Walnutte, but yf you can not myngle them together by reaſon of the dryneſſe of the thynges, then put thereto a lytle Maioram water or ſome other conuenient. Afterwardes let the head be well dryed in rubbynge it wyth warme lynnen clothes: but holde not youre head neare to the fyer, leſte Vapours bee drawen to it and the head ſtuffed.
               
               
                  ¶ Another, whiche is verye good for a moyſte head, and is to be vſed once or twyſe in a weke.
                  
                     
Take Senae, Roſes, Camomill flowers, Acorus, Stichas, Bay leaues, Cypres nuttes, Sage, Iua, Yuye berries, eche of them an equal quantitie, boyle theſe in the Winter in Lee to waſhe youre head withall: but in Sommer take awaye Stichas, and put in Roſes, and a fewe Myrtell berries, and vſe it not to whote.
               
               
                  ¶ Another moſt excellent remedye, but muche more difficile to begotten.
                  Take the flowers of drye Cytrons, Bugloſſe, Roſemary, eche of them two drammes, Comomil, Violettes, Roſes eche of them a dram and a halfe, Seſelis two drammes, Semen viticis or Agnus caſtus or Tutſon ſeede, fielde Rue, eche of them .iiii. Scruples, greene Baye leaues, Maioram, Stichas, Sage, Elder flowers, Artimiſia or Mugeworte,

eche of them three drammes: let them be verye well beaten, and powred into three pounde of the beſt Aquavite, and ſixe vnces of whyte Squilliticke Vinegre that is verye ſtronge, and let them reſt together in a glaſſe veſſell well couered for the ſpace of two dayes, and then diſtill them ouer aſhes with a ſofte fyer: afterwardes take good oyle of Turpentyne diſtilled eyghtene vnces, oyle of Been diſtilled eyght vnces, of the foreſayde water diſtilled xxiiii .vnces: in ſteede of oyle of Been you may take oyle of Beares greaſe diſtilled, but it is better yf you take of eyther of them halfe: but if you can fynde neither of them, take Elder oyle: put to theſe foreſayde thinges Mennes heares well burned, for of their owne propertie they cauſe wakefulnes, and ſtyrre vp them that haue the Lethargie: let them be mingled and diſtilled in a glaſſen

veſſell, euen vntyll all the water be drawen out, and kepe that ſame water a part: then take Euforbium .iiii. drammes, longe Pepper thre drammes and a halfe, Cummyn three drammes, cleare male Frankenſence two vnces and two drammes, Maſticke, Myrre elect, either of them an vnce, Anacardum well beaten an vnce and two drammes, Carpobalſamum, iiii. drammes, Pulpa Caſtorei, halfe a dramme, Myrob
                        •
                     lanū empeliticum, foure drammes and a halfe, Opopanax three vnces, rawe Sylke &amp; finely cut in pieces a drāme and a halfe, Coſtum, rootes of femall Pionye, fyne Cyperus, eche of them foure Scruples, Ladanum three drammes, Dragons bloude, (that is a Gumme ſo named for the lykenes of it) two drammes and a halfe, cleare Bdellium ſyxe drammes: let them that wyll be broughte to pouder be verye well beaten to

pouder, and all powred into all the foreſayde Oyle, and let them ſo reſte in a temperate bathe the ſpace of fyue dayes together in a glaſſe veſſell cloſſe ſtopped, but let them be ſtyrred or myngled with a drye reede or ſtycke euerye daye: then let them be ſtrayned forthe, and verye well truſhed or preſſed with a courſe cloth whiche hath fyrſte bene put into the water and well wronge oute: and afterwardes let the Oyle (beynge in ſuche ſorte ſtrained) be diſtilled, or let it bee ſo done withall as is done in the diſtillynge of Oyle of Ladanum: To wytte, fyrſte begynne wyth a ſmalle Fyer of Coales in an Ouen or Chymney, tyll in ſo boylynge ſoftelye, it begynne to diſtyll ſomewhat meanelye, then procede on wyth a ſmall and eaſye flame, ſomme tymes renewynge it, vntyll the moyſte and ſubtylle

ſubſtaunce of the Oyles that were put thereunto be almoſt all diſtiled, the whiche you maye perceyue by your eye ſyghte, but better by the weyght of the Oyle that is diſtilled: then holde on with a meane fyer of coales, in puttyng awaye altogether the flame: and that which is diſtilled ſhalbe kepte in a glaſſe veſſell well ſtopte. Laſt of all take Gallia muſcata, Cloues, Maces, Cubebe, Nutmygges, Cardamomū eche of them foure Scruples, Spyke, Calamus aromaticus, the outwarde barkes of an Orenge, of eche two Scruples, good Lignum aloes, two drammes and a halfe, fyne Ambergriſe three drammes and a halfe, of the beſte Muſke a dramme and a halfe: Let them be all beaten fynely to pouder, and mingled with all the foreſayde diſtilled Oyle, and let them ſo remaine together two or three dayes in a temperate heate, and then afterwardes

let them be diſtilled by their owne kinde, and be brought to a ſubtill or pure ſubſtaunce, and let them be kept in a ſtrong glaſſe veſſell well ſtopped with waxe, and it is exceding good. The maner of vſīg of it is ſuch, that firſte if it nedeth there be a purgation made of all or of the head, and than vſe it in the beginninge of the moneth of Nouember continuallye by the ſpace of fyftye dayes, and afterwardes once in eighte daies, and conſequently alſo when you will reduce thinges into youre Memorye, takinge it late in the euening when you purpoſe to rehearſe, preach or entreate, of a thing in the morning.
               
               
                  ¶ Alſo in a colde affectyon thys oyle folowynge ſhalbe notable good.
                  
                     
Take Turpentine reſine if it may be gotten, (for it is broughte for the moſt parte out of Cyprus to Venice) or in place thereof take laricine the waight of a pounde, olde bricke or tile after the boyling or making not moiſtened, the which being broken in pieces and ſet on fyer and quēched haue bene in olde oyle of Olyues, halfe a pound: Maſtike an vnce, let the tiles be rubbed or beatē in peices, and being well mingled with Turpentine let them be ſet to the fyer of an ouer or furnays in a glaſſe or earthen veſſell well hardened or nealed, and let the licoures that remayne be gathered a ſunder, for there will runne out three of a dyuers colour, good better, and beſte of al.
               
               
                  ¶ An Ointment for the ſame purpoſe.
                  Take the fatte of a Beare, of a Capon, of a Henne, of a Cowe, and

Yuye Gumme, eche of theym an equall wayght, and deſtil them al in a Lembicke of glaſſe with a ſofte fyer: with the which olye anointe your tē
                     ples and the pulſes of youre handes thriſe in a weeke, and you ſhall perceiue it to be an excellent good thing.
               
               
                  ¶ An Ointment wherwith you may moderately anoynte your temples onely in colde weather.
                  Take the fatte of a Moldwarpe of a Beare, of a Weſell, and of Caſtoreum, echof them a like, the iuyce of Betonye, and of Roſemary, either of them a like: and of al this make an oyntment, the whiche (as it is ſayde) Ariſtotle dyd vſe. Ariſtotle.
                  
               
               
                  ¶ To thende that you may retayne thinges profoundly and perpetually in your Memory, and that you may learne a thinge ſpedely: this haue many great men vſed.
                  
                     
Take the rootes of Langdebefe, the rotes of Valerian either of them foure vnces, the Rootes of Rewe twoo vnces: make thereof very fyne Poulder then take the Iuyce of Eybryghte, of Clarye or Orminum, and of Verueyne, eche of them foure vnces: lette the Iuyce be well ſtrayned oute thoroughe a lynnen clothe, then myngle the Iuyce together, and the poulders by theym ſelues, afterwardes take the vithe of Anacardum the waighte of an once, and make a poulddr as aforeſayd Alſo take the ſeede of Aſſhe kayes whyche is lyke a Byrdes tounge, and make a verye fyne Poulder, then myngle all the foreſayde thinges together, to wytte, the Iuyces and the Poulders, and take an earthen Glaſſye fryenge panne, and ſette it ouer the fyer, and putte therein Beares greaſſe, and poure it or melte it by lyttle and

lyttle, and caſte into the ſame the ſayde Poulders alwayes myngling it wyth the Iuyces, and putte in ſtyll of the ſame greaſe tyll it become a verye pure oyntmente wherwith annoynte youre temples and the parte of youre Memorye, and youre foreheade, and the parte of the Crowne of youre heade towardes the noddle: and doe this twiſe or thryſe in a yeare, and you muſt contynewe ſo in oyntynge, euen more or leſſe as it ſhall neede: for Sorcerye is ſuperſtious and vaine. thys excedeth in vertue the ſuperſtytious arte of Sorcerye.
               
               
                  ¶ To the ſame purpoſe.
                  Take eyghte cuppefulles of cō
                     mon water, leaues of Yuye, of Stichas, eyther of theym a pounde and a halfe, putte them together into the water to boyle tyll the water be almoſt conſumed away, then take thē
                     
out and preſſe or wrynge them wel, and put therein a lytle Turpentine waſhed in Roſe water, then waſhe your head with good Lee, and when it is dryed annoynte your temples and the hynder parte of youre head with the foreſayd lycoure.
               
               
                  ¶ An odoriferous or ſweete ſmellyng Apple for the comfortynge of a colde brayne,
                  Take Ladanum, Lignum aloes, Storar, eche of them a dramme, Cloues, Nutmygges, Baſill ſeede eche of them halfe a dramme, with Roſe water, in the which there hath been diſſolued or put a lytle Muſke and Ambergriſe, make there of an Apple.
               
               
                  ¶ To haue a profounde and good Memorie, or to recouer it again if it be loſt by weakenes or infirmity: it alſo helpeth the giddines
                  
                     
Take Roſemarye, that is Libanotis, Borage, Camomill, Violets, Roſes, eche of them an vnce, Stichas Baye leaues, Maioram, Sage eche of them two vnces: cutte or chop them all and putte them in excellent good wyne, and after a dayes ſpace diſtil them in a Lembick of glaſſe or earth well nealde, and being diſtilled kepe them, and put therin ſwete ſmellynge Turpentyne a pounde, whyte Frankenſence eyghte vnces, M
                        ••…
                     cke, Myrrhe, Bdellium, Anacardum, eche of them foure vnces: bruyſe all theſe, and let it ſo ſtande fyue dayes the diſtillation being couered, then diſtill them ſo long with a good fyer tyll you haue Oyle of them, the whiche youmuſte keepe well cloſed in a glaſſe bottell harde ſtopped with Ware and parchment. The vſe thereof is ſuche.
                  Receyue thereof at youre mouthe as muche as a Filberde ſhell would

conteyne, and annoynte alſo therewith the partes of youre Memorye, to wytte the hynder parte of youre head and the other partes heretofore rehcarſed: ſo ſhall you proue it to be excellent good.
                  I myghte here gather together moe yea and profitable remedyes, but theſe ſhall ſuffyce, and make a waye for others to prepare according to the occaſion: for I haue ſtudied breuitie, and haue choſen oute of good the beſte, nor I woulde not (as alſo it becōmeth not a Chriſtian) haue them lye hidden in me. He ſhal fynde moe compounded and thoſe not to be contemned whoſoeuer readeth Antonius Fumanellus Veronenſis chap 16. de compoſitione. mediciment. in Antonius Fumanellus a phiſicion of Verona, in hys worke of the compoſytyon of medecynes the xvi. Chapter I haue not wrytten ouer thoſe here, leſt I ſhoulde doe the thing already done, although ſome of his doe in ſome part agre with mine

let euery one choſe oute that whiche ſhalbe conuenient for him: and he that can not, let him take counſell at a learned Phiſition, and let him remembre that there is nothing done or gotten withoute labour that is praiſe worthy. For God hath appointed Nothinge without labour. al thinges to labour: nether are the meanes to bee deſpiſed of him that deſyreth to obteyne the endes for becauſe that (accordynge to the naturall Philoſophers) a man can Naturall Philoſophie. not paſſe from one extremitie to another without a conuenient meane: And it is the propertie of a ſluggard not to addicte him ſelfe to immitate &amp; folow euery good or beſt thing, for thoughe we can not fullye atteyne thervnto, yet at the leaſt let vs come as neare it as we may, ſythe that (as the Prouerbe ſayeth) Mercurye is not made of euery woode.
               
            
            
               
               The ſixte Chapter expreſſeth Philoſophicall Iudgementes, rules, and preceptes of Remembraunce.
               ARiſtotle thoughte good, to aſſigne Ariſtole. two actes of Memoratiō: to wytte, Memorie and Remē
                  braunce: although Remembraunce perteyneth to thoſe thinges whiche we haue forgotten, and is the offyce of the extymatyue or cogitatyue vertue, not principally of the Memoratyue, as Auerrhous and Auerrhous 
                  Auerrhous. Albertus. haue declared in their little Treatyſes: or you may name that faculty to be the minde and vnderſtandinge as Themiſtius ſsythe: becauſe there Themiſtius. is no power or facultie perceiued to wander about, but ye vnderſtanding. And this wtout ye preſence of ye obiecte is onely in Man: for with the preſence of the obiect it is alſo founde in brute Beaſtes, as Ariſtotle hath aſſented, Ariſtotle. and as it euidentlye apearethe in a

Greyhounde or Spayniel: and it is called the phantaſticall ſence.
               But Memorye is a retaynyng of the Images or ſymilitudes firſt perceyued of the ſoule, the which neuertheles is vnprofytable except it both retayne all, and alſo reſtore theym in the ſame order wherein it conceyued theym. And it belongeth not to preſent thinges nor thinges to come, Ariſtotle. but onelye to thynges paſte, as Ariſtotle ſaith. Alſo Memorie and Remembraunce althoughe they doe agree in one ſame ſubiecte kynde, yet they Dyffer in aptenes, becauſe that they that haue a good Remembraunce, haue commonlye an yll Memorye.
               Alſo as concernynge tyme, Memorye dothe alwayes goe before Remembraunce: for a man can not Remember excepte thoſe thinges whereof he hathe the Memorye. Alſo thys is graunted to manye

lyuynge thynges, but that onelye to men: for ſyth that to remember is as it were to argue perfitlye, that is to procede from knowen to vnknowē, therfore it appertaineth to man, whereof it commeth to paſſe that Rembraunce is a gift geuen to Man, as I haue alreadye expreſſed.
               To the Memorie there belongeth foure mouinges. Foure thinges belong to memorye.
               
               The fyrſte is a mouyng of the ſpirites which tranſport the figures or ſimilitudes from the cogitatiue to the memoratiue.
               The ſeconde is a picturynge and faynyng of fygures in the ſame Memorie.
               The thyrde is a reportation or caryinge agayne of the ſpirites from the memoratiue to the cogitatiue or ratiocinatiue.
               The fourthe is that action by the whyche the cogitatiue conſydereth

and knoweth thynges perfectelye, the whyche is properlye called the Memorie. We ſaye alſo that the arte of Memorye or Remembraunce falleth by it ſelfe vppon three thynges as it were three obiectes, to wytte, vppon a thynge apprehended or taken frome elles where, vppon the acte by the whyche the ſame thynge was frome elles where apprehended, and vppon the determinate or indeterminate ſyme in the whyche the ſame apprehenſion was made.
               Yf anye of theſe thynges fayle or bee lackynge, the Memoration muſt needes fayle.
               Therefore the Memorye maye alſo bee verye well thus defyned, that it is an apprehenſion of Another definition of Memorie. ſimilitudes remaynynge in the ſoule, wythe a dillygente ſearchynge or inquiſition: But of

theſe thinges it is alreadye ſpoken in the fyrſt Chapter. And nowe purpoſynge to ſpeake of Artificiall Memorie, we wyll fyrſte preſcribe certayne thynges which he ought to performe of him ſelfe that wyll haue a good Memorie. The whiche ſhalbe at this tyme conteyned in Twenty preceptes, but knyt vp in fewe words.
               1. Fyrſt iudge (let this and the like be ſpoken to yonge Studientes) the ſtudies which you folow to be moſte excellent of all other: and youre ſelfe to be happie yf you obteyne wyſdome and bee ſure to heare a learned teacher, whome alſo you maye bee conſtrained to haue in admiration: for certeynlye it muche helpeth the Memorie, yf you receyue ſuch thynges as you read and heare with admiration and pleaſure.
               2. Iudge the ſame ſcience or knowledge to be hard and wel knowen to very fewe, becauſe thereby

your wit muſt nedes ariſe and awaken: and that is profitable to the Memorye.
               3. You muſt attentiuely and dilygently geue eare to your teachers: lykewyſe yf you reade anye thynge your ſelfe, doe it earneſtly, gathering together all the powers of youre mynde to the ſtudye thereof, neither let youre mynde wauer, but conſtraine it to be onely vpon youre ſtudye, or with a lytle muttrynge call it backe againe, for he is eaſye to bee taughte who is readye to heare attentiuelye: for of a diligente attention procedeth a greater mouyng &amp; a more ſtedfaſt impryntyng. And therfore ſayeth Terrence. Terence.
                  
                     When earneſtly the mynde is ſet,
                     Then doth the Wit great vertue get.
                  
               
               4. At ſuche tyme as you intende to collect or gather together manye thynges, reduce them as muche as is poſſible to ſhortnes and breuitie,

for he that wyll encreaſe his learning procedeth one way, and he that will augment his Memorie another waye: for he that learneth doth cutte and deuide the generall into partes euen vnto the vttermoſte and laſte, but he that wyll haue a good Memorie, doth reduce and bryng a multitude into one, or at the leaſt into a fewe.
               Verſes alſo doe helpe muche to the ſtedfaſtnes of the Memorie by reaſon of ye order of the compoſ
                     ••••…
                   &amp; good makyng, not raſhly wandering or ſtrayinge abroade, but cloſed and ſhutte vp in certaine limittes and meaſures, in ſuch ſorte that they ſuffer not the mynde to wander and erre.
               5. Aboue all thynges let there be an order choſen out and obſerued in deuidyng of the body into his membres; for ſo ſhal you diſtribute Treatiſes in Chapters, and Chapters into

concluſions.
               6. Euery thinge muſt be often repeated ouer, in ſuche ſorte that when you haue learned one chapter, and the next folowing together, you muſt repeate or rehearſe againe in youre mind the firſt and the ſecond: &amp; when you haue learned the third, then you muſte beginne againe at the fyrſte, and ſo folowe ſucceſſyuely.
               7. When you entende to comprehende manye thynges, you ſhall ſeperate theym into members or partes: leſle that a dyffuſed multitude doe confound the Memorie. Wherof that Poete ſaith. A certaine Poete.
               
               
                  Yf you will this thinge well ſkan.
                  Into partes deuyde it than.
               
               8. You muſt haue an often and dayly cogytatyon or thyncking of the ſame thynge, or a dyſputation with other, or a declaration to another: for of frequented actes is engendred a ſtate or habite, which is yt Memory.

Nor let not the feare of erringe keepe you backe from diſputinge: for you ſhal holde faſter that which you haue lernid with ſhamefaſtnes and therefore ſaith Seneca: Memorye loſeth no Sences. thing, except that which it doth not of ten regarde or loke vnto.
               9. Endeuour your ſelfe to vnderſtande perfectlye that which you entende to remember: neyther oughte you to take ſo greate care to reade manye thinges as to vnderſtand manye thinges: or ells reade fewe thinges often, eſpecially of them that fyll not their papers or wryttinges wyth trifles.
               10. Take heede leſte the writinge of thinges doe not hurte your Memorye, to wytte, leſte you countynge thoſe thynges to be ſure and ſteadefaſte, whyche you haue written in youre Booke of remembrances, doe ceaſſe to thyncke anye more of theym, and ſo truſtynge

to that ſecurytye, doe ſuffre theym to ſlippe oute of your mynde. Herein the example of Antiſchenes the Athenyan Antiſthe, nes Athenienſis. ſerueth verye well, who aunſwerynge a certayne frende that made hys moone that he had loſte his commentaries, ſaid that he ſhuld rather haue writtē them in his mind then in hys Papers: meaninge the confydence of bookes to be the cauſe, wherby we doe / leſſe exercyſe our Memorye.
               11. The dygeſtion of meate is to be procured, and ſuche thynges as be hurtefull to the Memorye are to be auoyded, and lette ſuche thynthinges as helpe it be putte in vſe, as it is alreadye ſayde in the thyrde and fourth Chapter.
               12. Youre mynde muſte be made free from all ſtraunge cogitations, to witte from ſuche as doe not belonge to ſtudye: for beynge buſied wyth manye, &amp;c.
               
                  
13. Such thinges as you will remember, are not onelye to be hard, but alſo to be ſeene: for they that doe but once beholde a thynge doe better remember it, then they that heare the ſame verye often and beholde it not.
               14. Yf anye bodye aſke you a queſtion, doe not aunſwere haſtelye or forthwith, that is to ſay, without aduiſement or meditatiō: for a ſuddaine anuſwere is alwayes and inconſulted.
               15. You muſt meaſure the powers and ſtrengthes of youre witte and of your Memory, leſte you charge them wt more then they be able to ſuſtaine and kepe: an example may be takē of the ſtomake, which if it be lodē aboue it ſtrengthe, is made weaker for it doth not digeſt: nether doth a glutous body ware fat: euen ſo what ſoeuer is lerned, except it be reteined, doth litle profit: therfore if you cānot retaine aſ

muche as ſhoulde be needefull, you muſt multiplie the number, and ſtill diminiſhe the continued quantitie.
               16. You muſte appeint certaine howers or times for your ſtudye, and eſpecially thoſe in the which your ſtomake or ventricle ſhalbe emptye and not full of meate: for then the wytte is not fylled or darckned wt vapours: the conuenyent howers ſhalbe in the firſte parte of the nyghte when euerye thynge is at reſt, and in the mornynge at Cockes crowing: and take good heede leſte by any chaunce or fortune, you myſſe or lette ſlyppe the howeres appoynted for your ſtudye.
               17. Repeat ouer euery night that which you haue gotten by your ſtudye or lerning, after the imitation of Cato, who woulde call to Memorye Cato. in the eueninge, all that whiche he had done, reade or heard, in the daye tyme.
               
                  
18. Memorie is to bee exerciſed euen from youth, to the ende it maye be the readyer &amp; eaſyer bothe in children and men: and it forceth muche in what kynde of learnyng a man is broughte vp in from his younge and tender yeres, For,

                     An earthen pot wyll ſauour ſtyll,
                     Of that thing which did firſt it fyll.
                  
               
               Moreouer all thynges be newe vn to children: and newe or wonderfull things do make a ſtedfaſt infixion or impreſſion in the Memorie.
               19. For the recreation of your mynde and the reſtorynge of youre ſtrengthes, you muſte not flie to fylthye and diſhoneſt thinges, but you ſhal bring it to paſſe by chaunging of your ſtudye: for it is better ſomwhat to refreſhe youre mynde then altogether to loſe it. Yea alſo the playes paſtymes or Enterludes of Chriſtians ought to be ſage and honeſt.
               Therefore after earneſt and grane

ſtudies you muſte repaire to lighter and eaſier, as to Hiſtories or Muſicall exerciſes: for it reſtoreth the ſtrength and nouriſheth the conuenient reſt, and alſo vertue is of more power after leaſure and reſt. There be ſome that had rather playe, the which in deede is graunted and permitted, ſo that the playe bee a playe and not an earneſt or ſad thinge, and let it be ſhort, honeſt, without deceite hurte or couetouſnes. The Cheſtes Cheaſte playe. playe (a Treatiſe whereof I latelye tranſlated into Engliſhe) doth moue and ſtyrre vp the wit, but in the ſame is often beſtowed to much tyme and ſtudy, the whiche ought to be better Tenyce playe. applied. The baule or Tenyce play, doth alſo profite the hole bodye. (But aboue all the noble exercyſe of Shooting (Shooting is moſt cō
                     mendable) in the longe Bowe is moſt commendable). Walking abrode is good cheiflye for the heade: but it is better to diſpute together walkinge vp and

downe and mouing the hands. This recreatiō of the mind ought not to be daily nor oftē, &amp; eſpecially it muſt not be vſed at ye howres or time of ſtudy. Your witte being ſomewhat recreated or confirmed, you muſt immediatly reſort to yt ſtudy of your lerning leſte tyme doe not peryſhe, then the whiche nothinge is more precious or deare, and it muſt be brought to paſſe ye the time which is loſte, maye he recouered againe by earneſt &amp; dilligent ſtudy. For (as Philelphus ſaith). Philelphus▪
                  
               
               
                  Beleue me, ſure there is no playe,
                  more excellent and pure,
                  Or that more labour doth delaye,
                  and libertie procure:
                  Then wholly to addicte the mynde,
                  fayre vertues to attayne.
                  Fo
                        •…
                     ve tue doth the diffrence fynde
                  betwene good thinges and vaynes
                  And doth alſo refreſhe the ſpiryte
                  with ioyfulnes and reſte,
                  Cauſing the ſame ſo to delyte
                  
                     
                        •
                     hat therby it is bleſte.
               
               
                  
20. Do not depart from your teachers before it beſemeth or behoueth you. For many might become excellent men in ſcyence and knowledge yf they were not aſhamed to be ſcholers, before they be able to haue the iudgement and vnderſtandyng of wiſdome. Alſo it ſhal muche profite to teach others, to expounde, to declare, to aſke, and toanſwere: to doubt of ſome thyngsis good, ſo that it be not done wythout reaſon.
               Finallye you ſhall recken that amongeſt the vnhappye dayes, in the which you haue not profited or learned ſome thynge that myghte haue been yours or done you good.

                     So that (after the common ſaying)
                     No daye paſſe awaye without learnyng.
                  
               
               
                  ¶ Preceptes of remembraunce.
                  The firſte precepte is, of the order and conſequence of ſuche things as are to be remembred: for when we haue learned anye thynge orderlye

being ioyned together with a certayn connexion and copulacion, thoughe we forget the ſame, yet the order beinge repeated ouer, we ſhall eaſelye remember it againe: for the antecedent being knowen, we ſhall eaſelye be brought into the conſequent, and ſhall finde that which was loſte. And therfore a certaine Philoſopher ſaith right well. That ſuche thinges as be well ſet together in order, are eaſy to be remembred: but they that be yll, are difficultlye called againe into the Memorie. For we doe eaſely expreſſe or declare things that haue ben done when they be placed in the ſame order wherein they be donne: for looke what effycacye thinges that are done haue one towardes another: euen ye lyke haue they in mouinge and ſtyrring vp the minde.
                  The ſecond is, that when by one lyke thinge we be ledde into another lyke vnto the ſame, as yf we doe not

remember Homere, let vs call to Memorie Homere. Virgill yt prince of Latin Poetes Virgill. whereby we ſhall come to the remembraunce of Homere the Prynce of Greeke poetes.
                  The third is, that we do ſomtimes thincke vppon contraries: for he that wilbe mindefull of Hector, ſhall remember Hector. alſo Achilles. Achilles.
                  
                  The fourth is, the remembraūce of of yt place and time wherein yt thinge was done: for the place &amp; the time doe 
                        •••
                     ely bringe the thinge to Memorie. There be alſo three ſeates of arguments, frō like, frō contraries, &amp; from nere or betwene both.
                  The fifte is, to rehearſe all thinges by their properties: as, if we wolde remember a fatte man, let vs conſider Dionyfius, Siracuſanus. Iuſtinus or thinke of Dioniſius Siracuſanus: who (as Iuſtinus is author) by fatnes loſte hys eyes.
               
            
            
               
               ¶ The ſeuenth Chapter treateth in fewe wordes of locall or artificiall Memorie.
               ARtificiall Memorie is a diſpoſyng or placing of ſenſible thinges in the mynde by imagination, A diffination of artificiall Memorie. wherevnto the natural Memorie hauing reſpect, is by them admoniſhed that it maye be hable to call to mynde more eaſely and diſſinctly ſuch thynges as are to be remēbred: and (as Cicero ſaith in his ſeconde to Herennius) it conſiſteth or p
                     ••
                  
                  ces as it were of waxe or tables, and Clcero 2. to Herennius of Images as of fygures &amp; letters. For ſo it commeth to paſſe that ſuch thynges as we haue heard or learned, we rehearſe againe euen as though we read thē. Nor it ſkilleth not muche whether we beginne at the firſte or at the laſte. The places them ſelues muſt be ſet in order, for if there be a confuſion in them, it foloweth of neceſſitie that all the reſt

muſt be diſordered. And it behoueth alſo that there be manye places that manye thinges maye be placed by the ſame exerciſe and practiſe. Cicero Cicero. iudged that there ſhoulde be an hnndreth in number. Thomas Aquinas Thomas Aquinas. thought it good to haue me. For theſe places manye haue ſearched by diuers &amp; ſundrye artes, Metrodorus Metrodorus. founde oute thre hundred and ſixe places of the .xii. ſignes in the whiche the Sunne goeth hys courſe: becauſe the Aſtrologers doe deuide the Zodiarke into ſo manye degrees. Cicero inuented a certeine familiar houſe, ſeuered or parted into many places, &amp; he thought it good that we ſhoulde deuiſe after euerye fyfte place either a golden hande or ſome other diſtinction, whereby the one might be diſcemed frō yt other, &amp; alſo in thē to obſerue a ſtedfaſt &amp; vnmouable order, yt we might alwaies entre in and go out at the right ſide.

An other Authour not vnſkūfull, fayned places by certaine lyuynge creatures and deriued their order out of the Latyne Alphabete, in ſuch ſorte that euerye one of their names ſhoulde beginne with ſome one of euerye letter: euen as yf theſe were the names: an Aſſe, a Beare, a Cat, a Dogge, an Elephante, a Foxe, a Goate, a Horſe, a Iaye, a Kyte, a Lyon, a Mule, a Nightingale, an Oule, a Partrige, a Quaile, a Rabbet, a Shepe, a Throſtle, a Vnicorne Xiſtus the phiſopher (who wrote of theſe) Hyena, Zacheus. He deuided all theſe into fyue places: into the head, into the forefeete, into the bealy, into the hinder feete and the tayle, for this order nature her ſelfe miniſtreth; neither can the witte be confounded in countinge or rekennyng them. Hauynge thus gotten then an hundreth and fyftene places he graued in them the Images of

thinges worthye of Memorie, and alſo he cōmaunded that many thinges ſhoulde be written by the mynde or witte in the face of him that ſpeaketh, in the heares, in the forehead, in the eyes, and ſo to deſcend downewarde to the feete. But me thinketh it a very eaſye thing to deuiſe &amp; imagine not onelye an hundreth but alſo infinite places, ſeinge no man is ignoraunt of the ſituation of the Citie where he was borne, or in the whiche he hath long dwelled.
               Therefore when the mynde entreth in at the gate, whiles it conſidereth the diuerſitie of wayes, directinge and leadinge to diuers countreyes, and whyles it remembreth frendes houſes, publike dwellynge places, Palaces or common places of Iudgement, it ſhall fynde out a marueilous number of places. Hereto alſo it maye imagine greate courtes or places of larger roume, wherein it

maye deuiſe as greate a number of places as it liſteth, ſo that euerye thynge maye bee written therein that he wyll haue.
               And becauſe the teaching by examples is briefe and effectuall: nowe wyll I put forthe ſome examples, to the ende that thereby the matter maye be the better perceyued. I will put forth an example of ten, and conſequently by the proportion thereof ſhall bee deuiſed the example of a thouſande.
               And therefore I take or chooſe a great and emptie houſe, to the which you muſt not go often but feldome, and apoynte or ſet the fyrſte place which is at the doore, three foote diſtant from the doore. Let the ſeconde place be twelue or fiftene foote deſtant from that, as for example, let there be one corner or angle.
               Let the thyrde place be diſtant from the ſeconde euen as many, or twelue

foote and there maye be perchaunce another corner, or a middeſt betwene the firſt and the ſeconde corner. The fourthe, ſhalbe a corner. The fyfte, ſhalbe a corner diſtante by aſmuche. The ſixte lykewyſe: and the hall beyng finiſhed, you ſhall enter into one chamber, and immediatlye wythin the dore you ſhall note or appoynte the ſeuenth, and afterwardes in the firſte corner of the chamber the eyght and in the ſeconde corner the nynthe, and in the thirde the tenthe wyth hys diſtaunce. And yf you will haue anye moe places, goe oute of the chamber, &amp; ſo marke or note ye other chambers proporcionally.
               But yet remember that the dyſtaunce whiche is geuen is moderate and conuenyent, but yf there be not founde ſoe greate a dyſtaunce, but a leſſer euen vnto eyghte, or to leſſe euen vnto fyue foote, yei ſhoulde it be tollerable. As concernynge

the temple it oughte to be ſuche a one as muſt not be much frequented, eſpecially of your ſelf: to the ende that you be not confounded or troubled wyth the multytude of the fygures or Images. Theſe places ought to be Memorable and remoueable with ones hād, for yt corners are not places, but fyxed Images ſette and placed in the corners, vppon the which (euen as vpon paper) are painted other figures, which maye be put out, euen as letters vpon paper: As for example, the firſt place is marked The righte waye to haue artificiall Memorie, is the collocation and dilligent obſeruatiō of thinges. or knowē by an vrinall, in ſetting an vrinall in his place. The ſeconde by a ſalue bore, ſettinge there alſo a ſalue boxe. The iii. by a morter putting it there. The fourth by a peſtill. The .v. by a payr of writīg tables. The vi. by a hares fote. The. 7. by a ſearcer. The 8. by a bag. The .ix. by a lofe of waxe. The x. by yt canes of caiſſa. And theſe names muſt be kept always in mind

and yt places from .v. to .v. yt the quinaries or fifte places may alwaies be had in Memorye. Of yt diſtance there is enough ſpokē. Yet note yt you may paſſe to .xxv. and not beyonde, leſte there ſhuld chaunce a negatiō in the images. And be it ſpokē euē likewiſe of ye quantitie as thouching yt height, yt there be not many of a heighte, but frō v. euē vnto .xii. fote. And let euery fift place be marked, as it is ſaide of yt order. The quality alſo muſt be noted yt they be not to light nor to dark, nor to much frequēted. Let vs come to yt images which are yt things yt muſt be placed: yt images which be knowē vn to vs ought to be ſo ſet in theſe places with ſuche mouinges, that by them we maye call thinges to remembraunce. For example, I woulde remember twentye Names, I will doe thus: In the fyrſte place I wyll ſette the Image of Peter one whome I well knowe, wyth an

vrynall full of water in his hand the whiche he ſhall powre vpon Iames one alſo well knowen vnto me: and ſo by this notable acte I ſhall remembre theſe two &amp; ſo place in my remembraunce theſe two names.
               In the ſeconde place I wyll putte Henrye who is vnto me verye well knowen (for theſe fygures muſte be exactly knowen that they may quickely come into ones Memorie) who ſhall put his hande into a boxe and pull out the ſalue and therewith all to beſmyer Steuen one alſo whome I do verye well knowe.
               In the thirde place I wil ſet Thomas, one whome I know alſo, who ſhall take out of the morter a plaſter and ſhall putte it vppon Frauncis face: or by inuentynge ſome other madde ieſtes and toyes, whereby the Memorie maye be confirmed to beare awaye ſuche lyke names. And ſo in like maner procede wt the reſt.
               
                  
Likewiſe yf I woulde remembre anye man and alſo his acte, I wyll imagine him and the doing of hys acte: as, yf I woulde remembre one eating of Figges, then I wyll imagine that with a Figge he did ſome mery or ſtraunge thing.
               If you wyll remembre argumentes, you ſhall take the ſubſtaunce of the argument, and ſhall only place yt becauſe the whole argument can not be placed, and ſo of other things after their place.
               We wyll yet againe entreate of fygures by theſe fyue preceptes.
               The firſte is, that the fygure doe moue either to laughter, compaſſion or admiration: for one maye ſoone fynde a fygure that dothe ſtyrre vp and moue the affection of the ſoule. An example hereof is this, yf I ſhoulde ſette or place in the mouthe of a madde Aſſe the head of Antonye to bee almoſte bitten in pieces,

the bloude to guſhe out of him, and that he aſketh helpe, and holdinge vp his handes crieth out: for it can not be, but that when I would, I ſhould ſee him with the eyes of my minde, &amp; declare or expres Antony to him that ſhould aſke or enquire for him.
               Another is, that we ſhoulde repreſent either the like by the like, or by yt contrary, or els by the proprietie therof. An example of the firſte is, as yf I were about to place the name of Galene, I ſhould write the name of ſom other excellente Phiſition, whoſe authoritie (as nere as maye be) is either equall, or litle inferiour. An example of the ſecond is, yf I write the ſame by the name of an vnlearned Phiſition: yf I deſcrybe Therſites Therſites. Achilles. by Achilles, and the good for ye euyl: or the foule by the fayre. An example of the thyrde is, yf I repreſent Ouidius Naſo. Plato. Ouidius Naſo, by a greate Noſe: Plato by Large ſhoulders,

Criſpus by cryſped or curled heares Cicero: Gelaſinus. and Cicero by Gelaſinus.
               The thride is, that we accuſtome our ſelues to place things euen from oure verye youthe, and that we encreaſe with daily ercercyſe: althoughe that the teachinge thereof may helpe and prefyte euen theym alſo that be elder. The habite the perfectnes and dexteritie (I meane to practiſe theſe things) is much the more if they do ſo place al things which they ſhal either ſay or do &amp; alſo what ſoeuer thei heare in communycation or talkinge. And they muſt lyke wiſe painte and graue the maners, geſtures, and tymes: For in ſo doyng they ſhall in a ſhorte ſpace be notablye well exerciſed. It profiteth alſo to playe one wyth another, and to goe about to excell hym that ſhall recyte many thinges, more clearelye, orderlye, and ſpedelye then other.
               
                  
The fourth is, that (in euerye quinarie or fifte number of thoſe things that are to be marked) we repeate againe from the beginninge all ſuche thinges as are alreadye noted: for the repetition of thinges comonlye bringeth great vtilitie and profit.
               The fifte is, that we ſhould repreſent things compound with the ſimilitude of ſimple things. As for example: he that will remember this ſentence, Cicero contendethe with Hortenſius, Cicero Hortenſius. ſhall Imagine the peaſe called Cicer whiche complayneth of the barenes of the garden: for ſo doth Cicer reſemble Cicero and the garden called Hortus doth repreſent Hortenſius, and the complaint the contention. And thus alſo may the chief pointes of the lawe be kept in mind, as yf we wold place this lawe to be had in Memorye, Publicati teſtamenti fides: the aſſurāce of a teſtamēt publiſhed: let vs imagine a writing in forme of

a teſtament opened, vpon the whiche myre or dyrte hath been caſt by ſome man, and ſo the aſſurance therfore is loſte. Loe the aſſuraunce of the teſtament ones publiſhed can not be read again. But theſe things ſhalbe more eaſely done yf there be learninge adioyned hervnto, and the knowlege of thinges worthy of Memorie, and alſo perfecte and dailye exerciſe not wantinge, ſeying that exerciſe is hable to ouercome all things: ſo ſhall the philition alſo remēber the rules of Phiſick, and likewiſe ye Lawyer ye rules of the lawe with more facilitie.
               The place therefore is like and is compared to ware or paper or tables (in the which of olde time many thinges were written): alſo the image or figure is likned to letters or writing: and the recityng of the names is compared to the readinge or recitinge of things being reade. The place is the parte ſeruing in ſtede of the Memory

and receiueth thinges as the Memorie doeth, and it is multiplied by hauyng reſpect forward and backward to warde the right ſyde and towarde the left ſyde, vpwarde and downewarde, by addynge ſomewhat or dimiſhinge ſomewhat: and it is multiplied by meſuring the longe, the ouertwart, and the meane. The rule of the places briefly in order is thys alſo, that firſt there be an inuention of the places (whereof it is alreadye ſpoken) afterwardes an orderynge a meditation, a diſtaunce, a ſtedfaſtnes, a ſolitarines, a meane light, a diſſimilitude, a quantitie, a marking of the fifte places by a golden hande or of ſome other metall, and the varietie thereof, leſt the ſimitude ſhuld cauſe a confuſion. The images or figures are ſimitudes of things conceyued in the mynde, or a proportion either wholly or partly lyke vnto the thing yt we wolde remēber, yea they

be taken for yt thinges themſelues yt are to be placed. And thei be in two kindes: to wit, either knowen or vnknowen: of the notes or marks ſome be quicke, ſome dead: &amp; aſwell of the quicke as of yt dead ſome ſimple, and ſome compound. Again you ſhall not forget that in placing or ſetting of ye images or figures in their places the thing is alwaies to be placed wt a mery, a merueilous or cruel act, or ſome other vnaccuſtomed maner: for mery 
                     •…
                  uell, iniurious, merueilous, excellently faire, or excedīgly foule things do change &amp; moue yt ſenſes, &amp; better ſtyrre vp yt Memorie, when ye minde is much occupied about ſuch things. alſo yt images ar varied by yt trāſpoſitiō &amp; trāſumptiō of ye letters: as if I wold remēbre nep, I ſhal place a pen Nep (an herbe ſo called.) &amp; for a tiran, a rauenīg wolfe. It ſuffiſeth therfore that we haue expreſſed a Methode or compendious waye, the which whoſoeuer foloweth ſhall eaſly (ſo that exerciſe be not lacking)

get and attayne the certaine and ſure remembraunce, of many and ſondry thinges as due occaſion ſhal requyre: but as for the ſluggiſhe and idle, let them ſlugge and ſlepe ſtill, to whom all things are diſpleaſing.
            
            
               The Epilogue.
               Laſt of all, in ſtede of an epilogue and as it weare a concluſion I will Eraſmus Roterodamus. 3, booke Eccleſ. adde that whiche Eraſmus Roterodamus writeth in his. 3. booke of Eccleſ. To the power (ſaith he) of the n
                     •
                  
                  tyue Memory being good of nature, muſt be ioyned intelligence, care, exerciſe, and order, Phiſitions alſo doe promiſe ſome ayde to the confirming of the Memory and to this agreeth, Marcilius Ficinus. But beſydes Marcilius Ficinus. thoſe thinges that we haue ſayde, a perpetuall ſobrietie of lyfe doth moſt of all helpe: for gluttonye and dronckennes, lyke as they doe dulle the witte, ſo doe they alſo vtterly ouer

throwe &amp; deſtroye the Memorie: alſo the varietie of cares, and yt heape of buſyneſſes is hurtefull, the tumultuous readynge of diuers volumes or bookes is alſo noyous. I ſuppoſe this to bee the chiefe cauſe why age ſhoulde be forgetfull: becauſe the power or ſtrengthe of the mynde is ouerthrowen with the multitude of thynges. Alſo an imoderate baſhfulnes, the newnes or ſtraungenes of Auditours, care and trouble of mynde doe annoye the Memorie: but baſhefulnes and noultie are ouercome or remedyed by vſe and cuſtome.
               Alſo great or carefull ſtudye is likewiſe hurtefull, in as muche as it is not without an earneſt &amp; gredye deſyre. In another place he ſayeth thus. The beſt arte of the Memorie is, to vnderſtande thynges throughly, and being vnderſtanded to reduce them into order, &amp; laſt of all to repeat often

that which you woulde remember. Hitherto Eraſmus. If therefore you wil haue an excellēt Memory of good Eraſmus. things, you muſt take diligēt hede, ye you vnderſtād ye perfect reaſō of that you go about to lerne by hart, for reaſon is an vndiſſoluable bonde of the veritie and of the Memorie. For this cauſe poſſibly Plato ſayd, that thing Plato. which is once wel vnderſtanded, can neuer be altogether forgotten. Alſo thoſe thinges are to be cōmitted to yt Memory which are not only profitable but alſo pleaſaunt. For ſuch nouriſhments as bring yt ſweteſt taſt, do the eaſelier paſſe &amp; are cōuerted into our nature: &amp; wt how much yt better appetite yt any thīg is takē, it remaineth ſo much yt longer. Adde herevnto that which Ariſtotle &amp; Simonides thoughte good to be throughly obſerued Ariſtotle. Simonides (to wit) yt there ſhoulde either be in déede a certain &amp; ſure order in teaching, or els at yt leaſt excogitated &amp;

ſuppoſed. Order conſiſteth in a certaine proporcion and connexion. And if you take anye one thynge of thoſe that are ſet in an exquiſite &amp; perfect order, the reſte wyll followe forthewith by a certayne neceſſarye continuation eyther of Nature or of Arte. It is more ouer to bee obſerued, that we doe meditate manye tymes thoſe thinges that we haue learned: for ſo be the nouriſhementes of the mynde digeſtid, and as it 
                     •…
                   eare tourned into the minde. It is verye good alſo to renewe and rehearſe verye often ſuche thinges as are committed to the Memory, with an elegant oration or a ſwete ſonge, as it is heretofore declared. For pleaſure is the ſauce of thinges, the foode of loue, the quickning of the wit, the nouriſher of the affection, and the ſtrength of the Memorye. The ſoule alſo muſt be purged frō euil things, that it maye be filled wt good things:

And we muſt humbly deſyre of God with a faithfull praier to graunt vs his ſpirite of wiſedome and knowledge for our Lorde Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, to whome with the father &amp; the holye Ghoſte be all honour, laude and glorye, for euer and euer.
            
            Amen.
         
         
            ¶ Memorie ſayeth.
            
               To hym that would me gladly gaine?
               Theſe three preceptes ſhal not be vaine.
               The fyrſt is wel to vnderſtand:
               The thing that he doth take in hand.
               The ſeconde is, the ſame to place:
               In order good, and formed race.
               The thyrde is, often to repeate:
               The thing that he would not forgeate.
               Adioynyng to, this Caſtell ſtronge:
               Great vertue commes er it be longe.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

