
   
      
         
            The iudges scripture, or, Gods charge to charge-givers A sermon preached in St. Nicholas Church of Newcastle upon Tyne, before the judges, justices, and gentlemen of the towne and countrey, at the assises holden there the three and twentieth day of July. 1635. By Francis Gray, Master of Arts, and one of the preachers in the same towne.
            Gray, Francis.
         
         
            
               1636
            
         
         Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02057
            STC 12202
            ESTC S103403
            99839157
            99839157
            3557
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02057)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3557)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1139:18)
         
         
            
               
                  The iudges scripture, or, Gods charge to charge-givers A sermon preached in St. Nicholas Church of Newcastle upon Tyne, before the judges, justices, and gentlemen of the towne and countrey, at the assises holden there the three and twentieth day of July. 1635. By Francis Gray, Master of Arts, and one of the preachers in the same towne.
                  Gray, Francis.
               
               [6], 21, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed [by Augustine Mathewes?] for Robert Milbourne, and are to be sold at the signe of the Vnicorne neere to Fleet-bridge,
                  London :
                  1636.
               
               
                  Printer's name conjectured by STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-02
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-02
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE IUDGES SCRIPTVRE, OR, GODS CHARGE TO CHARGE-GIVERS.
A Sermon Preached in St. Nicholas Church of Newcaſtle upon Tyne, before the Judges, Juſtices, and Gentlemen of the Towne and Countrey, at the Aſſiſes holden there the three and twentieth day of July. 1635.
            By Francis Gray, Maſter of Arts, and one of the Preachers in the ſame Towne.
            Yee ſhall doe no unrighteouſnes in judgement. Lev. 19. 15.
            
            Hee that walketh righteouſly, and ſpeaketh uprightly; hee that deſpiſeth the gaine of oppreſſion, that ſhaketh his hands from holding of Bribes, that ſtoppeth his eares from hearing of Blood, and ſhutteth his eyes from ſeeing of evill, hee ſhall dwell on high, &amp;c. Iſai. 33. 15. 16.
            
            
               LONDON, Printed for Robert Milbourne, and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Vnicorne neere to Fleet-bridge. 1636.
         
         
            
            
               
TO THE RIGHT WORSIPFVLL, Sir Peter Riddel, Knight and Maior; to Sir Thomas Riddel, Knight and Recorder; to Sir Lionell Maddiſon, Knight and Alderman, and to all the reſt of his worthy Friends, the Worſhipfull Aldermen:
            
            As likewiſe to the Worſhipfull, Mr. Leonard Carr, Sheriffe, and the other late Sheriffs of the Towne and County of Newcastle upon Tyne. FRAN: GRAY wiſheth what is moſt worthy of wiſhing▪ Grace heere, and Glory heereafter.
            
               RIght Worſhipfull, and ever much reſpected Friends, I find it commanded under the Law, that hee who had not a Lambe to offer Levit. 5. 7. 11.in Sacrifice, was to offer two Turtle Doves, or two young Pigeons; and if his ſufficiencie could not reach thereunto, then the tenth part of an Epha of Flower was accepted: And it is written of Licurgus, that hee injoyned the people to offer little Sacrifices to their Gods; For (ſaith hee) they reſpect more the inward Affection, than the outward Action. What my hearts deſire is, and ever hath been, to expreſſe my thankfulneſſe to your Worſhips for your many favours, God who beſt knowes my heart, is by his all-ſeeing eye inſighted therein; yet what to offer that might any way proportionate your Bounties no way having, preſuming upon your accuſtomed courteſie, that you will not diſdaine a ſmall tribute of gratitude where a

greater is denyed, I have here made hold to commend to you my Patrons, the Patronage of this my poore and ſmall Labour, aſſuring my ſelfe that you will more tender the Authors inward Devotion▪ than his outward Oblation: Which, I preſent to your Worſhips, not after a Ceremoniall Submiſsion, but as a Serious and Reall Testification of my bounde
                  •
                Duty: The baſhfulneſſe of my Diſpoſition, and just conſciouſneſſe of mine owne unworthineſſe, were just Remoraes to ſtay me in this bold attempt to come into publick; Yet the due and daily experience that I have had, and now doe enjoy, of your kind acceptance, became a ſufficient attractive to countervaile all other retractive diſcouragements. I doe hereby expect to come under the laſh of raſh Cenſure, yet had I rather be unjustly taxed by the Vncharitable, than continue ever guilty of that Capitall crime of Ingratitude. Affection, to you (as I doe moſt ſincerely profeſſe) not any deſire of Ambition to my ſelfe was that, together with the motion of ſome friends which pricked mee forward to this raſh enterprize: Let it have but what I heartily deſire, Gods favour, your Worſhips acceptance, the Reformation of ſuch vices as therein are justly taxed, and the Practice of ſuch duties as are therein preſſed, together with the Readers favourable Conſtruction, and then it hath all that either it can beg, or the Author can expect. And I justly hope, that what not long ſince found your well-liking after your attentive and judicious hearings, will not in ſo ſhort a time meet with the poyſon of many malignant tongues: However it fare with others, let it I beſeech you, crave your Worſhips gracious eye of Patronage. I need not to relate unto you in how many reſpects it is your owne, when in ſo many reſpects the Author confeſſeth himſelfe to be yours▪ Receiving my Birth among

you, my Education in part from you, &amp; now for the preſent, the chiefeſt meanes of my Suſtentation, under God▪ by you. But whilst I ſtrive to expreſſe thankfulneſſe, that I might not be judged baſely to flatter, as knowing that the ſoūding out of your Praiſes is no ſuch pleaſing Muſicke to your eares; Let this ſuffice that I Dedicate this my poore paines unto you, and I ſhall never ceaſe to breath out my hearty prayers to God, the true Patron to us all, for your health and happineſſe, as alſo for the Peace, Plenty, and Safety of that flouriſhing Corporation, wherein you are placed Magiſtrates; which that you may the better Governe, and execute the truſt repoſed in you, Give mee leave to ſay to you in the Apostles words, wherewith I will conclude: Let the Peace Coloſſ. 3. 15.of God rule in your hearts, to the which yee are called in one body, and be yee thankfull, and my love be with you all in Christ Ieſus. Amen.
            
               From my Study in Newcaſtle upon Tyne, 
                  this 1 of December, 1635.
               
               Your Worſhips in all due reſpects, to his power to bee commanded,
FRANCIS GRAY.
            
         
         
            
            PErlegi hanc Concionem, cui Titulus (The Iudges Scripture, &amp;c.) in quâ nihil reperio ſanae fidei, aut bonis moribus contrarium.
            
               Tho: Weekes Epiſcopo Lond: Cap: Domeſt.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            GODS CHARGE TO CHARGE-GIVERS.
            
               PSAL. 2. VER. 10. the latter part.
               Be inſtructed, yee Iudges of the Earth.
            
            
               THis Verſe and Text, (Right Honourable, Right Worſhipfull, Worſhipfull, and the reſt Beloved) without Preface or Apologie, are nothing elſe but Gods charge by his Prophet, to them who were to give a charge to others; and his holy direction to them, who under him were appointed to give both Correction and Direction unto others.
            In the words be pleaſed, I beſeech you to obſerve with me theſe three Generall Heads.
            Firſt, you are given to conſider of the Perſons directed: Set downe by their Title, They are called Iudges.
            
            Secondly, you are to take notice of their appellative Reſtriction, or reſtrictive Appellation; which, you may be pleaſed to call their Circuit, or place for the execution of their Authority. In that they are called, Iudices terrae, Iudges of the Earth.
            
            Thirdly, there is to be conſidered, the Direction, or Charge it ſelfe which is given; and that is, To be Inſtructed.
            
            Be Inſtructed, yee Iudges of the Earth.
            The Point then upon which we are firſt to enter, and by Gods aſſiſtance and your gentle patience to handle,

is touching the perſons directed, here in the Text, called Iudges. The Prophet David, having in ſome foregoing verſes, ſpoken of the power and Majeſty of the Son of God, &amp; declared how able he is to take vengeance on all thoſe who ſhould dare to oppoſe him in his Soveraigntie; Now fearing that he ſhould chiefly meet with reluctance in Kings &amp; Iudges, as if becauſe they being Higher Powers, ſhould chiefly preſume to oppoſe the Higheſt of Powers: Or otherwiſe, well knowing of what force the ſilent Rhetorick of the Paternes of great Perſonages is, either in perſwading to good, or in diſſwading from evill, he principally directs his ſpeech to them, willing them to learne, and learning to know, and knowing, to acknowledge the Supremacie of the Son of God, and To ſerve the Lord in feare, as it follows in the beginning of the next verſe, whereupon in the Concluſion wee muſt alſo touch.
            I hope and preſume, that I am not in the midſt of a Maſterleſſe and lawleſſe Anabaptiſticall Auditory; a Sect, that with might aad maine ſtrives to ſtrike off the head of Government, and would frame the body of Men, like the body of Polyphemus, without an eye, or make it like the confuſed Chaos of old, that it be, Rudis indigeſta
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   moles. So that I ſhould need to ſtand much to prove the lawfulnes of Kings and Iudges, and how that there ought to be a Superiority amongſt the Sons of Men. If I ſhould go no further than the words here of the Prophet, we find God no way condemning them for being Kings and Iudges, neither doth hee wiſh and will them to leave theſe the places of their Dignity, but only ſeeks to put them in mind of their Duty: Be wiſe now therefore O yee Kings, &amp;c. How Lawfull and Laudable

it is that there ſhould be Kings and Iudges, Counſellors and Magiſtrates; yea, and how neceſſarily it ſtands with the good of the Common-wealth, Scripture confeſſeth, and Experience confirmeth.
            Whilſt wee ſee God in the very firſt Creation of the World, obſerving order, and eſtabliſhing a Superiority amongſt his Creatures, willing The greater Light to rule 
               Gen. 1. 16.
               the Day, and the leſſer to governe the Night. And when hee comes to the Creation of Man, whom you may be pleaſed, as it were, to call the Maſter-piece of that his Divine Work-manſhip, Giving him command over the 
               Gen. 1▪ 28.
               Birds of the ayre, the Beaſts of the field, and Fiſhes of the Sea. Whilſt we ſee Noah, a Commander in the Arke; Abraham, to be a chiefe Preſident; Moſes, to be a Ruler; Ioſhua, to be his ſucceſſour, both to perſons and places; Samuel, to be a Iudge, to goe from yeare to yeare in Circuit, to Bethel, Gilgal, and Mizpeh, and to judge 1 Sam. 7. 16. 2 Chron. 19.
               Iſrael; David, Salomon, Ioſia, and Iehoſhaphat, to be Kings; who alſo gave his expreſſe command to his Iudges. Whilſt wee behold our bleſſed Lord and Saviour JESVS CHRIST, no way overthrowing, but ſtill ſeeking to eſtabliſh Chriſtian government, paying Tribute, bidding to give Caeſar his due, and content to be brought before Pilate his Iudge; Paul alſo anſwering ſubmiſſively before his Iudges &amp; giving it in expreſſe charge, that Every ſoule ſhould be ſubject to the Higher powers, to 
               Rom. 13 
                     •
                  .
               Kings, and all that are in authority, and that not onely for feare, but for conſcience ſake; for that the powers which were, were ordained of God, the thrones▪ of heaven and earth being not contrary, but ſubordinate.
            Theſe, with many more inſtances which might be uſed, may ſerve to ſtop our mouthes, that wee doe not

               Verſ. 
                     •
                  . dare with thoſe wicked ones, in St. Iudes time, To ſpeak evill of Dignities, but humbly to acknowledge them to be the breathing Images of the moſt high God. If we cōpare the body Politick to the body Celeſtiall, there wee find an Hyerarchy; the Apoſtle therefore ſpeaks Coloſſ. 1. 16.of Principalities and Powers, Dominions and Thrones; mention wee find made of Cherubins and Seraphins, Arch-angels and Angels: If to the body Aſtronomicall, 1 Cor. 15. 41.the ſame Apoſtle ſheweth us, that One Star differeth from another in glory: If to the body Eccleſiaſticall, you Epheſ. 4. 11.have the ſame Apoſtle affirming, How that God hath given to ſome to be Prophets, ſome Apostles, ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtours and Teachers: If to the body Naturall, there wee ſee all the members of the body to be guided by the governance of the head: If to a body Occonomicall, the Apoſtle ſheweth us, and obſervation may teach us, that as there be veſſels of gold, and veſſels of ſilver, ſo alſo, veſſels of inferiour mettall: If to the body Military or Martiall, if there were not Generalls, Captaines, and the like Officers to command, as well as the common Souldier to obey, there were but ſmall hope of victory: If to an hive of Bees, there this ſuperiority is, Ipſius naturae theſis, the very inſtinct of Nature hath taught them to acknowledge a King, Et Rege incolumi mens omnibus una.
            
            If likewiſe we ſhall reſemble the Common wealth to a Ship, the Orator could tell us, that Alij ſentinam hauriunt, alij plumbum inijciunt, &amp; alius clavam tenet, ſome are ready to pumpe, ſome to ſound the depth by caſting in of the plummet, and ſome alſo to ſit at the ſtern. If laſtly, to an Inſtrument of Muſicke, there we ſee the ſweeteſt harmony to ariſe from differing notes. Thus

in the Common wealth, God will have an higher and a lower; ſome to governe, and ſome to be governed; ſome to command, and ſome to be commanded. Vbi eſt 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , ibi eſt 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , want of Government cauſeth confuſion, and equality breeds but contempt: where all will rule, there is no rule; where there is none to rule, there is all miſrule: to rule, and to rule well, and to be well ruled is the very bond of humane ſociety. God, we further know, hath ſet ſuch a majeſtie in the face of lawfull authority, that it workes confuſion, many times in the face of wickednes, to dare to approach nigh it: and if the viſible powers were not often more praevalent with the Sonnes of men, than the inviſible God, the world would ſoone be overrunne with outrage: were not Authoritie ready to curb the inſolencies of the ſtubbourne, what Inceſts, what bloodſheds, what lamentable outcries, and ſuperlative degrees of impiety would not abound? and each day would appeare to be that laſt time, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, Men 
               2 Tim. 3▪ 2, 
                     •
                  
               
               to become heady, high-minded, truce-breakers, diſobedient, without naturall affection: and every way guilty of the like enormities.
            Kings and Iudges there then are, Kings and Iudges there ought to bee, the law of God proves it, and the good of the Common wealth approves of it; Iudges you are, and Iudges you are of God; you receive your warrant from God, as you receive your Commiſſion from the King. It well becomes you to be moſt faithful to both: as you are of God, ſo in ſome ſenſe, you are even called Gods. I am ſure that your judgement is called the Lords judgement, Deut. 1. 17. And you are ſaid, as Iehoſaphat ſpoke to his Judges, to judge, not for
               
               man, but for the Lord; and the Lord hath promiſed to be with you in the judgement.
            Behold then, and conſider what a neere relation God hath to you; and you to God; what ſhall I then in the firſt place ſay, but as Gods Judges, to put on Gods courage, not to feare the face of men, to learne of God, not to have reſpect of perſons in judgement. The promiſe of Gods preſence was that which gave boldneſſe to Moſes, to Ioſua, and to many other godly governors. Doe as they did, and you may in ſome meaſure expect to partake of that favour which they found. Chriſtian courage in the heart of a Judge or Magiſtrate, is that which helpes to put life into thoſe Lawes, which are ready to languiſh for want of due and diſcreet execution. What are men in Authoritie more ſure to meet with, than diſtempered and refractory ſpirits, who hate to be reformed, and think that they may ſinne without controule; and if ever ſinne hath gotten head, and were countenanced both with might and multitude, ſurely now: and therefore, when more than now, doth it become Judges to bee men of courage? It was not without a miſterie, that the ſteps to Salomons. Throne were ſupported by Lyons; what better might the Embleme or morall thereof bee, but to intimate, that a Lyon-like courage becomes ſuch as ſit in the Seat of Judicature and Judgement? And let it ever be eſteemed an eſpeciall part of a Rulers honour, that he dare be juſt in puniſhing, whilſt others will be unjuſt in ſinning; and that hee dare to vſe his power, whileſt they will dare to abuſe theirs. Iob that holy man may very well ſerve Iob▪ 29. 19.as a patterne to all godly Magiſtrates, who was able to affirme this of himſelfe, that Hee did not ſtick to breake
               
               the jawes of the wicked, and to pull the prey out of their teeth. And why ſhould not every Judge and Juſtice, having Gods aſſurance of aſſiſtance, arme himſelfe with an holy obſtinacy, and learne to preferre Iuſtice before the favour and frownes of the ſtouteſt evill doer, becomming friends to all, as they become friends to Juſtice? yea, what more procures credit to Government, than the unpartiall execution of Authoritie, when great Offendors are forced to feele the ſmart of great offences? As God knowes no honour, no royaltie, no greatneſſe in the matter of ſinne: no more may his Deputies. Connivence at the rebellion of the Mighty, is that which cutts the very ſinewes of a Commonwealth; neither doth any thing helpe to make Lawes more contemptible, than the making difference of Offendors, that ſmall treſpaſſes ſhould bee puniſhed, when great ones are permitted to ride in triumph: when that old Complaint comes againe to bee in practiſe, that the Lawes are made like unto Cobwebbs, wherein the leſſer Flies are onely taken, and the greater doe uſually breake through, who will not dare at length to ſweepe them downe.
            The intention of the Law is an univerſall Reformation; now the Magiſtrate hee is tearmed 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , a living Law; and how ſhall hee goe through in the indifferent adminiſtration of Juſtice, unleſſe that whileſt hee puts on the place of a Magiſtrate, hee put off the perſon of a Friend, and goe right on, like the Sunne in the Zodiacke, with unreſiſted violence? Say not then when God, a good Conſcience, a good Cauſe, and the Law tells you, that heere is Juſtice to be executed againſt a great perſon offending, as Salomons ſluggard

ſpake, There is a Lyon without: I ſhall incurre the diſpleaſure of ſome great perſonage. Let not the contents of Agefilaus letters bee too prevalent and powerfull, Si cauſa bona pro juſtitia, ſin mala pro amicitia, utcunque parce; neither with Saul, goe about to ſpare the fatteſt of the ſpoyle for your owne advantage, but ſo ſtrive to proceed, that all both great and ſmall may know, that you beare not the Sword in vaine.
            Againe in the ſecond place, Iudges yee are; Gods owne mouth you ſee here honours you with this Title; now what doth more ſympathize, or as I may ſo ſay, ſynonamize with Judges, than Juſtice? So that the very Title of Judges ought to be a continuall remembrancer of that vertue which ſhould be a perpetuall companion of your places. What can be more peculiar to a Judge, than Juſtice? The Philoſopher could aſcribe this property to a Magiſtrate, that hee be 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , a preſerver of that which is juſt; and Iethro, in that his Character of a good Ruler makes this one particular requiſite, that they be Veraces, or as Iunius interprets the words, Rationē
                
               Exod. 18. 21.
               tantū veritatis habentes, according to the uſual reading, Men of Truth. Juſtice is ſo requiſit in a Commonwealth, that it is not onely the Grace and Glory of it, but the very Foundation, and as it were, the Cornerſtone thereof. Hence that old aſſertion, Tolle justitiam &amp; quid ſunt regna niſi magna latrocinea, The removall of Juſtice makes Kingdomes to become very Dens of Thieves. Now what is Juſtice I beſeech you, according to the old Deſcription, but a rendring to every man what is his due; So that it will well befit Judges and Juſtices, ere that they can paſſe for currant maintainers of Juſtice, ſo to goe on with an even and equall hand, that

Cauſes be ever rather heard to ſpeak, than Perſons: As you are not to exalt the proud Rich man, ſo neither to hate the poore Juſt man; as you are not to benefit for Affection, ſo neither to puniſh upon Paſſion; as you are not to do evill upon Malice, ſo neither to do good upon Covetouſneſſe; as you are not to permit evill to eſcape Vnpuniſhed, ſo neither to let goodneſſe to goe away Vnrewarded.
            To hang up a multitude of ſilly Snakes, who are more than halfe dead before they come to dye, through hunger, and the noyſome ſtench of a lamentable and baſe Priſon, which I dare boldly ſay, is more fit for Swine, than for Chriſtian Men; meaning thereby, the Countrey Jayle, a Grievance worthy of your Honours beſt Conſideration, and due Reformation, wherein Gentle and Simple, both Male and Female, the Debtor and the Fellon are turned hand over head, in each reſpect ſo wofull, that no Miniſter dare without great hazzard either to his life or health, goe to offer in Charity, and to afford Comfort and Inſtruction to the perſons condemned: I ſay, to truſſe up onely ſuch poore Peſants, Non habet victoria laudem, there is ſmall praiſe in ſuch Juſtice: If in the meane time notorious Fellons and Outlawes, the very bane and poyſon of the Countrey, bee not brought in; for Juſtices and Gentlemen of the Countrey, to be both niggards of their paines and purſes, on that behalfe to doe good, the King and the countrey good ſervice: If they ſhall be brought in, then for Witneſſes and Jurors, partly by feare, partly by favour, and partly by bribes to be laid off; for compoſition of thefts, to be as common as the Thefts themſelves; for miſchievous Murders, that ſo crying a ſinne; for every

drop of innocent blood is not onely vocall, but importunate with God for vengeance. For theſe to bee buried, and through the greatneſſe of friends to be ſmothered, for Inceſt, and Oppreſſions to walke with out-ſtretched neckes, and all the more Grand crimes of the place never ſo much as once to come into queſtion, this will denote that Iuſtice lyes a bleeding, this will prove an argument of gaſping Iuſtice.
            Right Honourable you are called Iudges, Right Worſhipfull you are called and ſworne to be Iuſtices, give, I beſeech you, not me leave, but God, in whoſe place I ſtand here, as you your ſelves are ſhortly to ſit elſewhere, to put you in minds of what God tells me doth become you: Hath God conferred theſe places of preheminence upon you? Non datur beneficium niſi propter officium, Dignity calls for and commandes duty, and to whom much is given, of them much ſhall be required. Know therefore that next to the prayers of the righteous there is no more acceptable ſacrifice to God then the upright adminiſtration of Iuſtice, the blood of Malefactours ſhed by lawfull authority, is no doubt pleaſing to the moſt high God: Governours doe even become guilty of thoſe ſinnes which they ſeeke not to reforme by Iuſtice: what better ſight in any ſtate then to ſee an impudent Malefactour ledd▪ to the place of deſerved execution. There Death may perhapps ſeeme harſh to ſome, but we muſt learne of God to know, that there is as well a puniſhing mercy as a mercifull puniſhing, and curſed be that mercy that provokes to anger the God of mercy; It comes to far ſhort God knowes of Iuſtice, when Magiſtrates ſhall dare to humour the people in their Sinnes, this is not with Moſes to make up

the gapp and breach betweene God and us, but to make it greater by connivence. Sinne we know is ready by every ſmall approbation to take heart, but if authority once ſeeme to countenance it, and will not puniſh it through fooliſh pitty, it will ſoone learne to grow impudent. As therefore you tender Gods glory, your fidelity to your Soveraigne, the Countries peace, and your owne Comfort, ſuffer not, I beſeech you, the great and outragious ſinnes of theſe Northerne parts to paſſe with a bare giving of them in Charge, or to eſcape with a Slender reproofe. Thus to doe, is onely to ſhave that head, which deſerves by Iuſtice to be cut off; this is like to a weake doſis that moves, but removes not the corrupt humours in the ſtomacke, it is a breach of Iuſtice not to proportionate the puniſhment according to the Sinne.
            Againe give me leave yet once more to touch vpon your title: Such as are Iudges have there name from there office, nomen ab officio convenienter habent: Iudgges they are ſo called, for that it is there office to judge; now, who knowes not that Iudging doth imply a deliberate action? So that it will be required that to right Iudging there goe along ſerious conſideration, and mature deliberation, that nothing be done raſhly, nothing be effected▪ unadviſedly. And as you are Gods Iudges, it may well become you to learne this manner and Method of proceeding even from God himſelfe, who in the Sentencing of ſinners went no way precipitately to worke: when our firſt Parents had ſinned, GOD firſt enters into parley with them, ere that he give them their deſerved Doome; ſo likewiſe hee examines and queſtions Cain before hee doth

               Gen. 18. 21. ſentence him, and when the Sinnes of Sodom cryed loud for vengeance, I will goe downe, ſaith God, and ſee whether or no, they have done altogether according to 
               Deut. 1. 17.
               their Cry: What God practiſeth thus in himſelfe, he gives in precepts to his Deputies, You ſhall not reſpect perſons in Iudgement, butye ſhall heare both ſmall and Great: So when Iehoſophat comes to give direction to his Iudges, he wils them againe and againe to take heed what they did: the Poet could ſay thus much:

                  
                     Ovid de Triſt. Iudicis officium eſt vt res ita tempora rerum querere.
               
            
            To conſider aright of matters, to poncer times and well to weigh all circumſtances, well becomes a Iudge: Mature and grave deliberation, hath ever beene eſteemed the Midwife to helpe to bring forth a good action; Temeritas judicis eſt calamitas innocentis, The Iudges temerity proves the guiltleſſe perſons calamity, Et judicium temere darum, non tameſt judicium, quam judicis vitium. An over haſty ſentence, deſerves an haſty repentance. The Graecians they placed Iuſtice betwixt Leo and Libra, and many are accuſtomed to protrature Juſtice with a ballance in her handes, thereby intimating, that as men in the places of Iuſtice ought to be ſtout hearted, ſo they ought to Ballance all actions and cauſes; ſo that it cannot but much tend to a Iudges honour, wiſely to weigh and judiciouſly to ponder, and not poſtingly to paſſe by the pooreſt mans matter: watchfull diligence then will prove a vertue moſt ſutable to Exod. 18 13.men in places of authority, like Moſes, of whom it is ſaid, that he ſat from morning till evening to judge the people. He that is diligent in ſeeking after theſe dignities, but having attained vnto them, care not which way

things goe, he is ſicke of Caligula's diſeaſe, who was bonus ſervus, ſed Dominus nequum; or as it was reported of Galba, that there was much rejoycing at his entrance, &amp; the people thought that they had done a good dayes worke when they had made him Emperour, but he was not long in, till they began to change there note; for they found by wofull experience that they had mett with a careleſſe and cruell governour. It is woefull when it is either with Magiſtrates or Miniſters as Pope Vrban writ to a Prelate in his time very ſcoffingly, Monacho fervido, Abbati calido, Epiſcopo vero tepido, &amp; Archiepiſcopoſrigido, The higher in meanes, the worſe for manners. There is then good hope, when Iudges, and all, in all places of precedency, can ſay with Adrian, Non mihi ſed populo; or as it was affirmed of Caeſar, Ipſe ſe non habuit poſtquam mundus habere caepit Prineipem, When he became a Governour, hee ceaſed in a manner to be his owne. And happy ſure that People, that Place, that Common-wealth, whoſe Rulers thinkes no time to long, no paines to great, nor no patience too much, whereby they may glorifie God, and ſeeke the peoples good, in the appointed places of their dignity: who are ſo deſirous to ſtudy the Arte of Government, that with Caeſar they can bee content to divide the night, ſtill reſerving one part to ponder of the peoples peace and ſafety.
            
               
                  
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Homer Iliad.
                  
               
It becomes not, (could the Greeke Poet ſay) a good Counſellour to be to great a ſleeper. It is ſaid of Aegiſilaus▪
                that through his care of the publicke good, hee could ſcarſe get time to be ſicke. Right Honourable then, and Right Worſhipfull, Hoc agite, minde chiefly

that, to which you are now chiefly called, let your natures become anſwerable to your names, ſo ſhall wee have cauſe to bleſſe you, and to bleſſe God for you, to bleſſe the care of our gracious Soveraigne through you, and juſtly to thinke our ſelues bleſſed in you.
            And thus from the firſt generall, we proceede in order unto the ſecond; which is, to conſider of the Appellative reſtriction or Circuit, being here called, Iudices terrae, Iudges of the Earth.
            
            Many may bee the reaſons of this denomination, which the time, and your Honours weighty occaſions will but permit to name. Firſt, what is the ſubiect matter of your judgement, it is but the things of this Earth, Lands, Livings, Liberties, Lives, and the like, all appertaining to the Earth, Quae ſupra vos nihil ad vos, the ſoules of men come not within the compaſſe of your judgement. Secondly, the place of your reſidence and abode, the place alſo where you doe execute your office of Iudicature, it is the very Element of this Earth. Thirdly, thoſe who are the proper object of your judgement, they are not Angels and Spirits, but mortall men, they are ſuch as are but duſt and earth. Fourthly, you your ſelues conſidered at the beſt, you are no more than a lumpe of Earth, Earth by creation, and to be Earth by corruption; he who was ready to call you Gods, was as ready in the next words to tell you, that you ſhould dye like men. It was the voyce of God by his Prophet, commanded to bee proclaimed, Iſai. 40. 6.That All fleſh is graſſe, and all the glory of man is as the flowre of the field. The ſupremeſt Monarke hath no more power to detaine his ſpirit in the houre of death, then the meaneſt member; Sickneſſe, and all other the Harbingers

of death, as not afraid of their Crownes and Scepters, of their glorious roabes, and ſumptuous array, dare without reſpect ceaze upon the very beſt of the Sonnes of men. You doe therefore beare thoſe▪ Enſignes of honour but in earthen veſſels: Let not therefore, I intreat you, the eminency of your places ſo tranſport you, as to blot out of your mindes the remembrance of your Mortality, but let the aſſurance of death and of judgement after death, be as continuall Watchbells▪ to will and to wiſh you to goe on with care and Conſcience, with humility and meekeneſſe, that as it was ſaid of Valentinian, ſo it may be ſaid of you, the people knewe not whether they had Dominum, or Patrem, a Lord or a Father, with ſuch a ſweet awfulneſſe did hee governe. Humility in the places and perſons of authority is a Virtue not more rare than commendable, and yet Saint Bernards rule is, that Quanto quiſque eſt ſublimior, tanto debet eſſe humilior, The higher in Majeſty, the humbler in mind; like the eare of Corne the fuller it is the more it ſtoupes. It was an excellent Commendation that St. Cyprian gave Aurelius and Celarinus, In quantum gloria ſublimes in tantum verecundia humiles fecit, donec nihil in honore ſublimius, et nihil in humilitate ſubmiſsius fuit. How much honour did exalte them, ſo much did Modeſty humble them, that Meekneſſe and Majeſty met together, Greatneſſe and Goodneſſe kiſſed each other; in one word, you are but Judges of earth, you are duſt and aſhes, duſt and aſhes therefore be not proud. Againe in the Fifth place, you are called Iudges of the earth, and why ſo, but to confine you to your proper places, to put a difference and diſtinction betweene you and another Iudgd, whoſe

juriſdiction is of a larger extent, in that he is, et cali et terre iudex, Judge both of Heaven and Earth, Judge of quicke and dead, and as Abraham ſpake, Iudex totius mundi: Shall not the Judge of all the world doe right. Gen▪
                18. 25. When man judgeth man, there is but earth judging earth, but when God comes to Iudge man, then there is Heaven judging earth, as hee is called 1 Tim. 6. 15.King of Kinges, and Lord of Lords, ſo alſo may he be entitled Iudge of Judges, and ſhall without reſpect of perſons render to every man according to his workes: Coll. 4. 1.Wherefore as Saint Paul willed Maſters to doe unto their ſervants that which was juſt and equall, remembring that they alſo had a Maſter in Heaven: So may it be ſaid to Iudges to doe onely that which is juſt and equall to every man, remembring that they themſelves have even a Iudge in heaven. Let not then gifts taken either by your ſelves, or ſervants, blind the eye of Iuſtice; if you doe, be ſure that he who ſhall judge the Secrets of men by IESUS CHRIST, ſhall diſcloſe them to your Eccleſ. 12. 14.ſhame, for He ſhall (ſaith Salomon) bring every worke to Iudgement with every ſecret thing, be it good or be it evel. Whilſt the Pſalmiſt calls you Gods, he would have you to be Gods for diſpoſition, upright and juſt▪ withall, this title may imply that your Courts ſhould be like Heaven, voyd of guile, and free from all injuſtice; nay more, it alſo wills, that your Attendants ſhould be like unto Saints and Angels, innocent in reſpect of all corruption. I wiſh therefore that both you &amp; yours would ſay to corrupting Clients, as Simon Peter ſaid to Simon Magus, You and your money periſh. Bee of Samuels integritie, and you may boldly ſpeake with Samuels alacritie. If therefore the poore, the fatherleſſe and widow

ſhall repaire to your Gravities, as Noahs Dove did to the Arke for refuge, or as the Sparrowe is ſaid to flie into Zenocrates his boſome, for ſhelter from the purſuing Hawke; oh doe not pocket up their Petitions without pitie, but ſtrive with holy Iob, to bee eyes to the blinde, and to bee legges to the lame; cauſe, O cauſe the Widdowes heart to goe away dancing for joy.
            And now in order it followes to proceed to the handling of the third and laſt Generall, which concernes the Direction it ſelfe, in theſe words, Bee inſtructed; or as it is in the uſuall reading, Bee learned: What more wholſome precept could the Prophet here give in charge to Judges, than to bee inſtructed. Neſcitis, ſaid one very well, quanta bellua ſit imperium, Government is not ſuch an eaſie taske as many make it, and as the moſt account of it. The right managing of Authoritie, and the ſwaying of the places of Supremacie, is called by that ancient Father Greg. Nazian. orat. 1. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the Art of Arts, and the very Science of Sciences. And why ſo? Firſt, for men in Authoritie to make their owne lives an Expoſition of that Law, whereof they are made to bee Magiſtrates, hic labor, hoc opus eſt; for by how much greater is the authoritie, by ſo much the more ſpitefull is the malignitie of that our miſchievous enemie, who in the fall of one great one, ſeekes the foyle of many. Likewiſe, to bring to unitie a many-headed multitude ſo divided by Action, by Faction, and in Affection, how hard is it, unleſſe that Governors be inſtructed, and ſo Wiſdome be made to ſit at the ſterne of Government; that doubtfull matters may be decided, Controverſies

comprimized, Cauſes weighed, abuſes reſpectively puniſhed, dangers prevented, Affaires managed, cunning conveyances brought to light, the falſhood of the ſeeming ſimple diſcovered, and that Juſtice bee ſincerely executed. How ſtands it moſt requiſite, that Kings bee wiſe, &amp; that they be learned who are Iudges of the earth: It was therefore not without very good ground, that God Deut 1. 13.gave that in command to Moſes to take Wiſemen, men of vnderſtanding and men knowne among their tribes, and to make ſuch to be rulers over them. Learning and inſtruction ſutes ſo well with perſons in places of eminency, Prov. 8 15. 16that we find Salomon, bringing in Wiſdome thus ſpeaking of herſelfe, By me Kings raigne, and Princes doe decree juſtice. Pythagoras his poſition runs much in the ſame ſtraine, Tum demum fore rempub: beatam, cum aut ſapientes regere, aut reges ſapere caepiſſent, then is there hope of happineſſe to a common wealth when wiſemen governe, or governors doe begin to become wiſe, wherfore that which was Salomons prayer, may well ſuite with every ſuperior, Cor intelligens da domine ſervo; Lord give unto thy ſervant an underſtanding heart.
            
            But what inſtruction, what learning is it, that David here would have Kings to know, and Judges to obtaine? that he ſhewes immediately in the next verſe, which is to ſerve the Lord with feare. For according to the Wiſemans aſſertion it is timor domini, that is, initium ſapientiae, 
               Prov. 9. 10.
               The feare of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdome, Nay more, this ſerving of God in feare it is the tye and knot, the very ground-worke, of all true faithfullneſſe betwixt God and man, betwixt ſoveraigne and ſubject, betwixt paſtour and people, betwixt the Judge judgeing, and ſuch as are to be Judged by him. Remove but

this, and you overthrow the building of goodneſſe it ſelfe. Hence St, Bernard, Omne virtutum adificium illic
                     •
                   vergit in pracipitium, ſi timoris domini amiſerit proſidium, baniſh Gods feare and give immediately poſſeſſion to all follyes: It was the ground of Abrahams feare, and that moſt iuſtly, to be ſlaine comming into Abimelecks land, when he conſidered that there was not Timor Domini in terra, The feare of God was not in that Land. 
               Gen. 20. 11▪
               And aſſuredly if Gods ſervice and feare be caſt behind our backes, farewell care and conſcience, both in Magiſtrate and Miniſter, farewell the true ground of goodneſſe, even in all.
            And to what chiefer cauſe can we aſcribe the generality of ſinnes now among us, and ſwarming in this Northerne Climate, then the dayly blaſpheming of Gods name, the continuall prophanation of his Sabbath, and other Holy-dayes, diſloyall to Magiſtrates, diſreſpect of Miniſters, Murders, Depopulations, Oppreſſions, Surfettings, Riots, Drunkenneſſe, dayly Thefts, and all the rabell of rebellious ſinnes; but to this one corrupt Fountaine, Men have not learned, and which is worſe, they will not ſeeke to learne to ſerve the Lord with feare. It then becomes Judges, and all others, called to places or 
                  •
               ignity, firſt, and principally, to looke to this leſſon, that with godly Ioſhuathey may be able to ſay, I and my houſe 
               Ioſu. 24. 15.
               will ſerve the Lord; that as they are above others, ſo they may ſtrive to goe before others in this, which will really make them to be more glorious then others: Prepoſiti vita eſt ſubditorum regula, &amp; quod facit faciendo jubet: 
               Cyprian.Your carriages being Superiours, carries a commanding power along with it; whether it bee in vice or in vertue: your faults, as likewiſe ours of the Miniſtry, are

like the Eclipſes of the Sunne, which helpes to bring Detriment to theſe ſublunary bodies: you are as the principle Wheels in a Clock, or as the Heart in the Body; and therefore, as He who hath called yee to theſe dignities is holy, ſo ought yee to bee holy in all manner of converſation.
            But though this inſtruction of ſerving God in feare, begin at home, yet it muſt not end there; for it moſt neerly concernes ſuch as are in high places, that they endeavour, to make their power to ſerve for the furtherance of Gods true Religion and vertue, that men bee brought to ſerve the Lord with feare; this well learned, will teach what it is that we owe to you, and you to us, what wee both owe to our King, and what indeed we all owe to God: Feare God, and depart from evill (ſaith Salomon;) Gods feare is to ſinne, as the bankes are to the raging waters of the Sea, to keepe 1. Pet. 2. 17.them within compaſſe: Feare God (ſaith the Apoſtle) and honour the King; the one helpes to bring on the other, for make Subiects truely religious, and make them all in all: wherefore it concernes Iudges, and all Chriſtian Magiſtrates, that Ab Ione fit principium, that in the firſt place they have an eye to the honour and ſervice of God, to be more tender, touching wrongs offered to God, his worſhip, and ſervice, then to their owne particular perſons: we dwell, and long may wee dwell under the guidance and government of a wiſe and religious King, who labours by all meanes, that Gods worſhip and ſervice may be preſerved, and his word may be purely preached. Your Honours are ſent out as eyes to eſpy out offences, and to ſee to abuſes: Be faithfull then to God, to your King, and bee true to

Gods feare. Let the ſervice of God bee as deare to you, as the aple of your eye, and be not reſpectleſſe of his honour, who hath beene ſo reſpective of yours. And now, Right Honourable, good luck have you with your Honours, ride on, and my hearts deſire ſhall ever be, that he who is one day, to come riding upon the wings of the wind, may ride on with you, to aſſiſt, to direct, and to encourage you in the ſeate of Iudicature and Iudgement; that you may ſo faithfully diſcharge the ſame, that the Countrey may have cauſe to bleſſe you, Poſterity cauſe to praiſe you, the Wicked cauſe to feare you, the Righteous cauſe to commend you, the Magiſtrates about you cauſe to thanke you; we of the Miniſtery cauſe to pray for you, all cauſe to love you; your Prince at your returne cauſe to approve of you, and the great Iudge of Heaven and Earth, in his due time, of his infinite mercy▪ cauſe to welcome you with that Ioyfull, Euge: Well done thou good and faithfull Servant, thou haſt beene faithfull in a little, come and I will make thee Ruler over more, enter into thy Maſters Ioy: Into the which joy, the Lord God in his appointed ſeaſon, bring us all for his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus ſake, to whom, together with the bleſſed Trinity, bee aſcribed, as is moſt due, all Honour and Glory, Praiſe, Power, Majeſty, Might and Dominion, both now and for evermore,
            Amen.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

