
   
      
         
            Little Timothe his lesson: or, A summary relation of the historicall part of holy scripture plainely and familiarly comprized in meeter, for the helpe of memory, and instruction of the ignorant in the writings of God. By E.G. Mr. in Arts, and practitioner in physicke for the Kings hospitall of St. Bartholomew, in the city of Glocester.
            Graile, Edmond, b. ca. 1577.
         
         
            
               1611
            
         
         Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02024
            STC 12171
            ESTC S117271
            99852486
            99852486
            17810
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02024)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17810)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1602:14)
         
         
            
               
                  Little Timothe his lesson: or, A summary relation of the historicall part of holy scripture plainely and familiarly comprized in meeter, for the helpe of memory, and instruction of the ignorant in the writings of God. By E.G. Mr. in Arts, and practitioner in physicke for the Kings hospitall of St. Bartholomew, in the city of Glocester.
                  Graile, Edmond, b. ca. 1577.
               
               [14], 106 p.   
               
                  Printed by William Hall for Ionas Man, and are to bee sold in Pater-noster-row at the signe of the Talbot,
                  London :
                  1611.
               
               
                  Author's name from the second edition in which the dedication is signed: Edmond Graile.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bible. --  Selections --  Paraphrases, English.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-10
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            LITTLE TIMOTHE his Leſſon: Or A Summary relation of the Hiſtoricall part of holy Scripture, plainely and familiarly compriſed in Meeter, for the helpe of memory, and inſtruction of the ignorant in the Writings of God.
            By E. G. Mr. in Arts, and practitioner in Phyſicke for the Kings Hoſpitall of St. Bartholomew, in the City of Gloceſter.
            
            
               DEVT. 11. 19.
You ſhall teach them your children, ſpeaking of them, when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lieſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp.
            
               COLOSS. 3. 16.
Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you plenteouſly, in all wiſdome, teaching and admoniſhing your own ſelues in Pſalmes and in Hymnes, and ſpirituall Songs, &amp;c.
            LONDON, Printed by William Hall for Ionas Man, and are to bee ſold in Pater-noſter-row at the ſigne of the Talbot.
1611.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE WORSHIPFVLL, and other the Officers of the Hoſpitall of St. Bartholmew, Mr. Iohn Browne Maior of the City of Gloceſter, and Preſident of the Houſe: Mr. Laurence Wilſhire Alderman and Surueiour, Mr. John Thorne, Alderman and Treaſurer, Mr. Richard Smith, Sheriffe and Surueiour, Mr. William Lockſmith, and Mr. Iohn Moore, Almoners, Mr. Iohn Bruſter and Mr. Antony Robinſon Scrutaners, or Viſiters of the poore.
            
               BEing long ſince enioined by that Reuerend Father and painefull preacher, the Lord Biſhop that lately liued amongſt vs, to publiſh this little Pamphlet; I haue at laſt aduentured it into the view of all. Many Criticks it muſt make account to meet with, and moe curious Readers then courteous, in this ſo literate and cenſorious age; wherein many Poems of the ſame argument are already extant, but moe of many other, and for due cadence

of words and poeticall meaſure, farre more excellent. Sith then the acceptance hereof may well ſeeme doubtfull, and the tenuity and nakedneſſe of it, is ſo apparant as iuſtly ſhameth to looke great learned men in face; I haue thought meete and moſt conuenient to ſhaddow it vnder your worſhips protection. Equity craueth at my hands no leſſe: Firſt, in reſpect of you, who being by place and Office protectors of the poore, may iuſtly challenge to patronize and ſupport, whatſoeuer poore and lame labours doe creepe out of the Houſe. Secondly, in regard of my ſelfe, who being much bounden to the body of this City, for the loue and fauour I found in my free election, ſhould much forget what I owe, if I ſhould not vpon ſo iuſt occaſion, thankfully acknowledge what is due. Thirdly, in reſpect of the poore people of the pl
                  •
               ce, whoſe benefit and good, charity doth challenge, and particular relation require me by all iuſt meanes and fit opportunities to purchaſe and procure. All the good that may be done them, muſt neceſſarily concerne either their ſoules or their bodies. For the body, as the miſeries thereof are more ſenſible, ſo is your care commendable, who at your ordinary and monthly Court, indeauour to increaſe their weekely pay. For the ſoule, I would to God

there were not ſome cauſe of complaint: and ſeeing this preſent argument is ſpirituall and diuine, giue me leaue in preſenting the ſame, to begge for them this heauenly benefit, that euen the ſoules of forty poore people, may by your due regard and prouiſion appeare to bee deare 
                  •
               nto you, as their bodily eſtate is tendered, pitied, and prouided for. What their caſe is, I neede not expreſſe: Saint Iohn deſcribeth it at full, and in few words, Reuel. 3. 17. where he calleth the Laodiceans, wretched, miſerable, poore, blind and naked: a dangerous ſtate, and (which is moſt to bee lamented) they know it not. That it is to be ſuccoured and releeued, I ſhall not need to vſe many arguments for proofe or perſwaſion: I will only remember you of the intention; firſt, of the Foundreſſe, and then of the poore people. In the eie of the Foundreſſe both ſoule and bodie had their due reſpect; and if ſhee were ſo carefull for the benefit of the body, as by a Phyſitian and Chirurgion to prouide for their griefes, and by meanes of maintenance in ſome meaſure for life and lodging, to bring their gray heads in peace vnto the graue; it cannot once bee imagined (without wrong vnto the dead) but that by the Miniſters office and place appointed, a greater care was intended of ſending their

ſoules with comfort to their Sauiour. And as touching the poore people that come to bee placed; it is knowne, to be the profeſsion of all, as to be maintained by the charity of the Houſe; ſo, to end their daies in the ſeruice of God. Conſider therefore I beſeech you, that the ſacrifice they offer, is halt, blinde and lame; t
                  •…
               at the daies they conſecrate, are their laſt and worſt; wherein they are neither fit to ſerue ſin and the luſts thereof, nor yet the Lord and his holy will; and ſeeing they profeſſe a deſire of the choice of the better part, let them not lacke helpe to direct them thereunto, that the eies of their vnderſtanding may be opened, the hand of their faith ſtrōgthned, and their feet guided to make ſtreight ſteps towards that narrow gate that leadeth vnto life. That this bleſsing may be vpon them, and the danger of the ditch auoided, Mat. 1 5. 14. inſteed of traſh and riffe raffe Vrſ
                     •
                  n Cat. 
                     〈◊…〉
                   Epiſt.(rightly ſo valued by the ſame Reuerend Father) let true wiſdome dwell among them, and a man of vnderſtanding be procured them, that ſo together with their daily double praying they may haue alſo often inſtruction, and plaine teaching. And the laborer (you know) is worthy of his hire; and the hire (you wil ſay) you know not where to haue, ſo that herewithall commeth all the difficulty. Here alſo let me be bold to put

you in minde (and to put it in Print, that it may remaine to put your ſucceſſors in minde) that ſpeciall care be had for raiſing and conferring maintenance to this purpoſe, by your prouident diſpenſation and husbanding of the profits appropriated heereunto. Your good endeuours heerein, may be a meanes (when God ſhall grant opportunity) to moue the heart of our noble King Iames, or the hopeful Prince Henry his ſonne, to raiſe this ſpirituall building higher, vpon ſo worthy a foundation, laid by that excellent Princeſſe, and peereleſſe Queene, Elizabeth of bleſſed memory and admired. Whatſoeuer you gaine the poore people, you ſhall reape to your ſelues a worthy recompence; praiſe and good report among men, peace &amp; cōfort to your own conſciences for diſcharge of your duty, and confidence before God in that great day of the appearing of your Sauiour and Iudge, when you ſhall without feare or fainting, giue vp an account, as of other actions, ſo of the truſt committed vnto you, of many the mēbers of Chriſt, the bodies &amp; ſoules of your poor brethren. If I ſeeme tedious, if importunate, if elamorous, let it be remembred, that it is no ſhame for a Bartholmews man to beg. Hoping therefore that I ſhall in time be heard, I leaue pleading, and conclude praying; firſt and principally for

your worſhips, and the reſt of your worthy ranke, that you may be euer found ſuch as the 
                  Exo. 18. 21Lord requireth, you ſhould be, men of courage fearing God, dealing truely, and hating couetouſneſſe; next and generally for the whole people of this City, that as they are politically one body, ſo the Lord would giue them one heart, for conſcience ſake to feare him and obey their Superiours, and to ſerue one another thorow loue; that ſo his bleſsings may be continued and increaſed vpon both Magiſtrates and people, from generation to generation for euer.
            
               Your worſhips in all duty E. G.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE RIGHT VVorſhipfull Sir William Throckmorton, Knight; and to the Lady Cecilie his vertuous and beloued wife, E▪ G. wiſheth continuance and increaſe of all heauenly and earthly happineſſe, to their perpetuall comfort.
            
               
                  TO none more rightly then to you I owe,
               this Map (for memory) of holy writ:
               The former part, you quickned as you know
               by daining grace and liking vnto it,
               When as in duſt it lay, a birth forlorne
               And durſt not further 
                     ••
                  ye for feare of ſcorne.
            
            
               And from that influence, the later budde
               hath ſprouted out to ſatisfie deſire:
               But all in priuate meant, for walles of mudde,
               fit countrey Cottages, but mount not higher.
               And that it comes with characters thus clad,
               Authority gaue charge they ſhould be had.
            
            
               To preſſe vnto the Preſſe, this world in Print,
               where wit with wiſdome vvarres, and humors hold;
               The raines on reaſon, to preſcribe the ſtint
               and meaſures that the beſt, which ſeemes moſt bold,
               In meaner vvits I doe it madneſſe deeme
               Since worthier works doe miſſe of right eſteeme.
            
            
               But call you that oppreſſion of the Preſſe,
               
               when higher powers command and I obey?
               I rather thinke, I ſhould be iudg'd no leſſe
               then void of reaſon heerein to gaine-ſay.
               The ſpreading theirs, the ſpringing is your owne▪
               
               And by the timely fruit, let tree be known.
            
            
               
               
                  
                     Gen. 18. 17. 18▪ 1. Sam. 1. 24 2. Iohn v. 4. If maſters would in Abrahams ſteps inſiſt,
               if Mothers Bathſh eha's, or Hanna's vvere,
               If Ladies like th'Elect, from vvhat they liſt,
               Would curbe their families to God his feare,
               Then ſhould this ſimple plant haue place inough,
               Then ſhould the fruits be ſeene to follow proofe.
            
            
               If grand-dame Lois, her Leſſon were in vſe
               vve ſhould not ſee young children from the ſhell
               To ſweare, to curſe, to practiſe all abuſe,
               and by their parents patterne to rebell:
               
                  2. Tim. 1. 5. compared with cap. 3. 15 For from the faith that in her firſt did dwell,
               young Timothy could talke and Scriptures tell.
            
            
               And for impreſſion in that tender mould,
               and beſt thoſe veſſels nevv at firſt to ſeaſon,
               This paines was meant, and by all meanes I could,
               made fitte for their capacity and reaſon.
               Story we know, with pleaſure ſpendeth time,
               And what runnes readier on the tongue then ryme?
            
            
               Bleſſed be God, good Ioſhua his minde,
               doth plenteouſly, your worſhips hearts poſſeſſe,
               The comforts in his ſacred worde you finde,
               procure no doubt the fruits which ſhew no leſſe.
               And that you may with grace be euer bleſt
               I humbly pray, and euermore I reſt
            
            
               Your worſhips moſt bounden EDMVND GRAILE.
            
         
         
            
            Vpon the Authors Worke.
            
               THey that haue pleaſ'd their knowledge to impart
               And to bequeath their skil to after-times,
               Haue euer writ their chiefeſt grounds of Arte
               In ſome Perſpicuous and compendious rymes:
               Which being well obſeru'd and con'd by heart▪
               
               Sticke faſter by vs, and do long remaine
               Firmely imprinted in the weakeſt braine.
            
            
               So long diſcourſes that whole volumes fill
               Containing Rules of life, or true narrations
               Of mighty men that liued well or ill,
               Or ſome good counſell, or ſound diſputations
               In verſe abridged, and with heedfull skill
               Summ'd vp in briefe, are by that means confin'd
               Within the narrow cloſet of mans mind.
            
            
               This and ſuch helpes hath humane skill prepard,
               For humane frailty: but vntill this day
               For other arts howeuer men haue car'd,
               The Art of Arts wanted this locke and keye
               To ſhut her treaſures vp: no man hath ſpar'd
               Time for this taske, vntill Grayle vndertook▪
               
               In this ſmall cheſte to locke vp Gods great booke▪
               
            
            
               
               Tis not to pleaſe the nice he tooke this paine,
               Their itching eares, and curious eies delight,
               In ſuch a fluent ſtile that muſt containe
               More words then matter: t'is his veine to write
               Much in fewe words, and in their ſenſe ſo plaine,
               That the vnlearned in his ſhallowe hart
               May now contayne the great Soule▪ſauing Art.
            
            
               I. M.
            
         
         
            
            In Momum.
            
               VVAs Mamus (crow you) whelp'd in butchers ſtall,
               That he reſembles ſo that greedie kinde?
               For marke: the worſt that is of men let fall,
               Lying in midſt of better fare halfe pind,
               He chambers, as a baite pleaſing his mind▪
               
               Fie on him, fie, that he ſo curriſhlie,
               Should ioy in that, which others do defie!
            
            
               Or was he of that curres moſt ſpitefull broode,
               Which ſat in cribbe, keeping the oxe from meat?
               For he from others keepes that wholeſome foode,
               Which (hungrie ſoules) they ſeeke for with their ſvveat,
               And yet himſelfe diſdaines thereof to eat.
               O curſed enuie, that to ſtroy the more,
               Will euen himſelfe leade way vnto deaths dore.
            
            
               Or rather ſprang he from that helliſh hound,
               That welcoms damned ſoules to Plutoes place?
               He ſo doth triumph vvhen ought may be found
               In others, that may turne to their diſgrace.
               (O worthy progenie, O noble race!)
               What ere he deemed vvas, I am ſure of this,
               Were he a God, yet now a Dogge he is.
            
            
               What, what, a Dogge? and ſhould his ſnarling bay,
               Scarre men from that the wiſe haue healthfull tried?
               No: worthy Jaſon held on in his way,
               Though he might ſeeme by ſea, and land denied,
               By Buls repeld, by Dragons fell enuied▪
               
               Shall hope of treaſures earthlie ſo inflame,
               And ſhall not heauenlie much more do the ſame?
            
            
               Io. Gr.
            
         
         
            
            The Author to the curious Reader.
            
               
                  I Leaue perfection of a Poets skill,
               (which doth with ſiluer raies poor ruſticks daunt)
               To Silueſters, and to Du Bartas quill,
               and ſuch as harbour, where the Muſes haunt,
               Bathing in cryſtall ſtreames of rare conceits,
               conceiting what they liſt, of any ſubiect,
               Subiecting whatſoeuer them delights,
               vnto their witte and art, their natures obiect.
               To ſuch leaue I, the maieſtie,
               of Poetrie diuine:
               more rife is their dexteritie,
               their wittes more ripe then mine.
            
            
               There needes no garland where the wine is good,
               nor colours, where the ſubſtance is moſt pure.
               Sinceritie by Truth hath euer ſtood,
               and ſhall, ſo long as doth the Truth indure▪
               
               More truth then Sacred veritie:
               no creature can require.
               And who ſo likes ſimplicitie,
               lo heere his full deſire▪
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE FIRST PART OF THE SVMME OF THE HOLIE HISTORY.
            
               The firſt Section.
               
                  
                     IN the beginning God the Lord,
                  did heauen &amp; earth create
                  Of nought; by his almighty word,
                  as Scriptures doe relate.
                  Out of a void and formeleſſe maſſe,
                  the matter of each creature,
                  
                     Geneſis He wrought them all in ſixe daies ſpace,
                  and gaue them ſhape and feature. 
                        cap. 1
                  
                  The firſt day he commanded light,
                  the darkeneſſe to preuent:
                  
                     
The ſecond day, hee reard in ſight,
                  the ſtately Firmament:
                  The third, the earth with fruits adorn'd
                  the ſwelling ſea debarres:
                  The fourth, the Sunne and Moone were form'd,
                  with all the glorious Starres:
                  The fifth, the Fiſh with ſcales and ſinnes,
                  and then the feathred Foule:
                  The ſixth, the beaſts and creeping things:
                  and then that liuing Soule,
                  Which that one God in perſons three,
                  made, as by conſultation,
                  With purpoſe that the ſame ſhould bee,
                  the glory of his Creation,
                  Euen man, fram'd out of earthly duſt▪
                  
                  yet Gods owne image bearing,
                  Thereby right holy, wiſe, and iuſt,
                  (earth farre aboue earth rearing.)
                  And for his aide, who was alone,
                  of Adams rib made Eue,
                  
                  That both, as of one fleſh and bone,
                  might mutuall comfort giue.
                  Thus hauing finiſh'd all with ſpeed,
                  and bleſt them, and proteſted,
                  That each thing made was good indeed;
                  the ſeuenth day he reſted.
                  Man made in perfect ſtate moſt pure,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 2 in paradiſe was placed;
                  
                     
As Lord of euery creature
                  with power aboue them graced.
                  There had he euery fruit for meat,
                  that then in Eden grew,
                  Saue one; whereof when he did eat,
                  death, death, ſhould then enſue.
                  But this ſtrict charge did not reſtraine, 
                        cap. 3
                  
                  the Serpent Eue beguiled,
                  And Adam ſhee; ſo both to paine,
                  with ſhame were thence exiled.
                  Now wretched man was wrap't in woe,
                  and in his loines, his heires,
                  For curſed and corrupt they goe;
                  yet to preuent deſpaires,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 15. God promiſed them to reſtore,
                  vnto a ſtate more ſtable.
                  And Eue vnto her husband bore,
                  his two ſonnes Kain and Abel. 
                     
                        cap. 4
                  
                  
                     Kain was accur'ſt for bloody deede,
                  againſt his better brother;
                  
                     Anno Mund 130.
                      But Habel ſlaine, God in his ſteed
                  gaue Sheth vnto his mother.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 2.
               
                  FRom Sheth did ſpring a righteous line 
                        cap. 5
                  
                  of iuſt and holy men,
                  
                     
                     Henoch a rare and pure Diuine
                  God tooke away as then.
                  
                     
                        Anno. 1056. His grand-child Lamech did beget
                  
                     Noah: and then began,
                  The ſonnes of God their face to ſet,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 6 on daughters faire of man:
                  Thence Giants came, a mungrel kinde
                  on whom the Lord did frowne,
                  And for their ſinne and wicked minde,
                  did threat the world to drowne.
                  
                     Noah alone one earth did liue
                  vprightly; him God ſent,
                  And did an hundred yeeres them giue,
                  and twenty to repent.
                  Meane while built Noah as his charge
                  an Arke three ſtories high:
                  The wicked world liu'd ſtill at large,
                  and dream'd that Noe did lie:
                  Till fountaines burſt, and open ſtood
                  
                     
                        cap. 7 heauen windowes all, for raine,
                  Which quickely cauſ'd a fearefull flood,
                  for downe it powres amaine,
                  
                     
                        Anno. 1656. And all the earth with ruine fils;
                  men, beaſts, and birds muſt die,
                  When as the flood aboue the hils
                  flow'd fifteene cubits high.
                  For twelue months ſpace wel neere it rag'd:
                  and then was Noah bidden,
                  
                     
To looſe thoſe creatures few, which cag'd,
                  and in the Arke were hidden.
                  So Noah, his wife, his ſonnes, and theirs
                  came foorth in number eight;
                  The vncleane creatures all by peires,
                  the cleane by ſeuens: ſtreight
                  He offered ſacrifice, God ſmell'd, 
                        cap. 8
                  
                  a ſmell of reſt: wherefore
                  He promiſed though man rebell'd
                  to drowne the world no more:
                  And gaue the Raine-bow for a pledge,
                  and alſo did make good.
                  Aboue the beaſts, mans priuiledge, 
                        cap. 9
                  
                  giuing their fleſh for food.
                  So, hauing now his couenant made
                  of mercy, grace and peace,
                  Bleſt Noah, and his ſonnes he bade
                  they ſhould mankinde increaſe.
                  Of Iapheth did the Gentiles ſpring, 
                        cap. 10
                  
                  the Canaanites of Cham, 
                     
                        cap 9. 22
                  
                  Who curſed was for opening
                  his fathers ſinne and ſhame.
                  Now all the world in ſpeech was one, 
                        cap 11
                  
                  
                     
                        Anno. 17
                           •
                        6. and did to build conſpire
                  A Babel, and confuſion
                  they gained for their hire.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 3.
               
                  FRom Shem the ſonne of Noah came,
                  an holy race and fruitfull,
                  
                     
                        Anno 2008. Continued euen to Abraham
                  
                  the father of the faithfull.
                  Who left his land, his kindred all,
                  and fathers houſe moſt deare,
                  When him the Lord his God did call
                  to goe, he knew not where.
                  
                     
                        cap. 12 From Vr, he went to Canaan,
                  
                  with Sarai and with Lot,
                  
                  To ſettle there he ſcarce began
                  but that by famine hot,
                  To Aegypt he was forc'd to flie,
                  where fearing much his life,
                  Before King Pharaoh fainingly
                  he did deny his wife.
                  
                     
                        cap. 13 To Bethel he goes backe againe,
                  where ſtrife began to grow,
                  Twixt Lot and him; for wealth amaine,
                  did in vpon them flow.
                  Old Abraham with humble heart,
                  to yonger Lot gaue place,
                  And after that in loue tooke part,
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 and reſcued him in chaſe.
                  
                     
So Melchizedek did him bleſſe,
                  but childleſſe ſtill he ſtaid
                  Till Iſmael: and that increaſe 
                        Cap. 16
                  
                  was but by 
                        
                           •
                        arai's maide.
                  Yet God by ſpeciall promiſes, 
                        Cap. 13. 16. 15. 5. 17. 6.
                  
                  himſelfe did often tie,
                  As heauens ſtars, and ſand of ſeas,
                  his ſeed to mu tiplie.
                  And for aſſurance, thereupon
                  a ſeale he did ordaine, 
                        Cap. 17
                  
                  The ſigne of circumeiſion, 
                  
                  on each male to remaine.
                  
                     
                        Jam. 2. 23. And as a friend did entertaine
                  him, full familiarly:
                  As (once for al) appeared plaine
                  when Sodoms ſinnefull cry 
                        Cap. 18
                  
                  Did pierce the skies, and God down came,
                  and if but tenne good men
                  Could there be found; for Abraham,
                  
                  the Lordhad ſpar'd it then.
                  So, fire and brimſtone fearefully
                  from heauen fell apace,
                  And furnace-like the ſmoake did flie. 
                        Cap. 19
                  
                  poore Lot preſerued was,
                  And vnto Zoar fled for life,
                  where, in a drunken moode,
                  On's daughters, (hauing loſt his wife)
                  he got a 
                        Moab the father of the Moabites.
                        Beniammi the father of the Ammoni
                              ••
                           s.
                      curſed broode.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 4.
               
                  
                     
                        cap. 20 THence Abraham went to Gerar land,
                  where he againe for feare,
                  His wife denied: and by Gods hand,
                  
                     Abimelech did forbeare.
                  Long had he waited, hope was paſt,
                  yet ſtill he did beleene:
                  
                     
                        cap. 21 So, God remembred him at laſt,
                  and Sarah did conceiue:
                  And in her old age Izhaak bare,
                  her ſelfe becomming nurſe:
                  Marke heere a good old Ladies care;
                  the child was neare the worſe.
                  This onely ſonne, and onely heire
                  of promiſe, God commands
                  
                     
                        Anno. 2108. Muſt now be ſlaine, and burnt with fire
                  and that by Abrahams hands:
                  Well, he obei'd, and call'd his men,
                  wood, knife, and ſonne he tooke,
                  On to the place they goe: and when
                  was bent the fatall ſtrooke,
                  God ſtaid his hand, and in the ſteed
                  of Izhaak there was tied,
                  
                     
                        cap. 22 A Ramme by th'hornes, and thus indeed,
                  good Abrahams faith was tried.
                  
                     
His ſonne thus ſpar'd, his godly care
                  was next about to ſpie
                  For him a wife, and therefore ſware 
                        cap. 24
                  
                  his mans fidelity.
                  Who full religiouſly perform'd
                  the office on him laid,
                  And with Rebeckah ſoone return'd,
                  a faire and vertuous maid,
                  Whom Izhaak married; but ſtill,
                  ſhe barren was; they praid: 
                        cap. 25
                  
                  God heard, and granted all their will,
                  and further to her ſaid,
                  That in her wombe the babes that ſtroue,
                  
                     
                        Anno. 2168. were twinnes and nations twaine,
                  The yonger ſhould preuaile aboue:
                  the elder ſhould remaine
                  A ſeruant: Eſau was his name,
                  and as he veniſon ſought,
                  And wearied backe and hungry came,
                  his yonger brother bought
                  His birth right, for a meſſe of broth:
                  God Izhaak bleſt meane while,
                  For which his enemies were wroth, 
                        Cap. 26
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ. 14. 15. and plaied parts moſt vile.
                  When age came on and eies waxt dimme,
                  then ſolemnely he ment,
                  To bleſſe his ſonne, requiring him,
                  Veniſon for that intent,
                  
                     
About goes Eſau with his bow,
                  but Iaacob doth preuent him;
                  The meanes his mother did him ſhowe,
                  
                     
                        cap. 27 and cunningly preſent him,
                  In Eſaus clothes and skinnes of kids,
                  vnto his father; who
                  Miſtruſts the voice, and therefore bids,
                  come neere to feele and know.
                  With fat of earth, and heauens dew,
                  with happy ſeed and kinne,
                  Hee bleſt him: (reuerend was the ſhew)
                  and then came Eſau in.
                  And he with teares and piteous mone,
                  the bleſſing ſought in vaine,
                  He came too late, alas 'twas gone.
                  With that he whet his braine,
                  Reuenge to ſeeke, and worke: and then,
                  the daies (quoth he) make ſpeede
                  Of mourning for my father, when
                  I will pay home this deede.
               
            
            
               Section 5.
               
                  THen did Rebekah forthwith call,
                  and ſend Iaacob away,
                  Leſt Eſau in his rage ſhould fall
                  on him, and ſhould him ſlay.
                  
                     
And Izhaak charg'd him (taking leaue)
                  to play a wiſer part
                  Then Eſau; who did vexe and grieue
                  by heathen wiues, their heart.
                  But he ſhould to his vncle goe, 
                        cap. 28
                  
                  and match in godly race,
                  And bleſsing ſhould be with him; ſo
                  he went out from their face.
                  As he in fields that night did ſleepe,
                  in Haran, on a ſtone,
                  By dreame he ſaw a ladder ſteepe
                  from heauen; and there-on
                  The Angels paſsing, and aboue
                  God ſtanding all in view,
                  The bleſſed promiſe of his loue,
                  with Iaacob to renew.
                  There Iacob vow'd, the Lord to feare:
                  thence on he went apace,
                  Inquiring in the fields to heare,
                  of Labans dwelling place.
                  The ſhepheards ſhewed him readily,
                  his coſen Rahel there: 
                        cap. 29
                  
                  Whom he ſaluted cheerfully,
                  and ſhee could not forbeare,
                  But ran and caried home the newes:
                  then Laban hies to meet him,
                  To dwell there he muſt not refuſe,
                  where all his kindred greet him,
                  
                     
A match was made, and ſeuen yeeres,
                  for Rahel he muſt worke,
                  But Leah in the light appeares,
                  (deceits in darkeneſſe lurke.)
                  Well, ſeuen moe he was content
                  to ſerue for his beloued,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 29 And thought the time full quickly ſpent,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 20. though full of toile it proued.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 31. 38. 39. God bleſſed Laban for his ſake,
                  but him he bleſt much more,
                  What euer wages he did take,
                  to him was gaine in ſtore.
                  Then Laban did enuie his wealth,
                  Yet loath'd to let him goe.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 31 So Iaakob fled away by ſtealth,
                  and made him (following) know
                  The wrong he did; and both good friends,
                  after a chiding, parted.
                  Then Iaakob in his iourney ſends
                  to pacifie hard-hearted
                  
                     Eſau his brother, who in Armes
                  was then againſt him bent;
                  But God preuented all the harmes,
                  by altering his intent.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 32 So Iaakob, called Iſrael,
                  
                  (for God had chang'd his name
                  When he preuail'd at Peniel)
                  
                  in peace to Shechem came.
                  
                     
Heere Dinah muſt a gadding goe, 
                        Cap. 34
                  
                  but ſauc'd her ſport with ſhame,
                  And cauſ'd the Shechemits much woe,
                  being too too much to blame.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 6.
               
                  THence vp to Bethel had he word, 
                        Cap. 35
                  
                  to goe to pay his vow
                  Of holy worſhip: for the Lord
                  againe to Canaan now,
                  From Padan Aram had him fet;
                  where mightily he grew,
                  In cattle, ſeruants, ſubſtance great,
                  and ſonnes, whoſe names enſue:
                  Reuben, Dan, Leui, Simeon, 
                        Cap. 29
                  
                  Iſſachar, Napthalim, 
                  
                  Aſher, Gad, Iudah, Zebulon,
                  Ioſeph and Beniamin.
                  Theſe Patriarks were, of whom great men
                  and Princes did proceed,
                  God keeping promiſe vnto them
                  and their ſucceeding ſeed.
                  
                     Iudah the royall line enioi'd,
                  who for a deede amiſſe,
                  Had Tamars life with fire deſtroi'd, 
                        Cap. 38
                  
                  but that the fault was his.
                  
                     
Yong Ioſeph, Iaakobs ioy, the reſt
                  ſtill ſtomacked and ſpited,
                  Yet hatred he deſerued leaſt,
                  had him his brethren righted.
                  For enuie they conſpir'd to kill;
                  
                     
                        Cap. 37 but Ruben did perſwade:
                  Yet ſecretly they did him ſell,
                  to men of Merchants trade;
                  Who ſold him vnto Potiphar,
                  
                  
                     
                        Cap. 39 where though he liued chaſt,
                  And faithfully himſelfe did beare,
                  he was in priſon caſt.
                  But God beheld his miſerie,
                  and gaue him wiſedom great,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 41 By which he was aduanced high,
                  euen next to Pharaohs ſeat.
                  For when the king no reſt could finde,
                  of dreames that him had paſt,
                  Th' vngratefull buttler, then to mind
                  doth Ioſeph call at laſt.
                  And then he was from priſon ſent,
                  and ſet before the King;
                  Where he to Pharaohs great content,
                  expounded euery thing.
                  Beſides, he▪ ſhew'd a ready way,
                  the famine to withſtand;
                  Which Pharaoh lik'd, and then did lay
                  on him the charge in hand.
                  
                     
So by him was prouiſion made, 
                        Cap. 47
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ 14. 17. 19. againſt the time of neede,
                  Wherewith (to Pharaoh gainefull trade)
                  all Aegypt he did feed.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 7.
               
                  OLd Iaakob and his ſonnes alſo, 
                        Cap. 42
                  
                  Were pinch'd with penurie,
                  Wherefore he charged them to goe
                  and foode in Egypt buy.
                  They went with griefe, and bought in feare,
                  not dreaming of their brother,
                  Nor did he countenance them beare
                  more kinde then any other.
                  Till when they came to him againe, 
                        Cap. 45
                  
                  affection was ſo great,
                  He could no longer it containe,
                  which in his breſt for heate
                  With weeping eie and ioifull tongue,
                  he then did plainely tell,
                  He was their brother, whom with wrong
                  to Egypt they did ſell.
                  The ioy of either was ſo much,
                  that neither now could beare it:
                  Their ſobbing paſsion was ſuch,
                  that Pharaohs houſe did heare it▪
                  
                  
                     
Who then aduertiſed of it,
                  commanded preſently,
                  With Charets and what elſe was fit,
                  For Iacob they ſhould hie.
                  
                     
                        Anno 2298. So he, with all his family
                  went thither out of hand,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 46 Where they were welcom'd louingly,
                  and plac'd in Goſhen Land.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 47 In Goſhen Land did Iacob ſee
                  the fulneſſe of his daies,
                  In Ioſephs liues proſperity,
                  his fill of earthly ioies.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 49 But ſolemnely before his death
                  he bleſt his ſonnes each one:
                  And Ioſeph eke gaue vp the breath,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 50 ere many yeeres were gone.
                  Now when theſe fathers both were dead,
                  and ſtill their ſeede did grow:
                  There roſe a Pharaoh in his ſtead,
                  that did not Ioſeph know.
                  
                     Exodus He tyrant-like, with heauy hand,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 1 of bondage preſt them downe,
                  And gaue the midwiues ſtrait command,
                  the males to kill or drowne.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 8.
               
                  
                     
                        Anno 2428. Borne in theſe flames was Moſes milde,
                  and by Gods prouidence,
                  Though caſt in Riuer flags (poore child)
                  yet was he freed thence,
                  By Pharaohs daughter, who did take,
                  and keepe him as her owne 
                        cap. 2
                  
                  Vntill he came to mans eſtate,
                  when fearing to be knowne,
                  For killing an Egyptian; he
                  forſooke the Court and fled:
                  And all this was by Gods decree,
                  whoſe worke muſt now be ſped.
                  For God had heard the grieuous crie
                  of Hebrues, ſore oppreſſed,
                  And Moſes he ment to imploy 
                        cap. 3
                  
                  in hauing it redreſſed.
                  Him then he call'd and ſent away
                  to proud King Pharaoh, 
                     
                        cap. 4
                  
                  Requiring him without delay
                  to let his people goe.
                  
                     
                        Anno 2508. But he the Lord God did deſpiſe,
                  and asked, what was he?
                  Increaſing more and more their cries,
                  by greater cruelty. 
                        cap 5
                  
                  
                     
The Lord, to tame this Tyrant ſtout,
                  and his own folke to right,
                  With Moſes ſendeth Aaron out,
                  
                     
                        cap. 7 
                     The ten plagues numbred in their order.to make him know his might.
                  They cauſed Blood, Frogs, Lice, and Flies,
                  and Murraine, Scabs and Haile,
                  
                     
                        cap. 8 And Graſhoppers and darkne Skies,
                  all Aegypt to aſſaile.
                  
                     
                        Cap 9 
                     
                        cap. 10 Excepting Goſhen land, where dwelt
                  Gods people Iſrael.
                  
                  Yet Pharaohs heart did nothing melt,
                  for ſtill he did rebell.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 12 Then God the Paſſe-ouer ordain'd
                  And bade them with the blood,
                  Their dore-poſts ſhould be ouerſtain'd,
                  for their ſafe-gard and good.
                  Leſt that his Angel paſſing by,
                  ſhould ſmite them with the reſt:
                  For he the firſt borne did deſtroy,
                  of Egypt, man and beaſt
                  From Egypt then they forced went,
                  with borrowed Iewels plenty,
                  When they in Egypt, yeeres had ſpent,
                  foure hundred ten and twenty.
                  But Pharaoh did repent the deed,
                  and forthwith did not ſlack,
                  With men and charrets to make ſpeed,
                  againe to fetch them back.
                  
                     
And to the red Sea them purſued, 
                        cap. 14
                  
                  they paſſed thorow dry,
                  He followed with courage proud,
                  but in the midſt did lie.
                  For God affrighted man and horſe,
                  and made his Charets fall;
                  The Sea return'd with raging force,
                  and drowned king and all.
                  Of this ſo ſtrange deliuerance,
                  was then a worthy ſong, 
                        Cap. 15
                  
                  Recorded for remembrance,
                  and ſo they march'd along.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 9.
               
                  
                     Iob. ABout this time (the learned Iudge)
                  did patient Iob indure
                  All miſchiefs that the Diuels grudge,
                  and malice could procure.
                  Spoile of his goods and children deare,
                  torments of bodie and minde,
                  As by his botches might appeare,
                  and wife and friends vnkind.
                  Who long and large diſcourſes had,
                  to proue him plagu'd for ſinne,
                  Whereby they did affliction adde,
                  to miſery he was in.
                  
                     
And to ſuch paſsions did him driue,
                  twixt hearts deſpaire and hope,
                  That fleſh and ſpirit did ſtrongly ſtriue,
                  and ſcarce to breath gaue ſcope:
                  
                     
                        cap. 42 But God in fine, his Iob commends
                  doubling his former weale,
                  And check'd his vniuſt iudging friends.
                  But now to Iſrael.
                  
                  
                     
                        cap. 13 The Lord their God in open ſight
                  directed them the way,
                  By firie pillar in the night,
                  and ſhading clowde by day.
                  With Angels foode and waters fine,
                  from rocks that forced ſtreame
                  
                     
                        c. 15. 24. He fill'd them: yet they did repine,
                  
                      full oft, ere that they came
                  
                      To Sinai; where the mighty God,
                  
                     
                        cap 19 in glory did appeare.
                  And they in feare, far off abode,
                  nor durſt, nor might come neere.
                  
                     
                        cap. 20 There did he giue the tenne commands,
                  and other Lawes did write,
                  For to containe them in the bands
                  of holineſſe and right.
                  There did he vnto Moſes ſhow,
                  
                     
                        cap. 26 the Tabernacles frame,
                  In euery point he taught him how
                  to make and vſe the ſame.
                  
                     
There made he choice of Leuies tribe, 
                        cap. 28
                  
                  the Prieſthood to attend,
                  Their duties all he did deſcribe,
                  and what to them pertain'd;
                  Meane while had Iſrael made a Calfe, 
                        cap. 32
                  
                  and grieuouſly offended;
                  But Moſes zeale in Gods behalfe
                  deſerues to be commended:
                  Who ſharpely puniſh'd with the ſword,
                  about three thouſand men,
                  And earneſtly beſought the Lord
                  to ſpare the remnant then.
                  God granted it, and promiſed 
                        cap. 33
                  
                  his Angell ſhould (in token
                  Of loue) them leade; and then hee did 
                        cap, 34
                  
                  renew the Tables broken.
                  Full forty daies and forty nights,
                  was Moſes in the hill,
                  Recording what the Lord indites,
                  his precepts, lawes, and will.
                  Familiarly and face to face,
                  and faſting from all food,
                  He waited in that holy place:
                  And thence he came and ſtood,
                  In preaſe of people to repeat
                  all that the Lord had ſaid;
                  When of his face, the brightneſſe great
                  made them the while afraid.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 10.
               
                  
                     
                        Anno 2510. VVHen as the Tabernacle now,
                  was rear'd and finiſhed:
                  
                     
                        cap. 40 And all wherewith in order due,
                  it ſhould be furniſhed:
                  
                     Numbers Towards Canaan the promiſed land
                  
                     
                        cap. 10 that flow'd with milke and hony,
                  They marched forth band after band;
                  But ſtubborne ſtill and ſtony:
                  For by the way they ſoone forgot
                  Gods mercy and his power,
                  And car'd not how they him prouok't
                  to anger euery houre.
                  They long for fleſh, they Manna loath,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 11 and backe they will retire,
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 They fret at God and Moſes both,
                  for croſsing their deſire.
                  Nor would they warned be, though they
                  his dreadfull iudgements law,
                  On them inflicted day by day,
                  which liu'd not vnder law.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 16 
                     As Korah, Dathan, Abiram,
                  with thouſands moe among,
                  
                     
                        cap. 12 Nadah, Abil
                        ••
                     , Miriam
                  and ſuch as ſerpents ſtong.
                  
                     
Yet tempted they the Lord ſo long, 
                        Cap. 12
                  
                  and with ſo high an hand,
                  That in his wrath he ſware, not one
                  ſhould enter to the land,
                  Saue Ioſhua and Caleb, who 
                        Cap. 14
                  
                  returning with the ſpies,
                  Affirm'd the truth that they did know,
                  and croſſ'd their fellowes lies,
                  So wandred they in wilderneſſe,
                  the ſpace of forty yeares,
                  Till all were dead that did tranſgreſſe; 
                        cap. 26
                  
                  as by Gods booke appeares.
                  Their children then he forward led,
                  but others kept them backe;
                  As Sihon, Og, and Moahs head, 
                        c. 15. 21.
                  
                  who nam'd was Balaak,
                  
                  Who hired Balaam them to curſe,
                  and ſo thought to moleſt them:
                  But for himſelfe it was much worſe, 
                        cap. 22
                  
                  for Balaam three times bleſt them.
                  He with thoſe two, and fiue kings moe, 
                        cap. 31
                  
                  which were of Midian,
                  
                  Were in reuenge of Baal-peor
                  
                  ſubdued, ſpoiled, ſlaine.
                  Heere Rubens Tribe, and alſo Gads, 
                     
                        cap. 32
                  
                  their heritage poſſeſt:
                  But they in armes, like luſty lads,
                  muſt march before the reſt,
                  
                     
                     
                        Num. 34. Heere Moſes named euery one,
                  that ſhould the Land diuide,
                  And giue a fit poſſeſsion,
                  to euery Tribe beſide.
                  
                     
                        Deut. 31. But Moſes now muſt make an end,
                  as did his fathers all:
                  Wherefore he did not time miſſpend,
                  but foorth did Ioſhua call,
                  As God had bid: and gaue him charge
                  the people to conduct,
                  
                     
                        cap. 28 Whom he by Sermons long and large,
                  
                      diuinely did inſtruct.
                  
                      Which with a ſweet and Swan-like ſong,
                  
                      in heauenly wiſe he ended,
                  
                      And bleſt the Tribes, each one along,
                  and foorth with hee aſcended
                  
                     
                        cap. 34 Mount Nebo, vnto Piſgah top,
                  where as he did ſuruay
                  The Canaan land, the earthly hope,
                  God tooke his ſoule away,
                  
                     
                        Anno 2549. To heauens reſt; and buried then,
                  his body none know where,
                  When peere-leſſe he amongſt all men,
                  had liu'd full ſixe ſcore yeare,
                  And yet his eie-ſight was not dimme,
                  nor natures force did wither,
                  There Iſrael lamented him,
                  for thirty daies together.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 11.
               
                  
                     
                        Joſh. 1. THen did the Lord call Ioſhua,
                  
                  and bid him to be ſtrong,
                  And truſt in him who was his ſtay,
                  and boldly goe along.
                  So he the Captaine ſends out ſpies, 
                        cap. 2
                  
                  whom Rahab ſafe did hide,
                  And they return'd in ioifull wiſe,
                  which made them to prouide
                  To paſſe with ſpeed into the land. 
                        cap. 3
                  
                  At Ioſhuah's powerfull word
                  The Iordan waters backe did ſtand,
                  and paſſage drie afford.
                  In mid'ſt whereof in open view, 
                        cap 4
                  
                  they did a pillar reare.
                  The circumciſion they renew,
                  the Manna ceaſed there. 
                        cap. 5
                  
                  Then ſet they vpon Iericho, 
                     
                        cap. 6
                  
                  and alſo vpon Ai. 
                     
                        cap. 7
                  
                  But Achans ſinne did worke them woe,
                  and from the conqueſt ſtay.
                  The Gibeonites dealt craftily, 
                        cap. 9
                  
                  ſo they eſcap'd alone.
                  The reſt they voided vtterly,
                  to place the Tribes each one.
                  
                     
They caſt them out and did them kill,
                  with a victorious hand.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 10 For this the Sunne and Moone ſtood ſtill,
                  at Ioſhuahs command.
                  When he had now fully poſſeſt,
                  each ſeuerall Tribe in order,
                  And giuen to all, content and reſt
                  by lot, in euery border:
                  
                     
                        cap, 24 He bent himſelfe, and grauely ſpake,
                  to ſtay them from back-ſliding,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 24. Twixt God and them, a league he ſtrake,
                  by his example guiding.
                  And ſtill exhorting them to feare
                  the Lord, and him obey,
                  
                     
                        Anno. 2566. He witneſſed for them his care,
                  and paſſ'd by death away.
                  Full ſoone had they the Lord forgot,
                  when Ioſhua was dead.
                  
                     
                        cap. 1 Then Iudah had the charge and lot
                  their Armies forth to lead.
                  But for their great tranſgreſsions,
                  and league with Canaanite,
                  
                  God gaue them to oppreſsions,
                  of cruell men of might.
                  Who ſpoil'd them without meane or end
                  and did them ſorely grieue,
                  
                     
                        cap. 2 Vntill their God did Iudges ſend,
                  their greeuance to releeue.
                  
                     
Againſt King Cuſhans tyranny, 
                        cap. 3
                  
                  ſtout Othniel raiſed he.
                  And when fat Eglon made them crie,
                  lame Ehud ſet them free.
                  Gainſt Siſera of Canaan, 
                     
                        cap 4
                  
                  did Deborah preuaile.
                  Now Ruth good Boaz woed and wan,
                  when neerer kinne did faile.
                  Gainſt Midian a mighty hoſt, 
                        cap. 7
                  
                  march'd captaine Gedeon.
                  
                  Bloody Abimelech did boaſt, 
                        cap. 9
                  
                  he next would raigne, or none.
                  The proud oppreſſing Ammonite, 
                     
                        Cap. 11
                  
                  by Iphtah was ſubdued.
                  The Philiſtines for all their ſpite, 
                        Cap. 15
                  
                  the birth of Sampſon rued.
                  Whoſe matchleſſe ſtrength miraculous,
                  was ouermatch'd by guile,
                  Of Dalilah perfidious, 
                        Cap. 16
                  
                  who wrought his bane the while.
                  When none amongſt them rul'd as king
                  ech what he liſted did;
                  Then Micah made a molten thing, 
                        Cap. 17
                  
                  and it he worſhipped.
                  And at ſuch time, that hainous ſinne,
                  vpon the Leuites wife, 
                        cap. 19
                  
                  Twixt Iſrael and twixt Beniamin,
                  
                  coſt many a thouſands life. 
                        cap. 20
                  
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 12.
               
                  
                     1. Sam.
                      
                     ELi was Iudge in Iſrael,
                  
                  when for his ſonnes lewd waies,
                  
                     
                        cap. 3 God threatned him by Samuel,
                  
                  ſharpe vengeance he would raiſe.
                  This Samuel a righteous man,
                  
                     
                        Anno 2905. was laſt of all that iudged,
                  And in his time the Kings began,
                  
                     
                        cap. 8 for then the people grudged,
                  And in their diſcontented moode
                  would haue a king to raigne:
                  Which motion Samuel withſtood,
                  as tending to ther paine.
                  
                     
                        Cap 9 But yet the Lord did them appoint,
                  a goodly man and taule,
                  And Samuel did him annoint
                  their King, his name was Saul.
                  
                  A Princely minde God to him gaue,
                  with complements of place,
                  
                     
                        cap. 13 And he with Ionathan did braue
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 his enemies oft in chaſe.
                  Yet God that him aduanc'd ſo high,
                  
                     
                        cap. 15. 2 from toile and Aſſes care,
                  Hee diſobeied when fooliſhly,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 15 King Agag he did ſpare.
                  
                     
Therefore the Lord did him reiect,
                  and little Dauid choſe,
                  Annointed Iſraels king elect, 
                        Cap. 16
                  
                  when he ſhould Saul depoſe.
                  Now great Goliah plaid his prize, 
                        Cap. 17
                  
                  but Dauid knockt him downe,
                  The people ſhout with ioifull cries,
                  and giue him chiefe renoune.
                  
                     Saul bit the lip at Dauids praiſe, 
                        cap. 18
                  
                  and hated him the more,
                  Yea ſought his life all manner waies,
                  and chaſ'd him lik a Bore 
                        cap. 19
                  
                  With Iauelling and with threatning ſword 
                  
                  with troupes of horſe and men,
                  From houſe and home, from bed &amp; boord 
                        Cap. 22
                  
                  from deſert den to den. 
                  
                  Forced he was himſelfe to faine, 
                        cap. 21
                  
                  with Achiſh to be mad,
                  And for defenſe to entertaine 
                        cap. 22
                  
                  lewd runnagates, was glad.
                  But Ionathan his faithfull frend, 
                        Cap. 18
                  
                  at no time did forſake him, 
                        Cap. 19
                  
                  And warning did of danger ſend,
                  when Saul vſ'd meanes to take him, 
                        cap. 20
                  
                  Although for it he did engage,
                  himſelfe in danger deepe,
                  For ſuch was Sauls ſuſpitious rage,
                  None might his counſell keepe.
                  
                     
                     
                        Cap. 22 
                     Ahimelech did giue him bread
                  in his neceſsity,
                  
                     
                        cap. 22 But for it he was murdered,
                  and all his progeny.
                  Had Dauid laboured like for like,
                  to Saul for to repay,
                  He had both time and place to ſtrike,
                  and followers bade him ſlay.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 24 As in the caue; and from his head
                  
                     
                        cap. 26 when he tooke pot and ſpeare.
                  But he, to touch did euer dread
                  the Lords annoited deare.
                  And that he did both mercy loue,
                  and bloody vengeance flee,
                  
                     
                        cap. 25 When churliſh Nabal did him proue,
                  wiſe Abigail did ſee.
                  Now Saul with enuie almoſt pin'de
                  and driuen to diſtreſſe,
                  
                     
                        cap. 28 Sought by a wrethed witch to finde
                  ſome comfort and redreſſe.
                  Of which he fail'd, and in the field
                  as deſperatly he fought,
                  His ſonnes were ſlaine, his ſoldiers yeeld,
                  and gaſtly he beſought
                  
                     
                        Cap. 31 His Armour-bearer, him to kill;
                  but he the deed, abhor'd;
                  His owne heart blood then did he ſpill,
                  with his owne hand and ſword.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 13.
               
                  
                     2. Sam. Anno 2945. THen Dauid was proclaim'd, and raign'd
                  in Hebron, Iudahs King:
                  But Iſhboſheth had Iſrael gain'd
                  by Abners counſelling.
                  Long warre was twixt the houſes both, 
                        cap. 2
                  
                  of Dauid and of Saul,
                  
                  Till Abner with his new king wroth, 
                        cap. 3
                  
                  to Dauids ſide did fall.
                  This Abner and eke Iſhboſheth,
                  
                  were ſlaine by villany:
                  But Dauid did lament their death,
                  and murderers all defie. 
                        cap. 4
                  
                  So, now he was eſtabliſhed
                  ſole king of all the Land;
                  His warres and all things flouriſhed, 
                        cap. 5
                  
                  that he did take in hand.
                  Then ſolemnely he thought it fit, 
                        cap. 6
                  
                  to fetch the Arke more neere him,
                  But Vzzahs death did hinder it,
                  Gods iudgement did ſo feare him.
                  Yet afterward he brought it on,
                  and purpoſed to reare
                  A houſe for God; but he would none, 
                        cap. 7
                  
                  as Nathan did declare.
                  
                     
When he had all his foes ſubdued,
                  and as a Monarch raigned,
                  In peace and eaſe; ſee what enſu'd,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 11 his vpright life was ſtained
                  With murder and adultery:
                  
                     
                        Cap. 12 whereof though he repented,
                  Yet was he puniſh'd diuerſly
                  with haps to bee lamented.
                  Firſt, Abſalom ſhed Amnons blood,
                  (vengeance doth inceſt cloſe)
                  
                     
                        Cap. 13 
                     
                        Cap. 15 And after like a Rebel ſtood,
                  His father to depoſe.
                  
                     Achitophel that crafty wretch
                  had chiefe hand in this matter,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 17 But Huſhai did him ouer-reach,
                  by skill hee had to flatter.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 16 Baſe Shimei with open throte,
                  did curſe him as he fled:
                  
                     
                        cap. 20 And Sheba ſhortly blowes his note,
                  but loſt his traitors head.
                  Loe yet againe, ſinne of the king
                  Gods fearefull wrath reuiues,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 24 The peoples haſtie numbering,
                  coſt ſeuenty thouſands liues.
                  And laſtly, in his aged yeares,
                  
                     1. Kings
                      his ſonne, a wanton bred,
                  
                     
                        cap. 1 Euen Adoniah, boldly teares
                  the Crowne from off his head.
                  
                     
This prophet after Gods owne heart,
                  Pſalmiſt of Iſrael,
                  Did yet at laſt in peace depart, 
                        cap. 2
                  
                  and cloſ'd his daies full well.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 14.
               
                  
                     
                        Anno 2985. NExt him did Salomon his ſonne,
                  the kingdomes Scepter ſway,
                  There neuer ſate on Regall throne,
                  his peere, vnto this day.
                  For wealth, for ſtate, for princely port,
                  for plenty and for peace,
                  For wiſdome rare, and great reſort;
                  which made his fame increaſe. 
                        cap. 3
                  
                  Witneſſe his ſentence in that caſe,
                  of queanes crying out of wrongs.
                  His purueiance, his horſes race, 
                        cap. 4
                  
                  his Prouerbs, Writings, Songs:
                  Witneſſe the glorious Temple, which 
                        cap. 6
                  
                  he built for Gods great name;
                  The coſtly furniture and rich,
                  the treaſures of the ſame.
                  Witneſſe his praiers that excell, 
                        cap. 8
                  
                  for knowledge zeale and fitneſſe.
                  His offerings great, wall'd townes, &amp; well
                  may queene of Saba witneſſe,
                  
                     
Who tooke ſome paines to find out fame]
                  a liar in her kind,
                  But found that though ſhe loaden came,
                  
                     
                        cap. 10. 7 ſhe left much more behinde.
                  Yet Salomon, in midſt of mines,
                  of wiſdome and of treaſure,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 11 A thouſand Wiues and Concubines,
                  got to him for his pleaſure.
                  Theſe drew him from religion
                  and from ſincerity,
                  To wicked ſuperſtition,
                  and groſſe Idolatry.
                  For which Gods iudgement did beginne,
                  his kingdome rent in twaine,
                  
                     Iudah alone and Beniamin,
                  
                  did to his heires remaine.
                  The other Tribes, in number ten.
                  from their allegeance fell,
                  Set vp a king, and nam'd him then,
                  the King of Iſrael.
                  
                  
                     Samaria held the throne Roiall,
                  on which he ruled them;
                  But Iudahs ſeate Imperiall,
                  was faire Ieruſalem.
                  
                  
                     
                        Anno 3025. And there did Rehoboam raigne,
                  when Shiſhak rob'd the Temple:
                  
                     
                        Cap. 12 And next him, his ſonne Abiam,
                  
                  
                     
                        Cap. 14 the worſe for his example.
                  
                     
Then Aſa, then Iehoſaphat,
                  
                  both, good and godly kings, 
                        c. 15. 14.
                  
                  For reformation; ſauing that, 
                        c. 22. 43.
                  
                  they let alone ſome things.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 15.
               Kings of Iſrael.
               
                  MEane while in Iſrael, Nebats ſonne, 
                        Cap. 12
                  
                  King Ieroboam raign'd,
                  An arch-idolater and knowne,
                  by withered hand he gain'd. 
                        cap. 15
                  
                  
                     Nadab his ſonne, King Baaſa,
                  
                  king Elah, and king Zimri,
                  
                  Did for the Crowne each other ſlea, 
                        cap. 16
                  
                  ſo likewiſe did king Omri:
                  
                  But his ſonne Ahab, with his wife,
                  that curſed Iezabel,
                  
                  Did worke ſuch villany and ſtrife,
                  and to ſuch fury fell:
                  That good Eliah fled for feare, 
                        Cap. 17
                  
                  who was by Rauens fed;
                  Who raiſ'd the widowes ſonne ſo deare;
                  who laid Baals Prophets dead. 
                        Cap. 18
                  
                  By whom king Ahab warning had:
                  But words did nought preuaile,
                  
                     
                     
                        verſ. 2. Nor famine; not yet Benhadad,
                  
                  who ſtrongly did aſſaile
                  
                     Samaria: yet for all that
                  he killed Naboth iuſt.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 21 And after, got Iehoſaphat,
                  
                  
                     
                        cap. 22 to ſerue vnto his luſt.
                  For croſſing which, poore Micaiah,
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ. 27. was in the dungeon caſt.
                  But Ioſaphat in battle ſaw
                  
                     
                        verſ. 34. proud Ahab ſlaine at laſt.
                  His ſonne tooke place when he was dead,
                  
                     
                        cap. 1 euen wicked Ahaziah;
                  
                  And after him was Ioram head.
                  as then did good Eliah
                  
                  
                     
                        cap. 2 In firy charret take his flight
                  to heauen; and in his place,
                  His ſpirit did on Eliſha light,
                  with ſpeciall power and grace,
                  To worke great miracles, as by
                  
                     
                        cap. 4 the increaſed oile was proued,
                  And by Naamans leproſie,
                  
                     
                        cap. 5 which ſtrangely he remoued.
                  And by the plenty prophecied,
                  
                     
                        cap. 7 in ſtaru'd Samaria,
                  
                  which th'infidel that ſaid he lied,
                  to his ſmall comfort ſaw.
                  
                     
                        cap. 9 But Iehu did this Ioram quell,
                  and raigned in his ſteed.
                  
                     
He ſlew alſo vile Iezebel, 
                     
                        cap. 10
                  
                  
                     Baals Prieſts and Ahabs ſeed.
                  His wicked ſonne Iehoahaz, 
                     
                        cap. 13
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ. 3. 4. ſucceeded; and the next
                  
                     
                        verſ. 25. Was his ſonne Ioaſh: either was
                  by Arams armies vext.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 16.
               Kings of Judah.
               
                  IN Iudah next Iehoſaphat, 
                     
                        cap. 8
                  
                  did his ſonne Ioram raigne,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 25. Then Ahaziah; then vp ſtart
                  
                     Athalia, who had ſlaine,
                  All the Kings ſonnes that ſhe could catch:
                  young Ioaſh ſcap'd alone, 
                        Cap. 11
                  
                  By helpe of friends who did him fetch,
                  and placed on the throne.
                  Gods houſe decai'd he did repaire, 
                        Cap. 12
                  
                  and left king, when he died,
                  
                     Amaziah his hopefull heire; 
                        cap. 14
                  
                  then Ioel propheſied.
                  Vzziah, Amazia'hs ſonne, 
                     
                        cap. 15
                  
                  was ſtrooke with leproſie,
                  As he did raigne: and then began
                  
                     Iſaiahs propheſie.
                  
                     
                     
                        verſ. 5. 
                     Iotham a Prince of Gods beheſt,
                  ſucceeded next Vzziah:
                  
                  
                     
                        Cap. 16 And after him, Ahaz that beaſt,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 18 and then raign'd Hezekiah.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  Section 17.
               Kings of Iſrael.
               
                  NExt vnto Ioaſh, Iſraels king,
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 did Ieroboam raigne,
                  To Niniue now did Ionas bring
                  Gods meſſage, not in vaine.
                  Then did Hoſea take his text,
                  and Amos propheſie.
                  
                     
                        Cap. 15 But Ieroboam dead; the next
                  was his ſonne Zacharie.
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ. 10. Whom Shallum ſlew in open ſight,
                  and raigned in his ſteed.
                  
                     
                        verſ. 14. But Menahem did him requite,
                  and in his ſeat ſucceede.
                  
                     
                        verſ. 23. Then Pekahia, Men'hems ſonne,
                  did weare the Crowne vntill
                  
                     
                        verſ. 25▪
                      His Captaine Pekah ſeaz'd thereon,
                  and did his Soueraigne kill.
                  Nor had this Pekah raigned long,
                  but he receiu'd his doome,
                  
                     
                     
                        verſ. 30. 
                     Hoſhea did reuenge the wrong,
                  and raigned in his roome.
                  In his time did Salmanaſer, 
                     
                        Cap. 17
                  
                  beſiege Samaria ſtrong,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 6. And tooke Hoſhea priſoner,
                  and led with him along
                  
                     
                        Anno 3265. All Iſrael into Syria;
                  
                  where they did ſtill remaine,
                  And planted in Samaria,
                  
                  of his Aſſyrian traine.
                  
                     
                        verſ 25. Whom God by Lions did moleſt,
                  for their blinde ſuperſtition,
                  Which made them get an Ebrue prieſt,
                  to mend their bad religion.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 18.
               Kings of Judah.
               
                  
                     
                        Anno 3260. THus leauing Iſrael diſpoſſeſt,
                  lets now returne againe,
                  To Iudah, whom the Lord had bleſt,
                  with Hezechias raigne.
                  Againſt him, proud Saneherib, 
                     
                        Cap. 18
                  
                  ſent railing Rabſhekee,
                  
                  Who to his coſt was anſwered, 
                        cap. 19
                  
                  and cauſ'd with ſhame to flee.
                  
                     
Now was the Prophet Micah heard,
                  and Nahum: but we finde,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 20 That this good king, from death preſeru'd
                  to Babel is too kind.
                  Next him, his ſonne Manaſſe raign'd,
                  
                     
                        cap. 21 a wicked cruell king,
                  
                     2. Chron. 33. 12. 13. Vntill he was in Babel chain'd:
                  but thence God did him bring.
                  
                     Ammon his ſonne, the next in row,
                  was for Idolatry,
                  
                     2. Kings 21. 23. Slaine of his ſeruants: and as now,
                  
                     Habakuk did propheſie.
                  Then yong Ioſiah, Ammons ſonne,
                  a worthy Prince and zealous,
                  
                     
                        cap. 22 Made ſuch a reformation
                  as was and will be famous.
                  Now Ieremiah Trumpet-like
                  cries out; and Zephaniah:
                  
                  
                     
                        cap. 23 But Necho's men in battle ſtrike,
                  and ſlea good king Ioſiah.
                  
                  His ſonne Iehoahaz the Crowne
                  obtain'd; but raign'd not long,
                  For Pharaoh Necho put him downe,
                  and chain'd with fetters ſtrong,
                  
                     2. Chron. 36. 4. 2. Kings 24. 1. And plac'd his brother in his roome,
                  
                     Iehoiachim by name,
                  Who Babels vaſſell did become
                  for three yeeres ſpace with ſhame.
                  
                     
                     
                        Anno 3389. And then rebelling brought againe
                  great Nabuchadnezer
                  
                  With all his huge and warlike traine:
                  who tooke him priſoner,
                  And bound and caried him away,
                  with whom to Babylon,
                  
                  Ezechiel, and Mordecai,
                  and Daniel are gone,
                  With other moe of roiall ſeed.
                  
                     1. Chron. 3. 16. 2. Kings 24. 8. verſ. 10. 11. yong Iechoni alone
                  Was left behind in's fathers ſteed,
                  to ſit on Iudahs throne:
                  Nor ſate he long but Babel doth,
                  his Souldiers ſtout command,
                  To fetch him and his treaſure both,
                  and chiefe men of of the Land.
                  
                     
                        Anno 3399. His vncle Zedekiah plac'd,
                  was in his roome, and crowned:
                  Who likewiſe did rebell at laſt:
                  but Babels king ſo frowned, 
                        Cap. 24
                  
                  That vp againſt Ieruſalem, 
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ. 17. 20. the fowerth time he came,
                  And by ſtrong ſiege ſo ſtarued them, 
                        cap. 25
                  
                  that warriours fled with ſhame.
                  
                     
                        verſ. 3. 5. King Zedekiah alſo fled,
                  but Chaldees quickly caught him,
                  And that due iudgement might be had, 
                        cap. 25
                  
                  They vnto Riblah brought him,
                  
                     
                     
                        verſ. 6. And ſlew his ſonnes before his face,
                  and then put out his eies,
                  And chained him with all diſgrace,
                  that elſe they could deuiſe.
                  
                     
                        Anno 3400. And ſo to Babel they returne,
                  with priſoners and with pray.
                  The Temple after that they burne,
                  and take all thence away.
                  
                     
                        verſ. 8. 9. Yea burnt the Palace faire and rich
                  which Solomon did build:
                  And all the goodly houſes which
                  
                     Ieruſalem did yeeld.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 19.
               
                  
                     Daniel BEing now at Babel faſt in hold
                  
                     
                        cap. 1 the fineſt wits were ſought,
                  Of captiue children, to be ſchool'd,
                  and Chaldea learning taught.
                  There Daniel among the reſt,
                  did to ſuch ripeneſſe come,
                  That when a dreame the king oppreſt,
                  and Wiſards all were dumbe,
                  
                     
                        cap. 2 The dreame forgotten, he diſcloſ'd;
                  
                     
                        verſ. 27. which was an Image great,
                  Of metals different compoſ'd,
                  from head vnto the feet.
                  
                     
                     
                        verſ. 46. This made the king much to admire,
                  him and his fellowes all;
                  Yet three were caſt into the fire, 
                        cap. 3
                  
                  for that they would not fall
                  Before his image hugely trimme:
                  but fire could take no hold.
                  Another dreame then vexed him, 
                        cap. 4
                  
                  which Daniel did vnfold;
                  And eke the ſtate of future times, 
                        cap. 7
                  
                  of Monarchs Crownes ſurpriſing. 
                  
                  Of Chriſt preciſely he diuines 
                  
                  and of the deads ariſing. 
                  
                  But Babels king reſtored back,
                  from beaſts, made better end. 
                        cap. 4
                  
                  Next him, raign'd Euilmerodach,
                  
                  euen Ieconiahs friend.
                  
                     
                        Ier. 52. To him ſucceeded Balſhazzar,
                  
                  who, in his drunken feaſt,
                  Did neither God nor's people ſpare, 
                        cap. 5
                  
                  for blaſphemy and ieſt;
                  Till fingers writing on a wall,
                  dazling his very ſight,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 6. Did ſo his countenance appall,
                  was neuer man ſo fright:
                  This writng Daniel expounds;
                  and ſo without delay,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 30. That night Darius all confounds,
                  and tooke his Crowne away.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 20.
               
                  VVHen now full ſeuenty yeeres were ſpent
                  
                     
                        Anno 3458. in their Captiuity;
                  King Cyrus Proclamation ſent,
                  for their deliuery.
                  
                     Zerubbabel doth them retire,
                  
                     Ezra. with all the Temples treaſure,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 1 And full commiſſion to repaire
                  the ruines at their pleaſure.
                  
                     
                        cap. 4 But crafty foes did plot apace,
                  the Lords worke to withſtand,
                  By flattering ſpeech vnto their face,
                  and letters vnder hand;
                  Yea Hammans hatred cankered,
                  had made an vtter riddance,
                  
                     Eſter. Had not Queene Eſter ventured,
                  
                     
                        cap. 3 her life for Iewes deliuerance.
                  
                     Ezra. Then Haggai; alſo Zacharie,
                  
                  
                     
                        Cap. 5 their ſlackneſſe doe reproue;
                  And ſhortly after Malachi,
                  
                  their lacke of zeale and loue.
                  
                     
                        cap. 6. 15. So was the Temple finiſhed,
                  
                     Nehemia by Duke Zerubbabel,
                  
                  
                     
                        Cap. 2 And Nehemi with patent ſped,
                  the walles to build as well,
                  
                     
Which he perform'd for all the hate, 
                        cap. 6. 15
                  
                  of enemies prophane,
                  Tobiah, wicked Sanballat
                  and worſe Samaritane. 
                     
                        Cap. 4
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ. 1. 2. And then he kept a ſolemne feaſt,
                  whereat the Law was read, 
                        Cap. 8
                  
                  And ſeal'd a couenant with the reſt,
                  their God to ſerue and dread. 
                        cap. 10
                  
                  Next Kings and Dukes, the Maccabees,
                  
                  (as ſtories doe recite)
                  
                     
                        
                           1 The Babylonians.
                        
                           2. The Grecians
                        
                           3. The Romans.
                      Did rule them: but the Monarchies,
                  ſtill top't them by their might.
                  In ſuch ſubiection did they mourne,
                  foure hundred yeeres and od,
                  Vntill Meſsiah, Chriſt was borne,
                  true Man, and very God.
               
            
            
               The Dukes of Dauids ſtocke, after the returne out of Captiuity.
               
               
                  1 Ieconias, Ier. 52.
                  2 Shealthiel, Hag. 1.
                  3 Zorobabel.
                  
                  4 Reza,
                  
                  5 Ioanna.
                  
                  
                     6 Iudas Hyrcanus.
                  
                     7 Ioſeph Primus,
                  
                     8 Abner Semei.
                  
                     9 Eli Mattathia.
                  
                     10 Azar Mahat.
                  
                     11 Nagid Artaxad.
                  
                     12 Haggai Eli.
                  
                     
                     13 Maſlot Naum.
                  
                     14 Amos Syrac.
                  
                     15 Mattathia Siloath.
                  
                     16 Ioſeph Secundus.
                  
                     17 Ianna Hyrcanus.
               
               This Ianna was ſlaine by Antiochus Epiphanes king of Syria, who tyrannized ouer them vntill Mattathias the high Prieſt armed and incouraged his ſonnes againſt him, who draue him out of the countrey and ſucceſſiuely raigned in his roome.
            
            
               The Princes and Kings of the Family of the Maccabees.
               
                  
                     
                        1
                        
                           Iudas Maccebeus the ſonne of Mattathias raigned—
                        5. yeeres
                     
                     
                        2
                        
                           Ionathan an other ſonne—
                        19. yeeres
                     
                     
                        3
                        
                           Simon a third ſonne,—
                        8. yeeres
                     
                     
                        4
                        Iohannes Hyrcanus—
                        31 yeeres
                     
                     
                        5
                        
                           Ariſtobulus his ſonne—
                        1 yeere
                     
                     
                        6
                        Alexander Ianneus—
                        27 yeeres
                     
                     
                        7
                        
                           Alexandra his wife—
                        9 yeeres
                     
                  
               
               8 Hyrcanus her ſonne ſucceeded, but Ariſtobulus his younger brother rebelled and made warre againſt him: wherefore Hyrcanus ſent Embaſſadours to Pompey the Romane captaine for aid. Pompey came to Ieruſalem, ſubdued the Rebels, gaue the gouernment

and Prieſthood to Hyrcanus, and caried Ariſtobulus with his two ſonnes Alexander and Antigonus captiues towards Rome. Alexander eſcaped by the way, and returned and got part of Galile, but was taken againe by Gabinius, and afterward put to death at Antioch by Scipio the father in law of Pompey. Antigonus was ſet at liberty by Iulius Caeſar after the battle betweene him and Pompey. But comming into Iewry hee dealt cruelly with his old vncle Hyrcanus the high Prieſt, cutting off his eares and baniſhing him into Parthia, for which cauſe hee was taken againe and executed at Antioch, by Antony, Herods Lieutenant in Iewry.
               
               
                  Herod alſo ſent for Hyrcanus out of Parthia, and put him to death, and ſo came the family of the Maccabees fully to an end, and the kingdome of Iewry was eſtabliſhed to Herod and his heires.
            
            
               The poſterity of Herod.
               THe kingdome or prouince of Iewrie was giuen by Iulius Caeſar to Antipater of I dumaea the father of Herod, in recompence of the faithfull and good ſeruice

which he did him in Egypt, in the time of his warres and danger there.
               1 Herod the ſonne of Antipater, called Herod the great, was made King by the Senate of Rome, and raigned 37. yeeres. He pulled downe the Temple that was built after the Captiuity, and built another after the patterne of Salomons wonderfull richly and ſtately. He put to death Ariſtobulus and Alexander his ſonnes vpon ſuſpition of Treaſon.
               2 Archelaus another of his ſonnes ruled Iudea nine yeeres.
               3 Herod Antipas another ſonne gouerned Galile; he beheaded Iohn Baptiſt.
               
               4 Plilip another ſonne gouerned Ituria.
               
               5 Herod Agrippa the ſonne of Ariſtobulus, who killed Iames, and was eaten vp of wormes, Acts cap. 12.
               
                  Agrippa his ſonne (mentioned with Bernice his ſiſter, Acts 5.) being a child was caried into Syria, and the Romans tooke the gouernment of Iewry againe into their owne hands as in former time.
            
            
               
               
                  A briefe ſupputation of the yeres and times, from the Creation of the World, vnto the birth of Chriſt: collected out of Iunius, according to the Scriptures. 
                  The age of the World.
               
               
                  
                     
                        Geneſis 5.
                     
                        
                           ADam being 130 yeeres old begat Sheth— 
                        
                        
                           Sheth at 105 yeeres old begat Enoſh— 
                        
                        
                           Enoſh at 90 begat Kenan— 
                        
                        
                           Kenan at 70 begat Mahalaleel— 
                        
                        
                           Mahalaleel at 65 begat Iared— 
                        
                        
                           Iared at 162 begat Henoch— 
                        
                        
                           Henoch at 65 begat Methuſhelah 
                           
                        
                        
                           Methuſhelah at 187 begat Lamech— 
                        
                        
                           Lamech at 182 begat Noah— 
                        
                        
                           Noah at 502 begat Shem— 
                        
                        In his 500. yeere he begat Iaphet, for thus Iunius readeth it out of the Hebrue (brother to Iapheth the elder,) Gen. 10. 21.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        Geneſis 11.
                     
                        
                            
                           Shem at 100. yeeres old begat Arphachſhad.—
                        This being two yeeres after the flood, (which came in Noahs ſixe hundreth yeers) it followeth that he was begotten in the fiue hundred and ſecond yeere of Noah, Gen. 11. verſ. 10.
                        
                            
                           Arphachſhad at 35. begat Shelah.
                        
                        
                            —Shelah at 30. begat Heber.
                        
                        
                            —Heber at 35. begat Peleg.
                        
                        
                            —Peleg at 30. begat Reu.
                        
                        
                            —Reu at 32. begat Serug.
                        
                        
                            —Serug at 30. begat Nahor.
                        
                        
                            —Nahor at 29. begat Terah.
                        
                        
                           Terah at 70. began to beget children, (ſaith Iunius) and at 130.  begat Abram—
                     
                  
               
               This plainely appeareth, for Terah was 205. yeeres old when hee died in Haran, Gen. 11. 32. and Abram going out of Haran ſhortly after was but 75. Gen. 12. 4. Now diduct the ſonnes age out of the fathers, and there remaineth 130. to Terah at Abrams birth.
               
                   
                  Abraham at 100 yeeres old begat Izhaak.
               
               
                   
                  Izhaak at 60. begat Eſau and Iaakob.
               
               
                   
                  Iaakob being 130. yeeres old, goeth down

into Egypt, Gen. 47. 9.
               
                  Iaakob died 17. yeeres after his comming  into Egypt, Gen. 47. 28
               
                  Ioſeph died 53. yeeres after his father Iaakob, 
                   
                  Gen. 50,
               
                  Moſes was borne 60. yeeres after the death  of Ioſeph.
               
               
                  Moſes was 80. yeeres old, when hee ſtood  before Pharaoh, Exod. 7. 7.
               The Tabernacle was reared the ſecond  yeere after, Exod. 40. 17.
               
                  Moſes died 40. yeeres after the departure  out of Aegypt, and 39. after the Tabernacle erect, Deut. 1. 3.
               
                  Ioſhua died 17. yeeres after Moſes. 
                  
               
               
                  Othniel died 40. yeeres after Ioſhua. 
                  
               
               
                  Ehud died 80. yeeres after Othniel. 
                  
               
               
                  Deborah died 40. yeeres after Ehud. 
                  
               
               
                  Gedeon died 40, yeeres after Deborah. 
                  
               
               
                  Abimelech vſurped 3. yeeres. 
               
               
                  Tola died 23. yeeres after Abimelech. 
                  
               
               
                  Iair died 22. yeeres after Tola. 
                  
               
               
                  Iphtah died 6. yeeres after Iair. 
                  
               
               
                  Ibzan died 7. yeeres after Iphtah 
                  
               
               
                  Elon died 10. yeeres after Ibzan. 
                  
               
               
                  Abdon died 8. yeeres after Elon. 
                  
               
               
                  Sampſon died 20. yeeres after Abdon. 
                  
               
               
                  Eli died 40. yeeres after Sampſon. 
                  
               
               
                  
                  Samuel ſucceeded to the time of Saul.
               
               
                   
                  Saul began his raigne, and raigned alone, and with Samuel—40. yeeres.
               
                   
                  Dauid raigned 40. yeeres
               
                   
                  Salomon raigned 40. yeeres
               
                   
                  Rehoboam raigned 17. yeeres.
               
                   
                  Abiam raigned 3. yeeres.
               
                   
                  Aſa raigned—41 yeeres.
               
                   
                  Iehoſaphat raigned 25 yeeres.
               
                   
                  Iehoram raigned 4. yeeres after his fathers death; hauing beene made Viceroy twice in his fathers life time. Firſt, in his ſeuenteenth yeere, as appeareth 1. Kings 22. 51. compared with 2. Kings 1. 17. And againe, in his 22. yeeres, as appeareth 2. Kings 3. 1. compared with cap. 8. 16.
               
                   
                  Athaliah raigned 6. yeeres.
               
                   
                  Ioaſh raigned 39. yeeres.
               
                   
                  Amaſiah raigned 29. yeeres.
               In his ſeuenteenth yeere (or the fourth of Ieroboam K. of Iſrael) there was a conſpiracie againſt him, and he fled to Lachiſh, and liued there a baniſhed man 11. yeeres, Vzziah his ſonne being in the meane ſpace made king by the common people, 2. Ki. 14. 21. See Iunius his note on the place.
               
                   
                  Vzziah raigned 52. yeeres
               About this time began the Greeke Olympiads,
                  
by which they made a computation of all memorable matters. It was againe inſtituted by Hercules on the hill Olympus in Greece, which was held in the beginning of euery fifth yeere, and continued fiue daies, with great ſolemnity, and concourſe out of all Countries. 
               
               
                  Iotham raigned alone—15. yeeres— 
               
               
                  Ahaz raigned—16. yeeres— 
               
               
                  Hezekiah raigned—29 yeeres— 
               
               
                  Manaſſe raigned—55 yeeres.
               
               
                  Ammon raigned—2 yeeres— 
               
               
                  Ioſiah raigned—31. yeeres.— 
               
               
                  Iehoiakim raigned—11 yeeres— 
               
               
                  Ieconiah raigned three months and was caried captiue to Babel, 2. Chron. 36. 
               
               
                  Zedekiah raigned—
                     •
                  1 yeeres.— 
               
               From Zedekiah to the exaltation of Iehoiakin 2. King. 25. 30.—26 yeeres—
               
                  In Summe.
                  From the Creation of Adam to the flood, are—1656 yeeres.
                  From the flood to the death of Ioſhua, are—910 yeeres.
                  From Ioſhua to the death of Eli, are—339 yeeres.
                  From Eli to the deportation of Ieconias, are—473 yeeres.
                  
                     
                     
                        Anno 3458. From the Captiuity of Ieconias to the Edict of Cyrus for their deliuerance (promiſed, Ier. 25. 11. and performed in the firſt yeere of his raigne) are—70. yeres.
                  From the Edict of Cyrus, beginneth the firſt of Daniels 70. weekes.
                  Theſe 70. weekes are to bee expounded as the Sabbaths, or Weekes of the yeere of Iubile, Leuit. 25. 8. and they containe in the whole—490 yeeres.
               
               Theſe are diuided by Gabriel the Angel into three parts, Dan. 9. 25.
               Firſt he appointeth 7. weekes, or a Sabbath of weekes, or a Iubile of 49. yeeres, for the building of the Temple, and reſtoring of the pure worſhip of God.
               Secondly, hee appointeth 62. weekes (which containe 434. yeeres) for repairing of the City, and building the walles. And theſe beginne with the commiſsion of Nehemiah, from Darius Artaxerxes Longimanus Neh. 2. 9. and reach vnto the laſt weeke in which Meſsiah began to preach.
               Thirdly, he ſpeaketh of the laſt weeke, and diuideth it into two parts.
               1 In the firſt part, and middeſt of it, or in the fourth yeere, he ſaith that Meſſiah ſhall aboliſh the ſacrifice and oblation:

namely by offering vp himſelfe once for all, Heb. 10. 14. Which is more plainely expreſſed, Dan. 9. 26. where he is ſaid to be cut off, or crucified and deliuered to death. But nothing to him, that is, death ſhall not preuaile ouer him, but that hee ſhall make good his iudgements vpon a rebellious and gaine-ſaying people. For it is ſaid, [He ſhall deſtroy the City, and the holy things,] or the Temple; and that with ſuch ſeuerity, as if a flood of wrath and iudgement ſwallowed vp all.
               Theſe 69. weekes and a halfe weeke, containe 487. yeeres, which fall out iuſt, by this account.
               
                  From the Edict of Cyrus to the re-edifying of the Temple, and the returne of 
                        Ezra. 6, 15 7, 12 Anno 3507.the people, by the command of Artaxerxes, the whole time of Ezra his ſtory, are—49. yeeres,
                  From the Temple finiſhed, to the repairing of the City Ieruſalem, and the end of 
                        Anno 3577.
                     Arſanes his raigne; the time of Nehemiahs ſtory,—70. yeeres
                  From thence to the death of Alexander the great, are—12. yeeres.
                  
                     Alexander died in the firſt yeere of the 114. Olympiade, and Chriſt was crucified

the laſt yeere of the 202. Olympiade. Which 89. Olympiades containe—356. yeeres, 
                        Anno 3945.and ſo is the ſumme 487. fully made vp.
               
               The latter part, or other halfe of the weeke, is referred vnto the Reuelation of the new Teſtament, cap. 11. 3. where it is ſaid, that the two Witneſſes ſhould prophecy, 1260 daies, or 42. months; which make vp three yeeres and a halfe: and ſo the full number of the 70. weekes.
            
         
         
            
            The ſecond Part.
            
               The firſt Section.
               
                  
                     OF Abrahams ſeed and Dauids line,
                  directly he deſcended;
                  
                     
                        Mat. 1. So haue th'Euangeliſts diuine
                  
                     
                        Luk 3. by ſcripture left cōmended
                  Before him was an Herauld ſent,
                  his comming to proclaime:
                  
                     
                        Mat. 3. Wo cried in wilderneſſe repent,
                  
                  the paths of God make plaine.
                  His cloathing was of haire and skinne,
                  his meat, of no great coſt:
                  
                     
                        Mat. 14. And for reprouing Herods ſinne,
                  his head at laſt he loſt.
                  
                     Iohn Baptiſt he was call'd: his name,
                  by Gabriel was fore-told
                  
                     
                        Luk. 1. (And eke his birth, and why he came)
                  to Zacharias old;
                  
                     
Too old to haue ſuch newes beleeu'd,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 18. and therefore was ſtrooke dumbe,
                  Vntill Elizabeth conceiu'd,
                  and all to paſſe was come.
                  
                     
                        verſ. 26. To Mary eke of Nazaret,
                  
                  a Virgin pure and chaſte,
                  With ſalutation high and great,
                  this Gabriel did haſte.
                  Shewing that ſhe muſt mother be,
                  Gods deare Sonne forth to bring,
                  The Holy Ghoſt by high decree
                  her ouer-ſhadowing.
                  Yet was ſhee at that time betroth'd
                  
                     
                        Mat. 1. to Ioſeph (Scriptures ſay)
                  Who finding her with child, bethought,
                  to put her cloſe away.
                  But then an Angell warned him,
                  by dreame, to keepe her ſtill,
                  For that ſhe had conceiu'd within
                  was Gods owne worke and will.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 2.
               
                  
                     
                        Luk 2. AT Bethlehem was Ieſus borne,
                  the Sauiour of mankind;
                  And laid in cratch, as one forlorne,
                  ſuch welcome did he finde.
                  
                     
By Angels was his birth made knowne,
                  to Shepheards: forthwith they
                  Found out the Babe, as had beene ſhowne,
                  and publiſhed it with ioy.
                  The eight day was he circumciſ'd,
                  th
                        •
                     n did the Temple grace him,
                  Where good old Simon well aduiſ'd,
                  and Anne, were glad t'imbrace him.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 2. Out of the Eaſt there came from farre,
                  wiſe men, him worſhipping,
                  Directed by a ſpeciall ſtarre,
                  to find out Iudahs king.
                  They offered gifts, and warned were
                  by God, in their returne,
                  To take good heede, and not come neere
                  king Herod, who did burne
                  With wrath and enuie for the bruit,
                  of this great king of kings,
                  And being mocked ſendeth out,
                  and ſlew all the ſucklings.
                  God vnto Ioſeph warning gaue
                  to Egypt thence to flye,
                  The babe and mother there to ſaue,
                  from Herods cruelty.
                  King Herod dead, then haſted he
                  to Iſrael againe:
                  But turn'd aſide to Galilee,
                  
                  becauſe his ſonne did raigne,
                  
                     
And all this was for to acquite
                  the Prophecies of old,
                  From Egypt and a Nazarite,
                  
                  to come, he was fore-told
               
            
            
               
                  Section 3.
               
                  AT twelue yeeres old, with Doctors he
                  
                     
                        Luk 2, in Temple doth diſpute;
                  The hearers all amazed be,
                  
                     
                        verſ. 46. his mother alſo is mute.
                  At thirty yeeres he was baptiz'd
                  
                     
                        Mat. 3 by Iohn in Iordan flood;
                  And by God, for his ſon agniz'd
                  while heauen open ſtood.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 4. To wilderneſſe then was he led,
                  and faſted forty daies:
                  The diuell there he vanquiſhed,
                  though tempted many waies.
                  And ſo, his miniſtry of waight,
                  he cloſely ſets about:
                  He chuſeth twelue Apoſtles ſtraight,
                  
                     
                        Mat. 10. and alſo ſends them out:
                  
                     
                        Luk. 10. And ſeuenty mo, by two and two,
                  he ſent with like command,
                  To preach, to heale, and to ſubdue
                  the diuels that did withſtand.
                  
                     
                     
                        Mat. 17 To quicken them the more, he did
                  part of his glory ſhew,
                  On mountaine high tranſfigured
                  into an heauenlie hew.
                  Nor was he idle, but did purge
                  
                     
                        Ioh, 2. 14. the Temple firſt and laſt,
                  
                     
                        Luk. 19. 45 And ſtill he did repentance vrge,
                  as vp and downe he paſt.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 4.
               
                  
                     
                        
                           Mat. 13 AT Nazeret he tooke his text
                     in Eſai's prophecie:
                     
                        
                           Luk. 4. Whence hardly ſcaping, he did next,
                     to Capernaum hie.
                     There Satan ſhew'd his diſcontent
                     
                        
                           Mat. 4. but ſtrongly was caſt out,
                     Vnto the great aſtoniſhment,
                     of all that ſtood about.
                     
                        
                           Ioh. 3. To Doctor Nichodemus old,
                     a leſſon ſtrange he taught.
                     The woman of Samaria bold,
                     
                        
                           Ioh. 4. and crafty, yet was caught:
                     Vpon the Mount he ſhew'd at large,
                     
                        
                           Mat. 5. true bleſſednes moſt cleare,
                     And then ſet out the weighty charge
                     his miniſters doe beare.
                     
                        
The Lawes of God he likewiſe there
                     did perfectly expound,
                     
                        
                           Mat. 6. He taught them how to pray and where,
                     and did a forme ſet downe,
                     Of almes, of faſting, carking care,
                     of iudgeing, knocking, ſtriuing,
                     Of Prophets falſe how to beware,
                     and other Chriſtian liuing.
                     Which, partly he by Parable,
                     and partly, plainely taught.
                     Eche word and euery ſyllable,
                     with power in hearers wrought.
                     By a Builders, b Bridegrome, c Birds and d Bread
                     bye Beaſts, f Theeues, g Spirits vncleane,
                     By h Seruants i Shepherds, k Salt, &amp; l Seed,
                     by m Nets, n new Cloth and Wine.
                  
               
               
                  Chriſts Parables.
                  
                     
                         
                        
                           Mat. 7. 24. THe Builders on the rocke and the ſand—
                     
                        
                           Mat. 21. 22 The Stone which the Builders refuſed—
                     
                        
                           Luk. 14. 28. To count the coſt, before building—
                     
                         
                        
                           Mat. 9. 15 The children of the Bride-chamber—
                     
                        
                           Mat. 22. 2.The Mariage of the Kings ſonne—
                     
                        
                           Mat. 25. 1. The Bridgrome and ten Virgines—
                     
                        
                        
                           Mat. 6-26.The Foules of heauen ſow not—
                     
                     
                        
                           Mat. 10. 
                              •
                           9  Two Sparrowes ſold for a farthing—
                     
                        
                           Ma. 23. 37Oh Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, how often—
                     
                        
                        
                           Ma. 15. 26Not to take the childrens bread—
                     
                        
                           Mat. 7. 9. If a ſonne aske bread, will he giue—
                     
                        
                           Joh. 6 48. I am the bread of life—
                     
                        
                        
                           Mat. 8. 20. Foxes haue holes—
                     
                        
                           Mat. 7. 6. Giue not holy things to Dogges—
                     
                        
                           Ma. 12 34.Generation of Vipers, how can ye ſpeak
                     
                        
                        
                           Ma. 24. 43   The th
                           •
                        efs time vnknowne—
                     
                        
                           Luk. 10. 30 A Traueller fell among theeues—
                     
                        
                           Joh. 10. 1Climbers another way are theeues—
                     
                        
                        
                           Ma. 12. 27. If I by Belzebub caſt out—
                     
                        
                           verſ. 47.When the vncleane ſpirit is gone—
                     
                        
                        
                           Mat. 6. 24. No man can ſerue two Maſters—
                     
                        
                           Ma. 18. 32The cut throat ſeruant—
                     
                        
                           Ma. 24. 46 The ſeruant bleſſed, ſo doing—
                     
                        
                           Luk. 17. 7.Who bids his ſeruant, ſit downe
                     
                         
                        
                           M. 18. 12 The ſtraied ſheepe, of a hundred
                     
                        
                           Joh. 10. 11The good ſhepheard giuing his life
                     
                        
                           Ma. 25. 33The ſheepe, and the goates
                     
                        
                           Mat. 9. 36. The multitude ſcattered as ſheepe
                     
                         
                        
                           Ma. 5. 13 Yee are the ſalt of the earth.
                     
                        
                           Luk. 14. 34 Salt is good, but if it hath loſt.
                     
                        
                           Mar. 9. 49Euery man ſhall be ſalted with fire
                     
                         
                        
                           Mat. 13. 3 The Sower went forth to ſow
                     
                        
                           Ma. 13. 24. The enemy ſowing Tares
                     
                        
                           verſ. 31.The kingdome of heauen like a muſtardſeede
                     
                     
                        
                           Mat. 17. 20Faith as a graine of Muſtard ſeed.
                     
                        
                        
                           Ma. 13. 4The kingdome of heauen like a drawnet.
                     
                        
                        
                           Ma. 9. 16New patches, old garments.
                     New wine, old bottles.
                     
                        
                        
                           Ma. 5. 14Ye are the the light of the world.
                     
                        
                           Mat. 5. 15. A candle vnder a buſhell.
                     
                        
                           Mat. 6. 22.The light of the body is the eie.
                     
                        
                           Ma. 7. 3. The mote in thy brothers eie.
                     
                        
                           Joh. 8. 12I am the light of the world.
                     
                         
                        
                           Ma. 13. 33It is like Leuen which a woman hid.
                     
                        
                           Mat. 16. 6.The Leuen of the Phariſies.
                     
                     
                         
                        
                           Luk. 14. 8 Sit not vpermoſt at a feaſt.
                     
                        
                           verſ. 12. Call not thy friends to feaſt.
                     
                        
                           verſ. 16.The great ſupper.
                     
                         
                        
                           Luk. 16. 9. Friends with the riches of iniquity.
                     
                        
                           Luk. 11. 5The friend comming at midnight.
                     
                        
                        
                           Luk. 12. 16 The rich Farmer pulling down his barns
                     
                        
                           Luk. 16. 19.The rich Glutton, clothed in purple.
                     
                        
                           Luk. 16. 1The rich mans Steward that waſted.
                     
                        
                           Luk. 18. 10The rich Phariſie, and poore Publican.
                     
                     
                         
                        
                           M. 7. 17 Euery good tree beareth good fruit.
                     
                        
                           Ma. 1
                              •
                           . 13Euery plant which my heauenly father.
                     
                        
                           Mat. 21. 19 The barren Fig-tree curſed.
                     
                        
                           Ma 26 32The greene fig-tree ſheweth Summer.
                     
                        
                           Luk. 13. 6.The fruitleſſe fig-tree ſpared.
                     
                         
                        
                           Ma 2
                              •
                           . 14 The Talents beſtowed.
                     
                        
                           Ma▪
                            6. 19.The Treaſure in heauen.
                     
                     
                        
                           Ma. 12. 35Treaſures of the heart.
                     
                        
                           Ma. 13. 44 Treaſures in the field.
                     
                        
                           verſ. 52.The good Scribes treaſure.
                     
                         
                        
                           Lu. 15. 11 The prodigall ſonne.
                     
                        
                           Ma. 11. 16The little children piping.
                     
                        
                           Ma▪. 18. 3 Except ye be conuerted as children.
                     
                        
                           Mat. 21. 28The diſſembling ſonne and his brother
                     
                         
                        
                           Luk. 15. 8.The womans loſt groate.
                     
                        
                           Luk. 18. 2. The importunate widdow.
                     
                        
                           Mat. 24. 41Two women grinding,
                     
                        
                           Ma. 12. 50 Chriſt his mother, ſiſter and brother.
                     
                        
                        
                           M. 7. 13 The ſtraight gate leading to life.
                     
                        
                           Joh. 14. 6  I am the way.
                     
                        
                        
                           Ioh. 15. 1. I am the true Vine.
                     
                        
                           Ma. 21. 33The Vineyard hedged and husbanded.
                     
                        
                           Mat. 20. 1. The labourers hired into the Vineyard.
                  
               
               
                  By o Light and p Leuen, q Feaſts &amp; r Friends
                  by ſ Rich men, t Trees, and u Treaſure.
                  By x Children, y Women, z Waies, and * Vines.
                  he vttered out of meaſure
                  Deepe myſteries which long lay hid,
                  which he from heauen brought:
                  And by miraculous power he did
                  confirme what he had taught.
               
            
            
               
                  Section. 5.
               
                  AT Cana he did at their need
                  
                     
                        Ioh. 2. turne water into wine.
                  
                     
                     
                        Mat. 14. And with fiue loaues, fiue thouſand fed,
                  by his great power diuine.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 15. Mat. 14. 26 Mat. 8. 26. Chriſts miracles. Another time fower thouſand men,
                  with ſeuen loaues he filled.
                  He walked on the ſea: and when
                  it raged, the waues he ſtilled.
                  Good 
                        Ma 9. 27 Mat. 12. 22 Mat. 20. 31 Mar. 8. 23. John. 9. 1.ſight he gaue to many blind
                  and 
                        Ma. 9. 32 Ma. 12. 22 Mar. 7. 32.ſpeech vnto the dumb,
                  The 
                        Ma. 12. 10 Joh. 5. 8. Luk. 13. 11.lame their limmes do firmely finde,
                  the 
                        Mar. 7. 32.deafe to hearing come.
                  He 
                        Mat. 8. 6. Mat. 8. 14. Mat. 9. 2. Mat. 9 20. Mat. 14. 26 Mat 22.healed ſickneſſes long bred,
                  euen 
                        Mat. 8. 3. Luk. 17. 12.foule and leprous euils.
                  Yea more, 
                        Luk. 7. 12 Iohn 11. 1. Iohn 5. 
                           •
                        7.he raiſed vp the dead;
                  and 
                        Ma. 8. 19 Mat. 9. 32 Ma
                              •
                           . 17. 1
                           •
                        . Mar. 9. 20diſpoſſeſ'd the diuels.
                  Yet for all this he was not free
                  but had controllers many
                  To carpe and quarrell, prie and ſee,
                  if fault they could find any:
                  Among the reſt, the Sadduces,
                  
                  with thoſe of Herods traine,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 21 
                     
                        Cap. 9 The Scribes alſo and Phariſes,
                  
                  did euer more remaine,
                  His deadly enemies and did ſeeke,
                  to trap him in a ſnare,
                  By crafty queſtions, rough or meeke;
                  what way, they did not care.
                  But yet his hower was not come
                  he ſtill preach'd painfully▪
                  
                  
                     
And them bequeath'd a heauy doom,
                  For their hypocriſie.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 23. Mat. 24. 
                     Ieruſalem her fearefull ſtate,
                  he did with greefe fore-ſay.
                  The manner eke he did relate,
                  of the laſt iudgement day.
                  But comforteth his choſen ones
                  
                     
                        John 14. with ſpirituall conſolation,
                  As ſweetly may be ſeene in Iohn's 
                     
                  
                  diuine, and long relation. 
                  
                  And ſo to Bethani he went, 
                  
                  where Simon him receiued:
                  And Maries box vpon him ſpent,
                  
                     
                        Mat. 26. diſſembling Iudas grieued.
                  Then was the paſſeouer prepar'd,
                  and Iudas pointed out,
                  A traitor to his Soueraigne Lord:
                  and then he went about,
                  A work of grace, a Sacrament,
                  a Supper to ordaine,
                  A ſeale of loue, a teſtament
                  that ſhould with his remaine.
                  Thence went he to Mount Oliuet,
                  
                  as was his vſe to pray:
                  Of ſcattering and of ſcandall great,
                  he told them by the way.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 6.
               
                  MEane while did Prieſts a Councill cal,
                  and did his death conſpire,
                  They hired Iudas in their Hall,
                  to worke them their deſire:
                  Who promiſ'd to effect it ſo,
                  as that they ſhould not miſſe,
                  With him their Captaine, on they goe,
                  their token is a kiſſe.
                  As Chriſt in garden praying was,
                  with ſighs and groanes moſt deepe,
                  That fearefull Cup to haue it paſſe:
                  the reſt oppreſt with ſleepe.
                  In comes this rude and bloody route,
                  which Peter could not beare
                  But drew his ſword, and laid about,
                  and cut off Malchus eare;
                  
                     
                        Ioh. 18. Which heal'd; they led him quietly,
                  with torches, clubs and ſwords,
                  Who at his very entery
                  
                     
                        Ioh, 18. 6. did fell them with his words.
                  The poore Apoſtles ſcattered are.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 26. yea Peter void of hope,
                  Deni'd his Maſter, curſ'd and ſware
                  
                     
                        Mat. 27▪
                      but Iudas ſtretch'd a rope.
                  
                     
To high Prieſts Hall, they led him then,
                  and witneſſe falſe ſuborned.
                  
                     
                        Mar. 14▪
                      Spat in his face, and by their men,
                  he was both beate and ſcorned.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 27 Then did they him to Pilat ſend,
                  where being found moſt cleare:
                  To free him Pilat did intend,
                  and that the Iewes did feare,
                  
                     
                        Luk. 23. And then began with might and maine,
                  tumultuouſly to cry,
                  To let looſe Barrabas againe,
                  and Chriſt to crucifie.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 27. Nor were the common Souldiers ſlacke.
                  to ſtrip him of his weede.
                  A Scarlet robe put on his back,
                  and in his hand a reede,
                  And on his head a crowne of thornes,
                  then doe they bow the knee.
                  So, on him hauing ſpent their ſcornes,
                  to Golgatha goes hee.
                  They forced Simon by the way,
                  to helpe his Croſſe to beare,
                  On which, his hands they did diſplay,
                  his fleſh they pierce and teare.
                  Betwixt to Theeues they did him place,
                  and gaue him gall to drinke,
                  They ſhew'd him all the vile diſgrace
                  that heart of man could thinke.
                  
                     
                     
                        Luk. 23. 34. Mar. 15▪ 29 Which patiently he did indure,
                  from all that by did paſſe.
                  Vntill was come that bleſſed houre,
                  wherein all finiſh'd was.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 7.
               
                  
                     
                        Mat. 27. THen rent the Temple vaile in twaine,
                  the rocks did cleaue aſunder,
                  The graues did ope, the dead againe,
                  did riſe and walke with wonder.
                  The earth lay trembling, and the ſunne
                  abaſht in darknes bode,
                  
                     
                        Luke 23▪ 
                        Mat. 27. And then cried the Centurion,
                  this was the Sonne of God.
                  His body Ioſeph did take downe,
                  and lap'd in linnen ſweet,
                  And in a new tombe of his owne,
                  did bury it as was meet.
                  The Prieſts his reſurrection fear'd,
                  and therefore tooke good heede,
                  To keep him ſure with watch and ward,
                  and ſeal'd the tombe with ſpeed.
                  
                     
                        Mat. 28. But he the third day did ariſe,
                  as he had them fore-told.
                  Then did the Prieſts, to publiſh lies,
                  corrupt the guard with gold,
                  
                     
He being riſen did appeare
                  and charged the eleuen,
                  To preach &amp; baptize euery where
                  by warranty from heauen.
                  And purpoſing to furniſh them,
                  with knowledg tongues and art,
                  He bids them, from Ieruſalem, 
                        Cap. 1
                  
                  in no wiſe to depart,
                  Till promiſes performed were:
                  which ſaid: out of their ſight,
                  A cloud to Heauen did him bear:
                  and two in garments white,
                  Did check their gazing and foreſhewd,
                  his comming backe againe.
                  Then to the City backe they goe,
                  where all as one remaine
                  In praier and requeſt to God:
                  There Peter doth propoſe
                  To fill the number that was od:
                  the lot Matthias choſe.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 8.
               
                  VPon the day of Pentecoſt, 
                        Cap. 2
                  
                  in clouen tongues like fire,
                  From Heauen high, the holy Ghoſt,
                  th' Apoſtles did inſpire.
                  
                     
Then did they in ſtrange tongues report,
                  the wondrous workes of God,
                  Aſtoni'ſt was their with each ſort
                  of ſtrangers that abode
                  Within the City; others mock't,
                  but Peter tooke their part,
                  
                     
                        cap. 3 And by his Sermon, ſoundly knock'd,
                  three thouſand at the heart.
                  
                     
                        cap. 3 Then Iohn and he together ioin'd,
                  and heal'd the Creeple lame.
                  To priſon though they were confin'd,
                  
                     
                        cap. 4 yet were they freed for ſhame.
                  To preach the truth they were all bold,
                  and many wonders wrought,
                  Nor would they be by Prieſts controul'd,
                  though oft in danger brought.
                  For they in ſuffering did reioice,
                  and God ſent helpe at need;
                  
                     
                        cap. 5 The Hypocrites at Peters voice,
                  were ſuddenly ſtrooke deade.
                  Then did they for poore widowes moane,
                  
                     
                        cap. 6 ſeuen honeſt Deacons chuſe,
                  Of which, was worthy Stephen one,
                  
                     
                        cap. 7 who martired was by Iewes.
                  
                  
                     Saul was conſenting to this deed,
                  
                     
                        cap. 8 and with his threatnings ſore,
                  Scatered th' Apoſtles farre and wide,
                  but Gods word grew the more.
                  
                     
By Philip in Samaria,
                  
                  with power it was taught.
                  And into Aethiopia,
                  
                  'twas by the Eunuch brought.
                  
                     Damaſcus was an harbourough,
                  for Saints: but Saul he frets,
                  And by high Prieſts commiſſion now, 
                        cap. 9
                  
                  not one ſpares whom he gets,
                  But by the way he was withſtood,
                  God turned all about.
                  
                     Saul of a perſecutor proud,
                  was made a Preacher ſtout.
                  At Ioppa Peter raiſ'd the dead
                  and did the Goſpell plant, 
                        cap. 10
                  
                  And in Caeſaria he ſped,
                  Captaine Cornelius want.
                  At Antioch the Word was ſpred, 
                        Cap. 11
                  
                  by Preachers there diſperſt,
                  Who truely following Chriſt their head,
                  were there call'd Chriſtians firſt.
                  Now Herod ſtorm's, kill's Iames, and cloſe 
                        Cap. 12
                  
                  in priſon Peter caſt,
                  An Angell ſent, his chaines doth loſe,
                  wormes eate the King at laſt.
               
            
            
               
                  Section. 9.
               
                  BVt Paul) call'd Saul) ſurpaſt them all,
                  in patience and paines-taking.
                  
                     
To preach the word to great and ſmall,
                  he euermore was waking;
                  By day, by night, by ſea, by land,
                  by pen and eke by mouth.
                  Though perils great were oft at hand,
                  yet publiſh'd he the truth:
                  Foure ſpeciall iourneies did he make,
                  in leſſer Aſia one,
                  And twice he croſſ'd the 
                        or Mare AEgaeum.
                     Graecian lake,
                  and then to Rome is gone.
                  With him alſo the holy Ghoſt,
                  
                     
                        cap. 13 ſet Barnabas apart,
                  Their charge was in the heathen coaſt,
                  the Gentiles to conuert.
                  From Antioch they firſt ſet out
                  and vnto Paphos came:
                  Where Sergius to the faith was brought,
                  and Elymas to ſhame.
                  Then in Piſidia did he preach,
                  and in Iconion
                  
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 He ſtaied long, and ſtill did teach,
                  till ſtirres cauſe him be gone.
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 Thence did hee vnto Liſtra flee,
                  
                     
                        v. 11. 19. and there he heal'd the lame,
                  For which, a god, then ſton'd, but he,
                  thence backe to Antioch came.
                  Th'Apoſtles at Ieruſalem
                  
                  
                     
                        cap. 15 did now a Councell call,
                  
                     
A falſe opinion to condemne
                  which did the Church befall.
                  A ſecond iourney they intend,
                  but Iohn Marke doth diuide them:
                  
                     Barnabas doth to Cyprus bend,
                  but Paul and Silas hide them
                  Through Syria and Silicia,
                  
                  and with them they conſort
                  Yong Timothe, of whom they haue, 
                        Cap. 16
                  
                  a ſpeciall good report.
                  To Macedonia by night,
                  they called were and ſent,
                  The Diuell there giues God his right,
                  there 
                        
                           •
                        ydia doth repent,
                  And eke the Iailor: foorthwith they
                  to Theſſalonica come,
                  Noble Berea next with ioy 
                        Cap. 17
                  
                  doth lend them eares and rome.
                  In Athens next he did diſpute, 
                        Cap. 18
                  
                  
                     
                        verſ. 3. and thence to Corinth came,
                  With Aquila he there doth ſute,
                  and Criſpus chriſtian frame.
                  There Gallio doth ſhift his hand,
                  though hardly Iewes complaine.
                  
                     
                        verſ. 22. So, backe he goes to Syria, and
                  to Antioch againe.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 10.
               
                  THen did he his third iourney haſte,
                  towards Graecia once more,
                  Thorow leſſer Aſia he paſt,
                  as he had done before.
                  
                     
                        cap. 19 At Epheſus he made ſome ſtay,
                  for their the word preuailed,
                  There was Appoll's ſhew'd the way,
                  and there Demetrius railed.
                  
                     Philippi laſt he viſited,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 20 and thence he ſailed backe,
                  To Troas; where he raiſ'd the dead
                  and after, did not ſlacke,
                  Vnto Ieruſalem to come;
                  yet ſailing thither-ward,
                  The planted Churches al and ſome
                  to ſee, he had regard.
                  For in his iourneies as he went,
                  he preach'd and Churches planted.
                  Returning too, was diligent,
                  for to ſupply what wanted.
                  He them confirm'd, ordain'd by choiſe,
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 Elders in euery place,
                  And laſtly did with cheerefull voice,
                  commend them to Gods grace.)
                  
                     
At Ptolemais one day they bide, 
                        cap. 21
                  
                  and to Caeſaria walked,
                  Where Philips daughters propheſied,
                  and Agabus fore-talked,
                  Of Paul his bands and ſufferings great,
                  but he was naught diſmai'd.
                  To ſuffer death (though they intreat)
                  he ready was he ſaid.
                  So, vp he went, and being there
                  made to them full relation;
                  With praiſe to God they gladly heare,
                  the Gentiles ſtrange vocation.
                  To pleaſe the Iewes, they did aduiſe
                  to purifie him there.
                  But in the Temple ſtirres ariſe,
                  and like to coſt him deere.
                  Had not the Captaine ceaſ'd the ſtriefe,
                  and by his great friendſhip.
                  Account he rendred of his life 
                        cap. 22
                  
                  and faith, and ſcapt the whipe.
                  Then was he brought before the Prieſt,
                  and ſmitten, but the fraie.
                  Twixt Saduces, Scribes, and the reſt▪ 
                     
                        cap. 23
                  
                  hindred the plea that day.
                  Then was he vnto Foelix ſent
                  his anſwere there to make,
                  Thither alſo the high Prieſt went, 
                        Cap. 24
                  
                  and did Tertullus take,
                  
                     
The Oratour, to plead their caſe;
                  but nothing yet they gained,
                  Till Feſtus came in Felix place,
                  before him being 'raigned,
                  
                     
                        cap. 25 And King Agrippa: he thinks well
                  to yeelde him vp in bands,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 26 But Paul to Caeſar did appeale,
                  and ſo eſcap'd their hands.
                  To Italie then was he bound,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 27 with a Centurions guard:
                  But perils great on ſea they found,
                  the like haue ſcarce beene heard.
                  Toſt vp and downe, the ſhip at laſt,
                  
                     
                        cap. 27 ſtucke faſt within the ſand:
                  And there was all to peeces daſht;
                  yet all came ſafe to land,
                  At Malta: where the Viper quick,
                  
                     
                        cap. 28 made the Barbarians quail,
                  
                     Paul ſcap'd the danger, heal'd their ſicke,
                  and thence to Rome did ſaile.
                  Where he arriuing was by Iewes,
                  both mette and entertained,
                  Hee told the brethren ioifull newes,
                  and two yeeres there remained,
                  In his owne houſe, and guarded by
                  a ſouldier of the traine,
                  Vntill that Nero cruelly,
                  did cauſe him to be ſlaine.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Reuelation 
                  Section 11.
               
                  AS Paul in preaching got the prize,
                  ſo, Iohn did mount moſt high,
                  Gods holy hidden myſteries,
                  and ſecrets to deſcrie.
                  In Patmos on the Lord his day, 
                        cap. 1
                  
                  he rauiſh'd was in ſpirit.
                  Bleſſed from heauen are all they,
                  that read and keepe his writ.
                  Firſt, to the ſeuen Churches he
                  ſends healthful ſaluation, 
                        cap. 4
                  
                  Then ſets he out Gods maieſty 
                        cap. 5
                  
                  with a booke of Reuelation.
                  
                  But ſeuen ſeales this Booke did cloſe,
                  and none could be found out
                  Worthy the ſeales for to vnloſe,
                  till came the Lion ſtout
                  Of Iuda's Tribe, the Lambe once ſlaine,
                  he euery ſeale did open,
                  And each ſeale drew as in a chaine,
                  ſome ſtrange and ſpeciall token.
                  The firſt, produc'd a Horſe milke-white,
                  (the Goſpels ſpeed and power)
                  The ſecond red, and did delight 
                        cap. 6
                  
                  by blood-ſhed to deuoure.
                  
                     
The third was blacke, and notice had
                  of plague and famine fell.
                  The fourth horſe full pall and ſad,
                  did Antichriſt foretell.
                  The fifth Seale open'd did bewray,
                  Saints ſoules that had beene killed;
                  Which vnder heauens alter lay,
                  till were the number filled,
                  The ſixth vnſealed, their were ſeene
                  moſt fearefull ſignes and wonders:
                  But God ſeal'd (ſpite of Satans ſpleene)
                  
                     
                        Cap. 7 twelue times, twelue thouſand numbers
                  Laſt, opening the ſeuenth ſeale,
                  
                     
                        cap. 8 loe, Angels ſeuen attend,
                  
                     
                        c. 11. 15. Before the Lord, and they reueale
                  
                     
                        Cap. 8 things to the worlds full end.
                  
                      Theſe Angels, ſeuen Trumpets had,
                  
                      but each in order bloes,
                  And for the world would be ſo bad,
                  denounced nought but woes.
               
            
            
               
                  Section 12.
               
                  
                     
                        cap. 10 THen mightely with glorious looke,
                  Chriſt Ieſus is reuealed,
                  And in his hand a little booke,
                  but open and vnſeled.
                  
                     
This Booke St. Iohn did take and ate,
                  and it th'eſtate contained,
                  Of Gods Church preſent, and of that
                  her glory which remained.
                  For preſent ſtate, ſhe neuer wants,
                  the preaching of Gods ſpell,
                  Two Candleſticks, two Oliue plants, 
                        Cap. 11
                  
                  two witneſſes this tell.
                  And though ſhe cloath'd be with the Sun
                  and on the Moone doe tread,
                  Yet warres againſt her are begun,
                  by foes that make her dread.
                  And firſt the Dragon cauſ'd her fly, 
                        Cap. 12
                  
                  into Gods wilderneſſe:
                  But Michael from heauen high,
                  his fury doth repreſſe.
                  Then did a Beaſt make warre on her, 
                        cap. 13
                  
                  ſeuen headed, and ten horned:
                  And after him there did appeare
                  another Beaſt adorned
                  Like to the Lambe, with hornes but two,
                  Yet Dragon-like he ſpake,
                  And did what the firſt beaſt could doe,
                  compelling all to take
                  His marke vpon their fore-head: yet
                  the Lambe hath thouſands ſtill,
                  On earth that him with praiſes greet, 
                        cap. 14
                  
                  ſigned to doe his will.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 13.
               
                  NOr doth he Babylon forget,
                  the Idolatrous drunken whore,
                  
                     Three Angels he againſt her ſet,
                  and after, ſeuen more:
                  
                     
                        cap. 14 The firſt, by preaching to deſcry,
                  the next, to ſhew her fall,
                  The third doth torments notifie,
                  bequeath'd her louers all.
                  Thoſe ſeuen, ſeuen vials had,
                  
                     
                        cap. 15 full of the wrath of God,
                  Which they powr'd out as they were bad
                  on all the earth abroad,
                  
                     
                        cap. 16 Vnto the ruine of the Beaſt,
                  and of the whore of Rome,
                  
                  
                     
                        Cap. 17 That golden-purple Antichriſt:
                  
                  for this her heauy dome,
                  Kings of the earth and Marchants proud,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 18 take vp a lamentation:
                  But holy Saints, ſing praiſes lowd,
                  
                     
                        Cap. 19 for Churches preſeruation,
                  Vnto the Conquerour of fame,
                  that cloath'd is with the word,
                  And beares on thigh, a mighty name,
                  
                  and in his mouth a ſword;
                  
                  
                     
Who ſummoned triumphantly,
                  to his victorious feaſt,
                  The fowles that by mid-heauen fly.
                  As for his foe, the Beaſt,
                  He with the Prophet falſe were caſt,
                  into the brimſtone lake:
                  The ſword deuoured all the reſt,
                  that part with him did take.
                  And then the Diuell that Dragon ſtout, 
                        cap. 20
                  
                  that Serpent old (once chained,
                  A thouſand yeeres, and then let out,
                  he fiercely rag'd and raigned,
                  With Gog and Magogs armed ſtrength,
                  whom God conſum'd in ire.) 
                        cap. 20 9
                  
                  The Diuell (I ſay) was caſt at length,
                  in lake of brimſtone fire.
                  And with him, all the damned race:
                  for God comes on his throne,
                  A dreadfull Iudge▪ before whoſe face,
                  both heauen and earth are gone,
                  And hell and graue and ſea and land,
                  deliuer vp their dead;
                  Who all before the Iudge doe ſtand,
                  and bookes are opened;
                  As they haue done, doom doth begin,
                  his worke eche one commendeth;
                  The wicked out, the godly in,
                  and ſo the Seſsion endeth.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Section 14.
               
                  Now doth St. Iohn liuely deſcribe,
                  the Church her glorious ſtate,
                  Wife of the Lambe, th'eſpouſed bride,
                  
                     Chriſt Ieſus heauenly mate:
                  
                     
                        cap. 19 Who was found worthy to be clad,
                  in pure and bright aray:
                  And was exhorted to be glad,
                  againſt her mariage day.
                  
                     Ieruſalem new, holy great,
                  
                     
                        cap. 21 from heauen downe deſcending,
                  God and the Lambe there hold their ſeat,
                  it lightning and defending.
                  The forme is ech way fower ſquare,
                  the matter gold and pearle,
                  The Citizens more noble are,
                  then earthly Lord or Earle.
                  Twelue gates there are for entrance wide,
                  the Porters, Angels ſtout,
                  A wall moſt high on euery ſide,
                  doth compaſſe it about.
                  The weight of glory there reſeru'd,
                  can no mans tongue impart,
                  Eie hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard,
                  nor enter can mans heart.
                  
                     
There is no ſorrow, paine, nor care,
                  no want of cloth or foode,
                  No filth, no darkeneſſe, curſe nor feare,
                  no want of any good.
                  There is of life the tree and ſpring, 
                        cap. 22
                  
                  the ſtore-houſe of all treaſures:
                  There Saints triumph, there Angels ſing,
                  in paradiſe of pleaſures.
                  There liu's our head, let vs not ſlacke,
                  but euer watch and pray:
                  Our Sauiour will come quickly backe:
                  euen ſo, come L
                        ••
                     d away.
               
            
            Sine fine ſit laus Deo.
         
         
            
            
            
               Certaine briefe notes, collected out of late and approued writers, for the better vnderſtan
               ding of the booke of REVELATION.
            
               SAint Iohn receiued &amp; wrote this Apocalyps, or Reuelation of the myſteries of God, when hee was in Patmos. Patmos is an Iland, lying in the Aegaean, or Grecian Sea, which diuideth Aſia from Europ, whither he was baniſhed by Domitian the perſecuting Emperor of Rome, about the yeere—96.
            The ſeuen Churches to which he wrote were ſeuen famous Cities of Aſia the leſſer, and Greece, where the Goſpell was planted.
            
               The ſeuen Seales.
               THe firſt is referred to the times of the primitiue Church, wherein Chriſt by his Apoſtles and Miniſters, ſubdued nations

to the obedience of the Goſpell, Acts 2. 41.
               
                   The ſecond, is referred to the time of the cruell perſecutions, vnder the bloody Emperours, Caligula, Nero, Domitian, and the reſt, vntill the time of Conſtantine, who comforted the Church.
               
                   The third, ſhewing the plagues of Famine, Peſtilence and Warres, that followed the contempt of the Goſpell, is referred, chiefely to the times of the Gothes, Hunnes and Vandals. And theſe plagues come on Horſebacke] noting the generality or diſperſion of them into many countries.
               
                   The fourth, ſome make to ſignifie a part of the plagues fore-mentioned: but more probably it ſignifieth Antichriſt; as King Iames is of opinion. See more in the deſcription of Antichriſt following; and more at large in that Chriſtian, learned, and magnanimous premonition of his Excellent Maieſtie, prefixed to his Apology for the oath of Alleagiance.
               
               
                   The fifth, ſheweth the ſafe eſtate of them that haue ſuffered for the truth, being vnder the altar of Gods protection.
               
                   The ſixth, ſheweth great alterations,

and commotions of ſtates and kingdoms; the Diuell ſtopping the courſe of the Goſpell; and Chriſt preſeruing his, in all corners of the earth. Cap. 7. 2.
               The ſeuenth ſheweth the effect of the Diuells rage, namely the ſpringing vp of hereſies, the fall of miniſters and teachers, the height of corruption and abomination in the Pope and Turke.
            
            
               The 7. Trumpets.
               BY theſe, God proclaimeth open warre with the world; but his elect are ſtill in ſafe eſtate. Cap. 8. 3.
               The foure firſt trumpets ſhew the hatching of hereſies and errors, and the increaſe of them after the firſt 300. yeares.
               The three laſt ſhew the full growth and diuelliſh power of them, in the Pope, and Turke, to the affliction of the Church and the finall iudgement and torment of Atheiſts and Papiſts, denounced by three woes: Cap. 8. 13.
            
            
               
               A Deſcription of the Church.
               SHe is called a woman, Cap. 12.
               Firſt becauſe without Chriſt her huſband ſhe is weake, and can do nothing▪
               
               2. By coniunction with Chriſt ſhe bringeth forth children vnto God.
               3. Becauſe her loue &amp; affection is alwaies ſet on Chriſt her huſband.
               She is cloathed with the Sun) of righteouſnes Chriſt Ieſus.
               She treadeth on the Moon, that is, contemneth the world and earthly things.
               She hath a crowne of twelue ſtarres, that is, the doctrine of the Goſpell garniſhed with the Miniſtry of the twelue Apoſtles.
               She laboureth of child) namely and firſt of all Chriſt Ieſus the heire of all; and then of his members in all ages: the deſtruction of whom, the Dragon did and doth ſtil watch. Cap. 12. 4.
            
            
               
               A Deſcription of the Diuell.
               HE is called a Dragon, Cap. 12. 3. for his cruelty and malice: and a red Dragon, for his thirſt and greedy deſire after blood.
               His 7. heads ſhew his manifold ſleights and ſubtilties.
               His ten horns ſhew his great and dreadfull power.
               His ſeuen Crowns, ſignifie the victories he hath gotten.
               His taile, of ambition, luſt, and couetouſneſſe, reacheth to Heauen, and bruſheth downe the third part of the ſtars: that is, many of the miniſters, from their glorious firmament, to the earth of ſhame and obſcurity. verſe 4.
               This Dragon was chained a thouſand yeares▪ 
                  Cap. 20. 2.
               Theſe yeares the learned do account frō the 36. yeere after the birth of Chriſt, (for then the Diuell began to bee madde, becauſe the Iewes being caſt off, the Church of the Gentiles began to increaſe by the

power of the Goſpell preached) vntill the time of Pope Hildebrand, or Gregory the ſeuenth, who was a wretched coniurer, &amp; familiar of the Diuell, and therefore a fitte inſtrument at hand, for the Dragons diuelliſh and perſecuting purpoſes, which with rage and eagerneſſe hee executed, during the time of the ſeuen Vials, the laſt ſeuen plagues.
            
            
               A deſcription of the firſt Beaſt.
               HE is called a Beaſt, Cap. 13. 1. and ſignifieth in ſcripture a monarchy ſomtimes. Dan. 7. 17.
               The reaſon is, for the tyranny of it.
               He is ſaid to riſe out of the Sea) that is, out of the boyling and broyling of heathē nations, did the great citie, the Queene of the nations, or Roman Monarchy ariſe, to tyrannize ouer the Church of God. Cap. 12, 15.
               His ſeuen heads ſignifie the ſeuen gouernments of Rome, namely Kings, Conſuls, Decemviri, Dictators, Tribuni militum,
                  
                  Emperors and Biſhops. Which laſt was not then come when Saint Iohn wrote. Cap. 17. 10.
               His ten heads ſignifie tenne Kings, that is, great power, large dominion and command.
               His ten crowns ſignifie many victories: but in that they are on his hornes, and not on his heads, it ſheweth he preuailed more by his power, then by ſubtilty; contrarily the Dragon, whoſe heads are ſaid to bee crowned. Or as petty Kings vſe to weare their crownes on their hats, in token of homage they ow, ſo this beaſt, on his horns in token of ſubiection to the dragon, of whom he receiued his throne and authoritie. Cap. 13. 2.
            
            
               The Deſcription of Antichriſt, obſerued by the learned to be foure times fully and definitelie ſet downe in this Booke.
               
                  
                     Cap. 6. 8.
                  
                     The firſt deſcriptiō. FIrſt by a pale horſe, hauing death for his rider, hell for his conuoy, and power

ouer the fourth part of the earth (or Europe,) to kill with the ſword, and with hunger (or the famine of the word, as the black horſe did by corporall famine) and by beaſts, (as Locuſts and frogs Cap. 9: 16) by whom ſhe procured the death ſpirituall of Kings, and nations, that dranke of the cup of her abominations. This being done, the ſoules of the Saints cry for vengeance, ver. 10. and their crie is heard and requeſt graunted vnder the ſixth Seale, ver. 12. &amp;. 17.
               
               
                  CAP. 9. 1
                  
                     The ſecōd deſcriptiō, MOre at large and in this kinde, by his craft and ſtrength &amp;c.
                  He is called a ſtarre fallen from heauen (or ſome notable perſon of great dignity in the Church: falling like Lucifer, from giuing light vnto the world, and erecting a kingdome by a noyſome packe of craftie and cruel vermine. He hath the key of the bottomleſſe pit: (Or of hell it ſelfe, whither he ſendeth and letteth in, thouſands of ſoules, thorow the ſmoakie miſts of darkneſſe, ignorance and ſuperſtition; out of which ſmoake, came thoſe Locuſts (or

Abbats, Cardinals, Monks, Friers, Prieſts and Shauelings) which ſting like to Scorpions (or, with damnable errors and hereſies,) al ſaue the greene ones of God. ver. 4. And theſe ſo ſtung, finding no comfort in pardons, maſſes, merits, dirges, croſſes, and the like, ſhall in torment of conſcience ſeek for death, and not finde it. verſe 6.
                  Theſe Locuſts are ſtrong and fierce as horſes; and their crownes ſhew them to be conquerours. They haue the faces of men (or faire pretenſes of holines) but haire of women (or hearts full of luſt) teeth of Lions (to catch inough, and hold faſt inough: witneſſe the manie fat morſels they did deuoure where-euer they were ſeated.) Their King is a badde one or Abaddon: the Diuell, and his Vicar the Pope, the ſpoilers and deſtroyers of the Church of God. Their doctrine is ſet down, ver. 20. Worſhip of diuels and idols (or ſpirituall fornication) murder (both ſpirituall &amp; corporall) ſorcery (by reliques agnus deies, inchanting praiers, to preſerue, from ſhot, ſword, thunder, and the like.) Fornication (corporall, through inordinate luſts, and lecherie, increaſed by idleneſſe, and bellicheere, in both ſexes, reſtrained

from holy mariage, to a filthy monaſticall life, as by many proofes hath beene made apparant,) theft, (robbing God of his Titles, and beſtowing them on Antichriſt: and coſening men of their goods, by pardons, Iubilees, iugling wares and marchandiſe.
                  The deſcription is ended, Cap. 10. 6. Where the Angel ſweareth, Time ſhall be no more: and the next Angell or ſeuenth, blowing the ſeuenth trumpet, doth ſhew the myſtery of God to be finiſhed. ver. 7.
               
               
                  CAP. 13. 11.
                  
                     The 3. deſcriptiō. THirdly by his growth and manner of gouernement. Hee is called another beaſt (becauſe he diſſers from the former (ver. 1.) or ciuill Romane Emperor, in ſpirituall iuriſdiction, tyrannizing ouer men by an eccleſiaſticall power, which the Emperors had not. He is ſaid to riſe out of the Earth (or from a baſe and low eſtate, to mount vp thorugh the Emperors fauor) by little and little. Hee hath two hornes

like the Lamb,) ſignifying his kingdom &amp; his Prieſt-hood, his ciuill and eccleſiaſtical power, which he vſurpeth from Chriſt but hath indeed from the dragon; like whom he ſpake) in all his Decrees, Canons, practiſes and proceedings. Hee did all that the firſt beaſt could doe) that is, hee is ſtrong and mighty, and nothing inferiour to the Ethnick Emperor, priding himſelfe in lies and wonders: verſe 13. ſending fire) of excommunication from Heauen; deceiuing by damnable doctrines of Diuels, verſe 14. Killing and burning for heretiks, all that wil not worſhip the beaſt, and marking all that do worſhip, for ſlaues and vaſſals. And this marke muſt be ſet in their foreheads) to ſignifie their profeſſiō, and to acknowledge their ſubiection; or in their right hād) to teſtifie their abſolute actuall obedience to his commands, vpon ſuppoſition that he cannot erre. None may buy or ſell without this marke, and therefore periury and breach of promiſe &amp; faith with Chriſtians, is a vertue in a catholique. Now that Rome is this Antichriſtian beaſt, the Number doth ſignifie and ſhew, verſe

18 &amp; 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , latine ſeruice, Romiſh faith, Romiſh Church, anſwereth to it in number and meaſure. Vpon this beaſt are ſeuen Vials of Gods wrath and vengeance, propheced to be powred out, cap. 16. and the ſeuenth being emptied, it is ſaid that Babylon came in remembrance before God: Verſe 19.
               
               
                  CAP. 17. 3.
                  LAſtly by his dangerous and deadlie allurements. As the true ſpouſe (cap. 12.) ſo heere the adulterous ſpouſe is likened to a woman; but yet a whore, for her ſpirituall adultery; and drunken with the blood of the Saints, though a gorgeous and glorious whore in outward ſhew. Verſe 6. The inſcription by which ſhee is to bee knowne is called a myſterie: Verſe 5.
                  Firſt, as ſhee takes herſelfe to bee the viſible head of the Church, the myſticall bodie of Chriſt, and the diſpenſer

of the myſteries of God.
                  Secondly, as ſhee deſerues indeede, and as the reſt of her titles beare witneſſe: Verſe 5. mother of whoordoms &amp;c.) or a myſterie of all abominations vnder a pretext of holines.
                  Now, this whore of Babylon, that rideth on the beaſt, is not any one man, but a ſucceſſion in gouernment, Cap. 17. 18. The beaſt is ſaid to haue ſeuen heads. cap. 13. 1. and cap. 17. 7. Which are expounded to be Roma Septicollis, or Rome built on ſeuen hills: the names whereof are theſe, Palatinus, Quirinalis, Auentinus, Viminalis, Coelius, Exquilinus, Capitolinus▪
                      Or elſe ſeuen formes of gouernment, as is ſhewed before, of which the ſixth. viz. the goruernement by Emperors) was in beeing, when Saint Iohn wrote: Cap. 17. verſe 10. The ſeuenth was not then come, namely the Eccleſiaſticall gouernment by Biſhops; which ſucceeded at Rome, vpon the Tranſlation of the imperiall ſeat to Conſtantinople, and was to continue but a ſhort ſpace) or, about two hundred ſeuenty ſixe

yeares, viz. from the time of Conſtantine, to the time of Phocas the Emperor, who gaue to Boniface Biſhop of Rome, the title of Vniuerſall Biſhop, and head of al Churches. And by this meanes (the perfection of defection, and popiſh corruption comming in) was brought forth 
                        〈◊…〉
                      eight beaſt, one of the ſeuen) in ſhew▪ 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      ſtill ſeeming to ſucceed the Biſhops in Eccleſiaſticall forme of gouernement.
               
            
            
               The meanes by which Antichriſt ſhall be confounded.
               CAP. 11. 3.
               THey are called two witneſſes, and they may ſignifie, either the old, and new Teſtaments, both which Antichriſt hath endeuoured to diſgrace, deface, corrupt, ſuppreſſe and deſtroy, calling the Scripture

a noſe of waxe, a dead letter, a leaden rule; and preferring the traditions of men aboue them. Theſe witneſſes in the primitiue Church, were cloathed in ſackcloth, and preached repentance, by the ſpace of fiue or ſixe hundred yeares. But hauing done their 
                     ••…
                  ſſage, the Romane beaſt made war vpon them, and ouercame them, ſo that they lay open to contempt, cared for of none, vnderſtood of few, and feared of all to bee medled withall. Yea they were killed) and the very throat of them cut, by a generall Cenſure, printed at Venice, anno 1562. Which condemneth all for hereticall, that contradict their traditions.
               Thus lay their bodies without vigor, verſe 8. (as ſometimes the Law, vntill it was reuiued, 2. Chron. 34. 14.) and worldly men reioiced, verſe, 10.) for now they had liberty to doe what they liſted, a pardon for all might be procured by their purſe.
               Yet at laſt (praiſed bee God) we ſee theſe witneſſes to ariſe againe, and beginning

to ſhine in their former glory verſe, 11.
               Which happy alteration and exaltation of them, hath bred ſuch an earth-quak, among the nations, that a good part of them that were in ſubiection to that City are fallen from her, and haue reiected her yoke, verſe 13.
               2 Or theſe witneſſes may ſignifie the preachers of the word. Two onely are mentioned, becauſe two are ſufficient in Law. Theſe for preaching the foreſaid truth and doctrine, diſcouering the man of ſinne, and his corruptions, were put to cruell deaths and torments; but roſe againe in the perſon of their ſucceſſors, ſupplying their roome, and ſtill bearing witneſſe to the ſame truth. Of which grew that memorable and miraculous obſeruation, Sanguis Martyrum, ſemen Eccleſiae, the Martyrs blood, the ſeed of the Church. The mighty and maruellous power of this truth, hath of latter times ſo increaſed that many Kingdomes and great nations, haue in few yeeres beene conuerted thereby, to the true worſhip of the almightie God.
            
            
               
               The ſeuen last plagues, and vials of Gods wrath.
               CHAP. 16. 1.
               
                   THe firſt Viall being powred out, there  fell a noyſome and greeuous ſore. Some vnderſtand by it the Poxe, called Morbus Neapolitanus, a ſtrange and lothſome vlſer, which firſt lighted on the ancient chiefe crutches and ſupporters of the Pope; namely, the Italians, Spaniards, and Frenchmen, for their filthy whordomes and beaſtilineſſe, in the yeeare of our Lord—1494.
               
                   The ſecond turned the Sea (of the  world) into blood, by Turkiſh and Popiſh maſſacres, murders and mortall warres. 
               
                   The third, ſheweth the increaſe of that plague: It commeth home euen to the very doores, their riuers and fountaines ran blood.
               
                   The fourth, cauſed the Sunne (by ſcorching 

and drying) to torment with dearth, plagues, and ſundry diſeaſes.
               
                   The fifth, darkened the Kingdome of the beaſt: which is fulfilled in the reuolt of proteſtant Princes, from obedience to the Pope, and it is to them the greateſt plague of all others, verſ. 10.
               
                   The ſixth, dried vp the riuer Euphrates, (which was the beſt truſted defence of the old Babylon) that is, conſumed the riches, honour, glory, and ſtrength of Romiſh Babylon. And this maketh the fiſh, nay, the frogs, to beſtirre themſelues: for it is ſaid, that three frogs came out] a plurall number; noting their multitude and their threefold directiō, For, Firſt they are raiſed and inſpired by the Dragon the Diuell.
               Secondly, they are maintained by the Beaſt, Antichriſt.
               
               And thirdly, they are inſtructed by the falſe Prophet, the Apoſtatique Church, to defend the Triple-crowned Monarch the Pope of Rome.
               
               Frogs they are fitly named, being indeed animals of either Element, Aire,

Earth, or water; Church-men by profeſsion, Stateſ-men, by practiſe and politike Trading. And they are euermore in action (mates for their walking-maſter the Diuell, Iob 1. 7.) muddily croaking, and couertly crauling in euery corner, in Princes palaces, courts of Nobles, chambers of Gentles, and countrey cottages, and all, to ſtop the leake, to fill vp their Euphrates, and to gather againe the Kings of the earth, verſe 14. murdering and maſſacring both Prince and people that refuſe lo be charmed, and inchaunted by their ſubtill inſinuations.
               That this is true, let the abominable and innumerable rabble of Ieſuites witneſſe, who refuſe no execrable meanes, to daube vp their Antichriſtian kingdome of darkeneſſe, without feare or reſpect of God and man: their practiſes proue, and their poſitions publiſhed in Print vnto the world, approue the ſame. 
               
                   The ſeuenth Viall foreſheweth the finall ouerthrow of Rome, by rents, conuulſions, confuſions and commotions of their Citie and Kingdome, and the

fearefull plagues of God vpon them all, ſuch as neuer were felt, heard, or ſeene in any age before, Cap. 16. 21.
               Goe out of her my people, that yee be not partakers of her ſinnes, and that yee receiue not of her plagues, ſaith the Lord God, Reu. 18. 4
               
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

