
   
      
         
            The light of the world A sermon preached at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boston, in Lincolnshire. By Thomas Granger, preacher of Gods word there.
            Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.
         
         
            
               1616
            
         
         Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02032
            STC 12179
            ESTC S103386
            99839141
            99839141
            3540
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02032)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3540)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1139:15)
         
         
            
               
                  The light of the world A sermon preached at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boston, in Lincolnshire. By Thomas Granger, preacher of Gods word there.
                  Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.
               
               [4], 34, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Yuie lane,
                  London :
                  1616.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2008-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE LIGHT OF THE WORLD. A Sermon preached at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boſton, in Lincolnſhire. By THOMAS GRANGER, Preacher of Gods word there.
            IOHN 95.
            As long as I am in the World, I am the light of the World.
            LONDON: Printed by T. S. for Thomas Pauier, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Yuie lane. 1616.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT VVorſhipfull Mr. THOMAS LEVENTHORPE Eſquire, Sonne and heyre to the renowned Knight, Sir IOHN LEVENTHORPE, T. G. wiſheth all happineſſe, and eternall bleſſedneſſe.
            
               RIGHT Worſhipfull. The ſpeciall affection that I beare to that louely Oliue, wherof you are a ſpecial branch, and the duty, wherein I euer remaine obliged vnto it, hauing heretofore receiued pleaſant nutriture from thence, and delightfull refreſhing in the ſhade thereof, haue often ſolicited me by one meanes or other, to ſhew and teſtifie my thankefull minde to the ſame, and to your ſelfe in particuler. Siluer and gold haue I none, nor any coſtly preſent, but ſuch as I haue freely receiued, I freely offer vnto you. The water is a common element; yet when one Synaeta hauing nothing to offer to Artaxerxes paſsing by, he tooke water out of the riuer Cyrus, with both his hands, and offered it to the king, who accepted it as a ſpeciall gift, (as Aelianus recordeth) firſt, becauſe water is the beſt element. Secondly, becauſe it

was taken out of Cyrus. So the Ayre &amp; the Light are common, and I not hauing any gift to preſent you withall, am glad to offer the Light vnto you, which I hope ſhal finde ſpecial acceptance with you. Firſt, becauſe that of many lights this is the beſt light, giuing light to all other lights of the naturall ſoule, without which they are vtter darkeneſſe, euen as the leſſer lights of the firmament are but darke and dead bodies without the light, and vitall influence of the Sun. Secondly, becauſe this light ariſeth, and ſhineth out of another world then is either the Macrocoſme or Microcoſme, to wit, the ſpirituall world, which is the word and Church of God: But though this light be common, becauſe it is offered to all, and ſhineth vnto all, yet it is receiued of few, becauſe darke earthy bodies cannot receiue the light: in which reſpect it becommeth a proper and ſpeciall light, and I make no doubt, but that you are one of thoſe few, who delight in this light: and therefore I truſt will alſo accept this as a ſpeciall gift, which is pretious and ſpeciall in it ſelfe, though it be not ſpecially, but vulgarly ſet forth by me, to whom the exhibiting, and ſhewing thereof to the world is alſo committed. The Lord protect and conduct you in the way euerlaſting.
            
               From Botterwike in Holland, neere Boſton, in Lincon. 
                  1616.
               

               Your worſhips to command euer in the Lord THOMAS GRANGER.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE LIGHT OF THE VVORLD.
            
               IOHN 8. 12.
               Then ſpake IESVS againe to them, ſaying, I am the light of the world: he that followeth me, ſhall not walke in darkneſſe, but ſhall haue the light of life.
            
            
               THESE words containe a Sermon of our Sauiour Chriſt, preached to the Iewes in the Temple: Wherein two things are principally to be conſidered, the Preface and the principall Scope. The Preface is in the former words [Then ſpake Ieſus to them &amp;c.] Wherein conſider theſe circumſtances: Firſt, The perſon ſpeaking [Ieſus ſpake:] his ſpeaking is amplified by a note of ſedulitie and oftenneſſe in ſpeaking [Spake againe.] Secondly, The perſons to whom he ſpake, [to them] viz. the people of the Iewes, flocking together about him, not to the Phariſies. Thirdly, The time when, [then]
               
that is, either after this time when the Phariſes had tempted him, vpon occaſion of a woman taken in adulterie, or elſe in the great and laſt day of the feaſt of Tabernacles, as ſome thinke; but whether, it mattereth not much.
            Whereas it is ſaid, that he ſpake to them againe, hence we obſerue, and learne that Chriſt was moſt diligent, laborious, and painefull in his calling, being in all things anſwerable to the commandement and will of his father. He was often weary, hungry, thirſtie with trauailing, and preaching; neither fainting, nor failing therein through want of earthly reward (as the maner of earthly men is) nor diſcouraged therefrom with the feare of his enemies In the Chapter aforegoing the Iewes ſeeking to kill him, he trauailed into Galilee, and from thence about the middle of the Feaſt to Ieruſalem againe, where he taught continually in the Temple till the end of the laſt day of the Feaſt, then he went into the mount Oliuet to reſt and refreſh himſelfe, and earely in the morning he came againe into the Temple to preach. By which Hiſtory, and many other places, it is apparent, that Chriſt was continually employed in the actions of his calling. Hereupon it is that Iohn ſaith, Cap. 21. 25. If all 
               Iohn 21. 25.
               things were written that Ieſus ſpake, and did, I ſuppoſe the world could hardly containe the bookes, that ſhould be written of him: which words he vttered out of the conſideration, and reuiew of Chriſts great and daylie pains in teaching, preaching, &amp; working miracles, which he thought could not more fitly be expreſſed than by ſuch an hyperbolicall kinde of ſpeaking. Likewiſe, Ioh. 4 34. Chriſt was wearied with trauaile, and thirſtie, hauing neither drunke, nor eaten any thing ſince the morning, it being now mid-day, therefore his Diſciples Iohn 4. 3 4.prayed him to eate; but he anſwered, I haue meate to eate that yee know not of: My meate is, that I may doe the will of him that ſent mee, and finiſh his worke. As if he

had ſaid, though meate be now neceſſarie for me, I hauing faſted thus long, yet is the doing of my fathers wil, and finiſhing of his worke more neceſſarie; therefore occaſion of preaching, by the comming of the Samaritans, at this inſtant, being offered, I muſt forget bodily hunger, I muſt not now regard bodily meate, but I muſt redeeme the preſent occaſion, with neglect of my body and bodily ſuſtenance. Likewiſe, Math. 26. 55. I ſate dayly 
               Math. 26. 55.
               teaching in the Temple among you, &amp;c.
            Hereby the Miniſters of Chriſt, are taught by his example to be laborious and painfull in the faithfull diſcharge of their office, in the diſtruction of the kingdome of ſinne and Satan, and in gathering and building vp the Church and kingdome of Chriſt, ſeeing that he hath ſent them in like manner as his father ſent him, as himſelfe ſaith. In Ioh. 4. 35. Chriſt exhorteth his Diſciples to performe the duties of faithfull labourers in the Lords harueſt, to be carefull in reaping his fruits; his argument is drawn from the compariſon of earthly harueſt-labour. Say yee not, there are yet foure months, and 
               Ioh. 4. 35.
               then commeth the harueſt? &amp;c. As if he ſhould ſay, you are ſo carefull for this earthly harueſt, that you count the moneths, the weekes, and dayes till harueſt come, ſo hungarly doe you looke for it, and painefully labour in it; but the Lords harueſt, for which you ought to be as careful, is euen now at hand, for yee may ſee the regions already white to the harueſt, therefore you muſt not now be ſo carefull for bodily meate, as to labour in the Lords harueſt, and to delight your ſoules in his worke doing, euen in reaping and gathering ſoules into his barne, redeeming all times and occaſions with loſſe of your meate, drinke, reſt, ſleepe, pleaſures, &amp;c. euen as earthly men do in the reaping and ining of their fruits. Furthermore he inforceth this exhortation by an argument drawne from the effect; namely, the reward of the harueſt-labour, verſe 36. He that reapeth receiueth wages,
               
               and gathereth fruit to eternall life. The wages is eternall Dan. 12. 3.life, and the beleeuing ſoules are eternall, Dan. 12. 3. They that turne many to righteouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine as the 
               Iohn 15. 16.
               ſtarres, for euer and euer. Ioh. 15. 16. I haue choſen you, and ordained you, that ye goe and bring forth fruit, and that your fruit remaine, i. to eternall life. Hence it is, that Paul ſaith, 1. Theſ 2. 19.1 Theſ. 2. 19. What is our hope, or ioy, or crowne of reioycing, are not you euen it, in the preſence of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt at his comming? yes, you are our glory and ioy. The Lord inioyneth Ieremie this duty, with denunciation of vengeance Ier. 1. 17.annexed, if he fayled therein. Ier. 1. 17. Truſſe vp thy loyns, &amp; ariſe and ſpeake vnto them all that I command thee, be not afraid of their faces, leaſt I deſtroy thee before them. 
               1. Cor. 9. 16.The conſideration hereof is a ſpur to Paul, exciting him to the ſerious performance of this dutie. 1 Cor. 9. 16. Neceſſitie is layd vpon me, and woe is vnto me, if I preach not the Goſpell: And heereupon is it, that he ſo ſtraightly 2. Tim. 4. 1. 2.chargeth Timothie, 2 Tim. 4. 1. 2. I charge thee before God, and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall iudge the quick and the dead at his appearing, and in his Kingdome: Preach the word, be inſtant, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, &amp;c. Theſe conſiderations of the reward on the one ſide, and of the puniſhment on the other, ſtirred vp the Apoſtles to preach the Goſpell with all boldneſſe and conſtancie. Act. 3. 14. 15. Act 4 13. 19. 20. Act. 5. 29. 30. Act▪
                7. 51. 52. Yea, ioyfully to ſuffer afflictions, Act. 5 41. They reioyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer rebuke for the name of Chriſt. 2 Cor. 11. 23. to 29.
            Secondly, this teacheth euery man to labour in his calling carefully and conſcionably, approuing himſelfe in all things to God, to a good conſcience▪ and to good men, Rom. 12. 6. 7. 8. Epheſ. 4. 28. 2 Theſſ. 3. 10. Gen. 3. 19. Gen. 31. 6.
            Furthermore, whereas it is ſaid that he ſpake to them, it is to be vnderſtood of the multitude, though the Phariſes in the next verſe make replie. For Chriſt preached

not to the Phariſees, but by accident, ſome of them euer being amongſt the people that came to heare him, as ſpies, to watch him, and to catch ſome thing from his mouth, that they might haue whereof to accuſe him, Luc. 11 54. Therefore, becauſe they were but dogs, and Luc. 11. 54.ſwine, i. contemners, and perſecuters of the Word, vtterly forſaken of God, and left to themſelues, he caſts not the holy things of God, the pearles of the Goſpell, before them, Math. 7. 6. but in all places where he hath Math. 7. 6▪
               to deale with them, he either conuinceth them, or confuteth them, or reprooueth them, or curſeth them, neither inſtructing, exhorting, nor dehorting them, which had beene in vaine, and to no purpoſe. Thus much of the Preface.
            Concerning the Scope, It is an exhortation, which is not ſimply propounded, but implyed in the reaſon thereof. The exhortation is [follow me:] It is enforced by two reaſons, the firſt negatiue, [He that followeth mee ſhall not walke in darkeneſſe.] The ſecond affirmatiue [but ſhall haue the light of life:] Theſe reaſons are confirmed by their principle or ground, [I am the Light of the World.] Of theſe foure things in order as they lie in the text.
            
               
                  I. I am the Light of the World.
               It is an vſuall thing in the Scriptures to repreſent ſpirituall and heauenly things, by bodily and earthly things, that therein, as in glaſſes, we may behold heauenly things, although obſcurely, which notwithſtanding wee cannot otherwiſe perceiue, and ſee immediately, being too glorious, and vehement obiects for vs. Therfore as we cannot behold the light of the Sun in the Sun, but by reflexion thereof in the Moone, in the ſtars, in the water, or other bright body, or elſe by refraction thereof in the miſtie ayre: ſo the ſoule, while it is in the body, heareth, ſeeth, vnderſtandeth, imagineth,

with the body, and in a bodily manner; and therefore is not capable of ſuch hearing, ſeeing, vnderſtanding, imagining, as it ſhalbe when it is ſeperate from the body. 1. Cor. 13. 12.Hence it is that Paul ſaith, 1 Cor. 13. 12. Wee now ſee through a glaſſe, darkely: We conceiue of Heauen by a Citie, whoſe walls, pauements and manſions are of gold, pearle, chryſtal, 
                  Reu. 21.
                  emerald, &amp;c. Reu. 21▪ 
                  We conceiue of Hel by a darke dungeon, a ſtinging ſerpent, a gnawing worme, a burning riuer 
                  Eſay 30. 33.
                  of brimſtone, Eſay 30. 33. So heere the wiſedome, loue, mercy, and goodneſſe of God in ſauing his elect, reuealed by, and in Ieſus Chriſt to the world, is cal ed Light.
               And becauſe light and darkeneſſe are much vſed in the Scriptures, I will ſpeake a little of this materiall, and bodily light; becauſe it giueth light, and vnderſtanding not onely to that, whatſoeuer may be ſpoken of in this text, but to many other places of Scripture.
               The Light is in ſubſtance cleane, pure, beautifull, ſubtile, ſimple, vniforme, voide of all mixture, free from outward pollution, and may more fitly be compared to the ſubſtance of the higheſt Heauen, which is the tabernacle, or Sanctum Sanctorum of God, and his Angels, than to any earthly thing. Such is the glory of the light, that the eye cannot behold it, being in a ſubiect of nature like it ſelfe, as the Sunne is.
               Againe, the light is pleaſant, delightfull, cheerefull, comfortable, ioyfull, hopefull. For the light is the life of the world, and of euery liuing creature, and the abſence of light is the deſtruction of euery creature. It is the life of the world in a double reſpect: firſt, in reſpect of the vitall vertue: ſecondly, in reſpect of the ſhining.
               1. The vitall power of the light is diſperſed throughout all nature, from the higheſt Heauen, to the center of the earth, comprehending, and contayning all things in it. And though it giueth not light to the eye in all things, yet it ſhineth inuiſibly in euery thing▪ whoſe vertue ſuſtaineth,

inuiſibly, ſence, motion, and life in all creatures, and without which the vertues, and operations of the ſtarres aboue, and elements below, are fruitleſſe, liueleſſe and dead: ſo that Light being a materiall creature Auguſt. Baſil.in it ſelfe, is the common life, and forme of euery creature. And this is the light that God created the firſt day.
               II. The light is the life of the World, in reſpect of the ſhining▪ for if there were no light, all things ſhould be hid in darkeneſſe, and inuiſible, and therefore could nothing mooue without ſtumbling, and falling, neither know whether to goe, Ioh. 12. 35. And what could be Ioh. 12. 35.looked for but ſudaine death? Againe, without light we ſhould haue no knowledge of any thing: the firmament, and elements, with all their creatures ſhould be inuiſible to vs, there ſhould be nothing but blindneſſe, ignorance, feare, horror, ſorrow, deſpaire, we ſhould be farre worſe than the priſoner that lies in the bottome of a naſtie dungeon: Yea, if the light of the Sunne were not, the World ſhould be a very picture, and reſemblance of Hell, a confuſion of beaſts, foules, and men, euery one treading other vnder foote, yea all things ſhould be mingled together into one Chaos, or maſſe: there ſhould be nothing but hunger, thirſt, cold, nakedneſſe, feares, terrours, mourning, and wailing, continuall dying, one thing deuouring another. Conſider therefore what is the neceſſitie, excellencie, glory and felicitie of the light, which is the life of the World. Hence it is that light is vſed in the Scripture to ſignifie good, and darkeneſſe euill. Light ſignifieth the glory of Heauen, the eſſence, and holineſſe of God, the ſonne of God, the doctrine of the Goſpell, naturall vnderſtanding, knowledge, and wiſedome in the minde, the knowledge of the glory and wiſedome of God in the ſaluation of the elect, holineſſe of life, Chriſtians, felicitie, and proſperitie, life. Contrarily, darkeneſſe ſignifieth Hell, the paines and

of Hell, ſinne and wickedneſſe, the blindneſſe and ignorance of man ſince the fall, ſinfull and luſtfull liuing, the Gentiles that know not God, calamitie, and miſerie, death. Theſe things are generally ſignified by Light and Darkeneſſe.
               But for the clearing of this perticular place, the light hath foure ſpeciall ſignifications. Firſt, It ſignifieth God, that is, the Trinitie in the Vnitie. Secondly, It ſignifieth the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, that is the Vnitie in the Trinitie. Thirdly, it ſignifieth the Doctrine of the Goſpell. Fourthly, it ſignifieth Chriſtians, and Chriſtian life.
               
                  1 Ioh. 1. 5. Concerning the firſt ſignification; It is ſayd, 1 Ioh. 1. 5. God is Light, and in him is no darkeneſſe. As if he ſhould ſay, God is holy. This holineſſe of the Diuine nature ſtandeth: Firſt, in the life, and incomprehenſible eſſence, or being of God: Secondly, in his other eſſentiall properties, as his power, wiſedome, iuſtice, mercy, goodneſſes Thirdly, in his vnſpeakeable, complete, celeſtiall ioy, bleſſedneſſe, and felicitie. And as God is all light, ſo there is no light without him, for all that is without him, is ignorance, darkeneſſe, and impuritie.
               
                  Concerning the ſecond ſignification. I. God the father is the light of the world, but this light in him is inuiſible 
                  1 Tim. 6. 16.
                  to the world, and to Angels, 1 Tim. 6. 16. Who onely hath immortalitie, and dwelleth in the Light, which none can attaine Ioh. 1. 18. Wiſ. 9. 13.vnto. Ioh. 1. 18. No man hath ſeene God at any time. Wiſ. 9. 13. What man is he, that can know the Counſell of God; or who can thinke what the will of God is? Alſo, No man knoweth the father but the ſonne, &amp;c. Therefore this light of the world in the perſon of the father is hid &amp; inuiſible.
               
               II. God the Sonne is the light of the world, by communication from the father, and in him is the light, and life of the world manifeſt, and viſible, which was hid in God from euerlaſting. Ioh. 5. 36. As the father hath life in himſelfe, ſo hath he giuen to the Sonne to haue life in himſelfe.
                  
For this cauſe is he called the image of the inuiſible God, and brightneſſe of his glory, whoſe glorious nature, wiſedome, and goodneſſe ſhineth in the ſonne, who with the father, is one and the ſame God. Heb. 1. 3. Hence it is, that he is called the wiſdome of the father, becauſe he perfectly knoweth all ſecrets hidden in the father. And he is in ſpeciall manner called the Word, becauſe he reuealeth theſe ſecrets, and this light to the Nazian in orat. de filio Dei. Baſil. in praefat. ante euang. Ioh.World, in mans nature, and by mans voice. Ioh. 1. 18. No man hath ſeene God at any time: the ſonne which is in the boſome of the father, he hath declared him.
               
               The Sonne therefore is the light, and life of men in a double reſpect. I. Chriſt is the light and life of man in the worke of creation: for by participation of his life, and light, he receiued life, motion, ſence, and knowledge. Ioh. 1. 4. In it was life, and the life was the light of men. 
                  Ioh. 1. 4.
               
               II. He is the life, and light of man in the worke of redemption: in which reſpect, here he calls himſelfe the light of the World. The former naturall life, and light, which we receiued from him in the creation, is turned into darkeneſſe and death, through the enuy of the Deuill, and ſinne. So that naturally we are without God, without light, without life, lying in the darkeneſſe of ignorance, and the pollution of ſinne. Ezech. 16. 4. Rom. 1. 18. Now therefore, ſeeing that we are darkneſſe and not light, death and not life, euen dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes. Epheſ. 2. 1. God out of the hidden treaſures Epheſ. 2. 1.of his wiſedome, goodneſſe, and mercy, hath quickned, reuiued, and begotten vs againe, by application of his liuely light, communicated from before the beginning of the world to the ſon, &amp; participated to vs by, &amp; through the ſon in the world. The ſon therefore is the light▪ and life of the world: he is the wiſedome and word of the father reuealing, declaring, and applying life and light to the world, and for this purpoſe the word was made fleſh, and dwelt among vs, 1 Ioh. 1. 1. That which was from the 
                  1 Ioh. 1. 1.
                  
                  beginning (euen Chriſt, God eternall) which we haue heard (euen the ſame Chriſt made man) which we haue ſeene with our eies, which we haue looked vpon, and our hands haue handled, of the word of life declare wee vnto you. The Sonne therefore i
                     •
                   our life, light, and felicitie: he alone of God is made vnto vs, wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, 1 Cor. 1. 30.ſanctification and redemption, 1 Cor. 1. 30. This place is a plaine expoſition of theſe words, [I am the light of the World;] for heere the Apoſtle excludeth a man wholly from himſelfe, as nothing but darkeneſſe and death, and ſetteth forth our ſpirituall, and liuely being, and manner of being in Chriſt. I. Hee is our wiſedome: All ſauing and true wiſedome is in Chriſt, for God hath fully reueiled himſelfe in Chriſt, and by him to vs, Coloſ. 2. 3.and by no other meanes, Coloſ. 2. 3. In him are hid all the treaſures of Wiſedome and knowledge, and if all be in him, then without him is nothing, II. He is made our righteouſneſſe, that is to ſay, by him, and in him, alone we are accepted and beloued of God▪ For, firſt he alone by himſelfe hath purged our ſinnes: Secondly, his obedience alone is imputed to vs for righteouſneſſe. In which two things ſtandeth the righteouſneſſe of faith, by which God is our God, and we are his people. III. He is our ſanctification: By nature we are profane, without God in the world, a maſſe of filthineſſe, and impuritie, Gen. 8. 21. Eſay 64. 6. Iob. 14. 4. but by the ſpirit of Chriſt, wee are mortified, and renewed in affections▪ will, &amp; euen in the ſpirits of our mindes▪ Rom. 8. 10. Epheſ. 4. 22. 23. 24. IIII. He is our redemption: As if he ſhould ſay, by him alone wee are redeemed both from the bondage of ſinne, and miſerie that commeth by ſinne. This redemption is begun in this life, being deliuered from the bondage of corruption, and accuſation of an euill conſcience, and perfected in the end of this life, when the ſoule is ſeperate from the burthen of the fleſh; but conſumate, and finiſhed in the reſurrection of the laſt day, when body

and ſoule being revnited and ioyned together, ſhall remaine for euer with Chriſt in his kingdome of glory.
               Now, that which the Apoſtle ſaith there, that Chriſt is our wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification and redemption, is all one with that, which Chriſt ſaith heere, I am the light of the world: Therefore if any man deſire to know more wiſdome, or other wiſedome, more righteouſneſſe, or other righteouſneſſe, more redemption, or other, in whole, or in the leaſt part, let him heare the Apoſtle, Coloſ. 2. 8▪ 9. Beware leaſt there be any man, that 
                  Coloſ. 2. 8. 9.
                  ſpoile you through philoſophies and vaine deceit through the traditions of men, according to the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt: for in him dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the god-head, bodily.
               
               III. The holy Ghoſt is the light of the world, Though God the Sonne be the wiſedome and word of the father, giuing light and life to the ſpirituall world, that is, the companie of the regenerate, euen as the Sun giueth light and life to the materiall world: yet the world, that is the vnregenerate, liuing in the darkeneſſe of ignorance and ſinne, doe not comprehend, nor receiue this light of life, no more then the dead eye, or body is beautified by the light of the Sun to ſee and liue therewith. Ioh. 1. 5. the light ſhineth in the darkeneſſe, and the darkeneſſe 
                  Ioh. 1. 5.
                  comprehended it not. 11. He came vnto his owne, and 
                  Eſay 53. 1.
                  his owne receiued him not. Eſay 53. 1. Who will beleeue our 
                  Ioh. 12. 37.
                  report, and to whom is the arme of the Lord reueiled? Ioh. 12. 37. Though he did many miracles before them, yet they beleeued not in him. So that the father is the fountaine of light, the Sonne is light begotten of the Light, and tooke fleſh on him to manifeſt, and participate this light to vs, &amp; the holy Ghoſt is light proceeding from both, being ſent of the Father and the Sonne to enlighten vs. But the Son is the light of the World in a more peculiar maner, becauſe he is Emanuell, and in, and by him, is the worke of our redemption wrought, but yet with the cooperation

of the father, and the holy Ghoſt, as if three men ſhould weaue a coate, and the third weare it. So that the Trinitie in the Vnitie, and the Vnitie in the Trinitie, is the light of the World.
               Concerning the third ſignification. The Doctrine of the Goſpell, is the light of the World. There be ſundry Doctrines, and arts in the World, which are lights alſo; but they are naturall lights, not lights of life; there is no vertue in theſe lights to quicken the mortall body, or to reuiue the dead ſoule: the Doctrine of the Goſpell is only Ioh. 6. 63.the light of life. Ioh. 6. 63. The words that I ſpeake to you, are ſpirit and life. Ioh. 17. 3. Pſal. 119. 105. Ioh. 24. 13.
               
                  Concerning the fourth ſignification: Chriſtians, and Chriſtian life are the light of the World, and eſpecially 
                  2 Cor. 4. 6.
                  the Miniſters of the Word. 2 Cor. 4. 6. God that commanded the light to ſhine out of darkeneſſe, is hee which hath ſhined in our hearts, to giue the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt Ieſus. Math. 5. 14. Epheſ. 5. 8.Math. 5. 14. Yee are the light of the World. Epheſ. 5. 8. Yee were once darkeneſſe, but now are yee light in the Lord, that is, you are now enlightened by the word of truth, 
                  Phil. 2. 15.
                  let your conuerſation be according to the truth, Phil. 2. 15. Be blameleſſe and pure, and the ſonnes of God, without reproofe in the middeſt of a naughtie and crooked nation, among Pro. 4. 18.whom yee ſhine, as lights in the world▪ Prou. 4. 18. The way of the righteous ſhineth as the light, more and more vnto the perfect day. Hereupon the workes of the regenerate, 
                  Rom. 13. 12.
                  are called the workes of light. Rom. 13. 12. Put on the armour of light, i. honeſt behauiour.
               
               Notwithſtanding all that hath beene ſaid, we muſt know, that although Chriſt, the Goſpell, and Chriſtian life, be the light of the world, yet the world, namely the vnregenerate, comprehend not, nor ſee this light, becauſe they take darkeneſſe to be light, and light to be darkeneſſe.
               Know therefore, that as Chriſt was reputed in the

world, ſo were the Prophets before him, and the Apoſtles after him, and in ſuch ſort are the true Miniſters, and true beleeuers eſteemed in the world. Marke what Eſay ſaith of Chriſt▪ chap. 8. 18. I and the children which thou haſt giuen me, are as ſignes and wonders in Iſrael, i. as monſters. As Dauid ſaith, Behold I am become a monſter vnto many. And Iohn ſaith of him, Ioh. 1. 10. He was in the 
                  Ioh. 1. 10.
                  world, and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not. Iohn 9. 29. Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, Mat. 11. 19. Mat. 11. 19.
                  The ſonne of man is counted a glutton, a drinker of wine, a companion of Publicans and ſinners. Mat. 27. 63. He is counted a deceiuer. Mat. 9. 34. A ſorcerer. Ioh. 8. 48. A Samaritane, and to haue the diuell. Mark. 3. 21. His kinsfolkes lay 
                  Ioh. 9. 24.
                  hold on him, ſuppoſing him to be beſide himſelfe. Ioh. 9. 24, The Phariſies know him to be a ſinner. If Chriſt was thus reputed of, who neuer ſinned, and in whoſe perſon, words and works, the Maieſty, power, and glory of God appeared, yea through which, as through a chryſtall, his diuinity ſhined forth to the world; how much more then the children of God that are clogged with infirmities? No maruell is it, though they be counted the vileſt, and moſt contemptible perſons of all other. See the cauſe hereof. Wiſd. 2. 22, They doe not vnderſtand the myſteries of God, nor can diſcerne the honour of the ſoules, that are faultleſſe. The cauſe of this ignorance and going aſtray is, verſ. 21. Their 
                  Ioh. 3. 19.
                  owne wickedneſſe hath blinded them. Ioh. 3. 19. This is the condemnation of the world, that light is come into the world, and men loued darkneſſe more then light, becauſe their deeds were euill. The wicked hate the light becauſe it diſcouers ſinne, which they loue; againe the righteous loue the light, becauſe it diſcouers ſinne, which they hate, and manifeſteth the right way vnto them, into which they deſire to enter, and wherein they delight to walke.
               The world knew not the Prophets that were before Chriſt. But what part or people of the world? The Phariſies, Amorites, Ammonites, Moabites, Edomites? No

maruell if theſe knew them not. But the Church of God, the Iſraelites knew them not: yea, they were worſe then the Aliants. For the Niniuites perſecuted not Ionas, but Ionas 3. 4. 5. &amp;c.beleeued God. Ionas. 3▪ 4 5. &amp;c. But the Iſraelites perſecuted al the Prophets with deriſion, contempt, impriſonment, death. Act. 7. 52. Which of the Prophets haue not your 
                  Acts 7. 52.
                  fathers perſecuted, and they haue ſlaine them that ſhewed before of the comming of that iuſt, &amp;c. Which were the ſlaughter-houſes of the Prophets, and Saints, before Chriſt? euen Samaria and Ieruſalem, Mat. 23. 37. Euen Ieruſalem, where was the Temple and worſhip of God, Ezech. 16. 46.where aboue all places in the world, Gods name was called vpon. Ezec. 16. 46. Thy eldeſt ſiſter is Samaria, thy younger ſiſter is Sodome.
               
               
                  Acts 5. 28. Againe, the world, knew not the Apoſtles, that were after Chriſt. In Acts 5. 28. the preaching of the Goſpell is counted ſedition, and rebellion. In verſe 38. 39. Gamaliel a Doctor of the Law doubteth whether it be of God, or of men, comparing the Apoſtles to Theudas and Iudas of Galile, that made inſurrection in the dayes of tribute. Acts 24. 5.In Acts 24. 5. Paul is counted a peſtilent fellow, a moouer of ſedition, a maintainer of the ſect of the Nazarites, In the verſ. 14. his doctrine is called Hereſie, chap. 26. 44. Madneſſe. 
                  1 Cor. 4. 13.1. Cor. 4. 13. We are counted the of-ſcourings of al things. And Iohn the Baptiſt, that came in the way of righteouſneſſe, is ſaid to haue the diuell.
               In the primitiue Church what euills ſoeuer happened to the City, or prouinces of Rome, whether famine, peſtilence, earth-quakes, warres, vnſeaſonable weather, the Chriſtians were thought to be the cauſes thereof: whereupon roſe great perſecutions; whereas indeed they themſelues were the cauſes thereof, which by reaſon of their vnbeliefe, and malice, brought theſe iudgements of God vpon thei owne heads. And herein note the condition of this blinde world, it alwayes hath beene and is ſuſpitious

of the truth, and the true profeſſion thereof, fearing and dreading the ſame, as an enemy to their peace, and ſafety. Worldly peace, reſt, ſafety, liberty, proſperity is all that the carnall man ſeeketh for, or careth for, making the end of their owne doings and Gods doings alſo, the reſt, eaſe, and pleaſures of their bodies, and the pompous gloryfying of their perſons.
               Whatſoeuer is aboue this, and for God, they take to be againſt them, becauſe they are againſt God, though not in outward ſhew, yet in ſpirit, yea, making themſelues their owne Idols, Ioh. 11. 48. If we let him alone, all men 
                  Ioh. 11. 48.
                  will beleeue in him, and the Romanes will come and take away both our place, and the Nation. Theſe worldly Politicians, whoſe policy was not guided nor ſeaſoned with grace, are afraid of Chriſt and Chriſtian profeſſion. If we let him thus alone, ſay they▪ all men will beleeue him to be the Prophet and Meſſias that ſhould come, and ſo make him King: which when Caeſar heareth, he will come with an inuincible hoſt againſt vs, and vtterly deſtroy this City, and the whole nation: Therefore our ſafeſt courſe is, by ſome meanes to plot his death: which plot and which meanes was the cauſe of the ſame deſtruction that they feared: for the Romane Emperour came, and tooke away their place and nation, becauſe they ſlew the ſonne of God, and perſecuted the Goſpell. Theſe wicked wretches neuer feared that their infidelity, pride, couetouſnes oppreſſion, hypocriſie, ſhould be the cauſes of their ruine, but they feared the Goſpell, and godly life. Againe, Acts 5. 24.
                  Act 5. 24. The chiefe Prieſt &amp; Saduces had put the Apoſtles in priſon, but an Angel deliuered them in the night, and commanded them to preach in the Temple the next day. Now the chiefe Prieſt and the Captaine of the Temple and the high Prieſts, hearing what was done, doubted of them whereunto this would grow. Theſe carnall and graceleſſe politicians regarding only the eſtabliſhing of their place, and of themſelues, and of all things for themſelues,

feared an alteration, &amp; doubted whether it would in the end proue to be with them or againſt them. And becauſe indeed that it could not but be againſt them (for the preaching of Ieſus to be the ſonne of God, the Prince and Sauiour of the world muſt needs conuince them of rebellion and murther, to their vtter diſgrace, ſhame, and confuſion, among all the people) therefore they laboured by all meanes to murther the Apoſtles, &amp; to quench the light of the Goſpell. In like ſort very many in theſe times, hanging between Popery and proteſtancy, doubt, and haue long doubted what this geare will grow to in the end: In the meane time not regarding at all what their vnbeleefe, pride, oppreſſion, couetouſneſſe, epicuriſme, and mocking will grow to.
               Furthermore, as the world in all times and ages heretofore hath not knowne the ſtraight paths of God; ſo in theſe preſent dayes of ours the true and right profeſsion of Chriſtianity is counted of many puritaniſme, and preciſeneſſe, phantaſticalneſſe, affectation of ſingularity, and hypocriſie. True it is indeed, that as there are true Preachers, and true beleeuers, ſo Satan ſtirs vp counterfeits, that haue an outward ſhew and reſemblance of them, but are not purged from their inward filthineſſe: Theſe are they that worldlings ſtumble at, concluding thus, euen ſo are they all, therefore their profeſsion is but a kind of ſect; and to follow the common courſe, and practiſe of the world, is the ſureſt and ſafeſt way. Here Satan hath his deſire. Againe if any godly man that hath alwayes made conſcience of his wayes, ſhall offend, though of meere infirmity, or occaſioned by ſome ſtrong temptation, but yet ſo as he may iuſtly be taxed, why then the matter is now out of all doubt; both he and all of his rancke are hypocrites, and none elſe: ſuch is the blindnes of the world, and their praeiudicate opinion of the children of God. But now to conclude this firſt part, let me leaue this as a bone for the world to gnaw on, that ſtumbling

blockes ſhall euer be caſt before the feet of the wicked, yet ſhall the lanterne of Gods word ſhine vnto them, to guide them without ſtumbling or erring; notwithſtanding ſtumble they will, and fall downe, euen to the breaking of their necke; for their owne wickedneſſe blindeth them, yea and they doe wilfully out of tbe hardneſſe of their hearts cloſe their eyes againſt the wayes of truth, becauſe the waies of errour, death, &amp; deſtruction are more pleaſant vnto them. Thus much of the principle or ground of the reaſons enforcing the exhortation, which followeth next in order to be ſpoken of.
            
            
               
                  II. He that followeth me.
               There are ſundry ſorts of followers. I. Yong gentlemen, that are trained vp for education ſake vnder great perſonages, and for experience, countenance, and preferment ſake in the world, are called their followers. II. They that hold on ſome ſect of the Philoſophers ſchooles, are called their followers. III. They that faſhion and conforme themſelues to the example of any man that excelleth in any faculty, are called his followers, but theſe are ſecular followers, and not pertinent to this place.
               When Chriſt the light and life of the world preached the Goſpell of ſaluation to the world, in the outward forme and appearance of the Prophets that were before him, and of his Apoſtles and miniſters after him, confirming his doctrine with miracles, he had diuers followers. I. Some followed him to be cured of their diſeaſes, and infirmities, Mat. 15. 30. Great multitudes came, hauing 
                  Mat. 15. 30.
                  with them the halt, blind, dumbe, maimed, &amp;c. Thus the ten leapers followed him, and eſpecially the nine, that returned not to giue God praiſe. Luke 17. 17. II. Some▪ followed 
                  Luke 17. 17.
                  him to gaze on him and his miracles, and for this purpoſe Herod was glad when Pilate had ſent him to him,

hauing been deſirous of a long ſeaſon to ſee him, becauſe he had heard many things of him, &amp; truſted to ſee ſome Luke 23. 8.ſigne done by him. Luk. 23. 8. III. Some followed him for their bellies ſake, as many doe in theſe dayes. Thus Iudas followed him; not becauſe he loued him, and embraced his doctrine in ſincerity, but becauſe he was a theefe, and Mat. 8. 19.had the bag, and bare that which was giuen. Iohn 12. 6. Thus the Scribe followed him. Mat. 8. 19. Master I will follow thee whither ſoeuer thou goeſt. He imagined in his earthly heart, as did Iudas and the people of the Iewes, that Chriſt ſhould in the end be crowned King of the Iewes, and that he would prefer and aduance his followers, as earthly Princes vſe to doe. Therefore Chriſt ſhapes him an anſwer accordingly, verſe 20. The foxes haue holes and the birds of the heauen haue neſts, but the Sonne of Man hath not where to reſt his head; conſequently he hath nothing at all wherewith to gratifie his followers and welwillers. Thus alſo a great multitude followed him ouer Ioh. 6. 26.the ſea of Tiberias, and from thence backe to Capernaum, Iohn 6. 26. Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, you ſeeke me not becauſe of the miracles, but becauſe of the loaues that ye ate, and were filled. Fourthly, ſome followed him of enuy to entangle him, in his ſpeechs, as did the Phariſies, Scribes, Sadduces, Lawyers, and the Herodians, which thought that Herod was the Chriſt. Theſe are carnall and hypocriticall followers, which neither are meant of here in this place.
               The true following of Chriſt, which here he ſpeaketh of, is expreſſed by diuers ſimilitudes in the Scripture. Ioh. 10. 21.
                  Iohn 10. 21. My ſheepe here my voice, and I know them, and they follow me, &amp;c. where hearing ſignifieth Faith, and following Obedience. In other countries the ſhepheards driue not their ſheepe, but they call them and they follow them. Euery flocke knoweth the voice of their owne ſhepheard, by often hearing him, &amp; they follow him, but after a ſtrange voice they will not follow: Euen ſo Chriſts

ſheep, the elect, heare his word, they know it and acknowledge it, and are obedient to it, that is, they ſuffer themſelues to be ruled, and gouerned by their chiefe ſhepheard Ieſus Chriſt, ſpeaking to them and calling them to him in his word, yea clocking them together as the hen doth her chickens. Mat. 23. 31. But mark the cauſe why they heare &amp; obey him, in theſe words (And I know them.) This knowing is not onely vnderſtood of Gods foreknowledge, whereby he knew who were his from before all times, but of his knowing of them effectually in time. I call it effectuall knowledge when the elect are poſſeſſed of this knowing or acknowledging them, by the inward calling of his ſpirit. And this aſſurance of Gods knowing them, acknowledging and owning them, is the cauſe why they know and acknowledge him, and are delighted with his word.
               Againe, this true following of Chriſt is farther expreſſed in Epheſ. 5. 1. Therefore be ye followers of God, as deare 
                  Epheſ. 5. 1.
                  children. This verſe is a concluſion of an exhortation of the laſt end of the verſe afore going, forgiue ye one another, euen as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiuen you: Therefore be ye followers, &amp;c. Children wee know doe imitate their parents, not onely in deeds and words, but euen in the affections of their hearts, and imaginations of their minds, reſembling them inwardly, as they doe outwardly; ſo that a man may ſay, this is right the fathers child, or the father will neuer be dead whiles the child liueth. Now the reaſon hereof is, becauſe he hath receiued the ſpirit of generation from the father, which frameth, faſhioneth, and worketh him into the image, ſimilitude, identity or ſelfeneſſe (as I may ſay) of his father: And this is a deare childe, becauſe the father doth not onely loue his child, but himſelfe alſo in the child; and the child not onely loueth his father, but himſelfe in the father; ſo that the one cannot hate the other, vnleſſe he hate himſelfe; and neuer man hated his owne fleſh▪ Therfore

this vnion is moſt firme, and perpetuall: euen ſo the children of God doe carry the reſemblance and likeneſſe of God in the inner man, in holineſſe by obedience to the firſt Table, and righteouſneſſe, by obedience to the ſecond Table of the Commandments, which both proceed from Loue, and Loue from Faith.
               Therefore as God is holy, ſo are his children holy. Leu. 11. 44.
                  Leu. 11. 44. I am the Lord your God, be ſanctified and be holy, for I the Lord your God am holy. As God is righteous, 1 Ioh. 3. 7.ſo are they righteous. 1 Ioh. 3. 7. He that doth righteouſneſſe is righteous, euen as he is righteous. As God is mercifull euen ſo are they mercifull. Luke 6. 36. As God is loue, ſo walke they in loue. Epheſ. 5. 2. Walke in loue, euen as Chriſt 
                  1 Ioh. 3. 14.
                  hath loued vs. 1 Ioh. 3. 14. We know we are tranſlated from death to life, becauſe we loue the brethren. As God is true and iuſt in all his words and works, ſo are they without hypocriſie, and doubting, both in reſpect of God their father, and in reſpect of their brethren. For the firſt, it is Ioſ. 24. 14. 1 Sam. 12. 24.commanded Ioſ. 24. 14. Feare the Lord and ſerue him in vprightneſſe and truth, 1 Sam. 12. 24. Feare the Lord and ſerue him in truth with all thy heart. For the ſecond, it is Epheſ. 4. 25.commanded, Epheſ. 4. 25. Caſt away lying and ſpeake euery one truth to his neighbour. The reaſon of the commandement is in the words following, drawne from the coniunction of our members (for we are one anothers members) but whoſe members are we? that the 15. verſe declareth, of Chriſt our head, into whom we grow, and by whoſe ſpirit we are knit together. Therefore if we be the true members we follow Chriſt our head: Contrarily, if we be not true members, but falſe, counterfeit, and dead limmes, we are cut off from him, ſeparate to the world, and bodily luſts: or at leaſt if we be not apparantly ſeparate from him, but doe ſtill outwardly profeſſe him, yet doe we draw no vertue from him, leauing no feeling thereof in vs, either mortifying ſinne in vs, or quickning vs to newneſſe of life; but are as the dead branches growing

in the tree, but drawing no ſucke or iuyce of life out of the tree. Secondly, if we be falſe and dead limbs, then are we ſeparate from the other members, hauing no hearty fellowſhip with them.
               
                  I need not to amplifie this following, whereby Gods children follow him, by any more ſpecialls; for as they follow him in holineſſe, righteouſneſſe, mercifulneſſe, loue, truth, vprightneſſe, ſo alſo in all other things. 1 Pet. 1 Pet. 1. 15.
                  1. 15. As he which hath called you is holy, even ſo be ye holy in all manner of conuerſation. Mat. 5. 48. Be you perfect as your father which is in heauen, is perfect, 1 Pet. 2. 9. Ye are a choſen generation, a royall Prieſthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people, that ye ſhould ſhew forth the vertues of him that hath called you out of darkneſſe into his maruellous light. To this purpoſe alſo Chriſt ſaith, Mat. 5. 16. Let your light ſo ſhine before men that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen. Yea, this is the end of your election, redemption, and calling, euen our ſanctification. 1 Pet. 2. 2. 
                  1 Pet. 1. 2.
               
               Now the cauſe why the children of God doe ſo reſemble him in true wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, and holineſſe, is becauſe they haue receiued from him the ſpirit of regeneration. Ioh. 3. 4. Except a man be borne of water 
                  Ioh. 3. 4.
                  and the ſpirit he cannot enter into the kingdome of God; that is, neither into the kingdome of grace, nor into the kingdome of glory. He is called the ſpirit of adoption, Rom. 8. 15. You haue not receiued the ſpirit of bondage Rom. 8. 15.to feare againe, but the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we cry Abba, or call God father. Whatſoeuer we are, how morally good ſoeuer we be, we are but children of wrath, quite cut off from God, hauing no part at all in him; wild Oliues, Rom. 11. 24. Baſtards and runnagates, Rom. 11. 24.as Cain and Cham, vntill God adopt vs into his family, giuing vs the ſpirit of ſonnes, of his owne free mercy, and grace, Tit. 3. 5. 6 Ezech. 36. 26. 17. Becauſe this politicall terme of adoption is vſed often in the Epiſtles, I will

briefly declare the meaning thereof.
               Generation or begetting of children is naturall or legall: legall generation is a politicall act maintaining nature, ordained for their comfort, which haue no chidren, the law prouiding children for them, whom nature hath failed. And thus may a man be ſaid to beget children legally.
               Legall generation is alſo twofold, Adrogation and adoption. Adrogation is when he that is a free man, and vnder no mans power, authority or command, viz. neither of father, or maſter, is receiued into the place of a ſonne, by an other, which thus by law becommeth his father. And if he that is thus adrogate haue children, they are alſo vnder his power, as Nephewes, that is, his ſons children.
               Adoption is when he that is vnder the power of an other, whether father or maſter, is taken by another man to be his ſonne and heire. And if he haue ſonnes that is thus adopted, they are the nephewes of the adoptour. And although the adoptour cannot giue the ſpirit of a ſonne vnto him (which only the naturall father can do) yet is the adopted ſo obliged &amp; bound to him for thoſe ſo great benefits both of freedome and inheritance, as that he cannot but for euer be moſt thankfull to him, yea alwayes ready and deſirous to teſtifie the ſame by his loue, dutifulneſſe, obedience, and all meanes towards his adoptour, euen as he were his owne ſonne, and he his naturall father.
               To apply this. We, euen the beſt that euer was, were vnder the power of others, to wit, in the bondage, and vnder the tyranny of the diuell, and ſinne, who had abſolute power and command ouer vs: and we miſerable wretches yeelded our ſelues willingly, yea with delight, into ſubiection, and homage vnto them, being deſtitute of the knowledge of God and godlines. Now God of his owne free loue, mercy, and grace, redeemed

vs out of the thraldome of thoſe tyrants with the bloodſhed and death of his owne ſonne: which willingly ſubmitted himſelf in obedience to his father herein; for by no other price, nor other meanes could this purchaſe be made. Who becauſe he was not only perfect man, but perfect God alſo, did by the ſpirit of ſanctification free himſelfe from the graue, the puniſhment, and imputation of our ſinnes; and by the power of the ſame raiſed himſelfe from death vnto life, corruption, and death hauing no power ouer him. This ſanctifying ſpirit of the ſonne hath the Father giuen vs, that by the power thereof our bond-mens minds, wills, affections, might be mortified and crucified; and that ſonne-like and ſpirituall minds, wills, affections, might be put into vs, daily renuing vs into the nature of ingenuous, and freeborne ſonnes. This is more then the legall father or adoptour can doe. For he can doe no more but binde his adopted ſonne to thankfulneſſe for his benefits of bodily freedome, and earthly inheritance; but God hath giuen vs the ſpirit of his ſonne, whereby we are made and tranſformed into naturall ſonnes, and therefore affectioned towards him, as the child is towards his naturall fathel. Much more thankfull therefore, louing, dutifull and obedient ought we to be (if we be true ſonnes) to God our father, and Chriſt our redeemer, that hath ſo dearely bought vs out of the power of ſinne, death, and damnation, and brought vs into the glorious liberty of ſonnes, and hope of euerlaſting inheritance together with his owne ſonne.
               Therefore it is apparant, that it is the ſpirit which quickneth, begetteth, faſhioneth, and conformeth the children of God into the ſimilitude and likenes of God their father, wherein at the firſt they were created, and into which they are renewed by the holy Ghoſt, by the Goſpell of faith. This begetting and quickning ſpirit is called immortall ſeede. 1. Pet. 1. 23. Being borne
                  
                  a new, not of mortall ſeede, but of immortall, by the 1 Ioh. 3. 9.word of God, &amp;c. 1 Ioh. 3. 9. Whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not, becauſe his ſeede remaineth in him, &amp;c. This ſeede is not the eſſence of the holy Ghoſt, but the power thereof, begetting faith of the Goſpell in vs, crucifying the body of ſinne in vs, and renuing vs into the Rom. 1. 13.image of God. Rom. 1. 13. 14. If ye mortifie the deeds of the fleſh by the ſpirit, ye ſhall liue; for as many as are led by the ſpirit of God, are the ſonnes of God. Tit. 3 4. We are ſaued by the waſhing of the new birth, and renuing of the holy Ghoſt.
               
               To conclude this point then: As the child doth imitate the father by the vnion and identity of the ſpirit communicated vnto him from the father: euen ſo the child of God doth imitate and follow Chriſt by the vnion of the ſpirit of God and Chriſt, which the Apoſtle 2 Pet. 1. 4.calls participation of the diuine nature. 2 Pet. 1. 4. Wherby moſt great and pretious promiſes are giuen vnto vs, that by them ye ſhould be partakers of the godly nature, in that ye flee the corruption which is in the world through luſt.
               
               
                  Queſt Hereupon it may be demanded, how we are partakers of the godly nature, and how we are ſaid properly to be the children of God.
               
                  Anſw. We are partakers of the godly nature two wayes. Firſt, in reſpect of the effect, vertues, and gifts of the holy Ghoſt working in vs, and by vs; as, firſt, enlightning our minds with the true knowledge of Chriſt: ſecondly, begetting faith in vs, and incorporating vs into Chriſt: thirdly, purging out the leauen of naturall corruption in vs: fourthly, faſhioning vs into new obedience: fiftly, applying Chriſt with his gifts, and treaſures vnto vs: ſixtly, leading vs into all truth: ſeuenthly, comforting vs in afflictions: eightly, ſealing the certainty of our inheritance in our hearts by his teſtimony, as a Epheſ. 1. 14.pledge or earneſt of the promiſes of God. Epheſ. 1. 14. Hence it is that he is called The ſpirit of wiſedome, and vnderſtanding, the ſpirit of counſell, and ſtrength, the ſpirit of
                  
                  knowledge, and feare of the Lord, Eſay. 11. 2. Becauſe hee Eſay 11. 2.begetteth, worketh, and increaſeth thoſe vertues and graces in vs. Likewiſe the ſpirit of meekneſſe, Galat. 6. 1. The ſpirit of faith. 2 Cor. 4. 13. The ſpirit of loue. 2 Tim. 1. 7. Moreouer the Apoſtles were partakers of the diuine nature in reſpect of thoſe extraordinary gifts wherewith they were endued for the execution of their Apoſtolicall office.
               Secondly, we are partakers of the godly nature, in reſpect of the eſſence of God: not that Gods eſſence is any part of vs; but as he is God euery where filling heauen and earth with his eſſence, ſo is he in ſpeciall manner with, and in his children, and by his preſence is effectuall in them. Whereupon Paul ſaith, Rom. 8. 11. The 
                  Rom. 8. 11.
                  ſpirit of him which hath raiſed vp Ieſus dwelleth in you. 
                  Ioh. 14. 23.
                  Ioh. 14. 23. If any one loue me he will keep my word, and my Father will loue him, and we will come and dwell with him. God is preſent with the wicked alſo, but it is in ſuch ſort as the Iudge is preſent with the malefactors.
               Thirdly, in this place the following of Chriſt is compared to the following of light, or to a lanterne that giueth light to trauellers to goe the right way without error, falling or ſtumbling. Such a compariſon the Pſalmiſt maketh, Pſal. 119. 105. Thy word is a lanterne to my 
                  Pſal. 119. 105.
                  feet, that I might not ſtumble, nor erre. The word then, both ſheweth the right way for a Chriſtian to walke in, and guideth him in the right way to walke without offence. So that to follow the light is to haue our conuerſation in this world according to the word of God, which by his ſonne he hath ſent and reuealed to vs, and is effectuall in them that are ſaued, bringing them out of the darkneſſe of this world into the glorious light and ſunſhine of his kingdome and grace. Thus much of the exhortation. It followeth now to ſpeake of the negatiue reaſon inforcing the ſame.
            
            
               
               
                  III. Shall not walke in darkneſſe.
               What it is to walke or liue in darkneſſe, the Apoſtle plainly declareth, Epheſ. 4. 17. 18. 19. the 17 verſe is a dehortation, Walke not as other Gentiles doe in the vanity of their minds. Vanity of mind is a priuation or want of true wiſedome and knowledge, whereupon the imaginations of the minde, the affections of the heart, and actions of life, are not according to true wiſedome and knowledge, but vaine, that is, fooliſh, fruitleſſe, vnprofitable, Rom. 6. 21.to no end. Rom. 6. 21. What fruit had you then in theſe things whereof you are now aſhamed? for the end of theſe things is death.
               
               In the two verſes following, he farther expreſſeth this vaine and fooliſh life of the Gentiles, ſhewing and declaring it by the cauſes thereof, which are two. The firſt is in the 18. verſe, namely the corruption of the mind. The ſecond is in the 19, verſe, and that is remorceleſneſſe of conſcience.
               The corruption of the minde ſtands in two things. Firſt, in the preſence of euill (hauing their cogitation darkned.) Secondly, in the abſence of good (Being ſtrangers from the life of God.)
               
               Concerning the darkneſſe of the minde, I thus expreſſe it. Man was created in the image of God, that is, Col. 3. 10.in the true knowledge of God. Col. 3. 10. And haue put on the new man, which is renued in knowledge, after the image of him that hath created him, and in true righteouſneſſe and 
                  Epheſ. 5. 24.
                  holineſſe. Epheſ. 5. 24. Put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe. This knowledge was as a pure and eleare light in the minde of man; but after that by the fall man was ſeparated from God, this light was darkned, that is, this knowledge was corrupted with ignorance as a puniſhment of the fall, ſo that there remained onely ſome ſmall notions, glimmering, or remainders of light or knowledge in him.

Then againe, this light or remainder of knowledge is farther corrupted by the frowardneſſe of the affections and will. Now this ſmall remnant being taken away, there ſucceedeth meere darkneſſe, and brutiſh ignorance. Mat. 6. 23. If the light that is in thee be darknes, how 
                  Mat. 6. 23.
                  great is that darkneſſe? As if he had ſaid, if thy naturall reaſon be darkned through the malice of thy heart, there is nothing but meere darkneſſe.
               Secondly, the corruption of the mind ſtandeth in the abſence of good (ſtrangers from the life of God.) Life is naturall, or ſpirituall; the former we haue by generation from Adam, and it is the function of the ſoule in motion, ſenſe, and reaſon.
               Spirituall life is that which we haue by regeneration or new birth, which is the action of the holy Ghoſt begetting faith in vs, by the power whereof we deſtroy the body of ſinne, and are renued into the image of God, which is here called the life of God. This life of God Paul doth plainly declare, Gal. 2. 19. 20. That I 
                  Gal. 2. 19. 20.
                  might liue to God I am crucified with Chriſt (as touching the old man) 20. Thus I liue, yet not I now, but Chriſt liueth in me (his ſpirit worketh new obedience in me.) In the words following he defineth this dying to ſinne, and newneſſe of life by the cauſe (And in that I now liue in the fleſh, I liue by the faith of the ſonne of God.) The Gentiles and prophane perſons are far from this godly life.
               Furthermore this their ſtrangeneſſe from the life of God is declared by the cauſe thereof, that is, their ignorance: their ignorance is declared by the cauſe alſo, to wit, the hardneſſe of their heart, which is the peruerſeneſſe of the will and of the affections in the heart. And becauſe froward and peruerſe men doe reſiſt, and ſeeke to quench the ſmall light that is in them, therefore God giueth them vp into a reprobate minde voide Rom. 1. 28.of all iudgement. Rom, 1. 28. This is the firſt cauſe of vaine, fooliſh, and fruitleſſe liuing.
               
               
                  
The ſecond cauſe is remorceleſneſſe of conſcience, verſe 19. Which being paſt feeling, haue giuen themſelues to wantonneſſe. Cuſtome in ſinne hardneth the heart, and the heart being hardned rebelleth againſt the mind, and putteth out the light of reaſon, which bringeth a curſe vpon the conſcience, and taketh away all remorſe of ſinne, which is a token of reprobation. The Apoſtle 1 Tim. 4. 2.calleth it a ſeared conſcience that cannot bleed. 1▪ 
                  Tim. 4. 2. Thus haue I ſhewed what it is to walke in darkneſſe which is to liue, not according to the knowledge of God, and his waves, but according to the imaginations and corrupt affections of our owne hearts. And thus doe all men naturally liue, though neuer ſo wiſe, learned, ciuill, and great in the world; their whole life is fooliſh, fruitleſſe, vnprofitable, and their end is eternall death.
               For the further clearing of this point, I will ſhew in what particulars the vaine and fooliſh life of the ignorant is compared to darkneſſe.
               Firſt, darkneſſe is a priuation and want of light: ſo ſpirituall darkneſſe, that is, the ignorance, and blindneſſe of the heart is a priuation, and want of the light or knowledge of God.
               Secondly, in darkneſſe all things are inuiſible, one thing cannot be diſcerned from another: Blacke, and white, good and euill, hurtfull things and profitable things are not diſcerned So in ſpirituall darkneſſe, men call good euill, and euill good; ſinne is delightfull and ſweet to them, yea they coun tit abhomination todepart 1 Pet▪ 4. 4.from euill. 1 Pet. 4. 4. Wherein it ſeemeth ſtrange vnto them, that yee run not with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot, therefore ſpeake they euill of you.
               
               Thirdly, in darkneſſe a man knowes not the right way, though he be neuer ſo quickeſighted, and although he be ſet in it, yet will he ſoone goe aſtray, running into by-paths and dangerous wayes, like a blind man: ſo in

So in ſpirituall darkneſſe, ignorance of God in his word, a man knowes not the way of life: this narrow way he can not finde, &amp; though he be neuer ſo ſubtill, politicke, wiſe, and learned, well may he grope for the ſtreight gate, as the men of Sodome did for Lots dore, but he ſhall neuer be able to finde it; and though he daily looke on it, yet ſhall he not diſcerne it: All his wayes are the wayes of death, and the good and right way ſeemeth to him to be the worſt way.
               Fourthly, if this light of the ſunne were not, the earth ſhould be a very picture and reſemblance of hell, a confuſed maſſe, or heape of beaſts, foules, and men, one thing treading other vnder foot, nothing but hunger, thirſt, cold, nakedneſſe, feare, terrours, ſorrow, deſpaire, mourning, and wailing, continuall dying, one thing deuouring another: Euen ſo in ſpirituall darkneſſe, where the knowledge of Gods word is not, there is a reſemblance of hell, and men are like diuels: there is nothing but diſorder and confuſion, no dueties towards God, nor towards man put in practiſe. Where this glorious light of the Goſpell ſhineth not in the hearts of men, they are like to beaſts and Serpents, yea, they degenerate into the natures of all noiſome and venemous beaſts. Firſt, they hatch cockatrice egges, that is, whatſoeuer Eſay 59. 5. Pſal. 14. 5.commeth from them is deadly poyſon. Eſay 59. 5. The poiſon of Aſpes is vnder their lippes. Pſal. 14. 5. Deſtruction and vnhappines is in their waies, verſe 7. Secondly, they are vipers, children deuouring parents, and parents their children. Mat. 3. 7. Thirdly, They are as fed 
                  Ier. 5. 8.
                  horſes, of vnbrideled and adulterous luſts, Ier. 5. 8. Fourthly, Reioycing and neighing in the victory and downfall of their neighbours, like to ſtrong horſes. Ier. 50. 11. Fiftly, deſtroying Ier. 50. 11.their Prophets, teachers, inſtructors, and the poore, like to Lyons. Ier. 2. 30. Pſal. 10. 9. &amp; 22. 13. Sixtly, ſubtile and wilely to deceiue, like Foxes. Luke 13. 32. Seuenthly, Luk▪ 11. 32.
                  
Girning and running about like dogges, if they be not ſatisfied in their vnſatiable deſires. Pſal. 59. 14. Eſay 56. 11. Eightly, rauenous and greedy of the prey, full of cruelty, and without all mercy, like to wolues, Mat. 7. 15. Where the light of the Goſpell ſhineth not in the hearts and mindes of men what can there be but pride, vaineglory, drunkenneſſe, exceſſiue drinkings, oppreſſion, deceiuing one another, and being deceiued, euery Superiour treading his Inferiour vnder foote; politicke and craftie circumuenting one another, wily intrapping and inſnaring one another; couſenage, fraudulent dealing, diſſembling and lying in bargaining, bloodſucking by cruell oppreſſion hatefull and heatheniſh rent-racking, vaine and prodigall ſpending, voluptuous liuing, and licentious gaming, murthers, enuy, ill will, contention▪ and trouble, whoredomes, adulteteries, and wantonneſſe? Theſe and ſuch like, are the workes of darkneſſe, euen of them that are aliue in body, and dead in ſoule. But Chriſt is the light of the world: they that follow him ſhall not liue in ſuch darkneſſe, but ſhall haue the light of life. Thus much of the negatiue reaſon: the affirmatiue followeth.
            
            
               
                  IIII. But ſhall haue the light of life.
               There be two lights of life, or liuely lights. Firſt the knowledge of God in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe, participated by the ſonne of God to Adam in the creation, is called liuely light: I ſay, the naturall knowledge of God in Adam before the fall, was the light of naturall life, which life ſtood in abſolute holineſſe, which was his perfect obedience to the firſt Table, and abſolute righteouſneſſe, which was his obedience to the ſecond.

But this liuely light by the fall was extinguiſhed, yet not wholly, but ſo buried in ignorance and impurity, as it is of no force to bring forth in vs any pure worſhip of God, or holineſſe of life, but ſerueth rather to bridle and reſtraine vs from outragious ſinne, and to giue vs ſome light to diſcerne our ignorance and malice, to our owne accuſation and condemnation, ſo that it is a deadly and not a liuely light.
               The ſecond light is a new knowledge, that is, the knowledge of God in Chriſt. Of God in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelfe: of God in Chriſt our mercifull and louing father: of God in Chriſt redeeming and purchaſing vs againe, when by ſinne we were vtterly loſt: of God in Chriſt reſtoring vs to ſight, that were vtterly blinde, and ignorant: of God in Chriſt aboliſhing the body of ſinne, and corruption in vs: of God in Chriſt renuing vs into his owne image and likenes, from which by Adams tranſgreſſion we fell: of God in Chriſt, turning the curſe of the earth, with all afflictions and troubles, into bleſſings and meanes to eternall bliſſe: of God in Chriſt, preparing a kingdome and heauenly Citty for vs, whoſe pauements, walles, and buildings are of Golde, Pearle, Emeraldes, Chryſolites, Carbuncles, and all coſtly ornaments, a thouſand times excelling the Sanctum Sanctorum of Salomons Temple in glory.
               He that followeth Chriſt hath this liuely light in him▪ he that followeth him not, hath no light in him, but is ſhut vp in ignorance and darkneſſe. Hee I ſay that denying carnall wiſedome, and fleſhly luſts, doth follow him, is enlightned to ſee and behold the glory of God in ſauing the elect▪ by and through Chriſt, which the Goſpell ſetteth forth: And by vertue of this light and ſauing knowledge is he made partaker of the diuine nature, that is quickned to liue the life of God, which

ſtands in new obedience. He therefore that followeth Chriſt hath the light of life.
               What it is to haue the light of life, or to walke in the light, is plainely expreſſed. Ioh. 12. 35. 36. Yet a little 
                  Ioh. 12. 35. 36.
                  while the light is with you; walke while yee haue light, leaſt the darkneſſe come vpon you, &amp;c. Chriſt exhorteth heere to walke in the light, which ſignifieth two things.
               Firſt, to beleeue in him, as it is in the verſe following, while yee haue light, beleeue in the light, &amp;c. firſt, I ſay, to walke in the light ſignifieth to beleeue in Chriſt, our wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, redemption.
               Secondly, it ſignifieth the performance of all duties worthy of a Chriſtian, which is to haue our conuerſation according to our faith in him. For as the light of the day is giuen to vs to walke, and labour in our callings; euen ſo this ſpirituall light or day, ſhining in the Goſpel, is giuen to vs to walke, to labour, and to liue therein. And he that walketh not in the light of the Goſpell, walketh in darkneſſe, euen after the imagination of his owne corrupt heart, in the craftineſſe and deceiueableneſſe of fleſhly luſts. For the further clearing of this point▪ I will ſhew in what particulars this liuely &amp; ſauing knowledge of God in Chriſt, reuealed in the Goſpell, and applied to the elect by the ſpirit, is called Light.
               Firſt, the light is ſo glorious a creature, that no fleſhly eye can behold it, being in a ſubiect of nature, like it ſelfe, as the Sunne is: euen ſo the light of the Goſpell is ſo glorious, that the eye of mans reaſon and vnderſtanding cannot in the leaſt meaſure apprehend it.
               Secondly, the light is pleaſant, delightfull, cheerfull, comfortable, ioyfull, and hopefull; but in the abſence

of light there is heauineſſe, ſadneſſe, ſleepineſſe, penſiueneſſe, ſorrowfulneſſe, diſpairfulneſſe, fearefulneſſe: euen ſo, this ſauing knowledge placeth the ſoule in much more happineſſe, and felicity, affording true and euerlaſting pleaſures, true delights, true cheerfulneſſe, true comforts, true ioyes, true hope, which the miſeries and afflictions of this life cannot aboliſh or corrupt, ſeeing that they are the rayes and beames of the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, ſhining in vs. How inuincible, and vnquenchable is this ſauing knowledge, the light of life?
               Thirdly, the viſible light is the life of the materiall world, maintaining life, motion, ſenſe, in all creatures in the firmament aboue, and elements below, euen ſo this ſauing knowledge is the life of the ſpirituall world, that is, the companie of Gods elect, kindling ſpirituall life in them, giuing ſpirituall wiſedome, vnderſtanding, reaſon, ſenſe, motion, vnto them, whereby they differ from other men, more then other men differ from beaſts.
               Fourthly, as by the ſhining light all things are viſible to vs, and euery thing is diſcerned and knowne: euen ſo by this ſauing knowledge are all things made manifeſt to the eyes of our minds. For by vertue hereof, we diſcerne betweene good and euill, betweene holineſſe and prophaneneſſe, betweene true wiſedome and worldly craftineſſe, betweene the true worſhip of God, and idolatrie, or falſe-worſhippe, betweene ſincerity and hypocriſie, between the workes of light and darkneſſe, betweene Chriſt, and Antichriſt; between God and the Diuell, who can transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light, to blinde the eyes of Infidels, that they that want this knowledge diſcerne little or nothing at all between the one and the other, yea they altogether take the one for the other, like to the blind man that goeth confidently

the contrary way.
               Fiftly, as the light doth enlighten the bodily eyes, whereby we ſee to walke in the right way, and that without ſtumbling or falling: euen ſo this ſauing knowledge ſheweth the right way to eternall bliſſe, and guideth vs without falling into the pitfalls of Satan, and this wicked world.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

