
   
      
         
            A direction for the health of magistrates and studentes Namely suche as bee in their consistent age, or neere thereunto: drawen aswell out of sundry good and commendable authours, as also vpon reason and faithfull experience otherwise certaynely grounded. Written in Latin by Guilielmus Gratarolus, and Englished, by T.N.
            De literatorum et eorum qui magistratibus funguntur conservanda præservandaque valetudine. English
            Gratarolo, Guglielmo, 1516?-1568?
         
         
            
               1574
            
         
         Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02048
            STC 12193A
            ESTC S105793
            99841519
            99841519
            6107
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02048)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6107)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1025:01)
         
         
            
               
                  A direction for the health of magistrates and studentes Namely suche as bee in their consistent age, or neere thereunto: drawen aswell out of sundry good and commendable authours, as also vpon reason and faithfull experience otherwise certaynely grounded. Written in Latin by Guilielmus Gratarolus, and Englished, by T.N.
                  De literatorum et eorum qui magistratibus funguntur conservanda præservandaque valetudine. English
                  Gratarolo, Guglielmo, 1516?-1568?
                  Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.
               
               [172] p.   
               
                  In Fléetestreete, by William How, for Abraham Veale,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1574.
               
               
                  Translation of: De literatorum et eorum qui magistratibus funguntur conservanda præservandaque valetudine.
                  Translator's dedication signed: Thomas Newton.
                  Signatures: A⁴ [par.]²  B-X⁴.
                  Running title reads: A direction for health.
                  Identified as STC 12193 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A Direction for the Health of Magiſtrates and Studentes.
            Namely ſuche as bee in their conſiſtent Age, or neere thereunto: Drawen aſwell out of ſundry good and commendable Authours, as alſo vpon reaſon and faithfull experience otherwiſe certaynely grounded.
            Written in Latin by Guilielmus Gratarolus, and Engliſhed, by T. N.
            
            Imprinted at London, in Fléet-ſtreete, by William How, for Abraham Veale. 1574.
         
         
            
            
            To the Right honorable Maiſter Francis Walſyngham Eſquier, one of the Principall Secretaries to the Duéenes moſte excellent Maieſtie, and of hir Maieſties moſte honorable priuie Counſell.
            
               
                  IN Phyſicke, and curinge of the Sick (Right honorable) three things onely (ſayth Hippocrates) are to be cōſidered, the diſeaſe, the Pacient, and the Phyſicion, who in his office and function in that behalfe is the miniſter of Arte and the deputie of Nature. The Phiſicion and the diſeaſe do mutually oppugne one an other and ſtriue for maiſtrie. For the Phiſicions charge and only care is, and ought to be, to recure his Pacient with

Sickneſſe attaynted. The Sickneſſe cō
               trarywiſe employeth his whole deuoire and bendeth all his force to the deſtruction, ſpoyle and ruyne of the bodye whereinto he hath made breache and entraunce. Now, is the Patient (all this while) the Subiect and partie in whom this conflict and combate is darreigned: who if for his part, he do wiſelye and politikely reſiſt the ſomonce of his enemie Sickneſſe, directing the order of his diete and daylie vſage by the Dyal of the Phyſicions learned preſcription and counſell, and abſteine from thinges hurtfull and inconuenient by practizinge that which is holeſome and expedient, he is ioygned in commiſſiō and made (as it were) felowe in office with the Phyſicion agaynſt all raginge aſſaultes of Sickneſſe. Whereby they twaine being thus firmely confederate and linked together, the diſeaſe and Sickneſſe ſhal be eaſely driuen to a narowe exigent and glad to diſclaime his intereſt, and great hope is to be conceiued of the victorie and vpperhand.
            
               
As contrarywiſe, if the Pacient reuolte from the Phyſicion, wilfully refuſe and ſtubbornely diſobey his lore &amp; aduiſe, altogether framinge himſelfe to ſerue the humour and will of his Sickneſſe, litle hope and leſſe helpe is to bee expected of his recouery. For in flyinge to thone, and ſtartinge from thother, hee addeth great increaſe to the diſeaſe and prouoketh it to ſhew the vttermoſt effect of his tyrannicall force and qualitie vppon the bodie that is ſo willinge and readie euen at the firſte onſette and Alarme to ſurrendre. The Phyſition for the better atchieuing and compaſſing of his purpoſe, vſeth. iii. ſpeciall weapons or Inſtrumentes whereby and wherwith he worketh his feact &amp; ſupplanteth his aduerſarie, Diet, Medicine, or els ſome actuall woorkmanshippe of the hand called Chyrurgery. Which. iij. are in the Greeke, tearmed by apt and ſeuerall names more liuely and plainlye expreſſinge their properties natures &amp; operations, the fyrſte beynge called Diaetetice, the ſeconde Pharmaceutice,
               
the third and laſt Cheirurgice. Beſide theſe thre, is there none, for by whatſoeuer names any remedies for Sickneſſe or preſeruatiues for health are called by otherwiſe, they are to bee referred to one of theſe three neceſſarilie. For eyther they belonge to diete, either elſe they are too be done by receipt of medicinable drouges, potions and applications, or elſe finallye by the miniſterie and artificiall woorkemanshippe of the hand, called (as I ſaide) Chyrurgerie. The beſt and ſureſt of all theſe is Diet, the which oftentimes of it ſelfe alone is hable and ſufficient to cure the diſcraſed, and without which, the other twoo cannot well and conuenientlie to purpoſe be practized. Be the Chirurgian neuer ſo ſkilfull, yet vnleſſe the partie paſſioned vſe good reſpect in daylie diete, his cunninge hand not onely turneth to no profitable conſequence and effect at all, but rather many times the partie is thereby brought into further hazard and daunger. Medicines (bee their vertues neuer ſo ſoueraigne and

effectual) are not hable to helpe in ſuch extremities as they be employed vnto, if Diet be not reſpected accordingly, as Galen in his booke De Theriaca written to Pamphilianus moſt learnedly aduoucheth. Thus is Diet the ſafeſt, the ſureſt and the pleaſanteſt way that can be vſed and farre to be preferred before all other kindes of remedies, vnleſſe the diſeaſe be of ſuch vehemence quality, condition and extremitie that it ſeeme to requyre ſome great ſpeciall conſideration otherwiſe, and in time of ſickneſſe is not onely a ſpecial &amp; harmleſſe recuratiue, but alſo in time of health, the beſt and almoſt the onely preſeruatiue. And for that I ſaw the ſame in this litle Pamphlet, ſo clerkely and compendiouſly decyphered, I haue aduentured to deueſt him of his Latine weede, and after a homely ſorte forced into barbarous Engliſhe, whereby although I haue miniſtred large occaſion to the worlde, to thinke in mee ſome ſpice of preſumption and foly, for thus entermedlyng in an Art nothinge appendant

to my profeſsion, yet do I not miſtruſt but the equanimitie of the honeſter ſort, weighyng my goodwill and meanynge in the balance of reaſonable conſideration, will freendly diſpence with my ouerſight that way, &amp; ſuſpēd the ſiniſtre doome of all opinionatiue affection. Man is ſubiect to very many diſeaſes. Antiquitie reckened vp in a beadrolle, and regiſtred in ſundry of their Monuments left behinde them for our erudition and furtheraunce, three hundred and odde ſeuerall kindes of Maladies, beſide caſualties. Since when, there hath encreaſed and ſprong vp a freſh ſupply and ſwarme of many ſtrange and new diſeaſes earſt not knowen nor heard of, ſeemyng as it were to denounce defiance and continual warre to al the cunnyng that Phiſicions haue. VVhich by good counſel and aduiſe to preuent, or maturely to remooue and take away (as farre as Arte hath his limitation) deſerueth in mine opinion to him that beateth his brayne for others auayle in that behalfe no ſmall

commendation. This cauſed learned Homere, after he had taken a perfect ſuruey of man, and cōpared his ſtate with euery other kinde of Creature to geeue verdict and affirme that man among all Creatures was moſt miſerable. Silenus iudged it beſt, either not to be borne at all, or els moſt quickly and out of hand to dye and bee ridde out of worldely thraldome. Plini helde opinion that ſhortneſſe of life was the greateſt and beſt gift that euer the Goddes gaue vnto man. In Lucian alſo wee do reade, that Pythagoras after he had oftētimes chaunged his ſexe, and ſhape and dwelled (Pylgrymelike) in the bodies of all men, women, and fourefooted beaſtes of euery degree and callyng, playnely confeſſed that hee liued a great deale more pleaſantly, when he was a Frogge then when he was a King. And al theſe, although abſurd in report, yet in ſenſe iarred not far from a truth, if that heauenly Philoſopher had not otherwiſe aſſured our weake conſciences of an euerlaſtyng felicitie after this life, layde

vp in the ſtorehouſe of his mercy for ſo many as vnfeynedly repoſe all their affiance, truſt and ankreholde in him and do frame their liues and conuerſacion by the ſquyre and leuell of his ſacred woorde. Chriſtian it is therefore and natural alſo, euery one accordyng to his talent to helpe an other. And if Chriſtian examples were ſcantie and hard to finde (wherof there be almoſt infinite) yet let vs conſider and call to memorie the maner and rite that was among the olde Aegyptians and Aſsyrians, amonge whom, if any happened to fall ſicke, he was ſtreightways layde abroade in the high way, that euery man paſsinge by and beholdyng the maner of his ſickeneſſe, might tell, if he or any other of his acquayntaunce had euer beene diſcraſed with the like, and if he or they had ſo beene attached, what Medicine or thyng it was that had cured and healed them, that the ſame remedie might likewiſe be applied to the pacient ther languiſshing. By whiche meanes and way, it is thought, yea conſtantly aduou

ched by Hiſtoriographers that the Art of Phiſicke was at the firſt founde out and practyzed. This poore myte of mine, ſuch as it is, I humbly offre vnto your good worshippe as vnto him, whome the very Tytle and argument of the Booke did peculierlie inuite me to make choyſe of. Not doubtynge but euen as God and nature hath enfraunchyſed you with a ſpeciall priuiledge of wisdome, learnyng and dignitie aboue many thouſandes of others, ſo your Honorable diſpoſition will not eſtraunge, your worthie patrocinie to the ſymple doynges of other inferiours, who in a farre lower degree by ſuch honeſt waies as this, do ſeeke to in ſinuate themſelues into your acquayntaunce, and deſire to be enrolled in the Kalender of your moſte faithfull Suppliauntes. The Lorde perfourme and finish that in you whiche he hath richlie beegunne, and graunte vnto you a moſte healthfull mynde within a healthfull bodie euen ſo longe as natures boundes

may ſtretche to the aduauncement of his glorie and the commodite of this your Countrey, and after your Pilgrimage heere ended, mercifully conduct you to the ioyes of his glorious hierarchie.
            
               
                  Your H. moſt humble
Thomas Newton.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               The Preface.
               
                  THAT MY MEAnyng and ordre wherein I purpoſe in this lytle Booke to procéede, may bée to ye Readers the better notified: I thinke it not amiſſe, nor impertinent to our matter, firſt briefly to declare, how that the indications or tokens vſed in the ordre of Phiſicke, are namely taken and learned out of foure principall poynctes: either of the nature of health, and the cauſes thereof, or of a ſounde and healthie body: or of the nature of Sickeneſſe and the cauſes thereof, and the bodie that is diſcraſed: or els of the meane and Neutral body, that is neither perfectly whole, nor throughly ſicke, or of certayne thinges common to all men. Such indications and tokens as doo procéede of the nature of healthe, and of thoſe bodies that are ſounde, haue one common or general indication, notwithſtandyng bipartite &amp;

deuided into two partes, that is to witte, Conſeruation, and Preſeruation. Conſeruation, when the bodie is of it ſelf perfitly ſounde (as ſeldome is to bée ſéene) but Preſeruation is, when the bodie beginneth to bée enfeebled and like to fall into ſome infirmitie. And theſe two Indications and common medicines appertayne to vs in this preſent worke to bée diſcuſſed. For ſithens Conſeruation and Preſeruation belonge either to the Gymnaſticer or els to the Phiſition, and Gymnaſticke Arte, which is the trade of exerciſing men in feates of Actiuitie, is in theſe our daies antiquate and growen out of vſe, therefore they do onely appertaine to the Phiſicion, as Galene, not only in one little ſeuerall boke of this ſame Argument, but alſo in others of his workes plainly affirmeth. The other Indications gathered of the nature of the diſeaſe and the cauſes therof, and the bodie diſtempered and diſcaſed (which are thinges againſt Nature, whoſe generall and common Indication is Correction and Ablation) belong to the Phiſicion,

whoſe office is to cure diſeaſes. But the Indications of the Neutrall or meane eſtate betwene health and ſicknes, the cauſes of thinges not naturall, do ſhew, ſo that ſomtime Conſeruation and ſomtime Ablation therein muſt be vſed. And the cauſes not naturall are theſe: Ayre, meate and drinke, moouinge and reſte, Emptineſſe and Repletion, Sleape and watch and the affections of the minde: wherunto are added the Age, Temperature, Cuſtome, Arte, and the proper nature of euerie ſeuerall perſon. And they be called meane, becauſe they do ſomtimes the office of Conſeruation and ſomtimes of Ablation. Ablation when (for example) the Ayre is hurtfull to ſickneſſe: For it is either altered with contraries: or elſe cleane chaunged: if it be holeſome and profitable, we do conſerue it with his like, and thus do we in conſeruing them yt be whole. Theſe Indications are called commune, becauſe aſwell the Conſeruer or the Preſeruer of health, as alſo the Curer of diſeaſes vſeth them. I therefore meaning to entreate

vppon theſe two poinctes of Conſeruation and Preſeruation, will follow Hippocrates his order in the diſcourſe of thoſe fiue thinges, which are alſo auouched by Galene, in diuerſe of his workes and namely in his ſecond boke, De Tuen. Sanit. And theſe be they: Laboure or excerciſe, Meate, Drinke, Sleepe, and the acte of carnall copulation. Theſe beinge orderly, conueniently, and competently vſed, haue great power and efficacie to kepe a man in health, and in thē chiefely (as theſe two Graunde Capitaines and Auncient fathers of Phiſicks doe affirme) conſiſteth the whole poyſe and cauſe of healthineſſe. Vnto theſe fiue, (through God his aſſiſtaunce) I entend to annexe a Surpluſage and addicion of other thinges not naturall and ſuche as ſeeme néedefulll and expedient hereunto.
               Let vs therefore begin with the firſt whiche is Exerciſe, with humble praier to Almightie God, to further our attemptes, for his deare ſonnes ſake Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour. But

this by the way muſt we admoniſh the Readers, that for aſmuch as the natures and complexions of men be diuers, they alſo require a diuerſe trade and order in diete and exerciſe. And therefore ſayth 
                     Lib. 5. detuend ſa.
                   
                  Galene, euen as a ſhoomaker cannot make one ſhooe to ſerue euery mannes foote, ſo neither can a Phiſicion deſcribe and appoint any one generall order and dietarie for all maner of perſons. For there be ſome, whiche if they ſhould refraine exerciſe &amp; intermit their wonted Agitation but thrée daies, would ſtraitwayes be ſicke: againe, there be other ſome, which geue themſelues altogether to eaſe and reſt, and yet be healthfull and luſtie, and in other thinges, is like diuerſitie to be found. Now, whereas there is both diuerſitie in bodies, and alſo diuerſe trades of liuinge, it cannot be that any one abſolute way ſhould be appoincted to ſerue euerie nature in euerie facultie generally. And therfore to write a ſpeciall dietary for ſuch as either becauſe they be Seruitours and muſt geue their attendaunce on there maiſters and other

charge wherby they may not, or for ſuch as be continually ſo encombred with other affaires wherby they cānot obſerue any preciſe diet, it were but a thinge vaine and ſuperfluous. For their ſakes therefore that liue of them ſelues freely and are not enthralled or mancipated to the inconueniences aboueſaide, we haue compiled this treatiſe, how and in what ſorte they may liue a long life in proſperous health and welfare. Furthermore that which in euerie kinde is ſimple and faultleſſe ought alwaies to be preferred before all others. And in bodies that ſame is called ſimple and faulteleſſe, which is in a very good plight &amp; likinge: but in the trade of life, that is to be accompted beſt, which is free and not in ſubiection. For it behooueth that ſuch a one as would liue longe and neuer be attached with any Sicknes, ſhould be exempt and frée from all turmoiling troubles and publique affaires in the Common wealth, liuinge onely to himſelfe, cheriſhinge his body and tendringe his health. For there is no meanes to make

that immortall, which naturally was begotten &amp; created mortall, but to make the ſame to be of longe life and continuance, may be done and brought to paſſe. Galene ſaieth, that if he which hath his bodye in good likinge and temperature doe not intermeddle with the laborious cares of worldly buſines, but geeue himſelfe onely to quietneſſe and tender regarde of his owne health ſhall not at all (as farre as is poſſible) be arreſted and vexed with any maladie, neither be preuented with death vntill he haue liued a merueilous long age. But who is he not onely among vs Chriſtians, but euen among Paymms and Epicures, ſo blockiſhe and inſenſate, to thinke that he is borne only for himſelfe and for his oſone priuate commoditie without hauing any reſpect or regarde at all, either of matter or perſon in the ſocietie of humaine life? vnto ſuch as theſe (if any ſuche be) we doo not addreſſe theſe our preceptes, but vnto thoſe which at ſuch times as they haue cōuenient leiſure to ſurceaſſe from their charges and offices accordinge as theire

callinge and vocation is, doo meaſurably and for healthes ſake tender their bodies to thintent they may be the better able to continue about their néedefull and vrgent buſineſſe, and not to addicte themſelues to voluptuouſnes and bellychere, as though they beleeued there were non other life but only this fraile and tranſitorie life, and therfore ſecurely to wallow in their diſordered and laſciuious appetites, tendryng and cockeryng their wanton Carkaſes, for whoſe toothe and appetite Galen hath fully written their deſired diet in his ſixe Bookes, De tuend. Sanitate. Where he doth ſo copiouſly and ſo exquiſitely depaynt out the Arte, that I ſuppoſe a man ſhall vnethe finde any amonge a great many of Princes &amp; Potentates (who liue fréely without checke at their owne pleaſure and eaſe) that doth obſerue all his precepts in thoſe bookes mencioned. That whiche here wée write ſhall bée good and auayleable in maner to all Ages (Childehoode and extreame Oldeage excepted) wherin my counſayle is to all men, that what

euery man ſhall finde, and by experience prooue beſt to agrée with his nature, the ſame to vſe as neare as he may.
            
            
               Of Exerciſe and Labour.
               BEcauſe a greate part of Healthineſſe conſiſteth in a conuenient and oportune exerciſe of the Body, as Auicen and before him Hippocrates and Galen affyrme, néedefull it is to haue a diligent eye and conſideration therevnto. It is commended for many ſpeciall cauſes, The commoditie of Exerciſe &amp; labour but namely becauſe it beeyng duely and ſeaſonablie vſed, will not ſuffre the ſubſtance of ouermuch meate engendrynge Surphet to clotter and cōgele within the body, and alſo maketh the whole bodye light, nymble and actiue. Furthermore it kéepeth and merueilouſly ſtirreth vp naturall heate, reſtoreth the powers of the whole body, and ſtrengthneth all the vertues therof. Small and weake heate it encreaſeth, and dayly diſſolueth the ſuperfluities

by litle &amp; litle gathered within the body, and conuaieth the ſame to ſuch places from whence they be conueniently ſent out and expelled. It alſo maketh the membres a greate deale the apter to receyue nouriſhment, becauſe the filth and excrementall matter of the bodie is thereby ſcattered and auoyded. Moreouer it openeth the cunduites of the body, &amp; the courſes or paſſages wherin the bloud (hauyng therto the conuenient miniſterie of the naturall powers apoynted for that office) is eaſely receyued and conuerted into the ſubſtance of the member: whiche continual nouriſhment is moſt neceſſarie vnto mans life. For without this vertue, preſent death enſueth. This gayne and commoditie is alſo gotten by exerciſe, that by expellyng ſuperfluous humours it excuſeth a man from the vſuall receipt of Purgations and Medicines. For wée muſt be very circumſpect and take greate héede, Purgations dangerous &amp; hurtfull as Plato ſaith in Timaeo, that we mooue not the body with medicines, and ſpecially Electuaries ſoluble, if wée may otherwiſe

chooſe: becauſe although they doo purge, yet doo they inueterate: And although there be no poyſon in them (as in deede in the moſt of them there is) yet are they very paynefull to be taken inwardly, becauſe their office is contrarie to nature. For they draw away from the membres thoſe humours which the powers of nature doo draw to the ſame for a nouriſhment: and alſo becauſe beſide the ill humours whiche they draw out, they doo for the moſt part alſo draw out thoſe whiche be good, and the vitall ſpirites whiche maintayne and comforte life. It is not therefore without good cauſe, that the learned &amp; wyſe Doctours of this Arte haue written ſo muche and ſo diligently of Exerciſe, that men therby might ſhunne and auoyde many ſortes of diſeaſes, whiche els woulde aſſault the body, by reaſon of ſundry ſurphets, and gurmandiſe. For the ſubſtance remayninge after digeſtion and diſtribucion of the meate and drynke, (whiche Nature beynge ouercharged, is not able to concocte and euacuate, beynge eftſoones

encreaſed by eatyng and fillynge gorge vpon gorge, muſt néedes engendre diſeaſes: In this caſe to auoyde and eſchew the recept of purging medicines, which ſerue either to recure the body beynge thereby ſicke, or els to preſerue it from beyng ſicke, Exerciſe is a thynge moſt cōmodious as the cauſes of maladies doo beginne ſo dayly hereby to expel the ſame. Theſe noble writers therefore were of this mynde, that if the reſidue of theyr preceptes (whiche hereafter ſhal alſo by vs bee recited) were obſerued and kept, bodyly health might very well in this conſiſtent Age be conſerued, yea and not in this age onely, but alſo in the Age whiche goeth before, and the Age whiche commeth after, a verie few pointes beyng thereto either added or els altered. As for any particuler Regiment for old age, we do not in this place namelie purſue, becauſe beſide Galene it is alſo at large deſcribed &amp; ſet out by diuerſe 3. De tuen ſanit.
                   other learned Phiſicions, and namely in a ſeuerall booke penned and publiſhed by that famous and excellent Grayehead

                  Antonius Fumanellus of Verona.
               
               Thou ſhalt therefore (Gentle Reader) with al thy deuoyre and diligence, ſo vſe thy ſelfe, that thou mayeſt paſſe ouer and lead this flouriſhing time of thine age by thine owne wiſedome and our holeſome counſaile in health and welfare, to the glory of god and the profit of thy neighboure, for this age of Conſiſtence is the very flowre and prime of a mans life.
               And by this meanes ſhalt thou ſo doo, if thou géeue diligent eare to the ſounde counſayles of approoued Phiſicions, by mée in this litle Booke breefely noted, the chiefeſt whereof is Exerciſe. And therefore Galen playnly writeth that all ſuch of his fréendes as tooke diligent and ſpeciall regarde to Exerciſe were neuer ſicke. But becauſe not euery kinde of Exerciſe, nor euery time and hower is conuenient and méete for it, therefore will I declare bothe the time when it ſhould be vſed, and alſo the particuler kindes thereof.
               Then is it a fit time (ſaieth Auicenna) to exerciſe the bodie when there be no

ill humours in the ſame, leaſt exerciſe When exerciſe is to be vſed. Ill humours. by motion and calefactiō ſhould diſperſe the ſame through the bodie or cauſe them to decline and goe to ſome principall mē
                  bre and part of the bodie and ſo to putrefie. Alſo when there is in the Stomake or Bowelles no great quātitie of meate vndigeſted or humours crude &amp; rawe, leaſt inconuenience might enſue by the conueighance of them into the officiall members, before they be throughly boyled and concocted in the Stomake. Furthermore to go to the Stoole and exonerate nature before the time of exerciſe, is very holeſome. Hippocrates, his counſaile is, that a man ſhoulde laboure and 6. Epid. par. 4. Aph. 28. &amp; Gal. 5. de tuen. ſanita.
                   chafe himſelfe before his meale: and therfore I thinke it very vnholſome immediatetly after meate to vſe exerciſe, becauſe the vehement accidentes of the mind and the ſtronge mocions of the bodie do hinder digeſtion and cauſe Putrefaction, but an eaſie and ſoft walking, that the meate may the better and the ſooner deſcend to the loweſt part of the Stomake where the ſame is better concocted)

is not to bee miſliked but is thought to be very holeſome and expedient. Therefore when the meate is paſſed downe from the Stomake and the time approcheth eftſoones to eate, then is exerciſe both fit and profitable. In Somer, about the Sunne riſinge, leaſt otherwiſe the bodie ſhoulde be annoyed with a double heate: and in the beginnyng of the Sprynge, and Autumne aboute twoo howers after the Sunne ryſing, that the coldeneſſe of the mornynge may be auoyded. For as the heate of the noone time of the day is hurtful and noyſome, ſo is the colde of the mornyng, and namely in Autumne, and winter to be eſchewed. Notwithſtandynge a man may exerciſe himſelfe at home aſſone as he ariſeth. In winter Auicen counſelleth vs to exerciſe our ſelues within the houſe, or in ſome cloſe couert place, about noone, hauyng the ayre a litle warmed, for feare leaſt colde els ſhould take away or hinder that commoditie that exerciſe bryngeth: For nothynge is more hurtful to the vertue Regitiue then cold,

namely if it be much, and at ſuche time as the body is hoat. Now wheras there be ſundrie ſortes of exerciſe, I will onely recite here ſuche as I know to be beſt and moſt agreable for them, vnto whom I namely haue penned and written this compendie.
               And firſt to beginne with walkynge: which if it be ſoft, and not faſt, nor apace Walking is a weake exerciſe and may beſt be vſed in hoate moonthes, &amp; in the beginnyng of Autumne, for at thoſe times heate and drineſſe cheifly reigneth. And therefore the body ought not to be more inflamed and dried by ſtronge motion and exerciſe eſpecially in a Cholerique man. For truely there is no time in all the yéere, wherein the body ought leſſe to be exerciſed then in Sommer, and therefore in hoat Regions and Climates, a ſofte and gentle motion is a greate deale better, and more requiſite then ſtrong motion, becauſe nothyng doth ſo muche incende and enflame naturall heate, as laboure and moouing. Often and longe walking vſed without intermiſſion, is a ſtronge

exerciſe and meeter too be vſed in the Springe ſeaſon, becauſe exerciſe in the Springe time by good reaſon ought to be greater and ſtronger then in Sōmer. And therfore ſomwhat long deambulacion being pleaſāt withal, not weariſome, nor exceſſiue, is in my oppinion very méete and apt for this ſeaſon of the yéere. I meane, it muſt be ſomwhat longe, to thend it may with more facilitie reſolue ſuche ſuperfluities as aboute that time were gathered and congeled together duringe the winter precedinge: and I would haue it to be ſomwhat gentle and pleaſant, leaſt the bodies ſhould be ſet in a chafing heate with too much Agitacion and ſtirring, eſpeciallie of them that are of a hoate complexion. For this kinde of ſofte and longe continuinge exerciſe is moſt agreeable &amp; commodious to hoate and moyſt bodies. A ſtrong and vehemēt walking, eſpeciallie vp and downe highe and vnequall places, as manytimes to goe vp and downe a ladder, or a ſtiepe hill, till a man pant and fetche his breath thicke and often with difficultie, is a very

good and comendable exerciſe, &amp; beſt to be frequented in cold &amp; moyſt ſeaſōs.
               There is an other kinde of exerciſe, whereof Galene wrate, but not conuenient Teniſe and ball play for ſuch as be graue perſonages and men muche buſied with waightie affaires, or for ſuch as haue not their heads in good temperature, which is called the Teniſe. In which kinde of paſtime, all members and partes of the body are equallie mooued, but it is hurtefull to the head by reaſon of often ſtowpinge: and therfore I counſell all them that delight to playe thereat, to ſtand holdinge theire heades vpright, whiche may be eaſely done, by ſtriking and receauing the balle with a raquet.
               There is an other kinde of pleaſaunt exerciſe fitteſt to be vſed in the countrey in ſeaſonable and tempeſtiuious times of the yeare, called Riding. It is highlie Riding. to be commended and is good for the head ſtomacke and intrayles, wherby men in the olde time got both health &amp; pleaſure.
               That exerciſe whiche Auicen teacheth to draw and bring down humours

from the head to the lower partes of the body is very profitable and to be done in this ſorte folowyng: Tie and make faſt Hanging by the handes a ſtronge roape to ſome Beame or poſt, and through the ſame roape put a good bigge wodden Cudgell ouerthwart, and takyng holde with your handes at bothe endes of the Cudgell, lift vp and poyſe your body ſo, that your feete touche not the grounde, and mooue your legges to and fro, hangyng ſtill by your handes.
               But the bodie muſt be very well purged, leſt when the ſuperfluous humours be drawen downe to the lower partes, there be engendred an Abſceſſe, which is ſome impoſtume or courſe of euill humours to ſome one parte of the body.
               As for wreſtling and daunſing, which be accompted amonge vehement exerciſes (becauſe they be nothyng agréeable and ſitting for a ſage Magiſtrate nor for a ſerious Student) I haue nothynge to ſay: but this by the way I may not omit, that thoſe perſons which féede vpon groſſe meates, and ſuche repaſt as bringeth ſtronge nouriſhment, may vſe vehementer

exerciſe and ſtronger ambulations, as running, wraſtling, hunting, quoytes, handeball, and to be breife all ſuche exerciſe as beſt agréeth with theyr nature, which may brynge difficultie in fetchyng the breath, augment heate and humecte the ſkynne and exteriour parte of the body, with a thin ſubtile ſweate.
               For quicke and nimble exerciſe maketh the body leane and ſlendre, and the contrarie maketh it groſſe and thicke: much exerciſe drieth the bodie, but meane and conuenable maketh it fat and corpulent. Notwithſtandyng, for them that vſe a ſlender diet and ſpare féedyng, a ſhorter ambulacion and ſmaller walkynge will ſuffice. Now, there be ſome whiche be of a very hoat temperature &amp; complexiō which ought not at all to be exerciſed: for ſuch perſons, a moderate walkyng, baynyng or a gentle Fricaſie and rubbynge Fricaſie ſhalbe fully ſufficiēt. Al ſuch are ſlender, leane and very Cholerique. And this is euermore to be noted, ye a man muſt vſe ſuch moderation in his exerciſe, that be get not a laſſitude or wearineſſe therwith,

but aſſoone as he perceaueth the ſame to come vpon him, it were beſt for him to deſiſt and leaue of. For the bodie with all his partes ought ſo to be exerciſed, that excremental matter by idleneſſe and reſt, be not gathered. But when you beginne to ſweate, and the exerciſe ſéemeth not to be ſo pleaſant as it did before, ceaſſe and leaue of, wypyng away the ſweate from your bodie: then again after that you haue a litle pauſed and reſted your ſelfe, the body muſt be refreſſhed. For in exerciſe aſwell as in meate and drinke and all other thinges, there ought to be a conuenient meaſure vſed, ſo that the thyng it ſelf be neither ouercharged with to much, nor yet debarred from that ſtinte and ſufficiencie that is néedefull and requiſite, becauſe by exceſſe, the powers are enfeebled and diſſolued, and by want or defect, there is ſo muche of the vtilitie abated, as there lacketh of due ſufficiencie. For our powers are muche ſtrengthened and chéered, if with moderate and fit exerciſe they be refreſhed and cheriſhed. Now let vs

bréeifly declare the kindes of ſmall and gentle exerciſes, whiche (notwithſtandyng) to the health of the body are néedfull and expedient. The firſt ſorte wée haue heretofore declared, that is to ſay a ſwéete and ſofte walkynge.
               Then there are Fricaſies or Rubinges, whiche are the exerciſes of them that be ſickly. For vnto them that be in perfit health, they are not ſufficient, as Plato moſt elegantly, and after him Galen affirmeth. But we adiudge and thinke thē to be very good both to mūdefie the head and diuert the fumes therof to the vttermoſt and extreame partes, and alſo to open the pores and conduites of the bodie therby to extenuate and expell ſubtill humours. In olde time, men vſed fricaſie and vnction before and after euerie kind of exerciſe: before, to the end that the paſſages and pores of the bodie beinge opened by fricaſie, the humours might haue more eaſie egreſſe: and after, beecauſe the matter, which did exude &amp; come out, might be wiped away from the ſkin, and that which remained in the fleſhe, might

be extenued and diſſolued, which order in my oppinion is not to be miſliked. And therfore my counſaile is, that before thou ariſe out of thy bed, either to rubbe or els to make ſome bodie els to rubbe, with warme hands or ſom warme linnen clothes, thy backe, breaſt and bealy eaſely &amp; ſoftlie, and thy armes and legges hardlie and ſtronglie, but ſuche partes as thou canſt reache and come vnto, vſe to rubbe thy ſelfe. For this fricaſie and rubbinge concocteth crude humours, and alſo nouriſheth and comforteth the whole bodie. And if thou chaunce to ſweate, cauſe it with a ſoft rubbing and fricaſie to be wiped of Hippocrates ſaith that hard fricaſie doth binde and conſolidate the bodie, ſofte doth looſe and mollifie, muche doth extenuate and diminiſhe fleſhe, meane augmenteth and maketh it wax bourlie. It is good alſo when you gee to bedde if your head be heauie or payned with the murre or reume, to rubbe and wringe hard your legges and handes, for by ſuch meanes the vapours that aſcend vpward are deriued and brought downeward.

Alſo fricaſie and rubbing the whole body in the eueninge, is profitable for them that be throughly wearie, or with driues to much moleſted, or with the Atrophie &amp; conſumptiō pined and troubled: which being done, there ſhould enſue an oyntement or perfuſion of temperate oyle (if the auncient and laudable cuſtome of vnction were not antiquated and growē out of vſe as many other good thinges are) for it helpeth to the ſpéedines and velocitie of frication, it looſeth and ſuppleth the members that be ſtiffe and indurate and it comforteth and mollifieth the mē
                  bers that are wearied.
               To be rowed vppon the water in a Rowing. wherrie or barge is an exerciſe gentleſt and eaſieſt of all other. Now ouer and beſide the fricaſies aforeſaide, let vs particulerlie recite thoſe motions that do exerciſe not all, but certaine partes of the Exerciſe for diuers partes of the bodie bodie. To ſhoote in a longe Bowe, to pitche or throwe great Stones or any other heauie thinges ſittinge or ſtandinge is the exerciſe of the armes and other partes next vnto them, albeit the whole

bodie may ſeeme to be therin exerciſed, In readinge, to ſpeake at the firſt with a ſofte voice, and afterward to ſpeeke lowder and lowder is the exerciſe of the Tongue, Breaſt, Throate and Lunges yea it is good for the ventricle or Stomacke alſo. But the exerciſe of the heade muſt verie carefullie be looked vnto, becauſe How the head muſt be vſed. amonge al the partes of the bodie the braine is the coldeſt, and therfore his naturall heate muſt with all diligent heede bée conſerued and kept, that it bee not diſtempered nor oppreſſed with the multitude and abundance of ſuperfluous humours. Therfore euerie daye when thou ariſeſt, after that thou haſt beene at the ſtoole, rubbe thy head with a cleane drie linnen cloath ſomwhat warme, frō the foreparte of thy head backewarde 
                     ••
                   the hinderparte, and at the firſt, let thy fricaſie be ſmall and eaſie, but afterward harder and faſter. Then kembe it with a cleane combe, beginnynge at the former and vpper part of the head bringing the Combe backeward, and then againe mundify and make it cleane with linnen

clothes as is aforeſayd. And if the ſame clothes be a litle perfumed with poudre of Lignum Aloes, or Gelouers and drie Roſes, their vertue is a greate deale the more to helpe the brayne and comforte the ſences. Certes thou ſhalt féele a merueilous effect for the healthineſſe of thy head if thou vſe this ordre of fricaſie and combyng. For therby naturall heate is excited and ſtirred vp, the pores are opened, (which beyng ſtopped, ſuperfluous matter and humours are retayned and conſequently the brayne payned and affected) but beyng opened, the ſame il humours and fumes are propulſed and diſperſed, and the brayne is made ſincere, ſtronge and healthfull. There is an opinion ſetled in the heades of many now adaies and eſpeciallie amonge the commō ſorte, that it is not good for the head to be waſſhed, alledgynge for their proofe an olde ſayinge, common almoſt in euery mans mouthe, neuertheleſſe for yt moſte parte vntrue, which is this: Waſh thy hands often, thy feete ſeldome, but thy 
                  Washing of the hed. 
                  head neuer. Vnto whom I do bréeifly

make this aunſwere, that ſuch perſons ought namely to waſh their heds, which haue a moyſt brayne, or ſuche as loue to haue their heare grow longe, becauſe the inwarde ſuperfluities whiche nature would expell, cannot haue paſſage to euaporate and vente out, but be retayned ſtill, by reaſon that the pores be ſtopped with filthe that lieth at the rootes of the heare next the head, which filthe by conuenient and orderly waſſhyng is taken away and clenſed. And for this cauſe Auicen affyrmeth that it is not good to ſuffre the heare of the bead and beard to grow longe, becauſe they gather and retayne muche groſſe filthe and baggage, ſtoppyng the pores about the rootes, if they be not waſſhed away. To theſe namely, and to all others generally that vſe waſſhynge, Auenzoar géeueth in charge to be waſſhed with warme water or Lie, and if you put into the ſame water or Lie, ſo it be not to ſtronge, a ſmall handfull of drie Roſes, and Lignū Aloes, and a litle Camomile or Betony for ſuch as he ſomwhat of a colde nature

it is very wholeſome. He that hath a weake head, colde and moyſte, and his memorie thereby empayred, ſhall in my litle booke of the Arte of Memorie finde moſte ſouerayne, ſinguler and eaſie remedies to ſatiſfie his deſire. As ſoone as the head is waſſhed, it muſte diligently and ſpéedely be wiped and dried with warme drie linnen clothes, and well looked vnto, yt it catche no harme through colde or wynde. But better it is, not to be waſſhed at all, eſpecially in winter or often, and namely for ſuche as vſe to be ſhauen and notted, but the Fricaſies and combynges aforeſayde muſt duely be vſed, becauſe (beſide the aforenamed helps that they bryng) they merueilouſly preſerue the ſight. The proper and peculier exerciſe of the ſight is to beholde and looke vpon ſmall letters and lightſome The exerciſe of the ſight. thinges: foreſéene, that a meaſure therin be adhibited, notwithſtandynge Auicen ſuppoſeth that ſmall and confuſe figures &amp; ſubtile or litle letters are hurtfull to the ſight and not to be looked on.
               The exerciſe of the Hearyng is to heare Hearing
                  
pleaſant ſowndes, yea and ſometimes great clappes and hideous noyſe: but in any wiſe aſwell in this as in all others, too vehement and ſtronge obiects muſt be warely and circumſpectly eſchued.
            
            
               Of Bathes.
               BAynyng ſometimes ſupplieth the office Bathes or Baines of Labour, and ſtandeth in ſtéede of exerciſe, beyng either ayrie or watrie in ſwéete water, for of Mineral waters, whiche wée terme Bathes I will ſay nothing, ſithens they rather ſerue for curyng of diſeaſes. They muſt vſe the ayrie Bayne faſtyng, that are corpulent and groſſe or haue abundance of concocte ſuperfluous humours and excrements: but ye watrie better accordeth with them that are ſlendre, whoſe vſe is diuers and manifolde, accordynge as the degrée of heate is more or leſſe, whereof Galen writeth thus: Swéete warme waters if they be temperate, their vertu is hoate and moyſte, if they be well and hoate,

their vertue and force is moyſt and cold, but if they be hoater then they ought to be, theyr ſtrength is in déede hoate, but not accordyngly moyſt. For they cauſe the body to ſhiuer and quake, and purſeth together the ſubtile pores thereof, in ſo much that it can neither be humected 3. De Tu ſanit. ca. 3 outwardly with acceſſe of humour, neither ſende out any of the excrementall matter that is within. Furthermore he ſaieth, that Bayninge orderlye vſed, mollifieth and ſoupleth harde and indurate fleſhe, and fetcheth out all the excrementes and liquide matter that cleaneth and adhereth after digeſtion to the exteriour parte of the bodie. They that haue fat and corpulent bodies or elſe bée replete with aboundance of humours, may ſoone take harme by vſing diſorderlie and vnduelie this bayning, but if they be firſt purged and ridde from them they may vſe the benefit thereof, becauſe it doth humect and moiſten the pores and paſſages, and maketh the fumoſities too bée diſpelled and ſent out. But as in all other thinges moderate vſe

is alwaies to be preferred before immoderate, euen ſo fareth it by bayning. For a man may not be ouer haſtie in aduenturinge to vſe it, eſpeciallie if the partie that is minded to be bained, be troubled with many humours gathered throughe continuall cruditie and vndigeſtion, or haue not longe afore enfarced himſelfe with plentie of meate vnboyled and vncocted in the ſtomake, whiche crude humours being within the bodie (by reaſon of the vehement force of heate) cauſe obſtructions. In very colde ſeaſons, and in Sommer time they ſhoulde alſo be forborne. For in winter the humours beinge ſtirred and diſquieted and a cold ſodeinlie ſucceding, they are driuen to ſom neceſſarie part of the body, &amp; there bréede diſeaſes and great annoyaunce. And aboute midſomer when heate chieflie raigneth and of itſelfe reſorteth to the exteriour partes, Bayninge doth diſperſe ſo much of the ſame heate as is yet remaininng, &amp; by yt meanes much weakeneth the inward powers. And vnleſſe the age and place of man ſéeme otherwiſe to require,

they are at this time a great deale more to be eſchewed. In déede no man doubteth but baines vſed at due and ſeaſonable times, help the bodie verie much (for nothinge doth ſo well concocte and driue away il humours &amp; corrupt iuyce as ſleepe after bayning) but I ſay that the vſe therof is very hurtfull, if they be vſed at inconuenient times and when they ought chieflie to be refrained. Now as concerninge waſhing in colde water, I do ſay that it is vtterly to be forborne of all ſuch as are not therto accuſtomed, as being more hurtfull then profitable, vnleſſe vrgent occaſion of great heate and luſtie youth do otherwiſe ſeeme to craue it. But he that would vſe it, muſt be ſlender of bodie and ſomwhat of a colde conſtitucion, for it is apter to pearce into ſuche colde within the bodie and inner partes. It bringeth al the humours in a maner to one place of the bodie and maketh the ſinewes and muſcles ſtiffe and numme, and not nimble or readie to mooue, yea and ſometimes it bringeth a man into diſtemperaunce and paſſions

much worſe then theſe, if it be not verie aduiſedly vſed. And amonge all others, a healthy and ſound bodie ſo long as it is in growing and waxinge, muſt not be waſhed in cold water, leaſt his groweth and waxing be thereby rebuked and hindered. But when he is come to his full growthe, then may he acquainte himſelf with colde bathes, becauſe the bodie is therby cooled and ſtrengthened, and the ſkinne made harder and thicker. And the fitteſt time thereto is the beginninge of Sommer, that ere winter come, by frequent cuſtome, it may not turne to any hurtfull diſtemperaunce of the bodie, and let it beginne in a verye hoate daye the place where it is vſed beinge likewiſe hoate.
            
            
               Of Meates
               NOw let vs ſay ſomwhat of meate and drinke. And herein I do firſte géeue the to vnderſtand, that it is beſt and holſomeſt to vſe meates that be

ſimple. For ſimple meate by good reaſon is moſt profitable, but many and ſundry diſhes and diuers ſortes of Viande and Cates is moſt hurtfull and a great enemie to health. Our predeceſſors whiche liued very long without Sicknes were wont (as Galen &amp; Auicen affirme) to eate at one meale fleſhe, and at another bread onely. Yet would I not wiſhe thée to accuſtome thyſelf to one onely meate ſpecially if thou be in youth: for Galen expounding one of the Aphoriſmes of Hippocrates ſaieth: Such thinges as we haue long times beene vſed vnto, yea although they be not of the beſt nouriſhing meates, are not ſo daungerous and hurtfull as other thinges are which in deede be far better, wherunto we haue not be accuſtomed. We muſt therefore (ſaieth he) now and then altre our diet, and vſe to eate ſuche meates as before we vſed not. Neither ought we to bind ourſelues to any one kinde, leaſt if we ſhould (perchaunce) be driuen at any time to change that cuſtome, we ſhould ſtraightwaies therupon fall ſicke. And Cornelius Celſus,
                  
counſaileth ſuche as be in health, to vſe their ordinarie fare and plaine vſuall diet. But to eſchue &amp; forbeare much varietie of meates is vndoubtedly bothe better and wholeſomer, becauſe the ſtomacke 
                     
                        Meates moſt commendable Sundrie ſortes of meates at one time eaten are not holeſō.
                     
                     
                        Meates moſt commendable.
                     
                   is to muche ſet a woorke and laboureth greatly in the digeſtyng &amp; concoctyng of ſundrie meates at once. It is thought good (and ſo it is in déede) to mingle moyſt with drie, colde with hoat, and hoat with colde, ſwéete and toothe ſome with ſower and eigre. But thoſe meates whiche be in the meane or mediocritie of all exceſſe are moſt commendable. Of whiche ſorte is Breade, made of cleane corne, ſufficiently leauened, well moulded and moderately baked: alſo the fleſh of Hennes and Capons, Pheſants, Partriches, Woodcockes, yonge Pigeons, Blackbirdes, Thruſhes, Turtles and ſuche like ſmall byrdes: Semblably, ſuche fiſhes as bréede amonge Rockes, and ſtones, or aboute the Sea ſide, and ſuche as in taſte are neither vnpleaſant and vnſauerie, nor yet clammy and vnctuous, of whom heareafter we will particulerly

ſpeake. Notwithſtandynge meates muſt be vſed accordyng to the diuerſitie that is in bodies: for they that haue very melancholique bloud, muſte vſe moyſte and hoate meates, they that be Cholerique muſt vſe colde and moiſt. But phlegmatique perſons muſt eate ſuch meates as haue vertue to drie and calefie. Furthermore the bloud is made What maketh good bloode. moſt perfit and pure by vſing moderate exerciſe and ſuche meates as engendre good iuice, beyng eaten at due and ſeaſonable howers, and in ſuch quantitie as is required and by moderate and tempeſtiuious drinkyng. And in meates, nothyng ſo wel encreaſeth and maketh good bloud, as for them to be throughly concocted and perfitly boiled in the ſtomake. For thereby is more eaſely finiſhed, the ſecond concoction whiche is in the veines and Liuer, and alſo admitteth the thyrde digeſtion which is in ye particuler membres and partes which be nouriſſhed. A due ordre therefore is to be kepte in meates: as for example: that whiche is Ordre ſlippery and moyſt before that whiche is

ſtipticke and harde: agayne that whiche is more eaſely concocted before yt which is of ſlow digeſtion: as potched Egges before fleſhe and ſuche like. Likewiſe ſuche as are of theyr owne nature ſoone corrupted, as Mylke and moyſt fruites, as wee ſhall hereafter more largely declare. For when meate of eaſie digeſtion is eaten after that whiche is ſlowly concocted, it is holden backe, and ſtopped by the meate of ſlow digeſtion before taken that it cannot paſſe into the entrayles, &amp; therfore the meate of eaſie digeſtion beyng perfitly concocted remayneth and is forcibly kept in the ſtomacke longer then it ought to be, whereby it is made very apt to corruption, whiche to health is very hurtfull and a great hindrance. But there be ſome meates betwéene whem there is but ſmall difference of digeſtion, as between a henne and a ſucking Calfe, a Chicken and a Kidde, the fleſh of a big olde Calfe and a younge Bullocke, or Steere, in ſuch reſpectes as theſe where the difference is ſo ſmall, it ſkilleth not greatly, if they whiche be ſomwhat hard

to digeſt, be eaten before other of ſōwhat lighter digeſtion. This (vnleſſe I be much deecaued) was the opion of Galen, and not without good conſideracion. For heauie meates and ſuch as be of ſlow digeſtion, require a ſtronger and greater power digeſtiue. And all men (without exception) doo confeſſe and know that the lower part of the Stomacke or Maw in the act of concoction is ſtronger then the vpper and middle parte is. Therefore meates of eaſie digeſtion ought to be taken before thoſe, which doo differ ſo farre from them in eaſineſſe of concoction as the power of the loweſt parte of the ventricle differeth from the firſt and middle: which difference ought to be referred to the diſcretion and iudgement of the ſkilfull Phiſicion. Thus may the fleſh of a Bullocke be eaten before the fleſh of a bigge calfe, and the fleſh of a ſuckinge kid or yonge tender calfe after veale of a calf of bigger growthe: thus alſo may yonge Pigeons, Hennes, and Capons be well eaten before Partriches and Chickens. Neither néedeth a man to feare leaſt thei

ſhould be corrupted in his ſtomacke, becauſe they are not eaſely corruptible, and alſo becauſe there ſéemeth to be ſuch proporcion of digeſtion in a maner betwéen theſe meates for facilitie or difficultie of concoction, as is betwéen the vpper and the loweſt part of the ventricle, and therfore they may at one and the ſame time be concocted in the ſtomack, becauſe meates of hard digeſtion are ſent to ye lower and ſtronger parte, and they of lighter digeſtion to the weaker.
               And alſo this muſt not be omitted, that we muſt altogether abſtaine from crude and rawe meates, and take beede that al our Cates be cleanlie dreſſed, well ſeaſoned and throughlie boyled or els roſted. But in any wiſe we muſt beware yt we do not infarce &amp; pamper our ſelues with to muche, and that we do not irrit
                     •
                   our Stomack and prouoke an appetite with fine Iunkets and delicious Sauees. For meate exceſſiuelie ingurgitate and eaten althoughe it be of good iuyce and nouriſhemtnt Raw mear commonly engendreth and breedeth cruditie, laſkes and vomit. Againe,

leſſe then neceſſitie and nature requireth, is the cauſe why the bodie is not nouriſhed, but weakened and enfeebled, and made vnhable to do his buſines as it did befeore, becauſe the bodie is emptie The hurt of too much meat The hurt of too litle and not able to diſtribute ſufficient and conuenable nouriſhement to the ſpirite. For euen as Repletion hindereth nouriſhment and rebuketh nature and the poore Animall: ſo all maner of abſtinence cauſeth vomites, hurteth the ventricle, reſolueth the powers of the bodie and encreaſeth ill humours. And euen as an ill diet bringeth heauines and drowſie lumpiſhenes to the bodie and a dulnes to the wit and ſenſes: ſo a conuenient and orderlie diet quickeneth the ſpirites and reuiueth the minde, making it more actiue and couragious to know and practize vertuous operations.
            
            
               Of Bread.
               NOw let vs particularlie declare the ſeueral kindes of meate and drink,

and firſt let vs begin with bread, whiche (as Nouius affirmeth) is called in latine Panis, a Paſcendo, of feedinge. The beſt Breade is made of fine wheate flower Breade. cleane boulted from all branne and other baggage, which grew on holeſome groūd ſufficiētly leauened, moderately ſeaſoned with Salte, well moulded and throughlie baked, but not burned in the ouen. Auenzoar would that bread ſhoulde be eatē the ſame day yt it is made whē it is colde, which then (as he thinketh) greatlie conſerueth health, and after it be a day olde, he ſaieth it ſhould not be eaten, becauſe it hath loſt his tymperatenes of complexion and the more it is hardened, the heauier is it to be concocted. Auicen his opinion is, that bread ought not to be eaten before it haue ſtoode one night, and as for hoate bread he vtterlie diſcommē
                  deth it, ſaying that it ought to be eſchewed, becauſe it is not (as he there affirmeth) receptible of nature, and alſo by reaſon of his warmenes cauſeth thirſte, and by reaſon of his vaporous moyſture ſwymmeth in the Stomacke, and is

longe ere it paſſe and deſcend into the entrailes. It doth alſo ſend an vnnaturall heate into the ſtomacke or ventricle, whereby it is checked, maiſtered and damnified. Therefore hoate bread muſt be eſchewed, and alſo in ſommer when it is aboue two dayes olde, and in winter after three daies age, it ought to be forborne. And we muſt be very circumſpect in the fanning and making cleane of ſuch graine and ſéedes as wée ſhall afterward eate. For of this let vs be well aſſured, that although, we do not preſentlie féele Breade corne muſt be well clenſed &amp; picked before it be grinded. the dailie harme that by little and little encreaſeth (vnperceaued of vs for a while becauſe of the ſmalenes thereof, yet notwithſtandinge in continuance of time, it bringeth much inconueniences and diſquietnes. And at length burſteth out to our great paine. Hauing ſpoken of bread which Homer termeth the pithe and marow of man and the ſacred Scriptures affirme to corborate mans hart, and nature, let vs now likewiſe make the like diſcourſe of wine, which of the ſame Authour is called the Strength of man and

in holie writte is ſayed to cheere vp the minde and make the hart mery.
            
            
               Of VVine.
               WYne hath great vertue and ſundrie Wyne. ſinguler effectes come by drinking thereof, as not onelie Ariſtotle &amp; Galen but other phiſicions of later daies haue noted and namelie the abſolute and learned man Andrew Matheolus Senenſis, 
                  
                     Com. Dioſ. lib. 5. ca. 7. out of whoſe worke I do not excerpe and alledge any thing, leaſt I ſhould vainely ſéeme to make a Commentarie out of Commentaries, and like a vaine glorious perſon ſéeke to trimme vp my ſelf with other birdes feathers, ſpeacially ſith his Bokes are to all perſons and in all places to be had. And brieflie to declare my opinion, I ſay that wine moderately dronken clarifieth the Spirit &amp; maketh it luſtie, and lightſome and of competent The profits that come by moderate drinking of wyne. ſubſtance, it nouriſheth and comforteth it, and greatlie refreſheth the minde, wherfore not without good reaſon it is

endued with great power and ſinguler vertue to letifie and conſerue nature.
               But being immoderatelie dronken and ingluuiouſlie ſwilled (as now adaies many The harme that commeth by the contrarie. vſe to do) it is moſt hurtfull and the ſpecial cauſe of many gréeuous diſeaſes. For it endamageth and hurteth ye braine and all the ſinewes &amp; ſenſes, and doth too much humect and moyſture the whole bodie. Therfore it muſt be temperately dronken and good regarde had that it be of the beſt kinde, growinge in the beſt ſoyle, &amp; here I will reken vp ſome kinds of the beſt, for all I neither can declare neyther will the breuitie of this ſmall compendie permitte.
               That wine is beſt, whiche is neither to olde nor to new, but meane betwéen bothe, well fined and cleare, reddiſh or of a citron couler, pleaſant in taſt and of a ſwéete ſmell, of ſuche reliſh (I ſay) as in taſt ſéemeth neither to be very tarte and ſharpe, nor yet very doulcet &amp; ſwéet. For thynges ſharpe and pontique, yea and ſwéete alſo do quickly cauſe obſtructions: the one becauſe they bynde, the other

becauſe they paſſe into the veines and members vnconcocted, of which ſort ſwéete wine is one of the chiefeſt. In ſo muche that Auerrois (althoughe he be a man not of the greateſt aucthoritie in phiſicke) affirmeth wine to be drawen of the Liuer vndigeſted euen aſſoone as it is dronken. But the drinkinge of white wine being ſubtile and cleare and ſpeciallie White wyne. in ſommer time, as it doth vnto other famous and expert doctours in phiſicke ſo alſo vnto me doth it ſeeme verie good and commendable. For this is it, that Galen the prince of phiſicions by actuall trial and experiment (yea Auerrois ſaieth the ſame alſo) affirmeth that he found in diuerſe places of Italie, wherin was to be found neither ſowernes, ponticitie, ſtipticitie, bitternes nor Swéetenes, which alſo engendred no inflacions and fumoſities, and this wine onelie is without all ſuch daungers and inconueniences as commonlie happen &amp; chaunce after the drinkinge of other wines or of water. And therfore this wine is moſte agréeable and fitte for ſtronge and mature

age or the age of conſiſtencie, and for hoate complexions and namelye in Sommer for many cauſes, but chieflie becauſe it cauſeth no headache but rather driueth it and taketh it awaye if it come throughe heate of the ſtomacke. Néere vnto it in goodnes is an other wine which in the olde time was named Ablutum, and in Italie (ſpeciallie in Lumbardie) it is commonlye termed by the Ablutum or the wine of Auicen. name of Auicen his wine. And in this maner is it made, Take three partes of Muſte and one parte of water, boyle thē together till the fowerth part be waſted. Other ſome vſe, when the Grapes be trodèn and the iuyce wringed out, to put water to it, in proporciō according to the ſtrength and power of the wine, and thē after a fewe dayes to put it in veſſelles. But when the ſeaſon of the yere is ſomwhat colde: or when the temperature of the bodie by reſon of age or otherwiſe is faint and weake, Claret and Citron couloured wine (if no impediment and cauſe to the contrarie) is beſt and to be preferred before any other.
               
                  
Whiche if it be endued with any fumoſitie, How to alaye wine. the ſame may be qualefied and alayed with water leaſt it ſtuffe the head, and cauſe thirſt. Yet may it not be to much alayed and made thinne, for then doth it debilitate and weaken the ſtomacke, cauſing many fumoſities in the ſame: but beyng moderately alayed and tempered it is muche prayſed of Galen, becauſe it qualefieth humours, exciteth and ſtirreth vp naturall heate and without harme pearceth the membres.
               Certes euery one of theſe kinds of wine are greatly avayleable to them that therwith be acquainted and accuſtonied.
               For it ſtrengthneth vertue, expelleth Choler and Melancholy by prouokynge of vrine, quickly ripeth the good iuice and humours wherewith the body is humected, and maketh the ill humours to deſcend from the vpper partes to the lower, whereby the head is eaſed and holpen.
               But in drinkynge of Wine, there muſt be no leſſe conſideration had of the countreys, times and exerciſes, then of the affections, appetites and complexions of

men, that wée maye conſerue them od
                     •
                  
                  rate with that ye is agréeable therto, &amp; amende the immoderate by their contraries. Therefore (as before I haue noted) to colde and drie complexions, the claret and ſwéet Wine (becauſe it is verie hoate) is beſt, and the contrarie ſerueth beſt for hoate temperatures. Furthermore thoſe wines are to be forborne What wines are to be eſchued. whiche be either very olde or very new: becauſe the one heateth vnmeaſurably, and the other neuer a whit, ſo longe as thei be new, which not onely helpeth nothing to digeſt the meate, but is itſelfe rather very ſlowly and with much a doe decocted. Now, I thinke I néede not to counſell men to refrayne drinkynge of Wyne when they be faſtyng, or before wine muſt not be drō
                     ken with a faſting ſtomacke. they haue eaten ſōwhat, becauſe I write to ſuch men as be ſobre and modeſt and not to toſſepottes and drunkards. For beyng drunken at any ſuche times, commonlye bryngeth many inconueniences and diſeaſes procéedyng of Fleame, and namely the Apoplexie in ſuche caſe is much to be feared. After meales alſo to

drinke much is hurtefull, becauſe it maketh Much drinking after meate is to be forborn the meate in ye ſtomacke, to deſcend before it be ſufficiētly boiled &amp; concocted. For while ye meate is in digeſting in the ſtomack, we ought to refrain much drinking. But after yt the meate is deſcended frō the mouth of ye Stomack &amp; is ſufficientlie concocted Auicen permitteth large and great drincking, to waſhe and mundefie the ſtomacke and to make the meat the better to pearce and be diffuſed into the veines: But till ſuche time, he leſſoneth To quēche thirſt. vs to abſtaine vnleſſe great occaſion of thirſte otherwiſe require. And to quenche a drye thirſte, it ſhall ſuffice eyther to drinke a litle at once, or in the Sommer time rather to rinſe and waſh your mouth wt cold water. And it is very good to haue Pomgranards in ſtore being of a middle relice, for they are good to eate, when throughe drinkinge of wine thereis any vpbraidinge and mordicatiō in the ſtomacke. Alſo to drinke after ſuch meat as encreaſeth ill humour (of which ſort are Muſheromes) Auicen vtterlie forbiddeth: ſemblably after ſuch fruictes,

as Melons, Pompons, yealow Quinces and ſuche like. For wyne being dronke after ſuche fruictes, enforceth them to perce to the veines, whereby their corrupt iuyce is mixed with the bloude, and ſo is cauſe of the corruption thereof. But men now a dayes do cleane contrarie, for they loue to drinke with theſe and ſuche like fruictes the beſt wine they can gette as a remedie (for ſo they ſay) of fruictes, yea and ſometimes they haue the phiſicions themſelues compaignions with thē. But if thou wouldeſt kéepe thy ſtomack from the harme that proceedeth by the coldnes and moyſtnes of theſe fruictes, it were a great deale better to vſe to take Aniſeede, or Cinnamome, or ginger, or Honie and ſuche like.
               Héere as it were in the way of an addicion to the declaration of Wyne, I wil ſpeake a woord or twaine more, to teache you to know whether your Wine bée pure, or els mingled. It is ſometimes ſéene (as now in many thinges there is muche legierdemayne and deceite vſed) that Wyne is mingled with Hony, to How to know whe
                  
make it ſwéete and pleaſant. If it be ther wyne be made ſweet with Hony. thus abuſed and mixed, it may be eaſely knowen by this meanes. Take a few droppes of it, and powre them vpon a hoate plate yron, and the Wyne if it be pure being reſolued, becauſe it is thinner and ſubtiler, the Hony wil remayne and thicken, becauſe it is of a groſer and thicker ſubſtance. If you ſuſpect, that your Wine be mingled with water, you may eaſely know whether it be ſo or no by How to know whether wine be mingled with water. putting a Peare into it: for if the Peare ſwim a lofte and deſcende not to the bottome, then is the wine pure &amp; vnmingled, but if it ſinke to the bottome, it is an infallible token that it is mingled with water. Many ſuche pretie concluſions might here be ſhewed, but theſe for this matter are ſufficient. As concernyng the hower when to eate theſe aforeſayde and ſuch like fruictes ſhall hereafter be declared, but firſt wée will ſhew of ſuch meates as nouriſh beſt.
            
            
               Of Fleaſh.
               
                  
AFter Breade and Wyne (two of the cheefeſt mainteiners of mans Fleſh. life) fleaſhe is next in order to be ſpoken of. For Auicen ſayeth, that fleaſh is a meate comfortynge the body and of néere tranſubſtantiation and conuerſion into bloud, ſpecially the fleaſh of thoſe beaſtes and fowles that be of the beſt nouriſhyng ſort. And the wiſe Sages of our profeſſion, commend as moſte profitable for the conſeruacion of healthe, amonge foure footed Beaſtes, the Fleſhe of younge Kiddes and ſuckyng Calues, whiche be ſo muche the better if they be nouriſhed with wholeſome milke and in good paſtures. For this is to be noted ye of al Beaſtes which be of ſound complexion and qualitie, the youngeſt are moſt wholeſome, as Kiddes, Calues and ſuch like: but of them that be moyſt, the youngeſt are moſt harmefull. And therefore Auicen ſayth, that Lambes ſhould be a yeere olde before they be eaten. Notwithſtandyng in this poinct the diſpoſicion and temperature of the Countrey muſt be reſpected, where vpon Auicen
                  
ſayde that in the Eaſt and South partes of the world, Lambe and Mutten nught without daunger be eaten, whiche in our moyſt Countrey, and in moyſt bodies is not alway expedient. Seldome therefore and warelie muſt Lambe be eaten, Lambes fleſh. and rather in the ſommer and Autumne then at any other time of the yeere, becauſe drineſſe then beareth ſway. And if wée eate therof in the Winter or in the beginning of the Springe, it were much better roſted then boyled. Younge Béeif bred vp in wholeſome paſture and well exerciſed and chaſed, is in the winter Beeife. and Spryng not to be miſliked, for then Ventres be moſte hoate of nature, and ſleape very longe as Hippocrates affyrmeth, and therefore they may the better digeſt heauie meates: but in ſommer and Autumne, meates of light digeſtion muſt be vſed, becauſe the internall and naturall heate is then weaker by reaſon of the heate of the Ayre. As for groſſe meates that are drie and harde as cowes Beeif and ſuche like I vtterly diſalow: becauſe beſide many other Cowes fleſh
                  
harmes that it bringeth by reaſon of the hardneſſe of it, and difficultie to be digeſted, this namely is one, that it inferreth harme to the reaſonable parte of man whiche is the minde. Porke or Hogges fleſh nouriſheth very much, and is pleaſant and toothſome in taſte, but if they be very younge, there fleaſh is too moyſte and heauie of digeſtion, and therefore we muſt leaue it to ploughmen and labourers of ſtronger Stomackes. But being of middle age, as from ſixe monthes to a yéere olde (if they be not to fatte) theyr fleaſh is reſtoratiue to them that neede meates of ſuch operation &amp; haue ſtronge Stomackes: for no kinde of fleſh (ſaieth Galen) more nouriſheth the body then it doth. The fleſh of wild hogges are much commended, for by reaſon of their exerciſe and drye feedinge they are not greatlie moyſte but in a manner temperate. The fleſhe of an Hare is not good to bee eaten often, but it is beſt about the beginninge Hare. of the ſpringe or winter becauſe of ye drineſſe of it, for it maketh groſſe bloud and melancholique humoure. But the

braine is good for them that haue verie moiſte braines and tender ſofte bodies.
               Of fethered fowles there be manye ſortes: wherof Hennes and Capons are holeſomeſt in winter and in the beginninge of the ſpringe, and Chickens in Sommer, and Autumne becauſe they encreaſe good bloude and humours, and qualefie thoſe that are ill. In this ſeaſon alſo Quailes, pheſantes and young Partriches Quaile Pheſant. Partriche are excellent, for they be of a good concoction, nouriſhe ſingularlie well, and cauſeth few or no ſuperfluities: and alſo they helpe the ſtomacke and binde the mouth thereof. I meane them that be young becauſe they are more temperate then the elder. Auicen ſayeth that the eatinge of Quailes is to be feared, leaſte therby be engendred the crampe and the diſeaſe called Tetanus (whiche is a ſtiffenes and incenſibilitie in the ſinewes) not onely becauſe they féede on the herb Elleborus (which of itſelfe is venemous) and be therwith nouriſhed, but alſo becauſe the ſame perillous infection is in their fleſhe. Notwithſtanding this their venenoſitie

attributed to them by Auicen, and auowched by Galen, Lucretius and Plinie, I woulde not willinglie refuſe them for ſuſtentation, neither woulde I feare a whitte the incurring of any the aforenamed diſeaſe. For thoſe kinde of Quailes that they wrate of, differ &amp; are not the ſame that the Quailes here in this countrey are. The difference betweene whome and the other, is largelie ſet forth and deſcribed by Alexander Mundella in his ſixt Epiſtle.
               As for Sparrowes becauſe they be exceeding hoate and drie my counſaile is to Sparowes. Dooues Pigeons Wood culuers or Stockdoues be forborne and becauſe they ſtir vp Venus merueilouſlie, they are fitteſt to be left for olde men that haue yoūge wiues. Culuers and home doues are a litle heauie in concoction, ſpecialie the yoūge Pigeons that are not yet flidge and cannot flie, becauſe they haue in them ſuperfluous humours. But when they be able to flie, they are excellent good meate and holeſome, making good humour and are lightly digeſted. Wood Culuers becauſe they beſtirre and exerciſe themſelues

more then the domeſticall dooues do, are lighter of digeſtion. Auicen thinketh them beſt to be eaten in Sommer (I thinke for their moyſtnes) for els if they be eaten at any other ſeaſon be apointeth the iuyce of a lower grape called Agreſla &amp; Coriandre to be eaten withall, to remooue and take awaye the heate that is in them. But I am of a contrarie opinion, for I thinke it is muche better to eate them in Autumne whiche is colde and drye and likewiſe in winter and beginninge of the Springe, and Northernly ſeaſons, whoſe moyſture is a good deale taken away in the roſting. But Turtles are farre better becauſe they haue leſſe Turtles. moyſture, albeit many thinke that they be of a drye complexion, and yet not to hoate: yea they haue a ſinguler vertue to 
                     Auerr. 5. Coll.
                   comfort the braine and ſharpen the wit, and may ſafelie be eaten in the later end of Autumne and in winter. The fleſh of bigge water fowles are not very holeſome, becauſe they make ill and blacke Water Fowles. humour. The fleſh of a ducke aſwell the wilde as the tame nouriſheth very well Ducke.
                  
but it is heauie to digeſt. Therfore it is better for Labouringe men and ſtronge ſtomackes then for quaſie and weake bodies. The winges of fowles do nouriſhe commendablie, becauſe they be wel Winges exerciſed and eaſier to digeſt, retaynyng very few ſuperfluities by reaſon of their frequent motion. The fleaſh that is about the bones is ſwéeter and better to digeſt then other: ſo is alſo the Fleaſh Fleshe neere the bone. of the right ſide. Looſe and ſpoongie fleſh as the Vdders and the rootes of tongues is toothſome in taſte, but ſlow of digeſtiō but béeynge concocted, ſometime they make phelgmatike nouriſhment, yet commonlie none but good. Marow and Marow. Braines. the braynes are (as Auicen ſayth) hurtfull to the ſtomacke. Alſo fleſh that is fat is eaſely conuerted into Choler mixed with phelgme, and ill vapours. And therefore fattineſſe in meate maketh verie ſmall and the ſame ill nouriſhment, Patte meates. and puffeth vp the meate in the bealy, Which made Auicen to thinke that verie litle of it, ſhould be mingled with other fleſh euen accordynge to that meaſure

that beſt agréeth to euerie mans delight. Alſo euery kinde of fleſhe is commended or diſcommended accordinge as Kindes of fleshe. it is in qualitie: for the more that the fleſhe of Beaſtes doth degenerate from whytenes, the leſſe good iuyee is therein it. And by all mens confeſſion this is true, that of thoſe beaſtes which be of one kinde, ſo longe as they be young and tender the make moyſte nouriſhement: beynge in their middle or conſiſtent age, their nouriſhement is hoater and dryer. But when they be olde, their fleſhe is worſt of all, becauſe it encreaſeth melancholique and excrementall humour, yea and the bigger bodied the worſe.
               Wylde beaſtes and they that liue abroade in the fieldes, are hoater and drier then homiſhe and domeſticall. All which (notwithſtandinge) beynge vſed and taken at conuenient times and in due order that is to ſay accordinge as the qualitie of their temperature requireth, are thought nothinge at all to imbecile and hinder health. Salte meates meates (althoughe Salt meats they were moyſte before) do retaine

a vehement power to drye and heate and geeue ill nouriſhement: and to be ſhorte, all maner of ſalte meate generally engendreth putrefiynge and rotten menlancholique bloude, and greatlie offendeth the lieuer. Therefore it muſt be ſeldome eaten and in moyſt times of the yere, to witte in winter. Furthermore this ſayinge of Auicen may not be pretermitted, that the fleſhe of any blacke couloured beaſt and alſo of the male, is pleſaunter and lighter then of others.
               And I haue thought good here alſo to recite the opinion of the expert man Auenzoar, who writeth that it is beſt to eate fleſhe immediately or not longe after it is killed. And if they be ſomewhat barde (as the fleſhe of wylde duckes and olde Turtles is) he thinketh it beſt, to haue them boyled in water within twelue howers after thei be killed, and in Sommer within ſeuen, of the whiche opinion Galen is alſo, which is in déede not to be Gal. de atten. vic. ratione miſliked, but both to be praiſed and followed. For the ayre doth alter them, wher by they are made apte to putrefaction,

when they remaine longe after their killinge, eſpeciallie in a hoate &amp; moiſt ayre. And this is verified &amp; plainly to be ſeene in fiſhes, which (doubtles) are much better if they be dreſſed and eaten immediatelie after they be taken out of the water: and I am not ignorant that by reaſon of their watriſh moyſtnes they wyll quicklie putrefie. And fleſhe is better hoate then colde, ſpeciallie in winter and Autumne: except kiddes fleſhe whiche Auicen ſuppoſeth to be better and holeſomer Whether hoate or cold fleshe be better when it is colde, becauſe it then yeldeth no vapoure, but Lambe (he ſayeth) is better when it is hoat. If the fleſh be ſomewhat fatte, tender and verye moyſt, it is beſt to roſte it and ſpeciallie in winter and the Springe, but otherwiſe it is beſt to boyle it, namely in Sō
                  mer and Autumne, becauſe thereby they are of lighter concoction and kéepe away ſiccitie or dryneſſe which at thoſe times chieflie reigneth in mans body. Of roſted When to roſte and when to boyle flesh. fleſhe the inner parte (becauſe better moyſture is gathered inwardlie) is better to be eaten then the vtter part. The

Spittes or broches beinge of Iuniper, Spittes or broches maketh al the meate to haue a pleaſaunt and delightfull ſauoure. Roſted fleſhe is then beſt to be vnſpitted and taken from the broche when it ſmelleth ſweeteſt. For ſmellinge is the diſcouerer and token teller of taſt. Thus muche of fleſhe.
               Now wée ſpeake ſomwhat of other ſortes of nouriſhment, amonge whom Egges wée do affirme the Egges of a Henne, Partriche and Pheſant to excell any other. Dioſcorides commendeth them being halfe roſted that is to ſay meane betwéene rere and hard, ſo that they may be ſupped, becauſe they be then eaſely digeſted and increaſe good bloud. Auicen reckeneth them amonge ſoueraigne and cordiall meates, affirmyng the yolke to be of a laudable temperature: albeit he ſayth in his ſecond Canon, that the yolke inclineth to heate, and the white to coldenes, but the whole to be temperate.
               
                  Serapio thinketh it to be more colde then hoate and not without good reaſon: for the whight of the egge is more colde then the yolke is hoate, becauſe the yolke is

thought to be temperate or very néere to temperatenes. Egges wooulde be eaten before other meates becauſe they are quicklie digeſted and ſoone deſcend from the mouth of the Stomacke, and nouriſh very quickly. For they haue all the proprieties that belongeth to good nouriſhment, &amp; are ſoone tranſmuted into bloud, and leaue ſmall ſuperfluities: finallye they make ſubtile and cleare bloud wher by the principall member is nouriſhed.
               For it goeth to the very hart, and for the diſſolution of the ſubſtance of the ſpirite and cordiall matter it is a preſent remedie. Beyng harde roſted, they be of illnouriſhment, Harde Egges. heauie to digeſt, cauſinge ſtinking fumes in the ſtomacke, and makyng the lower part of the belly ſtiptick, but poched, they do aſſwage and lenifie it. Wherefore Galen hath theſe wordes aboute the beginninge of his booke De Euchym. &amp; Cacochym. Cockels (ſaith he) are accompted to be of a groſſe iuice, and ſo are Egges, whiche are either ſodden or roſted harde. If they be fried, they make il iuice and cauſe fumes in the ſtomacke

ere they be decocted, and do alſo corrupt other meates with whom they be mingled. But beynge meaſurably ſodden and vſed, that is to wit ſomwhat rere, they are apt to digeſt, nouriſh, and encreaſe good bloud: ſo alſo are poched Egges good to aſſwage ſoreneſſe &amp; rough neſſe of the throate. In milke and egges there is great abundance of fat and clammie moiſture, the one appropriate to aliment and nouriture, the other to Sperm or ſéede of generation. The Egges or Spaune of fiſhes are nothyng ſo calefactiue and nutritiue: for ſo far as the fleſh of Birdes is better then fiſhe, ſo muche are the egges: of fiſhes inferiour in goodnes to the egges of birdes Auicen alloweth the eatinge of Mylke in rype and Mylke conſiſtent age better then in adoleſcencie and therefore he thinketh it good for collerique perſons, but ill for them that are phlegmaticke. Albeit he alſo ſayeth that it is not good for th'entrayles, nor for the ſtomacke, and alſo cauſeth dimneſſe of ſight, hurteth the teeth, annoyeth the ſinew, engendreth obſtructions in ye 
                  Meſaraike
                  
Veines is ſoone corrupted, quickly ſowreth and cauſeth headache.
               Wherefore that all theſe diſcommodities may be eſchued, he woulde that it ſhould be dronke alone, and after it is dronke to reſt from labour, and then to ſleepe and to eate nothynge vntill it he deſcended from the ſtomacke. But cheifly he warneth that in no wiſe vineigre, or ſower meates be eaten after it. Yet do I counſell them that eate it, for feare leaſt it ſhould congele in their ſtomacks to put a litle ſuger or Salt, or pure hony vnto it, and to ſtirre it all together.
               Salt ſeaſoneth and taketh away ye harmes that come by Mylke and all other kindes of victualles, ſo dothe Hony alſo make Milke muche the better. Now the commodities ye come by eating of Milke The commodities of mylke. are the moderate deiection and purging of thinges in the bealy ſuperfluous, good nouriſhment and making of wholeſome tuyce. The paſtures wherin the beaſtes What milke is beſt. feede, whoſe Milke wée vſe, is of greate force and validitie to this purpoſe. And whereas there be many ſortes of Milke

of all others, womans Milke is the excellenteſt, becauſe it is very good and beneficiall Womans mylke to mans bodie, namely to the brayne, for it is thought to increaſe it merueylouſly, and preſerueth agaynſt conſumption. Next vnto it, is Goates Mylke, for it is temperate and hath in Goates mylke it but ſmall quantitie of Butter. Likewiſe the milke of Camels and Aſſes, whiche by reaſon of the nature of the Camelles mylke and Aſſes milk beaſtes themſelues, hath in it but litle Chéeſe, and therefore doth purge excellently, and is very wholeſome. The Milke of Ryne and Ewes is fatter: but if the beaſt that géeueth it, féede in good and wholeſome paſtures, out of Fennes and Marſhes, and with temperate fodder, it is much better thē if thei ſhould féede in ſmall cloſes or watrie grounds. And it ſhould be dronke warme from When to drinke milke the vdder, or not very longe after, it is milked, for the ayre doth ſoone alter it, and of good and wholeſome, maketh it il and noyſome. But héere may ſome meruayle, why Milke ſhould be forbidden younge men and not to men of ripe and

conſiſtent age, conſiderynge that vnto younge infantes it is géeuen by the ſpecial benefite of Nature as a moſt fit and conuenient nouriſhment. But this and ſuch other ambiguous quiddities are els where to be ſought, for in this ſmal booke wée write a Regiment how to conſerue health and not arguyng diſputations.
               The vpper parte of the milke is not to Creame. be prayſed, for it loſeth the ſtomacke, and by reaſon of his vnctuoſitie is ſoone turned into yelow choler. The Creame or thicke ſummitie of Milke whiche is gathered after the milke hath been ſodden and ſuffred to ſtande a night is vnwholeſome and hurtefull.
               Butter is very vnctuous, and all vnctuous Butter meates eſpecially Butter (by the opinion of Auicen) is preiudiciall and harmefull to ye ſtomacke. For the power and vertue of the ſtomacke conſiſteth in the vnion of his partes, and in a certaine ſtipticitie and byndyng, whiche is by vnctuous foode hindered, and many times quight taken away and deſtroyed. The beſt Butter is that whiche is made of

Cowes milke in May. In hoate and moyſt complexions it is ſoone conuertible into Choler. The thicke and curdie Milke, whiche firſt commeth into the Dugges incontinently after the Cowe Bieſting hath calued, commonly called Bieſtings is very daungerous, for it is ſlow of digeſtion and deſcendeth ſlowlye from the ſtomacke, and is alſo groſſe of ſubſtance, cauſing groſſe humours and conſequently is thought to engender the ſtone.
               Freſh and new Cheeſe (ſayth Dioſcorides) is beneficiall to the ſtomacke, but Freshe Cheeſe. 
                  Auicen doubteth therof. But I thinke, that in hoate ſeaſons and aboute the beginnynge of Autumne it may without daunger be eaten. But being olde, and yet not rotten nor hard with age, conueniently ſalted, I iudge better to be eaten in colde ſeaſons and at the latter ende of meales: yet herein as in all other things, Nature and Cuſtome is of greate force and muche to be conſidered. For there are ſome, whiche do abhorre Chéeſe and cannot in any wiſe brooke it: as ſome others do lothe Wyne and ſo forthe of others.

                  Auicen ſayth that ſuch indiuiduall proprieties as theſe, are without the cō
                  paſſe of reaſon, and that experience and triall herein is aboue reaſon. The thinneſt part of the mylke called whaye beinge vſed by way of medicine rather thē 
                  Whaye for meate, and ſpeciallye in Maye wyth Sugar is very good to ſcower, clenſe and purefie the bloude and alſo to quenche choler and purge melancholie without any paine or greeuance. For it waſheth the breaſt, prouoketh vrine, maketh cleane the bladder, and without any pain or excoriation draweth out ill humours, and (as Auicen ſayeth) rectifieth nouriſhment and openeth the partes of the bodie that are with obſtructions ſtopped. All which vertues and operatious make Auicen to thinke that it maketh men fat.
               Into it may be put a conuenient quantitie of Roſes or Sene (accordinge as the pacient ſhalbe opplete with humoures) the ſpace of a night with a little Anyſe ſéede or Cinamome to make it woorke more ſtrongelie. But then were it good that the humours ſhoulde be concoct and

prepared. For the approued wiſe Hippocrates, commaundeth vs to miniſter 1. Aph. 22. Phiſicke to thoſe thinges that be concoct and to mooue the vncrude. Finally all thoſe meates are diſcommended that are compounded and made of Milke, Egges and Chéeſe or ſuche other like thinges. For although they be all of eaſie digeſtiō being ſeuerally taken, yet beyng mingled together they are hardly concocted &amp; muche endamage the ſtomack. For ſundrie meates of diuers ſubſtance and qualitie is a great enemie to health, and by reaſon of the groſſenes of ſome, and the fineneſſe of other ſome, there is required to be diuerſe operations of nature, and diuerſe temperatures of the ſtomacke, for it is greatly buſied in the decoction of them all And becauſe ſome tarie longer in the ſtomacke then ſome other doth, it cauſeth fumes and vapours to aſcende and ſtrike vp into the head, whereby health is much appayred.
            
            
               
               Of Fishe.
               FYſhes for the moſte parte are not holeſome, or they are of ſmale and illnouriſhement Fishes and leaue manye ſufluities in the body and alſo are eaſlie corrupted. And therefore Auicen counſaileth vs not to eate them after vehement and ſtronge exerciſe, becauſe they will ſoone be turned into corruption and do alſo corrupt the humours. And in an other place (which is alſo auouched by Galen) he ſayeth that fiſhe beinge new and freſh engendreth phlegme and mollifieth the ventricle, and is not to be eaten but of them which haue very hoate ſtomackes, becauſe they be verye colde and moyſte. Beynge ſalted they are hoate and drye, Salted Fishes and therfore for them that be phlegmaticke it is better to eate them ſalted, and in winter or at the beginninge of ſpring: but for cholerique perſons and in hoate ſeaſons they are beſt when they be new and moyſte, but the ſureſt and beſt way

is altogether to abſtaine from them. The Gréeke poet Homer for his manifolde knoweledge in al faculties worthie to be called the pereleſſe Phenix of learninge moſt learnedly bringeth in, that Vliſſes when he had trauailed longe vpon the Seas, and all his victualles were ſpent, was by neceſſitie enforced and driuen to fiſhe. Meaninge therby, that ſo longe as we may liue without fiſhe, we ſhoulde refraine it. But for aſmuche as euerie man may not alwayes eate egges nor fleſhe, nor at all ſeaſons without any reſpect and difference, and alſo appetite many times beareth ſwaye aboue reaſon: Therefore I will declare &amp; deſcribe ſuch fiſhes as are leſt hurtfull. And firſt this is to be knowen, that thoſe fiſhes are beſt which be neither verye harde and drye, Beſt fishes. neyther yet full of ſtimie and clammie toughnes, nether opplete with much fattineſſe (for all fatte is ill, but of fiſhes the fatteneſſe is worſe then anye other) neyther of ill ſauoure and relice: but pleaſant ſwéete and toothſome in taſte, and which will not ſoone ſtinke after they be taken

out of the water. It is further alſo to be noted that of thoſe which are ſoft and tender, the greateſt are beſt, but of hard fiſhe take the ſmaleſt. For that which among moyſt thinges is found drye, muſt be taken as moderate as that is, whiche amonge drye thinges is founde moyſte. Yet let a conuenient meaſure aſwell in the bigneſſe as in the ſmaleneſſe be obſerued. Alſo the fiſhes that liue about cleare Rockes and in ſtony places are (as Galen ſayeth) better then any other.
               And it is not without good cauſe that ſuche fiſhes be preferred and winne the commendaciō from others. For they exerciſe and mooue themſelues muche and often, and lye in ſuche places, where they are often toſſed and beaten with the continuall ſurges and waues of the tempeſtuous Sea, and neuer are embroyned with anye filth or diertie ſlimiſhnes.
               Thoſe fiſhes alſo are greatly commended that come ſwymminge out of the Sea into Riuers, ſith they come agaynſt the ſtreame, and the farther of that they be from the Sea, the holeſomer and better

they are. Next vnto them are thoſe that liue in ſandie places, and thoſe that breede in cleare and freſhe runninge water, that is without much mudde. Furthermore thoſe fiſhes that féede vpon ſwéete herbes, rootes and wéedes aboute the banke ſides are better then thoſe that liue by mudde and ſlime: amonge which ill ſorte are thoſe fiſhes that are called Mugles or Lompes, which are not holeſome although they ſéeme to haue a pleaſant Mugles or Lompes. taſte and ſauoure. Therefore al ſuch fiſhes as liue in filthye puddles, fennes, marſhes, dyches and ſtandinge waters whiche mooue not are to be eſchewed.
               This generall warninge now premiſed briefly and namelye let vs touche ſuche ſortes of fyſhes as are beſt and moſt ſufferable, ſuppoſed to be of good nouriſhement and of lighteſt concoction. Good and holeſome is the Gilthead (called Gilthead 
                  Aurata and of the Gréeques Chryſophris becauſe it hath in his forehead a thinge congelate which in the water ſhineth like golde as in the olde ones it is to be ſéene) they géeue muche nouriſhement

and therefore are difficultie digeſted. So is the Rochet and Seapearches. But Riuer pearches (whiche are like in Rochet Pearche of the Sea Riuer Pearch maner to the other) are of pleaſaunt taſte and good to be géeuen nowe and then to them that haue a feruent Ague, when their appetite is quight gone through vehemencie of heat. Carpes are pleaſaunt and tootheſome: ſo are alſo Troutes and Troute Gogeon Gogions, but thoſe are beſt that are white and little, for they be ſofte, mollefiynge, of good iuyce and concoction, but thoſe that are gréene and blackiſhe are worſte. Of good iuyce alſo are Mullets and Barbilles, beinge meane betwéene harde and tender as Cornelius Celſus 
                  3. de Re. Ruſt. 3. de aliment. virt.
                   wryteth and Galen affirmeth the ſame They binde the bellie ſpeciallie beinge broyled on the Coales: but fried they are heauie and hard to digeſt Athenaeus writeth that if a liuinge Mullet be put into wine and choked or ſtrangled therin, whatſoeuer man drinketh of the ſame wyne, ſhall not be able to do the acte of generatiō. Dioſcorides ſaieth that much and oft
                     •
                  n eatinge thereof dymmeth the

eyeſight. Plinie writeth that the pouldre made of the head of a freſhe Mullet, hath great vertue againſt al venime and poyſon, ſpeciallie if it happen throughe the ſtinging of any liuinge Creature. And they be called Mullettes and Barbilles, becauſe they haue two barbes or wartes on their neither iawes.
               Eeles are not holeſome becauſe they Eeles be moyſte and ſlymie: of whom I will here geeue a note or twaine, not hitherto of anye almoſte marked. All alonge the backebone of an éele, there goeth a blacke ſtringe like a ſmall veine (as it is in the tayle of a Crabbe) in which blacke veine a certaine poyſon is included, whiche ought to be drawen out before the Eele be boyled, and he requireth longer time of ſéething then any other fiſhe. Beynge broyled, it nouriſheth better then when it is boyled, becauſe the fier taketh away his vicious and naughtie humours.
               Phiſicions do altogether reiecte the eatinge of them about Midſomer. They that are moſte firme, ſolide and fatte are beſt, and ſpeciallie the femalles (there

ſnoute or noſe is tourned vpwarde more then the males) but if my counſell may be followed, it were beſt for ſuche perſons as in this treatiſe are ment to forbeare them altogether, at all ſeaſons in the yere, for they be of harde concoctiō and engendre very groſſe and flimie humour, albeit to cormerauntes and Epicures they ſéeme to go down their throfe pleaſauntlie. I once read this of an Eele, in a woorke of a certaine naturall Philoſopher and haue taught the ſame to manye, albeit I knowe no man that as yet hath put it in proofe, neyther yet my ſelf. Now whether his concluſion be true or no, let the Authoure himſelfe ſhifte and aunſwer it. If you woulde make ſome A way to make common drunkardes to loth and abhorre wine. notorious drunkard and common ſwilbowle to loth and abhorre his beaſtlie vice and for euer after to hate the drinking of wine: put an Eele alyue into ſome wyde mouthed potte with a couer, hauing in it ſuche a quantitie of wine as maye ſuffice of itſelfe to ſuffocate and ſtrangle the Eele to death. Which doone take out the dead Eele, and let the partie

whom you would haue reclaymed from his bibacitie, not knowing hereof drinke of that wine onely, euen as muche as he liſteth. The ſame vertue (as ſom write) An other waye hath the water that diſtilleth out of a vine when it is cutte and pruned, if it be mixed with wine, and geeuen to drinke twiſe or thriſe to one that knoweth not of it. But let vs againe retourn to fiſhes. Crabbes for the moſt parte are to be eſchewed Crabbes. for they be ill for the head: and vnder Crabbes we alſo meane all Periwincles and Shrimpes. All kindes of Shelfiſhes as Oyſters, Cockles, Limpettes, Shrimpes Periwincles. Oyſters Cockles. Limpettes. Muſcles. Muſcles &amp;c. are ſeldome and ſparingelie to be eaten. The dreſſinge of thē muſt be ſuch, as the nature of the fiſhes themſelues, time, ſeaſon and cuſtome requireth: but thoſe that be moyſte and ſoft ſpeciallie in moyſte ſeaſons are beſt roſted that is to ſay, dreſſed onely with fyer without any water or any other licoure. Notwithſtandinge, we maye vſe Oyle and Vinegre to ſauce and relice the ſame the better. But harde and toughe fiſhes were better to be boyled 
                     〈◊〉
                   wel ſodden

then either roſted or broyled. Finallie this I ſay for a generall rule, that al cold or moyſt meates are holpen and qualified by drinkinge good wine and eatinge good Spices withall.
            
            
               Of Sauces.
               But now let vs ſay a litle of thoſe thīgs that ſerue for ſeaſonyng and powderyng Salt and the nature of it. of meate and firſt of Salt, and afwardes of others. And as for ſalt there is no man that doubteth but it is moſte neceſſarie and conuenient almoſte in all kindes of meates, becauſe it maketh them more concoctible and pleaſant in taſte. Alſo it hath a vertue abſterſiue and reſolutiue, and by reaſon of a ſiccatiue or drying power whiche it hath, it kéepeth them from putrefaction and corruption, and comforteth the body with a bynding or ſtipticke power. Further more it maketh the meate to deſcende from the ventricle eaſily and expediently, expelleth ſuperfluities, ſubtileth phlegme and helpeth

digeſtion in them that haue colde ſtomackes. But it muſt with meaſure and moderation be vſed, for with his ſharpeneſſe it hurteth the Ventricle and Bowels, cauſeth vomite, induceth lothſomenes, and fretteth the guttes, greatly yea, if the weight of one dramme therof bée eaten in the morninge with a faſting ſtomacke it maketh the bealie ſoluble, and diſpoſed too the ſtoole. Now followeth Oyle, verie good alſo and requiſite Oyle. to ſauce manie &amp; ſundrie meates, but in the perticular recital of al ſorts of Oyles I wil not now ſtand, ſithens I only ſtudie for breuitie. Al Oyles (ſaith Auicen) do louſe ye vētricles vnleſſe it bee ye Oyle of nuts &amp; of y• kinde yt are called Piſtacea and the oyle of Oliues. The oyle of Piſtacea is better then any other, but wee haue neuer ſeene it made in any place: the oyle of Nuttes is not good for the breaſt and tongue, and therefore it remayneth for vs to entreate of the oyle of Oliues. The ſharpe and ſower licoure that is made of vnripe Oliues for thoſe that are healthfull and haue hoate bodies

                  Auicen doth greatly commende as very fit and congruent for them, and not with out cauſe. For it is not greatly vnctuous nor hoate, and by it the ventricle obteyneth a conuenient bindyng and oportune ſtipticitie. And therefore if you make oyle of theſe Oliues before they come to their full ripeneſſe, truely in hoate ſeaſons you ſhall finde the eatynge thereof very wholeſom. For it greatly helpeth the bodie without anye harme and ſtoppeth ouer much thinneſſé and fluxibilitie of bloude in cholericke and ſanguine perſons. Auerroys giueth much praiſe to the Oyle of ripe oliues oyle of rype Oliues beinge newe and ſwéete, becauſe the nature of it is in a maner temperate, hauing in it but ſmall heate. And alſo he thinketh it to be verye agréeable to mans temperature, accordinge to the whole nature of ſubſtance of it, and to fatten the Lieuer and augment the ſubſtance therof: and therefore he reporteth howe that in his Countrey they vſed to ſeaſon and ſauce their fleſhe therewith and that many by vſing it, became verye fatte and corpulent. We in

theſe our Regions thinke it beſt, to eate that which is ſower and bytinge in Sō
                  mer, &amp; ſwéete in the winter and Spring ſeaſons: becauſe the one is colde, and the other ſomewhat hoate. Oyle of ſwéete Almondes is good for them that haue the Oyle of Almondes. Stitche and other grief in their breaſtes. For it aſſwageth &amp; lenifieth the Iawes and rough arteries, and maketh the humours that are in the Breaſt apte to be proiected and expelled: and of the thicke Creame of Almondes beinge boyled, Creame of Almondes. there is made an excellent broath or ſuppinge, good both to nouriſhe and purge the Reynes, and alſo to ſcower &amp; cleanſe the bowelles and bulke of man, but it is not ſo good for the ſtomacke. Honye and the water of it is very good for a cold and Honie. moyſte ſtomacke, for olde men and them that be of colde complexions and in the winter and Springe ſeaſons: But it is not good for them that be Cholerique, or in the Sommer time. In makinge of honie water (that is to witte ſéethinge water and honie together with a ſofte fier) the fome or froath muſt be ſcummed

of cleane, for if it be not, it is prouoked to be windie and inflatiue. It hath a vertue abſterſiue, openeth obſtructions, reſolueth humours and educeth them beinge farre within the bodie, and kéepeth the bodie, from rottenneſſe and putrefaction. But the beſt honie muſt be taken for ſuche purpoſe, that is to ſay ſuche as Beſt honie. hath a true and perfect ſwéetenes, a good pleaſant ſmell, and a ſomewhat redde colour, not thinne, not ſubtile, but clammie and viſcious. The beſt honie is gathered in the Springe, the ſecond in Sommer, but that which is gathered in winter is worſte and moſt hurtfull. Alſo ſharpe and ſower honie is the worſt of al others foraſmuche as it is of ſome thought to be peſtilent and venemous. Sugar is heater and more ſubtile then honie, for it is Sugar. thought to be hoate and moyſt in the end of the firſt degrée: but by artificiall handlinge that is to witte, by further and longer boyling (whereby it is made white) it becometh not ſo hoate &amp; yet more dry. It hath in all poinctes as great vertue and power as honie hath, both to lenifie,

mitigate and open obſtructions, and alſo to drye vp and wype away il humours, and it is good for the ſtomacke if no yellow choler be therin, for it is eaſelie conuerted and turned into choler. Alſo it pur geth phlegme that is founde in the fromacke, and comforteth the bealie. This therfore is very good to be eaten at anye time of the yere, but honie is beſt in winter to be eaten and in the ſecond parte of Autumne. Vinegre is ſaid to be good for them that are melancholique but nought Vineiger. for them that be cholerique, and therfore it agréeth beſt to a ſtomacke that is hoat and moyſte: it ſtirreth vp appetite, helpeth concoction, repreſſeth choler and ſtoppeth humours from beinge diffuſed into the inward partes, it maketh them ſubtile, cutteth them a ſunder and preſerueth againſte phlegme, ſpeciallie if it be mixed with Cinamome and Corraunts to take awaye and alay the ouermuche coldenes and egerneſſe of it. Alſo beinge in this order and maner tempered it is good for a colde ſtomacke. And this waye do we thinke beſt to be vſed when you

would alay the ſharpe and bytinge ſowerneſſe of vinegre: boyle it wc very good Raiſons or Corrantes, and (if néede be) make it ſwéete with the odorifirous ſmell of good Cinamome. For Cinamome ouer and beſide the heate whiche Cinamon. it hath (for it is ſayde to be hoate toward the third degrée) it is alſo verye good for the ſtomacke and Lieuer. It openeth obſtructions and comforteth them both, and alſo it dryeth vp the humiditie or moyſture of the ſtomacke and kepeth it from corruption and putrefaction, it confirmeth and corborateth all the vertues and powers of the bodye, and reſtoreth them that be appayred and decayed, it cleanſeth and mundefieth the head by educinge and fetchinge out the humours that be in it, yea it lenifieth and helpeth the Coughe and Breaſt, drawing out all that is naught and hurtfull. And thus muche for Condimentes and Sauces.
            
            
               Of Grayne, Pulſe, Rotes, &amp; Herbes
               
                  
NOw let vs ſpeake ſomewhat of ſuch graine and herbes as ſerue at the table to be eaten. Rice is of Rice. muche nouriſhement enclininge to heat and dryneſſe and maye be beſt eaten in winter. Ryce ſodden in mylke cauſeth a good habite and plight of the body and encreaſeth ſéede of generation. Panick and Mill may be eaten in moyſt Seaſons either hoate or colde. But in Autumne, becauſe Panike. Mill. it is a colde and drye time, ſuche graine as is hoate and moyſte is more expedient. Barley is better to be eaten in Sommer, becauſe it is colde. Theſe graines muſt be ſodden with fleſhe potage or els in water, puttinge afterward therinto ſwéete Almonde mylke: or els let them be condite with oyle, which done you may put therto ſome Sugar accordinge to your owne diſcretion. Of ſmall pulſe, Phiſicions moſt commend Cichpeaſe, and ſpeciallie the potage or broath Cich peaſe Potage of Cichpeaſe. wherein it is ſodden, but they muſt (ſayeth Auicen) be eaten at the middeſt of Meales, and not at the beginninge nor ende. They nouriſhe the bodie ſtronglie

and purelie if they be eaten moderatelie, for otherwiſe they be windy and require a ſtronge ſtomacke and a good vertue digeſtiue, but the broath made of them is preferred before anye other, becauſe it chaſeth, away il humours and prouoketh vryne. Lintellès are miſliked and diſcō
                  mended, becauſe the annoy the ſtomack, Lintles. fill the Lieuer with obſtructions, engender melancholique humour, cauſe a dazelinge dimnes of the ſight, and amonge al kinde of pulſe are worſte to be eaten, for they bréede groſſe, terreſtriall and melancholique bloud. Beinge twiſe or thriſe or oftener warmed and eaten (the broath being caſt away) they binde the bealie, but the beſt and ſureſt way is altogether to abſtaine from them as moſte hurtefull, and fitter rather for Laborers and Rurall people then Magiſtrates and Studentes. Beanes are verye windie, and tarie longe ere they be digeſted Beanes yea although they be decocted the full ſpace of thrée dayes yet do they ſtill retaine their windines and ventoſitie. They make groſſe iuyce in the bodie,

and ſend ill vapours to the brain, which cauſe fearfull and ſtrange dreames, and they engender thicke groſſe bloude.
               Therefore vſe them not in diet although otherwiſe they ſéeme to haue a certaine abſterſiue and nutritiue power. But if thou be ſo be ſted, that néedes thou muſt eate of them, it were beſt to make potage or broath with them, for ſo, they haue more vertue to cleanſe the Reynes of the backe, and the bladder, and looſe much of their windineſſe in the boyling. And if thou be diſpoſed to put any other grayne or ſeedes vnto them which haue ſemblable power to expell and driue away windeneſſe (called of the Gréekes Aphuſa) &amp; put a litle Hony vnto them, it ſhalbe a meane to auoide much farther harme and inconuenience. Amonge whiche ſorte of ſéedes, theſe followinge are the beſt and chiefeſt: Carawayes, Anyſe, Fenell, and Cumine. Phaſelles are not ſo good, for they be hoate and earthie, Phaſelles and greatlie diſturbe the ſpirite of the braine, cauſinge manye vnreſtfull dreames throughe their vapours, together

with giddines and ſwimminge in the head called Vertigo. Hither to of pulſe, and by that whiche we haue heere declared, thou mayeſt diſcerne and haue iudgement of thoſe which be not here recited. Among the which, thoſe are accepted beſt, whiche be gréene, becauſe they yet retaine a light moyſtnes: but when by continuance of time they be withered &amp; haue loſt their verdure, they are more groſſe and terreſtriall. And euen as they which are full of iuyce are more to be ſet by, then they that are drie and wythered: ſo alſo are they that are boyled better then thoſe that be crude and raw, and the ſodden better then the vnſodden.
               After Pulſe, let vs ſpeak of Potherbes Rootes and ſuche fruites as growe vpon Rapes Trées. Rape rootes (notwithſtandinge Democritus deemeth them altogether hurtfull and to be eſchued) yet Galen approuinge the ſayinge and opinion of Diocles, praiſeth and muche commondeth them becauſe they concect Melancholie and prouoke vrine conuenientlie: and as Auenzoar witneſſeth, whom alſo Auerrois
                  
followeth, they haue a merueylous great power and vertue to clarefie the eyes. And althoughe they abounde with muche moyſture, whiche commonly annoyeth the ſtomacke and minſtreth matter to windineſſe: yet may this moiſture be qualified, if they be firſt boyled in water and Salte. Which being doone, &amp; the watrie humoure wrynged out of them, thou néedeſt not to caſt anye doubtes in the eatinge of them beinge ſufficientlie boyled in fleſhe potage, and (if néede ſo require) ſeaſoned and ſpiced with a ſmall quantitie of Anyſe ſéede or Cinamome. Caret rootes are muche like vnto rapes, if they be decocted and ſodden, they maye Caret rootes. Smalladge Perſely. without harme be eaten in the winter ſeaſon. The rootes of Smallage and Perſelie, beinge in this maner and time ſodden in pottage, are verye good in winter and chieflie at the beginninge of meales, becauſe they bringe downe humoures and prouoke vrine. Succorie both the leafe and the roote young and tender and boyled together, are verye good to keepe Succorie the ſtomacke and head in good plight, and

doth temper Choler wonderfullie, ſpecially in the Sommer and ſpringe ſeaſons. As for Radiſh rootes, Galen affirmeth Radishe. to be vnholeſome, yea he plainly ſaithe that the rootes of all potherbes engender excremental matter and be hard of digeſtion. Endiue and Lettiſe are wholeſom herbes to be eaten in Salets Endiue Lettiſe. Mint very holeſome for many purpoſes. and with meate in hoate weather. And if Minte be added and put to them or to other colde thinges, the ſalet is much the better and wholeſomer. For Minte hath vertue to comforte the Entrayles, and ſpecially the ſtomacke and Mawe, and encreaſeth thicke generatiue ſperme.
               It dothe alſo ſtrengthen and confirme the veſſels and conduits of the ſéede, and therefore it hath a ſpeciall force and efficacie agaynſt the profluuious iſſue of the ſéede called Gonorrhea: and the iuice thereof dronke with vineigre ſtencheth bloud. Yea it is very delectable &amp; pleaſant in ſmell, and much comforteth and chéereth vp the ſpirites of man.
               Sorrell is alſo good aboute the ſame Sorell time to be eaten, becauſe it is colde and

very comfortatiue, and (as Auicen writeth) hath a certayne ſubtile ſtipticitie in it. Purſelayne is to be forborne becauſe it is to colde, to wit, in the third degree, &amp; Purſelan alſo maketh ſmal, and the ſame noughty nouriſhment, and quight marreth appetite: notwithſtanding it quencheth burnyng choler, and is good againſt the ſpitting of bloud and the blouddie flixe, the Emorroydes and bloud procéeding from the breaſt. The great frigiditie and coldneſſe of it (if wee ſhoulde at any time chaunce to eate it) may be tempered and qualefied with Minte or with Fenell.
               Borage (whiche is the true Bugloſſe) and Langue du buefe are for the ſpringe Borage Lang debeefe. and ſommer ſeaſons, yea and for the other two partes of the yéere alſo either in Salets or meates right ſoueraygne and cordial. For they are ſayd to be temperate of complexion and qualitie and to engendre good bloud, and to exhilarate the heart. Hoppes ſemblablie are good to eate at that time wherein they be gathered at the beginninge of meales, becauſe Hoppes. they are named amonge the medicines

of the Liuer and are temperate, aperitiue, and prouoke vrine.
               But Sperage (wee know) hath in it greater prouocacion, for it maketh a pleaſant Sperdge odoure in m
                     •
                  ate, &amp; bringeth ſweetneſſe to ye whole body, clenſeth ſlinkinge vrine, mundifieth the 
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  d
                     ••
                  r, maketh ſweete the other officiall veſſels &amp; membres &amp; is ſoone conuerted into good I loud alſo it nouriſheth excellently, and is beſt to be eaten before other meate.
               White Béetes (by reaſon of a inti
                     •
                  ſitie or bitter ſaltiſhneſſe which they haue White Beetes are good for the bealy and obſtructions of the Splene and Liuer, and alſo they do not engendre ſuche Melancholicke humour as Colewortes doo. But blacke Béetes are not commendable, becauſe Black Beetes they make blacke iuyce and humeur.
               Béete rootes that are yelowiſh and red haue ſtronger nouriſhment, and make bloud a greate deale thicker then the leaues do: and this property they haue further, that they cauſe windineſſe and looſe the bealy, wherefore at ſometime they may be vſed. Colewortes and Cabages Coleworts Cabages.
                  
may without harme be eaten in cold and moyſt ſeaſons, ſithens they be hoate and drie: for they haue a vertue abſterſiue, and lauatiue, and prouoke vrine conueniently, but the brothe or Potage wherin they be ſodden is much better to be liked. Being lightly ſodden and not hauing loſt their moyſture altogether, they mollifie the bealy, but they binde &amp; ſtop it if they be eaten when their licour hath béene foure or fiue times caſt out and taken away from them. Albeit there are ſome harmes that come through theſe herbes, beyng eaten out of due time, order and quantitie. For beyng to muche vſed in meates, they engēder euil &amp; melancholique iuyce, hurteth the mouthe of the ſtomacke, dimme the Eyeſight, and trouble the ſléepe with phantaſticall imaginations. And therefore vnleſſe it be vpon ſome vrgent cauſe (as for lacke of other better meates) let them be reiected &amp; forborne. The great Cabages whiche Plinie calleth Lacuturres are not ſo good. All Colewortes are thought to haue in them a ſinguler vertue agaynſt drunkē
                  neſſe, Coleworts reſiſt dronkenneſſe.
                  
by reaſon of the repugnant contrarietie and naturall enemitie that is betwéene the Vyne and them. For it hath been and is often by experience proued, that if Colewortes be ſowed néere to the rootes of a Vyne trée, the Vine of his owne accorde will ſpreade on the other ſide, and turne away from them a pretie diſtance. Alſo the iuice of Colewortes is cleane contrarie to Wyne, and therefore whereas the Vyne with his tendrelles will take holde and lappe aboute all other thinges, it will neuer turne towarde the Coleworte. And for this cauſe many Nacions and namely the Germaines vſe ofter to eate Cabages and Colewortes at their meales, thereby to auoyde the harme that commeth by exceſſiue bibbynge of Wyne, whiche ought to be dronke not ingluuiouſly, but temperately and ſparingly. Thoſe that are of colour ſomewhat enclining to redneſſe are beſt for this purpoſe. And I once ſaw a certayne learned man beinge a good naturall philoſopher when he ſate downe at the table in a certaine

banquet (where he knew would be ſtoute quaffinge, priuilie and vnknowen to the reſt of the compaignie) eate a leafe of rawe Coleworte, whiche partly holpe him and kept him a good while from beinge Cuppeſhotte: but yet notwithſtandinge the much drinking of wine ſhewed his force vpon him ere he departed.
               Nauewes are verye groſſe, heauie to Rapes Nauewes Perſelye digeſt makinge crude and rawe iuyce in the veines and ingender black humours. Perſelie aboundantlie and largelye eaten in winter is expedient and healthfull for it is hoate and drye in the thirde degrée, it openeth obſtructions and maketh the vrine to paſſe well. If thou eate of it in Sommer, vſe it with ſuche fruictes and herbes as are colde, as the iuyce of Gourdes. Cucumbers bitter grapes, ſodden or boyled in potage and alſo with Gourdes &amp; Cucumbers. But theſe are ſeldome to be vſed becauſe Cucumbers make raw iuyce and make the bodie apt to long continuing Agues, and are of a very colde and moyſt temperature: and Gourdes are noyſome to the ſtomacke and almoſt neuer digeſted, and

alſo are very ill for the gutte called Colō
                   through whom the ordure ſhoulde paſſe, and generallie for al colde phlegmatique and melancholique perſons. Being eaten rawe, they are meane betwéene Pepons &amp; Cucūbers: but boyled they are a great deale better and of their proper nature géeue colde and drye nouriſhement to the bodie. Cheruile is verye fitte and Cheruyle profitable for cold ſtomackes, and hath a pleaſant and delightful taſt. Muſhromes (becauſe they haue a cold and moyſte nature Mushroms and engender groſſe &amp; crude iuyce) agrée beſt to a hoate and drye complexion. But if the Muſheroomes be kepte in bryne, they wyll be muche the better, and nothing ſo muche hurtefull, becauſe therby they looſe muche of their toughe clammineſſe and glewiſhe humoure. As for ſharpe and bytinge herbes as Onyons, Garlicke and Léekes we think better to be forborne, as not fit for a Studient or magiſtrate: vnleſſe peraduenture Onions. Garlike Leekes in winter they that are phlegmatique may vſe them beinge boyled or in Sauces to purge phlegme withall. Léekes

are better and more tollerable thē either Onyons or Garlicke if they be boyled, for the boylinge taketh awaye muche of their ill and ſharpe iuyce: albeit after a ſort, they be thought hard to digeſt by reaſon of the ſmall ſtringes that are in them but they are verye good to make one to ſpitte out eaſely the fleume that is in the breaſt, extenuate and cleanſe the bodie: and to prouoke vrine competentlie.
            
            
               Of Fruites
               THere be manye ſortes of fruictes, whereof ſome are verye nutritiue, and amonge them figges and raiſons, rype Grapes and Dates in thoſe Regions and Cities where they growe and are muche vſed, but in my iudgemēt they are ſeldome to be eaten and then alſo Figges very temperately for new Figges are windie and (as Galen ſayeth) are ill for the ſtomacke, and the bloude that is engendred of drye fygges is ill, and both of them aſwell the new as the drye bréede

lyce, aſwell becauſe of the corruption of their humour as alſo becauſe they driue matter from the internall partes of the bodie to the externall, and therfore Auicen is of opinion that they be dangerous for the Falling ſicknes and Apoplexſie.
               They are alſo ſayde to make one fatte: but althoughe ſuche fattineſſe continueth but a while, and differeth much from the nouriſhemēt that bread maketh, yet they géeue greater nouriſhement and are of more ſtrength then other fruictes. And becauſe figges do quicklie deſcend and are ſoone diſtributed into euerye parte of the bodie, and mundefie and ſcower the paſſage and way whereby the meate goeth downe, therefore they are beſt to be eaten before other meates. The beſt are of a white colour, redde are next, and blacke are worſt as Auicen wryteth.
               And they haue power to cleanſe the grauell being in the Reines of the backe.
               Drye fygges ſayeth Galen eaten with nuttes, are an excellent meate and likewiſe if they be eaten with Almondes, for ſo, they open obſtructions, but they nouriſhe

not ſo well neither engender they ſo good bloude and iuyce when they be mixed with nuttes. And therebe ſome, which plainly affirme, that drye figges Againſt poyſon eaten with rue and nuttes, are a Soueraigne remedie agaynſte all maner of poyſon. White Grapes are a greate deale better then blacke, ſo that the place Grapes of their growyng and ripeneſſe be like. And thoſe that haue béen hanged vp two or three dayes in the Sunne ere they beeaten are beſt, and moſt wholeſome, and make nouriſhment very néere as good as figges, whiche ought to be eaten before other meates aſwell as figges. For they lenifie the bealy, but much vſinge of them is ill for the bladder, and therefore thoſe that haue the grauell or ſtone either in their Reynes or Bladder muſt forbeare them. For they leaue much feculent and dreggie matter in the body and ſende many fumes to the brayne, as it may appéere by the veſſel wherein the Wyne that is made of them is put. Alſo Grapes &amp; Figges annoy the Bowels and Intrayles drawing them like a

purſe into harde lumpes or kernels, alſo for them that haue infarced themſelues with replecion and ſurphet they be very harmefull. Being olde they looſe muche of their excrementall humiditie.
               Rayſons of the Sunne clenſe the body and comfort digeſtion and be very holeſome Rayſons for the ſtomacke, but ſpecially for the Liuer totally. They are alſo good for the bladder and reynes and for the paine and excoriation of the Bowels and géeue good nouriſhment to the whole bodie and may bothe at beginninge and latter ending of Meales be boldly eaten. Of fruictes which géeue very ſmal nouriſhment or rather none at all to the body, there be ſome whiche paſſe from the ſtomacke eaſilie and whiche ought to be eaten before other meates: and ſome there be, whiche are beſt to be eaten after other meates. Of them that ſhould be eaten before other meate, Auicen amonge other kindes reckeneth theſe, Melons, Pompons, Mulberies, yealow Quinces Peaches, Plummes, Prunes, Sloes, Bullaſſe, Chéeries &amp;c. For theſe kindes

of fruictes engendre very much humour and ſuche as is eaſely corruptible.
               Therefore it is beſt to driue them out of the bodie as quicklie as may be conueniently, whiche by this way and meane may be done, if they be eaten alone with out any other meate and after the eating of them to walke and then to eate ſomethinge to make them ſlipperie and deſcendible. And he ſayeth further, that theſe fruicts being new are good for none but them which are exerciſed &amp; much troubled with redde Choler, and in Sommer ſeaſon, and géeueth counſell alſo that it is beſt to abſtaine from them becauſe they make watriſhe bublinge bloude whiche will ſoone putrefie. Notwithſtanding by reaſon that they be great coolers, they are good for them that be hoate, euen the verye ſame houre that they be eatē, becauſe they be colde and moyſte. Yet this their moyſture engendreth putrefaction and corruption and likewiſe maketh the bloude full of rawe and crude humiditie, as the gréene Melon which is commonly called Auguria: which alſo muſt be foreborne Melon
                  
for an other ſpeciall conſideration, and that is becauſe it is tourned into any humoure that it findeth in the ſtomacke. For if it finde phlegme, it is tourned into phlegme, and if it finde choler it is turned into choler &amp;c. And becauſe ſome peraduenture are deſirous to know theſe aforeſaid fruictes, which be beſt, or rather which be leſt hurtfull I will brieflie run ouer them. And among theſe fruictes, the Melon maketh better iuyce and more nouriſhement then any of the other and is not ſo ſoone conuerted into that humoure which it findeth in the ſtomacke as the gréene Melon called Auguria is: it is abſterſiue and prouoketh vryne, but it muſt be eaten in ſuche ſorte as before is declared, for els it putrefieth, and of his putrefaction cauſeth feruent and ſharpe diſeaſes.
               Mulberies although they haue a certayne ſtipticke vertue, yet dothe Auicen 
                  Mulberies. thinke that they annoy the ſtomack, and in him that is weake, are ſoone turned into corruption and rottenneſſe. They whiche are ſweete are hoate and moyſt,

but they which be tart &amp; ſower are colde.
               Muche like vnto them in nature are Cheries, for they are ſoone corrupted and Cheries putrefied: and thoſe Cheries (vndoubtedly) are moſt wholeſome, whiche are bothe ſharpe and bitter and alſo ſwéete and rype, whiche are commonlie named Maraſchae. For they are not ſo eaſelie corrupted as the other and do refrigerate and coole a great deale better. Al Cherics are cold and moyſt in the firſt degree and of them ſome are ſofte and ſwéete, ſome harde and harriſhe, and whiche do binde more. The firſt ſorte are better becauſe they be ſooner digeſted and deſcend from the ſtomacke quicklier. The ſecond ſorte agrée better to the ſtomacke encombred with choler, becauſe they are vneth at all corrupted and confirme the Stomacke with a certaine binding or aſtrictiue power: but much vſinge of them if they be not tourned into corruption by the inward humours engender watriſhe humoure.
               Peaches and Abrecockes are endued Peaches. A brecocks with a colde and moyſte temperature:

beinge well concocted they make thinne and moyſte bloude. But their propertie is, vnleſſe they be eaten before other meates and goe eaſclie downe the bealy to be turned to corruption and altered into ſuche humours as they find in the ſtomacke. Therfore thoſe that can not eaſelie digeſt them, but haue them longe abydinge in their ſtomacke, I would aduiſe and counſaile not at all to eate of them.
               For Abrecockes being moyſt and new, are muche ſubiecte to corruption and therfore engender Agues and Feuers. Auicen ſayeth that Maſticke and Amſe minged with Wyne made of drie and withered grapes or els with hony ought to be drunke when wée eate Abrecocks. Peaches (ſaieth Dioſcorides) are profitable to the ſtomacke and if they be ripe, Peaches they mollefie and comfort the bealy beyng eaten before other meates: but eaten after other meates, they are bothe corrupted themſelues, and alſo corrupt the other meates that are neere vnto them. Drie Peaches and Abrecockes muſt be eaten not before but after other

ſuſtenance, becauſe they are not onely heauy to the ſtomacke, but alſo géeue very litle nouriſhement. Notwithſtanding Auenzoar ſayeth, that peaches are good for them that haue ſtinkinge breathes, procéeding of diſtemperaunce of the ſtomacke: and as for anye other vertue he ſayeth they haue none. Plummes and Plummes Dameſons. Dameſons are better then they, if they be well digeſted and ſent downe into the mawe, for in ſome perſons, theſe alſo are many times corrupted, by reaſon that they abide longe in the ſtomack ere they be expelled. Plummes that are ſwéete make the ſtomack weake with to much moyſture, but thoſe that haue a meane taſte betwéene ſwéete and ſower are of more force to quenche and repreſſe choler. And as for the coldenes of them (ſayeth Auicen) it may be qualefied by drinkinge honie, water and wine of grapes withered in the Sunne.
               But now it is time for vs to entreate of ſome ſuche fruictes as maye be eaten after other meates. For there are manie whiche let vapours from aſcendinge and

moleſtinge the braine, and whiche do ſtrengthen the mouth of the ſtomacke, of whiche ſorte are Pomegranardes, Quinces, Pomegranardes Sweete Peares and ſuche like. But firſte let vs confuſelie ſpeake of them that maye be eaten either before or after meate indifferentlye. Of Pomegranardes there be thrée kindes, ſwéete, ſower, and mean betwéene both. Swéete Pomegranards beinge colde and moyſte in the firſte degree be very profitable for the ſtomacke and Lieuer, and merueilouſlie helpe and comforte the naturall ſpirites, and are reckened among thoſe things that make a man fatte. They alſo directe and prepare the waies and paſſages of the vrine much better then the ſower do. And therfore they are highlie to be praiſed, and may without any harme be eaten at any time of the yere, but ſpeciallie in Autūne at anye time of meales. They of meane Meane taſte betwéene ſwéete and ſower, are colder then the ſwéete are, and therfore they beſt agree to them that haue hoate Stomackes: and they are of an indifferent good abſtertion with ſtipticitie and refrigeration.

                  Auenzoar telleth a wonderfull vertue that they haue, and Auerrois confirmeth the ſame, that they do not ſuffer anye corruption of the meate in the ſtomacke if it be fumous or like to the ſauoure of Egges. But if the corruption be eigre or ſower, he warneth vs to be ware how we eate them, but ſwéete Pō
                  granardes in that caſe (he ſayeth) do no harme. Sower, are of more coldnes then the other, and are good for non but them Sower which are verye cholerique, becauſe thorough their ſower tartnes they annoye the Entrailes and Sinewes. But yet their tartnes may be alayed and taken away by eating a litle Sugar or Hony or ſome ſuche ſwéete thinge: They haue a great vertue to quenche hoate burninge choler and to repreſſe the euaporation of fumes in the head. To conclude, al Pomgranardes generallie are of a light nouriſhement and euer make thinne bloud, and are very amicable and holeſome for the ſtomacke, and do aboliſhe and driue awaye all frettinge iuyce and byting humours. And therfore thou mayeſt verye

conuenientlie and well vſe them at all times, when thou feeleſt in thy bodie muche heate to abounde, or els when the time and ſeaſon of the yeare ſhall ſeeme to require. For it were but a vaine and ſuperfluous thinge, to vſe ſuche thinges as be taken and reputed for medicinable, none otherwiſe, but as other commō
                  meates vſuallie and daylie taken.
               Quinces among Autumnall fruictes are Quinces reckened in the number of thoſe that are bindinge and ſuppreſſe the bealie. Being taken before meales, they are wont rather to binde and reſtrain the ſtomacke, but after meates they mollefie the bealie and cloaſe or drawe the ſtomacke together, which is not to be merueyled at: cō
                  ſideringe that the mouth of the ſtomacke by a certaine aſtrictiue power which is in them is ſhutte together, and the nouriſhement or meate before eaten, forciblie protruded and thruſte forward, as we ſée by experience in a bottle or in a bladder when we wring hard and thruſt out of them being full the licour.
               In the noumber of fruictes alſo, Seruice

bearies, Cornell bearies and Medlars Seruice bearies Cornel beries. Medlars are of all others moſt conſtrictiue, and may be very well vſed as medicine, but not as meate, becauſe they increaſe no commendable bloude, but bynde the bealie to muche and bringe muche harm to the head and the whole bodie.
               Of Apples, thoſe that are ſwéete (ſayeth Aegineta) haue more power to heate 
                     Apples Lib. 1. Cap. 81 then others, and are more eaſely digeſted, ſpeciallye if they be roſted or boyled. Sower apples do coole more and cutte a ſunder the congeled humoures in the ſtomacke. The harriſhe and roughe taſted apples do confirme the ſtomacke that is weake by diſtemperaunce of heate or muche moyſture and ſuppreſſe the bealy but yet Quinces for that purpoſe more then any others. But in goodnes thoſe apples excell all others that are called Regia poma, which are not altogether ſo colde, and are thought to be very holeſom and comfortatiue to the harte becauſe they repell and driue away al fuligiuous moyſte vapours which trouble the harte &amp; ſtrike vp into the head. Finallie when

the head is diſtempered throughe drinking muche wyne, they haue bene found right commodious to alaye and redreſſe the inconueniences thereof: but they be thought to be hurtefull to the Sinewes and to hebetate or dull the memorie, ſpeciallie if they be of nature ſower. For they be colde ynough and by the ſlyneſſe of there ſubſtaunce pearce and are conueighed euen into the very innermoſte partes. But ſwéete apples whiche are kept til the next winter, are farre better. For beinge then through tract and continuance of time, come to a full ripenes and perfecte maturitie are thereby alſo made more holeſome and apt to be digeſted and are not ſo ſoone corrupted, beinge orderly vſed. For them that haue weake ſtomackes they be excellent good beinge roſted in the aſhes or trimmelie ſodden in water when they be eaten. Peares alſo Peares in like maner being kept they be mellow and fully rype, haue the ſame vertu: but they géeue more plentifull nouriſhement to the eaters and are more pleaſant to the ſtomacke. As for Pome Citrons,

Limons, Orenges, and Adam Apples, ſith they rather ſerue for medicine then for meate, I will here ſay nothing: they that be diſpoſed to know the hiſtorie and operations of them, may at large ſée them moſt learnedly and truely deſcribed and ſet forth by Mattheolus in his commentaries vpon Dioſcorides.
               
               Oliues (although Auicen reckeneth 
                     Lib. 1 Cap. 131 Oliues
                   them, among thoſe fruictes that hurt the ſtomacke and Eyeſight) yet in another place he affirmeth that they beinge conduict in ſalte licour or Pickle, do ſtirre vp appetite, corroborate and comfort the ſtomacke and loſeth the bealie, ſpeciallie if they be eaten with vineigre. And Capers beinge in like ſorte vſed, are right Capers Cheſtnuts commendable for the ſame purpoſes.
               Cheſtnuttes becauſe they are of heauie concoction and engendre groſſe &amp; crude humours (albeit not verye ill) and cauſe windynes very greatly, I iudge fitter to be left to them that vſe labour and much exerciſe. Notwithſtanding they coole and drye and ſomewhat binde: but beinge boyled they nouriſh well and looſe much

of their windines, ſpecially if they be ſodden with the ſéedes of Anyſe or fenell or ſuche like. Haſill nuttes are hoate and drye in the firſt degrée, they cauſe headache Haſil nuts. &amp; inflate ye ſtomack if they be much eatē they be hardly digeſted, they degrauate ye tōgue &amp; hinder ye ſpeach: albeit being new they are ſomwhat more friēdlie to the ſtomack for they bring leſſe harm therunto, although they engender groſſe humours. Beinge eaten with figges, they are the better to be borne withall, becauſe they are ſooner conueighed from the ſtomacke downe into the mawe and thence expelled. But to eats them aloane or often, ſpeciallie out of winter is not ſo holeſome. Filberdes becauſe they be aſtrictiue Eilberdes and reſtraine Reumes and Catarres, might be thought to be profitable to the ſtomacke, but for all that, they are very ill and hard to be digeſted, by reaſō of the thicke ſubſtaunce that is in them, and conſequentlie becauſe they binde the bealie the more. But Auicen commendeth them, becauſe they are good for all Lieuers, by reaſon of the ſmall heate

wherwith they be endued. For they are hoate and drye in the firſte degrée: and therefore they do no hurte ſo a Lieuer that is hoat, and vnto it that is colde they do muche good. Alſo they are aperitiue and open oppilations and obſtructions and make good iuyce in ye bodie: but they inflate and engender windineſſe in the bottome of the bealie, and cauſe headache with augmentacion of the braine. They are ſlowe of digeſtion and prouoke vomite, and the ryndes of them bynde the bealie, and therfore they are but ſeldome and not of al men to be eatē. And if thou happen at anye time to eate of them to driue away the coughe and to helpe ſpettle (for they do eaſely cauſe ſpittinge and heale an inueterate cough) it is beſt firſte to drawe out and extract the iuyce out of the ſubſtance of them: for by that means they are made lighter of digeſtion, the ſubtiler ſubſtance being taken out of the groſſer left behinde. And if a little Anyſe or Cinamome be ſtamped and put vnto them, all their inflation and windines is taken awaye. And both of them as well

the filberd as the haſill nutte, eaten with figges are preſeruatiue againſt all ſmall poiſons as Auenzoar and ſince his daies Auicen haue written. Swéete Almonds Almonds are almoſte equall in heate with theſe aforeſaide, ſauinge that they ſomewhat decline to moyſture, vnleſſe they be vinewed and reſtie, for then they are drye. The nouriſhement which they géeue, although it be ſmal, yet it is good. Alſo they extenuate and cleanſe with out any binding, they do open and comfort the paſſages and veſſelles of the vrine and take awaye all obſtructions, ſpeciallye of the Splene and Lieuer, and they be very ſoueraigne and good for them that haue any diſeaſes in their Breaſtes or Kidneis or haue any inflamation of the Lunges. But becauſe they cauſe Sléepe and tary longe in the ſtomacke (for they be harde of digeſtion if they be eaten alone) they ſend vp fumes and vapours into the head, and trouble it with the Murre and Reume. And therefore I woulde wiſhe that the iuyce ſhoulde be taken out of thē 
                  Almond mylke (whiche is called the milke of Almonds)

and this is the beſt way to eate them beinge made in little diſhes, rather then to eate the whole harde Almondes, ſpeciallie in Autumne. For by this meanes it will eaſely deſcend and bringe muche profit without doinge any harme. Moreouer there is made a right excellent confection, of the Creame of theſe Almonds beinge made in a Ptiſan or the decoction of Barley or ſuche like, but ſpeciallie the fine wheate called Amylum. It is moſt cordiall for them that be ſhorte wynded, or payned with the coughe, and it is beſt to be made in Sommer and Autumne. It ſurpaſſeth any other, and is moſt ſubtile and fine, it eaſely digeſteth, maketh good iuyce and engendreth cleane, thinne and perfecte bloude. The kernelles of Pyne apples are almoſte temperate, for Pyne apples they haue but ſmall heate and moyſture, they géeue ſtronge nouriſhment and the ſame not ill. They are good to help a mā to ſpette matter out of his Breaſt and Lunges, they reſtore and helpe the debility or weaknes of the bodie, they purefie corrupt humours, help the cough, amend

and qualeūe putrified matter of the body and ſtirre vp Venus. They are barde of digeſtion, and further (ſayeth Auicen) there is in them a certaine mordication and ſharpenes: but if they be ſtieped in hoate water, he ſayeth, they are cleane altered from the ſame. For ſo they haue great power and vertue to nouriſhe, and do inferre no hurte to the bodie. He alſo commaundeth them that be of a colde cō
                  plexion and habite to eate them with honie: but them that be hoate of complexiō, he willeth to eate them with Sugar.
               Furthermore they purge the 
                     •
                  eines &amp; cleanſe the bladder, they coroborateth and kepeth them from vlcers, and haue a ſinguler vertue in helpinge them that cannot piſſe. The nuttes called Piſtacia (as Galen wryteth) géeue but little nouriſhement, 
                     Piſtacia 2. De alimont
                   notwithſtanding they are verie good for the Lieuer, clenſinge and expellinge euell humours from the ſame, and makinge way for them to haue paſſage out, and diſcharge it from all harins grieues &amp; encombrances. Auicen ſaieth: that they haue a ſinguler power againſt

the noyſomeneſſe and lothſomeneſſe of the ſtomacke and do corroborate all the ventricles: whiche may plainlye be perceaued by the ſomwhat bitter and ſower qualitie that is in them. And therefore they are good to be mixed with meates, as well for nouriſhement as for medicine, both againſt the infartion of the lieuer, and alſo to ſtrengthen and corroborate aſwell the ſtomacke as the lieuer. Alſo they be good to ſtirre vp Venus, and to make them fatte that are leane, or whiche haue that kinde of conſumption that is called Maraſmus. They be hoate and drye meaſurably, ſo that they maye be thought to be in a manner temperate. In Sommer they may be eaten, ſo that no great quantitie thereof be taken, but in winter they maye be eaten copiouſlie and in greater quantitie, ſpeciallie of thē that are hoate complexioned. The rindes of Cittrons (ſpeciallie if they be condite) Cytron ryndes may be eatē in winter, becauſe they corroborate the heart and the other principall members, as Auenzoar (approuing the opinions of other auncient wryters)

affirmeth. And althoughe by reaſon of there hardnes they be difficultlye digeſted, yet hath it ben, (vndoubtedly) proued that they bringe muche helpe to the ſtomacke, and the mouth being gargarized with the decoction of it, hath a ſwéete breath. Moreouer the flower and leaues of it do comfort the ſtomacke, and ſo doth the wyne or other licoure wherein the ryndes haue bene ſtieped. But as for the meate or inner parte of them within the paringe, is both il for the ſtomacke and breaſt, and alſo engendreth the Colicke, vnleſſe the hurt that may thereof enſue, be preuented and taken away by eatinge clarefied honie and ſome cordiall Spices. Anyſe ſeede I muche commend, becauſe A nyſe ſeede it taketh awaye windines, and openeth the obſtructions of the Lieuer and ſplene not without a certaine ſtipticke vertue. Alſo if a man do ſmell vnto it with his noſe, it cureth the ſwimminge and ache of the head and prouoketh vrine. Fenell is ſomewhat hoater and of ſlower digeſtion, Fenell and géeueth but ill nouriſhement, and is ſomewhat dangerous for exulceracion

and inflamation of the Reines and bladder, notwithſtanding it openeth obſtructions and cauſeth one to piſſe, and alſo hath an excellent vertue to clarifie the ſight, in ſomuche that Democritus y• Philoſopher was of opinion, that Serpents when they come out of their dens vſe to eate of it and to rubbe their eyes therewith. Coriander (of whoſe qualitie Coriandre and temperature Phiſicions cannot agroe for Galen ſayeth it is heate, but Auicen and others ſay it is colde, is ſlowe of digeſtion, and as Auicen witneſſeth comforteth a hoate ſtomack, and driueth fumes (eſpeciallye cholerique) from the head, whereby the ſtomacke is holpen, (which it doth rather by reaſon of the vineigre wherewith it is prepared) but yet it cauſeth dimneſſe of ſight: yea &amp; whiche is more, Dioſcorides ſayeth that it troubleth mans wittes with great ieoperdie of madnes, and in an other place he reckeneth it among poyſons: therefore ofte vſinge of it ought to reiected, and not to aduenture to eate it vpon truſte of anye kinde of preparing whatſoeuer it be, for

ye nature of it cānot be takē quite away.
            
            
               Of Repletion
               FOraſmuche as we haue alreadie ſhewed ſuch kindes of meate and drink as we thought worthy and néedefull to be noted (for we purpoſed not to declare al becauſe that woulde haue bene a longe piece of work and almoſt infinite) now let vs addreſſe our ſelues to ſpeake of ſome other poinctes that are expedient for health, I meane ſuche as amonge phiſicions are reckened in the number of thinges not naturall. And firſte great héede and care muſt be taken, that thou do not infarce nor pampre thy ſelfe with any maner of exceſſe either in meate or drinke: but to take of euery kind of meat Meate. ſuche quantitie, that the ſtomacke maye not be cloyed and glutted with ſacietie, but to leaue eatinge (as it were) with an appetite. For by this meanes, naturall heate retaininge his full power and bigoure, wilbe the better able to concoct

thoſe meates that are in the ſtomacke.
               We muſt alſo haue an eye to conſider the qualities and natures of meates: as if they be ſuche that géeue ſtronge nouriſhement to the body, they muſt ſo temperately be eaten, that we maye leaue a pretie while before our appetite be filled. But of thoſe meates which nouriſhe but lightlye and ſmallie, wée maye eate more largelye. For the one requireth good ſpace ere they be concocted, but the other do ſoone deſcende downe into the bealie. In drinke we muſt vſe ſuch coniecture and quantitie as the meates ſhall Drinke ſeeme to be eyther in moyſture or dryneſſe. It were better to be mixed with the meate by manye ſmall draughtes, then with one great draught at thende of the meale. For the mixture tempereth wel the meate without annoyance, but a great gluttinge draught droweneth the meate and rebuketh naturall heate that then worketh in concoctiō. And although Hippocrates hath left in wryting, yt exceſſe of drinke doth leſſe harme and is more tollerable then the ingluuious repletion

of meate: and Auicen (alledging the opinion of diuerſe others) ſayeth, that to be dronk once in euerie month is holſome Dronkenes and healthfull to the bodie: yet we (becauſe it may do more harm then good and ſpecially in them that haue weake and feeble braines) are, and euer were of a contrarye minde and opinion. Wyne (I cannot denye) is moſt congruent and agréeable to naturall heate: but euen as too muche Oyle quencheth the light of a Lampe, ſo doth exceſſiue bibbinge of wyne, oppreſſe and ſuffocate naturall heate. In ſo muche that manye haue ben brought to their longe home by thys ſuperfluous bollinge and beaſtlie ſwilling of muche wyne. Now, if (perchaunce) thou paſſe beyonde the limittes of ſobrietie and excéede natures meaſure, eyther in meate or drinke, the former erroure and faulte of exceſſe muſte be recompenced with ſpare féedinge and as it were almoſt with abſtinence followinge. For after repletion, abſtinence ought to be vſed as the propre remedie to redreſſe the ſame, and if at diner thou do ouercharge

nature, let thy ſupper be verye little or none at all, and vſe longer ſléepe then at other times thou art accuſtomed, and thē ſome exquiſite exerciſe. But the beſte way of all is, to deſiſt and leaue eatinge and drinkinge, while yet thy ſtomacke woulde ſerue to eate and drinke more.
               For thy hungrye luſte yet remaininge, will within one hower paſſe awaye.
               And that kinde of eating (ſayeth Auicen) is worſte, that maketh the ſtomack heauie: and that drinkinge is moſt vituperable, which paſſeth the boundes of temperaunce and ſwimmeth in the the ſtomacke. Therefore that the meate maye be the better concocted and the more conuenientlye diſtributed into all the partes of the body, let drinke be vſed by a little and a litle at once.
            
            
               Of Emptines.
               EVen as to muche repletion and gurmandize is moſt hurtefull and pernicious: ſo is to muche hunger and abſtinence

moſt noyfull and dangerous. For exceſſe and defect (that is to ſaye ſuperfluitie and wante or to muche and too litle) engender and cauſe (as the phiſicions affirme) manye maladies and diſeaſes. But here to enter into a diſputacion whether of theſe is worſe, neither place nor time will permitte, becauſe our purpoſe is to wryte a compendious Dietary for health, and not phiſicall quiddities.
               Therefore in any wiſe refraine to much abſtinence, becauſe it bringeth great annoyance to the whole bodie, and chieflie The harms of muche hunger or abſtinence. to the ſtomacke which is the ſeruant and officiall miniſter to the whole bodie.
               The whole bodie is thereby harmed, becauſe by to muche abſtinence and hunger his moyſture is withdrawen and diminiſhed, &amp; conſequentlie it is debilitated and made leane, and naturall heate is to muche incended, inſomuche that not findinge humour to worke on, it tourneth his violence and power to the radicall and ſubſtantiall humour, and exhauſtinge that moyſture, bringeth the bodie into a conſumption. The ſtomacke

is thereby annoyed, becauſe beſide the common diſcomoditie and hurt done to the whole bodie, it is alſo replete with rotten and putrefied humours. Therefore at conuenient and ordinarie howers and when appetite well ſerueth (whiche may be knowen by the alacritie or luſtines of the bodie, and when the Stomack is not ouer laden with heauines and pō
                  deriſitie of other meate) and after a conuenable ſpace of certaine howers betwéene meale and meale, it is beſte to eate. The Arabians, appoincted xvi. howers betwéene meale and meale: For they thought it beſt to eate no oftener but thriſe in xlviii. howers or two daies. But I ſuppoſe that ten howers are ſufficient for Studientes and them that be not altogether of hoate temperatures, eſpectallie for them that vſe neither to infarce themſelues with repletion, nor yet to eate meates of harde digeſtion. Some others, very wel, appoincte eight houres to be betwéene meales. But this by the way may not be omitted, that euery one muſte be wayned and reduced to ſuche

and ſo manye meales, as their cuſtome and education hath ben vſed vnto, vnles their cuſtome hath ben verye ill and diſcōmendable, and as their naturall appetite ſerueth them. If thy buſines be ſuch, that thou muſte watche muche of the night, or if thou haue a weake braine or Diner and ſupper a heauines and ſwimminge in thy head, or if thy ſtomacke and power digeſtiue be weake and féeble, it is beſt to take but a light ſupper: but other wiſe, let thy dinner be leſſe in quantitie then thy ſupper, if cuſtome will ſo permitte, whiche in an olde man cannot be altered, but in a younge man by litle and litle (if it be ill) muſt be reduced to better order. For a large ſupper, is by the ayde of ſléepe muche better digeſted, for ſléepe comforteth naturall heate whiche is occupied about the matter wherof procéedeth nouriſhement, and ſo digeſtion is made better, the bodie fatter, the minde quieter and the humours temperater. And in the night the Ayre is cooler and darker, whereby the ſpirittes beinge gathered and collected vnto the inner partes, and

without the cares &amp; functions of ye mind and ſences, are verye conducible to helpe digeſtion. And alſo there is longer time betwéene ſupper and the nexte meale on the morrowe after, then is betweene dyner and ſupper. Notwithſtanding, Cuſtome, as is afore ſhewed, may not be forgotten. Finally at ſupper it is beſt to eat dry meates: and therfore roſted meates are very commendable and beſt then to be lyked, to cutte a ſunder and driue away ſuperfluous humoures, but in the morninge or daye time boyled meates are better.
            
            
               Of Purgation by ſiege or other wiſe.
               IT is expedient and healthfull alſo for a man euerye daye to purge his bodie &amp; exonerate nature by cōueniēt euacuation and tempeſtiuious Sieges or ſtooles Going to the ſtoole. for theſe excrementes of ordure and vrine are matter ſuperfluous and vnſauerie,

which by the natural powers may not be conuerted into fleſhe, but remaininge in the body, corrupt the members, and therefore nature abhorringe them, deſireth to haue them expelled. For as the noble Arrabian Auenzoar ſayeth: All Phiſicions do agrée that in the bealie being not coſtiue, but meaſurably ſoluble and ſofte, reſteth muche of the health and ſoundnes of all the whole bodye, by benefit wherof it is preſerued from manye diſeaſes and namely the Pleureſie. Howe to make the bealie ſo ſuble. But if the bealie be ſore bounde and coſtiue, Raiſons being throughly rype &amp; eaten in winter or at anyother time of the yere with Sugar will helpe that inconuenience. They be (as before we haue declared) great fréendes to the ſtomacke and Lieuer. There be alſo other fruictes but not in all poinctes ſo holeſome as theſe, which are good to be eaten in ſommer and Autumne, of whom we haue ſufficientlye ſpoken before, as Mulberies, Plummes, Damſons, Mellons, Pompons, Fygges and rype Grapes. Which beinge eaten before meate, haue

vertue and power to mollifie and looſe the bealie. And there be other fruictes, which being taken after meate, are ſtipticke, as Peares, Quinces Medlers and ſuch like. Alſo Béetes eaten before meat Beete. are very good, ſpeciallie in the Springe ſeaſon, at which time hearbes haue their moſt ſtrength, vertue and validitie.
               Olde auncient wryters haue highlie extolled Mallowes, whoſe proper office and vertue is to looſe and mollifie the belie: Mallowes. If theſe do not ſuffice, adde the herbe called Mercurie vnto them, or elſe take Mercurie it alone by itſelfe. But if there be in the body great plentie and abundance of humours, we muſt aſſay and trye whether they wilbe reſolued and waſted by abſtinence or diet. For abſtinence (ſaieth Galen) 
                  Diete is one maner of euacuation. And Damaſcene ſayeth, if we may cure any maladie or griefe by dyet, we were not beſt to trye anye other waye, for all thinges touchinge bodily health will fall out proſperouſly. But if their be ſuch abundance of ill humoures, that diette or abſtinence is not hable to purge them, then

muſt thoſe humours be educed and drawen foorth by eaſie and light purgacion, ſpeciallye in two quarters of the yere, Springe and Autumne. In ſommer the the fitteſt purginge are Caſſia fiſtula or a Siruppe of Roſes ſolutiue. But in ſpringe and Autumne, Rhabarbe, Agaricke, and Sene: and alſo the communelie knowen Electuaries as Lenitiue, Diachatolicon, Diaſabeſte: foreſéene that the Ingredientes be well concocted, ſod, and prepared with ſuche thinges as belonge and pertaine to the humour then raigning, leaſt otherwiſe the confection ſhoulde be ouer raginge or endued with any venenoſitie. And the dryneſſe and heate of Rubarbe, Agaricke and Sene, maye be mitigated and taken awaye, if they be mixed with ſuche thinges as be moyſte and colde: of whiche ſorte are Plummes, Sebeſtens and cordiall flowers. And vnto them it were not amiſſe, to put a little quantitie of Anyſe or Cinamome becauſe of the weakenes and imbecilitie of the ſtomacke. And if great extremitie and néede ſéeme to require, to

take ſome purgation or medicinable potion for healthes ſake in a great heate, let the confect be dronk with the waters or rather with the decoctions of Sorell, Endiue, Borage, Violettes, Succorie, Hoppes and Raiſons, accordingelie as it ſhall ſéeme expedient by the aduiſe and counſell of the ſkilfull Phiſicion. Prouided alwayes, that non of all theſe whiche are here rehearced, nor yet of any other, be taken in anye great quantitie. For ſome (ſayeth Galen) are glad when they often and largelie make great Stooles: But the more they be emptied, the more is their bealie bounde within few dayes afterward, whiche to be true, not onlye good reaſon, but alſo daylie experience perſwadeth. And therfore in ſuche caſe it it were better to prouoke ſiegez, by ſome gentle ſuppoſitories of Gliſters or Oyle infuſed at the foundiment, or els ſome other ſofteninge ſubſtance, that may diſſolue the matter which ſtoppeth the paſſage of the ordure in the ſtraicte gutte Colon. But the nature of our Countrey men is (rather thē they would willinglie

vſe thoſe helpes to take confectionate and medicinable drouges downewarde at the mouth then vpwarde at the foundement: feare of diſhoneſtie and a certaine ſhamefaſtnes enforcing them therunto.
            
            
               Of Sleepe.
               ANd becauſe they which are in helth ought to haue a ſpeciall regarde to Sléepe, that it neyther be ſuperfluous nor leſſe then nature requireth, but vſed in due and conuenient moderation, to thende that the commodities whiche come therby may be felte and taken, and the harmes comminge by longe watche auoyded: we will here briefely entreate of both. And firſt, this muſt diligently be inculcate, that neither the one nor the other paſſe meaſure. For beinge vſed out of meaſure (as Hippocrates affirmeth) they bringe ſo muche hinderance and annoyance 2. Aph. 3 Much Sleepe
                   to health as nothing more. For immoderate and too muche ſléepe filleth the body with many humours and retaineth

not onely ſweate but alſo all other ſuperfluities maketh the bodie dull and heauie, weakeneth and in a maner boyleth all the ſenſes and maketh thē blunt and vnapte to honeſt exerciſes, euen as if muche ſtore of aſhes ſhoulde be caſte vpon fier, they couer and quight quenche it out, yea Auicen alſo doubted not to ſay that it dampnified and hurte the ſoule or reaſonable part of man. Contrarily, moderate ſléepe after meate doth moyſten the whole bodie and is thought to humecte euen the very innermoſte partes of the bodie, to ſtirre vp and exuſcitate the powers and vertues therof, to make the actions of the Senſes more freſh and luſtie, to reuiue and quicken the ſpirites Naturall, Vitall and Animall and as it were to refreſhe and repaire the whole bodie new agayne. Beinge vſed before Sleepe before meat. meate, it dryeth vp the bodye, while the naturall heate worketh inwardly extendinge his force and violence againſte itſelfe. For ſléepe is nothinge elſe but a pleaſant and delightfull detention of the ſenſes and a reuocacion of heate into the

inwarde partes of the body: where, if it finde nouriſhment ready to work vpon, it digeſteth and diſtributeth it into all the veines, Arteries and members of the whole bodie. The ſame effect hath it, if it finde crude and rawe humours vnconcocte. Thus ſléepe before meate is commended. But if naturall heat finde no alyment or moyſture inwardlie, then is it too muche incended, and tourneth all his violence againſt the radicall and ſubſtanciall moyſture of the bodye, and for want of other exhauſteth it. Semblably immoderate and too muche watchinge is as Watch hurtfull to the powers and hindereth the chiefe functions of life, for therby natural heate is cooled (as Auerrois ſayeth) like as fier which with too muche moouinge and ſtirringe is blowen abroade and diſpercled. Thereby alſo the ſpirites be reſolued, and the power Animall troubled, digeſtion letted, the body made apte to Conſumptions, the braine debilitate and filled with many noyſome vapours and fumoſities. But moderate Sleepe, as before is ſaide, ſtrengtheneth the vitall power,

and maketh the vertue naturall hable to accompliſhe and completelie diſpatche all her operations, whereof the chiefeſt is digeſtion and concoction of the meate. Furthermore it maketh the vertue Animall to take reſt, and remooueth and taketh away the weakenes and debilitie that commeth by ſtudie and labor. But ſome will ſtande in doubte concerninge the meaſure and time of ſléepe whether it ought to be ſo great and ſo longe as Hippocrates appointeth it. For he ſayeth, that that Sleepe is laudable and naturall whiche lacketh no parte of the night, neither hindreth anye parte of the daye. Whiche ſéemeth to be the cuſtome and maner of men in the auncient time (if we beléeue Homere) who hath diligently deſcribed the maners, rytes and ſtudies of men. For aſſoone as the Sunne is downe, he wryteth and deſcribeth that men ſurceaſſed from their labours and betooke themſelues to reſt: and when the Sunne was riſen and vp, he alwayes lightlie ſéemeth to ſtirre vp and cal men to their buſines and vocatiō.

Whereby he ſignified and ment, that all the night we ought to ſléepe, and all the daye to watche. Neither is it without good reſpecte and conſideracion that the ſame Hippocrates in an other place 1. Aph. 16 wryteth, that ventres in winter and Springe are very hoate and ſleepe verye longe. As concerninge what howers of the daye time are fitteſt to ſléepe in, he in his booke entituled De praeſagiis affirmeth 2. Prae. 11. the morninge to be leſt hurtefull vntill the thirde houre of the day whiche is nine of the clocke. But becauſe common cuſtome may not be forgotten and neglected as he the ſame Hippocrates alſo noteth, therefore I thinke, that wée ought not to ſléepe the whole night longe in winter. For eight houres for the age The time &amp; ſpace of Sleepe and common cuſtome of them for whoſe ſake this ſmall Treatiſe is purpoſelye written, is ynoughe or rather too muche vnleſſe it be in them whoſe ſtomackes are very weake and of ſlow digeſtion. In Sommer let ſléepe be equall with the night in length becauſe thē ye nightes are ſhorte: and it will not be very ill, to

recompence the diſſolution and drineſſe of the Spirites with longer ſléepe and to take a little nappe in the morninge or at noone daies (if néede be) Albeit it is much better not to ſléepe at all at noone, vnleſſe Sleepe at noone common cuſtome be to the contrarie, or elſe that thou feeleſt yt it doth thée good, and guardeth thee from further &amp; worſe inconueniences. For it bréedeth manye moyſte diſcraſies and maladies and maketh humours to fall downe, marreth the coloure of the face and bodie and maketh it ſalowe, inflateth and puffeth vp the Splene, loſeth the ſinewes, cauſeth dulneſſe, weakeneth and enféebleth appetite, and is a foremeſſanger or waymaker to Feuers, Apoſtumations, and Abſceſſes. But cuſtome (as before hath ben often noted) is of ſo great force, that it becommeth and is made nature. For as we daylie ſee by experience that ſome do and haue a longe time accuſtomed themſelues to very ill dyet and to meats of naughtie nouriſhement, and yet haue not thereby béen endaungered and hurt: ſo is it alſo to be thought by Sléepe, ſpecially

when neceſſitie enforceth, as when we haue watched before and our Spirites through heate and labour of the body or mind be greatly diſſolued and wearied. For then they ſéekinge a refreſhing and inſtauracion againe gather and conueyghe themſelues into the inwarde partes, whereby the ſenſes beinge for a time lefte and forſaken, there hapneth Sléepe. For Sléepe is nothinge elſe but a bonde or detencion of the ſenſes, wherby they intermitte their offices and functions for the tyme, and is therefore called by the name of Reſt. But in Sommer ſpeciallie I do aduiſe and counſaile thee for one hower at the leaſt after diner, to ſitte and recreate thy ſelfe wyth reading of ſome light and mery matter, abandoning cares and fancies out of thy minde, and not in any wiſe to ſléepe. For commonlye this reſte doth no leſſe good, yea perhappes it is more holeſome to a great maignye then ſléepe, becauſe it bringeth a commoditie without any diſcommoditie. For thereby the ſpirites are gathered together and (the cogitacions of

the minde being relaxed) are wonderfullie refreſhed and comforted. But if ſléepe wil néedes come vpon thée, and as a thief ſteale vpon thée (for the auncient Sages of Greece tearmed ſléepe by that Epithete) looke that thou ſléepe with thy head vpright, hauing al the windowes of thy chamber faſt ſhutte for the ſpace one hower. But in any wiſe beware of ſléepe immediately after ſupper, for ther ought Sleepe very ill immediatelie after ſupper to be a conuenient ſpace betwéene ſupper and ſléepe, to witte an hower and a halfe at the leaſt. For thou muſt not ſléepe, vntill the meate be deſcended from the vpper parte of the ſtomacke to the lower: which thinge that it may the more eaſelie and ſpeedelie be doone, it ſhalbe beſte after ſupper to walke ſoftely and temperately. For by that meanes ſléepe ſhalbe both the quieter and longer, &amp; the braine ſhall not be ſo muche troubled with fumes and vapours, whiche are wont to ſtrike vp into the heade when the meate tarieth to longe in the mouth of the ſtomacke. If the ſpace betwéene ſupper and goinge to bedde be ſomewhat longe, and

the walkinge hath made the meate to deſcend to the loweſt part of the ſtomack thou ſhalt firſt lye vpon thy lefte ſide, becauſe in this liynge the Lieuer approcheth The maner of lying in bedde better to the Stomack and helpeth the better to haſten digeſtion. To ſleepe proſtrate or grouelinge vpon the bealie is verye good and namelye for them that haue feeble digeſtion, for that kinde of liynge containeth and keepeth in the naturall heate wherewith the meate is concocted. But if ſléepe come vpō thée before they meate be deſcēded from ye mouth of thy ſtomacke, firſt lye on thy right ſide, vntil it be deſcended from ye vpper parte (for ye mouth of the ſtomack is on ye lefte ſide) and then muſt thou tourne thée on the lefte ſide or vpon thy bealie, that the meate may more eaſely be concected in a more fleſhie and hoate parte, not without the helpes and furtherances aforenamed. But lyinge vpright vpon the backe is vtterlie to be abhorred, for it cauſeth manye perillous diſeaſes and fond paſſions, as the Lethargie, the Mare, the Apoplexie &amp;c. and not without cauſe whye:

for this maner of liynge bringeth the humours backewarde to the hinder partes of the bodie and head and hindreth them that they cannot haue egreſſe and vente out by their proper and conuenable iſſues which are the palate and noſethrils. When thou haſt ſlepte conueniently and meaſurablie, thou ſhalt finde an excellent commoditie if thou vſe fricaſie and rubbing ouer thy body, firſt with thy ſhirte ſléeue or bare hande to rubbe and chaufe thy legges, then thy armes, and afterwarde thy whole bodie both before and behinde, and then to put on thy cloathes What is to be done in the mor, ninge at our vpriſinge and goe to the ſtoole, then to rubbe and kembe thy head and to ſtretche thy ſelfe and to waſhe thine eyes (if néede ſo require) with water of Roſes and Fenell, and to cleanſe thy téeth with ſome handſome Toothpicker, and to chawe a litle Maſticke or Galingale, for they drawe ſuperfluous humours from the head and are moſte ſoueraigne both for the head and the ſtomacke. And if thou be driuen to ſleepe ſtraightwaies after ſupper or if thy ſtomacke be full gorged and replete,

or if it be weake and féeble and ſpecially in moyſte and wette weather, it ſhalbe very good to chawe theſe or elſe to ſwallowe downe a grayne or twayne of the whiteſt frankencenſe.
            
            
               Of the Accidentes and affections of the minde.
               ANd foraſmuche as there is a verye great connexion or knittinge together betwéene the bodye and the mind, in ſo much yt many times we ſee ſundry &amp; diuerſe great alteracions of the body (yea now and then) death to enſue, onely throughe carefull thoughtes and phantaſticall immaginacions, it is very requiſite and expedient that vnto the conſeruatiō of the body in good health the minde ſhoulde be in perfecte frame and ſoundnes. And therfore Auicen géeueth De Ca
                        ••
                     . vs a learned note, that wee ſhoulde haue a diligent care to our minde if wee deſire to propulſe and eſchue maladies

and diſeaſes: whiche opinion alſo Galen helde before him, ſayinge that wée muſt abſtaine from the intemperance and deformitie of al theſe paſſions &amp; affectiōs of ye mind, Angre &amp; ſorrow furiouſnes and fear, enuie and thought. For they alinate &amp; bringe a man from the vſe of reaſon, &amp; tranſforme him from that ſtate and ordre that is accordinge to nature. For moderate mirthe helpeth muche to accompliſhe all the offices and functions of the Mirth. minde, ſpeciallie to furder and make excellent concoction: as contrariwiſe heauines and ſorrowe is the greateſt hinderaunce and obſtacle to let it. Beware therefore in any wiſe of heauines or deſparation (for a heauie and ſorrowfull ſpirite ſaieth Solomon drieth vp the bones) 
                     Prouer. 17. &amp;. 25. and géeue thy ſelfe to honeſt mirthe and Chriſtianlike ioye. For as Auicen ſayeth, The often vſe of mirthe diſpoſeth a man to be mery, and thereof come twoo no ſmale commodities. One is, that naturall vertue is corroborated and ſtrengthened, and continual regeneration of the ſpirites is cauſed and verye ſmall or rather

no diſſolution of them at al enſueth. The other is, that the ſame ſpirits thereby are dilated, and conſequently lyfe prolonged. Moreouer it is expedient, temperately to recreate ye ſenſes, as for example, the ſight with viewinge and beholding faire ſhewes and beautifull things, How the ſenſes are properly refreshed and delighted. Sight. Hearing Smelling
                   the hearing, with harmonicall and melodious Muſicke, the ſmellinge, with ſoote ſauours and fragaraunt odours, (ſuch as in ſomer the ſmell of Roſe water is) I do not ſay, Roſes themſelues or violettes, becauſe throughe their moyſtnes, they ſtuffe and fill the head with vapours and fumoſities. But in winter, with the ſmell of Lignum Aloes, whiche comforteth, and cheereth vp the Hart, Braine, Entrailes and all the ſenſes of Man wō
                  derfullye. But beware of too hoate and ſharpe ſauours for they ſend vapours to the braine. The taſtinge, with a meane Taſtinge relice and taſt, as that which is confectionate of Sugar and the Iuyce of Pomegranades or Quinces, thickened by decoction, or ſom other of like temperature, being not harmefull neither excéeding in

the exceſſe of any qualitie.
            
            
               Of Venery or the Acte of Generation.
               THe delectation and pleaſure that cometh by touchinge muſte be well meaſured by mediocritie: for if it Touchinge excéede and be vſed intemperatlie, it reſolueth the ſpirites and naturall heate aboue meaſure, and dryeth vp the radicall moyſture, whereby naturall heate is preſerued and nouriſhed and ſo, daungerous diſeaſes (I will not ſaye death) happeneth vnto man ſooner then otherwiſe by nature they would. Therfore ſithens in the act of Generacion, there is ſo great reſolution of the ſpirites, exceſſe thereof (ſpecially of them that be Studients and leane of bodie) is to be eſchewed. Albeit (as hath ben before often ſhewed) great regarde and accompte muſte be made of cuſtom. We muſt (ſaieth Hippocrates) goe from one thinge to another by litle

and litle and not change vpon a ſodaine. Therfore Galen and before hs daies Ariſtotle in his Problemes affirmeth that 2. Aph. 51 Cuſtome.
                   ſodaine alteracions and changes are verie noyſome to nature, and concludeth how that the Tiranne Dioniſius, being expulſed and driuen out of his Kingdome, fell into a gréeuous maladie and diſeaſe, by forbearing his former laſciuiouſnes and wanton order, becauſe contrari to his cuſtome (which he had before vſed) he ſodainelie gaue himſelfe to continencie, and of a monſtrous whoremonger became a verye chaſte liuer. Therefore let vs conclude with Galen: that the vſe of carnall copulation doth litle or no harme, ſo that ſo muche ſpace and time 
                     Art. med. cap. 86 in the vſe thereof be adhibited, that neyther any reſolution of the ſpirites be felt, and alſo that a man may thereby after a ſorte ſéeme to be lighter then he was before, and to fetche his breath the better and with more facilitie. But this I will further aduouche, which both reaſon and experience prooueth to be true, that it is much better to vſe it ſeldome then often:

becauſe among many other harmes and daungers, which much Coiture and carnalitie bringeth, this is not the leſt, that it weakeneth the heart, debilitateth the The hurt of muche vſing carnall act. braine, and dryeth vp all the bodie, becauſe it waſteth the ſubſtance of the laſt alimēt. For Sperm or Séede of generation is (as Ariſtotle ſayeth) the laſt ſubſtance of profitable aliment. And alſo, as we haue before declared, becauſe through the great pleaſure that is in it, the ſpirits and naturall heate are to muche reſolued and the ſtomacke principallie endamaged: as contrarywiſe, by conuenient continencie and oportune forbearing therof it is cheriſhed and preſerued. It was not without good cauſe that Auicen thought if neuer ſo litle Sperme or Seede ouer and aboue the meaſure and ſtinte of nature, Sperme do paſſe from a man in doing this acte of generation it harmeth him more, then if he ſhould bléede fortie tymes ſo muche. For the Sperme is a thing more conforme to natural heate and moyſture and more ſpiritual then bloude is. Moreouer carnall apetite is a deadlie enemie

to dry complexions &amp; likewiſe to colde: but vnhurtfull (beinge moderately vſed) onely to them that are hoate and moyſte and whiche haue naturally great aboundance of Sperme. Galen ſayeth, that the Venerie whom it hurteth &amp; whom not. De tuend. Sanit. 6. ſtate of thoſe bodies is worſt, which haue abundaunce of hoate Séede, becauſe it doth prorite and tickle them to expell it ſithens both the mouth of their ventres is reſolued, and all their bodie is not onely relaxed and made weak, but alſo they be drye, ſlender, pale, and holow eyed, vnto whome he in that ſame place preſcribeth ſtore of remedies. But if a man woulde abſtaine from very hoate meats and wyndie, and muche drinkynge of How to eſchue venerie. headie wyne and refrayne venerous imaginations, and ſuche like pleaſures, he ſhall not lightly be muche aſſailed and tempted with deſire of any carnall appetite. Likewiſe if he erneſtly addicte himſelfe to the ſtudie of Morall Philoſophie and of the ſacred Scriptures, baniſhinge Idlenes and forbearinge the companye (ſo farre as he conuenientlye maye) of beawtifull damſelles and amorous women.

Or if a man vſe the Séede of Agnos Caſtus (which is alſo called Viter) he ſhall ſée and féele a merueilous effecte to repreſſe his fleſhlie concupiſcence. If thy loynes be to hoate, annointe them with the Oyle of Henbane or Popie, and do likewiſe to thy Genitories, and do not vſe to lye in a ſofte feather bedde. Some there be, whiche coole there Priuities in colde water, and finde thereby a preſent remedie, They that drinke the iuyce of water Lillie (called of the Apothecaries Nenuphar) the ſpace of xij. dayes together, ſhall haue no maner of deſire to carnalitie. And therefore it is good for wiueleſſe Bachelers and huſbandleſſe maydens to drinke, to driue away theire vncleane dreaminge of venerie and the filthy pollutions that they haue by night.
               But in fine, bidde daintie fare a dieu, and vſe not to pamper thy ſelfe with muche gurmandize, but onely ſo muche as nature requireth to kéepe thy bodye in perfecte health and ſoundnes. For there is an olde Prouerbe and a true ſayinge:

                  From frequent Venus, muche cheere and ſleepe, Eche Studient ought, himſelfe to keepe.
               
               I remember that I haue read in ſainct Chriſoſtome, that our Sauiour Chriſte when he dwelled héere amonge vs on earth vſed to eate and drinke ſo litle and ſo ſeldome, that he encreſed not this ſuperfluous Seed. But as in this poinct ſo in many other Chriſt hath but very few Imitatours and folowers wheras (notwithſtandinge) there be many whiche haue ſtill this ſaying in there mouthes how that euery action of Chriſte is our inſtruction.
               But let vs draw towarde an ende of our purpoſe. When nature is deſirous of carnall coniunction and is neither prouoked The time of carnall copulation therevnto by imagination and thought, nor any other outwarde cauſe but with multitude and abundance of Sperme it muſt be vſed in a fit and conuenient time. And that is when the meat is throughlie concocted and yet no hunger nor deſire to eate approcheth: that Sleepe or reſt immediatlie after it, may take away the laſitude gotten and cauſed through the action there of or at the leaſt

mitigate and lenifie the ſame. But if we ſhould erre in either parte it were much better (as Galene ſayth) to offend being replete and armed with a full Stomack then when it is emptie and pynched with ouermuch defect and want of foode. For it is better, that is to ſay, it doth leſſe harme to vſe when the bodie is warme and calefied then when it is cold and infrigidate: and full infarced rather then when it is emptie, and when it is humected rather then when it is drye. But he the ſame Galene taught before, that meaſure and temperateneſſe therein ought to be choſen and obſerued that the bodie neither ſhould be too hoate nor too cold, too moyſt nor too drie, too much replete nor to much emptied. Neither do I heere allow the Law and ordinance of Solon whereby the enacted that a man ſhoulde carnally know his wyfe at leaſt Solons Lawe thriſe in a moneth For often vſe thereof to many men is harmefull, yea to ſome, once is to muche. Againe, this acte is not a thinge neceſſarie to conſerue the partie that vſeth it, but onely to repaire and encreaſe

the Spece or kinde, whiche otherwiſe in ſhort time woulde decaye. Therfore let Solon beinge an heathen Eathnique take his lawe to himſelfe.
               Studientes many tymes are troubled with a phlegmaticke humour deſcending from their heades into their ſtomackes being of them ſelues colde: whiche inconuenience may eaſely be remedied, if they take in the morning a dragme or twaine of the confection named Diatrion Piperion. Or elſe, they may drinke Pepper alone (ſpecially that whiche is white) beinge brayed and put into water, or let them take betime in the morning a litle Ginger condite, or elſe a Chebule condite, which is a kinde of mirobolanes.
            
            
               Of Ayre Holſome and vnholſome.
               AYre althoughe we deſcribe it laſt in order, and what qualitie therof is beſt for bodily health: yet is it a

principall poinct and no leſſe to be regarded then the other preceding. For néedes muſt it inſpi
                     ••••
                  d breath into vs continuallye, that the heart and lunges may therby be competentlye and conuenablie cooled. This among all other, is ſo néedefull and neceſſarie vnto man, that he is vneth able to liue one moment of an houre, vnleſſe new freſh Ayre comming in and out, coole and refrigerate his hart. Therfore vnto all men without any exception, it is hole ſome and expedient, to drawe into lunges, the beſt that is to wit the pureſt Ayre. For corrupte and vnpure Ayre is vnto all age a great backefriende and enemie. Now, the diuerſitie of Ayres, procedinge of heate, colde, drought or moyſtnes, accordeth not to euerie mans nature alike. For vnto thoſe bodies that are of the beſt temperature, the moſt temperate Ayre is holeſomeſt. But in whom, anye excellinge qualitie beareth domination, vnto ſuch, that Ayre is moſte holeſome, whiche in like degrée reſiſteth and oppugneth that qualitie.
               For temperature is altered with contrarious

diete and order, and is conſerued with his like. Thou ſhalt therefore (as farreforth as may be) 
                     〈…〉
                   thy ſelfe to liue neither in a troubled and contagions ayre, nor in that which is very cold, or too hoate, or too moyſt, or whiche is open to vaporous blaſtes and peſtilent windes, ſuch as blowe out of the South. In winter it is beſt to liue in a warme and open Sunnye place, lyinge open to What dwelling is beſt for winter the Caſt: but we muſt alwayes tourne our heads from the Rayes and Beames of the Sunne, ſpeciallye about noone: becauſe beſide calefaction and heate whiche they bring to the head, they do alſo draw vnto it humours and matters, wherfore manye times they cauſe headache and bléedinge at the noſe. But the Rayes or Beames of the Moone are a great deale more to be eſchewed and taken héede vnto, that they ſhine not vpon vs, ſpeciallye when we ſléepe, for they cauſe ill diſeaſes. For aſmuche as the Moone is Ladie of moyſture and mooueth humours. Alſo the night aire is not holeſome, becauſe the Sunne géeuer of life, is gone out of

our Hemiſphere. In winter if the Ayre be troubled and darke (which as Auicen ſaieth maketh ye ſoule ſorrowful) it muſt in part (if it may not in all) be qualified and by ſome artificiall meanes bettered. Whiche is done either by remaining in a houſe, or in ſome couert place, ſhrowded from the ſturdie ſtormes of diſmall Boreas certaine houres of the daye, and alſo by purifinge the Ayre with a good fyer in our Chamber, made with good woodde, or elſe by makinge in it a perfume with Iuniper or Lignum Aloes. In Somer it is beſt to dwell in ſuche a Dwelling for Somer. temperate place, that the windowes of our houſe may open towarde the North or if we will, we may ſprincle our Chā
                  ber with Roſe water and vineigre, ſpecially when the Ayre is corrupt with anye ſtinkinge fauour, or anye other fulſome exhalacion. Auicen praiſeth the Aire of Mountaines and Downes for the Somer time, and thinketh it beſt for a man in the night to lye in the vpper parte or Garettes of his houſe, but in the daye time, he ſayeth the lower roomes are fitteſt

and holeſomeſt. Ariſtotle chooſe him a dwellinge place that ſtoode highe and laye open with proſpectes towarde the South and the Eaſt, in a ſubtile Ayre Choiſe of ayre. neither moyſt nor colde. Plato found verye olde and aged perſons dwelinge in high and temperate regions. And this is to be noted and knowen, that the Ayre in highe places (which by repercuſſion and reflection of the Sunne Beames are not warmed) be cold, and the higher the place is, the colder is the Ayre, Therfore the middle loftes of the houſe are fitteſt for winter, and the higheſt for Somer. You muſte alſo beware, that when yow be hoate yow ſtand not longe in the winde or colde Ayre, becauſe euerye ſodaine alteration and chaunge hurteth nature very muche, and colde, ſtoppinge the pores and paſſages of the humours, hindereth conuenient refrigeration and difflation of vapours: and alſo is a great Enemie to naturall heate, but chieflie to the brain and ſinewes. To be ſhorte, the ſentence and opinion of Hippocrates is alwayes to be ſette before our eyes, whoſe woords

I haue here recited. For he ſayeth, that to euacuate muche and ſodainelie, or to be filled with repletion, to warme, to 1. Aph. 51. coole, or by anye other meanes to mooue the bodie, more then naturall courſe tolerateth, is dangerous. For too much of any thing is hurtfull and a great Enemie to nature. But beinge orderly and by litle and litle done, there is no perill at anyé time. Finallye when the Ayre is hoate, the beſt dwellinge is in a colde Climate and Ayre and to eate ſuche meates as do humecte and coole. In fine, to vſe a colde and moyſte diete, therby to qualitie and countreuaile the heate and dryneſſe of the Ayre. As when the winter is very colde and moyſt, a ſomewhat hoate and drye dietarie is moſt profitable. Nowe, in the beginninge of the Springe, ſuche an order of diete is commended as is exſiccatiue or drye, and in Autumne, a humectinge or moyſte regiment is moſt allowable. But in Somer all dryneſſe and exſiccation muſt be eſchewed. In Somer and towarde the end of the Springe and beginninge of Autumne,

a reaſonable and conuenient order muſt be vſed: But in the beginninge of the Springe and later ende of Autumne ſuche diette to be vſed as was in winter.
            
            
               The whole Summe of holeſome diette.
               IN ſtéede of a finall Peroration, I woulde wiſhe thée (Gentle Reader) to beare well in memorie, howe that to refrain Repletion and exceſſe of meat, to be preciſe and actiue in exerciſe, and to conſerue the Séede of Generation are thrée thinges for healthineſſe of the body moſt holeſome and profitable and forget not, howe that Ariſtotle in his Problemes, imitatinge Hippocrates, referreth 
                     Probl. 47 6. Epid. Par. 4. Aph. 20 all the cauſe of proſperous health vnto temperate moderature of meate and drinke, and an expedient Mediocriture of ſeaſonable exerciſe. But ſithen for our ſinnes and offences aduerſitie &amp;

ſicknes is layde vpon vs, let vs not be ſtiffe necked neither forgetfull ſo ſhewe our ſelues thankefull to Almightie God for whatſoeuer he ſhall ſend vnto vs for our better amendement, and in our vocation and trade of life wherunto we be called verteouſlie, ſoberly, and Iuſtlie, to liue to the honour of Almightie God: renouncing all vngodly wayes and worldlye concupiſcences, expecting and looking for that bleſſed hope and illuſtration of the glorie of God and Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, who offered vp and gaue himſelfe a Sacrifice to redeeme vs from all iniquitie and from the tirranie of the deuill, and to puriefie and make vs a peculiar people to himſelfe, to walke in the pathe of good woorkes and godly conuerſacion of life to his Glory.
            
            FINIS
            
         
      
   

