
   
      
         
            The pleasant historie of Dorastus and Fawnia VVherein is discovered, that although by the meanes of sinister fortune, truth may be concealed; yet by time, in spight of fortune, it is manifestly revealed. ... By Robert Greene, Master of Arts in Cambridge.
            Pandosto
            Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
         
         
            
               1636
            
         
         Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02151
            STC 12292
            ESTC S103413
            99839167
            99839167
            3567
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02151)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3567)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1205:08)
         
         
            
               
                  The pleasant historie of Dorastus and Fawnia VVherein is discovered, that although by the meanes of sinister fortune, truth may be concealed; yet by time, in spight of fortune, it is manifestly revealed. ... By Robert Greene, Master of Arts in Cambridge.
                  Pandosto
                  Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
               
               [56] p.   
               
                  Printed [by Elizabeth Purslowe] for Francis Faulkner, and are to be sold at his shop in Southwarke, neere Saint Margarets Hill,
                  London :
                  1636.
               
               
                  Originally published in 1588 as: Pandosto.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-G⁴.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Running title reads: The history of Dorastus and Fawnia.
                  In this edition, A3r has catchword "tue"; line 8 of text ends: pinching.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-10
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-11
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2005-11
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
PLEASANT
HISTORIE OF
Dorastus and Fawnia. Wherein is diſcovered, that although
by the meanes of ſiniſter Fortune, Truth
may be concealed; yet by Time, in ſpight
of Fortune, it is manifeſtly revealed.
            Pleaſant for age to avoyd drowſie thoughts,
Profitable for Youth to avoyd other wanton
Paſtimes: And bringing to both
a deſired Content.
            Temporis filia Veritas.
            By ROBERT GREENE, Maſter of Arts in Cambridge.
            
            Omne tulit punctum qui miſcuit utile dulci.
            LONDON,
Printed for Francis Faulkner, and are to be ſold at
his ſhop in Southwarke, neere Saint
Margarets Hill. 1636.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE
HISTORIE OF
DORASTVS AND
FAWNIA.
            
               AMongſt all the paſſions wherewith humane
minds are perplexed there is none that ſogalleth
with reſtleſſe deſpight as that infectious
ſore of iealouſie. For all other griefes are either
to be appeaſed with ſenſible perſwaſion,
to be cured with wholeſome counſell, to be relieued
in w
                  •
               nt or by tract of time to be worne out, Iealouſie only
excepted which is ſauced with ſuſpitious doubts, and pinching
miſtruſt, that who ſo ſéekes by friendly counſell to raze out this
helliſh paſſion, it forthwith ſuſpecteth that he giueth this aduice
to couer his owne gui
                  •
               tines. Yea, who ſo is pinched with this
reſtleſſe torment, doubteth all diſturbeth himſelfe is alwayes
frozen with feare, &amp; fired with ſuſpition, hauing that wherein
conſiſteth all his ioy, to be the breeder of his miſery. Yea, it is
ſuch an heauy enemy to that heauy eſtate of matrimony ſowing
betweene the married couples ſuch deadly ſéeds of ſecret hatred,
as loue being once razed o
                  •
               t by ſpightfull diſtruſt, there often
enſueth bloody reuenge, as this enſuing Hiſtory manifeſtly proueth
wherein Pandoſto (furiouſly incenſed by a cauſeles iealouſie)
procured the death of his moſt louing and loyall wife, and
his owne endleſſe ſorrow and miſery.
            IN the Country of Bohemia, there raigned a King called Pandoſto,
whoſe fortunate ſucceſſe in Warrs againſt his foes,
and bountifull courteſie towards his friends in Peace, made
him to be greatly feared and loued of all men. This Pandoſto
had to wiſe a Lady called Bellaria, by birth, Royall, learned
by education, faire by nature, by vertues famous: ſo that
it was hard to iudge, whether her beauty, fortune, or vertue,

w
                  •
               n ſhe greateſt commendations. Theſe two linked together
in perfect loue, led their liues with ſuch fortunate content,
that their ſubiects greatly reioyced to ſée their quiet diſpoſition.
They had not béen married long, but fortune (willing to increaſe
their happineſſe) lent them a Sonne, ſo adorned with the gifts
of Nature, as the perfection of the Child greatly augmented
the loue of the Parents, and the ioy of their Commons: in ſo
much, that the Bohemians, to ſhew their inward ioyes by outward
actions, made Bone-fires and Triumphes thorowout all
the Kingdome, appoynting Iuſts and Turneis, for the honour
of their young Prince: whether reſorted not onely his Nobles,
but alſo diuers Kings and Princes, which were his neighbours
willing to ſhew in their friendſhip they ought to Pandoſto,
and to win fame &amp; glory by their proweſſe &amp; valour. Pandoſto
whoſe mind was fraught with Princely liberality entertained
the Kings, Princes, and Noble-men with ſuch ſubmiſſe courteſie,
and magnificall bounty, that they all ſaw how willing hée
was to grat
                  •
               fie their good wills, making a generall feaſt for all
his Subiects, which continued by the ſpace of twenty dayes;
all which time the Iuſts and Turneis were kept, to the great
content both of the Lords and Ladies there preſent▪ This ſolemne
Triumph being once ended, the aſſembly taking their
leaue of Pandoſto and Bellaria, the young Son (who was called
Carinter) was n
                  •
               rſed vp in the houſe, to the great ioy and content
of their Parents. Fortune enuious of ſuch happy ſucceſſe,
willin
                  •
                to ſhew ſome ſigne of her inconſtancy, turned her whéele
and darkned their bright Sunne of proſperity, with the miſty
clouds of miſhap and miſery. For ſo it hapned▪ that Egiſtus
King of Sicila, who in his youth had béen drought vp with Pandoſto,
deſirous to ſhew, that neither tract of time▪ or diſtance of
place could diminiſh their former friendſhip, prouided a Nauie
of ſhips, and ſailed into Bohemia to visit his old friend and companion:
who hearing of his arriuall, went himſelfe in perſon and
his wife Bellaria accompanied with a great t
                  •
               aine of Lords &amp;
Ladies, to meét Egiſtus &amp; eſ
                  •
               ying him, alighted from his horſe,
embraced him very louingly proteſting, that nothing in the
world could haue hapned more acceptable for him then his comming,
wishing his wife to welcome his old friend and acquaintance;

who to ſhew how ſhe liked him whom her husband loued)
entertained him with ſuch familiar curteſie, as Egiſtus perceiued
himſelfe to be very well welcome. After they had thus ſaluted
and embraced each other they mounted againe on Horſebacke;
and rode toward
                  •
                the City deuiſing and recounting how
being children, they had paſſed their youth in friendly paſtimes:
where, by the meanes of the Citizens, Egiſtus was receiued
with triumphs and ſhewes, in ſuch ſort that he maruelled how
on ſo ſmall a warning they rould make ſuch proparation. Paſſing
the Stréets thus with ſuch rare ſights, they rode on to the
Palace▪ where Pandoſto entertained Egiſtus and his Sicilians,
with ſuch b
                  •
               nque
                  •
               ing and ſumptuous chéere ſo royally, as they
had all cauſe to commend his princely liberality: yea▪ the very
baſeſt flaue that was knowne to come from Sicilia, was vſed
with much curteſie, that Egiſtus might eaſily pereiue, how
both he and his were honoured for his friends ſake. Bellaria (who
in her time was the flowre of courtesie) willing to ſhew how
vnfainedly ſhe loued her husband by her friends entertainemet
vſed him like wiſe ſo familiarly that her countenance bewraied
how her heart was affected toward him▪ oftentimes comming
her ſelfe into his bed chamber to ſée if nothing ſhould be amiſſe
to diſlike him. This honeſt familiarity increaſed daily
more and more betwixt them▪ for Bellaria noting in Egiſtus a
Princely and bountifull mind, adorned with ſundry &amp; excellent
qualities, and Egiſtus finding in her a vertuous &amp; curteous dispoſition,
there grew ſuch a ſecret vniting of their affections,
that the one could not well be without the company of the other:
inſomuch, that when Pandoſto was buſied with ſuch vrgent affaires
that he could not be preſent with his friend Egiſtus, Bellaria
would walk with him into the garden, &amp; there they two in
priuate pleaſant deuices, would paſſe away their time: to both
their contents. This cuſtome ſtill continuing betwixt them a
certain emelantholy paſſion entrring the mind of Pondoſto droue
him into ſundry and doubtfull thoughts Firſt he called to mind
the beauty of his wife Bellaria▪
                the comelines and brauery of his
friend Egiſtus thinking that loue was aboue all Lawes, &amp; therfore
to be ſtaied with no law, that it was hard to put 
                  ••
               re &amp; flax
together without burning; that their open pleaſure might bréed

his ſecret diſpleaſure. He conſidered with himſelfe that Egiſtus
was a man, and muſt needs loue: that his wife was a woman,
and therfore ſubiect to loue: and that where fancy forced friendſhip
was of no force. Theſe &amp; ſuchlike doubtfull thoughts a long
time ſmothering in his ſtomacke, began at laſt to kindle in his
minde a ſecret miſtruſt, which increaſed by ſuſpition, grew at
laſt to flaming iealouſie that ſo tormented him, as he could take
no reſt. He then began to meaſure all their actions and miſconſtrue
of their too priuate familiarity, iudging that it was not for
honeſt affection, but for diſordinate fancy: ſo as hee began to
watch them more narrowly, to ſée if he could get any true or certaine
proofe to confirme his doubtfull ſuſpition. While thus he
noted her lookes and geſtures, and ſuſpected their thoughts, and
meanings, they two ſilly ſoules, who doubted nothing of thishis,
treacherouas intent, frequented daily each others company: which
draue him into ſuch a franticke paſſion, that he began to beare
a ſecret hate to Egiſtus, and a lowring countenance to Bellaria;
who maruelling at ſuch vnaccuſtomed frownes, began to caſt
beyond the Moone, and to enter into a thouſand ſundry thoughts,
which way ſhee ſhould offend her husband: but finding in her:
ſelfe a cleere conſcience, ceaſed to muſe; till ſuch time as ſhee
might find opportunity to demand the cauſe of his dumps. In
the meane time Pandoſtos mind was ſo farre charged with iealouſie,
that he no longer doubted, but was aſſured (as he thought)
that his friend. Egiſtus entred a wrong point in his tables, and
ſo had played him falſe play. Whereupon deſirous to reuenge ſo
great an iniury he thought beſt to diſſemble the grudge with a
faire and friendly countenance: &amp; ſo under the ſhape of a friend,
to ſhew him the tricke of a foe: deuiſing with himſelfe a long
time how he might beſt put away Egiſtus, without ſuſpition of
treacherous murther, concluded at laſt to poyſon him. Which
opinion pleaſing his humour, he became reſolute in his determination,
&amp; the better to bring the matter ſo paſſe hee called to
him his Cup-bearer with whom in ſecret he brake the matter?
promiſing him for the performance thereof▪ 
               
                  •
               to giue him a thouſan
                  •
               
Crowns of yeerely▪ reuenue▪ His cup-bearer, either being
of a good conſcience be willing for faſhions ſake to deny ſuch a

                  〈◊〉
                requeſt, began with great reaſons to perſwade Pandoſto
               
from his determinate miſchiefe: ſhewing him what an offence
murther was to the gods, how much vnnaturall actions did more
diſpleaſe the heauens, then men: and that cauſeleſſe cruelty did
ſeldome or neuer eſcape without reuenge: hée laid before his
face, that Egiſtus was his friend, a King, and one that was come
into this Kingdome, to confirme a league of perpetuall amity
betwixt them, that hee had, and did ſhew him a moſt friendly
countenance: how Egiſtus was not onely honoured of his owne
people by obedience, but alſo loued of the Bohemians for his courteſie:
And that it hee now ſhould without any iuſt or manifeſt
cauſe, poyſon him, it would not only be a great diſhonour to his
Maieſty, and a meanes to ſow a perpetuall enmity betwéen the
Sycilians and the Bohemians, but alſo his own ſubiects would repine
at ſuch trecherous cruelty. Theſe and ſuch like perſwaſions
of Franion (for ſo was his cap-bearer called) could no whit preuaile
to diſwade him from his diuelliſh enterprize: but remaining
reſolute in his determination (his fury ſo fixed with rage, as
it could not be appeaſed with reaſon) he began with bitter taunts
to take up his man, and to lay before him two baits, preferment
and death: ſaying, that if he would poyſon Egiſtus, hée would
aduance him to high dignities: if he refuſed to doe it of an obſtinate
minde, no torture ſhould be too great to requite his diſobedience.
Franion, ſéeing that to perſwade Pandoſto any more, was
but to ſtriue againſt the ſtreame, conſented as ſoone as opportunity
would giue him leaue, to diſpatch Egiſtus: wherewith Pandoſto
remained ſomewhat ſatisfied, hoping now hee ſhould be
fully reuenged of ſuch miſtruſted iniuries, intending alſo as ſoone
as Egiſtus was dead, to giue his wife a ſop of the ſame ſauce,
and ſo to be rid of thoſe which are the cauſe of his reſtleſſe ſorrow:
while thus he liued in this hope, Franion being ſecret in his
chamber, began to meditate with himſelfe in theſe termes.
            AH Franion, treaſon is loued of many, but the traytor hated
of all, vniuſt offences may for a time eſcape without danger,
but neuer without reuenge. Thou art ſeruant to a King, and
muſt obey at command: yet, Franion, againſt law and conſcience
it is not good to reſiſt a tyrant with armes, nor to pleaſe an vniuſt
King with obedience. What ſhalt th
                  •
               u doe? Folly refuſed

gold, and frenzy preferment; wiſdome ſéeketh after dignity, and
counſell looketh for gaine: Egiſtus is a ſtranger to thée, and
Pandoſto thy Soueraigne: Thou haſt little cauſe to reſpect the
one, and oughteſt to haue great care to obey the other. Thinke
this Franion, that a pound of Gold is worth a Tunne of leade:
great gifts are little gods; and preferment to a meane man is
a whet-ſtone to courage. There is nothing ſwéeter than promotion,
nor lighter than report: care not then though moſt count
thée a traytor, ſo all call thée rich. Dignity, Franion, aduanceth
thy poſterity, and euill report can but hurt thy ſelfe. Know this,
where Eagles build, Faulcons may prey; where Lions haunt,
Foxes may ſteale. Kings are knowne to command, ſeruants
are blameleſſe to conſent: feare not thou then to lift at Egiſtus,
Pandoſto ſhall beare the burthen. Yea, but Franion, conſcience
is a worme that euer biteth, but neuer ceaſeth. That which is
rubbed with the ſtone Galactities, will neuer be hot. Fleſh dipped
in the Sea Aegeum, will neuer be ſwéete. The Herbe
Trigion, being once bit with an Apſis, neuer groweth: and conſcience
once ſtained with innocent blood, is alwaies tyed to a
guilty remorſe. Preferre thy content before riches, and a cleare
minde before dignity: ſo being poore, thou ſhalt haue rich peace,
or elſe rich, thou ſhalt enioy diſquiet.
            
               FRanion hauing muttered out theſe, or ſuch like words, ſéeing
either he muſt die with a cleare minde, or liue with a ſpotted
conſcience: hée was ſo cumbred with diuers cogitations, that
hée could take no reſt, vntill at laſt he determined to breake the
matter to Egiſtus: but fearing that the King ſhould either ſuſpect,
or heare of ſuch matters, hée concealed the deuice till opportunity
would permit him to reueale it. Lingring thus in
doubtfull feare, in an Euening he went to Egiſtus lodging, and
deſirous to ſpeake with him of certaine affaires that touched the
King, after all were commanded out of the Chamber, Franion
made manifeſt the whole conſpiracy which Pandoſto had deuiſed
againſt him, deſiring Egiſtus not to account him a traytor
for bewraying his Maſters counſell, but to thinke that hée did
it for conſcience: hoping that although his Maſter inflamed
with rage, or incenſed by ſome ſiniſter reports, or ſlanderous

ſpéeches, had imagined ſuch cauſeleſſe miſchiefe, yet when time
ſhould pacifie his anger, and try thoſe tale-bearers but flattering
Paraſites, then he would count him as a faithfull ſeruant,
that with ſuch care had kept his Maſters credit. Egiſtus had
not fully heard Franion tell forth his tale, but a quaking feare
poſſeſſed all his limmes, thinking that there was ſome treaſon
wrought, and that Franion did but ſhadow his craft with theſe
falſe colours: wherefore hée began to waxe in choller, and ſaid,
that he doubted not Pandoſto, ſith hée was his friend, and there
had neuer as yet béene any breach of amity: he had not ſought
to inuade his Lands, to conſpire with his enemies, to diſſwade
his Subiects from their allegians: but in word and thought
he reſted his at all times: he knew not therefore any cauſe, that
ſhould moue Pandoſto to ſéeke his death, but ſuſpected it to be a
compacted knauery of the Bohemians, to bring the King and
him at oddes. Franion ſtaying him in the midſt of his talke,
told him, That to dally with Princes was, with the Swannes
to ſing againſt their death, and that if the Bohemians had intended
any ſuch miſchiefe, it might haue béene better brought
to paſſe, than by reuealing the conſpiracy: therefore his Maieſty
did ill, to miſconſtrue of his good meaning, ſith his intent
was to hinder treaſon, not to become a Traytor: and to
confirme his promiſes. If it pleaſed his Maieſty to flye into
Sycilia, for the ſafegard of his life, hee would goe with him:
add if then hée found not ſuch a practice to be pretended, let his
imagined treachery be repayed with moſt monſtrous torments.
Egiſtus hearing the ſolemne proteſtations of Franion,
beganne to conſider, that in Loue and Kingdomes neither
Faith nor Law is to be reſpected: doubting that Pandoſto
thought by his death to deſtroy his men, and with ſpéedie
Warre to inuade Sycilia. Theſe and ſuch doubts throughly
weighed, hée gaue great thankes to Franion, promiſing, if
he might with life returne to Syracuſa, that he would create
him a Duke in Sycilia: crauing his counſell how hée might
eſcape out of the Countrey. Franion, who hauing ſome ſmall
ſkill in Nauigation, was well acquainted with the Ports and
Hauens, and knew euery danger of the Sea, ioyning in counſell
with the Maſter of Egiſtus Nauy, rigged all their ſhips,

and ſetting them afloat, let them lie at anchor, to be in the more
readineſſe, when time and wind ſhould ſerue. Fortune, although
blinde, yet by chance fauouring this iuſt cauſe, ſent them within
ſix daies a good gale of winde: which Franion ſéeing fit for their
purpoſe, to put Pandoſto out of ſuſpition, the night before they
ſhould ſayle, hée went to him, and promiſed, that the next day he
would put the deuice in practice; for hée had got ſuch a forcible
poyſon, as the very ſmell thereof would procure ſudden death.
Pandoſto was ioyfull to heare this good newes, and thought euery
houre a day, till he might be glutted with bloody reuenge: but
his ſuit had but ill ſucceſſe: for Egiſtus fearing that delay might
bréed danger, and willing that the graſſe ſhould not be cut from
vnder his féete, taking bag and baggage, by the helpe of Franion
conueyed himſelfe and his men out at the Poſterne gate of the
City, ſo ſecretly, and ſpéedily, that without any ſuſpition they
got to the Sea ſhore: where, with many a bitter curſe taking
their leaue of Bohemia, they went aboard, weighing their Anchors,
and hoyſting ſaile, they paſſed as faſt as winde and Sea
would permit toward Cycilia: Egiſtus being a ioyfull man that
he had ſafely paſſed ſuch trecherous perills. But as they were
quietly floating on the ſea, Pandoſto and his Citizens were in
an vprore: for ſéeing that the Cycilians without taking their
leaue were fled away by night, the Bohemians feared ſome treaſon,
and the King thought that without queſtion his ſuſpition
was true, ſéeing the Cup bearer had bewrayed the ſumme of his
ſecret pretence. Whereupon he began to imagine that Franion
and his wiſe Bellaria had conſpired with Egiſtus, and that the feruent
affection ſhe bare him, was the only meane of his ſecret departure,
inſomuch, that incenſed with rage, he commanded that
his wife ſhould be carried ſtraight to priſon, vntill they heard
further of his pleaſure. The Guards vnwilling to lay their
hands on ſuch a vertu
                  •
               us Princeſſe, and yet fearing the Kings
fury, went very ſorrowfully to fulfill their charge: comming
to the Quéenes Lodging, they found her playing with her
young Sonne Garinter, vnto whom with teares doing their
meſſage, Bellaria, aſtoniſhed at ſuch a hard cenſure, and finding
her cleare conſcience a ſure aduocate to plead in her cauſe,
went to the Priſon moſt willingly: where with ſighes and

teares ſhe paſt away the time, till ſhe might come to her tryall.
            But Pandoſto, whoſe reaſon was ſuppreſſed with rage, and
whoſe vnbridled Folly wks incenſed with fury, ſéeing Franion
had bewrayed his ſecrets, and that Egiſtus might well be railed
on, but not reuenged, determined to wreake all his wrath on
poore Bellaria. Hee therefore cauſed a generall proclamation to
be made through all his Realmè, that the Quéene and Egiſtus
had by the helpe of Franion, not onely committed moſt iuceſtuous
adultery, but alſo had conſpired the Kings death: whereupon
the traytor Franion was fled away with Egiſtus, and Bellaria
was moſt iuſtly impriſoned. This Proclamation being once
blazed through the countrey, although the vertuous diſpoſition
of the Quéene did halfe diſcredit the contents, yet ſo ſudden and
ſpéedy meſſage of Egiſtus, and the ſecret departure of Franion induced
them (the circumſtances throughly conſidered) to thinke
that both the Proclamation was true, and the King greatly enuied:
yet they pittied her caſe, as ſorrowfull that ſo good a Lady
ſhould be croſſed with ſuch aduerſe Fortune. But the King,
whoſe reſtleſſe rage would admit no pitty, though that although
hee might ſufficiently requite his wiues falſhood with
the bitter plague of pinching penury, yet his minde ſhould neuer
be glutted with reuenge, till hée might haue a fit and opportunity
to repay the trechery of Egiſtus with a fatall iniury.
But a curſt Cow hath oftentimes ſhort hornes, and a willing
minde but a weake arme. For Pandoſto, although he felt that
reuenge was a ſpurre to warre, and that enuy alwaies proffereth
ſtéele, yet he ſaw, that Egiſtus was not onely of great puiſſance
and proweſſe to withſtand him, but had alſo many Kings
of his alliance to aid him, if néed ſhould ſerue: for hee married
the Emperous daughter of Ruſſia. Theſe and the like conſiderations
ſomething daunted Pandoſto his courage, ſo that he was
content rather to put vp a manifeſt iniury with peace, then
hunt after reuenge, diſhonour and loſſe: determining, ſince
Egiſtus had eſcaped ſcot-frée, that Bellaria ſhould pay for all at an
vnreaſonable price.
            Remaining thus reſolute in his determination, Bellaria
continuing ſtill in priſon, and hearing the contents of the Proclamation,
knowing that her minde was neuer touched with

ſuch affection, nor that Egiſtus had euer offered her ſuch diſcourteſie,
would gladly haue come to her anſwer, that both ſhe might
haue knowne her iuſt accuſers, and cléered her ſelfe of that
guiltleſſe crime.
            But Pandoſto was ſo enflamed with rage, and infected with
iealouſie, as he would not vouchſafe to heare her, nor admit any
iuſt excuſe: ſo that ſhée was faine to make a vertue of her néed,
and with patience to heare theſe heauy iniuries. As thus ſhée
lay croſſed with calamities (a great cauſe to increaſe her griefe)
ſhée found her ſelfe quicke with childe: which as ſoone as ſhe felt
ſtirre in her body, ſhée burſt forth into bitter teares, exclaiming
againſt Fortune in theſe termes.
            ALas, Bellaria, How infortunate art thou, becauſe fortunate!
Better thou hadſt béene borne a Begger then a Prince, ſo
ſhouldeſt thou haue bridled Fortune with want, where now ſhée
ſporteth her ſelfe with thy plenty? Ah happy life, where poore
thoughts, and meane deſires liue in ſecure content, not fearing
Fortune, becauſe too low. For Fortune, thou ſéeſt now, Bellaria,
that care is a companion to Honour, not to pouerty: that high
Cedars are cruſhed with tempeſts, when low ſhrubs are not
touched with the winde: precious Diamonds are cut with the
File, when deſpiſed Pebbles lies ſafe in the ſand: Delphos
is ſought to by Princes, not Beggers: And Fortunes Altars
ſmoke with Kings preſents, not with poore mens gifts. Happy
are ſuch, Bellaria, that curſe Fortune for contempt, not feare:
and may wiſh they were not ſorry they haue béene. Thou art a
Princeſſe, Bellaria, and yet a priſoner: borne to the one by deſcent,
aſſigned to the other by deſpight: accuſed without cauſe,
and therefore oughteſt to die without care: for patience is a
ſhield againſt Fortune, and a guiltleſſe mind yéeldeth not to ſorrow.
Ah, but infamy galleth vnto death, and liueth after death:
Report is plumed with Times Feathers, and Enuy oftentimes
ſoundeth Fames Trumpet: the ſuſpected Adultery ſhall flie in
the Ayre, and thy knowne vertues ſhall lie hid in the Earth:
one Mole ſtaineth a whole Face; and what is once ſpotted with
Infamy, can hardly be worne out with Time. Die then,
Bellaria, Bellaria, die, for if the gods ſhould ſay, thou art guiltleſſe,

leſſe, yet Enuy would heare the gods, but neuer beléeue the
gods. Ah, hapleſſe wretch, ceaſe theſe Termes: Deſperate
thoughts are fit for them that feare ſhame, not for ſuch as hope
for credit. Pandoſto hath darkened thy Fame, but ſhall neuer
diſcredit thy Vertues. Suſpition may enter a falſe Action, but
proofe ſhall neuer put in his Plea. Care not then for Enuy ſith
Report hath a bliſter on her Tongue: and let ſorrow bite them
which offend, not touch thée that art faultleſſe. But alas, poore
Soule, how canſt thou but ſorrow? Thou art with Childe, and
by him, that in ſtead of kinde pity, pincheth thée in cold Priſon.
And with that, ſuch gaſping ſighes ſtopping her breath that ſhée
could not vtter any more words, but wringing her hands, and
guſhing forth ſtreames of teares, ſhée paſſed away the time with
bitter complaints.
            THe Iaylor pittying thoſe her heauy paſſions, thinking that
if the King knew ſhe were with childe, he would ſomewhat
appeaſe his fury, and releaſe her from priſon, went in all haſt, and
certified Pandoſto, what the effect of Bellaria's complaint was:
who no ſooner heard the Iaylor ſay ſhe was with childe, but as
one poſſeſſed with a frenzie, hée roſe vp in a rage, ſwearing that
ſhée, and the baſtard brat ſhée was withall ſhould die, if the gods
themſelues ſaid no: thinking ſurely by computation of time,
that Egiſtus, and not he, was father to the child. This ſuſpitious
thought galled afreſh his halfe-healed Sore, inſomuch as hée
could take no reſt, vntill hée might mittigate his choler with a
iuſt reuenge, which happened preſently after. Bellaria was
brought to bed of a faire and beautifull▪ Daughter, which no ſooner
Pandoſto heard, but he determined that both Bellaria and the
young Infant ſhould be burned with fire. His Nobles hearing
of the Kings cruell ſentence, ſought by perſwaſions to diuert him
from his bloody determination: ſaying before his face, the innocency
of the childe, and vertuous diſpoſition of his wife how
ſhe had continually loued and honoured him ſo tenderly, that
without due proofe he could not, nor ought not to appeach her of
that crime: and if ſhe had faulted, yet it were more honorable
to pardon with mercy, then to puniſh with extremity, and more
Kingly to be commended of pitty, then to diſcredit her. And

as for the Childe, if he would puniſh it for the mothers offence,
it were to ſtriue againſt nature and iuſtice; and that vnnaturall
actions doe more offend the gods, then men: how cauſeleſſe cruelty,
nor innocent blood neuer eſcapes without reuenge. Theſe
and ſuch like reaſons could not appeaſe his rage, but hée reſted
reſolute in this, that Bellaria being an Adultreſſe, the childe was
a baſtard, and hee would not ſuffer that ſuch an infamous Brat
ſhould call him Father. Yet at laſt (ſéeing his noble men were
importunate vpon him) hée was content to ſpare the childs life.
and yet to put it to a worſe death. For he found out this deuice,
that ſéeing (as hée thought) it came by Fortune, ſo hée would
commit it to the charge of Fortune, and therefore hee cauſed a
little cock-boate to be prouided, wherein hee meant to put the
babe, and then ſend it to the mercies of the ſeas, and the deſtinies.
From this his Péeres in no wiſe could perſwade him, but
that he ſent preſently two of his Guard to fetch the childe: who
being come to the priſon, and with wéeping teares recounting
their Maſters meſſage, Bellaria no ſooner heard the rigorous reſolution
of her mercileſſe huſband, but ſhee fell downe in a
ſwound, ſo that all thought ſhée had béene dead: yet at laſt being
come to her ſelfe, ſhe cried and ſcréeked out in this wiſe.
            ALas, ſwéete infortunate Babe, ſcarce borne before enuied
by fortune, would the day of thy birth had béene the terme
of my life: then ſhouldeſt thou haue made an end to care, and
preuented thy Fathers rigour. Thy faults cannot yet deſerue
ſuch hatefull reuenge, thy daies are too ſhort for ſo ſharpe a
doome: but thy vntimely death muſt pay thy Mothers debts,
and her guiltleſſe crime muſt be thy gaſtly curſe. And ſhalt
thou ſwéet Babe, be committed to Fortune, when thou art already
ſpighted by Fortune? Shall the ſeas be thy harbour, and
the hard boat thy cradle; Shall thy tender mouth, in ſtead of
ſwéete kiſſes, be nipped with bitter ſtormes? Shalt thou haue
the whiſtling windes for thy Lullaby, and the ſalt ſea ſome in
ſtead of ſwéet Milke? Alas, what deſtinies would aſſigne ſuch
hard hap? What father would be ſo cruell? Or what gods will
not reuenge ſuch rigour? Let me kiſſe thy lips (ſwéete Infant)
and wet thy tender chéekes wilh my teares, and put this chaine

about thy little necke: that if Fortune ſaue thée, it may helpe
to ſuccour thée. Thus, ſince thou muſt goe to ſurge in the gaſtfull
Seas, with a ſorrowfull kiſſe I bid thée fare well, and I pray
the gods thou maiſt farewell. Such and ſo great was her griefe,
that her vitall Spirits being ſuppreſt with ſorrow, ſhee fell
againe downe in a trance, hauing her ſenſes ſo ſtopped with care,
that after ſhe was reuined, yet ſhee loſt her memory, and lay for
a great time without mouing, as one in a trance. The Guard
left her in this perplexity, and carried the childe to the King:
who quite deuoid of pity, commanded that without delay it
ſhould be put into the Boat, hauing neither Saile nor Rudder to
guide it, and ſo to be carried into the midſt of the Sea, and there
left to the windes and the waues, as the Deſtinies pleaſe to appoint.
The very Ship-men, ſéeing the ſwéet countenance of the
young Babe, began to accuſe the King of rigour, and to pity the
childs hard Fortune: but feare conſtrained them to that which
their nature did abhorre: ſo that they placed it in one of the
ends of the Boat, and with a few gréene boughes made a homely
Cabbin to ſhroud it, as well as they could, from wind and weather.
Hauing thus trimmed a Boat, they tyed it to a Ship, and
ſo haled it into the maiue Sea, and then cut in ſunder the Cord:
which they had no ſooner done, but there aroſe a mighty Tempeſt,
which toſſed the little Boat ſo vehemently in the waues,
that the Ship-men thought it could not continue long without
ſincking: yet the ſtorme grew ſo great, that with great labour
and perill they got to the ſhore. But leauing the Childe to her
Fortunes, wee will returne to Pandoſto: who not yet glutted
with ſuffcient reuenge, deuiſed which way he ſhould beſt increaſe
his wiues calamity. But firſt aſſembling his Nobles &amp; Councellours,
hee called her (for the more reproach) in open Court,
where it was obiected againſt her, that ſhe had committed adultery
with Egiſtus, and conſpired with Franion to poyſon Pandoſto
her huſband; but their pretence being partly ſpyed, ſhée
counſelled them to flie away by night, for their better ſafety.
Bellaria (who ſtanding like a priſoner at the Barre, and féeling
in her ſelfe a cléere conſcience to withſtand her falſe accuſers)
ſéeing no leſſe then death could pacifie her Huſbands wrath,
waxed bold, and deſired that ſhée might haue Law and Iuſtice:

(for mercy ſhe neither craved nor hoped) and that thoſe periured
wretches, which had falſely accuſed her to the King, might
be brought before her face to give in evidence. Pandoſto (whoſe
rage and iealouſie was ſuch, as no reaſon nor equity could appeaſe)
told her, that for her accuſers, they were of ſuch credit,
as their words were ſufficient witnes and that the ſodaine and
ſecret flight of Egiſtus and Franion confirmed that which they
had confeſſed; and as for her, it was her par to deny ſuch a
monſtrous crime, and to be impudent in forſwearing the fact,
ſince ſhée had paſſed all ſhame in committing the fault: but her
countenance ſhould ſtand for no coyne: for as the baſtard which
ſhée bare was ſerved, ſo ſhée ſhould with ſome cruell death bée
requited. Bellaria no whit diſmaid with this rough reply, told
her Husband Pandoſto that hée ſpake upon choller, and not
conſcience; for her vertuous life had ever beene ſuch, as no
ſpot of ſuſpition could ever ſtaine it. And it ſhée had borne a
friendly countenance to Egiſtus, it was in reſpect he was his
friend, and not for any luſting affection: therefore if ſhée were
condemned without any further proofe, it was rigour and not
Law. The Noble-men which ſate in Iudgement▪ ſaid that
Bellaria ſpake reaſon, and intreated the King that her accuſers
might bee openly examined, and ſworne: if then the evidence
were ſuch as the Iury might finde her guilty (for ſeeing ſhe was
a Prince▪ ſhée ought to be tried by the Péeres) then let her have
ſuch puniſhment as the extremity of the Law will aſſigne to
ſuch malefactors. The King preſently made anſwer that in
this caſe hee might, and would diſpence with the Law. And
that the Iury being once pannelled, they ſhould take his word
for ſufficient evidence otherwiſe hee would make the proudeſt
of them repent it. The Noblemen ſéeing the King in choller
were all whiſt, but Bellaria, whoſe life hung in the ballance,
fearing more perpetuall infamy, then momentany death, told
the King, if his fury might ſtand for a Law, that it were vaine
to have the Iury yéeld their verdict, and thereupon ſhe fell down
upon her knées, and deſired the King, that for the love he bare
to his yong Sonne Garinter, whom ſhée brought into the world
that hee would grant her requeſt, the which was this, that it
would pleaſe his Maieſtie to ſend ſixe of his Noblemen whom

hée beſt truſted to the Iſle of Delphos, there to inquire of the
Oracle of Apollo, whether ſhée had committed adultery with
Egiſtus, or conſpired to poyſon him with Franion: and if the
god Apollo, who by his divine eſſence knowes all ſecrets, gave
anſwer that ſhe was guilty, ſhee was content to ſuffer any torment,
were it never ſo terrible. The requeſt was ſo reaſonable,
that Pandoſto could not for ſhame deny it, unleſſe he would
bée counted of all his Subiects more wilfull then wiſe. Hée
therefore agréed, that with as good ſpéed as might bée, there
ſhould be certaine Ambaſſadors diſpatcht to the Iſle of Delpos:
and in the meane ſeaſon he commanded that his wife ſhould be
kept in cloſe Priſon. Bellaria having obtained this grant, was
now more carefull of her little Babe that floated on the Seas,
then ſorrowfull for her owne miſhay; for of that ſhee doubted;
but of herſelfe ſhe was aſſured: knowing that if Apollo ſhould
giue ſentence according to the thoughts of her heart, yet the
ſentence ſhould goe on her ſide, ſuch was the cléereneſſe of her
mind in this caſe. But Pandoſto (whoſe ſuſpicious head ſtill
remained in one ſong) choſe out ſixe of his Nobility, whom he
knew were ſcarce indifferent men in the Quéenes behalfe, and
prouiding all things fit for their iourney, ſent them to Delphos.
They willing to fuffill the Kings command, and deſirous to
ſée the ſituation and cuſtome of the Iſland, diſpatched their affaires
with as much ſpéed as might bée, and embarked themſelues
to the voyage, which, (the wind and weather ſeruing fit
for their purpoſe) was ſoone ended. For within thrée wéekes
they arriued at Delphos: where they were no ſooner ſet on
Land, but with great deuotion they went to the Temple of Apollo
and there offering ſacrifice vnto the god, and gifts to the
Prieſt, as the cuſtome was, they humbly craued an anſwer of
their demand. They had not long knéeled at the Altar, but Apollo
with a loud vo
                  •
               ce ſaid: Bohemians what yée find behind
the Altar, take and depart. They forthwith obeyed the Oracle,
found a ſcrowle of parchment, wherin were written theſe
words in letters of Gold.
            
               
                  
                     
                        The Oracle.
                        Suſpition is no proofe: Jealouſie is an vnequall Judge: Bellaria
is chaſte: Egistus blameleſſe: Franion a true Subject:

Pandoſto trech
                              •
                           rous, his Babe innocent, and the King ſhall die
without an heire, if that which is loſt be not found.
                     
                  
               
            
            AS seene as they had taken out this ſcrowle, the Prieſt of
the god commanded them, that they ſhould not preſume to
reade it before they came to the preſence of Pandoſto, unleſſe
they would incurre the diſpleaſure of Apollo. The Bohemian
Lords carefully obeying his command, taking their leaue of
the Prieſt, with great reuerence departed out of the Temple
and went to their Ships: and as ſoone as Wind would permit
them, ſayled towards Bohemia, where in ſhort time they ſafely
arriued, and with great Triumph iſſuing out of their ſhips,
went to the Kings Palace, whom they found in his Chamber,
accompanied with other Noble-men. Pandoſto no ſooner ſaw
them, but with a merry countenance he welcomed them home,
asking, what newes? They told his Maieſty, that they had receiued
anſwer of the god, written in a Scrowle: but with this
charge, that they ſhould not read the contents before they came
in the preſence of the King: and with that they deliuered him
the Parchment. But his Noblemen intreated him, that ſith
therein were conteined either the ſafety of his Wifes life and
honeſty, vr her death and perpetuall infamy; that hee would
haue his Nobles and Commons aſſembled in the Iudgement
Hall, where the Queene, brought in as a priſoner, ſhould heare
the contents: If ſhe were ſound guilty by the Oracle of the god,
then all ſhould haue cauſe to thinke his rigour procéeded of due
deſert: if her Grace were found faultleſſe, then ſhe ſhould be cléered
before all, ſith ſhe had beene accuſed openly. This pleaſed the
King, ſo that hée appointed the day, and aſſembled all the Lords
and Commons, and cauſed the Quéene to be brought in before
the Iudgement Seat, commanding that the Iudgement ſhould
be read: wherein ſhe was accuſed of Adultery with Egiſtus, and
of conſpiracy with Franion. Bellaria hearing the contents, was
no whit aſtoniſhed, but made this chéerefull anſwer.
            IF the Diuine powers be priuy to humane Actions, (as no
doubt they are) I hope my patience ſhall make Fortune bluſh,
and my vnſpotted life ſhall ſtaine ſpitefull diſcredit. For although

lying report hath ſought to appeach mine honour, and
ſuſpition hath intended to ſoyle credit with infamy: yet where
Vertue kéepeth the Fort, report and ſuſpition may aſſayle,
but neuer ſacke. How I haue led my life before Egiſtus
comming, I appeale (Pandoſto) to the gods, and to thy conſcience.
What hath paſſed betwéene him and mee, the gods
onely know, and I hope will preſently reueale. That I loued
Egiſtus, I cannot deny, that I honoured him, I ſhame
not to confeſſe. To the one I was forced by his vertue; to
the other, for his dignities. But as touching laſciuious luſt, I
ſay, Egiſtus is honeſt, and hope my ſelfe to be found without
ſpot. For Franion, I can neither accuſe him, nor excuſe him:
I was not priuy to his departure: And that this is true
which I haue here rehearſed, I referre my ſelfe vnto the Diuine
Oracle.
            
               BEllaria had no ſooner ſaid, but the King commanded that
one of the Dukes ſhould reade the contents of the Scrowle,
which after the Commons had heard, they gaue a great ſhoute,
reioycing and clapping their hands that the Quéene was cleare
of that falſe accuſation. But the King, whoſe conſcience was a
witneſſe againſt him of his witleſſe ſury, and falſe ſuſpected
iealouſie, was 
                  •
               o aſhamed of his raſh folly, that hee intreated
his Nobles to perſwade Bellaria to forgiue and forget theſe iniuries,
promiſing not onely to ſhew himſelfe a loyall and louing
Husband, but alſo to reconcile himſelfe to Egiſtu and Franion:
reuealing then before them all the cauſe of their ſecret flight,
and how trecherouſly hee thought to haue practiſed his death, if
the good minde of his Cup-bearer had not preuented his purpoſe.
As thus hee was relating the whole matter, there was
word brought him, that his young Sonne Garinter was ſuddenly
dead: which newes ſo ſoone as Bellaria heard, ſurcharged
before with extreme ioy, and now ſuppreſſed with heauy ſorrow,
her vitall ſpirits were ſtopped, that ſhée fell downe preſently
dead, and neuer could be reuiued. This ſudden ſight
ſo appalled the Kings ſenſes, that hée ſunke from his Seate in a
ſwound, ſo as hée was faine to be carried by his Nobles to his
Palace, where hée lay by the ſpace of thrée daies without ſpéech.

His Commons were as men in deſpaire, ſo diuerſly diſtreſſed
there was nothing but mourning and lamentation to be heard
throughout all Bohemia: their young Prince dead, their vertuous
Quéene bereaued of her life, and their King and Soueraigne
in great hazzard: this tragicall diſcourſe of Fortune ſo
daunted them, as they went like ſhadowes, not men: yet ſomewhat
to comfort their heauy hearts, they heard that Pandoſto
was come to himſelfe, and had recouered his ſpéech: who, as in
ſury, brayed theſe bitter ſpéeches.
            O Miſerable Pandoſto! what ſurer witnes then conſcience?
What thoughts more ſowre then ſuſpition? what plague
more bad then Iealouſie? Vnnaturall actions offend the gods,
more then men: and cauſeleſſe cruelty neuer ſcapes without reuenge.
I haue committed ſuch a bloudy fact, as repent I may,
but recall I cannot. Ah Iealouſie a hell to the mind, and a
horrour to the conſcience, ſuppreſſing reaſon, and melting
rage: a worſe paſſion then frenzy, a greater plague then madneſſe.
Are the gods iuſt? then let them reuenge ſuch brutiſh
cruelty: my innocent Babe I haue drowned in the Seas: my
louing wife I haue ſlaine with ſlanderous ſuſpition: my truſty
friend I haue ſought to betray: and yet the gods are ſiacke
to plague ſuch offences. Ah vniuſt Apollo, Pandoſto is the man
that hath committed the fault; why ſhould Garinter, ſilly Child
abide the paine? Well, ſith the gods meaneto prolonge my daies
to increaſe my dolour, I will offer my guilty bloud a ſacrifice
to thoſe guiltleſſe ſoules, whoſe liues are loſt by rigorous folly.
And with that hée reached at a Rapier to haue murthered himſelfe:
but his Péeres being preſent ſtayed him from ſuch a
bloudy act: perſwading him to thinke, that the Commonwealth
conſiſted on his ſafety, and that thoſe ſheepe could not
but periſh that wanted a Shepheard: wiſhing that if he would
not liue for himſelfe, yet he ſhould haue a care of his Subiects,
and to put ſuch fancies out of his mind, ſith in ſores paſt helpe,
ſalues doe not heale, but hurt: and in things paſt cure, care is
a corroſiue. Withtheſe and ſuch like perſwaſions the King was
ouercome, and began ſome what to quiet his mind: ſo that ſo
ſoone as he could goe abroad, he cauſed his wife to be imbalmed,

and wrapt in Lead, with her young Sonne Garinter: erecting a
rich and famous Sepulchre, wherein he intombed them both,
making ſuch ſolemne obſequies at her Funerall, as all Bohemia
might perceiue he did greatly repent him of his fore-paſſed
folly: cauſing this Epitaph to be ingrauen on her Tombe, in
Letters of Gold.
            
               The Epitaph.
               Here lyes intombde Bellaria faire,
               Falſly accus'd to be vnchaſte:
               Cleer'd by Apollo's ſacred doome,
               Yet ſlaine by Jealouſie at laſt.
            
            
               What ere thou be that paſſeſt by,
               Curſe him that caus'd this Queene to die.
            
            THis Epitaph being ingrauen, Pandoſto would once a day
repaire to the Tombe, and there, with watry plaints bewayle
his misfortune: coueting no other companion but ſorrow,
and no other harmonie but repentance. But leauing him
to his dolorous paſſions, at laſt let vs come to ſhew the tragicall
diſcourſe of the young Infant.
            WHo being toſſed with wind and waues, floated two
whole dayes without ſuccour, ready at euery puffe to
be drowned in the Sea: till at the laſt the tempeſt ceaſed &amp; the
little Boat was driuen with the tide into the Coaſt of Cicilia:
where ſticking vpon the Sands, it reſted, Fortune minding
to bee wanton, (willing to ſhew that as ſhée hath wrincles on
her browes, ſo ſhe hath dimples in her chéekes) thought after ſo
many ſowre lookes, to ſend a fained ſmile; and after a pufting
ſtorme, to bring a pretty calme, ſhée began thus to dally. It
fortuned a poore mercenary Shepheard, that dwelled in Sicilia,
who got his liuing by other mens Flockes, miſſed one of his
ſhéepe, and thinking it had ſtraied into the couert that was hard
by, ſought very diligently to find that which hee could not ſée,
fearing either that the wolues or Eagles had vndone him, (for

he was ſo poore, as a Sheepe was halfe his ſubſtance) wandred
downe, towards the Sea-cliffes, to ſee if perchance the Sheepe
was browzing on the Sea-Iuy, whereon they doe greatly feed.
But not finding her there, as hée was ready to returne to his
Flocke, he heard a childe cry: but knowing there was no houſe
neere, he thought he had miſtaken the ſound, and that it was the
bleating of his ſheepe. Wherefore looking more narrowly, as
he cast his eye to the Sea, hée eſpied a little Boat, from whence
(as he attentiuely liſtened) he might heare a cry to come. Standing
a good while in a maze, at laſt he went to the ſhore, and wading
to the Boat, as he looked in, he ſaw a little Babe lying all
alone, ready to die for hunger and cold, wrapped in a Mantle of
Scarlet, richly embrothered with Gold, and hauing a Chaine
about her necke. The Shepherd, who before had neuer ſéene ſo
faire a Babe, nor ſo rich Iewels, thought aſſuredly that it was
ſome little god, and began with great deuotion to knocke on his
breaſt. The Babe, who writhed with the head to ſéeke for the
Pap, began againe to cry afreſh: whereby the poore man knew
that it was a Childe, which by ſome ſiniſter meanes was driuen
thither by diſtreſſe of weather: maruelling how ſuch a ſilly Infant,
which by the Mantle and Chaine could not but be borne
of Noble parentage, ſhould be ſo hardly croſſed with deadly
miſhap. The poore Shepherd perplexed thus with diuers
thoughts, tooke pity of the Childe, and determined with himſelfe
to carry it to the King, that there it might be brought vp, according
to the worthineſſe of the birth: for his ability could not
afford to foſter it, though his minde was willing to further it.
Taking therefore the Childe in his armes, he folded the Mantle
together, the votter to defend if from the cold, there fell downe at
his foote, a very faire and rich purſe, wherein hee found a great
ſumme of gold: which ſight ſo reuiued the Shepherds ſpirits, as
he was greatly rauiſhed with ioy, and daunted with fea
                  •
               e: ioyfull
to ſée ſuch a ſum in his power; fearefull, if it ſhould be knowne,
that it might bréed his further danger. Neceſſity wiſht him at
the leaſt to retaine the gold, though he would not keepe the child:
the ſimplicity of his conſcience feared him from ſuch a deceitfull
bribery. Thus was the poore man perplexed with a doubtfull
Dilemma, vntill at laſt the couetouſneſſe of the coyne ouercame

him: for what will not the gréedy deſire of gold cauſe a man to
doe? So that he was reſolued in himſelfe to foster the child, and
with the ſumme to relieue his want. Reſting thus reſolute in
this point, he left ſéeking his ſhéepe, and as couertly, and ſecretly
as he could, went a by way to his houſe, leaſt any of his
neighbours ſhould perceiue his carriage. As ſoone as he was
got home; entring in at the doore, the child began foiery, which
his wife hearing, and ſéeing her husband with a young babe in
his armes, began to be ſome what iealous: yet maruelling that
her husband would be ſo wanton abroad ſith he was ſo quiet
at home. But as women are naturally giuen to beleeue the
worſt ſo his wife thinking it was ſome baſtard began to 
                  •••
               w
againſt her good man, and taking vp a cudgell (for the moſt maſter
went bréechleſſe) ſware ſolemnly, that ſhee would make
Clubs trump, if he brought any baſtard brat within her doores.
The good man ſéeing his wife in her maieſty, with her 
                  •••
               e
in her hand, thought it was time to bow, for feare of blowes,
and deſired her to be quiet, for there was no ſuch matter: but
if ſhe could hold her peace they were made for euer▪ And with
that he told her the whole matter: how hee had found the child
in a little boats without any ſuccour, wrapped in that coſtly
mantle, and hauing that rich chaine about her necke: But at laſt
when he ſhewed her the purſe full of gold, ſhe began to ſimper
ſome what ſwéetly. And taking her husband about his necke,
kiſſed him after her homely faſhion: ſaying that ſhe hoped God
had ſéene their want and now meant to relieue their pouerty,
and ſéeing they could get no children had ſent them this little
babe to be their heire. Take héed in any caſe (faith the ſhéepheard)
that you be ſecret; and blab it not out when you méete
with your Goſſips For if you doe, we are not like not onely to
loſe the gold and Iewels, but our other g
                  •••
               s and liues.
Tuſh (quoth his wife) profit is a good hatch before the doore:
Feare not, I haue other things to talke of, then this, but I
pray you let vs lay vp the money ſurely; and the Iewels, leaſt
by an
                  •
                miſhap it be eſpied. After that they had ſet all things in
order the Shepheard went to his ſhéepe with 
                  〈…〉
               , and
the good wife learned to ſing Lullaby at home with her young
babe, wrapped it in a homely blanket instead of a rich mantle,

nouriſhing it ſo cleanly and carefully, as it began to be a iollie
Girle▪ inſomuch that they began both of them to bee very fond
of it, and as it waxed in age, ſo it increaſed in beauty. The
Shepheard euery night at his comming home, would ſing and
daunce it on his knee, and prattle, that in ſhort time it began to
ſpeake, and call him Dadde, and her Mam. At laſt, when it
grew to riper yéeres, that it was about ſeeuen yéeres old, the
Shepheard left kéeping of other mens ſheepe, and with the money
hée found in the purſe, he bought him the Leaſe of a pretty
Farme, and got a ſmall flocke of Shéepe: which when Fawnia
(for ſo they named the child) came to the age of ten yéeres, he let
her to kéepe ſhéepe, and ſhe with ſuch diligence performed her
charge, as the ſhéepe proſpered maruellouſly vnder her hand.
Fawnia thought Porrus had béene her father, and Mopſa her
mother (for ſo was the Shepheard and his wife called) and honoured
and obeyed them with ſuch reuerence, that all the neighbours
praiſed the dutifull obedience of the child. Porrus grew
in ſhort time to be a man of ſome wealth and credit. For Fortune,
ſo fauoured him, in hauing no charge but Fawnia, that
hée began to purchaſe Land, intending after his death to giue
it to his daughter: So that diuers rich Farmours ſonnes
came as wooers to his houſe. For Fawnia was ſomething
cleanly attired, being of ſuch ſingular beauty, and excellent wit,
that who ſo ſaw her, would haue thought ſhée had béene ſome
heauenly Nymph, and not a mortall creature. In ſo much that
when ſhee came to the age of ſixteene yéeres, ſhee ſo increaſed
with exquiſite perfection both of body and minde, as her naturall
diſpoſition did bewray that ſhee was borne of ſome high parentage.
But the people thinking ſhe was the daughter to the
Shepheard Porrus, reſted onely amazed at her beauty and wit.
Yea ſhee won ſuch fauour and commendations in euery mans
eye, as her beauty was not onely praiſed in the Countrey, but
alſo ſpoken of in the Court. Yet ſuch was her ſubmiſſe modeſty,
that although her prayſe daily increaſed, her minde was
no whit puffed vp with pride▪ but humbled her ſelfe as became
a country maid, and the daughter of a poore Shepheard. Euery
day ſhe went forth with her ſleep to the field: keeping them with
ſuch care and diligence, as all men thought ſhe was very painefull,

defending her face from the heat of the Sunne with no other
vaile, but with a Garland made of boughes and flowers.
Which attire became her ſo gallantly, as ſhe ſeemed to be the
goddeſſe Flora her ſelfe for beauty. Fortune who all this while
had ſhewed a friendly face, began now to turne her backe, and
to ſhew a lowring countenance: intending as ſhée had giuen
Fawnia a ſlender checke, ſo ſhee would giue her a harder mate.
To bring which to paſſe, ſhe laid her trains on this wiſe: Egiſtus
had but one onely ſonne called Doraſtus about the age of twenty
yéeres: a Prince ſo decked and adorned with the gifts of Nature,
ſo fraught with beauty and vertuous qualities, as not only
his father ioyed to haue ſo good a ſonne, but his Commons reioyced
that God had ſent them ſo noble a Prince to ſuccéed in the
Kingdome. Egiſtus, placing all his ioy in the perfection of his
ſonne (ſéeing that hee was now marriageable) ſent Ambaſſadours
to the King of Denmarke, to intreate a marriage betwéen
him and his daughter. Who willingly conſenting, made anſwer,
that the next Spring, if it pleaſed Egiſtus with his ſonne
to come into Denmarke, he doubted not, but they ſhould agree
vpon reaſonable conditions. Egiſtus reſting ſatisfied with this
friendly anſwer, thought conuenient in the meane time to break
it vnto his ſonne. Finding therefore on a day fit opportunity,
he ſpake to him in theſe fatherly termes.
            
               DOraſtus, thy youth warneth me to preuent the worſt, and
mine age to prouide the beſt. Opportunities neglected, are
ſignes of folly: actions meaſured by time, are ſeldome bitten
with repentance. Thou art young, and I old: age hath taught
me th
                  •
               t, which thy youth cannot conceiue.
            I therefore will counſell thée as a Father, hoping thou wilt
obey as a child. Thou ſeeſt, my white haires are bloſſomes for
the Graue: and thy freſh colours, fruit for time and Fortune:
ſo that it behooueth me, to thinke how to dye: and for thee, to
care how to liue. My Crowne I muſt leaue by death, and
thou enioy my Kingdome by ſucceſſion. Wherein, I hope, thy,
Vertue and proweſſe ſhall be ſuch, as though my ſubiects
want my perſon, yet ſhall ſee in thee my perfection. That

nothing either may faile to ſatisfie thy minde, or increaſe thy
dignities: the onely care I haue, is to ſée thee well married before
I die, and thou become old.
            
               Doraſtus (who from his infancy, delighted rather to die with
Mars in the field, then to dally with Venus in the chamber)
fearing to diſpleaſe his father, and yet not willing to be wed,
made him this reuerend anſwer.
            SIr, there is no greater bond then duty, nor no ſtricter Law
then Nature: diſobedience in youth, is often galled with deſpight in
age. The commend of the father ought to be a conſtraint
to the child: ſo parents wills are lawes, ſo they paſſe
not all Lawes. May it pleaſe your grace therefore, to appoint
whom I ſhall loue: rather the▪ by deniall I ſhould beappeached
of diſobedience, I reſt content to loue, though it be the onely
thing I hate.
            
               Egiſtus hearing his ſonne to flie from from the marke, began
to be ſome what chellericke, and therefore made him this
anſwer.
            What Doraſtus, canſt thou not loue? Commeth this Cinicall
paſſion of proud deſires, or péeuiſh frowardnes?
What, doſt thou thinke thy ſelfe too good for all, or none good
enough for thee? I tell thee Doraſtus, there is nothing ſweeter
then youth: nor ſwifter decreaſing while it is increaſing.
Time paſt with folly, may be repented, but not recalled. If
thou marrie in age, thy wiues freſh coulours will bréd in thée
dead thoughts and ſuſpition, and thy white haires her loathſomnes
and ſorrow. For Venus affections are not fed with
Kingdomes or treaſures, but with youthfull conceits, and ſwéet
a
                  •
               ours. Vulcan was allotted to ſhake the trée, but Mars
allowed to reape the fruit. Yéeld (Doraſtus) to thy fathers perſwaſions,
which why preuent thy perils. I haue choſen thée a
wife▪ faire by nature, Royall by birth by vertues famous, learned
by education, and rich by poſſeſſions: ſo that it is hard to
iudge whether her bounty or fortune, her beauty or vertue be of
greates force: I meane (Doraſtus) Euphania, daughter and
heire to the King of Denmarke.
            
            
               
               Egiſtus pauſing here a while, looking when his ſonne ſhould
make him anſwer: and ſéeing that he ſtood ſtill, as one in a
trance, he tooke him vp thus ſharpely.
            VVEll (Doraſtus) take héed, the trée Alypa waſteth not
with fire, but withereth with dew: that which loue
nouriſheth not, periſheth with hate. If thou like Euphania, thou
bréedeſt my content, and in louing her thou ſhalt haue my loue:
otherwiſe: and with that he flung from his ſonne in a rage, leauing
him a ſorrowfull man, in that he had by denyall diſpleaſed
his father: and halfe angry with himſelfe, that he could not
yéeld to that paſſion, whereto both reaſon and his father perſwaded
him. But ſee how fortune is plumed with times feathers,
and how ſhe can miniſter ſtrange cauſes, to bréed ſtrange
effects.
            It hapned not long after this, that there was a méeting of all
the Farmors daughters in Sicilia, whither Fawnia was alſo
bidden as the miſtreſſe of the feaſt: who hauing attired her
ſelfe in her beſt garments, went amongſt the reſt of her companions
to a merry meeting: there ſpending the day in ſuch homely
paſtime as Shepheards vſe. As the Euening grew on, and
their ſport ceaſed, each taking their leaue of other: Fawnia deſiring
one of her companions to beare her company, went home
by the flocke, to ſee if they were well fowlded. And as they returned,
it fortuned that Doraſtus (who all that day had beene
hawking, and killed ſtore of game) incountred by the way theſe
two maides, fraring that with Acteon he had ſeene Diana: for
he thought ſuch exquiſite perfection could not be found in any
mortall creature. As thus he ſtood in a maze, one of his Pages
told him that the maid with the garland on her head, was Fawnia,
that faire Shepheardeſſe, whoſe beauty was ſo much talked
of in the Court. Doraſtus deſirous to ſee if nature had adorned
her mind withany inward qualities as ſhe had decked her body
with outward ſhape, began to queſtion with her whoſe daughter
ſhe was, of what age, and how ſhee had beene trained vp?
Who anſwered him with ſuch modeſt reuerence and ſharpneſſe
of wit, that Doraſtus thought her outward beauty was but a

counterfeit to darken her inward qualities: wondring how ſo
courtly behauiour could be found in ſo ſimple Cottage; and
curſing Fortune, that had ſhaddowed wit and beauty with ſuch
hard Fortune. As thus he held her a long time with chat, beauty
ſéeing him at diſcouert, thought not to looſe the vantage, but
ſtrucke him ſo déepely with an inuenomed ſhafte, as he wholly
loſt his liberty, and became a ſlaue to Loue, which before contemned
Loue, glad to gaze vpon a poore ſhepheardeſſe, who before
refuſed the offer of rich Princeſſe. For the perfection of Fawnia
had ſo fixed his fancie, as he felt his mind greatly changed,
and his affection altered; curſing Loue, that had wrought ſuch
a change and blaming the baſeneſſe of his minde, that would
make ſuch a choyce. But thinking theſe were but paſſionate
toyes that might be thruſt out at pleaſure: to auoyd the Syren
that inchanted him hee ſpurs his horſe, and had his faire Shepheardeſſe
farewell.
            
               Fawnia (who all this while had marked the Princely geſture
of Doraſtus) ſéeing his face ſo well featured, and each limbe ſo
perfectly framed, began greatly to praiſe his perfection, commending
him ſo long, till ſhe found her ſelfe faulty: and perceiued
that if ſhe waded but a little further, ſhe might ſlip ouer the
ſhooes She therefore ſeeking to quench that fire which neuer
was put out went home and faining her ſelfe not well at eaſe,
gother to bed: where caſting a thouſand thoughts in her head,
ſhée could take no reſt: for if ſhée had waked, ſhe began to call
to mind his beauty: and thinking to beguile ſuch thoughts with
ſléepe, ſhée then dreamed of his perfection. Peſtered with theſe
vnacquainted paſſions ſhe paſſed the night as ſhée could in ſhort
ſlumbers.
            
               Doraſtus (who all this while rode with a flea in his eare)
could not by any meanes forget the ſweete fauour Fawnia,
but reſted ſo bewitched with her wit and beauty, as hee could
take no reſt. He felt fancie to giue the aſſault, and his wounded
mind ready to yéeld as vanquiſhed: yet hee began with diuers
conſiderations to ſuppreſſe his franticke affection, calling
to mind, that Fawnia was a Shepheardeſſe, one not worthy to
be looked at of a Prince: much leſſe to be loued of ſuch a Potentate:
thinking what a diſcredit it were to himſelfe, and what a

griefe it would be to his father: blaming fortune, and accuſing
his owne folly, that ſhould be ſo fond, as but once to caſt a glance
at ſuch a Country ſlut. And as thus he was raging againſt himſelfe▪
Loue (fearing if ſhe dallyed long, to loſe her Champion)
ſtept more nigh, and gaue him ſuch a freſh wound, as it pierſt
him at the heart that he was faine to yéeld maugre his face, and
to forſake the company, and get him to his chamber, where being
ſolemnly ſet, he burſt into theſe paſſionate termes.
            AH Doraſtus, art thou alone? No, not alone, while thou art
tyred with theſe vnacquainted paſſions. Yéeld to fancie
thou canſt not by thy fathers counſell: but in a frenzie thou art,
by iuſt deſtinies. Thy father were content, if thou couldeſt
loue: and thou therefore diſcontent, becauſe thou doſt loue. O
diuine Loue; feare of men, becauſe honoured of gods: not to be
ſuppreſſed by wiſedome, becauſe not to be comprehended by reaſon:
without law, and therefore aboue law.
            How then Doraſtus? why doſt thou blaze that with praiſes
which thou haſt cauſe to blaſpheme with curſes? Yet why
ſhould they curſe loue, which are in loue?
            Bluſh Doraſtus at thy Fortune, thy choyce, thy loue: thy
thoughts cannot be vttered without ſhame, nor thy affections
without diſcredit. Ah Fawnia, ſweet Fawnia, thy beauty Fawnia.
            
            Shameſt not thou, Doraſtus, to name one vnfit for thy birth,
thy Dignities, thy Kingdomes? Die, Doraſtus, Doraſtus, die.
Better haddeſt thou periſh with high deſires, then liue in baſe
thoughts. Yea, but beauty muſt be obeyed, becauſe it is beauty:
yet framed of the gods to féed the eye, not to fetter the heart.
            Ah, but he that ſtriueth againſt loue, ſhooteth with them of
Scyrum againſt the wind, and with the Cockatrice pecketh
againſt the ſteele. I will therefore obey, becauſe I muſt obey.
Fawnia yea Fawnia ſhall be my fortune, in ſpight of fortune.
The gods aboue diſdaine not to loue women beneath. Phoebus
liked Daphne; Iupiter, Io: and why not 3 then Fawnia?
one ſomething inferiour to theſe in birth, but farre ſuperiour to
them in beauty: borne to be a Shepheardeſſe, but worthy to be
a goddeſſe.
            
               
Ah, Doraſtus, wilt thou forget thy ſelfe, as to ſuffer affection
to ſuppreſſe wiſdome, and loue violate thine honour? How
ſowre will thy choice be to thy father, ſorrowfull to thy ſubiects,
to thy friends a griefe, moſt gladſome to thy foes? Subdue
then thy affection, and ceaſe to loue her whom thou couldeſt not
loue, vnleſſe blinded with too much loue? Tuſh, I talke to the
wind, &amp; in ſéeking to preuent the cauſes, I further the effects,
I will yet praiſe Fawnia, honour, yea and loue Fawnia, and at
this day follow content, not councell. Doe Doraſtus, thou
canſt repent: and with that his Page came into the chamber:
whereupon hee ceaſed from complaints, hoping that time
would weare out that which fortune had wrought. As thus
he was pained, ſo poore Fawnia was diuerſly perplexed. For
the next morning getting vp very early, ſhe went to her ſhéepe,
thinking with hard labours to paſſe away her new conceiued
amours, beginning very buſily to driue them to the field, and
then to ſhift the folds. At laſt, wearied with toyle, ſhe ſate her
downe, (where poore ſoule) ſhe was more tyred with fond affection.
For loue began to aſſault her, inſomuch that as ſhe ſate
vpon the ſide of a hill, ſhe began to accuſe her owne folly in theſe
termes.
            IN fortunate Fawnia, And therefore infortunate, becauſe Fawnia,
thy Shepheards hook ſheweth thy poore eſtate, thy proud
deſires an aſpiring mind: the one declareth thy want, the other
thy pride. No baſtard Hawke muſt ſore ſo high as the Hobby,
no fowle gaze againſt the Sun but the Eagle: Actions wrought
againſt nature, reape deſpight: and thoughts aboue fortune, diſdaine.
            
               Fawnia thou art a Shepheardeſſe, daughter to poore Porrus: if
thou reſt content with this, thou art like to stand if thou climb,
thou art like to fall. The hearbe Anita growing higher then ſix
inches, becommeth a weed. Nilus flowing more then twelue
cubits procureth a dearth. Daring affections that paſſe meaſure,
are cut ſhort by time or fortune. Suppreſſe then Fawnia
thoſe thoughts which 
                  〈…〉
                ſhame to expreſſe. But ah,
Fawnia, Loue is a Lord who will command by power and conſtraine
by force.
            
               
               Doraſtus, ah Doraſtus is the man I loue: the worſe is thy
hap, and the leſſe cauſe haſt thou to hope. Will Eagles catch at
flyes? Will Cedars ſtoope at Brambles? Or mighty Princes
looke at ſuch homely Truls? No, no, thinke this Doraſtus,
diſdaine is greater then thy deſire. He is a Prince, reſpecting
his honour: Thou a beggars brat forgetting thy calling. Ceaſe
then not onely to ſay, but to thinke to loue Doraſtus; and diſſemble
thy loue, Fawnia. For better it were to die with griefe then
to liue with ſhame. Yet in deſpight of Loue, I will ſigh to ſée if
I can ſigh out Loue. Fawnia, ſome what appeaſing her griefes
with theſe pithy perſwaſions, began after her wonted manner
to walke about her ſheep, and to kéepe them from ſtraying into
the Corne, ſuppreſſing her affection with the due conſideration
of her baſe eſtate, and with impoſſibilities of her loue, thinking
it were frenzy (not fancy) to couet that which the very deſtinies
deny her to obtaine.
            But Doraſtus was more impatient in his paſſions: for loue
ſo fiercely aſſailed him, that neither company, nor Muſicke
could mitigate his martyrdome: but did rather farre the more
increaſe his malady. Shame would not let him craue counſell
in this caſe: nor feare of his fathers diſpleaſure, reueale it to
any ſecret friend: but he was faine to make a ſecretary of himſelfe,
and to participate his thoughts with his owne troubled
mind. Lingring thus a while in doubtfull ſuſpence, at laſt ſtealing
ſecretly from the Court without either men or Page, hée
went to ſée if he could eſpie Fawnia walking abroad in the field.
But, as one hauing a great deale more skill to retriue the
Partridge with the Spaniels then to hunt aſter ſuch a ſtrange
prey, he ſought, but was little the better. Which croſſe-lucke
draue him into a great choller that hee began both to accuſe
Loue and Fortune: But as hee was ready to retyre, he ſaw
Fawnia ſitting all alone vnder the ſide of an hill, making a Garland
of ſuch homely flowers as the fields did affoord. This ſight
ſo reuiued his ſpirits that he drew high, with more iudgement
to make a view of her ſingular perfection: which he found to be
ſuch▪ as in that Countrey attyre ſhee ſtained all the Courtly
Dames of Sicilia. While thus he ſtood gazing with piercing
lookes on her ſurpaſſing beauty, Fawnia caſt her eye aſide, and

eſpyed Doraſtus. Which ſudden ſight made the poore girle to
bluſh, and to dye her chriſtall cheekes with the vermillion red:
which gaue her ſuch a grace, as ſhe ſeemed farre more beautifull:
and with that ſhe roſe vp, ſaluting the Prince with ſuch
modeſt courteſies, as he wondred how a Country maid could
affoord ſuch comely behauiour. Doraſtus repaying her courteſie
with a ſmiling countenance, began to parle with her on this
manner.
            FAire maid (quoth he) either your want is great, or a Shepheards
life is very ſwéet, that your delight is in ſuch country
labours. I cannot conceiue what pleaſures you ſhould take, vnleſſe
you meane to imitate the Nymphs, being your ſelfe ſo like
a Nymph. To put me out of this doubt, ſhew me what is to be
commended in a Shepheards life, and what pleaſures you haue
to counteruaile theſe drudging labours. Fawnia, with bluſhing
face, made him this anſwer.
            SIr, what richer ſtate then content? or what ſwéeter life then
quiet? We Shepheards are not borne to honour, nor beholding
vnto beauty: the leſſe care wee haue to feare fame or fortune.
We count our attyre braue enough, if warme enough, and
our food dainty, if to ſuffice nature: our greateſt enemy is the
Wolfe: our onely care in ſafe kéeping our flocke: in ſtead of
Courtly Ditties, we ſpend the dayes with Country ſongs: our
amorous conceits are homely thoughts, delighting as much to
talke of Pan and his country pranks, as Ladies to tell of Venus
and her wanton toyes. Our toile is in ſhifting our folds
and looking to the Lambes, eaſie labours, of ſitting and telling
tales; homely pleaſures: our greateſt wealth not to couet: our
honour, not to climbe: our quiet, not to care. Enuy looketh not
ſo low as Shepheards: Shepheards gaze not ſo high as ambition:
we are rich, in that we are poore with content: and proud,
onely in this, that we haue no cauſe to be proud.
            THis witty anſwer of Fawnia, ſo inflamed Doraſtus fancy
that he commending himſelfe for making ſo good a choyſe:
thinking, if her birth were anſwerable to her wit and beauty;

that ſhee were a fit mate for the moſt famous Prince in the
world. Hee therefore began to ſift her more narrowly on this
manner.
            
               FAwnia, I ſée thou art content with country labours, becauſe
thou knoweſt not Courtly pleaſures: I commend thy wit,
and pitty thy want. But wilt thou leaue thy fathers Cottage,
and ſerue a Courtly miſtreſſe?
            Sir (quoth ſhe) beggers ought not to ſtriue againſt fortune,
nor to gaze againſt honour, leaſt either their fall be greater, or
they become blind. I am borne to toyle for the Court not in the
Court: my nature vnfit for their nature: better liue in meane
degrée, then in high diſdaine.
            Well ſaid, Fawnia (quoth Doraſtus) I geſſe at thy thoughts,
thou art in loue with ſome country Shepheard.
            No ſir (quoth ſhe) Shepheards cannot loue, that are ſo ſimple
and maids may not loue, that are ſo young.
            Nay therefore (quoth Doraſtus) maids muſt loue becauſe
they are young: for Cupid is a child, and Venus, though old, is
painted with freſh colours.
            I grant (ſaid ſhe) age may be painted with new ſhadowes,
and youth may haue imperfect affections: but, what art concealeth
in one, ignorance reuealeth in another. Doraſtus ſéeing
Fawnia hold him ſo hard, thought it was vaine ſo long to beate
about the buſh: therefore he thought to haue giuen her a freſh
charge; but he was ſo preuented by certaine of his men, who
miſſing their matter, came poſting to ſeeke him, ſéeing that he
was gone forth all alone: yet before they drew ſo nigh, that
they might heare their talke, he vſed theſe ſpéeches.
            Why, Fawnia, perhaps I loue thée, and then thou muſt néeds
yeeld: for thou knoweſt I can command and conſtraine. Tuſh
Sir (quoth ſhe) but not to loue, for conſtrained loue is force,
not loue: And know this, Sir, mine honeſty is ſuch, as I had
rather dye, then be a Concubine, enen vnto a King: and my
birth is ſo baſe, as I am vnfit to be a wife vnto a poore Farmor.
Why then (quoth he) thou canſt not loue Doraſtus. Yes, ſaid
Fawnia, when Doraſtus becomes a Shepheard. And with that,
the preſence of his men broke off their parle, ſo that hee went

with them to the Pallace, and left Fawnia, ſitting ſtill on the hill
ſide: who ſéeing that the night drew on, ſhifted her Folds and
buſied her ſelfe about other worke, to driue away ſuch fond fancies
as began to trouble her braine. But all this could not preuaile;
for the beauty of Doraſtus had made ſuch a déepe impreſſion
in her heart as it could not be worne out without cracking,
ſo that ſhe was faine to blame her owne folly in this wife.
            AH Fawnia why doſt thou gaze againſt the Sunne, or catch
at the wind? Starres are to be looked at with the eye, not
reached at with the hand: thoughts are to be meaſured by fortunes,
not by deſires▪ falls comes not by ſitting low, but by climing
too high. What then ſhall all feare to fall, becauſe ſome
hap to fall? No, lucke commeth by Lot, and Fortune windeth
thoſe threeds which the Deſtinies ſpin. Thou art fauoured,
Fawnia, at a Prince, and yet thou art ſo fond to reiect deſired
fauours. Thou haſt deniall at thy tongues end, and deſire at thy
hearts bottome. A womans fault, to ſpurne at that with her
foot, which ſhe greedily catcheth at with her hand. Thou loueſt
Doraſtus, Fawnia; and yet ſeemeſt to lowre. Take heed, if he
retire thou wilt repent▪ for vnleſſe he loue, thou canſt but dye.
Dye then Fawnia▪
                for Doraſtus doth but ieſt. The Lion neuer
preyeth on the Mouſe: nor doe Fawlcons ſtoop to dead ſtales.
Sit downe then in this ſorrow: ceaſe to loue and content thy
ſelfe, that Doraſtus wi
                  •
               l vouchſafe to flatter Fawnia, though not
to fancy Fawnia. Heigh hoe: Ah foole, it were ſéemlier for thée
to whiſtle as a Shepheard, then to ſigh as a Louer: and with
that ſhe ceaſed from theſe perplexed paſſions, folding her ſhéep,
and hying home to her poore Cottage. But ſuch was the vnconſtant
ſorrow of Doraſtus, to thinke on the wit and beauty
of Fawnia, and to ſée how fond he was, being a Prince: and
how froward ſhe was being a begger: that he began to loſe his
wonte dappetite: to looke pale and wan: in ſtead of mirth, he
fed on melancholly: for Courtly dances, to vſe cold dumps.
Inſomuch that not onely his owne men, but his father, and all
the Court began to maruell at his ſudden change, thinking that
ſome lingring ſickneſſehad brought him into this ſtate. Wherefore
hée cauſed Phyſicians to come. But Doraſtus neither

would let them miniſter, nor ſo much as ſuffer them to ſée his
vrine: but remained ſtill ſo oppreſſed with theſe paſſions as
hee feared in himſelfe a further inconuenience. His honour
wiſhed him to ceaſe from ſuch foſly: but loue forced him more
to follow fancy; yea, and in deſpight of honour, Loue won the
conqueſt, ſo that his hot deſires cauſed him to find new deuices.
For he preſently made himſelfe a Shepheards Coate, that hée
might goe vnknowne, and with leſſe ſuſpition, to prattle with
Fawnia; and conueied it ſecretly into a thicke Groue, hard adioyning
to the Palace: whither, finding fit time and opportunity,
he went all alone, and putting off his Princely apparell,
got on thoſe Shepheards robes, and taking a great hooke in
his hand (which hée alſo had gotten) hée went very anciently
to finde out the Miſtreſſe of his affection. But as he went by
the way, ſéeing himſelfe clad in ſuch vnſéemely rags, hée began
to ſmile at his owne folly, and to reproue his fondneſſe in theſe
termes.
            VVEll ſaid, Doraſtus, thou kéepeſt a good decorum, baſe
deſires, and homely attires; thy thoughts are fit for
none but a Shéepheard, and thy apparell ſuch onely as becomes
a Shepheard. A ſtrange change, from a Prince to a Peaſant.
What, is it thy wretched fortune or thy wilfull folly? Is it thy
curſed Deſtinies, or thy crooked deſires that appoint thee this
penance: Ah, Doraſtus, thou canſt but loue, and vnleſſe thou
loue, thou art like to periſh for loue. Yet, fond foole, chuſe
flowers, not wéeds: Diamonds, not Pebbles: Ladies which
may honour thée, not Shepheards, which may diſgrace thée.
Venus is painted in ſilkes, not in ragges, and Cupid treadeth
on diſdaine, when he reacheth at Dignity. And yet Doraſtus,
ſhame not at thy Shepheards wéed: the heauenly gods haue
ſometime earthly thoughts: Neptune became a Ram: Iupiter
a Bull: Apollo a Shepheard: they gods, and yet in loue: and
thou a man appointed to loue.
            Deuiſing thus with himſelfe, hée drew nigh to the place
where Fawnia was keeping her ſheepe: who caſting her eye
aſide, and ſeeing ſuch a manerly Shepheard, perfectly limmed,
and comming with ſo good a pace, ſhée began halfe to forget

               Doraſtus, and to fauour her pretty ſhepheard, whom ſhe thought
ſhe might both loue &amp; obtaine. But as ſhe was in theſe thoughts
ſhe perceiued then it was the young Prince Doraſtus; wherefore
the roſe vp, and reuerently ſaluted him. Doraſtus taking
her by the hand, repayed her courteſie with aſwéet kiſſe, and
praying her to ſit downe by him, hee began thus to lay the battery.
            IF thou maruell, Fawnia at my ſtrange attire, thou wouldſt
more muſe at my vnaccuſtomed thoughts: the one diſgraceth
but my outward ſhape: the other diſturbeth my inward
ſenſes: I loue Fawnia, and therefore what loue liketh, I cannot
miſlike. Fawnia thou haſt promiſed to loue, and I hope thou
wilt performe no leſſe. I haue fulfilled thy requeſt, and now
thou canſt not but grant my deſire. Thou wert content to loue
Doraſtus, when hee ceaſt to be a Prince, and became a Shepheard:
and ſée I haue made a change, and therefore not to miſſe
of my choyce.
            TRuth, quoth Fawnia: But all that weare Cowles, are not
Monkes. Painted Eagles are pictures, not Eagles: Zeuxis
Grapes were like Grapes, yet ſhaddowes; rich cloathing
make not Princes, nor homely attire beggers: Shepheards
are not called Shepheards, becauſe they weare hooks &amp; bags,
but they are borne poore, and liue to keepe ſheepe: ſo this attire
hath not made Doraſtus a Shepheard, but to ſéeme like a
Shepheard.
            WEll Fawnia, anſwered Doraſtus, were I a Shepheard
I could not but like thée; being a Prince, I am forced
to loue thee. Take héede Fawnia, bee not proud of beauties
painting; for it is a flower that fadeth in the bloſſome. Thoſe
which diſdaine in youth, are deſpiſed in age. Beauties ſhadowes
are trickt vp with times colours, which being ſet to dry
in the Sunne, are ſtained with the Sunne, ſcarce pleaſing the
ſight: yet they begin not to be worth the ſight: not much vnlike
the hearbe Ephymeton, which flouriſheth in the morning, and
is withered before the Sunne ſetting. If my deſire were

againſt loue, thou mighteſt iuſtly deny me by reaſon: but I loue
thée, Fawnia, not to miſuſe thée as a Concubine, but to vſe thée
as my wife; I can promiſe no more, and meane to performe
no leſſe.
            
               Fawnia hearing this ſolemne proteſtation of Doraſtus, could
no longer withſtand the aſſault, but yéelded up the fort, in theſe
friendly termes.
            AH, Doraſtus, I ſhame to expreſſe that thou forceſt me with
thy ſugred ſpéech to confeſſe: my baſe birth cauſeth the one,
and thy high dignities the other. Beggers thoughts ought not
to reach as farre as Kings, and yet my deſires reach as high as
Princes. I dare not ſay, Doraſtus, I loue thée, becauſe I am
a Shepheardeſſe: but the gods know, I haue honoured Doraſtus
(pardon if I ſay amiſſe) yea, and loued Doraſtus, with ſuch
dutifull affection, as Fawnia can performe, or Doraſtus deſire:
I yeeld, not ouercome with prayers but with loue: reſting
Doraſtus hand-maid, ready to obey his will, if no preiudice at
all to his honour, nor my credit.
            
               DOraſtus hearing this friendly concluſion of Fawnia, embraced
her in his armes, ſwearing that neither diſtance,
time, nor aduerſe fortune, ſhould diminiſh his affection: but
that in deſpight of the deſtinies hee would remaine faithfull to
death. Hauing thus plight their troth each to other, ſeeing they
could not haue the full fruition of their loue in Sicilia, for that
Egiſtus conſent would neuer be granted to ſo meane a match:
Doraſtus determined, as ſoone as time and opportunity would
giue him leaue, to prouide a great maſſe of mony, and many
rich and coſtly Iewels, for the eaſier carriage; and then
to tranſport themſelues and their Treaſure into Italy, wherethey
ſhould lead a contented life, vntill ſuch time as either hée
could be reconciled to his father, or elſe by ſucceſſion come
to the Kingdome. This deuice was greatly praiſed of Fawnia:
for ſhee feared, if the King his father ſhould but heare of
the contract, that his fury would be ſuch, as no leſſe than death
ſhould ſtand for payment. Shée therefore told him, that delay
bred danger: that many miſhappes did fall out betwéene the

cup and lip; and that to auoyd danger, it were beſt with as
much ſpéede as might be, to paſſe out of Sicilia, leaſt fortime
might preuent their patience with ſome new deſpight. Doraſtus,
whom loue pricked forward with deſire, promiſed to diſpat
                  •
               h
his affaires with as great haſte, as either time or opportunity
would giue him leaue: and ſo reſting vpon this point
after many embracings and ſwéet kiſſes, they departed. Doraſtus,
hauing taken his leaue, of his beſt beloued Fawnia went
to the Groue where he had his rich apparell, and there vncaſing
himſelfe as ſecretly as might be, hiding vp his Shepheards attyre,
till occaſion ſhould ſerue againe to vſe it, hée went to the
Palace, ſhe wing by his merry countenance, that either the ſtate
of his body was amended, or the cauſe of his minde greatly addreſſed.
Fawnia, poore ſoule, was no leſſe ioyfull, that being a
Shepheardeſſe, fortune had fauoured her ſo, as to reward her
with the loue of a Prince: hoping in time to be aduanced from
the daughter of a poore Farmour, to be wife to rich a King. So
that ſhe thought euery houre ayéere, till by their departure they
might preuent danger: not ceaſing ſtill to goe euery day to her
ſheepe: not ſo much for the care of the flocke, as for the deſire
ſhe had to ſée her Loue and Lord, Doraſtus: who oftentimes,
when opportunity would ſerue, repaired thither to feed his
fancy with the ſwéet content of Fawnia's preſence. And although
hée neuer went to viſite her, but in theſe Shepheards ragges,
yet his oft repayre made him not onely ſuſpected, but knowne
to diuers of their neighbours: who for the good will they bare
to old Porrus, told him ſecretly of the matter, wiſhing him
to kéepe his daughter of home, leſt ſhee went ſo long to the
field, that ſhe brought him home a young ſonne. For they feared
that Fawnia being ſo beautifull, the young Prince would
allure her to folly. Porrus was ſtricken in a dumpe at theſe
newes, ſo that thanking his neighbours for their good will, he
hyed him home to his wife: and calling her aſide, wringing his
hands and ſhedding forth teares hee brake the matter to her in
theſe termes.
            I Am afraid, wife, that my daughter Fawnia hath made her
ſelfe to ſinne, that ſhe will buy repentance too déere, I haue

newes, which if they be true, ſome will wiſh they had not proued
true. It is told me by my neighbours, that Doraſtus the Kings
ſonne, begins to looke at our daughter Fawnia: which if it be
ſo, I will not giue her a halfe-peny for her honeſty at the yéeres
end. I tell thée, wife, now a dayes beauty is a great ſta
                  •
               e to
trap young men, and faire words and ſwéet promiſes are two
great enemies to maides honeſty: and thou knoweſt▪ where
poore intreat, and cannot obtaine, there Princes may command,
and will obtaine. Though Kings ſonnes daunce in nets they
may not bee ſéene: yet poore mens faults are eſpied at a little
hole. Well, it is a hard care where Kings luſts are lawes, and
that they ſhould bind poore men to that which they themſelues
wilfully breake.
            Peace, husband (quoth his wife) take heed what wee ſay:
Speake no more then you ſhould, leaſt you heare what you
would not. Great ſtreames are to be ſtopped by ſleight, not by
force: and Princes to be perſwaded by ſubmiſſion, not by rigour.
Doe what you can, but no more then you may, leaſt in
ſauing Fawnia's maiden-head, you loſe your owne head. Take
heed, I ſay, it is ill ieſting with edged tooles, and bad ſporting
with Kings The Wolfe had his skin pulled ouer his eares, for
but looking into the Lyons den.
            Tuſh, wife (quoth he) thou ſpeakeſt like a foole: If the King
ſhould know that Doraſtus had gotten our daughter with child
(as I feare it will fall out little better) the Kings fury would
be ſuch, as no doubt we ſhould both loſe our goods and liues: neceſſity
therefore hath no law, and I will preuent this miſchiefe
with a new deuice that is come into my head, which ſhall neither
offend the King, nor diſpleaſe Doraſtus. I meane to take
the chaine and the Iewels that I found with Fawnia, and carry
them to the King; letting him then to vnderſtand, how ſhee is
none of my daughter, but that I found her beaten vp with the
water alone in a little boat, wrapped in a rich mantle, wherein
was incloſed this treaſure. By this meanes, I hope the King
will take Fawnia into his ſeruice, and wee, whatſoeuer chance
ſhall be blameleſſe. This deuiſe pleaſed the good-wife very well,
ſo that they determined as ſoone as they might know the King
at leiſure, to make him priuy to this caſe.
            
               
In the meane time, Doraſtus was not ſlacke in his affaires,
but applied his matters with ſuch diligence, that he prouided all
things fit for their iourney. Treaſure and Iewels he had gotten
great ſtore, thinking there was no better friend then mony
in a ſtrange Countrey. Rich attire he had prouided for Fawnia:
and becauſe hee could not bring the matter to paſſe without the
helpe and aduice of ſome one, he made an old ſeruant of his called
Capnio, who had ſerued him from his child hood, priuy to
his affaires: who, ſéeing no perswaſions could preuaile to diuert
him from his ſetled determination gaue his conſent, and
dealt ſo ſecretly in the cauſe, that within ſhort ſpace he had gotten
a ſhip ready for their paſſage. The Marriners ſéeing a fit
gale of winde for their purpoſe, wiſhed Capnio to make no delayes,
leſt if they pretermitted this good weather, they might
ſtaylong ere they had ſuch a faire wind. Capnio fearing that his
negligence ſhould hinder their iourney, in the night time conueyed
the truncks full of treaſure into the ſhip, and by ſecret
meanes let Fawnia vnderſtand, that the next morning they
meant to depart. She vpon theſe newes ſlept very little that
night, but got her vp very early, and went to her ſhéepe, looking
euery minute when ſhe ſhould ſée Doraſtus: who tarryed
not long, for feare delay might breed danger: but came as faſt
as he could gallop, and without any great circumſtance tooke
Fawnia vp behind him, and rode to the hauen where the ſhip
lay, which was thrée quarters of a mile diſtant from that place.
He no ſooner came there, but the Marriners were ready with
their cock-boat to ſet them aboord: where being coucht together
in a Cabbin they paſt away the time in recounting their old
loues, till their man Capnio could come.
            
               Porrus, who had heard that this morning the King would go
abroad to take the ayre, called in haſte to his wife, to bring him
his holi-day-hoſe, and his beſt Jacket, that he might goe like
an honeſt ſubſtantiall man to tell his tale. His wiſe a good
cleanly wench, brought him all things fit and ſpunged him vp
very hanſomely, giuing him a chaine and the iewels in a little
box: which Porrus for the more ſafety put in his boſome. Hauing
thus his trinkets in a readineſſe, taking his ſtaffe in his
hand he bade his wife kiſſe him for good lucke, and ſo he went

towards the Palace. But as he was going, Fortune (who
meant to ſhe whim a little falſe play) preuented his purpoſe in
this wiſe.
            He met by chance in his way Capnio, who trudging as faſt
as he could, with a little coffer vnder his arme to the ſhip, and
ſpying Porrus, whom hee knew to bee Fawnia's father going
towards the Palace: being a wylie fellow, began to doubt the
worſt, and therefore croſt him the way and asked him whither
he was going ſo early in the morning.
            
               Porrus (who knew by his face that he was one of the Court)
meaning ſimply, told him that the Kings ſonne Doraſtus dealt
hardly with him: for he had but one daughter, who was a little
beautifull, and that his neighbours told him, the yong Prince
had allured her to folly: he went therefore now to complaine to
the King how greatly he was abuſed.
            
               Capnio (who ſtraight way knew the whole matter) began
to ſooth him in his talke, and ſaid, that Doraſtus dealt not like
a Prince, to ſpoyle any poore mans daughter in that ſort: hée
therefore would doe the beſt for him he could, becauſe he knew
he was an honeſt man. But (quoth Capnio) you looſe your labour
in going to the Palace: for the King meanes this day to
take the ayre of the ſea, and to goe aboord of a ſhip that lyes in
the hauen: I am going before, you ſée, to prouide all things in
a readineſſe: and if you will follow my counſell, turne backe
with me to the hauen where I will ſet you in ſuch a fit place,
as you may ſpeake to the King of your pleaſure. Porrus giuing
credit to Capnio's ſmooth tales, gaue him a thouſand thanks for
his friendly aduice, and went with him to the hauen, making
all the way his complaint on Doraſtus; yet concealing ſecretly
his chaine and the Iewels. As ſoone as they were come to the
ſea-ſide, the Marriners ſéeing Capnio, came to land with their
cocke-boat: who ſtill diſſembling the matter, demanded of Porrus,
if hee would goe ſée the ſhip: who vnwilling, and fearing
the worſt, becauſe hee was not well acquainted with Capnio,
made his excuſe that he could not brooke the ſea, and therefore
would not trouble him.
            
               Capnio, ſéeing that by faire meanes he could not get him
aboord commanded the Marriners that by violence they ſhould

carry him into the ſhip, who like ſturdy knaues holſted the poore
Shepheard on their necks, and bearing him to the boat lanched
from the land.
            
               Porrus ſeeing himſelfe ſo cunningly betrayed, durſt not cry
out, for hee ſaw it would not preuaile: but began to intreate
Capnio, and the Marriners to be good to him, and to pitty his
eſtate, hee was but a poore man that liued by his labour: they
laughing to ſee the Shepheard ſo affraid, made as much haſt as
they could to ſet him aboord. Porrus was no ſooner in the ſhip
but he ſaw Doraſtus walking with Fawnia, yet he ſcarce knew
her: for ſhee had attyred her ſelfe in rich apparell, which ſo increaſed
her beauty, that ſhe reſembled rather an Angell, than
a creature.
            
               Doraſtus and Fawnia, were halfe aſtoniſhed to ſee the old
Shepheard; maruelling greatly what wind had brought him
thither, till Capnio told them all the whole diſcourſe: how Porrus
was going to make his complaint to the King, if by pollicy
he had not preuented him; and therfore now ſith he was aboord,
for the auoiding of further danger, it were beſt to carry him into
Italy.
            
            
               Doraſtus, praiſed greatly his mans deuice, and allowed of his
counſell: but Fawnia, (who ſtill feared Porrus as her father)
began to bluſh for ſhame, that by her meanes he ſhould either incurre
danger or diſpleaſure.
            The old Shepheard hearing this hard ſentence: that he ſhould
on ſuch a ſuddaine be carried from his wife, his Country and
kinsfolke, into a forraigne Land among ſtrangers began with
bitter teares to make his complaint, and on his knees to intreat
Doraſtus, that pardoning his vnaduiſed folly, he would giue him
leaue to goe home: ſwearing that he would keepe all things as
ſecret as he could wiſh. But theſe proteſtations could not preuaile,
although Fawnia intreated Doraſtus very earneſtly: but
the Marriners hoiſted their maine ſailes, weighed anchors, haled
into the deepe: where wee leaue them to the ſuccour of the
wind and ſeas, and returne to Egiſtus.
            
            VVHo hauing appointed this day to hunt in one of his
forreſts, called for his ſonne Doraſtus, to goe ſport

himſelfe, becauſe he ſaw that of late he began to lowre: but his
men made anſwer that he was gone abroad none knew whither,
except he were gone to the groue to walke all alone, as his cuſtome
was euery day.
            The King willing to waken him out of his dumpe, ſent one
of his men to goe ſeeke him, but in vaine: for at the laſt he returned,
but find him he could not, ſo that the King went himſelfe
to go ſee the ſport: where paſſing away the day, returning
at night from hunting, he asked for his ſon, but he could not be
heard of, which draue the king into a great choller: whereupon
moſt of his Noblemen and other Courtiers poſted abroad
to ſeeke him, but they could not heare of him through all Sicilia:
onely they miſſed Capnio his man, which againe made the King
ſuſpect that he was not gone farre.
            Two or thrée dayes being paſſed, and no newes heard of Doraſtus,
Egiſtus being fearefull that he was deuoured with ſome
wild beaſts, and with that made out a great Troupe of men
to goe ſéeke him: who coaſted through all the Country and
ſearched in euery dangerous and ſecret place, vntill at laſt they
met with a Fiſher-man, that was ſitting in a little couert, hard
by the ſea ſide, mending his nets, when Doraſtus and Fawnia
tooke ſhipping: who being examined if hee either knew or
heard where the Kings ſonne was, without any ſecreſie at all,
reuealed the whole matter, how he was ſailed two dayes paſt,
and had in his company his man Capnio, Porrus, and his faire
daughter Fawnia. This heauy newes was preſently carried
to the King, who halfe dead for ſorrow, commanded Porrus
wife to be ſent for: ſhee being come to the Palace, after due
examination, confeſſed that her neighbours had oft told her,
that the Kings ſonne was too familiar with Fawnia her daughter:
Whereupon her husband fearing the worſt, about two
dayes paſt, (hearing the King ſhould goe a hunting) roſe early
in the morning, and went to make his complaint, but ſince
ſhe neither heard of him, nor ſaw him. Egiſtus perceiuing the
womans vnfained ſimplicity, let her depart without incurring
further diſpleaſure, conceiuing ſuch ſecret griefe for his ſons
wretchleſſe folly, that hee had ſo forgotten his honour and Parentage,
by ſo baſe a choice to diſhonour his father, and diſcredit

himſelfe, that with very care and thought, he fell into a quartaine
feuer: which was ſo vnfit for his aged yéeres and complexion,
that hee became ſo weake, as the Phyſicians would
grant him no life.
            But his ſonne Doraſtus little regarded either father, Countrey
or kingdome, in reſpect of his Lady Fawnia: for Fortune
ſmiling on this yong nouics, ſent him ſo lucky a gale of wind,
for the ſpace of a day and a night, that the Marriners lay &amp; ſlept
vpon the hatches: but on the next morning about the breake of
the day, the ayre began to ouer-caſt, the winds to riſe, the ſeas
to ſwell: yea preſently there aroſe ſuch a fearefull tempeſt, as
the ſhip was in danger to be ſwallowed vp in euery ſea; the
maine maſt with the violence of the wind, was throwne ouerboord,
the ſailes were torne, the tackling rended a ſunder, the
ſtorme raging ſtill ſo furiouſly, that poore Fawnia was almoſt
dead for feare, but that ſhe was greatly comforted with the preſence
of Doraſtus. The tempeſt continued thrée dayes, all which
time the Marriners euery minute looked for death, and the aire
was ſo darkened with clouds, that the maſter could not tell by
the compaſſe in what coaſt they were. But vpon the fourth day
about ten of the clocke, the winde began to ceaſe, the ſea to
waxe calme, and the skie to be cléere, and the Marriners deſcried
the coaſt of Bohemia, ſhooting off their Ordinance for ioy,
that they had eſcaped ſuch a fearefull tempeſt.
            
               Doraſtus hearing that they were arriued at ſome Harbour,
ſwéetly kiſſed Fawnia, and bade herbe of good chéere. When
they told him that the Port belonged to the chiefe Citty of Bohemia
where Pandoſto kept his Court, Doraſtus began to bee
ſad; knowing that his father hated no man ſo much as Pandoſto,
and that the King himſelfe had ſought ſecretly to betray
Egiſtus: this conſidered, he was halfe affrayd to goe on Land,
but that Capnio counſelled him to change his name and his
Countrey, vntill ſuch time as they could get ſome other Barke
to tranſport them into Italy. Doraſtus liking this deuice, made
his caſe priuy to the Marriners, rewarding them bountifully
for their paines, and charging them to ſay, that he was a Gentleman
of Trapolonia, called Meleagrus. The ſhip-men willing
to ſhew what friendſhip they could▪ to Doraſtus, promiſed to be

as ſecret as they could; or he might wiſh: and vpon this, they
landed in a little village a mile diſtant from the City: where
after they had reſted a day, thinking to make prouiſion for their
marriage, the fame of Fawnia's beauty was ſpred throughout
all the City, ſo that it came to the eare of Pandoſto: who then
being about the age of fifty, had notwithſtanding young and
freſh affections: ſo that the deſired greatly to ſée Fawnia: and to
bring this matter the better to paſſe, hearing they had but one
man, and how they reſted at a very homely houſe he cauſed them
to be apprehended as Spies, and ſent twelue of his Guard to
take them, who being come to their lodging, told them the
Kings meſſage. Doraſtus no whit diſmayed, accompanied with
Fawnia and Capnio, went to the Court (for they left Porrus to
kéepe the ſtuffe,) who being admitted to the Kings preſence,
Doraſtus and Fawnia with humble obeiſance ſaluted his Maieſty.
            
               Pandoſto amazed at the ſingular perfection of Fawnia, ſtood
halfe aſtoniſhed, viewing her beauty, ſo that hee almoſt forgot
himſelfe what he had to do: at laſt, with ſterne countenance he
demanded their names, and of what Country they were, and
what cauſed them to land in Bohemia? Sir (quoth Doraſtus,)
know that my name is Meleagrus a Knight borne and brought
vp in Trapolonia, and this Gentlewoman, whom I meane to
take to my wife, is an Italian borne in Padua, from whence I
haue now brought her. The cauſe I haue ſo ſmall a traine with
me, is, for that her friends vnwilling to conſent, I entended ſecretly
to conuey her into Trapolonia, whither I was ſayling,
and by diſtreſſe of weather, I was driuen into theſe Coaſts.
Thus haue you heard my name, my Country, and the cauſe of
my voyage. Pandoſto ſtarting from his Seat, as one in choller,
made this rough reply.
            
               MEleagrus, I feare, this ſmooth ta
                  •
               e hath but ſmall truth,
and that thou couereſt a foule skin with faire paintings.
No doubt, this Lady, by her grace and beauty, is of higher degrée,
more méet for a mighty Prince, then for a ſimple Knight:
and thou like a periured traytor haſt bereft her of her Parents,
to their preſent griefe, and her enſuing ſorrow. Till therefore

I heare more of her Parentage, and of her calling, I will ſtay
you both here in Bohemia.
            
            
               Doraſtus, in whom reſted nothing but Kingly valour, was
not able to ſuffer the reproaches of Pandoſto, but that he made
him this anſwer.
            IT is not meete for a King without due proofe to appeach
any man of ill behauiour, nor vpon ſuſpition to inferre beliefe,
ſtrangers ought to be entertained with courteſie, not to be entreated
with cruelty; leſt being forced by want to put vp iniuries,
the gods reuenge their cauſe with rigour.
            
               Pandoſto hearing Doraſtus vtter theſe words, commanded
that he ſhould ſtraight be committed to priſon, vntill ſuch time
as they heard further of his pleaſure: but as for Fawnia, he charged
that ſhe ſhould be entertained in the Court, with ſuch courteſie
as belonged to a ſtranger and her calling: the reſt of the
ſhip-men put in the Dungeon.
            Hauing thus ſo hardly handled the ſuppoſed Trapolonians,
Pandoſto contrary to his aged yeeres, began to be ſome what
tickled with the beauty of Fawnia, inſomuch that he could take
no reſt, but caſt into his old head a thouſand new deuices: at
laſt he fell into theſe thoughts.
            HOw art thou deſired (Pandoſto) with freſh affections, and
vnfit fancies, wiſhing to poſſeſſe with an vnwilling mind,
and a hot deſire troubled with a cold diſdaine? Shall thy mind
yéeld in age, to that thou haſt reſiſted in youth? Peace Pandoſto,
blab not out that which thou maiſt be aſhamed to reueale to thy
ſelfe. Ah, Fawnia is beautifull, and it is not for thine honour
(fond foole) to name her that is thy captiue, and another mans
concubine. Alas, I reach at that with my hand, which my heart
would faine refuſe: playing like the bird Ibis in Aegypt, which
hateth ſerpents, yet féedeth on their egges.
            Tuſh hot deſires turne oftentimes to cold diſdaine: Loue is
brittle, where appetite, not reaſon beares the ſway: Kings
thoughts ought not to climbe ſo high as the heauens, but to
looke no lower then honour: better it is to pecke at the ſtarres
with the young Eagles, then to prey on dead carcaſſes with

the Vulture: it is more honourable for Pandoſto to dye by concealing
loue, then to enioy ſuch vnfit Loue. Doth Pandoſto then
loue? Yea, Whom? A maid vnknowne, yea, and perhaps
immodeſt, ſtragled out of her owne Country: beautifull, but
not therefore chaſte: comely in body, but perhaps crooked in
minde. Ceaſe then Pandoſto, to looke at Fawnia, much leſſe to
loue her: be not ouertaken with a womans beauty, whoſe eyes
are framed by Art to euamour: whoſe heart is framed by nature
to inchant: whoſe falſe teares know their due time, and
whoſe ſwéete words pierce déeper then ſharpe ſwords. Here
ceaſt Pandoſto from his talke, but not from, his loue for although
he ſought by reaſon and wiſdome to ſuppreſſe this franticke
affection, yet he could take no reſt, the beauty of Fawnia
had made ſuch a déepe impreſſion in his heart. But on a day
walking abroad into a Parke, which was hard adioyning to
his houſe, he ſent by one of his ſeruants for Fawnia, vnto whom
he vttered theſe words.
            
               FAwnia, I commend thy beauty and wit, and now pitty thy
diſtreſſe and want: but if thou wilt forſake Sir Meleagrus
(whoſe pouerty, though a Knight is not able to maintaine an
eſtate anſwerable to thy beauty) and yéeld thy conſent to Pandoſto,
I will both increaſe thée with dignities and riches. No
Sir, anſwered Fawnia, Meleagrus is a Knight that hath wonne
me by loue, and none but he ſhall weare me: this ſmiſter miſchance
ſhall not diminiſh my affection, but rather increaſe my
good will: thinke not though your Grace hath impriſoned him
without cauſe, that feare will make me yéeld my conſent: I had
rather be Meleagrus wife, and a begger, then liue in plenty, and
be Pandoſto's Concubine.
            
               Pandoſto, hearing the aſſured anſwer of Fawnia, would notwithſtanding
proſecute his ſuite to the vttermoſt: ſéeking with
faire words and great promiſes to ſcale the fort of her chaſtity:
ſwearing that if ſhee would grant to his deſire, Meleagrus
ſhould not onely be ſet at liberty, but honoured in the Court amongſt
his Nobles. But theſe alluring baites could not intice
her mind from the loue of her new-betrothed mate Meleagrus,
which Pandoſto ſéeing, he let her alone for that time to conſider

more of the demand. Fawnia being alone by herſelfe, began to
fall into theſe ſolitary meditations.
            AH infortunate Fawnia, thou ſéeſt, to deſire aboue fortune is
to ſtriue aboue gods and fortune. Who gazeth at the Sun,
weakeneth his ſight: They which ſtare at the skie fall of into
déep pits: hadſt thou reſted content to haue béen a ſhepheardeſſe,
thou néedeſt not to haue feared miſchance: better had it béen for
thée, by ſitting low, to haue had quiet, then by climing high, to
haue falne into miſery. But alas, I feare not mine own danger
but Doraſtus diſpleaſure. Ah ſwéet Doraſtus, thou art a Prince,
but now a priſoner, by too much loue, procuring thine own loſſe;
haddeſt thou not loued Fawnia, thou hadſt béen fortunate. Shall
I then bee falſe to him that hath forſaken kingdomes for my
cauſe? 
                  •
               o, would my death might deliuer him ſo mine honour
might be preſerued. With that fetching a deepe ſigh, ſhe ceaſed
from her complaints and went againe to the Palace enioyning
a liberty without content, and proffered pleaſure with ſmall ioy.
But poore Doraſtus lay all this while in cloſe priſon, being pinched
with a hardreſtraint and pained with the burthen of cold &amp;
heauy yrons, ſorrowed ſometimes that his fond affection had
procured him this miſhappe, that by the diſobedience of his parent,
he had wrought his owne deſpight: another while curſing
the gods and Fortune, that they would croſſe him with ſmiſter
chance, vttering at laſt his paſſions with theſe words.
            AH vnfortunate wretch, borne to miſhap, now ſhyfolly hath
his deſert: art thou not worthy for thy vaſe mind, to haue
bad fortune? Could the deſtinies fauour thée, which haſt forgot
thine honour and dignity? Will not the gods plague him with
deſpight that paineth his father with diſobedience? Oh gods if
any fauour or iuſtice be left plague me but fauour poore Fawnia,
and ſhrowd her from the tyrannies of wretched Pandoſto: but
let my death frée her from miſhap, and then welcome death. Doraſtus
pained with theſe heauy paſſions, ſorrowed and ſighed
but in vaine; for which he vſed more patience.
            But againe to Pandoſto, who broyling in the heat of vnlawfull
luſt, could take no reſt, but ſtill felt his minde diſquieted

with his new loue; ſo that his Nobles and Subiects maruelled
greatly at his ſodaine alteration, not being able to coniecture
the cauſe of this his continued care. Pandoſto thinking euery
houre a yéere till he had talked once againe with Fawnia, ſent
for her ſecretly into his chamber: whither Fawnia though vnwillingly
comming, Pandoſto entertain'd her very courteouſly,
vſing theſe familiar ſpéeches, which Fawnia anſwered as ſhortly
in this wiſe.
            
               Pandoſto.
               
                  Fawnia are you become leſſe wilfull, and more wiſe, to preferre
the loue of a King, before the liking of a poore Knight? I
thinke ere this you thinke it is better to be fauoured of a King,
than of a ſubiect.
            
            
               Fawnia.
               
                  Pandoſto, the body is ſubiect to victories, but the mindes
not to bée ſubdued with conqueſt: honeſty is to be preferred
before honour, and a dram of faith weigh downe a tunne of
gold. I haue promiſed Meleagrus my loue, and will performe
no leſſe.
            
            
               Pandoſto.
               
                  Fawnia, I know thou art not ſo vnwiſe in thy choyce, as to
refuſe the offer of a King, nor ſo vngratefull as to deſpiſe a good
turne: thou art now in that place where I may command, and
yet thou ſéeſt I intreat: my power is ſuch, that I may compell
by force, and yet I ſue by prayers. Yéeld Fawnia, thy loue
to him which burneth in thy loue: Meleagrus ſhall be ſet frée,
thy Countrey-men diſcharged, and thou both loued and honoured.
            
            
               Fawnia.
               I ſée Pandoſto, where luſt ruleth, it is a miſerable thing to
be a virgin: but know this, that I will alwayes preferre fame
before life, and rather chooſe death then diſhonour.
            
            
               Pandoſto ſéeing that there was in Fawnia a determinate
courage to loue Meleagrus, and a reſolution without feare to
hate him, fléeing away from her in a rage, hee ſware that if in
ſhort time ſhe would not be won by reaſon, he would forget all
courteſie, and compell her to grant by rigour. But theſe threatning
words no whit diſmayed Fawnia; but that ſhee ſtill both

deſpighted and deſpiſed Pandoſto. While thus theſe two Louers
ſtroue, the one to winne loue, the other to liue in hate: Egiſtus
heard certaine newes by Merchants of Bohemia, that
his ſonne Doraſtus was impriſoned by Pandoſto: which made
him feare greatly, that his ſonne ſhould be but hardly intreated:
yet conſidering that Bellaria and hée were cleered by the
Oracle of Apollo, from the crime wherewith Pandoſto had
vniuſtly charged them: hee thought beſt to ſend with all ſpéede
to Pandoſto, that hée ſhould ſet frée his ſonne Doraſtus, and
put to death Fawnia, and her father Porrus. Finding this, by
the aduice of counſell, the ſpeedieſt remedy to releaſe his ſonne,
hée cauſed preſently two of his ſhips to be rigged, and thorowly
furniſhed with prouiſion of men and victuals, and ſent diuers
of his Nobles Embaſſadours into Bohemia: who willing to
obey the King, and receiue their young Prince, made no delayes
for feare of danger, but with as much ſpéed as might be,
ſayled towards Bohemia; the wind and ſeas fauoured them
greatly, which made them hope of ſome good hap: for within
thrée dayes they were landed: which Pandoſto no ſooner heard
of their arriuall, but hee in perſon went to méet them, intreating
them with ſuch ſumptuous and familiar courteſie, that
they might well perceiue how ſorry he was for the former iniuries
he had offered to their King and how willing (if it might
be) to make amends. As Pandoſto made report to them how
one Meleagrus a Knight of Trapolonia, was lately arriued with
a Lady called Fawnia in his Land, comming very ſuſpitiouſly:
accompanied onely with one ſeruant, and an old Shepheard:
the Ambaſſadours perceiued by the halfe, what the whole tale
meant, and began to coniecture that was Doraſtus, who for
feare to be knowne, had changed his name. But diſſembling
the matter▪ they ſhortly arriued at the Court▪ where after they
had béene very ſolemnly and ſumptuouſly feaſted, the Noblemen
of Sicilia being gathered together, they made report of their
Ambaſſage: where they certified Pandoſto, that Meleagrus
was ſonne and heire to the King Egiſtus: and that his name
was Doraſtus: and how contrary to the Kings mind he had priuily
conueyed away that Fawnia, intending to marry her being
but daughter to that poore Shepheard Porrus. Whereupon the

Kings requeſt was, that Capnio, Fawnia, and Porrus, might
be murthered and put to death, and that his ſonne Doraſtus
might be ſent home in ſafety. Pandoſto hauing attentiuely and
with great maruell heard their Ambaſſage, willing to reconcile
himſelfe to Egiſtus, and to ſhew him how greatly he eſtéemed
his fauour, although loue and fancy forbad him to hurt
Fawnia, yet in deſpight of loue he determined to execute Egiſtus
will without mercy, and therefore hee preſently ſent for Doraſtus
out of priſon: who maruelling at his vnlooked for courteſie,
found at his comming to the Kings preſence, that which hee
leaſt doubted of, his fathers Ambaſſadours: who no ſooner ſaw
him, but with great reuerence they honoured him, and Pandoſto
embracing Doraſtus, ſet him by him very louingly in a chaire
of ſtate. Doraſtus aſhamed that his folly was bewrayed, ſate
a long time as one in a maze, till Pandoſto told him the ſumme
of his fathers Ambaſſage: which he had no ſooner heard, but he
was touched to the quicke, for the cruell ſentence that was pronounced
againſt Fawnia: but neither could his ſorrow nor perſwaſions
preuaile: for Pandoſto commanded, that Fawnia, Porrus,
and Capnio, ſhould be brought to his preſence: who were
no ſooner come, but Pandoſto hauing his former loue turned
into diſdainefull hate, began to rage againſt Fawnia in theſe
termes.
            THou diſdainefull vaſſall, thou curriſh kite, aſſigned by the
Deſtinies to baſe fortune, and yet with an aſpiring minde
gazing after honour: how durſt thou preſume being a begger,
to match with a Prince? by thy alluring lookes to inchaunt
the ſonne of a King, to leaue his owne Country, to fulfill thy
diſordinate luſts? O deſpightfull minde: A proud heart in a
begger, is not vnlike a great fire in a ſmall cottage, which warmeth
not the houſe, but burneth it: aſſure thy ſelfe thou ſhalt
dye: and thou old doting foole, what folly hathbeene ſuch, as
to ſuffer thy daughter to reach aboue thy fortune: looke for no
other meede, but the like puniſhment. But Capnio, thou
which haſt betrayed the King, and haſt conſented to the vnlawfull
luſt of thy Lord and Maſter, I know not how iuſtly I may
plague thée: death is too eaſie a puniſhment for thy falſhood,

and to liue, (if not in extreame miſery) were not to ſhew thée
equity. I therefore award, that thou ſhalt haue thine eyes put
out, and continually till thou dyeſt, grind in a mill like a brute
beaſt. The feare of death brought a ſorrowfull ſilence vpon
Fawnia, and Capnio: but Porrus ſéeing no hope of life, burſt
forth in theſe ſpéeches.
            
               PAndoſto, and ye noble Ambaſſadours of Sicilia, ſéeing without
cauſe I am condemned to die. I am yet glad I haue opportunity
to disburden my conſcience before my death, I will
tell you as much as I know and yet no more then is true, wheras
I am accuſed that I haue béen a ſupporter of Fawnia's pride
and ſhée diſdained as a vile beggar; ſo it is, that I am neither
father vnto her, nor ſhe daughter vnto me.
            For it ſo hapned, that I being a poore Shepheard in Sicilia,
liuing by kéeping other mens ſlocks, one of my ſhéep ſtraying
downe to the ſea-ſide, as I went to ſeeke her, I ſaw a little
boat driuen vpon the ſhore, wherin I found a babe oſ ſixe dayes
old, wrapped in a mantle of ſcarlet, hauing about the necke
this chaine: I pitying the child, and deſirous of the treaſure,
carryed it home, to my wiſe, who with great care nurſed it
vp, and ſet it to kéepe ſhéepe. Here is the chaine and Iewels,
and this Fawnia is the child whom I ſound in the boat; what
ſhe is, or of what Parentage I know not: but this I am aſſured,
that ſhe is none of mine.
            
               Pandoſto would ſcarce ſuffer him to tell out his tale, but
that he required the time of the yéere, the manner of the boat,
and other circumſtances: which when he found agréeing to his
count, ſodainely he lept from his ſeat, and kiſſed Fawnia, wetting
her tender chéeks with his teares, and crying, My daughter
Fawnia, ah my ſwéet Fawnia, I am thy father Fawnia: this
ſudden paſſion of the King draue them all into a maze, eſpecially
Fawnia and Doraſtus. But when the King had breathed himſelfe
a while in this new ioy, he rehearſed before the Ambaſſadours
the whole matter, and how hee had entreated his wife
Bellaria for Iealouſie, and that this was the child whom he ſent
to float in the ſeas.
            
               Fawnia was not more ioyfull that ſhe had found ſuch a father,

then Doraſtus was glad he ſhould get ſuch a wife. The Ambaſſadors
reioyced that their young Prince had made ſuch a choice:
That thoſe Kingdomes which through enmity had long time
béene diſſeuered, ſhould now through perpetuall amity be vnited
and reconciled. The Citizens and ſubiects of Bohemia
(hearing that the King had found againe his daughter which
was ſuppoſed dead, ioyfull that there was an heire apparant to
the Kingdome) made Bone-fires and ſhewes throughout all the
City. The Courtiers and Knights appointed Iuſts and Turneis,
to ſignifie their willing mindes in gratifying the Kings
hap.
            Eightéene dayes being paſt in theſe Princely ſports, Pandoſto
willingto recompence old Porrus, of a Shepheard, made him
a Knight: which done, prouiding a ſufficient Nauy to receiue
him and his retinue, accompanied with Doraſtus and Fawnia,
and the Sicilian Ambaſſadours, he ſailed towards Sicilia, where
he was moſt princely entertained by Egiſtus: who hearing this
Comicall euent, reioyced greatly at his ſonnes good hap, and
without delay (to the perpetuall ioy of the two young Louers)
celebrated the marriage. Which was no ſooner ended, but Pandoſto
(calling to mind how he firſt betrayed his friend Egiſtus,
how his iealouſie was the cauſe of Bellaria's death, that contrary
to the law of nature, he had luſted after his owne daughter)
moued with theſe deſperate thoughts, hee fell in a melancholly
fit, and to cloſe vp the Comedy with a Tragicall ſtratagem, he
ſlew himſelfe: whoſe death being many daies bewayled of Fawnia,
Doraſtus, and his deare friend Egiſtus, Doraſtus taking
leaue of his father, went with his wife and the dead corps
into Bohemia: where after it was ſumptuouſly
intombed, Doraſtus euded his
dayes in contented
quiet.
            FINIS.
            
            
         
      
   

