
   
      
         
            Tormenting Tophet: or A terrible description of Hel able to breake the hardest heart, and cause it quake and tremble. Preached at Paules Crosse the 14. of Iune 1614. By Henry Greenvvood, Master of Arts, and preacher of the word of God.
            Greenwood, Henry, b. 1544 or 5.
         
         
            
               1615
            
         
         Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02192
            STC 12336
            ESTC S120478
            99855674
            99855674
            21176
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02192)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21176)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 713:16)
         
         
            
               
                  Tormenting Tophet: or A terrible description of Hel able to breake the hardest heart, and cause it quake and tremble. Preached at Paules Crosse the 14. of Iune 1614. By Henry Greenvvood, Master of Arts, and preacher of the word of God.
                  Greenwood, Henry, b. 1544 or 5.
               
               
                  The second edition corrected and amended.
               
               [6], 82, [6] p.   
               
                  Imprinted by George Purslowe for Henry Bell, and are to be solde at his shop without Bishopsgate,
                  London :
                  1615.
               
               
                  Caption title reads: "An earnest and zealous prayer, to be saued from the damnation of Tophet" has caption title.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
               Hell --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-02
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-04
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-04
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            TORMENTING TOPHET: OR A terrible Deſcription of HE
                  •
               L, able to breake the hardeſt heart, and cauſe it quake and tremble.
            
            Preached at Paules Croſſe the 14. of Iune 1614.
            BY HENRY GREENVVOOD, Maſter of Arts, and Preacher of the Word of GOD.
            
            The ſecond Edition corrected and amended,

                  Eſay 30.33.
                  Tophet is prepared of old; it is euen prepared for the King: he hath made it deepe and large: the burning thereof is fire &amp; much wood: the breath of the Lord like a Riuer of Brimstone doth kindle it.
               
            
            LONDON Imprinted by George Purſlowe for Henry Bell, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop without Biſhopſgate. 1615.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND my very deare friends Sir LESTRAVNGE MORDAVNT of Maſſingham Hall in the County of Norfolke Knight Baronet, and Lady FRAVNCIS MORDAVNT his moſt louing Bed-fellow, HENRY GREENVVOOD Wiſheth all increaſe of Grace in this Life, and Eternall Life in Life to come.
            
            
               IT is, and hath beene long ſince (Right Worſhipful) the cuſtome of the learned, that when they commended to publike view (therein ayming at cōmon good) their Chriſtian paines and diuine indeuours,

(knowing that the truth hath, and alwayes had many oppoſitions and detractions) to preſent them to men of high place, and well affected in Religion, that ſo their works might paſſe with leſſe feare, and danger of diſgrace and opprobrie: I (though vnlearned) making bold to imitate their Chriſtian policy herein, haue preſumed to preſent that doctrine to your Worſhips eies, that lately in publike place was ſounded in your eares, both of which ſenſes are great Inſtruments in the furtherance of our ſoules in the way of Gods Kingdome; for as the eare conueieth grace to the affections of the ſoule, ſo the eye bringeth much matter to the vnderſtā
               ding of the mind; nay, the eare cannot ſo often be an Auditor, as the eye an Oratour to the conſcience.
            For which cauſe (your Worſhips nothing more affecting than growth in Grace and Religion) I haue attempted to commend to your often conſiderations Tormenting Tophet, for as nothing allureth the heart to grace, more than Gods mercies, ſo nothing more preualent

againſt ſinne, than his fearefull and terrible iudgements.
            If therfore your gracious Worſhips ſhall vouchſafe to accept of theſe my poore preſented paines, it will giue content to mine own heart, and (doubtles) anſwerable comfort to your owne ſoules.
            And to conclude, as the Lord hath abundantly bleſſed your Worſhips with graces internall, and bleſſings external; So (to vſe the words of the Apoſtle) the very God of peace ſanctifie you ſtill throughout, and I pray God that your whole spirits, and ſoules and bodies, may be kept blameles to the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Amen. From Hempſted in Eſſex, Aprill, 3. 1615.
            
               Your Worſhips alwayes ready to bee commaunded in the Lord, HEN. GREENVVOOD.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.
            CHriſtian Reader, I commend to thy charitable view, this terrible and lamentable deſcription of Hell, a Subiect moſt neceſſary in theſe dayes, wherin Iniquity hath gotten the vpper hād: the greateſt part of mankind laboreth of this dangerous diſeaſe, namely, hardnes of hart and contempt of all grace, I therefore for the remouing of this damnable euil, haue prepared this Tormenting Corraſiue. Blame mee not if I be too bitter in denouncing GODS Iudgements againſt ſinne, the preſumption of the time compels me, this onely is the ayme of my intention herein, that many may bee ſaued from the damnation hereof.
            Let not the Quotations of Latine and other tongues offend thee, but know this they are but as country Stiles, ſtepping ouer them thou loſeſt not the way by them, for their Expoſitions follow them.
            Thus commending this Tractate to thy chriſtian conſideration, and thy ſelf to Gods moſt bleſſed protection, I reſt
            
               Thine euerlouing and vvelvvilling brother in the Lord, HEN. GREENWOOD,
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               ¶ TORMENTING TOPHET, OR A terrible deſcription of Hell, able to breake the hardeſt heart, and cauſe it quake and tremble.
               
               
                  
                     
                        Eſay 30.33.
                     
                     Tophet is prepared of old; it is euen prepared for the King: he hath made it deepe and large: the burning thereof is fire &amp; much wood: the breath of the Lord like a Riuer of Brimstone doth kindle it.
                  
               
               
                  ALbeit the Lord in the beginning created man in glorious manner, omninō ad imaginem ſui, ratione ſapientem, vita innocentem, dominio potentem, altogether after his own moſt glorious image, in purity, and in perfection of holineſſe both in ſoule and body
                  : yet withall, he gaue him naturam flexibilem, a mutable and changeable nature,
                   creating him inpoteſtate standi, ſeupoſſe cadendi: in power

of ſtanding, and in poſſibilitie of falling:
                   power of ſtanding, that he had from God his creatour, poſſibility of falling, that he had from himſelfe, being a creature.
               
                  Auguſt.A reaſon whereof S. Auguſtine giueth in his booke of Confeſſions: Becauſe the Lord created man ex nihilo: of nothing
                  : therefore hee left in man poſſibility to returne in nihilum: into nothing,
                   if he obey'd not the will of his Maker.
               
                  Baſil,And as Baſil ſayth, Si Deus dediſſet Adae naturam immutabilem, deos potius quàm homines condidiſſet: id eſt: If God had giuen Adam an immutable and vnchangeable nature hee had created a God, not a man:
                   for this is a mayne trueth in Diuinity, immutabiliter eſſe bonum, proprium ſoliuseſt Dei: id est, to be immutably, and vnchangeablie good, onely proper to God.
                  
               
               
                  Adam therefore being thus created, that hee might eyther ſtand or fall, by the Diuels ſubtill ſuggeſtion, and by the abuſe of his owne free will, receyued a double downefall, the fall of

ſinne by diſobedience, and the fall of death by ſinne, the laſt fall being the wages of the firſt fall, as ye may reade in the laſt verſe of the ſixt to the Romanes, The wages of ſinne is death.
                  Rom. 6.
               
               The Lord therefore hauing pitty vpon this his miſerable eſtate, vouchſafed in his Sonne to ſhew mercy vpon ſome by election to ſaluation: as to ſhew iuſtice vpon other ſome by reprobation to damnation.
               According to which irreuocable decree, the Lord hath prepared euen from the foundations of the earth, anſwerable places: a glorious habitation for the one, and a terrible dungeon for the other.
               Which generall truth is confirmed in the words of my Text, hauing particular reference to the reprobat Aſſyrians. For as the Lord in his mercy doth promiſe in this Chapter to his people repenting them of their ſinnes, manifold bleſſings, ſpirituall and corporall, temporall and eternall: ſo doth he threaten in his iuſtice terrible vengeance to their enemies, the idolatrous

                  Babylonians and Aſſyrians, not onely temporall, but alſo eternall, not to the meane ſubiect alone, but to the King himſelfe, ſaying: Tophet is prepared of old, it is euen prepared for the King, &amp;c.
               
               Not to inſiſt therefore too long vpon introductions, leſt it ſhould be ſayde to mee, as once a flowting Cynicke ſayde to the Citizens of Myndus, a little City with great Gates: Shut your Gates leſt your City runne out: I come to the Text it ſelfe, which containeth in it a terrible and lamentable deſcription of Hell, prepared of olde for the tormenting of all vngodly people of the world, of what eſtate or condition ſoeuer they be, euen for the King. For Tophet is prepared of olde, it is euen prepared for the King, &amp;c.
               
            
            
               In which terrible Deſcription of Hell, I obſerue ſo many ſeuerals, as the Beaſt had heads in the Reuelation,Reu. 13.1. that muſt be tormented in her.
               
                  Firſt, the certainety of this place of torment: Tophet is prepared of old.
               
               Secondly, The parties for whom: for all vngodly wretches, yea euen for the King: It is euen prepared for the King.
               
               Thirdly, the impoſſibility of getting out, once in: He hath made it deepe.
               
               Fourthly, the great number that ſhall bee tormented in her: expreſſed in this word, Large.
               
               Fiftly, the extremity and bitternes of the torments of Tophet: the burning there of is fire.
               
               Sixtly, the eternity and euerlaſtingneſſe of the torments of Tophet: Much wood, ſo much as ſhall neuer be waſted.
               Seuently, the Authour or inflictour of theſe fearefull tortures: &amp; that is the Lord offended: in theſe words, The breath of the Lord like a riuer of brimſtone doth kindle it: wherein I note the ſeuerity of God againſt ſinne and ſinners.
               The certainety of this place of torment is here deſcribed by three:The firſt part. by the

Name, by the Act, by the Antiquity.
               Firſt, by the name: Tophet.
               
               Secondly, by the Act: is prepared.
               Thirdly, by the Antiquity: of olde.
               
                  Tophet is prepared of old.
               
                  Tophet.This Tophet was a valley neare vnto Ieruſalem, iuxta piſcinam fullonis &amp; agrum Acheldema, ad auſtrum Sion:
                   that is, Neare to the Fullers poole and the field Acheldema, on the South ſide of Sion: Called alſo Gehinnom, the valley or dale of Hinnom: Quialoeus iſte in praedio erat viri cuiuſdam Hinnom dicti: Becauſe this place was in the poſſeſſion of a certaine man called Hinnom:Aretius. as ſayth Aretius: In which place the Iewes (following the curſed example of the Ammonites) did ſacrifice their children in the fire to the idol Moloch, Quempro Mercurio colebant: whom they worſhipped for Mercurie, as ſayth Montanus:
                  Montan. in Eſai. Scultet. in Eſai. or rather, pro Saturno colebant, for Saturne,
                   as ſayth Scultetus, Quena Poetae proprios fingunt deuoraſſe filios: whom the Poets fained to haue deuoured his owne children.
               
               This Moloch was Idolum aereum,

concauum, paſſis brachijs, ad excipiendos infantes ſacro nefario deſtinatos,
                  Scultet. in Eſai. 
                  ſubiectis prunis torrendos: that is, A brazen Idoll, hollow within, his hands ſpred abroad, to receiue infants that were through their curſed Idolatry tortured in the fire, and ſacrificed to him: as writeth Scultetus. Snepfſius deſcribeth this Idoll on this manner:Snepfſius in Eſai. 
                  Idoli ſtatua erat cuprea (ſic enim annotarunt Hebraei) porrigens brachia ad excipiendos pueros: that is, This Idoll was made of Copper (ſo the Hebrewes haue obſerued) ſtretching forth his hands to receyue thoſe maſſacred children.
               
               The Iewes more at large write of him, that hee was of a great ſtature,Deſcriptio Moloch. and hollow within, hauing ſeuen places or chambers within him: the firſt, to receiue meale offered: the ſecond, Turtle Doues: the third, a Sheepe: the fourth, a Ramme: the fift a Calfe: the ſixt, an Oxe: the ſeuenth, a Child: he was faced like a Calfe, imitating the idolatry of Egypt: his hands were euer ſtretched out to receyue bribes and gifts: his Prieſts were called

                  Chemmarims, becauſe they were ſmoked with the incenſe offered to Idols, of whom yee may reade, 2. King. 23.5. Hoſ. 10.5. Sephan. 1.4.
               
               
                  2. Ki. 23.10This Tophet or valley of Hinnom was put downe by good King Ioſiah, and in contempt thereof, dead carrions and the of-ſcowrings of Ieruſalem commaunded to be caſt.
               The Iewes report, that in Tophet there was a deepe ditch, which they called Os inferni,
                  Iere. 7.32. 
                  the mouth of hell, which neuer could be filled: into which the Chaldeans hauing ſlain the Iſraelits, threw them.
               For the deriuation of this word, ſome thinke that it is deriued à Tophis lapidibus pretioſis in modum Punicis, inter quos nutriebatur ignis: that is, Of the Topaze ſtone like the Punicke, in which fire was nouriſhed: but this deriuation is farre fetcht and faulty.
               
                  TophetBut for moſt certaine, Tophet is deriued of that Hebrew Toph, quod tympanum ſonat:
                   which ſignifieth a Tabret, or a loude Inſtrument: becauſe when they ſacrificed their children to

                  Moloch, they did tympana pulſare,
                  Piſcat. in Eſay. 
                  ne exaudirent eiulatum liberorum qui comburebantur: that is, Smite vpon the tabret, that they might not heare the lamentable ſcreeching of their children in the fire: as ſayth Piſcator.
               
               So that by a certaine Simile,
                  How Tophet taken for hell. the Spirite of God doth here compare hel to Tophet: for as in Tophet there was lamentable ſcreeching of the children in the fire: ſo in hell there ſhall be ſcreeching and ſcreaming, weeping &amp; wayling for euermore.
               Hell hath many names in like reſpects:
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . as it is called 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   of 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   to terrifie: becauſe of the terrours thereof.
               It is called 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   of the priuitiue particle 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : and 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   not to ſee:
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Chytreus in 20. ca. Apoc. numero 7 de poenis. impiorum Auernus. a place without light: which expreſſeth the dolour of hell: as ſayth Chitreus.
               
               It is called Auernus: abſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      vera temperatura: without true temperature:
                   for there the freezing cold ſhall not mitigate the ſcorching heat, nor the ſcorching heat the freezing cold.
               And here it is compared to Tophet,
                  
in regard of the terrible tortures, and pittious outcries of the condemned.
               
                  Simile.
                  
                     Ʋt per hortum voluptatis, Paradiſi ſcilicet, ſedes beatorum figuratur: ita per hunc locum terroris, Tophet, ſcilicet, infernus deſcribitur: that is: As by the garden of pleaſure, namely Paradiſe, the place of the bleſſed is figured: So by this place of terrour, namely, Tophet, the dungeon of hell is deſcribed.
               
               
                  Obſeru.From which fearefull Metaphor we may iuſtly make this our obſeruation: namely, that Hell is a moſt lamentable and wofull place of torment, where (in regard of the extremity of torments impoſed vpon the damned) there ſhall bee ſcréeching and ſcreaming, weeping, wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth for euermore: and this is Tophet.
               
               Where torment ſhall bee vpon torment, each torment eaſeleſſe, endleſſe, remedileſſe; where the worme ſhall be immortall, colde intolerable, ſtinch indurable, fire vnquenchable, darkeneſſe palpable, ſcourges of Deuilles terrible, and ſcreeching and ſcreaming

continuall: and this is Hell.
               In hell (ſayth S. Auſtine) there is vermis conſcientiae, ignitae lachrymae,
                  August. and dolor ſine remedio: that is, The gnawing worme, the burning teares, and ſorrow that can neuer be eaſed.
               
               And againe, hee ſayth in his third Tom. de Spiritu &amp; Anima:
                  Aug. 3. tom. de Spiritu &amp; Anima. 
                  Ibi erit metus, &amp; moeror: luctus &amp; dolor: tunc verè nihil lugere erit niſi flere, quia poenitere tunc nullipoterit valere: ibi erit tortor caedens, vermis corrodens, ignis conſumens: that is, In hell there is howling and horrour, ſobbing and terrour: where weeping helpes not, and repentance bootes not: where is paine killing, worme gnawing, and fire conſuming. 
                        Ʋermis &amp; tenebrae flagellū, frigus &amp; ignis: Daemonisaſpectus, ſcelerum, confuſio, luctus.
                  
               
               
                  Tertullian in Apologetico,
                  Poeta Tertul. in Apologet. ſpeaking of Hell, ſayth thus: Gehenna eſt ignis arcani ſubterraneus ad poenam theſaurus: that is, Hell is a treaſure of ſecret fire kept vnder the earth to puniſh withall. The truth of this heauy report Diues with the reſidue of the damned, doe finde by wofull experience, who ſtill cries out,

I am tormented in this flame.
               This is miſerable Tophet, prepared for all vngodly people of the world.
               
                  
                     Ʋſe. 1 The meditation of theſe torments ſhould breake our ſtony hearts in peeces, and ſtrike vs into ſuch a diſmall dumpe,Dan. 5.5. as was Baltazar, when hee ſaw the hand writing on the wall againſt him: theſe ſhould be of an extractiue force and power, to draw grones from our hearts, teares from our eyes, and ſinnes from our ſoules: Grauia peccata grauia deſiderant lamenta: Great ſinnes require great lamentations:
                   Sweet meat muſt haue ſowre ſawce: ſinne muſt haue mourning, eyther here by attrition Legall and contrition Euangelicall, or elſe hereafter wee ſhall be caſt into Tophet, where wee ſhall lie ſcreeching and ſcreaming continually.
               
                  Gregor.
                  Plangite igitur plangenda: Bewayle your ſinnes therefore that ought to be lamented:
                  
                  
                     
                        •••
                     ſiodor. 
                  Eſtote tam proni ad lamenta, ſicut fuiſtis ad peccata: Bee as prone to lamentation, as euer you were to tranſgreſſion,
                   as prone to lament them, as

euer yee were to commit them.
               In a booke inſcribed De natura rerum, I read of a Byrd called Auis Paradiſi: the Birde of Paradiſe:
                   which is ſo called in regard of her ſplendid and excellent beauty: which Birde being taken in the ſnare of the Fowler,Lib. de nat. rerum doth ingemiſcere ac lachrymare dies nocteſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     , mourne and lament night and day,
                   vntill ſhee be reſtored to liberty: So we that were once Aues Paradiſi,
                  Simile. 
                  Birdes of Paradiſe, but now captiuated in the thraldome of ſinne and Sathan, and lyable to this tormenting Tophet, ſhould neuer ceaſe mourning &amp; wayling, vntill wee bee reſtored to Grace againe.
               Bleſſed are you that haue grace thus to mourne, yee ſhall bee comforted: the Lord will wipe away, as all ſinnes from your ſoules, ſo all teares from your eyes in the kingdome of ſaluation.
               Againe, the conſideration of this 
                     Ʋſe 2 terrible Tophet ſhould cauſe vs willingly to embrace the counſell of the Pſalmiſt:Pſal. 4.4 
                  To ſtand in awe and ſinne

not: And worke in our hearts that feare ſpoken of in the Goſpel of Matthew, Feare him that is able to deſtroy both body and ſoule in hell:
                  Mat. 10.28. This terrible report ſhould ſtrike vs into a threefold feare.
               Feare to be depriued of the grace of God.
               Feare to be excluded the louing preſence of God.
               Feare to be tormented in the Lake vnquenchable.
               
                  ExemplumIt was the practiſe of an holy man, who ſayth: I feare him that is able to damne both body and ſoule: I tremble at hell: I tremble at the Iudges countenance, which is able to make all the Angells and powers of Heauen to temble: I tremble at the voyce of the Archangell: I tremble at the roaring deuils: I am afraid of the gnawing worme, the ſmoake, the vapour, the brimſtone, the darkneſſe, the burning: Ah woe is me that am the ſonne of bitterneſſe, indignation, and eternall weeping.
               
                  Act. 24.16This made Paul indeuour to keepe

a cleare conſcience both towards God and man.
               This made Ierome afraid to offend: Whether I eate or drinke (ſaith hee) or whatſoeuer I doe elſe, me thinkes I heare this ſaying ſounding in mine eares, Ariſe yee dead and come to Iudgement, Ariſe yee dead and come to iudgement: Which when I conſider, it makes me quake and ſhake, and not dare to commit ſinne, which otherwiſe I ſhould haue committed.
               And what is the cauſe (I pray) that wicked wretches runne into al exceſſe and riot of ſinne as they do? Is it not becauſe they lay not to heart this tormenting Tophet? witneſſe elſe the prophet Amos, who ſayth,Amos. 6.3 
                  That they put off from them the euill day, and boldly approach to the ſeates of iniquity: If putting off the remembrance of the vengeance to come, will make men diſſolute and retchleſſe, then ſurely laying to heart the inutterable torments of Tophet, will bee a notable meane to reclayme men from all vngodlineſſe.
               
                  But if men will harden their hearts aboue the hardnes of an Adamant, and will not be moued, neyther by mercies nor iudgement: let all ſuch know that Tophet groaneth for them, where they ſhall howle and yell in fiery torments for euermore.
               Thus much in a word for the word Tophet.
               
               The ſecond, obſeruable for the certainety of this place of torment, is the Act or thing done, in theſe words: Is prepared.
                  Is prepar'd 
                  Parata Tophet, non paranda: It is not ſayd, That Tophet ſhall bee hereafter prepared, or it is now preparing; but it is already prepared: Tophet is prepared.
               The malicious deuil laboureth nothing more then to perſwade men that there is no ſuch place of torment, that ſo the more eaſily hee may leade them thither,Simile. as the thiefe is led to execution with a vayle before his eyes. But for the trueth hereof, let theſe things following duely be obſerued.
               
                  Simile.As a princely magnificence requireth that a King haue a beautifull pallace

for the beſt ſort of men, and a diſmall priſon for the rebellious: So the King of kings hath a glorious pallace wherein are many manſions for his Saints, &amp; a darke and loathſome dungeon for the Diuell and his Angels.
               The law of nations requireth that malefactors for their offences bee baniſhed for euer: ſo the Lord doth baniſh from his gracious preſence all the vngodly of the earth into the fearefull Iland of hell.
               The Cicilian Aetna called at this day Gibillo Monte,
                  Actua. where roarings are heard, and flames of fire are ſéene: the flaſhing of Veſuuius: the cracking, as it were, of fire in a furnace, in the Marine Rocke of Barry: what doe all theſe preſage, but aſſure all thoſe that feare the Lord (beſides his counſel reuealed in his word) that Tophet is already prepared.
               Againe, in all things naturall and ſupernaturall, there is an oppoſition, there is a contrariety: there is good, there is euill: there is light, there is darkenes: there is ioy, there is ſorrow:

there is a Heauen, and therefore there muſt be a Hell, into which the ſoules of the reprobate ſhall be carried when they die, by the blacke and griſly angels.
               Againe, the Scripture ſpeaketh euery where of this place of torment: Whoſoeuer ſhall ſay,
                  Mat. 5.22. 
                  Foole, ſhall bee worthy to be puniſhed with hell fire.
               
               
                  Mar. 9.43.35.47.Againe, It is better for thee to goe into the Kingdome of God, with one foot, with one hand, with one eye, then hauing two feet, two hands, and two eyes, to bee caſt into Hell fire.
               
               But that of the 25. of Matthew is very pregnant for this purpoſe, where the word it ſelfe is vſed:Matth. 25. 
                  Goe from me yee curſed into euerlaſting fire, which is prepared for the Deuill and his Angels.
               
               This doctrine méeteth with all Atheiſts that ſay, There is no heauen, no hell,Refut. Atheist. Pſal. 14.1.
                   no God, no deuill: As that noted foole, that ſaid in his heart, There is no God.
               
               
                  Epicure.With all Epicures, that think there is neyther time nor place, either of heauen

or hell after death: that ſung that curſed Epitaph of Sardanapalus.
                  Eſa. 22.13. Poet.
               
               
                  Ede, bibe, lude: charum praeſentibus exple Delitijs animum, poſt mortem nulla voluptas Eate, drinke, and be merry: for after death there is no pleaſure:
                   They ſay true, for after death they ſhal find ſmal pleaſure in Tophet.
               
               This Doctrine conuinceth alſo all heretikes that deny both Reſurrection and Iudgement,Heretike. nineteene ſeuerall ſorts whereof are reckoned vp together all on a row by that learned writer Danaeus: the Appellites,
                  Danaeus. 
                  Archontikes, Baſilidians, Bardeſaniſts, Caians, Carpocratians, Cerdonians, Heraclites, Hermians, Marcites, Marcionites, Ophites, Proclians, Symonians, Saturninians, Sethians, Seuerians, Seleucians, &amp; Valentinians.
               
               Seeing then that Hell is already prepared, and ſtandeth ready to receiue 
                     Ʋſe 1 to torment all that worke iniquity: ſeing there is but a twine threed betwixt the ſoule of a ſinner, and this ſcorching flame: O how ſhould this prepare vs for the kingdom of heauen?

                  Paratis patet ianua, imparatis clauditur: this is ſayd for Heauen: The prepared Virgins enter in, the imprepared, not.
               
               
                  Imparatis patet ianua, &amp; paratis clauditur: and this is ſayde for Hell: The imprepared enter, the prepared, not.
               
               But, alas the preſumptuous ſecurity of this our age: mē liue as though there were no Hell; or if there be, as though it were afarre off, and yet notwithſtanding it followeth them as neere as the ſhadow doth the body:Reuel. Death and Hell both follow cloſe the perſon of euery ſinner: Death to deuoure the body, and Hell to ſwallow vp the ſoule.
               Yet for all this, the wicked wil ſport themſelues in their ſinnes, and iouiall be in their iniquities: but marke the end, Nouiſſima illarum eſt mors: the end of theſe wayes is death: as wel noteth that iuſt and vpright man Iob:
                  Iob. 21.12.13. they reioyce in the ſound of Organs, and in a moment they goe downe into Tophet: they ſay, Peace, peace, when

                  Tophet is prepared to take away their ſoules.
               O that careleſſe people would conſider this: it would make them liue ſo preciſely, as though it were the laſt moment they had to liue: it would make them cry out in the terrors of their ſoules with the Iaylor,Act. 16. 
                  O what muſt I doe to bee ſaued from the damnation of Tophet?
               
               The third thing obſeruable for the certainety of this place of torment, is the antiquity of the ſame: Of olde.
                  Of olde.
               
               
                  Non caſu aut fortuna parata erat Tophet, ſed certo iudicio omnipotentis definita: id eſt; Tophet was not caſually prepared, but in the determined counſell, and decreed purpoſe of God:
                   not lately founded, but from the foundations of the earth, before man or Angell was created.
               For Hells antiquity, I referre you to the ſecond of Peter,
                  2. Pet. 2.4 the ſecond chapter and fourth verſe; where it is ſayd: If God ſpared not the Angels that fell, but caſt them downe to hell: now they could not be caſt into that which was

not: therefore Hell was ordayned before the fall of Angelles: for the Lord (who beholdeth all things, paſt, preſent, and to come, vno actu, vno ictu, ſimul, &amp; ſemel, at one and the ſelfe ſame preſent) foreſéeing what would become of angels and men, pre-ordayned anſwerable places: for thoſe whom hée hath elected in CHRIST, heauen he hath created of olde: and for thoſe whom he hath left to glorifie his iuſtice, Tophet is prepared of olde.
               
                  Note.Where wee plainely ſée, that the Lord hath irreuocably decréede of the ſtate of Angells and men, before all worlds, for Heauen, and for Hell: as there are but two wayes, ſo there are but two ends, Saluation and Damnation, Heauen and Hell.
               
                  Error Romae.Idle is the opinion of Rome, concerning their inter media loca, middle places,
                   twixt heauen and hell.
               The peruerting Papiſt hath added to Tophet thrée ſubterreſtriall places more: Purgatory, Lymbus Infantum, Lymbus Patrum.
               
               
                  Purgatory.
                  Purgatorie, for thoſe that die in

their veniall ſinnes,Bellar. lib. 2. de Purgatorio. c. 1.
                   and light tranſgreſſions: and for thoſe which haue their ſinnes remitted, but not ſatiſfied for the puniſhment.
               And they place this next to Tophet, where there is both poena damni, and poena ſenſus, puniſhment of loſſe, and puniſhment of feeling; this laſteth not euer, but for a time: for it ſhall be diſſolued at the comming of CHRIST to iudgement.
               
                  Lymbus Infantum,
                  Lymbus Infantum where children remayne dying without Baptiſme.
               And this they place next to Purgatory; where there is poena damni, but not ſenſus, the puniſhment of loſſe, but not of féeling: and this laſteth for euerlaſting.
               
                  Lymbus Patrum,
                  Lymbus Patrum where the Fathers were before CHRISTS comming.
               And this they place vppermoſt: where there was poena damni, but not ſenſus, the puniſhment of loſſe, but not of féeling: but this was diſſolued long ago, by CHRISTS deſcenſion into Hell.
               Thus you ſee how the Pope by

theſe his lies and fopperies, thorowly proueth himſelfe the moſt deare childe of the deuill, the author &amp; founder of all lies.Iohn 8.44 But let euery Chriſtian take this for an inalterable truth, that there is but Election and Reprobation, grace and ſinne, the narrow gate, and the broade way: but two ends, Heauen and Hell; to one of theſe muſt all fleſh goe.
               
                  Athanaſ. de incarnat. Chriſti.
                  Athanaſius ſpeaking to this point, ſayth: Impius in duas partes diſcerpitur, &amp; vt ad duo loca diſcedat, condemnatur: that is, A wicked man is diſtracted in two parts, and condemned to two places, his body to the Graue, and his ſoule to 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   that is, to Hell.
               Séeing then that the Lord hath prepared Tophet of olde, and the Decree of God is gone out vpon all fleſh, eyther for heauen or for hell: this ſhould haſten vs carefully to worke out our ſaluation with feare and trembling, and to make ſure our Election: For what if we haue all the world, and be caſt into Tophet? what ſhall become of vs? it had been better for vs neuer

to haue béene borne.
               Obſerue (I beſéech you) the carriage of the Apoſtles in the Goſpell, when they heard that one of them ſhould betray their Lord and Maſter CHRIST, &amp; woe worth that party that ſhould doe that curſed act: it had béene good for that party neuer to haue béene borne: they were all amazed and aſtonied, and could not bee at quiet, till they knew who ſhould doe that damnable déed: they came therefore to our Sauiour, ſaying:Mar. 14.19 
                  Numquid ego Domine? Is it I, Lord
                  ? Another, Is it I, Lord? So we hearing, that Hell is prepared of old, and the greateſt part of mankind (as ſhall bee ſhewen hereafter,) ſhall bee ſwallowed vp of her: Oh this ſhould make vs carefull,Math. 6. firſt, and aboue all things to ſeeke the kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, that wee may ſee our ſelues in the number of thoſe few, whoſe names are written in the booke of Election, and not in the number of thoſe that ſhall be tormented in Tophet.
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 132.3.Let vs reſolue with the Pſalmiſt, not to ſuffer our eyes to ſléepe, nor our eye-liddes to ſlumber, nor the temples of our head to take any reſt, till wee haue found the ſaluation of our God, our ſoules ſealed to the day of redemption, and freed from the damnation of Tophet. But where is this religious care and godly reſolution? O the diſſolute and deſperate courſe of this our ſinnefull age: men put their ſaluation to a hazard with Ludouike,
                  Ludouic. 
                  Si ſaluabor, ſaluabor, Si damnabor, damnabor: that is, If I be ſaued, I bee ſaued: If I bee damned, I bee damned, there is the care that I take.
               In the feare of God, I earneſtly beſéech you,Rom. 8. aboue al things to make ſure your Election, and that by your Vocation: your Vocation by your Iuſtification: your Iuſtification by your Sanctification, the reward whereof will be eternall glorification.
               Ioyne Vertue with your Faith: with Vertue Knowledge:2. Pet. 1.5. with knowledge Temperance: with Temperance Patience: with Patience Godlineſſe:

with Godlineſſe brotherly Kindneſſe: and with brotherly Kindneſſe Loue: Labour hereby to make your calling and election ſure, for if yée doe theſe things, yee ſhall neuer fall into the vengeance of Tophet.
               
            
            
               The ſecond part of this Text,The ſecōd part. are the parties for whom Tophet is prepared, and that is for al vngodly people of the world, of what eſtate or condition ſoeuer they be:It is euen prepared for the king. 2 Reg. 39.37. 
                  It is euen prepared for the King.
               
               Theſe words in particular haue reference to blaſphemous Senacherib, who was ſlaine of his two ſonnes in a temple of Nineueh, worſhipping his god Niſroſh: and in general, it extēdeth to all idolatrous Kings, Emperours, and Superiours whatſoeuer.
               Here then firſt we ſee,Obſer. 1. that no perſon, in what dignity ſoeuer he be, by his eminent place, is exempted from hell.
               
                  Diues a great perſonage,Luke. 16. yet tormented in thoſe flames: Quid profuit ſibi ſuperbia? quid diuitiarum copia?
                  Wiſd. 
                  What hath pride profited him? or what hath the pompe of riches done him good?
                  
Alas, theſe could not ſaue his Soule: For (as ſayth the Pſalmiſt) a man by his riches cannot redéeme his brother, he cannot giue his ranſome to God:Pſa. 49.67. ſo precious is the redemptiō of ſoules, and their continuance for euer.
               And in Samuel wee rea
                     •
                  e, That Kings are not exempted from the iudgements of God:1. Sa 12.25. 
                  If yee doe wickedly, yee ſhall periſh, and your King.
               
               In the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinths, we may read who they are that are threatned with Tophet:
                  1. Cor. 6.9. neyther fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor wantons, nor theeues, nor couetous, nor drunkards, nor extortioners ſhall inherite the Kingdome of God: This is ſpoken of Kings, as well as of others.Reu. 21.8. And in the Reu. wee finde, that the fearefull and vnbelieuing, the abominable, murtherers and whooremongers, and ſorcerers, idolaters, and all lyers ſhall haue their part in the Lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone: And this is ſpoken of the King as well as of the Begger: for the Lord in iudgement fréeth frō hell, not

according to place, but grace: not outward conditiō, but inward diſpoſition.
               Nay moreouer, great men, Noble men, and mighty Princes, are not onely lyable to Tophet, but the greateſt part of them ſhall to the deuill: Not many wiſe men, not many mighty,1. Cor. 1.26. not many noble are called:1. Tim. 2.4 for as God would haue all men ſaued, and come to the knowledge of the truth .i. ſome of all ſorts, ſome Iewes, ſome Gentiles, ſome Kings, ſome Nobles, ſome Preachers, ſome Rich, ſome Poore: ſo of all theſe, the greateſt ſumme goe downe to Tophet. Yet for all this, great men muſt not bee reproued forſooth, the trueth that maketh againſt them, muſt not be imbraced of them.
               
                  Abner could not abide to heare Iſboſheth tell him of his going into Rizpah his father Sauls Concubine.2. Sam. 3.
               
               
                  Ahab hated Micaiah the ſonne of Imlah for not propheſying (as he ſayd) good vnto him.1. King. 22
               
               The people cryed out in Eſayes time: Dicite nobis placentia, placentia:Eſay 30. that is, ſpeak pleaſing things vnto vs.
               
                  
                  Iere. 11.21.The Prieſts and people of Anathoth threatned Ieremy to take away his life, if he propheſied to them in the name of the Lord.
               
                  Amos 7.
                  Amaziah ſayd to Amos the Prophet: Goe, bee gone, propheſie in Iudah: but prophe
                        •
                     ie no more in Bethel, for it is the Kings Chappell, &amp; it is the Kings Court.
               
               
                  Amos 5.10They hated him that rebuked in the gat
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  nd abhorred him that ſpake vprightly.
               
                  Micah 2.11The people in the time of Micah, liked them well that propheſied to them of Wine and ſtrong Drinke. I pray God that the great ones of this land be not tainted with this corruption.
               Well, for mine owne part I had rather bee ſtormed againſt for preaching Tophet to you here, then yee ſhould curſe me in Tophet hereafter, for ſmoothing and flattering you.
               Yet this reprehenſion of great men, I would wiſh it might be done in wiſdome and humility: with I beſeech you, O King, by the tender mercies of God,
                  Rom. 12.1. reforme theſe and theſe things:

for ſome in this caſe are indiſcreet and too too ſawcy, and rather exaſperate the hearts of their hearers againſt them, then winne them to the Lord by their exhortation.
               If then Kings and great men be not exempted from Tophet,
                  
                     Ʋſe. what ſhould this worke in them but obedience to that counſell of the Pſalmiſt,Pſalm. 2. 
                  Bee wiſe now therefore O yee Kings, ſerue the Lord in feare? Looke vp to heauen, acknowledge your ſelues ſubiects to a greater.
               As the Lord hath honoured Kings aboue others, ſo hee looketh for a greater returne of honour from them than from others: for where the Lord giueth much, there the Lord requireth the more.
               Kings and Princes are the kéepers of the two Tables of the Law of God:Deu. 17.18 and to them is committed from God the gouernement both of Church and Commonwealth: they muſt therefore be carefull that the Word may runne very ſwiftly throughout euery Angle of their realmes:Pſal. 147. So ſhall God gaine

an vniuerſall glory, and Kings themſelues a more ſtable ſubiection.
               
                  Eſa. 49.23.
                  Kings and Queenes are called nurſing Fathers and nurſing Mothers: and all to commend vnto them the care they ſhould haue of Gods glory, and the good of their people.
               
                  Io
                        •
                      15.
                  Ioſua was ſuch a Ruler, that remained reſolute and conſtant in the worſhip of God to his liues end.
               
               
                  
                     
                        •••
                     h. 15.1
                  Dauid prepared a place for the Arke of God, and was careful for the church of the Lord.
               
                  2. Ch. 17.3.
                  Iehoſaphat, Ezechias and Ioſias were reformers of their Kingdoms, enemies to idolatry,cha. 29.1.2 ch. 34.1.2. and graciouſly defended the word of God.
               And bleſſed be God for our Kings moſt excellent Maieſty: who is maieſticall in his place: in religion zealous: in life vertuous: and in mercy aboundantly gracious: The Lord increaſe his graces in him: the Lord annoint him with the oyle of Holyneſſe aboue his fellow princes: and the Lord keepe him from this terrible Tophet: and let all people that beare good will

to this our Engliſh Sion, to this my Prayer ſay, Amen.
               
               
                  It is euen prepared for the King.
               
               Secondly,Obſeru. 2. Act. 10. we may here perceyue with Peter, that verily there is no reſpect of perſons with God in iudgement: he iudgeth the rich as the poore; the father as the child; the maſter as the ſeruant; the king as the beggar: as the Prophet Dauid ſayeth, With righteouſneſſe ſhal he iudge the world, and the people with equity.
               
               
                  Though wickedneſſe among men,
                  Eccle. 3.16 
                  bee in the place of iudgement; yet the Lord our God will deale iuſtly.
               Though among men there is reſpect of perſons to bee had, without which a confuſion would (and this is neceſſary to be vrged, for men are full of contempt, and too ſawcy with them of ſuperiour place and authority:) yet when all ſhal be ſummoned before the tribunall of God, the Lord will indifferently procéed to Iudgement without any reſpect of perſons.
               And this ſhould not onely pull down the haughty minds of the noble (who
                     Ʋſe.
                  
thinke for their greatneſſe here, it will be eaſier for them hereafter than others:) but alſo this ſhould be an vnalterable preſident to all Iudges of the world.
               As they ſit in Gods place, ſo they ſhould imitate the Lord in iudgement: this ſhould make them obey the counſell of the Lord deliuered by the Prophet Dauid:
                  Pſal. 2. 
                  Bee learned yee that are Iudges of the earth.
               
               O the care that Iehoſaphat tooke for iuſt and righteous iudgement: after he had made Iudges, and ſet them in euery City of Iudah, hee gaue them this charge:2. Ch. 19.5.6.7. 
                  Take heed what yee doe, for yee execute not the iudgements of man, but the iudgements of the Lord, and the Lord will bee with you to preſerue you, if you doe iuſtly, but to confound you if you doe vniuſtly: wherefore now let the feare of the Lord bee vpon you, take heed and doe it: for there is no iniquity with our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor receyuing of rewards.
               
               O that this gracious counſell were

intertayned of the Iudges of this land, then we ſhould not heare of ſo many complaints in our land as wee doe: then we ſhould not haue cauſe to complayne with the Prophet,Eſay 59.14 
                  That iudgement is turned backeward, and iuſtice ſtandeth afarre off: that trueth is gone, and equity no where to be found: then wee ſhould not haue ſo many beggard by the Law, as dayly are: Law was neuer made to vndoe men, but to compell men to doe well: it was made to curbe the vnruely, but not to beggar the innocent: it is grown to this ſaying now a dayes, I had rather looſe it, being my right, than goe to law for it; why, what is the cauſe? O becauſe of rackt fees, cloſe bribes, and the perpetuity of attendance.
               
               
                  Iudicate ſecundum iuſtitiam, Iudge, iudge, O yee ſonnes of men, according to righteouſneſſe:
                   let your iudgement be in

                     
                        veritate, in trueth.
                        
                     
                     
                        iudicio, in iudgement.
                        
                     
                     
                        iuſtitia, in righteouſnes.
                        
                     
                  
               
               I pray God it may neuer bee ſayde of our Iudges of England, as once

was ſayd of the Iudges of Iſrael;Eſa. 5.7. 
                  The Lord looked for iudgement, but behold oppreſſion: for righteouſneſſe, but behold a crying.
               
               Let not there be found in a land where the Goſpell dwelleth, ſuch Iudges as were thoſe that killed innocent Naboth.
                  1. King. 21
               
               Let none be like the ſonnes of Samuel,
                  1. Sam. 8.3. 
                  That turned aſide after lucre, and took rewards, and peruerted the iudgement.
               
               The duety of Iudges is notably ſet down in the 23. of Ex. Thou ſhalt not receyue a falſe tale: Thou ſhalt not ouerthrow the truth for the multitudes ſake; Thou ſhalt not ouerthrow the right of the poore in his ſuite: Thou ſhalt keepe thee from a falſe matter: Thou ſhalt take no gift, for the gift blindeth the wiſe, and peruerteth the words of the righteous.
               
               And this charge is continued in Leuiticus;
                  Leu. 29.15. 
                  Yee ſhall not doe vniuſtly in iudgement: Thou ſhalt not fauour the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty, but thou ſhalt

iudge thy neighbour iuſtly.
               
               A Iudge muſt be Scientia potens,
                  Iudicis officium. and 
                     Ʋirtute valens: that is, Able in learning, and zealous in liuing: by the one he ſhall, diſcernere inter allegata, Diſcerne betwixt caſes propounded:
                   by the other, diſrumpere iniquitatem, without hinderance puniſh and confound all manner of iniquity.
                  
               
               In all your Iudgements let theſe be aymed at, the glory of God, the righting of wrong, the ſuppreſſion of euill, and the maintenance of truth.
               Be zealous for the glory of our God; and let the good lawes that are, bee duly and impartially executed.
               It was a great commendation that was giuen to Seleucus Gouernour of the Locretians,
                  Seleucus. who hauing made this Law againſt whoredome, That whoſoeuer committed the act, ſhould looſe both his eyes: his ſonne being taken in the fact, was not pardoned, though the Citizens begged it earneſtly: but hee cauſed one of his ſonnes eyes to bee pulled out, and one of his owne

eyes: So hee ſhewed himſelfe a mercifull Father, and a iuſt Iudge.
               O that we had the like laws againſt this, and the like moſtodious offences, and that they were as ſtrictly executed: that many hereby may bee ſaued from Tophet.
               
               The Lord guide that honourable aſſembly in Court of Parliament, that they may all ioyne with one voyce and ſpirit, for the baniſhing of Popery, the reforming of iniquity, and maintaining and countenancing of the word of trueth, and painefull Preachers of the ſame.
               And you (my honourable Lord) as you haue begun wel, in reforming many foule abuſes in this City, ſo in the zeale of the Lord,Pſal. 45.4. 
                  Proſper with your glory: ride on with the word of truth, meekeneſſe and righteouſneſſe, and your right hand ſhall teach you terrible things.
               
               Thus am I bolde to caſt in among you the ſilly mite of my counſell, meerely of Chriſtian Charity, tha
                     •
                   yée may neuer taſte of the woefull

damnation of Tophet.
               
            
            
               The third part of the deſcription of Tophet, is ſet downe in theſe wordes,The third part. He hath made it deepe. 
                  He hath made it deepe.
               
               Many from theſe words do goe about to proue the locall place of Hell, concluding it to bee below: as from the ſignification of Sheol alſo.Sheol.
               
               
                  Sheol is taken for a Pit, or Graue, or Hell: the ſtate of the dead, the place of the damned ſpirits.
               In the Scriptures, ſometimes it is taken for the Graue, and ſometime for Hell: ſo is 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   alſo.
               The Septuagint tranſlating the Hebrew into Greeke, and expreſſing there the ſenſe of Sheol, vſed 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   both for the death of the body in the Graue, and of the ſoule in Hell.
               
                  Mercer vpon Geneſis ſayth,Mercer in c. 37. Gen. 
                  That the proper ſignification of Sheol, is to ſignifie all places vnder the earth, and not the pit or graue alone: wherupon it is euery where oppoſed to heauen, which is higheſt of all.
               Hell is called by the name of Abyſſus in the Scriptures,Abyſſus. which ſignifieth

a déepe and vaſt gulfe vnder the earth, a bottomleſſe pit: into which the deuils feare to bee ſent: and where they are chained and bound when it pleaſeth God.
                  Luke 8. Reu. 20.
               
               From which Abyſſus, there is an aſſent to the earth, no deſcent lower: Reuelat. 9.2. and 11.7. and 17.8. and therefore hell ſuſpected to bee beneath.
               
                  Nic. de Lyra in Eſai.Becauſe Tophet is here ſayd to be profunda, deepe, Nicolaus de Lyra putat eſſe circa centrum terrae: Thinketh that it is about the centre of the earth.
                  
               
               The Apoſtles that preached to the Iewes, vſed the word Gehenna, from the Hebrewes, which they well vnderſtood: and Saint Iames writing to the Iewes, ſayth; The tongue is inflamed of Gehenna, of hell: but the reſt of them that preached to the Gentiles, vſed the word 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , which name was knowne vnto them, and they tooke it to be a place vnder the earth, where the wicked after this life were puniſhed.Tartarus Heſiod. in Theogonia.
               
               
                  Tartarus (which is vſed for Hel) is ſo farre vnder the earth, as Heauen is

aboue the earth, ſayth Heſiodus.
               
               The Poet ſpeaking of it, ſayth, Tartarus ipſe bis patet in praeceps tantum: .i. Tartarus is twice as deepe as Heauen is high.
                  
               
               The Rabbines hold Hell to bee below: as Rabbi Abraham ſayth:Rab. Ab. in c. 2. Ionae. 
                  Sheol makom, &amp;c. Sheol is a deepe place oppoſed to Heauen which is on high.
                  
               
               And Rabbi Leui ſayth,Rab. Leu. in cap. 26. Ioh. 
                  Sheol hi mattah, &amp;c. Sheol is abſolutely below, and is the centre.
                  
               
               The Scriptures alſo place Hell below:Eſay 14.9. 
                  Sheol beneath is moued for thee to meete thee at thy comming.
               
               
                  Moſes calleth it the lower hell:Deu. 32.22. 
                  Fire is kindled in my wrath, and ſhall burne vſque ad infernum inferiorem, to the bottome of hell.
               
               The Pſalmiſt calleth it a déepe pit: Let him caſt them into the fire,
                  Pſa. 140.10. 
                  and into the deepe pits, that they riſe not: And in another place, he calleth it the Pit of Perdition.
                  Pſal. 55.
               
               
                  Iohn calleth it a Burning Lake,
                  Reu 20. in the Reuelation, which muſt needs bee below.
               
                  
                  Pron. 9.18.
                  Salomon ſpeaketh of the depth of this place, ſaying, The gh
                        •
                     ſts of an harlot are in the depth of hell.
               
               
                  Pro. 15.24.And againe, The way of Life is on high, to auoyde from hell beneath.
               
               Thus it is manifeſt, that Hell is beneath in the loweſt parts of the workemanſhip of God: But preciſely to ſay, where,Locus inferni. whether in the centre of the centre of the world, or in the ayre, or in the water, or vpon the earth, it is not reuealed: neyther is it needful for vs to know: but ſurely it ſhall bee in the moſt remote place from Heauen, which is in and about the earth: for the ſoules of the righteous when they are diſſolued from their bodies, do preſently paſſe to the locall place of Coelum Empyraeum: and the ſoules of the damned are conſtrayned to ſtay below in the loweſt Elements, where they are and ſhall be tormented for euermore.
               But if a man be too curious in this poynt,Socrates. I would wiſh him conferre with Socrates, who being aſked what was done in hell, ſaid: Hee neuer went thither, nor communed with any that

came from thence: By which anſwere he derided the curioſity of the demander.
               
                  Euclides (as Maximus writeth) being demaunded of one what the Gods did,Maxim. ſerm. 23. and with what things they were beſt delighted, ſayde, As for other things I know not, but I am ſure of this, that they hate all curious perſons.
               
               But this is not the thing we ayme at in this depth of Hell.
               This word Deepe doth bewray vnto vs the impoſſibility of getting out,Obſeruatio. once in: for God hath made Hell ſo déepe, as there is no bepe of crawling out.
               
                  In inferno nulla redemptio: In hel there is no redemption:
                   Therefore,Infernus 
                  Infernus ab inferendo dictus, quia ita inferuntur &amp; praecipitantur, vt nunquam aſcenſuri ſint: that is, Hell is ſayde of caſting in, for they ſhall bee ſo caſt downe, as they ſhall neuer haue hope or power of cravvling out.
               
               
                  Infernus (ſaith Hugo) est profundus fine fundo
                  : that is,Hugo. 
                  A deepe vvithout

bottome. That party that had not on the wedding garment, was not onely caſt into hell, but hee was alſo bound hand and foot: and all to ſhew the impoſſibility of getting forth, once in: Binde him hand and foote,
                  Mat. 22.13 
                  and caſt him into vtter darkenes.
               
               
                  Simile.Now alas, if a man be bound hand and foot, and caſt into a well fiue thouſand fadomes deepe, what hope hath he of euer comming out? ſo hell is deep, and he that is once tumbled in, ſhall neuer come forth more.
               
                  Luk. 16.28.This is euident by the ſpeech of Diues, who ſaid: O Father Abraham, ſend Lazarus, or ſome from the dead, that my brethren may not come into the like place of torment. What is the reaſon that Diues begged not for his own paſſage from thence vnto them, who was able to haue taught the dolours of hell by wofull experience? O he knew that that had been booteleſſe, for he ſaw ingentum hiatum, A great gulfe ſet betwixt heauen and hell,
                   that made the paſſage impoſſible.
               In earthly priſons and dungeons, a

man by ſome or other meanes happily may get out: but hell is deepe, ſo deepe, as Heauen, Earth, and Hell, can neuer helpe one poore ſoule forth.
               This then well conſidered, ſhould 
                     Vſe 1 worke deepe humiliation in the ſoules of euery of vs, that ſo grace may receyue vs, and not this deepe deuoure vs.
               
                  One depth cryeth and calleth out for an other: the depth of hell calleth to vs for anſwerable humiliation: hee that will not bee humbled for his ſins héere, ſhall bee humbled and tumbled to the deepe of hell hereafter.
               
                  God giueth grace to the humble:
                  Simile. yea the déeper thou art in the Law, the higher ſhalt thou be in the Goſpel, the deeper in hell, the higher in heauen: a bucket, the déeper it goeth into the well, the more water it bringeth vp with it: ſo the déeper a man is humbled for ſinne, the more ſhall bee his grace of ſaluation. Humble your ſelues therefore vnder the mighty hand of God, that yee may bee all exalted in the day of Viſitation.
               
               
                  
                  Luk. 18.13.In this déep was the poore Publican, when in bitterneſſe of heart he vttered theſe words, Lord be mercifull to me à ſinner: A ſinner by birth, a ſinner by life, a ſinner by thought, a ſinner by word, a ſinner by worke, a ſinner by ſins of omiſſion, a ſinner by ſinnes of commiſſion, a ſinner beforè my conuerſion, a ſinner many thouſand times ſince my conuerſion: Lord bee mercifull to me a lamentable ſinner.
               
               
                  
                     Ʋſe 2 Againe, ſéeing hell is ſo deepe, as once in, no hope of crawling out: Let vs ſeeke the Lord while hee may bee found,
                  Eſay 55.6. 
                  and call vpon him while hee is neare.
                  1. Cor. 6.2. 
                  Ecce nunc tempus acceptum: Behold novv the accepted time, behold novv is the day of ſaluation.
                  
               
               This life is the time wherein wee muſt worke out our ſalúation with feare and trembling, if after this life we will bée fréede from the deepe damnation of Tophet.
               
               The irrationall creatures themſelues are very carefull to take their times and ſeaſons, as ſaith the Prophet Ieremy, 8.7. The Storke, the Turtle,

Crane and the Svvallovv obſerue their times and ſeaſons: there is a time when the Swallow is with vs in England, and there is a time when hee takes his leaue of vs.
               That ſilly creature in the ſixt of the Prouerbs, Gathereth in Summer to maintaine the poore life of it in Winter: So ſhould wee take our time; for after this life, there is neyther place for pardon, nor time for repentance.
               Yet for all this, golden Time is not reſpected, but men doe poſte off their repentance from day to day, till at the laſt, they ſinke into the depth of hell.
               Yea the time of Grace is tedious to many, they muſt haue ſome or other carnall delight to driue it away: Tis death to many to attend willingly vppon the meanes of their ſaluation, an houre or two; but there will come a time, when they ſhall wiſh, that all their life had been ſpent at the hearing of Sermons and Prayer, as tedious as it ſéemeth to them now.
               O the damned in Hell would giue (if it were in their power) a million of

worlds to haue but one houre granted them to liue on the earth againe,Tempus gratiae negligere, eſt abſolute animam perdere. that ſo they may come within compaſſe of offered grace to ſaluation. But if yee will not heare the Lord when hee calleth to you, there will come a day when ye ſhall cry, Lord, Lord, and his eares ſhall be ſhut to your prayers, and his iuſtice ſhall caſt you into the deep dungeon of 
Tophet,
                  Math. 5.26. there to remayne, till yee haue payed the vttermoſt farthing.
               
            
            
               
                  The 4. part And large Oecolam. in Eſay. Obſeruat.
                  The fourth part of the Deſcription of Tophet, mentioned in this word, Large.
               
               As the Lord hath made Hell Deepe, ſo hath he made it Large, in regard of the great number that ſhall be tormented in her, as ſayeth Occolampadius.
               
               
                  Eſay 5.14.This word is vſed in the fift chapter of this propheſie, Hell hath inlarged her ſelfe, and hath opened her mouth without meaſure: It hath ſet open her mouth, as it were, with a gag, and all to receyue the great multitudes that ſhall deſcend into her.
               It is called Lacus magnus in the Reuelation,

14.19. A great Lake.
               
               That this doctrine is too true, witnes that of the Goſpell of Matt. 20.16. Multi vocati: Many are called, but few conuerted: Many called, but few choſen.
               
               
                  The moſt high made this world for many,
                  4. Eſd. 8.1 
                  but the world to come for verie few.
               
               
                  Obiect,But ſome man may obiect againſt theſe Scriptures other Scriptures to proue the great number of them that ſhall be ſaued, and ſo by conſequence, the ſmall number that ſhall be tormented in Tophet.
               
               Saint Mathew ſayth,Math. 8.1
                        •
                     
                   
                  That many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and ſhall ſit downe with Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob in the Kingdom of God: many an innumerable company ſhall be ſaued.
               Saint Iohn in Reuelat. 7.9. dooth point out that great number that ſhall bée ſaued, with that nota ſtellifera, that ſtarry note, Beholde, I ſaw a great multitude of all Nations and Kinreds, and People, and Tongues, that ſtoode

before the Throne, &amp; before the Lambe clothed in long white robes, &amp; palmes in their hands:
                   long white robes in token of purity, and palms in their hands in token of victory.
               It may ſeeme by theſe Scriptures, that many ſhall bee ſaued, and not ſuch a multitude damned.
               
                  AnſwereI anſwere, That though the number of the Elect be great, by it ſelfe conſidered (to the prayſe of Gods mercy be it ſpoken) yet if it be compared to the number of thoſe that ſhal glorifie Gods iuſtice in hell, Alas then a remnant of Iſrael ſhall be ſaued: they are but a handful, and therfore hell muſt be made excéeding Large.
               
               This great deſtruction of the damned in hell, is liuelily ſhadowed out vnto vs in the iudgements of God on earth, mingled with mercy; as in the deſtruction of the olde world by water, how few eſcaped there aliue?Gen. 7. only Noah with his Family: in the deſtruction of Sodome by fire,Gen. 19.16 how few eſcaped there aliue? only Lot vvith his daughters: in the deſtruction of Iericho by

the ſword, how few eſcaped there aliue? only Rahab with her family,
                  Ioſua. 6.22 that intertained the Iſraeliticall Spies. To come to later times, in the deſtruction of Ieruſalem by Titus Veſpaſian, how few eſcaped there aliue? Many hundred thouſands of them were ſtarued to death, many hundred thouſands of them taken captiues to the Romane Empire, ſome put to one death, ſome to another, and few eſcaped aliue, and thoſe of the meaner ſort, agricolae vinitores, huſbandmen and labourers in vineyards.
               If (beloued) in the iudgements of God in this world ſo few haue eſcaped aliue, how few (thinke you) ſhall ſcape at the dreadfull day of Iudgement, when of euery idle word that men ſhal ſpeake, a great account muſt bee made for the ſame? yea,Mat. 12.36 when Inquiſition ſhall bee made for the very thoughts of the vngodly:
                  Wiſd. 1.9. 
                  If the iuſt ſhall ſcarce be ſaued, where ſhall the ſinner appeare? Againe, that great is the number of thoſe that ſhall to Tophet, and therefore Tophet made large to giue them

fiery intertainement, it appeareth in the very liues of men vpon earth: for where there is one that commeth to the profeſſion of the truth, truly with the ſincere heart of Nathanael:Iohn 1. there are ten, yea twenty, yea more, that walke in the way of ſinne, in the roade to Tophet, without any checke of conſcience, remorſe for their ſinnes, or reclamation from their ſinnefull courſes in the world: ſome in the way of Atheiſme, ſome in Paganiſme, ſome in Epicuriſme, ſome in Brovvniſme, ſome in Anabaptiſme, ſom in Mahometiſme, ſome in Papiſme, yea ſome in Deuiliſme: a matter with many teares to be lamented.
               But wouldeſt thou not be with this large company,
                     Ʋſe. in this large place of torment: O then follovv not a multitude to doe euill! Reuelation, 18.4. Come out from amongſt them, for if thou beeſt partaker with them in their ſinnes, thou muſt bee partaker with them in their puniſhments: Faſhion not thy ſelfe after the wicked faſhion of this world: rather walke alone by thy

ſelfe to heauen, than goe with the multitude to Hell: Walke in the narrow way of grace to ſaluation, ſhunne the broade and large way, for that will bring thee to Tophet, which (as thou heareſt) is made excéeding deepe and large.
            
            
               The fift part of the deſcription of Hell, in theſe wordes,The fift part. The burning thereof is fire. 
                  The burning thereof is fire: expreſſing the bitterneſſe of the torments of Tophet. There is great controuerſie among the learned about this fire.An in inferno ignis. Whether it be true ſubſtantiall fire, or fire allegoricall? if it be true fire, whether it be materiall, corporall, or ſpirituall.
               If it be Corporall, whether it burneth the body onely, or ſoule and body alſo?
               Whether there be true fire in Hel?
                     Quaeſtio. 1 or whether theſe words (the burning thereof is fire) be taken allegorically?
               
                  Caluin would haue it taken allegorically,Caluin in Eſai. 
                  and thinks there is no true fire in hell.
               
               His reaſon is this, If Wood and the Worme be taken metaphorically, vvhy

not then the fire alſo?
               
               But this is no argument to prooue this fire allegoricall: For in the holy Scriptures things ſpoken together,Reſolutio 1. quaeſtionis. are not alway taken in the ſame maner and nature: For example ſake: Chriſt is called a Dore, a Vine, a Rocke, a Stone, figuratiuely: and doth it therefore follow, that he was not God and man ſubſtancially?
               Againe, in Saint Lukes Goſpel our Sauiour ſayth,Luke 22. 
                  I appoint you a Kingdome, as my Father hath appointed to mee, that yee may eate and drinke at my Table in my Kingdome: Eat
                     •
                  ng is allegoricall, but will you ſay, that the kingdome is allegoricall alſo?
               I confeſſe that wood in hell is taken allegorically, but that fire is taken ſo, I vtterly deny.
               
                  Bulling. in Eſai.
                  Bullinger holdeth true and ſubſtanciall fire in hell: and ſo do the moſt and beſt of the learned.
               Chriſt puniſhed with Fire in this world,Gen 10. Numb. 1
                        •
                     . 
                  Sodome: and the Murmurers in the Booke of Numbers, chap. 11. and called the name of that place Thabherah:
                  
becauſe the fire of the Lord burnt amongſt them.
               And Chriſt ſhall come to Iudgement with Fire:Eſay 66, which ſhall haue two properties.
               
                  To burne:
                  Theodoret. in Pſal. 96. this property ſhal puniſh the wicked: to ſhine: this property ſhal comfort the Saintes, as ſayeth Theodoret.
               
               And what ſhall hinder the being of fire in hell, when the extremity of tortures ſhall be put vpon the damned? hee that will not belieue this, ſhall one day feele it to his ſorrow.
               If then it be graunted, that there is Subſtantiall fire in hell, the next queſtion will bee, Whether it be Materiall,
                  Quaeſt. 2.
                   
                  Corporall, or Spirituall?
               Surely Materiall fire, that is,Reſolutio 2. quaeſtionis. fire nouriſhed and maintayned with wood, it ſhall not be: for as the flaſhings of Aetna and Veſuuius, and other places of the earth, doe burne without fuell; ſo ſhall the fire of hell doe: hee that is able to make the damned liue without food, is able to maintaine this fire without wood.
               
                  Whether then it bee Corporall or Spirituall, (for if it bée Subſtantiall, it muſt be one of theſe) Gregory calles it Ignem incorporeum,
                  Gregor. 
                  a Spirituall fire, but that is not likely, for it paſſeth the nature of fire to be Spirituall, and to goe about to make it Spirituall, is to make it no fire at all.
               But it is moſt probable that it is, &amp; ſhall be, a Corporall fire, vvith an extraordinary afflicting povver, giuen vnto it, tormenting both ſoule and body.
               
               
                  Auguſt.Saint Auguſtine affirmeth the fire of hell to be Corporall.
               
               
                  Quaeſt. 3.
                  If it be Corporall, whether it tormenteth the body onely, or both ſoule and body: and how a Corporall fire ſhould worke vpon a ſpirituall ſubſtance,
               Saint Bernard ſayth, that Ignis exteriùs carnem comburit,
                  Bernard. de interiere domo. c. 38. Idem. part. ſer. 16.
                   
                  vermis interiùs conſcientiam corrodet: that is, Fire ſhall outvvardly burne thy fleſh, &amp; a vvorm ſhall inwardly gnavv thy conſcience.
               
               Again, he ſayth, Duo mala ſunt vermis &amp; ignis, altero roditur conſcientia, altero

concremantur corpora: that is, the worme and fire are two inſufferable torments: by the one the ſoule is vexed, by the other, the body ſcorched.
                  
               
               Againe he ſayth:Idem meditat. 4, cap. 
                  In carne cruciabuntur per ignem, in spirituper conſcientiae vermem: that is, in the fleſh they ſhal be tormented by fire, and in the Spirite by the worme of conſcience.
               
               
                  Iſodore ſayth,Iſodor. de ſummo bono. l. 1. c. 31.
                   that there is duplex poena damnatorum, quorum mentem vrit tristitia, &amp; corpus flamma: that is, Their minds burne vvith ſorrovv, and their bodies with the flame.
               
               
                  Beda ſayth,Bed. lib. 3 in cap. 9. Mar. 
                  Ignis erit poena extrinſecus ſaeuiens, vermis dolor, interiùs accuſans: that is, The fire ſhall be a torment outwardly raging, and the vvorme a griefe invvardly accuſing.
               
               Though theſe maintaine fire in hel, yet they hold (as you ſee) that it is not of power to touch the ſoule, but only to torture the body: but I am perſwaded according to the iudgement of many learned Fathers, That this fire tormē
                     teth both body and ſoule.
               
               
                  Zanchy de Operibus Dei, ſayth,Zanch. de Operibus 
                  That

the deuils,
                  Dei, part. 1. lib. 4. cap. 19.
                   
                  mens bodies and ſoules, are tormented with fire euerlaſting. For as they were (as Simeon and Leui) brethren in the ſame euill, ſo both of them ſhall be tormented in the ſame fire.
               
                  Iuſtin. Mart. Apologia 1. pro Chriſtianis. Mat. 25.41
                  
                  Iuſtine Martyr ſaith, That the Deuil ſhall ſuffer puniſhment and vengeance, encloſed in euerlaſting fire: and they are no bodies, but ſpirits.
               The truth of this is ratified by Chriſt himſelfe: Goe from me yee curſed, into euerlaſting fire, prepared for the Deuill and his Angels.
               
               And the ſpeech of Diues prooueth this moſt true:Chryſoſt. for it is no Parable, but Hiſtory (as Chryſoſtome ſaith) Parabolae ſunt vbi exemplum ponitur, tacentur nomina: that is, Thoſe are Parables, where an example is propounded, and no names mentioned: he crieth out, and ſhall for euerlaſting,Luk. 16.24 
                  I am tormented in this flame.
               
               And if any man will not beleeue this, I make bold to vſe againſt him, the words of Ruffinus,
                  Ruffinus. who ſaith, Si quis negat diabolum aeternis ignibus mancipandum, partem cum ipſo aeterni ignis accipiet,

vt ſentiat quod negauit: that is, If any man doth deny that the Deuill is tormented with euerlaſting fire, hee ſhall one day bee partaker with him of that fire, that hee may feele that which hee would not be brought to beleeue.
               
               But how this Corporall fire ſhall torment the Deuils and the Spirits of the damned, I know not, and I truſt neuer to know, and it is but curioſity to be too too inquiſitiue in theſe points: for as a Father ſaith,Auguſt, 
                  Melius eſt dubitare de occultis, quam litigare de incertis: viz. It is better to doubt of vnknowne things, then to ſtriue for vncertaine.
                  
               
               
                  Compeſcat igitur ſe humana timeritas, &amp; id quod non eſt, non quaerat, ne illius quod eſt non inueniat: that is, Let no man raſhly meddle about theſe things that are not reuealed, leſt hee findeth not the good of thoſe things that are reuealed.
               
               It being probable that there is in hell a Subſtanciall and Corporeall fire, that vexeth both the ſoules and bodies of the damned, let vs now ſée the difference of this fire frō our elemētall fire.
               
                  
                  Ignis infernimultum differt ab elementari.This fire of hell differeth from our elementall fire in fiue reſpects.
               Firſt, In regarde of heate: Our fire in regard of hel fire, is but as fire painted on a wall, in regard of our fire.
               Oh it is a fierce and an intollerable fire.
               
                  Exemplū.We reade of one, who (vpon the violence of any ſtrong temptation) would lay his hands on burning coales, and being not able to endure the ſame, would ſay to himſelfe: O! how ſhall I be able to indure the paines of Hell fire?
               
               
                  Dan. 3.21.The fire into which Sydrach, Miſach and Abednego were caſt, was excéeding fearefull: but alas, nothing to hell fire.
               
                  Eſa 33.14.
                  Eſay ſpeaking of this terrible fire, ſayth: Who is able to dwell in this deuouring fire? or, who ſhall bee able to dwell in theſe euerlaſting burnings?
               
               Secondly, In regard of light: Our fire giueth a comfortable light, but the fire of hell giueth no light.
               
                  Greg. Moral. l. 9. c. 46
                  Cremationem habet, lumen vero non habet, (ſayth Gregory:) It burneth, but

giueth no light at all.
               
               
                  It is a darkiſh fire (ſayth Baſil) that hath loſt his brightneſſe,
                  Baſil. in Pſal. 33. 
                  but kept his burning.
               
               
                  Phauorinus in verbo
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   ſayth:Phauor. in verb. hades 
                  hades is a place voyde of light, and full of eternall darkeneſſe.
               
               
                  Sophocles cals it 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  :Sophoc. in Oedipo. 
                  black darkneſſe.
               
               
                  Euripides cals it 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  :Euripid. in Ariſtide. Theognidis gnomae. Euſtath. in 1. Iliados Exo. 10.21 
                  the houſe without Sunne-light.
               
               
                  Theognis calles it 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : the blacke gates.
               
               
                  Euſtathius ſayth, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : Hell is a darke place vnder the earth.
               
               The darkeneſſe of Egypt was wonderfull and fearefull: Wonderfull, becauſe it was ſo thicke as it might bee felt: Fearefull, and therefore made the ninth plague of Pharao: yet that darkneſſe was nothing to the darkeneſſe of hell,Iude 13. which is called the Blacke darkneſſe.
               
               The Poets, in regard of the darkneſſe thereof, do compare hell to a certaine territory in Italy, betwixt Ba
                        •
                     ae and Cumae, where the Cimerii inhabite:

ſo inuironed with hills, that the Sunne neuer commeth to it: wherevpon this Prouerbe commeth:Cimerae tenebrae. 
                  Cimeris tenebris atrior, Darker then the darkeneſſe of Cimeria.
                   Whoſoeuer hee bee, that loueth darkneſſe more then light, ſhall haue his heart full of darkneſſe in Tophet.
               
               Thirdly, Our elementall fire burneth the body onely, but the fire of hell burneth both ſoule and body, as yee haue heard at large.
               Fourthly, Our elementall fire conſumeth that which is caſt into it, but the fire of hell doth alway burne, and neuer conſume.
               Fiftly, Our elementall fire may bee quenched,
                  Math. 3. but hell fire can neuer bee quen
                     •
                  hed: The chaffe will hee burne with vnquenchable fire: their worme ſhall neuer die,
                  Eſay 66. 
                  their fire ſhall neuer goe out.
               
               As there is nothing that maintaineth it, ſo there is nothing that can extinguiſh it.
               
                  Obſerua
                     
                        ••
                     o.From all this wee may obſerue the extremity &amp; bitterneſſe of the torments

of Tophet:
                  Tho. Aquin. Yea minima poena inferni maior est maxima poena huius mundi: that is, The leaſt torture in hell is greater than the greateſt torture that euer was deuiſed vpon the earth. That Hell-hound that murthered the King of France, had as heauy a puniſhment as this world could affoord: for his arme that did that curſed act, was taken from his ſhoulder, his nayles pulled from his hands and feet, his fleſh piece by piece pulled from him with hot burning pincers, and in the end rent in pieces with foure horſes: all this is nothing to the leaſt torment of Tophet.
               
               
                  Chryſoſtome ad populum Antiochenum,
                   ſaith: That fire and ſword,
                  Chryſoſt. ad pop. Antioch. hom. 49.
                   
                  and wilde beaſts, or any thing more grieuous than theſe, are ſcant a ſhadow to the torments of hell.
               
               And this bitter torment ſtandeth in theſe two: In poena damni: that is: In the puniſhment of loſſe: and in poena ſenſus:
                   that is, In the puniſhment of feeling:
                  Idem. the former wherof is the greateſt (as ſaith Saint Chryſoſtome) this poena damni, this puniſhment of loſſe is

more bitter then the paines of hell, yea, worſe then a thouſand hels.
                  
               
               
                  Poena damni.This Poena damni, though it bee a priuatiue puniſhment, yet it hath a poſitiue effect: For, to bee depriued of Ioy, cannot but bring intollerable ſorrow:Simile. euen as the abſence of the Sunne cauſeth darkenes, ſo the want of Gods preſence bringeth inexpreſſible griefe.
               
                  1. Sam. 4.18.When the Arke of God was taken by the Philiſtimes, olde Eli with griefe fell backeward and died.
               
               
                  Plutarc. in vita Demost.
                  Demoſthenes tooke his baniſhment ſo heauily, that many times hee would weep bitterly when he looked towards Athens, though hee found much kindeneſſe at the hands of his enemies.
               
                  Tully, when he was baniſhed from Italy, though he were in Greece, yet he wept bitterly when he looked towards Italy.
               
               
                  1. Sam. 14.22.
                  Abſolon tooke his baniſhment from his fathers preſence very grieuouſly.
               
               If theſe exiles breede ſuch ſorrow, how fearefull will it be to be baniſhed from the preſence of the Lord, Who is the Father of mercies,
                  2. Cor. 1.3. 
                  and God of all

conſolation: in whoſe preſence is ioy, in whoſe pleaſure is life: to be baniſhed from the preſence &amp; louing countenance of the Lambe: from the fellowſhip of Saints and Angells: from all ioyes and felicity,Math. 25. with that bitter ſentence, Goe from me yee curſed into euerlaſting fire, prepared for the Deuill and his angells. Goe from mee: theſe are words of ſeparation: yee curſed: theſe are wordes of obiurgation: into euerlaſting fire; theſe are words of deſolation: prepared for the Deuill and his Angels: theſe are words of dolefull exemplification.
               This is the greateſt part of the ſecond death: for as the firſt death ſeparateth the ſoule from the body, ſo the ſecond death ſeparates ſoule and body from the preſence of the Lord for euermore.
               
                  Oh vvhat vveeping and wayling wil there be, when yee ſhall ſee Abraham,
                  Luke 13. 
                  Iſaac, and Iaacob intertayned into the Kingdome of God, and yee your ſelues ſhut out.
               
               Ye therefore ſpake truly that ſaid,

                  The teares of hell are not ſufficient to bewayle the loſſes of heauen.
               
               
                  Infoeliciſſimum genus infortunij, meminiſſe fuiſſe foelicem: that is, it is the vnhappieſt thing of all, to thinke that euer we were happy.
               
               
                  Poeta.
                  Dura ſatis miſeris memoratio priſca bonorum:
               
               
                  It is miſery enough, and though there were no more miſery, to remember the ioyes we haue loſt.
               
               
                  Terent.As the olde man in the Poet ſayd, I haue a ſonne, nay, alas, I had a ſonne; ſo the damned may ſay; Wee haue a heauē, nay, alas, we had a heauen.
               
               
                  Lyſimach.
                  Lyſimachus King of Macedonia warring againſt the Scythians, béeing inforced by extreme thirſt, to yéeld himſelfe into the hands of his enemies, after he had drunke colde water, brake out into theſe lamētable words: Good God, for how ſhort a pleaſure, how great a Kingdome haue I loſt? So the damned ſoule may ſay, Good God, for how ſhort a time of pleaſure, how great a Kingdome haue I loſt?
               
               And ſurely this is iuſt with GOD, that thoſe that ſeparate themſelues

from him héere, ſhould bee baniſhed from him hereafter: That thoſe that hate the Saints héere, ſhould be debarred their company hereafter: that thoſe that crucifie the Lambe here, ſhould be curſed of the Lambe euerlaſtingly hereafter.
               The ſecond thing that maketh Hell torments ſo bitter and intollerable, is poena ſenſus: the puniſhment of feeling.
                  
                  Poena ſenſus. Euery member of body, and euery faculty of ſoule, together tormented for euer.
               The eye afflicted with darkeneſſe, the eare with horrible and hideous outcries, the noſe with poiſonous and ſtinking ſauours, the tongue with gallie bitterneſſe, the whole body with intolerable fire: a fire that ſhall burne ſo violently, that the danmed ſhall prize a droppe of water aboue tenne thouſand worlds.
               The faculties of the ſoule alſo ſhall be moſt pitteouſly tormented: the memory with pleaſures paſt: the apprehenſion with paines preſent: the vnderſtanding with ioyes loſt: and in this

faculty ſhall lie the worm of conſcience gnawing,Miſeria reproborummaxima. which the Scriptures ſo often threaten to ſinners: this worme is a continual repentance and ſorrowful of rage, and deſperation, by reaſon of their ſins: and this worme or remorſe ſhall chiefly conſiſt in bringing to their minds the meanes and cauſes of their preſent calamities: how eaſily they might haue bin fréed from hell, &amp; how often they haue beene inuited to heauen, and they would none, but now when they would they cannot. And this worme biteth and gnaweth on the bowels of theſe miſerable mē for euermore.
               The will alſo ſhall be moſt grieuouſly tormented with a furious malice againſt God, and againſt the Elect. And in this their curſed eſtate, they ſhall recurſe, curſe God againe, becauſe hee made them, and making them, adiudged them to death, and dying, they can neuer find death: they ſhall curſe his puniſhments, becauſe hee puniſheth them ſo vehemently: they ſhall curſe his benignities, becauſe they are ſawced

with contrary ſeuerities: they ſhall curſe CHRISTS bloud ſhed vpon the Croſſe, becauſe it hath beene auayleable to ſaue thouſands, &amp; nothing auailable to ſaue them: they ſhall curſe the Angels in heauen, and the Saints in bliſſe, becauſe they ſhall ſée them in ioy, and themſelues in torment: curſings ſhall be their hymnes, and howlings their tunes: blaſphemy ſhall be their ditties, and lachrymae their notes: lamentations ſhall bee their ſongs, and ſcriching their ſtraines: theſe ſhall bée their euening and morning, yea mourning ſongs: Moab ſhall cry againſt Moab: father againſt child, and child againſt father that euer he begat him: vae, vae, vae, Reuel. 8. 
                     Ʋae prae amaritudine, vae prae multitudine, vae prae aeternitate poenarum: that is, Woe in regarde of the Bitterneſſe, woe in regard of the Multitude, and woe in regard of the Euerlaſtingnes of the torments of Tophet.
               
               Now therefore I may truely ſay of all the damned crue, as our Sauiour ſayde of Iudas,
                  Mat. 26.24 
                  It had beene good for him if he had neuer been borne. So

it had been good for the damned, if they had neuer beene borne: or if they muſt needes haue a being, they had bin toads or ſerpents, that ſo they might neuer haue known theſe vnſpeakeable ſorrowes of Tophet.
               
               I cannot but muſe at a company of wicked hell-hounds, that will vſe theſe execrable words: Would I ware damned if euer I knew of this or that: God damne me body and ſoule, if I do it not: Alas, alas, full little doe theſe wretches know what it is to be damned, if they did vnderſtand aright, they would bee hanged vp before they would vſe theſe fearefull ſpeeches: vnleſſe they meant with the moth-flie, neuer to be at quiet, till they haue clipt their winges in thoſe flames.
               I therefore conclude this part with the admonition of Proſper,
                  Proſper de vita contemplatiua, l. 3. c. 12.
                   
                  who wiſheth all men to thinke, how great an euill it is to be excluded the preſence of God, to be baniſhed from heauen, and caſt into euerlaſting fire with the deuil and his Angelles, to ſee no light, but feele exceſſiue heate, to bee drowned

in the deepe Lake of Gehenna, and to be eternally torne with moſt greedie wormes: To thinke on theſe thinges (ſayth he) is a ſure way to renounce al vice whatſoeuer: and he that wil not be brought to lay to heart theſe, I leaue him to féele the ſmart of them for euerlaſting.
            
            
               The ſixt part of the Deſcription of Tophet, is ſet downe in theſe wordes,The 6. part And much wood. Obſeruat.
                   
                  Much wood.
               
               Wherein is noted the eternity of the torments of Tophet.
               
               The Perpetuity of theſe torments is euery where mentioned in the booke of God.
               The Prophet Daniel ſpeaking of the condemnation of the wicked,Dan. 12.2. addeth perpetuity to their ſhame: ſaying, Som ſhall awake to perpetuall ſhame and contempt.
               
               Saint Marke ſpeaking of the vexing worme,Mar. 9.24. addeth Perpetuity to the gnawing of it: their worme neuer dyeth.
               
               Saint Paul addeth to the perdition of the wicked Perpetuity alſo: Their

                  perdition is euerlaſting, 2. Theſſ. 1.9.
               
               
                  Iude.Saint Iude addeth the like: That they ſuffer eternall fire.
               
               
                  Reu. 20.10And Saint Iohn doth adde vnto the lake perpetuity: The Deuill was caſt into the lake, where he ſhall be tormented day and night for euermore.
               
               Thus wee ſee that the torments of hell are infinite,Reu. 9.6. 
                  ratione finis: without end:
                   and though they ſéeke death, yet find it they ſhall neuer.
               
                  Simile.Thus ſhall they be like a man that is to be preſſed to death, who calleth for more weight, more weight to diſpatch him of his paine: but alas, he muſt not haue it: So in hell they ſhall cry for death, and go without it.
               As the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh of Gods mercy,Pſal. 136. 
                  That his mercy endureth for euer; ſo ye damned may ſay of his iuſtice, that his iuſtice endureth for euer.
               
               There were ſome comfort to the damned ſoules, if theſe their torments might haue end, but that ſhal neuer be: that is that that breaketh the hearts of the damned: no torment in hell comparable to this of perpetuity: what, neuer

haue end, neuer? O this is ſuch a torment, that the damned themſelues are not able to expreſſe.
               It is a common ſaying;Adagium. 
                  But for hope the heart would burſt; but they are ſhut out of all hope: and therefore who can expreſſe their torments?
               O (ſayth a heathen man) God ſhall once giue an end to theſe euils: but the damned ſhall neuer be able to ſay this. For, (as Gregory ſayth) Mors miſeris fit ſine morte: finis ſine fine:
                  Gregor. 
                  defectus ſine defectu: quoniam mors ſemper viuit, &amp; finis ſemper incipit, &amp; defectus deficere neſcit: that is, The death of the damned is ſuch as ſhall neuer die; their end ſhal neuer end; and their deſtruction, a perpetuall confuſion.
               
               No maruell therefore if Saint Bernard ſayth,Bern. de conſid. ad Eugen. li. 5.
                   
                  Horres in manus incidere mortis viuentis, &amp; vitae morientis: that is, It is a terrible thing to fall into the hands of liuing death, and dying life.
               
               If there might be an end of theſe paines, it were ſomething, though it were after ſo many millions of yeares, as there are drops of water in the ſea,

ſtarres in the firmament, motes of duſt vpon the earth, and as there haue béen moments of time ſince time beganne: but this cannot be graunted: but when the Lord doth giue ouer his being, then and neuer before then ſhall the damned be diſcharged, though the blockiſh Catabaptiſt perſwadeth the contrary.
               The reaſon of the perpetuity of theſe torments, is thréefold.
               The firſt, Drawne from the Maieſty of God offended: an infinite Maieſty offended, an infinite torment impoſed.
               The ſecond, Drawne from the ſtate and condition of the damned: For as long as they remayne ſinnefull, ſo long ſhall they remaine tormented for ſinne: but in hell they euer remayne ſinneful, therefore in hell they ſhall euer be tormented.
               Sinne is like oyle, and the wrath of God like fire: as long as the oile laſteth ſo long the fire burneth: and ſo long as they are ſinnefull, ſo long for ſinne tormented; therefore for euer damned.
               For moſt ſure it is, that in hell there is neyther grace nor deuotion: the wicked

ſhall be caſt in exteriores tenebras extra limitem diuinae miſericordiae: They ſhal be caſt into outward darkeneſſe, out of the limits both of grace and mercy.
                   Though their weeping in hell may ſéeme penitentiary, yet they doe but lugere poenas non peccata: they doe but mourne their ſorrowes, not lament their ſinnes.
                  
               
               And though Diues his prayer for his brethren may ſeem to proceed from a charitable ſoule, yet it was not for their good, but for his owne: for hee knew that if they ſhould come to hell, (his lewd and vicious example being part occaſion therof) his tormēts ſhould be doubled, nay centupled vpon him.
               In hell therfore, there being neither grace nor deuotion, but ſtill affected iniquity, their torments muſt bee euerlaſting.
               The third reaſon, Drawne from that ſtinging attribute of Gods iuſtice: becauſe life was offered them here, and they would none, it is iuſt with God, that when in Hell they begge it, they ſhould goe without it: yea, that they

ſhould ſéeke death, and neuer find it.
               Once they were offered ſaluation, being gone in Adam, but that offer being neglected, let them neuer looke for another.
               O if this long torment were alwaies thought vpon, it would make vs vſe this ſhort time of our life better: they are Spirituall Lunatikes, and worſe than mad Bedlomites, that will purchaſe an eternall torment for ſo ſhort a pleaſure.
               I beſéech you therfore (beloued brethren) for your ſoules ſake, which ſhould bee more worth vnto you than a thouſand worldes, let not theſe infinite torments be paſſed ouer with a ſhort or ſhallow conſideration, but write the remembrance of them in the inward parts of your ſoules with the Diamond of déepeſt meditation, that ſo this Tophet may neuer be your deſtruction.
            
            
               
                  The ſe
                     
                        •
                     enth and 
                        ••
                     ſt part. 
                        •
                     he breath 
                        •
                     f the lord 
                        〈…〉
                      c.The ſeuenth and laſt part of the Deſcription of Tophet, ſet downe in theſe words: The breath of the Lord like a riuer of brimſtone doth kindle it.
                  
In which words there is not onely a Proſopopeia in the breath, but a Topographia in the brimſtone vſed: both which figures doe notably expreſſe the furious indignation of the Author, and the fierce ſeuerity of the act: the Author or Inflictour of all theſe fearefull puniſhments is the Lord God offended, at whoſe anger the Heauens do melt, the Earth quakes, &amp; the whole Creation trembles, into whoſe hands to fall, is moſt fearefull,Heb. 12.29 
                  For the Lord our God is a conſuming fire.
               
               The Lord is the decréer, appointer and commaunder of all theſe fearefull torments: and the Lord doth execute them vpon the damned, both immediate, immediately from himſelfe: &amp; mediate, mediately by his inſtruments, as by the deuils, fire, darkenes, ſtinch, and other creatures.
               Feare therfore (in the feare of God) this fearefull and terrible name Iehouah: that at the day of néed, ye may find him a mild and gentle Lambe,Reuel. 5. and not A roaring Lion of Iudah.
               
               The ſeuerity of puniſhment is ſet

downe by a double allegory, Breath, &amp; Brimſtone.
               
               To expreſſe the rage and tyranny of Saul againſt the Lambes of IESVS, this word is vſed in the Actes: And Saul yet breathing out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the Diſciples of the Lord,
                  Act. 9.1. 
                  &amp;c.
               
               So here to expreſſe the furious indignation of the Lord againſt ſinners, the Breath of the Lord is vſed.
               
                  Like a riuer of Brimſtone.
               
               The perplexing property of brimſtone is to burne, Darkely, to grieue the ſight: Sharply, to afflict the more: Loathſomly, to perplex the ſmell.
               We reade in the Scriptures, that the Lord being much prouoked, puniſhed not onely with fire, but with burning brimſtone, which is tenne to one more terrible.
               
                  Gē. 19.24.As vpon Sodome, hee rained fire &amp; brimſtone from heauen.
               
               
                  Ezec. 38.22. Pſal. 11.6.
                  I will raine vpon him a ſore raine, haile-ſtones, fire and brimſtone.
               
               
                  Vpon the wicked God ſhall raine ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and ſtormy

tempeſt, this ſhall bee their portion to drinke.
               
               
                  The beaſt, and the falſe Prophet,
                  Apo. 1
                        •
                     .20. 
                  both aliue, were caſt into the Lake of fire and brimſtone.
               
               Oh who can expreſſe now the lamentation of Tophet, for the breath of the Lord like a riuer of brimſtone doth kindle it!
               
               As this ſhould bee of power to kéepe you from the leaſt iniquity: ſo it ſhould poſſeſſe you with the knowledge of the right nature of ſinne: that it is the moſt odious and loathſome thing in the world: A ſtinking carkaſe ſtinketh not ſo in the noſtrils of man,
                  Auguſt. 
                  as a polluted ſinner ſtinketh in the noſtrils of almighty God.
               
               As Plato ſayth of vertue: That if it could be ſeene with a bodily eye,
                  Plato. 
                  it is ſo ſplendid and glorious a thing, as all the world would be rauiſhed with the loue of her: So may I ſay the contrary of vice: That if ſinne could bee ſeene in his owne colours, and in his right Nature, all the world would loath, and vtterly deteſt it.
               
               
                  But miſerable man (the more is the pitty) conceiueth not aright of ſinne, one would thinke that Adam had committed but a ſmall ſinne in eating the forbidden fruit, at the intreaty of Eue, yet he and all his poſterity guilty of eternall death for the ſame: One would thinke that that poore man had committed but a ſmall fault, In gathering a few chippes on the Sabbaoth day: (wée haue fouler matters committed on our Sabbaoths, and goe vnpuniſhed) yet hee was ſtoned to death for his labour: one would thinke that Ananias detayning part of the money,Act. 5. and maintayning the contrary with a lie, had committed but a ſmall fault, yet hee was ſtrooke dead for the ſame at the féete of Peter: one would thinke that an idle word were but a ſmall ſinne, yet of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, a great account muſt bee made for the ſame.
               And as men conceiue of ſinne, ſo they imagine of puniſhment, they thinke that the Lord will not deale ſo ſeuerely with them; and yet my Text

ſayth, That the breath of the LORD like a riuer of brimſtone dooth kindle it: The terror of whoſe wrath is indurable.
               Hearken here all you that make but a ſport of ſinne, looke vpon your puniſhments preſcribed:Zach. 5 8. the leaſt ſinne that euer you haue committed (being weighty as lead) is able to ſinke your ſoules downe to damnation.
               Ceaſe therefore from euill, and doe that which is good: Caſt away the workes of darkeneſſe, and put on the armour of light: hate the little ſinne as well as the great, an idle thought as well as blaſphemy: make much of offered grace to ſaluation: Chriſt now knocketh at the dore of your ſoules, and would gladly come in and dwell with you:Pro. 8. 
                  For it is his delight to dwell with the ſonnes of men: ſhut him not out as did the Bethleemites: Bid him not be gone, as did the Gadarens, but Bee yee open yee euerlaſting doores, that the King of glory may come in; yt you hauing giuen him entertainement héere, hee may do the like by you hereafter,

placing you with the ſheepe on his right hand, and ſinging this bleſſed harueſt-ſong vnto you, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherite the kingdom prepared for you from the beginning of the world. To the which moſt bleſſed place of glory, the LORD bring euery ſoule of vs at the day of our death and diſſolution; and that for IESVS CHRIST his ſake, to whom with GOD the Father, and GOD the bleſſed Spirit, three glorious perſons, but one immortal GOD, be aſcribed all honour and glory, both in Heauen and Earth, this day and euer, Amen.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            AN EARNEST AND ZEAlous Prayer, to be ſaued from the damnation of TOPHET.
            
               O Moſt glorious euerliuing, and euerlouing Lord God, the fountaine and well-ſpring of all our happineſſe, we thy poore ſeruants (vnworthy, in regarde of our manifold tranſgreſſions of the leaſt of thy bleſſings) doe moſt humbly fall downe before the throne of thy dreadfull Maieſty, confeſſing in the bitterneſſe of our ſoules, the baſeneſſe and vilenes of our eſtates by ſinne: O Lord, aſhamed wee are to come before thee that are nothing but ſinneful corruption and abhomination, but

thou a maieſty moſt pure, in compariſon of whom the Angells themſelues are counted impure: we dare not therfore (being thus loathſome and abhominable) preſume to preſent our ſelues before thee, as in our ſelues, but in thy manifold mercies, and thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt his merites, in whom thou art delightfully pleaſed with all that faithfully call vpon thy name.
            Lord in thy Sonne behold vs, wee moſt humbly beſeech thee, accept vs in his worthineſſe, clenſe vs in his bloud, iuſtifie vs in his righteouſnes, ſanctifie vs with his ſpirit, and in his moſt precious death free vs from the damnation of hell. O till theſe comfortable tidings be ſealed vp to our ſoules, how perplexed are we! O how do our harts quake and tremble till we haue found the ſaluation of thee our God! Reiect vs not (O heauenly Father) that faine would, as be ſaued of thee, ſo vprightly ſerue thee: we pleade now and euer as for pardon ſo for grace, whereby wee may in plentifull manner, bring foorth fruits worthy of amendment.
            
               Lord keepe vs in body and ſoule to thy euerlaſting Kingdome and ſaluation, Lord preſerue vs from the terrible torments of Tophet: O what ſhall become of vs, if we for our ſinnes, when we die, be throwne into that Lake that burnes with fire and brimſtone, ſo bitterly, as forceth ſcreeching and ſcreaming continually! Lord deale not with vs according to our ſinnes, and thy iuſtice, but in the multitude of thy mercies, ſaue our ſoules aliue: O conſider the terrors of our troubled ſoules: Let not the grones of our hearts bée deſpiſed, but ſuffer them to pierce the heauens for a bleſſing: O thou that art the God of endleſſe compaſſion, caſt vs not away from thy preſence, wee are the workemanſhippe of thine handes, O Lord confound vs not: O Lord (that delighteſt not in ye death and damnation of a ſinner) bee moued to ſhew pitty vppon vs: O Chriſt our bleſſed Sauiour, make interceſſion to God the father for vs, ſpeake by thy gracious ſpirit peace to our diſquieted ſoules, bind vp our broken hearts, giue vs that we

may clearely ſee our names written in the Booke of Life: and our ſoules releaſed from the fearefull damnation of Tophet.
            
            To this end (gracious God) remoue all ſinne from our ſoules, and plant in the garden of our hearts, all thoſe ſpirituall and heauenly graces that are proper and peculiar to thine Elect, that we may be alwayes a ſweet ſmelling ſauour before thee: giue vs faith in thy promiſes, loue to thy Maieſty, zeale to thy glory, obedience to thy lawes, and guide vs dayly by thy bleſſed ſpirit into all truth and godlineſſe: Lord giue vs to be out of loue with the vanities of this life, to hate euery worke of darkenes, the little ſinne aſwell as the great, quicken vs (O Lord) by thy quickening Spirit: O giue vs hearts to bee inflamed with the loue of thy truth, O that we could hunger, and thirſt after grace, as the chaſed Hart doth the running brooke, O that we could experimentally ſay with thy ſeruant Dauid, that all our delight is in thy commandements.
            
               Thus (O Lord) we receyuing grace from thy Maieſty, to repell the fierie darts of the Deuill, and to flie euen frō euery apparition of euill, ſo doing we may reape much comfort to our ſoules in this world of trouble, and at the fearfull day of iudgement, we may be 
                  〈◊〉
                from the lamentable tortu
                  •••
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  
                     ••
                  
                  phet, where howling and yelling 
                  〈◊〉
                be for euermore, and that for Ieſus Chriſts ſake thy Sonne our Sauiour: to whom with thee and thy moſt glorious Spirit wee deſire, euen from the bottome of our hearts, to haue offered vp all thankſgiuing and prayſe both in heauen and earth, this day and euermore, Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

