
   
      
         
            The iaylers iayl-deliuery. Preached at Great Saint Maries in Cambridge, the 6. of February. 1619. By Henry Greenvvood, Master of Art, and preacher of the Word of God
            Greenwood, Henry, b. 1544 or 5.
         
         
            
               1620
            
         
         Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02189
            STC 12333
            ESTC S118959
            99854166
            99854166
            19575
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02189)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19575)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1068:17)
         
         
            
               
                  The iaylers iayl-deliuery. Preached at Great Saint Maries in Cambridge, the 6. of February. 1619. By Henry Greenvvood, Master of Art, and preacher of the Word of God
                  Greenwood, Henry, b. 1544 or 5.
               
               [6], 27, [5] p.   
               
                  Printed by George Purslow, for Henry Bell, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Sunne in Bethlem,
                  At London :
                  1620.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-10
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE IAYLERS IAYL-DELIVERY.
Preached at Great Saint Maries in CAMBRIDGE, the 6. of February. 1619.
            
               By HENRY GREENVVOOD, Maſter of Art, and Preacher of the Word of God.
            
               1. PET. 5. 5. 
God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to the humble.
            
            
               AT LONDON Printed by George Purſlow, for Henry Bell, and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the ſigne of the Sunne in Bethlem. 1620.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT WORTHY AND WORSHIPFVLL Mrs IANE BVRGOYNE, Wife to the Right Worſhipfull M. IOHN BVRGOYNE of Sutton in Bedford, and Daughter to the Right Worſhipfull Mr. WILLIAM KEMPE, of Spainſhall in Fiching-field Eſſex, Eſquire, all encreaſe of grace from the Father of light and of life be moſt heartily commended.(*⁎*)
            
               RIght vertuous and much belou'd and grac'd of God, J cannot but preſent this trembling, (yet not all trembling) Tractate to

you, partly knowing how welcome holy ſubiects are vnto your ſoule, and eſpecially conſidering your importunity for a written Copie of the ſame.
            It is not fit that holy things bee giuen to dogges, nor pearles be caſt to ſwine: but matters diuine, to perſons denoute moſt meete for preſentment, both for godly vſe, and ſtrong defence againſt diſgracers of them.
            J haue therefore made this Jayler your Priſoner, and committed him to your ſafe watch and warde: looke what paines you take, and time expend about him, the Preacher of deliuerance to all Captiues, Luke 4. 18. will one day moſt faithfully and richly reward.
            
               
I pray haue an eye alwayes vnto him, ſee him ſicke, ſee him ſound, ſee him condemned, ſee him ſaued, ſee his paſſage through Hell to Heauen: Let his example be your inſtruction, his feare your humbling, his faith your happying: you muſt bee touchd with Legall attrition, or elſe no taſte of heauenly remiſſion.
            Let not his Hell deſpaire you, nor his Heauen preſume you: but by the one, hold awe of God and feare, and by the other, hope of happineſſe for euer.
            Now the Lord adde vnto your glory by theſe and other holy helps and meanes, and his beſt bleſſings bee multiplyed vpon you, your learned, louing, and religious Huſband,

and all your tender Oliuebranches, for his deare Chriſts ſake.
            Amen.
            
               From Hempſtead in Eſſex, 
                  this 3. of April. 1620.
               
               Your Worſhips faithfull welwiller, and euer to bee commanded in the Lord,
HENRY GREENVVOOD.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE IAYLERS IAYL-DELIVERY.
            
               ACTS 26. 30, 31.
               Sirs, what muſt I doe to be ſaued? And they ſaid, Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, thou ſhalt be ſaued, and thine houſhold.
            
            
               THE onely courſe the Lord our God doth take in the effectuall calling and conuerting of ſuch, whoſe names are written in the booke of Life, is this: hee humbleth, before he exalteth; he ſhews our daninable eſtate through ſinne by the Law, before euer hee ſignifieth vnto vs, that hee is our ſaluation.
            A three-fold reaſon may be rendred thereof:
            Firſt, becauſe till men bee thus humbled, they  will neuer ſeek after Chriſt nor deſire him, without which they can neuer finde him, for God hath appointed that by ſeeking we ſhall finde him.
            
               
Secondly, that our redemption might be more  precious vnto vs: as health is more pleaſant after ſickneſſe; liberty, after bonds; plenty, after ſcarcitie; peace, after warre; and faire weather after foule.
            Thirdly, that Gods mercy in our deliuerance  might bee prized in his kinde: the redeemed, in heauen for this eſpeciall cauſe extoll the Lord and the Lambe with a perpetuall Halleluiah: for an euerlaſting redemption from an euerlaſting damnation requireth an euerlaſting glorification.
            This generall truth is confirmed by a particular example, in the words of my text: for this poore Iayler is moſt greeuouſly tormented through the horror of the Law, before euer hee can finde his ſoule recouered by the ſaluation of the Goſpell.
            
               Sirs, what muſt I doe to bee ſaued? and they ſaid, Beleeue in the Lord, &amp;c.
            
            In which words I commend to your religious conſiderations in generall theſe two.
            Firſt, an earneſt inquiſition for ſaluation, and  that on the Iaylers part: Sirs, what muſt I doe to bee ſaued?
            
            Secondly, a comfortable reſolution to this perplexed  Iayler; and that on Paul and Syla's part: Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, thou ſhalt bee ſaued and thine houſhold.
            
            In this Iaylers earneſt enquiry for ſaluation, I note theſe three.
            Firſt, his reuerent carriage to the Miniſters of 
               
the moſt high God, in the firſt word, Sirs.
            
            Secondly, the occaſion of this his earneſt inquiſition,  and that was his humiliation by the Law, in thoſe words: What muſt I doe? I that am the ſonne of bitterneſſe, indignation and eternall weeping; what muſt poore, lamentable, damnable I doe to bee ſaued?
            Thirdly, the inquiſition it ſelfe, and that is for  ſaluation, in theſe words: To be ſaued. Sirs, Sirs, what muſt I doe? Sirs, what muſt I doe to be ſaued?
            
            
               Sirs, It is nomen honoris, a name of honour, and Sirs. title of dignity, elim tributum ijs qui ſapientia abundarunt: in elder time appropriated to wiſdome and learning.
            Heere firſt I might take occaſion to ſhew with how great reuerence Miniſters of the Goſpell are to bee reſpected: good Paſtors are to bee had in double honour: yea their feet to be eſteemed bleſſed, that bring glad tidings of peace to our ſoules; but I forbeare the proſecution of this point, and propound vnto you the marueylous change that is 
               Note. 
               found in this Iayler: for in the precedent verſes it is euident how doggedly and deſpectiuely hee vſed theſe holymen: he laid vpon them hand and foot bolts and fetters as many as they could beare, hee thruſt them into the inner dungeon and priſon: but now the Lord hauing taken him to doe, and giuen him the true and terrible fight and ſenſe of his ſinnes, hee is of another minde: now he brings them out, waſheth their wounds, refreſheth their bodies, and reuerenceth their perſons; Sirs, Reuerend

Sirs, you Miniſters of the moſt high God; what muſt I doe to be ſaued?
            
            No reaſon can be rendred for this miraculous change, but this: The winde bloweth where it luft
                     •
                  th: 
               John 3. 8. and God hath mercy on whom he will haue mercy: and Rom. 9. 15. 
               Of this ſtone God can raiſe a childe to Abraham. 
               Math. 3. 9.
            
            This change wee muſt all be acquainted with, if euer wee will proue our ſelues truely conuerted.
            The Greek word for repentance, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                by name ſignifieth a change, ſignifying vnto vs, that hee that will proue himſelfe truly penitent for his ſinne, muſt bee truly changed from his ſinne.
            This change we finde in penitent Mary: thoſe eyes which once inticed to ſinne, and thoſe hayres which once were employed to iniquity, were wondrouſly altered and changed; for her eyes were conduits to diſtill whole buckets of teares to waſh our Sauiours feet, and her hayres an acceptable towell 
               Iohn 11. 2. 
               to wipe them.
            
            This change wee finde in penitent Paul: who of a Perſecutor became a Profoſſor, of a Lyon a Lambe: Acts 9. 6. and as he put to death others for the Goſpell; ſo in the end himſelfe put to death for the ſame.
            This change wee finde in Zacchee: who before his conuerſion was a notable pick-purſe and poller of the Commons: but when Chriſt came to the houſe and home of his heart, proued bountifull and liberall, inſomuch, that halfe of his goods hee 
               Luke 19. 8. 
               gaue to the poore, and if any man could proue that hee had wronged him a penny, he would make him quadruple reſtitution.
            
            
               
So this Iayler before his conuerſion, an inſidell, prophane, and hard-hearted member: but the Lord hauing taken him to taske, and trembling him by the ſpirit of bondage, now hee reuerenceth Gods Miniſters, now hee humbly ſues vnto them for counſell and inſtruction, ſaying: Sirs, Renerend Sirs; what muſt I doe to be ſaued?
            
            And thus muſt wee all be changed, (beloued in the Lord) from darkeneſſe to light, or el
                  •
                hell and damnation muſt bee our portion to drinke.
            The Lord then worke this excellent change in our hearts, the Lord create in vs all a new heart, and renew a right ſpirit within vs; the Lord take away our ſtony hearts and giue vs hearts of fleſh; the Lord renew vs in our minds and iudgements, wills and affections, words and actions: turne vs (O Lord) and wee ſhall be turned, conuert vs thus (O God) and then, and neuer before then ſhall we bee conuerted.
            Thus much for the firſt word, Sirs.
            
            The ſecond orderly to be conſidered, is the occaſion of this his earneſt enquiry for ſaluation: and that was his humiliation by the Law in theſe words: What muſt I doe? I that am the childe of wrath and What muſt I doe? ſonne of perdition, I that am leprous, lothſome, and out of meaſure ſinfull, I that haue the wrath of God ſenſibly vpon my ſoule for my ſinnes, I that know no way out of this my feare and miſery; O what muſt poore lamentable, damnable I doe to bee faued?
            
               
Whence wee note the power, office, and property of 
               Note. 
               the Law: that it is (as we reade Galathians 3. 24.) A 
               Gal. 3. 24. 
               notable Schoolemaſter to ſend vs to Chriſt: it ſends vs to Chriſt, non aliciendo, ſed compellendo, not by alluring, but by compelling.
            The Law is a killing letter: When the commandement came, I dyed, ſaith Paul: it killeth by ſhewing Rom. 7. 10. vs and making vs feele the damnability of our ſinnes: ſome by the Law killed to deſtruction, as Caine, Eſau, Iudas, and ſuch as wholly deſpaire: others killed to ſaluation, as Paul and ſuch as by their deſpaire are driuen vnto Chriſt.
            The property of the Law is to humble and quake vs for our ſinnes: it ſheweth vs our ſinne, and miniſtreth wrath vnto our ſoules.
            This humiliation ſtandeth in two.

                  Confeſſion.
                  Attrition.
               
            
            The firſt brings ſhame, the ſecond horror: ſhame from ſinnes filthineſſe, horror from ſinnes fearefulneſſe: This doth the Law being knowne and applyed, as a Centinel it bewrayeth the enemy, and makes vs flye vnto Chriſt.
            Thus were they humbled that heard Peter in the Acts: they were wounded in conſcience and pricked in heart before they cried out, Men and brethren, 
               Act. 2. 37. 
               what muſt we doe?
            
            Thus the Law wrought vpon them that heard Iohn, before they cryed out, What muſt wee doe 
               Luke 3. 10. 
               then?
            
            And ſo Nineueh being firſt humbled, ſought vnto 
               Ion. 3. 5. 
               God, and Paul firſt trembled, then ſaid, What ſhall I 
               Act. 9 6.
               
               doe Lord? And heere a poore Iayler in the ſorrow of his ſoule, cryeth out for ſaluation; Sirs, what muſt I doe to be ſaued? ſo that the Law prepares vs to Chriſt.
            It is moſt certaine that ſaluation belongeth to none but the humble: To whom will I looke (ſaith Eſay 66. 2. the Lord) euen to him that is of a contrite heart, and trembleth at my words: yea the refreſhing is promiſed to none but the laden: for we muſt go through Math. 11. 28. the hell of a wounded conſcience, before wee ſhall taſte of the heauenly refreſhing: Merchants waxe Similie. muſt leach in a candle, before it can take a ſtampe or impreſſion: the terror of ſinne muſt languiſh our ſoules, before wee can come to bleſſed remiſſion.
            The comming of God into the ſoules of his choſen, is notably reſembled by his appearance to Eliah: Firſt, there came a mighty ſtrong winde 
               1. Kin. 19. 11. 12. 
               that rent the mountaines, and brake the rockes, but the Lord was not in the winde: after the winde came an earthquake, but the Lord was not in the earthquake: after the earthquake came fire, but the Lord was not in the fire: at laſt came there a ſtill and ſoft voyce. So the Lord appeareth to his redeemed ones, firſt by the winde of his wrath, breaking their hearts; then by the earth-quake of his anger, ſhaking their ſoules; then by the fire of his diſpleaſure, ſmoking their conſciences: but in the end, by the ſtill voyce of his mercy hee refreſheth their ſoules.
            This poore Iayler had an earth-quake in his conſcience, as an earthquake in his Caſtle,

before euer hee perceiued his election and ſaluation.
            There is an old ſaying, Wee muſt goe by the gates of Hell to Heauen: but I ſay more, We muſt after a ſort be in Hell before euer we can bee capable of Heauen: that is, in the hell of an aſhamed, affrighted, and confounded conſcience, before euer the Lord will ſay vnto our ſoules that he is our redemption.
            If humiliation by the Law precedes the ſaluation  of the Goſpell, then they are not conuerted that more or leſſe were neuer humbled.
            Secondly, they that are troubled and amazed  at their ſinnes, let them not be diſparaged; ſo farre they are in this their hell from Hell, as hereby they are compoſed and fitted for Heauen; for wee muſt be loſt before we can be found, wee muſt bee condemned before we can be ſaued.
            Thirdly, let not humbled conſciences reſt here,  but paſſe on ſtill till they haue found the ſpirit of bondage become the ſpirit of adoption to their ſoules.
            And this counſell I giue all troubled ſoules for ſinne:
            Let them come to the Temple. 
            
            Let them impart their griefe to ſome friend or  Miniſter.
            Let them conferre with them that haue beene in  the like caſe.
            Let them know that they muſt be thus ſicke, before  Chriſt will euer heale them.
            
               
Let them build vpon Gods mercy promiſed  to ſuch.
            Let them pray that God in his good time would  miniſter refreſhing.
            
               What muſt I doe? Text.
               
               AGaine heere wee may note the miſerable Note. miſchiefe and curſed condition of ſinne: how burthenſome and irkſome it is to the ſoule, it miniſtreth nothing but horror and hell to our ſoules.
               The ſeruice of ſinne is farre worſe then the ſlauery of Egypt.
               
               The bondage of Egypt was of the body onely:  this of ſinne is both of ſoule and body.
               In the bondage of Egypt they ſerued men: in this,  ſinne and Satan.
               In the firſt, they had a ſenſe of their bondage and  deſired liberty: in the ſecond, they thinke themſelues free and deſpiſe deliuerance.
               In the firſt the miſery was but temporall: in the  ſecond eternall.
               In outward bondage men may help themſelues  by running away, by intreaty, by ranſome: in the the ſecond they lye ſtill till Gods mercy deliuer them.
               A wofull thing it is to abide in the eſtate of ſinne: yea the damned themſelues confeſſe that the way of ſinne is a weariſome way to bee walked

in: Wee haue wearied our ſelues in the wayes of wickedneſſe, 
                  Wiſd. 5. 7. 
                  and the light of righteouſneſſe hath not ſhined vpon our ſoules.
               
               No maruell therefore if the bands of wickedneſſe bee called, heauy and importable burthens. 
                  Eſay 58. 6.
               
               Sinne is onus Deo, a burthen to God: Eſay 1. 14. Your ſacrifices are a burthen vnto me.
               
               Sinne is onus Angelis, a burthen to the Angels: for it ſunke them downe from heauen. Luke 10. 18.
               Sinne is onus creaturis, a burthen to the creatures: for it makes them grone. Rom. 8. 22.
               Sinne is onus hominibus, a burthen to men: Mine iniquities are gone euer my head, and as a weighty burthen too heauy for me to beare. Pſal. 38. 4.
               Let vs then beware of ſinne that made this Iayler roare and cry, O what muſt I doe to be ſaued? For though ſinne fawne vpon thee now, yet it will in the end pluck out the very throat of thy ſoule.
               Let vs then flye from ſinne as from a ſtinging ſerpent and biting Cockatrice; for they that doe ſuch things, ſhall neuer ſee the ſaluation of God.
            
            
               To bee ſaued. Text.
               
               THirdly, let vs behold the ſubſtance and ſubiect of his fute,
               It is not with Iames, to ſit by Chriſt in his 
                  Mat. 20. 21. 
                  glory:
               
               
                  
It is not to haue an inheritance diuided with that Luk. 12. 13. worldling in the Goſpell:
               It is not for any worldly pompe or honor, but it is for ſaluation: What muſt I doe to be ſaued?
               
               The moſt principall thing that all men ſhould Note. ſtriue for vnder Gods glory, is the ſaluation of their ſoules.
               
                  Firſt, and aboue all things ſeeke the Kingdome of 
                  Math. 6. 33. 
                  God and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and in a ſubordinate manner the things of this life: for what if wee haue all the world, and bee damned when wee dye, what a miſerable condition is this?
               O how Moſes beg'd to ſee the face of the Lord! Lord (ſaith he) ſhew me thy glory. 
                  Exod. 33. 18.
               
               O how Dauid ſued to God for his loue: Some 
                  Pſal. 4. 6. 
                  craue worldly goods, and riches doe imbrace; but Lord, grant me thy countenance, thy fauour and thy grace.
               
               O how this Iayler cries out heere for ſaluation! O what muſt I doe to be ſaued?
               
               This meets with careleſſe and deſperate people of the world, that worke not out this their ſaluation with feare and trembling, that make not ſure their election and calling: O better for theſe neuer to haue beene borne, than not to be reborne.
               O how carefull were the Apoſtles, when Chriſt told them that one of them ſhould betray him! they could neither eate nor drinke till they knew themſelues freed from that curſed fact: Numquid 
                  Math. 26. 22. 
                  ego Domine? Is it l, Lord, is it l?
               
               O wee ſhould reſolue with Dauid, not to ſuffer our 
                  Pſal. 132. 4.
                  
                  eyes to ſleepe, nor eye-lids to ſlumber, nor the temples of our head to take any reſt, till wee haue found the boxe of Election opened vnto vs, and the ſweete odour of Gods loue ſhed abroad in our hearts.
            
            
               To bee ſaued. Text.
               
               IN that this Iayler by the Iudgements of God, is drawne neerer to God, wee may ſee the different Note. working of Gods iudgements vpon the Elect and Reprobate: the one hardened by them, the other humbled: the one deſperate, the other ſeeking to God for remiſſion and ſaluation.
               Euen as the Sunne in the Heauens melieth wax, Similie. but hardeneth clay: as the ſame water ſaued Iſrael, but drowned Pharao: and as the ſame trumpe in battell incourageth the one ſide, but diſcourageth the other: So the ſame word and iudgements of God draw neerer to the Lord the elect, but harden the hearts of the wicked: Cain hardened, Manaſſes humbled: Iudas deſperate, but Paul by Gods iudgements conuerted.
               It makes againſt ſuch as with Pharac harden their hearts againſt God by his iudgements, vtterly deſpairing of his mercy for remiſſion: Maior eſt Deipictas, quam quaeuis iniquitas.
               
               Gods mercy is greater then mans miſery: God is more merciful then man can be ſinful, if man wil be truly and heartily ſorrowfull.
               
                  All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth: God Pſal. 25. 10.
                  
hath two feet whereby hee walkes in his wayes, the foot of mercy and the foote of iuſtice: If we looke vpon his mercy only, ten to one we ſhall periſh by preſumption; if wee looke vpon his iuſtice onely, ten to one wee ſhall periſh by deſperation: therefore let vs humbly fall downe and kiſſe both of his feete, that in reſpect of his mercy wee may keepe hope, and in reſpect of his iuſtice wee may keepe awe, reuerence and feare.
               If therefore the Diuell tempts thee to preſumption, look what thou art in thy ſelfe, vile, wretched, miſerable, and thou ſhalt neuer preſume: if hee tempts thee to deſparation, looke what thou art or maiſt be in Chriſt Ieſus, ſpotleſſe, holy, glorious, then thou ſhalt neuer deſpaire.
               Thus the Church of Chriſt did: I am blacke, (O 
                  Cant. 1. 4. 
                  yee daughters of Ieruſalem) yet comely as the curteines of Salomon. How could ſhee bee black and beautifull? black in her ſelfe, and beautifull in Chriſt Ieſus.
               Thus plainly haue I vnfolded the firſt part of my text, the Iaylers miſery: the ſecond part is miniſtred mercy by Paul and Sylas, and as plainly by Gods aſſiſtance I purpoſe to paſſe thorow that: for I had rather pleaſure your hearts then pleaſe your heads, worthy is your ſcience, but (I feare me) farre ſhort comes your conſcience: giue me leaue then to beſtow my labour where there is moſt need, and I pray God as meane an inſtrument as I am, I may be a meane to further you all in the way of Gods Kingdome.
            
            
               
               And they ſaid, Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus Text. Chriſt, thou ſhalt be ſaued and thy houſe.
               BEfore I come to the particulars of their anſwere, I muſt needs commend the wiſdome and diſcretion of theſe Preachers: they miniſter a fit ſalue to this poore mans ſore: they put oyle to vineger, mercy to iudgement, Goſpell to Law: an excellent temper for health euerlaſting.
               Had they preached the Law, and denounced Gods curſes againſt him, they had ſunke him downe to hell by deſpaire: but perceiuing him ready to bee ſwallowed vp of damnation, by the caſting-net of the Goſpell they ſaue his ſoule from ſinking.
               A good preſident for all Gods miniſters, that they bee carefull wiſely, diſcreetly, and rightly to breake the Bread of life to the people.
               Wee muſt preach the Goſpell to languiſhing ſoules, and the Law to preſumptuous: otherwiſe wee ſhall ſooner damne then ſaue by our preaching.
               To this poore Iayler in the very iawes of Hell and mouth of damnation, Paul and Sylas tender Chriſt Ieſus for his recouery and ſaluation.
            
            
               
               And thy houſe. Text.
               
               I Muſt here reſolue a doubt, before I come to this heauenly reſolution.
               Some may obiect and ſay, What, ſhall the Iaylers Ob. faith redeeme his family? if the maſter beleeueth, ſhall the houſhold be ſaued? It may ſeeme ſo by the words of the text: Beleene thou, and thy houſe ſhall be ſaued.
               
               To anſwer this: heere is ſomething implyed Anſ. that is not expreſſed: Beleeue on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, thou ſhalt bee ſaued and thy houſhold: that is, they beleeuing with thee
               As if they had ſaid: Poore Iayler, be no diſparaged, but looke vpon Chriſt Ieſus, there's mercy enough in ſtore, not onely for thy ſelfe, but for thy whole houſhold if they can but beleeue, yea aboundant ſaluation for all humbled beleeuers.
               That the faith of one ſaueth not another, (at leaſt in adultis) looke into Ezekiel. That ſoule that 
                  Ezek. 18. 20. 
                  ſinneth, that ſoule ſhall dye: the righteouſnes of the righteous ſhall be vpon him, and the wickedneſſe of the wicked ſhall be vpon himſelfe alſo.
               
               In the old Law, it was Fac hoc and viues, Do this, and thou ſhalt liue. God gaue vs leaue to doe it by another Ieſus Chriſt the righteous: but in the new Law it is Crede &amp; viues; beleeue and thou ſhalt liue. God gaue vs leaue to doe this by no other.
               
                  
Can a man ſee with another mans eye? No more can a man goe to heauen by another mans faith; Euery man muſt beleeue for himſelfe, if he will be ſaued himſelfe.
               This is notably apparant in the Parable of the Virgins: The fooliſh would haue borrowed oyle of the 
                  Math. 25. 9. 
                  wiſe, but they anſwered, Not ſo, leſt there be not enough for vs and you: they had (it ſeemeth) grace little enough to ſaue themſelues, they could ſaue none for their ſiſtren.
               I know, for the godly mans ſake, God many times ſpareth the wicked: as if there had beene found ten righteous in Sodome, for their ſakes the 
                  Gen. 18. 32. 
                  City had beene ſpared, but this was in a temporary ſaluation: but in the point of iuſtification to eternall happineſſe, euery man muſt haue faith in himſelfe: therefore quod dixit Chriſtus, dico vobis, Habete ſalem in vobis: what Chriſt ſaid in his Goſpel, that I ſay vnto you al, Haue the ſalt of faith in your ſelues: for Iuſtus exſua fide viuet: the iuſt ſhall liue Hab. 2. by his faith.
            
            
               Beleeue on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and thou Text. ſhalt be ſaued.
               IN this heauenly reſolution I note three.
               
                  
                     1. Firſt, the act: Beleeue. 
                  
                  
                     Secondly, the obiect: on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. 
                  
                  
                     Thirdly, the euent: And thou ſhalt be ſaued. 
                  
               
               
                  Beleeue: Beleeue on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: Beleeue

on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt bee ſaued.
               
            
            
               Beleeue. Text.
               
               
                  FIdes, faith, in the Hebrew is called Amnah, of Aman, which ſignifies firmum eſſe, to be firme or ſtrong, or well reſolued.
               In the Greeke it ſignifies a perſwaſion: in the Latine, fides, quaſi fiat quod dicitur, of the two ſillables, fi-factum, des, dictum: that ſhall bee done, that is ſpoken. 'Tis Auguſtines deſcant vpon them.
               Thus therefore I deſcribe faith: It is firmus ac 
                  Faith. 
                  conſtans animi aſſenſus Verbo Dei, Spiritus Sancti afflatu ad credentium ſalutem: Faith is a ſtedfaſt and reſolute aſſent or conſent of the heart to Gods Word, by the breathing of the holy Ghoſt to the ſaluation, of beleeuers. The materiall cauſe of faith, is the Word of God. The formall cauſe, is the act of conſent. The efficient cauſe, is the holy Ghoſt, the finall cauſe, is the ſaluation of our ſoules.
               Now leſt wee ſhould imagine euery beleeuer to bee bleſſed, wee are to know that there is a fourefold faith, yet but one ſalutiferous.
               The firſt, Hiſtoricall: when a man aſſents to the  truth of the word; the Diuels goe thus farre in Iam. 2. 19. faith, and tremble.
               
               The ſecond momentany: when a man with 
                  
ſome howerly delight imbraceth the Word, meerely for knowledge ſake and no further, and ſuffers not the power of it to bee lodged and ſeated in his ſoule, in proſperity to make a great flouriſh in Religion, but in the time of triall to fall away, as in that of Saint Luke, They depart from 
                  Luke 8. 13. 
                  God in time of tribulation.
               
               The third, Miraculous: ſpoken of in the Corinths, 
                   
                  What if I had all faith, that I could remoue mountaines, 
                  1 Cor. 13. 2. 
                  and haue not Charity, ſuch a faith profits me nothing.
               
               The fourth, Iuſtifying: whereby a man poſſeſſing  and imbracing Chriſt Ieſus with his merits and graces, is accepted as iuſt before God: This is alſo called a liuely faith, ſhewing that it may bee as eaſily perceiued in the wombe of the conſcience, as a childe after quickening in the wombe of the mother. Bede makes a triple diſtinction of faith.
               
                  Credere
                  Deum:
                  Deo:
                  In Deum.
               
               To beleeue there is a God: to beleeue that he is faithfull and iuſt in his mercies and iudgements: to beleeue that hee is reconciled to vs in the bloud of his Sonne, into whom wee are inſerted as an ympe or ſciens into a ſtocke or tree, and ſo liue by the ſap and iuyce of his deriued merits and graces: this is the faith that inſtrumentally is ſaid to ſaue all our poore ſoules euerlaſtingly

aliue: And I may well ſay inſtrumentally: for faith, as it is a bare and meere quality, ſaueth no man, but as it hath reference to the obiect Ieſus: As a Diamond Ring is ſaid to be rich Simile. and precious: but take out the Diamond and it is worth little: Faith is this Ring, Chriſt is this Diamond which enricheth vs all with heauenly ſaluation.
               Now leſt wee ſhould build vpon the ſands of preſumption, and thinke wee are in this faith, being yet farre wide: Let vs examine this faith by his fruits; for as fire is not without heate, and the Sunne without ſhine; ſo this faith is neuer knowne without workes of amendment: Hee that rubbleth muske, cannot but ſmell thereof; ſo hee that hath put on Chriſt, cannot but bee a new creature, cannot but ſmell of 
                  Pſal. 45. 8. 
                  Myrrhe, Aloes and Caſſia, out of Chriſts Iuory Palaces, whereby his heart is made exceedingly glad.
               
               There are fiue eſpeciall euidences and fruits of this faith.
               It brings peace of conſcience, and ioy in  the holy Ghoſt, vpon our reconcilement with God: Being iuſtified by faith, wee are at peace with 
                  Rom. 5. 1. 
                  God &amp;c.
               
               It cauſeth a man, boldly and openly to  confeſſe the name of Chriſt: For, by the heart 
                  Rom. 10. 10. 
                  a man beleeueth to righteouſneſſe, and by the tongue, a man confeſſeth to ſaluation: Where there is a beleeuing heart, there will bee a

confeſſing tongue and profeſſing life to Gods glory.
               It teacheth a man to reſt vpon Gods promiſe  and prouidence in all ſtreights and tryalls whatſoeuer: The iuſt ſhall liue by faith: that is, they by faith Hab. 2. 4. ſhall reſt vpon God in their ſtreights, and God will preſerue them.
               It ſtirres vs vp to often and earneſt prayer: Lord, 
                   
                  I beleeue: there is his faith: Helpe mine vnbeliefe: 
                  Mark. 9. 24. there is his prayer: therefore no prayer, no faith; cold prayer, dead faith; vehement prayer, ſtrong faith.
               It behaueth it ſelfe as a Preacher in the Pulpit of  the ſoule, alwayes mouing the ſoule to holineſſe: Beleeue thus on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, thou ſhalt be ſaued and thy houſhold.
               
               Now by theſe examine your ſelues, proue your ſelues whether you are in the faith: know yee not that Ieſus Chriſt is thus in you, except you bee reprobates? yee are reprobates, if theſe things more or leſſe be not in you.
               The Lord then worke in our hearts this faith, and encreaſe it towards perfection, that ſo our ſelues with our houſhold, euerlaſtingly may bee ſaued.
            
            
               
               On the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Text.
               
               THe obiect of our faith, is the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.
               There is not a name vnder Heauen, wherein ſaluation Note. can be expected and had, but in the name, merit, and power of Ieſus.
               Hee is our Iacobs Ladder, on whom wee muſt climbe to life euerlaſting.
               Let vs not goe to Rome for a Pardon, nor to Mahomet for a bleſſing, nor to the Sorcerer for skill, nor to the Magician for counſell; but let vs come vnto Chriſt, and hee will refreſh vs. Quo ibimus? Whither ſhall we goe? Thou (O Chriſt) and none but thou, haſt the words of eternall life.
            
            
               Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Text.
               
               ALl the names of our bleſſed Redeemer are happily met together.
               
                  Lord: his name of power.
               
                  Ieſus: his name of propriety.
               
                  Chriſt: his name of Office.
               
                  Lord: a name of power, attributing to God his Eſſence and being, ſhewing that hee receiued his being from none but himſelfe alone, as all things elſe haue their being from him: For in him wee 
                  Act. 7. 28. 
                  li
                        •
                     e, wee moue, and haue our being.
               
               
                  
                  Chriſt is a Lord 
                     
                        By power, coequall with his Father.
                     
                        By purchaſe, redeeming vs by his bloud.
                  
               
               And therfore called, Dominus Dens, Dominus Electorum, the Lord of the Elect.
               Heerein his Deity is apparant: He muſt be thus a Lord, or elſe hee could neuer haue beene a Ieſus. Firſt, a Lord, to ſupport, deliuer, and make conquer his humanity: Againe, a Lord, to dignifie and make meritorious euery act done in his humanity for the ſaluation of his Elect.
               That this glorious title is duely giuen vnto our Sauiour, witneſſe that of the Pſalmes, The Lord 
                  Pſal. 110. 1. 
                  ſaid vnto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, till I make thine enimies thy foot-ſtoole.
               
               And Thomas thus confeſſeth him, Thou art my 
                  Ioh. 20. 28. 
                  Lord and my God.
               
               This then is no ſmall comfort to the faithfull, that they haue ſo powerfull and glorious a Meſſiah; And it maketh alſo much againſt thoſe baſe Heretickes, that mock vs for our dependance on Chriſt for ſaluation.
               Againe, in the laſt place, it ſhould teach vs what manner of perſons wee ſhould bee to our Redeemer. A ſonne honoureth his father, and a ſeruant his 
                  Mal. 1. 6. 
                  master; if I then be your Lord and maſter, where is then my feare? Many would haue Chriſt their Ieſus, but few can brooke him their Lord; Wee muſt bee conformed to this our Lord in two, in grace, in croſſe, if euer wee will be glorified with him.
               
                  
There are fiue properties of a faithfull ſeruant, which we muſt labour to haue, if euer we will make account of Chriſt for our Lord.
               The firſt is Obedience; ſuch were the Centurions 
                   ſeruants, He ſaid to one, Come, and hee commeth: to 
                  Luke 7. 8. 
                  another, Goe, and he goeth: to another, Doe this, and hee doth it. O that wee were ſuch obedients to our Lord!
               The ſecond is Diligence; He toyleth and labours  dayly in his maſters ſeruice for his maſters aduantage and gaine: ſo induſtrious and laborious ſhould wee be for the glory of our Lord Ieſus.
               The third is Reuerence; if his maſter doth but  bend his browes, hee quakes and trembles: ſo when our Lord ſeemes angry, we muſt (with Noah) 
                  Heb. 11. 7. 
                  be moued with reuerence.
               
               The fourth is Patience; if his maſter correcteth  him, hee beares it meekely, quietly, and patiently: ſo when wee are chaſtiſed of our Lord, wee ſhould vndergoe it with meekeneſſe and patience.
               The fift is Loue; if his maſter bee wronged or reuiled, he will not beare it with patience, but ſtand vp to reuenge it: ſo if wee heare or ſee our Lord Chriſt blaſphemed, and his moſt holy Profeſſion derided, it ſhould be a Simeons ſword to pierce our ſoules.
            
            
               
               Ieſus. Text.
               
               THis name was giuen him by an Angell, before hee was conceiued in the wombe, and a reaſon thereof rendred, Becauſe hee ſhould ſaue his people 
                  Math. 1. 21. 
                  from their ſinnes. Hee ſaues vs
from ſinnes
                     Guilt.
                     Puniſhment.
                     Regiment.
                  
               
               From ſinnes guilt and puniſhment, by his imputatiue paſſions; from ſinnes regiment, by his merits and graces applyed and deriued vpon vs: and by his actiue obedience imputed, he doth entitle vs to the glory of heauen.
               Old Simeon acknowledged Chriſt ſuch a ſaluation: Mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation, yea and my ſaluation; thine for ſending, mine for ſauing; thine Luke 2. 30. for loue, mine for life: Mine eyes haue ſeene this ſaluation.
               And the ſpirit of Mary alſo exulted in this her Sonne Sauiour. 
                  Luke 1. 47.
               
               And all you that would finde him a Ieſus from Hell, bee carefull yee finde him a Ieſus from ſinne.
               
            
            
               
               Chriſt. Text.
               
               
                  CHriſt ſignifieth Anoynted: In the Old Law they anointed three:
               
                  Kings,
                  Prieſts,
                  Prophets.
               
               And for the worke of our Redemption, Chriſt was neceſſarily anoynted to a triple Office, with the oyle of holineſſe aboue his fellowes.
               
                  He was anoynted to be a
                  King,
                  Prophet,
                  Prieſt.
               
               To be a King, a type whereof was Salomon; to be a Prophet, a type whereof was Dauid; to bee a Prieſt, a type whereof was Melchiſedech; Melchiſedech, not Aaron: Aaron a Prieſt, but not a King; Dauid a King, but not a Prieſt; Melchiſedech both King and Prieſt, King of Salem, and Prieſt of the moſt high God; and therefore a notable type of Ieſus.
               Hee was anoynted to bee a King, to rule his Elect and protect them; hee was anoyuted to bee a Prophet, to teach his Elect and direct them; hee was anoynted to be a Prieſt, to ranſome his Elect and redeeme them.
               If Chriſt be thy Chriſt as King, then the Diuell reignes not in thee but Chriſt; if Chriſt bee thy Chriſt as Prophet, then his word, not thy will, is the rule and ſquare of all thine actions; if Chriſt bee

thy Chriſt as Prieſt, then thy affections are ſlaine concerning ſinne, and thy whole man ſacrificed to God.
            
            
               And thou ſhalt be ſaued. Text.
               
               THe reward of our faith is the ſaluation of our Note. ſoules: Bleſſed is the eſtate of Chriſtianity, for it is rewarded with inexpreſſible felicity.
               The benefit of beleeuing is multiple.
               Firſt, heereby wee are adopted the children  of God: Yee are all the ſonnes of God by faith in Chriſt 
                  Gal. 3. 26. 
                  Ieſus.
               
               Secondly, hereby our ſinnes are forgiuen vs, as  we reade in the Goſpell: Confide, fils, &amp; remittuntur tibi peccata: Beleeue, my ſonne, and thy ſinnes are for giuen thee.
               
               Thirdly, hereby we haue right and intereſt in all  Gods bleſſings of this life: Godlineſſe hath the promiſes 
                  1. Tim. 4. 8. 
                  of this life, as well as of that which is to come.
               
               Fourthly, hereby we are freed from the damnation  of hell: Now then there is no condemnation to 
                  Rom. 8. 1. 
                  thoſe that are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walke not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit.
               
               Laſtly, hereby we ſhall be poſſeſſed with the ſaluation  of heauen: the glories and ioyes whereof are ſo great, as they cannot bee numbred; ſo precious, as they cannot be valued; ſo laſting, as they are euerlaſting.
               
                  Neither, eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor 
                  1. Cor. 2. 9.
                  
                  heart of man hath euer imagined, the thouſand part of this heauenly felicity.
               
               
                  Beleene on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: thus thou ſhalt bee ſaued and thine houſhold.
               
               If then to bee members of Chriſt Ieſus bee ſo bleſſed a condition; O let vs begge of God the heauenly Huſbandman, to rend vs off by true humbling from the ſtocke of corruption, and to plant vs into Chriſt Ieſus, by effectuall beleeuing, that at that terrible Iudgement, wee all with our poore houſholds euerlaſtingly may be ſaued: And that for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, our only Lord and euerlaſting Redeemer.
               Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A GODLY AND Zealous Prayer.
            
               O Moſt glorious God, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and in him our Father, the Fountaine of all our welfare, and the giuer of all grace: we thy poore children (according to our bounden duty) are at this preſent aſſembled together before thee in Prayer, to offer vp euen from the ground of our hearts, the Sacrifice of thankſgiuing, for all thy louing mercies and tender kindneſſes whatſoeuer beſtowed vpon vs. We highly bleſſe thy Maieſty for electing vs in thy Chriſt to life eternall, before all worlds, for creating vs after thine owne moſt glorious Image in purity and perfection of holineſſe, for iuſtifying vs by the perfect obedience of thy Sonne, for ſanctifying vs by thy holy Spirit; and for the hope that thou haſt giuen vs of our future glorification with thee heereafter in Heauen. We alſo returne vnto thee all due and poſſible prayſe, for preſeruing vs hitherto of thine eſpeciall goodneſſe and mercy; ſupplying aboundantly all our

neceſſities both in ſoule and in body; and for thy bleſſing vpon vs and ours, keeping vs from diuers dangers, that might iuſtly for our ſinnes haue come vpon vs, both ſpirituall and corporall. O what ſhall we render vnto thee for all theſe thy mercies done vnto vs? what are wee, that thou ſhouldſt thus reſpect vs? or what are our deſeruings, that thou ſhouldſt thus eſteeme vs? To vs, O Lord, to vs moſt miſerable ſinners, there nothing belongeth but ſhame and confuſion. If thou (Lord) markeſt ſtrictly what is done amiſſe, who is able to abide it? O how farre doth thy mercy exceed thy iuſtice! O the deepneſſe of thy fauours towards vs! So vnſearchable are they, as no man can expreſſe them, ſo vn-vtterable, as no man can declare them.
            And (moſt mercifull Father) wee humbly intreat for thy Chriſts ſake the continuance of theſe mercies towards vs: Bleſſe vs this day and euer with thy heauenly protection and benediction, guide vs by thine owne Spirit into all godlineſſe, that we may profitably and conſcionably walke before thee in our vocations, both generall and particular: bleſſe vs in the houſe, and bleſſe vs in the field: bleſſe vs in the basket, and bleſſe vs in the ſtore: bleſſe vs in our out-goings, and in our commings in; compaſſe vs on euery ſide with thy mercies; guard thine Angels round about vs; keepe vs from the euill of this world, and euery worke of darkneſſe; and ſanctifie both our ſoules and bodies with thy feare to thy ſeruice, that as heretofore we

haue ſerued the Diuell and the world by prophaneneſſe; ſo euer heereafter (redeeming the time) wee may apply our ſelues vnto holineſſe.
            To which end we moſt earneſtly craue (O heauenly Father) the preſence of thy Spirit alwayes to direct vs, the powerfull preaching of thy Goſpell, alwayes to inſtruct vs, the holy vſe of thy Sacraments alway to confirme vs, that (all hereſie and vngodlineſſe remoued farre from vs) by theſe meanes ſanctified vnto vs, we may glorifie thy holy name, by our holy conuerſations in this life, and bee glorified of thee euerlaſtingly in the life to come.
            And becauſe (by reaſon of our ſinnes) in ſtead of thy mercies we haue deſerued thy furious indignation againſt vs: we therefore ſeriouſly begge at the throne of thy mercy, in the meritorious mediation of Ieſus Chriſt, that thou wouldeſt remoue far from vs and our Land, all thy fearefull and heauy iudgements whatſoeuer, as famine, peſtilence, ſword, and the like; and giue vs all grace from the King to the beaſt, that we may be truly humbled for all our iniquities, that wee repenting vs of our euill which is ſinne, thou maiſt be pleaſed to repent thee of thy euill which is puniſhment for ſinne.
            Heare vs (Obleſſed Lord God) in theſe our Petitions, pardoning our ſinnes, and granting to vs all our requeſts, with all other thy graces that we ſtand in need of, that may make for thy glory, and the ſauing of our poore ſoules, at the diſmall Day of

Iudgement, and that for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake: To whom with thee and thy bleſſed Spirit, three glorious perſons, but one immortall God, wee deſire to returne all poſſible praiſe, power, dominion, and thankſgiuing, this day and euerlaſting.
            Amen.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

