
   
      
         
            Pandosto the triumph of time. VVherein is discouered by a pleasant historie, that although by the meanes of sinister fortune truth may be concealed, yet by time in spight of fortune it is most manifestlie reuealed. Pleasant for age to auoyde drowsie thoughtes, profitable for youth to eschue other wanton pastimes, and bringing to both a desired content. Temporis filia veritas. By Robert Greene Maister of Artes in Cambridge.
            Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
         
         
            
               1588
            
         
         Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02143
            STC 12285
            ESTC S108586
            99844244
            99844244
            9036
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02143)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9036)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 546:03)
         
         
            
               
                  Pandosto the triumph of time. VVherein is discouered by a pleasant historie, that although by the meanes of sinister fortune truth may be concealed, yet by time in spight of fortune it is most manifestlie reuealed. Pleasant for age to auoyde drowsie thoughtes, profitable for youth to eschue other wanton pastimes, and bringing to both a desired content. Temporis filia veritas. By Robert Greene Maister of Artes in Cambridge.
                  Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
               
               [56] p.   
               
                  By Thomas Orwin for Thomas Cadman, dwelling at the signe of the Bible, neere vnto the north doore of Paules,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1588.
               
               
                  Running title reads: The historie of Dorastus and Fawnia.
                  Signatures: A-G⁴.
                  Imperfect: signature B lacking.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. --  Winter's Tale --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2000-00
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2001-00
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2001-00
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2001-00
            AptaraRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2001-11
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2001-11
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Text and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2001-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            PANDOSTO.
            ¶The Triumph
of Time.
            VVHEREIN IS DISCOUERED
by a pleasant Historie, that although by the meanes
of sinister fortune Truth may be concealed,
yet by Time in spight of fortune it
is most manifestly reuealed.
            Pleasant for age to auoyde drowsie thoughtes,
profitable for youth to eschue other wanton
pastimes, and bringing to both a desired
content.
            Temporis filia veritas.
            ¶By Robert Greene Maister of Artes
in Cambridge.
            Omne tulit punctum qui miscuit vtile dulci.
            Imprinted at London by Thomas Orwin for Thomas
Cadman, dwelling at the Signe of the Bible, neere
vnto the North doore of Paules,
1588.
         
         
            
            TO THE GENTLEMEN READERS
HEALTH.
            THe paultring Poet Aphranius being
blamed for troublinge ye Emperor
Traian with so many doting
Poems: aduentured notwithstanding,
stil to present him with rude
and homely verses, excusing himfelfe
with the courtesie of ye Emperour,
which did as friendly accept, as he fondly
offerd. So Gentlemen, if any condemne my rashnesse
for troubling your eares with so many vnlearned
Pamphlets: I will straight shroud my
selfe vnder the shadowe of your courtesies, &amp; with
Aphranius lay the blame on you aswell for frendly
reading them, as on my selfe for fondly penning
them: Hoping though fond curious, or rather currish
backbiters breathe out slaunderous speeches:
yet the courteous Readers (whom I feare to
offend) wil requite my trauell, at the least
with silence: and in this hope I
rest: wishing you health
and happines.
            Robert Greene.
         
         
            
            TO THE RIGHT HOnorable
George Clifford Earle of Cumberland,
Robert Greene wisheth increase
of honour and vertue.
            THE Rascians (right honorable) when by
long gazing against the Sunne, they become
halfe blinde, recouer their sightes
by looking on the blacke Loade stone. Vnicornes
being glutted with brousing on
roots of Licquoris, sharpē their stomacks
with crushing bitter grasse.
            Alexander vouchsafed as well to smile at the croked picture
of Vulcan, as to wonder at the curious counterfeite of
Venus. The minde is sometimes delighted as much with
small trifles as with sumptuous triumphs, and as wel pleased
with hearing of Pans homely fancies, as of Hercules renowmed
laboures.
            Syllie Baucis coulde not serue Iupiter in a siluer plate, but
in a woodden dish. Al that honour Esculapius, decke not his
shrine with Iewels. Apollo giues Oracles as wel to the poore
man for his mite, as to the rich mā for his treasure. The stone
Echites is not so much liked for the colour, as for vertue,
and giftes are not to be measured by the worth, but by the
will. Mis
                     •
                  n that vnskilfull Painter of Greece, aduentured 
                  •
               o
giue vnto Darius the shielde of Pallas, so roughlie shadowed,
as he smiled more at the follie of the man, then at the imperfection
of his arte. So I present vnto your honour the triumph
of time, so rudelie finished, as I feare your honour wil
rather frowne at my impudencie, then laugh at my ignorancie:
But I hope my willing minde shal excuse my slender skill,
and your honours curtesie shadowe my rashnes.
            
               They which feare the biting of vipers doe carie in their
hands the plumes of a Phoenix. Phydias drewe Vulcan sitting
in a chaire of luory. Caesars Crow durst neuer cry, Aue, but
whē she was pearked on the Capitoll. And I seeke to shroude
this imperfect Pamphlet vnder your honours patronage,
doubting the dint of such inuenomed vipers, as seeke with
their slaunderours reproches to carpe at al, being oftentims,
most vnlearned of all: and assure my sel
                  •
               e, that your honours
renowmed valure, and vertuous disposition shall be a
sufficient defence to protect me from the Poysoned tongues
of such scorning Sycophants, hoping that as Iupiter vouchsafed
to lodge in Philemons thatched Cotage: and Phillip
of Macedon, to take a bunche of grapes of a country pesant:
so I hope your honour, measuring my worke by my will, and
wayghing more the mind than the matter, will when you
haue cast a glaunce at this toy, with Minerua, vnder your golden
Target couer a deformed Owle. And in this hope
I rest, wishing vnto you, and the vertuous
Countesse your wife: such happy successe
as your honours can desire,
or I imagine.
            Your Lordships most duetifully to commaunde:
Robert Greene.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE HISTORIE OF
DORASTUS AND
FAWNIA.
            AMong al the Passions wherewith humane
mindes are perplexed, there is none that so
galleth with restlesse despight, as ye infectious
soare of Iealousie: for all other griefes
are eyther to bee appeased with sensible perswasions,
to be cured with wholesome counsel,
to be relieued in want, or by tract of tune
to be worne out, (Iealousie only excepted) which is so sawsed with
suspitious doubtes, and pinching mistrust, that whoso seekes by
friendly counsaile to rase out this hellish passion, it foorthwith suspecteth
that he geueth this aduise to couer his owne guiltinesse.
Yea, who so is payned with this restlesse torment doubteth all,
dystrusteth him-selfe, is alwayes frosen with feare, and fired with
suspition, hauing that wherein consisteth all his ioy, to be the br
                  •
               eder
of his miserie. Yea, it is such a heauy enemy to that holy estate
of matrimony, sowing betweene the married couples such deadly
seedes of secret hatred, as Loue being once rased out by spightful
distrust, there oft ensueth bloudy reuenge, as this ensuing Hystorie
manifestly prooueth: wherein Pandosto (furiously incensed
by causelesse Iealousie) procured the death of his most loving and
loyall wife, and his owne endlesse sorrow and misery.
            IN the Countrey of Bohemia there raygned a King called
Pandosto, whose fortunate successe in warres against his foes,
and bountifull curtesie towardes his friendes in peace, made him
to be greatly feared and loued of all men. This Pandosto had to
Wife a Ladie called Bellaria, by birth royall, learned by education,
faire by nature, by vertues famous, so that it was hard to
iudge whether her beautie, fortune, or vertue, wanne the greatest

commendations. These two lincked together in perfect loue, led
their liues with such fortunate cōtent, that their Subiects greatly
reioyced to sée their quiet disposition. They had not beene married
long, but Fortune (willing to increase their happines) lent
them a sonne, so adorned with the gifts of nature, as the perfection
of the Childe greatly augmented the loue of the parentes, and
the ioy of their commons: in so much that the Bohemians, to shew
their inward ioyes by outwarde actions, made Bonefires and triumphs
throughout all the Kingdome, appointing Iustes and
Turneyes for the honour of their young Prince: whether resorted
not only his Nobles, but also diuers Kings and Princes which
were his neighbours, willing to shewe their friendship they ought
to Pandosto, and to win fame and glory by their prowesse and valour.
Pandosto, whose minde was fraught with princely liberality,
entertayned the Kings, Princes, and noble men with such submisse
curtesie, and magnifical bounty, that they all sawe how willing
he was to gratifie their good wils, making a generall feast
for his Subiects, which continued by the space of twentie dayes:
all which time the Iustes and Turneys were kept to the great
content both of the Lordes &amp; Ladies there present. This solemne
tryumph being once ended, the assembly taking their leaue of
Pandosto and Bellaria: the young sonne (who was called Garinter)
was nursed vp in the house, to the great ioy and content of the
parents. Fortune enuious of such happy successe, willing to
shewe some signe of her inconstantie, turned her wheele, and darkned
their bright sun of prosperitie, with the mistie cloudes of mishap
and misery. For it so happened that Egistus King of Sycilia,
who in his youth had bene brought vp with Pandosto, desirous to
shewe that neither tracte of time, nor distance of place could diminish
their former friendship, prouided a nauie of ships, and sayled
into Bohemia to visite his old friend and companion, who
hearing of his arriuall, went himselfe in person, and his wife Bellaria,
accompanied with a great traine of Lords and Ladies, to
meete Egistus: and espying him, alighted from his horse, embraced
him very louingly, protesting that nothing in the world
could haue happened more acceptable to him then his comming,
wishing his wife to welcome his olde friend and acquaintance:
who (to shewe how she liked him whom her husband loued) intertayned

him with such familiar curtesie, as Egistus perceiued himselfe
to bée verie well welcome. After they had thus saluted and
embraced eche other, they mounted againe on horsbacke, and rode
toward the Citie, deuising and recounting, howe being children
they had passed their youth in friendely pastimes: where, by the
meanes of the Citizens, Egistus was receyued with triumphs and
showes in such sort, that he maruelled how on so small a warning
they coulde make such preparation. Passing the streetes thus with
such rare sightes, they rode on to the Pallace, where Pandosto entertained
Egistus and his Sycilians with such banqueting and
sumptuous cheare, so royally, as they all had cause to cōmend his
princely liberality, yea, the verie basest slaue that was knowne to
come from Sycilia was vsed with such curtesie, yt 
               Egistus might
easily perceiue how both hee and his were honored for his friendes
sake. Bellaria (who in her time was the flower of curtesie, willing
to shew how vnfaynedly shee looued her husband by his friends intertainemēt,
vsed him likewise so familiarly, that her countenance
bewraied how her minde was affected towardes him: oftentimes
comming her selfe into his bed chamber, to sée that nothing should
be amis to mislike him. This honest familiarity increased dayly
more and more betwixt them: for Bellaria noting in Egistus a
princely and bountifull minde, adorned with sundrie and excellent
qualities, and Egistus finding in her a vertuous and curteous disposition,
there grew such a secret vniting of their affections, that
the one could not well be without the company of the other: in so
much that when Pandosto was busied with such vrgent affaires,
that hee could not bee present with his friend Egistus, Bellaria
would walke with him into the Garden, where they two in priuat
and pleasant deuises would passe away the time to both their contents.
This custome still continuing betwixt them, a certaine melancholy
passion entring the minde of Pandosto, draue him into
sundry and doubtfull thoughts. First, he called to minde the beauty
of his wife Bellaria, the comelines and brauerie of his friend
Egistus, thinking that Loue was aboue all Lawes, and therefore
to be staied with no Law: that it was hard to put fire and flaxe together
without burning: that their open pleasures might breede
his secrete displeasures. He considered with himselfe that Egistus
was a man, and must needes loue: that his wife was a woman,

and therfore subiect vnto loue, and that where fancy forced, friendship
was of no force. These and such like doubtfull thoughtes a
long time smoothering in his stomacke, beganne at last to kindle in
his minde a secret mistrust, which increased by suspition, grewe at
last to a flaming Iealousie, that so tormented him as he could take
no rest. He then began to measure all their actions, and to miscenstrue
of their too priuate familiaritie, iudging that it was not for
honest affection, but for disordinate fancy, so that hee began to
watch them more narrowely, to sée if hée could gette any true or
certaine proofe to confirme his doubtfull suspition. While thus he
noted their lookes and gestures, and suspected their thoughtes and
meaninges, they two séely soules who doubted nothing of this his
treacherous intent, frequēted daily eache others companie, which
draue him into such a franticke passion, that he beganne to beare a
secret hate to Egistus, and a lowring countenaunce to Bellaria,
who marueiling at such vnaccustomed frowns, began to cast béeyond
the Moone, and to enter into a thousand sundrie thoughtes,
which way she should offend her husband: but finding in her selfe a
cleare cōscience, ceassed to muse, vntil such time as she might find
fit opportunitie to demaund the cause of his dumps. In the meane
time Pandostoes minde was so farre charged with Iealousy, that
he did no longer doubt, but was assu
                  ••
               ed (as he thought) that his
Friend Egistus had entered a wrong pointe in his tables, and so
had played him false play: whervpō desirous to reuenge so great
an iniury, he thought best to dissemble the grudge with a faire and
friendly countenance: and so vnder the shape of a friend, to shew
him the tricke of a foe. Deuising with himself a long time how he
might best put away Egistus without suspition of treacherous
murder, hee concluded at last to poyson him: which opinion pleasing
his humour, he became resolute in his determination, and the
better to bring the matter to passe he called vnto him his cupbearer,
with whom in secret he brake the matter: promising to him for
the performance thereof, to geue him a thowsande crownes of
yearely reuenues: his cupbearer eyther being of a good conscience,
or willing for fashion sake, to deny such a bloudy request, began
with great reasons to perswade Pandosto from his determinate
mischief: shewing him what an offence murther was to the Gods:
how such vnnaturall actions did more displease the heauens, than

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
               deuoide of pity, commanded that without delay it should bee put
in the boat, hauing neither saile nor other to guid it, and so to bee
carried into the midst of the sea, and there left to the wind &amp; waue
as the destinies please to appoint. The very shipmen seeing the
sweete countenance of the yong babe, began to accuse the King of
rigor, and to pity the childs hard fortune: but feare constrayned
them to that which their nature did abhorre: so that they placed it
in one of the ends of the boat, and with a few greene bows made a
homely cabben to shroud it as they could from wind and weather:
hauing thus trimmed the boat they tied it to a ship, and so haled it
into the mayne Sea, and then cut in sunder the coarde, which they
had no sooner done, but there arose a mighty tempest, which tossed
the little Boate so vehemently in the waues, that the shipmen
thought it coulde not continue longe without sincking, yea the
storme grewe so great, that with much labour and perill they got
to the shoare. But leauing the Childe to her fortunes. Againe to
Pandosto, who not yet glutted with sufficient reuenge, deuised
which way he should best increase his Wiues calamitie. But first
assembling his Nobles and Counsellors, hee called her for the
more reproch into open Court, where it was obiected against her,
that she had committed adulterie with Egistus, and conspired with
Franion to poyson Pondosto her husband, but their pretence being
partely spyed, shee counselled them to flie away by night for
their better safety. Bellaria, who standing like a prisoner at the
Barre, feeling in her selfe a cleare Conscience to withstand her
false accusers: seeing that no lesse then death could pacifie her husbands
wrath, waxed bolde, and desired that she might haue Lawe
and Iustice, for mercy shee neyther craued nor hoped for, and that
those periured wretches, which had falsly accused her to the King,
might be brought before her face, to giue in euidence. But Pandosto,
whose rage and Iealousie was such, as no reason, nor equitie
could appease: tolde her, that for her accusers they were of such
credite, as their wordes were sufficient witnesse, and that the sodaine
&amp; secret flight of Egistus, &amp; Franion confirmed that which
they had confessed: and as for her, it was her parte to deny such a
monstrus crime, and to be impudent in forswearing the fact, since
shee had past all shame in committing the fault: but her stale
countenaunce should stand for no coyne, for as the Bastard which

she bare was serued, so she should with some cruell death be requited.
Bellaria no whit dismayed with this rough reply 
                  •
                tolde her
Husband Pandosto, that he spake vpon choller
                  •
               , and not con
                  ••••
               
               ence:
for her vertuous life had beene euer such, as no spot of suspition
could euer staine. And if she had borne a frendly countedaunce
to Egistus, it was in respect he was his friende, and not
for any lusting affection: therefore if she were condemned without
a
                  •
               y further proofe, it was rigour, and not Law. The noble
men which sate in iudgement, said that Bellaria spake reason, and
intreated the king that the accusers might be openly examined,
and sworne, and if then the euidence were such, as the Iury might
finde her guilty (for seeing she was a Prince) she ought to be 
                  •
               ryed
by her péeres, then let her haue such punishment as the extremitie
of the Law will assigne to such malefactors. The king presently
made answere, that in this case he might, and would dispence
with the Law, and that the Iury being once panneld, they
should take his word for sufficient euidence, otherwise he would
make the proudest of them repent it. The noble men séeing the
king in choler, were all whist, but Bellaria, whose life then hung
in the ballaunce, fearing more perpetuall in famie, then momentarie
death, tolde the king
                  •
                if his furie might stand for a Law, that
it were vaine to haue the Iury yéeld their verdit, and therefore
she fell downe vpon her knées, and desired the king that for the
loue he hare to his young sonne Garinter, whome she brought
into the world, that hee woulde graunt her a request, which was
this, that it would please his maiestie to send sixe of his noble men
whome he best trusted, to the Isle of Delphos, there to enquire
of the Oracle of Apollo, whether she had committed adultery
with Egistus, or conspired to poyson him with Franion: and if
the God Apollo, who by his deuine essence knew al secrets, gaue
answere that she was guiltie, she were content to suffer any torment,
were it neuer so terrible. The request was so reasonable,
that Pandosto could not for shame deny it, vnlesse he woulde d
                  •
               e
counted of all his subiects more wilfull then wise, he therefore agréed,
that with as much speede as might be there should be certaine
Embassadores dispat
                  ••
               ed to the Ile of Delphost 
               
                  ••
               d in the
meane season be commanded that his wife should be kept in close
prison. Bellaria hauing obtained this graunt, was now more

carefull for her little babe that floated 
                  ••
                the Seas, then 
                  •••••
               |
full for her owne mishap. For of that she doubted: of her selfe shee
was assured, knowing if Apollo should giue Oracle according to
the thoughts of the hart, yet the sentence should goe one her sid
                  •
               ,
such was the clearenes of her minde in this case. But Pandosto
(whose suspitious head still remained in one song) chose out six of
his Nobility, whom hee knew were scarse indifferent men in the
Quéenes behalfe, and prouiding all things fit for their iourney,
sent them to Delphos: they willing to fulfill the Kinges commaund,
and desirous to see the situation and custome of the Iland,
dispatched their affaires with as much spéede as might be, and embarked
themselues to this voyage, which ( the wind and weather
seruing fit for their purpose) was soone ended. For within three
weekes they arriued at Delphos, where they were no sooner set
on lande, but with great deuotion they went to the Temple of Apollo,
and there offring sacrifice to the GOD, and giftes to the
Priest, as the custome was, they humbly craued an aunswere of
their demaund: they had not long kneeled at the Altar, but Apollo
with a loude voice saide: Bohemians, what you finde behinde
the Alter take, and depart. They forthwith obeying the Oracle
founde a scroule of parchment, wherein was written these words
in letters of Golde.
            
               
                  
                     
                        The Oracle.
                        SVspition is no proofe: Iealousie is an vnequall Iudge:
Bellaria is chast: Egistus blamelesse: Franion a true
subiect: Pandosto treacherous: his Babe an innocent,
and the King shal liue without an heire: if that which
is lost be not founde.
                     
                  
               
            
            AS soone as they had taken out this scroule, the Priest of the
God commaunded them that they should not presume to read
it, before they came in the presēce of Pandosto: vnlesse they would
incurre the displeasure of Apollo. The Bohemian Lords carefully
obeying his commaund, taking their leaue of the Priest,
with great reuerence departed out of the Temple, and went 
                  ••
               
their ships, and assoone as wind would permit them sailed toward

               Bohemia, whither in short time they safely arriued, &amp; with great
tryumph issuing out of their Ships, went to the Kinges pall
                  ••
               e,
whom they found in his chamber accompanied with other Noble
men: Pandosto no sooner saw them, but with a merrie countenaunce
he welcomed them home, as king what newes: they tolde
his Maiestie that they had receiued an aunswere of the God written
in a scroule, b
                  •
               t with this charge, yt they should not reade the
contents before they came in the presence of the King, and with
that they deliuered him the parchment: but his Noble men intreated
him that sith therein was contayned either the safetie of his
Wiues life, and honestly, or her death, and perpetuall infamy, that
he would haue his Nobles and Commons assembled in the iudgement
Hall, where the Queene brought in as prysoner, should
heare the contents: if shee were found guilty by the Oracle of the
God, then all should haue cause to thinke his rigour proceeded of
due desert: if her Grace were found faultlesse, then shee should bee
cleared before all, sith she had bene accused openly. This pleased
the King so, that he appointed the day, and assembled al his Lords
and Commons, and caused the Quéene to be brought in before the
Iudgement seate, commaunding that the inditement shoulde bee
read, wherein she was accused of adultery with Egistus, and of
conspiracy with Franion: Bellaria hearing the contentes, was
no whit astonished, but made this chearefull aunswer.
            IF the deuine powers bee priuy to humane actions (as no doubt
they are) I hope my patience shall make fortune blushe, and my
vnspotted life shall staine spightfully discredit. For although lying
Report hath sought to appeach mine honor, and Suspition hath
intended to soyle my credit with infamie: yet where Uertue keepeth
the Forte, Report and suspition may assayle, but neuer sack:
how I haue led my life before Egistus comming, I appeale Pandosto
to the Gods, &amp; to thy conscience. What hath passed betwixt
him and me, the Gods onely know, and I hope will presently reueale:
that I loued Egistus I can not denie, that I honored him
I shame not to confesse: to the one I was forced by his vertues: to
the other for his dignities. But as touching lasci
                  ••••
               s lust, I say
Egistus is honest, and hope my selfe to be found without spot: for
Franion. I can neither accuse him, nor excuse him: for I was not

priuie to his departure, and that this is true which I haue heere
rehearsed, I referre my selfe to the deuine Oracle.
            
               BEllaria had no sooner sayd, but the King commaunded that one
of his Dukes should reade the contentes of the scroule: which
after the commons had heard, they gaue a great showt, reioysing
and clapping their hands that the Quéene was cleare of that false
accusation: but the King whose conscience was a witnesse against
him of his witlesse furie, and false suspected Iealousle, was so ashamed
of his rashe folly, that he intreated his nobles to perswade
Bellaria to forgiue, and forget these iniuries: promising not onely
to shew himselfe a loyall and louing husband, but also to reconcile
himselfe to Egistus, and Franion: reuealing then before
them all the cause of their secrete flighte, and how treacherously
hee thought to haue practised his death, if the good minde of his
Cupbearer had not preuented his purpose. As thus he was relating
the whole matter, there was worde brought him that his
young sonne Garinter was sodainly dead, which newes so soone
as Bellaria heard, surcharged before which extreame ioy, and now
suppressed with heauie sorrowe, her vitall spirites were so stopped,
that she fell downe presently dead, &amp; could be neuer reuiued. This
sodaine sight so appalled the Kinges Sences, that he sanck from
his seate in a soūd so as he was fayne to be carried by his nobles
to his Pallace, where hee lay by the space of three dayes without
speache: his commons were as men in dispaire, so diuersly 
                  •••
               
               sed:
there was nothing but mourning and lamentation to be heard
throughout al Bohemia: their young Prince dead, their vertuous
Queene bereaued of her life, and their King and Soueraigne in
great hazard: this tragicall discourse of fortune so daunted them,
as they went like shadowes, not men: yet somewhat to comfort
their heauie hearts, they heard that Pandosto was come to himselfe,
and had recouered his speache, who as in a fury brayed out
these bitter speaches.
            O Miserable Pandosto, what surer witnesse then conscience?
What thoughts more sower then suspition? What plague
more bad then Iealousie? Unnaturall actions offend the Gods,
more than men, and causelesse crueltie, neuer scapes without reuenge:

               
                  〈…〉
               
recall I cannot 
                  〈…〉
               
the conscience, suppressing reason, and inciting rage: a worse passion
then phrensie, a greater plague than madnesse. Are the Gods
iust: Then let them reuenge such brutishe crueltie: my innocent
Babe I haue drowned in the Seas: my louing wife I haue slaine
with slaunderous suspition: my trusty friend I haue sought to betray,
and yet the Gods are slacke to plague such offences. Oh vniust
Apollo, Pandosto is the man that hath committed the faulte:
why should Garinter, séely childe, abide the paine: Well sith the
Gods meane to prolong my dayes, to increase my dolour, I will
offer my guiltie bloud a sacrifice to those sackles soules, whose
liues are lost by my rigorous folly. And with that he reached at a
Rapier, to haue murdered himselfe, but his Péeres being present,
stayed him from such a bloudy acte: perswading him to think, that
the Common-wealth consisted on his safetie, and that those shéepe
could not but perish, that wanted a shéepheard: wishing, that if hée
would not liue for himselfe, yet he should haue care of his subiects,
and to put such fancies out of his minde, sith in sores past h
                  •
               lp,
salues doe not heale, but hurt
                  •
               nd in thinges past c
                  •
               re, care is a

                  ••
               rāsiue: with these and such like perswasions the Kinge was ouercome,
and began somewhat to quiet his minde: so that assoo
                  •
               e
as h
                  ••
                could goe abroad, hée caused his wife to bée embalmed, and
wrapt in lead with her young sonne Garinter: erecting a rich an
                  •
               
famous Sepulchre, wherein hée intombed them both, making
such sollenme obsequies at her funeral, as al Bohemia might perceiue
he did greatly repent him of his forepassed folly: causing this
Epitaph to be ingrauen on her Tombe in letters of Golde:
            
               ¶The Epitaph.
               Here lyes entombde Bellaria faire,
               Falsly accused to be vnchaste:
               Cleared by Apollos sacred doome,
               Yet slaine by Iealousie at last.
            
            
               What ere thou be, that passest by,
               Cursse him that causde this Q
                     •
                  eene to die
            
            
               THis Epitaph being ingr
                  •
               uen, Pandosto would once a-day repaire
to the Tombe, and there with watry plaintes bewaile
his misfortune: coueting no other companion but sorrowe, nor no
other harmonie, but re
                  •
               entance. But leauing him to his dolorous
passions, at last let vs come to shewe the tragicall discourse of the
young infant.
            WHo béeing tossed with Winde, and Waue, floated two
whole daies without succour, readie at euery puffe to bée
drowned in the Sea, till at last the Tempest ceassed, and the little
boate was driuen with the tyde into the Coast of Sycilia, where
sticking vppon the sandes, it rested. Fortune minding to be wanton,
willing to shewe that as she hath wrinckles on her 
                  ••
               owes: so
shée hath dimplés in her chéekes: thought after so many sower
lookes, to lend a fayned smile, and after a puffing storme, to bring
a pretty calme: shee began thus to dally. It fortuned a poore mercenary
Shéepheard, that dwelled in Sycilia, who got his liuing by
other mens flockes, missed one of his shéepe, and thinking it had
stra
                  •
               ed into the cou
                  •
               rt, that was hard by, sought very diligently
to 
                  •
               ind that which he could not see, fearing either that the Wolues,
or Eagles had vndone him (for hée was so poore, as a shéepe was
halfe his substaunce) wandered downe toward the Sea cliffes, to
sée if pl
                  •
               chaunce the shéepe was browsing on the sea Iu
                  •
               , whereon
the
                  •
                
               
                  •
               reatly doe féede, but not finding her there, as he was ready
to returne to his flocke, hée heard a childe crie: but knowing
there was no house nere, he thought he had mistakē ye sound, &amp; yt it
was the ble
                  ••
               yng of his Shéepe. Wherefore looking more narrowely,
as he cast his eye to the Sea, he spyed a little boate, from
whence as he attentiuely listened, he might heare the cry to come:
standing a good while in a maze, at last he went to the shoare, and
wading to the boate, as he looked in, he saw the little babe lying al
alone, many to die for hunger and colde, wrapped in a Mantle of
Scarlet, richely imbrodered with Golde, and hauing a chayne about
the necke. The Shéepeheard, who before had neuer séene so
faire a Babe, not so riche Iewels, thought assuredly, that it was
some little God, and began with great deuocion to knock on his
breast. The Babe, who wrythed with ye head, to seeke for the pay,
began againe to cry afresh, whereby the poore man knew that it

was a Childe, which by some sinister meanes was driuen thither
by distresse of weather: maruailing how such a seely infant, which
by the Mantle, and the Chayne, could not be but borne of Noble
Parentage, should be so hardly crossed with deadly mishap. The
poore sheepheard perplexed thus with diuers thoughts, tooke pitty
of the childe, and determined with himselfe to carry it to the
King, that there it might be brought vp, according to the worthinesse
of birth: for his ability coulde not afforde to foster it, though
his good minde was willing to further it. Taking therefore the
Chylde in his armes, as he foulded the mantle together, the better
to defend if from colde, there fell downe at his foote a very faire
and riche purse, wherein he founde a great summe of golde: which
sight so reuiued the shepheards spirits, as he was greatly rauished
with ioy, and daunted with feare: Ioyfull to see such a summe in
his power, and fearefull if it should be knowne, that it might bréede
his further daunger. Necessitie wisht him at the least, to retaine
the Golde, though he would not kéepe the childe: the simplicity
if his conscience feared him from such deceiptfull briberie. Thus
was the poore manne perplexed with a doubtfull Dilemma, vntil
at last the couetousnesse of the coyne ouercame him: for what
will not the gréedy desire of Golde cause a man to doe? So that
he was resolued in himselfe to foster the child, and with the summe
to relieue his want: resting thus resolute in this point, he left séeking
of his shéepe, and as couertly, and secretly as he coulde, went
by a by-way to his house, least any of his neighbours should perceaue
his carriage: assoone as he was got home, entring in at the
doore, the childe began to crie, which his wife hearing, and séeing
her husband with a yong babe in his armes, began to bée somewhat
ielousse, yet marueiling that her husband should be so wanton
abroad, sith he was so quiet at home: but as women are naturally
giuen to beléeue the worste, so his wife thinking it was some
bastard: beganne to crow against her goodman, and taking vp a
c
                  ••
               gel (for the most maister went bréethles) sware solenmly that
shee would make clubs trumps, if hee brought any bastard brat
within her dores. The goodman seeing his wife in her maiestie
with her mate in her hand, thought it was time to bowe for 
                  •
               eare
of blowes, &amp; desired her to be quiet, for there was non such matter:
but if she could holde her peace, they were made for euen and with

that he told her the whole matter, how he had found the childe
in a little boat, without any succ
                  ••
               r, wrapped in that costly
mantle, and hauing that rich chain
                  •
                about the neck: but at last
when he shewed her the purse full of gold, she began to simper
something swéetely, and taking her husband about the neck,
kissed him after her homely fashion: saying that she hoped God
had séene their want, and now ment to reliéeue their pouerty,
and séeing they could get no children, had sent them this little
babe to be their heire. Take héede in any case (quoth the shepherd)
that you be secret, and blabbe it not out when you méete
with your gossippes, for if you doe, we are like not only to
loose the Golde and Iewels, but our other goodes and liues.
Tush (quoth his wife) profit is a good hatch before the doore:
feare not, I haue other things to talke of then of this: but I
pray you let vs lay vp the money surely, and the Iewels, least
by any mishap it be spied. After that they had set all things in
order, the shepheard went to his shéepe with a merry note, and
the good wife learned to sing lull
                  •
               by at home with her yong
babe, wrapping it in a homely blanket in sted of a rich mantle:
nourishing in so clenly and carefully as it began to bee a iolly
girle, in so much that they began both of them to be very fond
of it, séeing, as it waxed in age, so it increased in beauty. The
shepheard euery night at his comming home, would sing and
daunce it on his knée, and prattle, that in a short time it began
to speake and call him Dad, and her Mam: at last when
it grew to ripe yeeres, that it was about seuen yeares olde,
the shepheard lest keeping of other mens sheepe, and with the
money he found in the purse, he bought him the lease of a pretty
farme, and got a smal flocke of shéepe, which when Fawnia
(for so they named the child) came to the age of ten yeres, hee
set her to keepe, and shee with such diligence performed her
charge as the sheepe prospered marueilously vnder her hand.
Fawnia thought Porrus had ben her father, and Mopsa her
mother, (for so was the shepheard and his wife called (honoured
and obeyed them with such reuerence, that all the neighbours
praised the du
                  •
               tifully obedience of the child. Porrus
grewe in short time to bee a man of some wealth, and cre
                  •
               ite:
for fortune so fauoured him in hauing no charge but Fawnia,
               
that he began to purchase land, intending after
                  〈…〉
               
giue it to his daughter: so that diuerse rich farmer
                  •
                sonne
                  •
               
came as wo
                  •
               rs to his house
                  •
                for Fawnia was something 
                  •••
               
               ly
attired, beeing of such singular beautie and excellent 
                  ••
               te,
that whoso sawe her, would 
                  •
                thought, shee had bene some
heauenly nymph, and not a mortal creature: in so much, that
when she came to the age of six
                  •
                yeeres, shee so increased
with exquisite perfe
                  •
               tion both of body and minde, as her natural
disposition did bewray that she was borne of some high parentage:
but the people thinking she was daughter to the shephard
Porrus; tested only amazed at hir beauty and 
                  •
               e: yea
she won such fauour and commendations in euery mans eye,
as her beautie was not onely praysed in the countrey, but also
spoken of in the Court: yet such was her submisse modestie,
that although her praise daily increased, her mind was no whit
puffed vp with pride, but humbled her selfe as became a country
mayde and the daughter of a poore sheepheard. E
                  ••
               ry day
she went forth with her sheepe to the field, keeping them with
such care and diligence, as al men thought she was verie painfull,
defending her face from the heat of the sunne with
                  •••
                other
vale, but with a garland made of bowes and flowers:
which atire became her so gallantly, as shee seemed to bee the
Goddesse Flora her selfe for beauty 
                  •
                Fortune, wh
                  •
                al this
while had shewed a frendly face, began now to turne her back,
and to shewe a lowring countenance, intending as she had giuen
Fawnia a flenderchecke, so she woulde g
                  •••
                her a harder
mate: to bring which to passe, she layd her trains on this wise.
Egistus had but one only son called Dorastus, aboue ye age of
twenty yeeres: a Prince so decked and adorned with the
gifts of nature: so fraught with beauty and vertuous qualities,
as not onely his father ioyed to haue so goode a sonne, 
                  •
                al
his commons reioyced that God had lent them such a noble
Prince to succeede in the Kingdom. Egistus placing all his
ioy in the perfection of his sonne: seeing that hee was now mariage-able,
sent Embassadors to the King of Denmarke, to
intreate a mari
                  •
               ge betweene him and his daughter, who willingly
consenting, made answer, that the 
                  〈…〉
                please
Egistus with his sonne to come into Denmarke, hee doubted

not, but they shoulde agrée vpon reasonable conditions. Egistus
resting satisfied with this friendly answer, thought conuenient
in the meane time to breake with his sonne: finding
therfore on a day fit oportunity he spake to him in these fatherly
tearmes.
            
               DOrastus, thy youth warneth me to preuent the worst, and
mine age to prouide the best. Oportunities neglected, are
signes of folly: actions measured by time, are seldome bitten
with repentance: thou art young, and I olde: age hath taught
me that, which thy youth cannot yet conceiue.
            I therefore will counsell thee as a father, hoping thou wilt
obey as a childe. Thou séest my white hayres are blossomes
for the graue, and thy freshe colour fruite for time and fortune,
so that it behooueth me to thinke how to dye, and for thée
to care how to liue. My crowne I must leaue by death, and
thou enioy my Kingdome by succession, wherein I hope thy
vertue and prowesse shall bee such, as though my subiectes
want my person, yet they shall see in thee my perfection. That
nothing either may faile to satisfie thy minde, or increase thy
dignities: the onely care I haue, is to see thee well marryed
before I die, and thou become olde.
            
               Dorastus who from his infancy, delighted rather to die
with Mars in the Fielde, then to dally with Venus in the
Chamber: fearing to displease his father, and yet not willing
to be wed, made him this reuerent answere.
            SIr, there is no greater bond then duetie, nor no straiter law
then nature: disobedience in youth is often galled with despight
in age. The commaund of the father ought to be a constraint
to the childe: so parentes willes are laws, so they passe
not all lawes: may it please your Grace therefore to appoint
whome I shall loue, rather then by deniall I should be appeached
of 
                  〈…〉
               re:I rest content to loue, though it bee the
only thing I hate.
            Egistus hearing his sonne to 
                  〈◊〉
                from the 
                  〈◊〉
               , began to be somewhat chollericke, another 
                  〈…〉
               .
            
               WHat Dorastus canst thou not 
                  〈…〉
               
cynicall passion of pr
                  •
               ne de
                  ••
               res, or p
                  ••
               uish 
                  •••
               
               wardnesse.
What dorst thou thinke thy selfe to
good for all, or none good inough for thee: I tel thee, Dorastus,
there is nothing sweeter then youth, nor swifter decreasing,
while it is increasing. Time past with folly may bee
repented, but not recalled. If thou marrie in age, thy w
                  •••
               es
freshe couloures will breede in thee dead thoughtes and suspicion,
and thy white hayres her lothe somnesse and sorrowe. For
Venus affections are not fed with Kingdomes, or treasures,
but with youthfull conceits and sweete amours. Vulcan was
allotted to shake the tree, but Mars allowed to reape the fruit.
Yeelde Dorastus to thy Fathers perswasions, which may
preuent thy perils. I haue chosen thee a Wife, faire by nature,
royall by birth, by vertues famous, learned by education, and
rich by possessiōs, so that it is hard to iudge whether her bounty,
or fortune, her beauty, or vertue, bee of greater force: I
mean
                  •
                
               Dorastus, Euphania Daughter and h
                  •
               ire to the King
of Denmarke.
            
            
               EGistus pausing here a while, looking when his son should
make him answere, and seeing that he stoode still as one in
a trance, he shooke him vp thus sharply.
            WEll Dorastus take he
                  •
               de, the tree Alpya wasteth not
with fire, but withereth with the dewe: that which loue
nourisheth not, perisheth with hate: if thou like Euphania, thou
breedest my content, and in louing her thou shalt haue my
loue
                  •
                otherwise; and with that hee flung from his sonne in a
race leauing him a sorrowfullman, in that he had by deniall
displeased his Father, and halfe angrie with him selfe that hee
coulde not yeelde to that passion, whereto both reason and his
Father perswaded him: but see how fortune is plumed with
times feathers, and 
                  •
               ow shee can minister st
                  ••••
               ge causes to
breede straunge effectes.
            It happened not long 
                  •
               fter this that 
                  〈…〉
               ng of all the farmers D
                  •••
               hters 
                  〈…〉
                whither F
                  •••••
                was also bidden as the mistres of the feast, who 
                  〈…〉
               
               
her selfe, in her best garments, went among the rest of her companions
to the merry meeting
                  •
                there spending the day in such
homely pastimes as shephea
                  ••
               s vse. As the euening grew on,
and their sportes ceased, ech taking their leaue at other, Fawnia
desiring one of her companions to beare her companie,
went home by the flocke, 
                  •
               o see if they were well folded,
and as they returned, it fortuned that Dorastus (who all that
daye had bene hawking, and 
                  •••
               de store of game) incountred
by the way these two mayds, and casting his eye sodenly on
Fawnia he was halfe afraid, fearing that with Acteon he had
seene Diana, for hee thought such 
                  ••
               uisite perfection could
not be founde many mortall creature. As thus he stoode in 
                  •
                maze, one of his Pages told him, that the maide with the garland
on her head was Fawnia the faire shepheard, whose beauty
was so much talked of in the Court. Dorastus desirous to
see if nature had adorned her minde with any inward qualities,
as she had decked her body with outward shape began
to question with her whose daughter she was of what age and
how she had but trained vp, who answered him with such madess
reuerence and sharpnesse of witte, that Dorastus thought
her outward beautie was but a counterfait to darken her inward
qualities, wondring how so courtly behauiour could be
found in so simple a cottage, and cursing fortune that had shadowed
wit and beauty with such hard fortune. As thus he held
her a long whise with that. Beauty seeing him at discouer
                  •
               
thaught not to lose the 
                  ••
               tage, but strooke him in deepely
with an inuenomed shafte, as he wholy lost his libertie, and became
a slaue to Loue, which before containned Loue, glad now
to gaze on a p
                  •
               ore shephea
                  •
               d, who before refused the offer of a
riche Princesse: for the perfection of Fawnia had so fi
                  •
               ed his
fancie as he felt his mind greatly chaunged, and his affections
altered, cursing Loue that had wrought such a chaun
                  •
               e, and
blaming the basenesse of his mind that would make such a
choice
                  •
                but thinking these were but passion
                  〈7 letters〉
                that migh
                  •
                be thrust out at pleasure to auoid the Syren that inchaunted him 
                  〈…〉
                his horse and had this f
                  〈…〉
               
            
            Fawnia (who all this while had marked the 
                  〈…〉
               
               
of Dorastus) seeing his face 
                  〈◊◊◊〉
                and each time
so perfectly frame
                  •
               , began greatly to praise his perfection,
commending him so long, till she found her sel
                  •
               e faultie, and
perceiued that if she waded but a little further, she might slippe
ouer her shooes: shee therefore seeking to quench that fire which neuer was put out, went home, and 
                  •••
               n
                  •
               ing her selfe not
well at ease, got her to bed
                  •
                where casting a 
                  ••
               sand thoughts
in her head, she could take no rest: for if she wake
                  •
               , she begā to
call to minde his beautie, and thinking to beguile such
thoughts with 
                  ••
               eepe, 
                  •
               he 
                  ••
               en dreamed of his perfection: pestred
thus with these vnacquainted passions, she passed the night
as she could in short 
                  ••
               umbers.
            
               Dorastus (who all this while rode with a flea in his eare)
coulde not by any meanes forget the sweete fauour of Fawnia,
but rested 
                  •
               o bewitched with her wit and beauty, as hee could
take no rest. He felt fancy to giue the a
                  ••
               ault, and his wounded
mind reap
                  ••
               te to yeeld as vanquished: yet he began with diuers

                  •
               on
                  ••••
               rations to suppresse this frantick affecti
                  ••
                ca
                  ••
               ing to minde, that Fawnia was a 
                  •
               heph
                  •
               ard, one not worthy to bee 
                  〈◊〉
                at of a Prince, much lesse to bee loued of such a potentate thinking what a discredite it were to himselfe, and what a griefe it would be to his father, blaming fortune and acc
                  ••••
               ng his owne 
                  〈◊〉
                that shoulde bee so fond as but once to 
                  •
               ast a gla
                  〈…〉
               .  As thus he was raging against 
                  ••
               mselfe, Loue fearing if shee dallied long, to 
                  〈…〉
               ept more nigh, and gaue him such a fresh wounde as it pra
                  ••
               t him at the heart, that he was faine to yeeld, maugre his 
                  •
               a
                  •
                   e, and to forsake the companie and gette him to his chamber: where being solemnly set, hee burst into these passionate 
                  ••
               armes.
            "Ah Dorastus, art tho
                  •
                alone?  No not alone, wosste t
                  •
               o
                  •
                art tired with these vnacquainted passions.  Yeld to fancy, thou can
                  ••
                not by thy fathers coun
                  ••••
               e, but in a frenzie t
                  •
               o
                  •
                art by 
                  〈◊◊〉
               .  THy father were content 
                  〈…〉
               
               
               
                  •••
               
               
by reason without Lawe
                  •
                and therefore aboue all Law.
            How now Dorastus, why 
                  •••
                thou blaze that with maises,
which thou hast cause to blaspheme with curses. Yet why
should they curse Loue that are in Loue:
            Blush Dorastus at thy fortune, thy choice, thy loue: thy
thou
                  •
                
               
                  ••
               s cannot be vttered without shame, nor thy affections
without discredit. Ah Fawnia, sweete Fawnia, thy beautie
Fawnia.
            
            Shamest not thou Dorastus to name, one vnfitte for thy
birth, thy dignities, thy Kingdomes? Dye Dorastus, Dorastus
die, better hadst thou perish with high desires, then liue in
base thoughts. Yea but, beautie must be obeyed because it is
beauty, yet framed of the Gods to feede the eye, not to fatter
the heart.
            Ah but he that striueth against Loue, shooteth with them of
Scyrum against the winde, and with the Cockeatrice pecketh
against the steele. I will therefore obey, becaue I must obey.
Fawnia, yea Fawnia shal be my fortune, in spight of fortune.
The Gods aboue disdain not to loue womē beneath. Pho
                     •
                  bus
liked Sibilla, Iupiter Io, and why not I then Fawnia, one
something inferiour to these in birth, but farre superiour to
them in beautie, horne to be a Shepheard, but worthy to be a
Goddesse.
            Ah Dorastus, wilt thou so forget thy selfe as to suffer affection
to suppresse wisedome, and Loue to violate thine hononour?
How sower will thy choice be to thy Father, for
                  •••
               
               full
to thy Subiects, to thy friends a griefe, most gladsome
to thy foes? Subdue then thy affections, and seaseto loue her
whome thou couldest not loue, vnlesse blinded with too much
loue. Tushe I talke to the wind, and in seeking to preuent the
causes. I further the effectes. I will yet praise Fawnia, honour,
yea and loue Fawnia, and at this day followe content,
not counsaile. D
                  ••
                
               Dorastus, thou canst but repent: and with
that his Page came into the chamber, whereupon hee ceased
from his complaints houing that time would weare out that,
which fo
                  ••
               une had wrought. As thus he was pained, so poore
Fawnia 
               
                  〈◊〉
                diuersly perplexed: for the next morning gett
                  •••
               
               
                  〈◊〉
                very earely, shee went to her sheepe, thinking with

hard 
                  〈◊〉
                to passe 
                  〈◊〉
                her 
                  〈…〉
               
(poore soule) she was more tryed with 
                  〈…〉
               
beganne to assault her, in so much 
                  〈◊〉
                as she 
                  〈◊〉
                vpon the side
of a hill, she began to accuse her o
                  ••
               e folly in these 
                  〈◊〉
               .
            INfortunate Fawnia, and therefore infortunate because
Fawnia, thy shepherds hooke sheweth thy poore 
                  〈◊〉
               , thy
proud desires an aspiring mind: the one declareth thy 
                  〈◊〉
               ,
the other thy pride. No bastard hauke must so
                  •
               re so hie as the
Hobbie, 
                  •
               o Fowle gaze against the Sunne but the Eagle,

                  〈◊〉
                wrought against nature reape despight, and 
                  〈◊◊〉
               
aboue Fortune disdaine.
            
               Fawnia, thou art a shepheard, daughter to poore Porrus: if
thou rest content with this, thou art like to stande, if thou
climbe thou art sure to fal. The Herb Anita growing higher

                  〈…〉
                weede. Nylus flodding more then twelue cubits procureth a dearth. Daring affect
                  •••
                that
passe measure, ar
                  •
                cut shorte by time or fortune: suppresse then
Fawnia those thoughes which thou 
                  〈◊〉
                to expresse.
But 
                  ••
                
               Fawnia, loue is a Lord, who will comm
                  •••
                by power,
and constraine by force.
            
               Dorastus, a
                  •
                
               Dorastus is the man I loue, the woor
                  •
               e is thy

                  〈◊◊〉
                the lesse 
                  〈◊〉
                hast thou to hope. Will Eagles catch

                  〈◊◊〉
               ; will Cedars stoupe to be brambles, or mighty Princes

                  •••••
                at such homely tru
                  ••
               es. No, no, thinke this, Dorastus
               
                  〈…〉
               , hee is a Prince respecting
his 
                  〈◊〉
               , thou a beggars brat forgetting thy calling. Cease
then not onely to say, but to thinke to loue Dorastus, and dissemble
thy loue Fawnia, for better it were to dye with griefe,
then to liue with shame: yet in despight of loue I will sigh, to
see if I can sigh out loue. Fawnia somewhat appea
                  ••
                her
griefes with these pithie perswa
                  •••
               s, began after her 
                  〈◊〉
               
manner to walke about her shéepe, and to 
                  〈…〉
               
               
the very ve
                  ••
               inies did deny herto 
                  ••
               erine.
            But Dorastus was more impatient in his passions: for
loue so fiercely assayled him, that neither companie, nor musicke
could mittigate his martirdome, but did rather far
the more increase his maladie: shame would not let him craue
counsaile in this case, nor feare of his Fathers displeasure reueyle
it to any secrete friend: but hee was saine to make a Secretarie
of himselfe, and to participate his thoughtes with his
owne troubled mind. Lingring thus awhile in doubtfull suspence,
at last stealing secretely from the court without either
men or Page, hée went to sée if hée coulde espie Fawnia walking
abroade in the field: but as one hauing a great deale more
skill to retriue the partridge with his spaniels, then to hunt
after such a straunge pray, he sought, but was little the better:
which crosse lucke draue him into a great choler, that he began
both to accuse loue and fortune. But as he was readie to
retire, he sawe Fawnia sitting all alone vnder the side of a hill,
making a garland of such homely flowres as the fields did
afoord. This sight so reuiued his spirites that he drewe nigh,
with more iudgement to take a view of her singular perfection,
which hée found to bée such, as in that countrey attyre shée
stained al the courtlie Dames of Sicilia. While thus he stoode
gazing with pearcing lookes on her surpassing beautie,
Fawnia cast her eye aside, and spyed Dorastus, with sudden
fight made the poore girle to blush, and to die her christal chéeks
with a vermilion red: which gaue her such a grace, as she séemed
farre more beautiful. And with that she rose vp, saluting
the Prince with such modest curtesies, as he wondred how a
country maid could afoord such courtly behauiour. Dorastus,
repaying her curtesie with a smiling countenance, began to
parlie with her on this manner.
            FAire maide (quoth he) either your want is great, or a
shepheards life very swéete, that your delight is in such
country labors. I can not conceiue what pleasure you
should take, vnlesse you meane to imitate the nymph
                  ••
               , being
you, selfe so like a Nymph. To put me out of thi
                  〈…〉
               
me what is to be commended in a shepherdes l
                  ••
               e, 
                  〈◊◊〉
               
               
pleasures you haue to counter
                  ••
               aile these drudgi
                  •
               g laboures.
Fawnia with blushing face made him this ready aunswere.
            SIr, what richer state then content, or what swéeter life then
quiet, we shepheards are not borne to honor, nor beholding
vnto beautie, the lesse care we haue to feare fame or fortune:
we co
                  ••
               t our attire braue inough if warme inough, and our
foode dainty, if to suffice nature: our greatest enemie is the
wolfe: out only care in safe kéeping our flock: in stead of courtly
ditties we spend the daies with cuntry songs: our amorous
conceites are homely thoughtes: delighting as much to talke
of Pan and his cuntrey prankes, as Ladies to tell of Venus
and her want on toyes. Our toyle is in shifting the fouldes,
and looking to the Lambes easie labours: oft singing and telling
tales, homely pleasures: our greatest welth not to 
                  ••
               ouer,
out honor not to climbe, our quiet not to care. Enuie looketh
not so lowe as shepheards: Shepheards gaze not so high as
ambition: we are rich in that we are poore with content, and
proud onely in this that we haue no cause to be proud.
            THis wittie answer of Fawnia so inflamed Dorastus fancy,
as he commended him selfe for making so good a choyce,
thinking, if her birth were aunswerable to her wit and beauty,
that she were a fitte mate for the most famous Prince in the
worlde. He therefore beganne to sifte her more narrowely on
this manner.
            
               FAwnia, I sée thou art content with Country labours, because
thou knowest not Courtly pleasures: I commend thy
wit, and pitty thy want: but wilt thou leaue thy Fathers Cottage,
and serue a Courtlip Mistresse.
            Sir (quoth she) beggers ought not to striue against fortune,
nor to gaze after honour, least either their fall be greater,
or they become blinde. I am borne to toile for the Court, not
in the Court, my nature vnfit for their nurture, better liue
th
                  ••
                in meane degrée, than in high disdaine.
            
               
                  ••
               ll 
                  〈◊〉
               , Fawnia (quoth Dorastus) I gesse at thy

                  〈◊〉
               , thou art in loue with some Countrey Shephearde.
            
               No sir (quoth she) shepheards cannot loue, that are so simple,
and maides may not loue that are so young.
            Nay therefore (quoth Dorastus) maides must loue, because
they are young, for Cupid is a child, and Venus, though olde,
is painted with fresh coloures.
            I graunt (quoth she) age may be painted with new shadowes,
and youth may haue imperfect affections: but what arte concealeth
in one, ignorance reuealeth in the other. Dorastus seeing
Fawnia helde him so harde, thought it was vaine so long
to beate about the bush: therefore he thought to haue giuen
her a fresh charge: but he was so preuented by certaine of his
men, who missing their maister, came possing to séeke him: séeing
that he was gone foorth all alone, yet before they drewe
so 
                  •
               ie that they might heare their talke, he vsed these spéeches.
            Why Fawnia, perhappes I loue thée, and then thou must
néedes yéelde, for thou knowest I can commaunde and constraine.
Trueth sir (quoth she) but not to loue: for constrained
loue is force, not loue: and know this sir, mine honesty is such,
as I hadde rather dye then be a Concubine euen to a King,
and my birth is so base as I am vnfitte to bée a wife to a poore
farmer. Why then (quoth he) thou canst not loue Dorastus?
Yes saide Fawnia, when Dorastus becomes a shepheard, and
with that the presence of his men broke off their parle, so that
he went with them to the palace, and left Fawnia sitting still
on the hill side, who séeing that the night drewe on, shifted her
fouldes, and busied her selfe about other worke to driue away
such fond fancies as began to trouble her braine. But all this
could not preuaile, for the beautie of Dorastus had made such
a déepe impression in her heart, as it could not be worne out
without cracking, so that she was forced to blame her owne
folly in this wise.
            AH Fawnia, why doest thou gaze against the Sunne, or
catch at ye Winde: starres are to be looked at with the eye,
not reacht at with the hande: thoughts are to be measured by
Fortunes not by desires
                  •
                falles come not by sitting low, but
by climing too hie: what then shall al feare to fal, because some

happe to fall? No lucke commeth by lot, and fortune 
                  〈◊〉
               
those thréedes which the destinies spin. Thou art fau
                  ••••
               
               Fawnia of a prince, and yet thou art so fond to reiect desired fauours:
thou hast deniall at thy tonges end, and desire at thy
hearts bottome: a womans fault, to spurne at that with her
foote, which she greedily catcheth at with her hand. Thou louest
Dorastus, Fawnia, &amp; yet séemest to lower. Take h
                  ••
               de, if
hée retire, thou wilt repent: for vnles hée loue, thou canst but
dye. Dye then Fawnia: for Dorastus doth but iest: the Lyon
neuer prayeth on the mouse, nor Faultons stoupe not to dead
stales. Sit downe then in sorrow, ceasse to loue, and content
thy selfe, that Dorastus will vouchsafe to flatter Fawnia,
though not to fancy Fawnia. Heigh ho: Ah foole, it were
séemelier for thée to whistle as a Shepheard, then to sigh as a
louer, and with that shè ceassed from these perplexed passions,
folding her shéepe, and 
                  •
               ying home to her poore Cottage. But
such was the incessant sorrow of Dorastus to thinke on the
witte and beautie of Fawnia, and to sée how fond hée was being
a Prince: and how froward she was being a beggar, then
he began to loose his wonted appetite, to looke pale and 
                  •
               an:
in stead of mirth to féede on melancholy: for courtly 
                  •
               aunces
to vse cold dumpes: in so much that not onely his owne men,
but his father and all the court began to maruaile at his sudden
change, thinking that some lingring sickenes had brought
him into this state: wherfore he caused Phisitions to come, but
Dorastus neither would let them minister, nor so much as
suffer them to sée his vrine: but remained stil so oppressed with
these passions, as he feared in him selfe a farther inconuenience.
His honor wished him to ceasse from such folly, but Loue
forced him to follow fancy
                  •
                yea and in despight of honour, loue
wonne the conquest, so that his hot desires caused him to find
new deuises, for hée presently made himselfe a shepheards
coate, that he might goe vnknowne, and with the lesse suspition
to prattle with Fawnia, and conueied it secretly into a thick
groue hard ioyning to the Pallace, whether finding fit time,
and oportunity, he went all alone, and putting off his princely
apparel, got on those shepheards roabes, and t
                  ••••
               g a great
hooke in his hand (which he had also gotten) he w
                  •••
                very 
                  ••
               
               ciently

to stode out the mistres of his affection: but as he went
by the way, séeing himselfe clad in such vnseemely ragges, he
began to smile at his owne folly, and to reproue his fondnesse,
in these tearmes.
            WEll said Dorastus, thou kéepest a right decorum, base
desires and homely attires: thy thoughtes are fit for
none but a shepheard, and thy apparell such as only become a
shepheard. A strang change from a Prince to a pesant? What
is it? thy wretched fortune or thy wilful folly? Is it thy cursed
destinies? Or thy crooked desires, that appointeth thée this
penance? Ah Dorastus thou canst but loue, and vnlesse thou loue,
thou art like to perish for loue. Yet fond foole, choose flowers,
not weedes: Diamondes, not peables: Ladies which may
honour thée, not shepheards which may disgrace thée. Venus
is painted in silkes, not in ragges: and Cupid treadeth on disdame,
when he reacheth at dignitie. And yet Dorastus shame
not at thy shepheards wéede: the heauenly Godes haue sometime
earthly thoughtes: Neptune became a Ram, Iupiter a
Bul, Apollo a shepheard: they Gods, and yet in loue: and thou
a man appointed to loue.
            Deuising thus with himselfe, hée drew nigh to the place
where Fawnia was kéeping her shepe, who casting her eye aside,
and seeing such a manerly shepheard, perfectly limmed,
and comming with so good a pace, she began halfe to forget
Dorastus, &amp; to fauor this prety shepheard, whom she thought
shee might both loue and obtaine: but as shee was in these
thoughts, she perceiued then, it was the yong prince Dorastus,
wherfore she rose vp, and reuerently saluted him. Dorastus
taking her by the hand, repaied her curtesie with a sweete
kisse, and praying her to sit downe by him, he began thus to lay
the batterie.
            IF thou maruell Fawnia at my strange attyre, thou wouldest
more muse at my vnaccustomed thoughtes: the one disgraceth
but my outward shape, the other disturbeth my inward
sences. I loue Fawnia, and therefore what loue liketh
I cannot mislike. Fawnia thou hast promised to loue, and I

hope thou wilt performe no lesse: I haue fulfilled thy request,
and now thou canst but graunt my desire. Thou wert content
to loue Dorastus when he ceast to be a Prince; and to become
a shepheard, and see I haue made the change, and therefore
not to misse of my choice.
            TRueth, quoth Fawnia, but all that weare Cooles are not
Monkes: painted Eagles are pictures, not Eagles,
Zeusis Grapes were like Grapes, yet shadowes: rich clothing
make not princes: nor homely attyre beggers: shepheards
are not called shepheardes, because they were hookes and
bagges: but that they are borne poore, and liue to keepe sheepe,
so this attire hath not made Dorastus a shepherd, but to steme
like a shephherd.
            WEll Fawnia, answered Dorastus: were I a shepherd,
I could not but like thee, and being a prince I am forst
to loue thee. Take heed Fawnia, be not proud of beauties
painting, for it is a flower that fadeth in the blossome. Those
which disdayne in youth are despised in age: Beauties shadowes
are trickt vp with times colours, which being set to
drie in the sunne are stained with the sunne, scarce pleasing the
sight ere they beginne not to be worth the sight, not much vnlike
the herbe Ephemeron, which flourisheth in the morning
and is withered before the sunne setting: if my desire were against
lawe, thou mightest iustly deny me by reason, but I
loue thee Fawnia, not to misuse thee as a Concubine, but to
vse thee as my wife: I can promise no more, and meane to
performe no lesse.
            
               Fawnia hearing this solemne protestation of Dorastus,
could no longer withstand the assault, but yeelded vp the forte
in these friendly tearmes.
            AH Dorastus, I shame to expresse that thou forcest me with
thy sugred speeche to confesse: my base birth causeth the
one, and thy high dignities the other. Beggars thoughts
ought not to reach so far as Kings, and yet my de
                  ••
               es reach
as high as Princes, I dare not say Dorastus, I 
                  〈◊〉
                thee, because

I am a shepherd, but the Gods know I haue honored
Dorastus (pardon if I say amisse) yea and loued Dorastus
with such dutiful affection as Fawnia can performe, or Dorastus
desire: I yeeld, not ouercome with prayers, but with loue,
resting Dorastus handmaid ready to obey his wil, if no preiudice
at all to his honour, nor to my credit.
            
               DOrastus hearing this freendly conclusion of Fawnia embraced
her in his armes, swearing that neither distance,
time, nor aduerse fortune should diminish his affection: but
that in despight of the destinies he would remaine loyall vnto
death. Hauing thus plight their troath each to other, seeing
they could not haue the full fruition of their loue in Sycilia
for that Egistus consent woulde neuer bee graunted to so
meane a match, Dorastus determined assone as time and oportunitie
would giue them leaue, to prouide a great masse of
money, and many rich &amp; costly iewels, for the easier cariage,
and then to transporte them selues and their treasure into Italy,
where they should leade a contented life, vntil, such time as
either he could be reconciled to his Father, or els by sucession
come to the Kingdome. This deuise was greatly praysed of
Fawnia, for she feared if the King his father should but heare of
the contract, that his furie would be such as no lesse then death
would stand for payment: she therefore tould him, that delay
bred daunger: that many mishaps did fall out betweene the
cup and the lip, and that to auoid danger, it were best with asmuch
speed as might be, to passe out of Sycilia, least fortune
might preuent their pretence with some newe despight: Dorastus,
whom loue pricked forward with desire, promised to
dispatch his affaires with as great hast, as either time or oportunitie
would geue him leaue: an so resting vpon this point,
after many imbracings and sweete kisses they departed. Dorastus
hauing taken his leaue of his best beloued Fawnia,
went to the Groue where hee had his rich apparel, and there
vncasting himself as secretly as might be, hiding vp his shepheards
attire, till occasion should serue againe to vse it: hee
went to the pallace, shewing by his merrie countenaunce, yt either
the state of his body was amended, or the case of his minde

greatly redressed: Fawnia poore soule was no lesse ioyful, that
being a shepheard, fortune had fauoured her so, as to reward
her with the loue of a Prince, hoping in time to be aduaunced
from the daughter of a poore farmer, to be the wife of a riche
King: so that she thought euery houre a yeere, till by their departure
they might preuent danger, not ceasing still to goe euery
daye to her sheepe, not so much for the care of her flock,
as for the desire she had to see her loue and Lord Dorastus: who
oftentimes, when oportunitie would serue, repaired thither to
féede his fancy with the sweet content of Fawnias, presence:
and although he neuer went to visit her, but in his shepheards
ragges, yet his ofte repaire made him not onely suspected, but
knowne to diuers of their neighbours: who for the good will
they bare to old Porrus, tould him secretly of the matter, wishing
him to keepe his daughter at home, least she went so oft
to the field that shee brought him home a yong sonne: for they
feared that Fawnia being so beautifull, the yong Prince
would allure her to folly. Porrus was striken into a dump at
these newes, so that thanking his neighboures for their good
will: hee hyed him home to his wife, and calling her aside,
wringing his handes, and shedding foorth teares, he brake the
matter to her in these tearmes.
            
               I Am afraid wife, that my daughter Fawnia hath made her
selfe so fine, that she will buy repentance too deare. I heare
newes, which if they be true, some will wish they had not proued
true. It is tould me by my neighbours, that Dorastus the
Kinges sonne begins to looke at our daughter Fawnia: which
if it be so, I will not geue her a halfepenp for her honestiect
the yeeres end. I tell thee wife, now adaies beauty is a great
stale to trap yong men, and faire wordes and sweete promises
are two great enemies to a maydens honestie: and thou knowest
where poore men intreate, and cannot obtaine, there
Princes may commaund, and wil obtaine. Though Kings
sonnes daunce in nettes, they may not be seene: but poore mens
faultes are spied at a little hole: Well
                  •
                it is a hard case where
Kinges lustes are lawes, and that they should binde poore men
to that, which they themselues wilfully breake.
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               Peace husband (quoth his wife) take héede what you say:
speake no more then you should, least you heare what you
would not, great streames are to be stopped by sleight, not by
force: and princes to be perswaded by submission, not by rigor:
doe what you can, but no more then you may, least in sauing
Fawnias maydē-head, you loose your owne head. Take heede
I say, it is ill iesting with edged tooles, and had sporting with
Kinges. The Wolfe had his skinne puld ouer his eares for
but looking into the Lions den. Tush wife (quoth he) thou
speakest like a foole, if the King should knowe that Dorastus
had begotten our daughter with childe (as I feare it will fall
out little better) the Kings furie would be such as no doubt we
should both loose our goodes and liues: necessitie therefore
hath no lawe, and I will preuent this mischiefe with a newe
deuise that is come in my head, which shall neither offend the
King, nor displease Dorastus. I meane to take the chaine and
the iewels that I found with Fawnia, and carrie them to the
King, letting him then to vnderstand how she is none of my
daughter, but that I found her beaten vp with the water alone
in a little boate wrapped in a riche Mantle, wherein was inclosed
this treasure. By this meanes I hope the King will take
Fawnia into his seruice, and we whatsoeuer chaunceth shal be
blamelesse. This deuice pleased the good wife very well, so
that they determined assoone as they might know the King
at leisure, to make him priuie to this case. In the meane time
Dorastus was not slacke in his affaires, but applyed his matters
with such diligence, that he prouided all thinges fitte for
their iourney. Treasure and Iewels he had gotten great store,
thincking there was no better friend then money in a strange
countrey: rich attire he had prouided for Fawnia, and because
he could not bring the matter to passe with out the helpe and
aduise of some one, he made an old seruant of his called Capnio,
who had serued him from his childhood, priuie to his affaires:
who seeing no perswasions could preuaile to diuert him
from his setled determination, gaue his consent and dealt so
secretly in the cause, that within short space hee had gotten a
ship ready for their passage: the Mariners seeing a fit gale of
winde for their purpose, wished Capnio to make no delayes,

least if they pretermitted this good weather, they might stay
long ere they had such a fayre winde. Capnio fearing that his
negligence should hinder the iourney, in the night time conueyed
the trunckes full of treasure into the shippe, and by secrette
meanes let Fawnia vnderstand, that the next morning
they meant to depart: she vpon this newes slept verie little
that night, but gotte vp very early, and wente to her sheepe,
looking euery minute when she should see Dorastus, who caried
not long, for feare delay might breede daunger, but came as
fast as he could gallop, and without any great circumstance
tooke Fawnia vp behinde him and rode to the hauen, where
the shippe lay, which was not three quarters of a mile distant
from that place. He no sooner came there, but the Marriners
were readie with their Cockboate to set them aboard, where
being coucht together in a Cabben they past away the time in
 recounting their old loues, til their man Capnio should come.
Porrus who had heard that this morning the King would go
abroad to take the ayre, called in haste to his wife to bring him
his holyday hose and his best Iacket, that he might goe like
an honest substantiall man to tell his tale. His Wife a good
cleanly wenche, brought him all things fitte, and spungd him
vp very handsomlie, giuing him the chaines and Iewels in a
little boxe, which Porrus for the more safety put in his bosom.
Hauing thus all his trinkets in a readines, taking his staffe
in his hand he had his wife kisse him for good lucke, and so hée
went towards the Pallace. But as he was going, fortune
(who meant to showe him a little false play) preuented his
purpose in this wise.
            He met by chaunce in his way Capnio, who trudging as
fast as he could with a little coffer vnder his arme to the ship,
and spying Porrus whome he knewe to be Fawnias Father,
going towardes the Pallace, being a wylie fellow, began to
doubt the worst, and therefore crost him the way, and askt him
whither he was going so earely this morning.
            
               Porrus (who knew by his face that he was one of ye Court)
meaning simply, told him that the Kings son Dorastus dealt
hardly with him: for he had but one Daughter who was a little
Beautifull, and that his neighboures told him the young

Prince had allured her to folly, he went therefore now to complaine
to the King how greatly he was abused.
            
               Capnio (who straight way smelt the whole matter) began
to soth him in his talke, and said, that Dorastus dealt not like
a Prince to spoyle and poore manes daughter in that sort: he
therefore would doe the best for him he could, because he knew
he was an honest man. But (quoth Capnio) you lose your labour
in going to the Pallace, for the King meanes this day to
take the aire of the Sea, and to goe aboord of a shippe that
lies in the hauen, I am going before, you see, to prouide all
things in a redinesse, and if you wil follow my counsaile, turne
back with me to the hauen, where I will set you in such a fitte
place as you may speake to the King at your pleasure. Porrus
giuing credit to Capnios smooth tale, gaue him a thousand
thanks for his frendly aduise, and went with him to the hauen,
making all the way his complaintes of Dorastus, yet concealing
secretlie the chaine and the Iewels. Assone as they were
come to the Sea side, the marriners seeing Capnio, came a
land with their cock-boate, who still dissembling the matter,
demaunded of Porrus if he would go see the ship, who vnwilling
and fearing the worst, because he was not well acquainted
with Capnio, made his excuse that he could not brooke the
Sea, therefore would not trouble him.
            
               Capnio, seeing that by faire meanes hee could not get him
aboord, cōmaunded the mariners that by violence they should
carrie him into the shippe, who like sturdy knaues hoisted the
poore shepheard on their backes, and bearing him to the boate,
lanched from the land.
            
               Porrus seeing himselfe so cunningly betraied durst not crie
out, for hee sawe it would not preuaile, but began to intreate
Capnio and the mariners to be good to him, and to pittie his
estate, hee was but a poore man that liued by his labour: they
laughing to see the shepheard so afraide, made as much haste
as they could, and sette him aboorde. Porrus was no sooner in
the shippe, but he saw Dorastus walking with Fawnia, yet he
scarfe knew her: for she had attired her selfe in riche apparell,
which, so increased her beauty, that shee resembled rather an
Angell then a mortall creature.
            
               
               Dorastus and Fawnia, were halfe astonished to see the olde
shepherd, maruailing greatly what wind had brought him
thither, til Capino told them al the whole discourse: how Porrus
was going to make his complaint to the King, if by pollicie

                  •
               he had not preuented him, and therefore now sith he was aboord,
for the auoiding of further danger, it were best to carrie
him into Italy.
            
               Dorastus praised greatly his mans deuise, and allowed of
his counsaile: but Fawnia, (who stil feared Porrus, as her father)
began to blush for shame, that by her meanes he should
either incure daunger or displeasure.
            The old shephard hearing this hard sentence, that he should
on such a sodaine be caried from his Wife, his country and
kinsfolke, into a forraine Lande amongst straungers, began
with bitter teares to make his complaint, and on his knees to
intreate Dorastus, that pardoning his vnaduised folly he
would giue him leaue to goe home: swearing that hee would
keepe all thinges as secret as they could wish. But these protestations
could not preuaile, although Fawnia intreated Dorastus
very earnestly, but the mariners hoisting their maine
sailes waied ankers, and hailed into the deepe, where we leaue
them to the fauour of the wind and seas, &amp; returne to Egistus.
            
            WHo hauing appointed this day to hunt in one of his
Forrests, called for his sonne Dorastus to go sport
himselfe, because hee saw that of late hee began to loure: but
his men made answer that hee was gone abroade none knew
whither, except he were gone to the groue to walke all alone,
as his custome was to doe euery day.
            The King willing to waken him out of his dumpes, sent
one of his men to goe seeke him, but in vaine, for at last he returned,
but finde him he could not, so that the King went himselfe
to goe see the sport: where passing away the day, returning
at night from hunting, hee asked for his sonne, but hee
could not be heard of, which draue ye King into a great choler:
where vpon most of his Noblemen and other Courtiers, poasted
abroad to séek him, but they could not heare of him through
all Sicilia, onely they missed Capnio his man which againe

made the King suspect that he was not gone farre.
            Two or three daies being passed, and no newes heard of
Dorastus, Egistus began to feare that he was deuoured with
some wilde beastes, and vpon that made out a greate troupe of
men to go seeke him: who coasted through all the Countrey
and searched in euerie daungerous and secrete place, vntill at
last they mette with a Fisherman that was sitting in a little
couert harde by the sea side mending his nettes, when Dorastus
and Fawnia tooke shipping: who being examined if he either
knewe or heard where the Kings Sonne was, without
any secrecie at all reuealed the whole matter, how he was sayled
two dayes past, &amp; had in his cōpany his man Capnio, Porrus,
and his faire Daughter Fawnia. This heauie newes was
presently caryed to the King, who halfe dead for sorow, commaunded
Porrus wife to bee sent for: she being come to the
Pallace, after due examination, confessed that her neighbours
had oft told her that the Kings Sonne was too familier with
Fawnia her Daughter: wherevppon, her husband fearing the
worst, about two dayes past (hearing the King should goe an
hunting) rose earely in the morning and went to make his
complaint, but since she neither hearde of him, nor saw him.
Egistus perceiuing the womans vnfeyned simplicity, let her
depart without incurring further displeasure, conceiling such
secret greefe for his Sonnes recklesse follie, that he had so forgotten
his honour and parentage, by so base a choise to dishonor
his Father, and discredit himselfe, that with very care and
thought he fel into a quartan feuer, which was so vnfit for his
aged yeeres and complexion, that he became so weake, as the
Phisitions would graunt him no life.
            But his sonne Dorastus little regarded either father, countrie:
or Kingdome, in respect of his Lady Fawnia, for fortune
smyling on this young nouice, lent him so lucky a gale of
winde, for the space of a day and a night, that the maryners lay
and slept vpon the hatches: but on the next morning about the
breake of the day, the aire began to ouercast, the winds to rise,
the seas to swel, yea presently there arose such a fearfull tempest,
as the ship was in danger to be swallowed vp with euery
sea, the maine 
                  ••
               ast with the violence of the wind was thrown

                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
ouer boord, the sayles were torne, the tacklings went in sunder,
the storme raging still so furiously that poore Fawnia was
almost dead for feare, but that she was greatly comforted with
the presence of Dorastus. The tempest continued thrée dayes,
al which time the Mariners euerie minute looked for death,
and the aire was so darkned with cloudes that the Maister
could not tell by his compasse in what Coast they were. But
vpon the fourth day about ten of the clocke, the wind began
to cease: the sea to wax calme, and the sky to be cleare, and the
Mariners descryed the coast of Bohemia, shooting of their
ordnance for ioy that they had escaped such a fearefull tempest.
            
               Dorastus hearing that they were arriued at some harbour,
sweetly kissed Fawnia, and bad her be of good cheare: when
they tolde him that the port belonged vnto the cheife Cittie of
Bohemia where Pandosto kept his Court, Dorastus began
to be sad: knowing that his Father hated no man so much as
Pandosto, and that the King himself had sought secretly to
betray Egistus: this considered, he was halfe afraid to goe on
land, but that Capnio counselled him to chaunge his name
and his countrey, vntil such time as they could get some other
Barke to transport them into Italy. Dorastus liking this deuise
made his case priuy to the Marriners, rewarding them
bountifully for their paines, and charging them to saye that he
was a Gentleman of Trapalonia called Meleagrus. The
shipmen willing to shew what friendship they could to Dorastus,
promised to be as secret as they could, or hee might wish,
and vppon this they landed in a little village a mile distant
from the Citie, where after they had rested a day, thinking to
make prouision for their mariage: the fame of Fawnias beauty
was spread throughout all the Citie, so that it came to the
eares of Pandosto: who then being about the age of fifty, had
notwithstanding yong and freshe affections: so that he desired
greatly to see Fawnia, and to bring this matter the better to
passe, hearing they had but one man, and how they rested at a
very homely house: he caused them to be apprehēded as spies,
and sent a dozen of his garde to take them: who being come
to their lodging, tolde them the Kings message: Dorastus no

whit dismayed, accompanied with Fawnia and Capnio, went
to the court (for they left Porrus to keepe the stuffe) who being
admitted to the Kings presence. Dorastus and Fawnia with
humble obeysance saluted his maiestie.
            
               Pandosto amased at the singular perfection of Fawnia, stood
halfe astonished, viewing her beauty, so that he had almost forgot
himselfe what hee had to doe: at last with stearne countenance
he demaunded their names, and of what countrey they
were, and what caused them to land in Bohemia. Sir (quoth
Dorastus) know that my name Meleagrus is a Knight borne
and brought vp in Trapalonia, and this Gentlewoman, whom
I meane to take to my wife is an Italian borne in Padua, from
whence I haue now brought her. The Cause I haue so small
a trayne with me, is for that her friends vnwilling to consent,
I intended secretly to conuey her into Trapalonia: whither
as I was sailing, by distresse of weather I was driuen into
these coasts: thus haue you heard my name, my country, and
the cause of my voiage. Pandosto starting from his seat as one
in choller, made this rough reply.
            
               Meleagrus, I feare this smooth tale hath but small trueth,
and that thou couerest a foule skin with faire paintings. No
doubt this Ladie by her grace and beauty is of her degree
more meete for a mighty Prince, then for a simple knight, and
thou like a periured traitour hast bereft her of her parents, to
their present griefe, and her insuing sorrow. Till therefore I
heare more of her parentage and of thy calling, I wil stay you
both here in Bohemia.
            
            
               Dorastus, in whome rested nothing but Kingly valor, was
not able to suffer the reproches of Pandosto, but that he made
him this answer.
            IT is not meete for a King, without due proofe to appeach any
man of ill behauiour, nor vpon suspition to inferre beléefe:
straungers ought to bee entertained with courtesie, not to bee
intreated with crueltie, least being forced by want to put vp
iniuries: the Gods reuenge their cause with rigor.
            
               Pandosto hearing Dorastus vtter these wordes, commanded
that he should straight be committed to prison, vntill such

time as they heard further of his pleasure, but as for Fawnia,
he charged that she should be entertained in the Court, with
such curtesie as belonged to a straunger and her calling. The
rest of the shipmen he put into the Dungeon.
            Hauing thus hardly handled the supposed Trapalonians:
Pandosto contrarie to his aged yeaxes began to be somwhat
tickled with the beauty of Fawnia, in so much that hee could
take no rest, but cast in his old head a thousand new deuises: at
last he fell into these thoughtes.
            HOw art thou pestred Pandosto with fresh affections,
and vnfitte fancies, wishing to possesse with an vnwilling
mynde, and a hot desire troubled with a could disdaine:
Shalt thy mynde yeeld in age to that thou hast resisted
in youth? Peace Pandosto, blabbe not out that which thou
maiest be ashamed to reueale to thy self. Ah Fawnia is beautifull,
and it is not for thine honour (fond foole) to name her that
is thy Captiue, and an other mans Concubine. Alas, I reach
at that with my hand which my hart would faine refuse: playing
like the bird Ibys in Egipt, which hateth Serpents, yet
feedeth on their egges.
            Tush, hot desires turne oftentimes to colde disdaine: Loue
is brittle, where appetite, not reason beares the sway: Kinges
thoughtes ought not to climbe so high as the heauens, but to
looke no lower then honour: better it is to pecke at the starres
with the young Eagles, then to pray on dead carkasses with
the Uulture: tis more honourable for Pandosto to dye by concealing
Loue, their to enioy such vnfitte Loue. Dooth Pandosto
then loue? Yea: whome? A maide vnknowne, yea and
perhapps, immodest, stragled out of her owne countrie: beautifull,
but not therefore chast: comely in bodie, but perhappes
crooked in minde. Cease then Pandosto to looke at Fawnia,
much lesse to loue her: be not ouertaken with a womans beauty,
whose eyes are framed by arte to inamour, whose hearte is
framed by nature to inchaunt, whose false teares knowe their
true times
                  •
                and whose sweete wordes pearce deeper then
sharpe swordes. Here Pandosto ceased from his talke, but not
from his loue: for although he sought by reason, and wisedome

to suppresse this franticke affection: yet he could take no rest,
y• beautie of Fawnia had made such a déepe impression in his
heart. But on a day walking abroad into a Parke which was
hard adioyning to his house, he sent by one of his seruants for
Fawnia, vnto whome he vttered these wordes.
            
               FAwnia, I commend thy beauty and wit, and now pittie
thy distresse and want: but if thou wilt forsake Sir Meleagrus,
whose pouerty, though a Knight, is not able to
maintaine an estate aunswerable to thy beauty, and yeld thy
consent to Pandosto: I wil both increase thee with dignities
and riches. No sir, answered Fawnia: Meleagrus is a knight
that hath wonne me by loue, and none but he shal weare me:
his sinister mischance shall not diminishe my affection, but
rather increase my good will: thinke not though your Grace
hath imprisoned him without cause, that feare shall make mee
yéeld my consent: I had rather be Meleagrus wife, and a begger,
then liue in plenty, and be Pandostos Concubine. Pandosto
hearing the assured aunswere of Fawnia, would, notwithstanding,
prosecute his suite to the vttermost: séeking with
faire words and great promises in scale the fort of her chastitie,
swearing that if she would graunt to his desire, Meleagrus
should not only he fet at libertie, but honored in his course amongst
his Nobles: but these alluring baytes could not intise
her minde from the loue of her 
                  ••
                we betrothed mate Meleagrus:
which Pandosto séeing, he left her alone for that time to
consider more of the demaund. Fawnia being alone by her
selfe, began to enter into these solitarie meditations.
            AH infortunate Fawnia, thou 
                  •
               éest to desire aboue fortune, is
to striue against the Gods, and Fortune
                  •
                Who gazeth at
the su
                  ••
               e we akeneth his sight: they which stare at the skie, fall
oft into déepe pi
                  •
               s: haddest thou rested content to haue bene a
shepheard, thou neededst not to haue feared mischaunce: better
had it bene for thée, by sitting lowe, to haue had quiet, then by
climing high to haue fallen into miserie. But alas I feare not
mine owne daunger, but Dorastus displeasure. Ah swéete
Dorastus, thou art a Prince, but now a prisoner, by too much

loue, procuring thine owne losse: haddest thou not loued Fawnia
thou haddest bene fortunate, shall I then bée false to him
that hath forsaken Kingdomes for my cause: no, would my
death might deliuer him, so mine honor might be preserued.
With that feching a déepe sigh, she ceased frō her complaints,
and went againe to the Pallace, inioying a libertie without
content, and profered pleasure with smal ioy. But poore Dorastus
               
                  •••
                all this while in olose prison, being pinch
                  •
               d with a
hard restraint, and pained with the burden of colde, and heauie
Irons, sorrowing sometimes that his fond affection had pr
                  •
               
               cured
him this mishappe, that by the disobedience of his parentes,
he had wrought his owne despight: an other while cursing
the Gods and fortune, that they should crosse him with
such sinister chaunce: vttering at last his passions in these
words.
            Ah vnfortunate wretch borne to mishappe, now thy folly
hath his desert: art thou not worthie for thy base minde to haue
bad fortune: could the destinies fauour thée, which hast forgot
thine honor and dignities: wil not the Gods plague him wt despight
that payneth his father with disobedi
                  •
               nce. Oh Gods, if
any fauour or iustice b
                  ••
               left, plague me, but fauour poore Fawnia
and shrowd her from the tirannies of wretched Pandosto,
but let my death frée her from mishap
                  •
                and then welcome
death: Dorastus payned with these heauie passions, sorrowed
and sighed, but in vaine, for which he vsed the more patience.
But againe to Pandosto, who broyling at the heat of vnlawfull
lust coulde take no rest but still felte his minde disquieted
with his new loue, so that his nobles and subiectes marueyled
greatly at this sudaine alteration, not being able to coniecture
the cause of this his continued care: Pandosto thinking euery
hower a yeare til he had talked once againe with Fawnia, sent
for her secretly into his chamber, whither though Fawnia vnwillingly
comming, Pandosto entertained her very courteously
vsing these familiar speaches, which Fawnia answered
as shortly in this wise.
            
               Pandosto.
               
                  
                  Fawnia are you become less
                     •
                   wilfull and more wise, to pre
                  
                     •
                  erre
the loue of a King before the liking of a poore Knight: I
thinke ere this you thinke it is better to be fauoured of a King
then of a subiect.
            
            
               Fawnia.
               Pandosto, the body is subiect to victories, but the mind not
to be subdued by conquest, honesty is to be preferred before honour,
and a dramme of faith weigheth downe a tunne of gold.
I haue promised Meleagrus to loue, and will performe no
lesse.
            
            
               Pandosto.
               
                  Fawnia, I know thou art not so vnwise in thy choice, as to
refuse the offer of a King, nor so ingrateful as to dispise a good
turne: thou art now in that place where I may commaunde,
and yet thou séest I intreate, my power is such as I may
compell by force; and yet I su
                     ••
                  y prayers: Yéelde Fawnia thy
loue to him which burneth in thy loue, Meleagrus shall be set
frée, thy countrymen discharged: and thou both loued and honoured.
            
            
               Fawnia.
               I sée Pandosto, where lust ruleth it is a miserable thing to
be a virgin, but know this, that I will alwaies preferre fame
before life, and rather choose death then dishonour.
            
            
               Pandosto séeing that there was in Fawnia a determinate
courage to loue Meleagrus, and a resolution without feare to
hate him, flong away from her in a rage: swearing if in shorte
time she would not be wonne with reason: he would forget all
courtesie, and compel her to graunt by rigour: but these threatning
wordes no whit dismayed Fawnia: but that she still both
dispighted and dispised Pandosto. While thus these two louers
stroue, the one to winne loue the other to liue in hate: Egistus
heard certaine newes by Merchauntes of Bohemia,
               
that his sonne Dorastus was imprisoned by Pandosto, which

                  •••
                h
                  •••
                feare greatly that his sonne should be but hardly intreated:
yet considering that Bellaria and hee was cleared by
the Oracle of Apollo from that crime wherewith, Pandosto
had vniustly charged them, hee thought best to send with all
spéed to Pandosto, that he should set free his sonne Dorastus,
and put to death Fawnia and her father Porrus: finding this
by the ad
                  •••
               e of Counsaile the spéediest remedy to release his
sonne, he 
                  •
               aused presently two of his shippes to be rigged and
thoroughly furnished with prouision of men and victuals, and
sa
                  •
               ediuers of his nobles, Embassadoures into Bohemia: who
willing to obey their King, and receiue their yong Prince:
made no delayes, for feare of danger, but with as much speede
as might be, sailed towards Bohemia: the winde and seas fauored
them greatly, which made them hope of some good
happe, for within three daies they were landed: which Pandosto
no soner heard of their arriuall, but hee in person went
to méete them, intreating thē with such sumptuous and famili
                  ••
               
courtesie, that they might well perceiue how sory he was
for the formet mi
                  •
               ries hee had offered to their King, and how
willing (if it might be) to make amendes. As Pādosto made
report to them, how one Meleagrus a Knight of Trapolonia
was lately ariued with a Lady called Fawnia in his land, comming
very suspitiously, accompanied onely with one seruant,
and an olde shepheard. The Embassadours perceiued by the
halfe, what the whole tale ment, and began to coniecture, that
it was Dorastus, who for feare to bee knowne, had chaunged
his name: but dissembling ye matter, they shortly ariued at the
Court, where after they had bin verie solemnly and sumptuously
feasted, the noble men of Sicilia being gathered togither,
they made reporte of their Embassage 
                  •
                where they certified
Pandosto that Meleagtus was sonne and heire to the King
Egistus, and that his name was Dorastus: how contrarie to
the Kings minde he had priuily conuaied away that Fawnia,
intending to marrie her, being but daughter to that poore shepheard
Porrus: wherevpon the Kings request was, that Capnio,
               Fawnia, and Porrus might bee murthered and put to
death, and that his sonne Dorastus might be sent home in safetie.

               Pandosto hauing attentiuely and with great meruaile
he
                  •
               rd their Embassage, willing to reconcile himselfe to Egistus,
and to shew him how greatlie he estéemed his labour: although
loue and fancy forbad him to hurt Fawnia, yet in despight
of loue hee determined to execute Egistus will without
mercy, and therefore he presently sent for Dorastus out of prison,
who meruailing at this vnlooked for curtesie, found at his
comming to the Kings presence, that which he least doubted
of, his fathers Embassadours
                  •
                who no sooner sawe him, but
with great reuerence they honored him: and Pandosto embracing
Dorastus, set him by him very louingly in a chaire of estate.
Dorastus ashamed that his follie was be wraied, sate a
long time as one in a muse, til Pandosto told him the summe
of his Fathers embassage, which he had no sooner heard, but
he was toucht at the quicke, for the cruell sentence that was
pronounced against Fawnia: but neither could his sorrow nor
perswasions preuaile, for Pandosto commaunded that Fawnia,
Porrus, and Capnio, should bee brought to his presence:
who were no sooner come, but Pandosto hauing his former
loue turned to a disdainful hate, began to rage against Fawnia
in these tearmes.
            THou disdainfull vassal, thou currish kite, assigned by the
destinies to base fortune, and yet with an aspiring minde
gazing after honor: how durst thou presume, being a beggar, to
match with a Prince: By thy alluring lookes to inchant the
sonne of a King, to leaue his owne countrie to fulfill thy disordinate
lusts. O despightfull minde, a proud heart in a beggar
is not vnlike to a great fire in a smal cottage, which warmeth
not the house, but burneth it: assure thy selfe thou shalt die, and
thou old doating foole, whose follie hath bene such, as to suffer
thy daughter to reach aboue thy fortune: looke for no other
méede, but the like punishment. But Capnio, thou which hast
betrayed the King, and hast consented to the vnlawfull lust of
thy Lord and maister, I know not how iustly I may plague
thée: death is too easie a punishment for thy falsehood, and to
liue (if not in extreme miserie) were not to shew thée equitie.
I therefore award that thou shall haue thine eyes put out, and

continually while thou diest, grinde in a mil like a brute beast.
The feare of death 
                  •
               rought a sorrowfull silence vpon Fawnia
and Capnio, but Porrus séeing no hope of life, burst forth into
these spéeches.
            
               PAndosto, and ye noble Emabassadours of Sicili
                     ••
                  , séeing
without cause I am condemned to die: I am yet glad I
haue opportunitie to disburdē my conscience before my death:
I will tel you as much as I know, and yet no more than is
true: whereas I am accused that I haue bene a supporter of
Fawnias pride, and shee disdained as a vilde begger, so it is,
that I am neither Father vnto her, nor she daughter vnto me.
            For so it happened that I being a poore shepheard in Sicilia,
liuing by kéeping others mens flockes: one of my shéepe
straying downe to the sea side, as I went to séeke her, I saw a
little boat driuen vpon the shoare, wherein I found a babe of
sixe daies olde, wrapped in a mantle of skarlet, hauing about
the necke this chain
                  •
                : I pittying the child, and desirous of the
treasure, carried it home to my wife, who with great care nursed
it vp, and set it to keepe sheepe. Heere is the chaine and
the Iewels, and this Fawnia is the childe whome I found
in the boate, what shee is, or of what parentage I knowe not,
b
                  ••
               t this I am assured that shee is none of mine.
            
               Pandosto would scarce suffer him to tell out his tale, but
that he enquired the time of the yeere, the manner of the boate,
and other circumstaunces, which when he found agreeing to
his count, he sodainelie leapt from his seate, and kissed Fawnia,
wetting her tender cheeks with his teares, and crying my
daughter Fawnia, ah swtete Fawnia, I am thy Father, Fawnia.
This sodaine passion of the King draue them all into a
maze, especially Fawnia and Dorastus. But when the
King had breathed himselfe a while in this newe ioy, hee rehearsed
beefore the Embassadours the whole matter, how
hee hadde entreated his wife Bellaria for iealousie, and
that this was the childe whome hee sent to floate in the
seas.
            
               Fawnia was not more ioyfull that she had found such a Father,
then Dorastus was glad he should get such a wife. The

Embassadors reioyced that their yong prince had made such a
choice, that those Kingdomes which through enmitie had long
time bin disseuered, should now through perpetual amitie be vnited
and reconciled. The Citizens and subiects of Bohemia
(hearing that the King had found againe his Daughter,
which was supposed dead, ioyfull that there was an heire aparant
to his Kingdome) made Bonstres and showes throughout
the Cittie: The Courtiers and Knights appointed Iusts
and Turneis, to signifie their willing mindes in gratifying
the Kings hap.
            Eighteene daies being past in these princely sports, Pandosto
willing to recompence old Porrus, of a shepheard made
him a Knight: which done, prouiding a sufficient Nauie to receiue
him and his retinue, accompanied with Dorastus, Fawnia,
and the Sicilian Embassadours, he sailed towards Sicilia,
where he was most princelie entertained by Egistus: who hearing
this comicall euent, reioyced greatly at his sonnes good
happe, and without delay (to the perpetuall ioy of the two
yong Louers) celebrated the marriage: which was no sooner
ended, but Pandosto (calling to mind how first he betraied his
friend Egistus, how his iealousie was the cause of Bellarias
death, that contrarie to the law of nature hee had lusted after
his owne Daughter) moued with these desperate thoughts, he
fell in a melancholie fit, and to close vp the Comedie with a
Tragicall stratageme, hee slewe himselfe, whose death being
many daies bewailed of Fawnia, Dorastus, and his deere
friend Egistus, Dorastus taking his leaue of his father,
went with his wife and the dead corps into Bohemia,
wh
                  ••
                after they were sumptuouslie

                  ••••••
               bed, Dorastus
ended his daies in contented
quiet.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

