
   
      
         
            Penelopes vveb VVhere, in a christall mirror of feminine perfection represents to the view of euery one those vertues and graces, which more curiously beautifies the mind of women, then eyther sumptuous apparell, or iewels of inestimable value: the one buying fame with honour, the other breeding a kinde of delight, but with repentance. In three seuerall discourses also are three speciall vertues, necessary to be incident in euery vertuous woman, pithely discussed: namely obedience, chastity, and sylence: interlaced with three seuerall and comicall histories. By Robert Greene Master of Artes in Cambridge.
            Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
         
         
            
               1601
            
         
         Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02152
            STC 12294
            ESTC S103424
            99839178
            99839178
            3579
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02152)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3579)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1140:04)
         
         
            
               
                  Penelopes vveb VVhere, in a christall mirror of feminine perfection represents to the view of euery one those vertues and graces, which more curiously beautifies the mind of women, then eyther sumptuous apparell, or iewels of inestimable value: the one buying fame with honour, the other breeding a kinde of delight, but with repentance. In three seuerall discourses also are three speciall vertues, necessary to be incident in euery vertuous woman, pithely discussed: namely obedience, chastity, and sylence: interlaced with three seuerall and comicall histories. By Robert Greene Master of Artes in Cambridge.
                  Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
               
               [60] p.   
               
                  Printed [by E. Allde] for Iohn Hodgets, and are to be solde at his shop at the Flowerdeluce in Fleetestreete, neere to Fetter Lane end,
                  London :
                  1601.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-G⁴ H² .
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2002-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-07
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2002-09
            AptaraRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2002-10
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2002-10
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            To the Right Honorable
&amp; vertuous his very good Ladie
and Mistresse, the Lady Margaret Countesse
of Cumberland: and to the no lesse Honorable and vertuous
the Lady Anne Countesse of Warwicke: Robert
Greene wisheth increase of Honor
and Vertue.
            
               SOcrates (Right Honorable) being forced
by the Athenians to send presents to Apollo,
offered not vp, as others did, the superfluity
of wealth, but the Aenigmaes of
Hermes Tresmegistus, yeelding this reason,
that Apollo was not poore but wise. Achilles beautified
the Temple of Pallace with Speares and Helmets,
in that the Goddesse was patronesse of Souldiers. Dyanas
present was a bow: And I by chaunce finding so precious
a monument as the Web of Penelope, the onely trophee
of her chastity, was perswaded to bestow it vpon your
Honors, as vpon two Ladies, whose vertues deserues among
the best the patronage of such a famous antiquity.
For if truth be the daughter of time, and time the Heralt
that best imblazeth affections. The report that the Grecians
made of the Princesse of Ithaca, may seeme but a fiction
compared with the fame of your Ladiships vertuous

resolutions: which are such and so rare, as your very
enemies (if you haue any) are forced maugre their teeth
to be true discouerers of your vertues. Homer penned his
Odissea comprehending the life of Vlisses because hee
was wise. And I (may it please your Ladiships) haue attempted
the discourse of Penelopes Web, for that sh
                  •
               e
was chast, that as diuers reading the Poets works did immitate
his wisdome spoke well of his pollicie: so some by
glancing at this toy may take a president of her chastitie,
&amp; giue thanks to your Honors, whose chast &amp; vertuous
life brought this worke to light. But some may obiect
that Homers pen deawd forth such 
                  •
               ugred eloquence, as
beseemed the discourse of Vlisses trauailes: whereas my
harsh style and method makes the Web that of it selfe
was as soft as the Seres wool, be as rough as Goates haire.
I confesse my fault, and therefore by custome cla
                  •
               me pardone
of course: yet thus farre dare I answere for my selfe,
that although Demosthenes had a Plaudi
                  •
               e for his Oratiō
because it was curious: yet Nemius got the sentence for
the trueth of his plaine tale. Penelope her self was more
chast then eloquent. Virgill was seene to haue Ennius in
his hand. The Romain Ladies spurned at the sweet verses
of Ouid, when they read ouer the Satyres of Inuenall▪
And I hope your Ladiships w
                  •
               l vouchsafe of Penelopes
Web, at least for the vertue of the wowan that first
wrought it, though the Cloath workers arte haue giuen
it so bad a glosse. Damydas caused his Parrat to pea
                  •
               ke vnder
a Dragon of brasse to defend it from the Vulturestyranny:
and I shrowde this simple worke vnder your Honors
patronage, that the enuious, whose tungs cut like
Swords, may like the Serpent feare to offend that hearb,
whereon the beames of the Sunne doth rest. Thus hoping

your Ladiships will▪ 
               
                  •
               r Penelopes sake vouchsafe
of such a homely present, though otherwise vnworthy
the patronage of 
                  〈◊〉
                Honorable
personages▪ I commit your honors
to the Almightie.
            
               Your Ladiships in all duetifull seruice
to commaund, Robert Greene.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE GENTLEMEN
READERS HEALTH.
            
               SO oft (Gentlemen) haue I relyed vpon your courtesie,
and found you so fauorable, that still I aduenture
to present what I 
                  〈◊〉
                to your iudgements, hoping as
my intent is to pleaseall, if it might be without offence,
so I shallbe pardoned of all, though presumiug to farre: It
may be the forehead is not alwaies a true heralt of affections, neither
the rules of Phisiognomie infallible principles: for they
which smiled at the Theatre in Rome, might assoone scoffe at the
rudenesse of the Scaene, as giue a Plaudite at the perfection of the
action, and they which passe ouer my toies with silence, may perhappes
shrowde a mislike in such patience, if they doe, yet soothing
my selfe in the hope of their courtesies, I sleepe content like
Phid
                     •
                  as in mine owne follies, thinking all is wel, til proofe tels me
the contrarie. I was determined at the first to haue made no appeale
to your fauorable opinions, for that the matter is womens
prattle, about the vntwisting of Penelopes Web. But considering
that Mars will sometime bee prying into Venus papers, and gentlemen
desirous to heare the parlie of Ladies, I thought rather to
write a line to much, and so be counted forward, then by leauing
out one title, incurre your displeasures, and so be iudged froward:
but whatsoeuer I haue done or written, I onely desire for my
paines your fauorable acceptance, and so wish to you, as to my
selfe, to liue fortunate, and dye happy.
            
               Yours to vse, Robert Greene.
            
         
         
            
            To the Courteous and Courtly Ladyes
of England.
            
               AFter that (Gentlewomen) I had finished
this worke of Penelopes Web, and
was willing to commit it to the
Presse, I 
                  •
               ell to parlye with my selfe,
whether I should stay it as Apelles did Venus picture,
halfe vnfinished in the Printers fourmes: or
thrust it out as Myson did a ragged table bescratcht
with a pensell. Apelles was froward, and Myson too
forward, both faulty, and euery man hath his folly.
It may be some will thinke me of Antisthenes faction,
that layed platformes of euery mans life, and
yet the Philosopher was more vvise in his precepts
then vvary of his ovvne gouernment: and count
me very oeconomycall that seeke to sette dovvne
the duety of a vvife, &amp; to deliuer principles to such
a purpose. If I haue intermedled too far, it is (Gentlevvomen)
in discouering the vertues of your sex,
not in censuring seuerely of your actions: for I present
but the vievv of those vertues that naturally

are, or incidently ought to be as well in virgins that
sacrifice to Vesta, as in wiues▪ that make secrete
vowes to Lucyna. I reprehend not (as one thinking
all generally to be vertuous,) but perswade as
one wishing particularly euery one should lyue
well and dye better. If any that are enuyous
grudge at my dooing, I straight for refuge flye to
your good words, which I count as a sufficient defensory
against such as loue to backbyte. Committing
therefore my Booke to your pa
                  •
               ronage, least
the gates being too big for the Citty, the Mountaine
should seeme to swell and bring foorth a
Mouse, I wish you all such happy
successe as you can desire
and I imagine.
            
               Robert Greene.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            Penelopes VVeb.
            
               VVhen as the stately Citty of Troy
was sackt by the Grecians, &amp; al the Princely brood of Priamus either vtterly extinguished by the sword, or fatally exiled the place of their natiue residence: Vlisses, Prince of Ithaca, who had remained ten yeares at the siege, resolued to leave the confines of Asia, &amp; to returne to the gouernment of his owne Monarchy: but especially to see the mistres of his thoughts chast Penelope, frō whome these broiles had so long frowardly detained him: thinking as it was the part of a friend to accōpany Menelaus in reuenge, so it was y
                  •
                duety of a husband by smal delay to bewray his affectiō: that it was the office of a Prince as wel to study in Pallas as to cry Alarum with Mars: that as great honour dyd depend in the Scepters as in the sword: tha the gréene Lawrell in the Senate house, was as pleasing an obiect to y
                  •
                eye, as glittering armour in the field: Consideratiō, ther preuenter of bad I wist, tyed him so to the performing of these forenamed premisses, that causing his weather Ships to be warped out of the Hauen assoone as they were made tyght, rigged and trimmed, able to brooke winde &amp; weather, be 
                  •
               oysed sayle and thrust into the mayne, conuerting his course toward Ithaca: but Fortune the enemy to prosperous resolutions, willing to bewray her selfe, hauing commission from angry Neptune to shewe her inconstancy, kept him still in the Court of Ithaca, for that Nature had made her beautiful by a superficiall glory of well proportioned lineaments, and vertue had made her wise by ayming after fame with wel ordred actions, thse two perfections the speciall friend to fancy, armed with the long absence of Vlisses, &amp; with many rumors of his death, brought all the Péeres of Ithaca to become sutors to Penelope.  She whom Loue hadarested for a subiect, but neuer brought to any seruile obedience, whom the Idea of Vlisses printed in her thoughts, had resolued to dye the wife of so good a Prince, refused their proffers, &amp; with the warrant of her chastity sought to appease their humorous perswasions. But the Noble men whom delay and tyme had made impatient of denyall, fell in to flat tearmes and craued an answer. Penelope seeing that fortune had conspyred her mishap, by breeding such a restlesse importunity to her wooers, was driuen to seeke a knot in a Rush, and with policy to preuent that which the honest and honorable pretence of her chastity was not able to defend. She therfore beguiling time with labour, hauing begun a webbe wherein she spent the day, to keep her selfe from ydelnesse, knowing that Otia si tollus 
                     〈◊〉
                   cupidinis arcus, gaue answer, that when her worke was finished she wold make a choice of some one of them for her husband. The Noble men who knew that as ye work was not great, the dated time could not be long, contented themselues with this reply, which somewhat eased the mind of Penelope: but when she fell into consideration with herselfe, that the longest Sommer hath his Autumne, the largest sentence his Period, and the greatest labour his performance, she began to be melancholy til Loue had learned her a shift to make her work endles, by vntwisting as much in the night as shée woue in the day: this policy put in practice, (for that the night the friend of sweet and golden sléepes grudged that her benefits should be despised by the restlesse labour of such a politick huswife) she determined accompanied with her Nurse and two Maides, to passe away the time in parle, thinking thus both to further her content, and procure paine to bée mittigated by such pleasing delights: seeing therefore that her Nurse began to nodde and her Maides to winke, she wakened them out of their dreames with this mercy chat. I can but smile (Nurse) to sée how time maketh a distinction of ages by affections, and the disposition of the sences followes truely the temperature &amp; constitution of theyr bodies, as a particuler instance makes manifest: for the time of the night (growing to rest) summons both you and my Maydes to sleepe: yet though the affectis al one the effects are diuers▪ for age whom nature hath stored
with imperfection and disease, and therefore fréed from the taxe
of disquieted thoughts, teacheth the sences by the desire of sleep,
how the number of your yeres are dated vnto death: that with
Antisthenes wee may say how the bed r
                  •
               sembleth the graue,
and ye closing of the sences the dissoluing of life: my maides whō
youth perswades vnto rest, and want of care, prooues that the
blacke Oxe neuer troade on their féete, onely cares how to serue
time▪ for that no other care hath yet bitten them by the héele, &amp;
so resoluing their minds in quiet by such content, séekes to pleasure
the sences by swéet slumbers: but I poore soule whom fortune
hath set as a subiect, wheron to worke the variable points
of her inconstancy, finde my sences so countermanded with disquieted
thoughts, as desire of content drawes mée into a laborinth
of restlesse passions.
            
               Eubula one of her Maides that was most familiar with her
Lady, made this pretty and pithy reply: I remember (Madam)
that Ph
                     •
                  dias, drawing the counterfaite of youth, f
                  •
               gureth labour
as the task-master of his actions, &amp; ease as the paymaster of his
deserts: meaning as I can coniecture by the Embleame, that as
it behoueth youth to spend the day in worke, whereby to auoide
the sugred snares that idlenesse layeth to intrap the sences: so
the guerdō for such forward inde
                  •
               ours is to consume the night
in swéet and quiet slumbers, least the vitall spirits ouercharged
with too much labour, should either grudge at too sore an impost,
or else fall to inconuenience by ouerlong toyle and watchings:
Extremity is euer a vice, too much in euery thing is hurtful, and
the greatest prodigality is the expence of the eye: I meane not
(Madame) in gazing want
                  •
               nly, but in watching ouer niggardly:
which when I consider how prodigal your honour is in this
point, I cannot but (as euer I haue done) merua
                  •
               le at your wisdome
and vertue, so now to wonder at your loue and constancy:
forthinking with my self that your Grace is seated in a Throne
of Maiesty, adorned with a Scepter and a Dyadem, honoured
with the possession of a Kingdome &amp; the tytle of a Quéene, rich,
beautifull and young, the very aduocates of vanity: and séeing

that the affection your Highnes beares to Vlisses, the loue to
your Husband, the vow to your Lord, though in long absence
still qua
                  •••
               fies the forenamed pleasures with the swéet deaw of a
modest chastity: I must (Madame) without flattery say, that in
requitall of such constant affection, the Gods in iustice must
crowne you with immortality, and the world reward you with
fame and honour.
            Indéed quoth Vygenia (for so was her second Maide called)
when I sée maiesty a contented copartner with labor, and a resolute
farewell to ease: the chosen companion to a Quéene, I
cannot thinke but loue is a great Lord, that in a womans affections
worketh such straunge effects. Take héede quoth Ismena
(which was the last and youngest of the thrée) that in this word
loue, you deceiue not your selfe: for there is an Amphibological
equiuocation in it, which drowneth y• hearers oft in a laborinth
of perplexed conceipts. As how quoth Penelope, let vs heare
you make this distinction? Ismena that was young and very
quicke witted, willing to content her Ladies humour by beguiling
the night with prattle, applying as well her fingers to the
web as her tongue to the tale, went forward thus in her description.
Although (Madame) experience hath not taught mée to set
downe the diuers effects of Loue, yet the Phisition by reading▪
oft knoweth the nature of the Simple as well as the Gardner
that planteth it: &amp; he which séeth Fortune standing on a Globe,
may iudge she is fickle though he try not her incōstancy: many
speak of the Crocadiles teares that neuer felt her deceipts, and
diuers condemne Diogenes for a sinick that saw not his Tub:
The Shoomaker corrected Appelles picture, yet he kn
                  •
               w not
the vse of the Pensell: &amp; I may by your honours patience talke
of Venus Temple that neuer smelt the fume of her Sacrifice:
but to say what I haue heard, thus to the matter. Anacreon,
Menander and Ouid, with others, who were studious in this
amorous Philosophy, haue as they set down principles, so penned
down precepts, wherby the fond and variable effects of loue
is manifestly deciphered, calling it by the name of a God, as vnder
that tytle bewraying the forceable efficacie that by a predominant

quality, it doth infuse into humane minds: other whiles
a Fury, as discouering the sorrows, griefes, and disquiets that
procéeded from such a furious humour, pain
                  •
               ing Cupid blind,
as noting the selfconceipt in choice, like a little boy, as figuring
small gouernment, not leueled by the proportion of reason, winged,
as absolutely pourtaying inconstant and fickle passions of
Louers, whose thoughts are variable, whose ioyes are momē
               tary,
like to the shadows which Iuno presented to the Giants,
bringing forth like the Ceader trées faire leaues but no 
                  ••
               ui
                  •
               es,
and as the Date hauing soft rindes, but with in stones as hard
as stéele: This loue (Madame) presented by Venus as an inueagle
obiect, no sooner entreth the eye but he pierceth the heart, not
accompanied with vertue to perswade, but armed with the outward
hew of beauty to constraine, which what effect soeuer ensueth,
waxeth at last sorrow and repentance: Such was the loue
of Dido to Aeneas, that séeing the curious forme of the dissembling
stranger, through too ouer hasty affection, did both ruinate
herselfe and her Kingdome. Ariadna by crediting the swéete
tales of Theseus, Med
                     •
                  a of Iason, Phillis of Demophon, and infinite
other, which entring into this passion runs headlong after
endlesse repentance.
            This loue is like the Baaran Leafe which séene pleaseth, but
touched pierceth the skinne, this loue is that which ouerruling
yong heads, sotteth the sences, dulleth the wittes, hindreth quiet,
and maketh a passionate confusion in the minde of man called
by the title of loue, which indéed is méer
                  •
                lust and vanity: wheras
true and perfect loue hath his foundation vpon vertue onely,
ayming at the inward perfection of the mind, not at y• outward
complection of the body, which decreaseth not but increaseth wt 
time, vniting the harts with such strickt leages of amity, that it

                  •
               ccounteth all labour a pleasure, to shew endles desire by effects,
as (Madam) to infer your self for an instance▪ who not po
                  •
               
               sessed
with this fond fury, which mē faine to come from Venus,
but that settled fancy, which we are sure procéedes from vertue,
although the Prince Vlisses hath ten yéeres béen absent at the
siedge of 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , and report in this space hath made sundry and

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
time nor pretence of loue can euer be able to reconcile where De
                  
                     •••
                  pita

                     〈◊〉
                  
                olde age whom diseases hath tyed to the Crouch,
will now with the babe returne to the Cradel: that stoo
                  •
               ing to
the graue by burden of ouer many yéers, wil yet offer a toothles
Sacrifice to Venus for a young husband: this well may becalled
a mariage of Labour, where the maried couples so inequall
in match, are continually troubled with a spirit of dissention▪ for
as the fower Elements are different in their properties, so are
these disagreeing in their manners: the earth &amp; ayre are not placed
well in one ballance: the fire and water brookes not the selfe

                  •
               amelimites: age and youth may conioyne in law but not in
loue, sith the sanguine complection of the one, &amp; the melancholye
&amp; saturnine cōstitutiō of the other, are alwaies in thoughts,
effecte, and desires opposite ex dyametro: so that by the opinion
of Aristotle they be as it were immediat contraries: which
Dyonisius the elder noted very, well, when séeing his Mother
passing old and ouer growne with age, desirous to mary a yong
stripling, told her that it was in her power to violate the lawes
of Syracusa, but not the lawes of nature: this affirmeth Plato in
his Androgina, &amp; agréeth to the censure of Dionisius, affirming
that marriage in olde Women is with the Giants bellum ger
                     ••
                  e,
cum Diis, which the Romane Lady Valeria well noted, who alwaies
had this saying in her mouth, that her husband dyed to
others, but liued to her foreuer. And héerin can I commend my
good daughter Penelope, that hating such marriages of labour,
doth intend both toliue and dye to Vlisses. Nay good Nurse
quoth Penelope, lets heare your last distinction, I meane the
mariage of griefe: tis Madam quoth she, where the old prouerb
is sulsil'd, better one house troubled then two, I meane where a
bad husband is coupled with a bad wife, where the one striueth
to ouercome the other, not in vertuous actions, but in disquiet
and murmurings. I cannot thinke quoth Penelope, that there
is any husband so bad, which the honest gouernment of his wife
may not in time reforme, especially if she kéep those three speciall
points that are requisite in euery woman, Obedience, Chastity,
and Silence, thrée such graces Nurse, as may reclay me

the most gracelesse husband in the world: and because my mayds
are young, and may in time trie the fortune of mariage, we wil
this night discourse of this poynt, to discouer the effects and efficacie
of obedience: which (for that I wil be first in this newe deuised
disputation) I will take in hand to discourse of, that both
we may beguile the night with prattle, and profite our mynds
by some good and vertuous precepts.
            The maides hearing their Lady in so good a vain were glad,
and therfore setting their hands to the Web, and their eares to
hir talke, Penelope began in this manner. Zenobia the wife of
Radamysius, King of Armenia, being demanded of a Lady in
her Court, how she procured hir husband so déepely to loue hir
as he feared in any wise to offer her occasion of displeasure, answered
by fearing ot displease him, meaning that the chiefest
point of wisdome in a good wife, is to make a conquest of her
husband by obedience. Aristides the true and perfect Iusticiari
                  •
               
of his time, caused the portraiture of a woman figured on her
knées, to be caried before y• Brydes at their espousals, to signifie
that they meant now to obey &amp; submit, not to rule or command,
for quoth he, such fond and fanastick women as make choise of
effeminate Husbands, thereby to challenge a soueraine superiority
ouer them, may rightly be compared to chose presumptuous
fooles y• had rather be masters of blind men, then seruants
to the discréete and learned, which caused Plato in his Androgina
to say that a wise woman ought to thinke hir husbands maners
ye lawes of her life, which if they be good, she must take as
a forme of her actions, if they be bad, she must brooke with patience:
His reason is thus. As a looking glasse or Christal though
most curiously set in Ebonie, serueth to small purpose if it doth
not liuely represent the proportion and lineaments of the face
inspicient: so a woman, though rich &amp; beautifull, deserueth smal
prayse or fauour, if the course of her life be not directed after her
husbands compasse. And as ye Mathematicall lines which Geometricians
doe figure in their carracters, haue no motiō of them
selues, but in the bodies wherin they are placed, so ought a wife
to haue no proper nor peculiar passion or affection, vnlesse framed

               ans, prouiding Soldiours, money and Munition, took her iourney
as farre as Athens, where she receiued letters from Anthony
to returne backe to Rome, which she with great obedience
performed, sending him al the forenamed necessaries, although
she perfectly knew that Cleopatra was with him in the fielde:
But when the warres betwixt him and Augustus were ended,
he sent straight to commaund Octauia that she should depart
from his house, which she did so obediently, that Rome after her
death would haue erected an Image in her praise, but that Augustus
would not suffer it, kéeping Anthonies children, that hée
had by his first wife, with such care and diligence, as it did wel
note to the world her loue and obedience. To confirme which
more at large, I will rehearse a pleasant history.
            
               Penelopes Tale.
               
                  
                     SAladine the Souldan of Aegipt, who by his prowesse
had made a generall conquest of the Southeast
part of the world, tooke to wife Barmenissa the
onely daughter and heyre of the great Chan, who
amongst sundry Sutors not inferiour to him in parentage
and progeny, yet made such a carefull choyce of this
yong Aegiptian Prince, not for his beauty (for that Nature had
denied him that fauour) but for his vertue (fith he was wise and
valiant) that imprinting the perfection of his mind with a déep
insight into the déepest place of her heart, and sealing the knot of
fancy with y• signet fo mariage, she neuer so much as in thought
crost him with any discourtesie: yet for that men are the subiects
of Fortune and therfore variable, and the true disciples of time,
and therefore momentary, he began to loath that in the fruite
which he loued in the bud, &amp; to spurne at that in ye saddle, which
he secretly vsed in the cradle, repaying the faith of Bermenissa,
not with flattery to inueagle her, but with foule language t
                     •
                  e
better to manifest his hate: which although Nature forbad her
to brooke, yet obedience the Heralt y• best imblazeth loue, taught

her that against such sorrow there was no better salue then patience:
that reuenge in a woman was not to be executed by the
band, but by the hart, and yet not with rigour but with clemency
persisting in this opinion, Olinda the Concubine which Saladine
so greatly loued, sent a letter to this effect.
               
                  
                     Olinda to Saladine health.
                     IF the inward affects of the minde be manifested by outward
effects or the brow the bashful bewrayer of secrets, and yet
the true discouerer of thoughts, may bée credited, the Emperour
of Aegipt in his loues resembleth the Pyne trée, whose
leaues remaine in one colour but one day: Well might the censures
fo wise Clarks haue bin caueats of my likely misfortune:
for they say Princes affections as they are glorious so they are
brittle: that he fauour of Kings hangs in their eye lids ready
with euery winke to be wiped out: that as they are full of Maiesty
and aboue law, so they are full of incōstancy, because without
law: this which other spoke by proofe, now I alledge by experience:
for your Highnes abridgeth me of my wonted allowance,
not onely in expence but in lookes, so that I account that
day happy when Saladine but glanceth at Olinda. The mistris
of my mishap is thy iniurious wife Barmenissa, to whō I wish
thy ill fortunes &amp; my miseries: she with a fained obedience séeketh
to inueagle thée with a conceipt of her loue, who if shée did
loue, could not content, for she wants the eye pleasure, beauty:
thou tickled with an inconstant humour dost listen to the melody
of the old Syren, whose necke shadowed with wrinckles affoords
but had harmony: Kéep not (Saladine) fire and water in
one hand: in running with the Hare hold not with the Hound:
beare not both a Sword and an Oliue. Paris gaue sentence but
on Venus part, affection brooketh no diuision? therefore if thou
loue Olinda, hate Barmenissa: follow the example of Anthony,
who after his choyce of thy Countriwoman neuer fauoured
Octauia: tis beauty that mertis a Crowne, and as well would
the Diadem of Aegipt beséeme they Lemons head, as thy wiues:

I should, and yet were loth to flatter in saying what I would
not: but if I may haue free libertie to speake what I think, my
verdit shall be soone giuen. I confesse that what pleaseth the father
ought to content the sonne: and therefore I count the will
of Saladyne a lawe to Garinter: yet as obedience wisheth a consent,
so Nature willeth with a friendly denyall to diswade from
things that offende not onely men, but y• are euen hatefull to the
Gods. I say therefore that Saladyne should get more honour by
exyling Olynda, not onely from Babylon, but out of all the confines
of Aegipt, then if he had obtayned more tryumphes then
that inuincible Caesar. No doubt your Grace shall soone, nay I
feare to soone, finde my words to be true, that in hoping to get a
swéete content you gayne a sower mislike: like to them which
pleased with the colour of the trée Lotos, are poysoned assoone as
they taste of the Apples.
                  
               
               
                  Barmenissa, hearing how sharply her sonne shooke vp the Emperour,
with a modest countenance, as nothing grudging at the
iniurie of fortune, at her last farewell gaue him this charge: Although
sonne the law of nature willes thée to be partner of thy
mothers misfortunes, yet the Gods, whose lawes are aboue nature,
commaunds that thou gainsay not the Edict of thy father:
For as Proclus the Academick affirmes, there is nothing which
we ought more to regard then duetie and obedience: the commaunde
of the father is not to bée limited by the conceipt of the
child, for as their superiority is without proportiō, so their wils
ought to be without denials, first the frowne of a father (saith Epictetus)
is like the eleuation of a Commet which foreshewes
euer some fatall and finall ruine. Then Garinter offend not
thy father in thought, least the gods grudging at thy secret disobedience
plague thée with an open reuenge: further sonne, thou
art his subiect, and be thy soueraine, what duetie is due to such a
mighty potentate thou must by law and conscience offer vnto
him. And séeing by the consent of the Aegiptian lawes I am deposed,
and O
                        ••
                     nda inuested with the regall crowne: if a mothers
commaund may be a constraint to the sonne. I charge thée that
thou shew her the same obedience that belongs to a Princesse,

and thy fathers wife, Philarkēs y• sonne of Psamnet
                        •
                     chus 
                  
                     •
                  beyed
Rhodope, whom his father raised from a common courteza
                     •
                   to
a Princesse. Antiochus the sonne of Demetrius buil
                     •
                  ed stately
Sepulchres for his fathers Concubines: Reuenge (son) ought
not to go in purple, but in white, &amp; the salue for iniuries i
                     •
                   not
choller but patience: for myne owne part Garinter I set thée
down no precept but y• which my self meane to hould for a principle,
and thou by imitating thy mothers actions, shew thy selfe
to be duetiful, which if thou performe, I will continnually pray
to the Gods of thy good, otherwise, if for my cause thou intend
reuenge, I wish thy ill: &amp; so wishing to thy father as to my soueraigne,
&amp; to the Princesse as to one honored with a Diademe, I
take my leaue at yt Court, as wel cōtent with my aduersitie, for
y• it is ye kings cōmaund, as euer I was wi
                     •
                  h prosperitie: And
with this the Princesse departed, leauing both her sonne and the
Nobles passing pensiue for her present disgrace, The Souldan
not satisfied with this iniurie, caused presently Proclamatiō to
be made, that the Princesse should haue no reliefe, but what she
earned with her hands, that her ladies should be labour, and her
maintenance, no other then her owne indeuour could prouide:
This edict commaunded to be published, the King solempnised
his marriage with sumptuous showes and triumphes, &amp; Garinter
that he might shew how carefull he was to obey his mothers
last command, broght in Maskes and comicall delightes
to finish vp the solempnitie of y• nuptials. The festiual time being
past, Olinda puffed vp with a swéete conceipt of her prosperitie,
so ruled and ouerruled in her gouerment, vsing such tiranny
in words, and perswading her Husband to such disordred actions,
that she generally fell in hate of all the people, in so much
that the Souldan himselfe grudged at her ambitious presumptions:
Well leauing her to her follies, againe to the Lady Barmenissa,
who fallen from a Crowne to a Cottage, and from a
Scepter almost to a Scrip, stil salued her want with labour and
her pauertie with patiēce, bearing as princely a mind in aduersitie,
as she did in prosperity, neither grudging at iniury, nor gaping
after reuenge, staied thus vpon this vertuous founda
                     •
                  ion,

                     
                     The happy fates thy sor
                           •
                        ows haue withstood,
                     By syning want and pouerty thy share.
                     For now content (f
                           •
                        nd fortune to despight)
                     VVith patience lows thee quiet and delight.
                  
               
               
                  Barmenissa had no sooner ended her madrigale, but that she
heard a great noise, which at the first amazed her, but at the last
she perceiued it to be the voice of men: desirous therfore to bée a
partner of their secrecy, she kept her selfe silent wtin the thicket,
when she perceiued certaine of the nobles of Aegipt y• were retyred
to that solitary place, to confer of the ambitious supremicy
that Olinda vsed since her Coronation, and amongst the rest one
of the Lords, whose name was Egistus, burst foorth into these
tearmes.
               
                  Egistus Oration to the
Lords of Egipt.
                  IT is not vnknowne (right Honorable Lordes of Aegipt) not
onely to vs, but to the whole Empire, how the King, seduced
by the flattering allurements of a Strumpet, hath not onely
violated the law of our Gods, in prophaning the nuptiall Bed,
made sacred by the holy law of Matrimony, but also the law of
Aegipt, which forbiddeth diuorce wtout cause: but sith in a Monarchy
the willes of Princes may abide no ch
                        •
                     ck, but their reasons
(how soeuer vnreasonable) are the principles y• may not be
infringed, it resteth only for vs to complaine, but not to redresse:

                        〈◊〉
                      ayming more at y• weale of our coūtry thē our own liues,
we set our rest on the hazard and so desperatly throw at al. First
let vs consider that Saladine the mighty Souldan of Aegipt,
puffed vp with the Highnes of his Maiesty, and number of his

                        •
                     errisories subiect to his gouernment, hath been so tyrannous
to his commons from his first Coronation, that vnlesse his unmod
                        ••
                     ate
pride and presumption, had bin mittigated by the verteous
clemency of his wife, the burthen of his cruelty long time

since had béen intollerable: but now hauing deposed that péerelesse
Princesse, whose vertues made her famous, and vs happy,
and maried a Concubine, whose vanities bréedes her enuy and
our mishap: we are to look for no other euent but our particuler
ill fortune, and the generall ruyne of the weale publicke. Then
my Lords, least we should be spotted with the staine of ingratitude,
in suffering the Princesse iniury vnreuenged: and least we
should séeme to be borne more for our selues then our Country,
let vs attempt the restitution of the Queene, and the fatal ouerthrow
of the insolent Concubine, although death and daunger
were the end of our enterprize: The plot my Lords I haue laid
by impoysoning her cup at the next supper: but with this prouisō,
that no intent of treachery, shall so much as in thought bée
pretended to the person of our Soueraigne, whom next vnder ye
Gods we are bound to loue &amp; reuerence. This my Lords is my
purpose, wherto if you consent, I meane this night to put it in
practise: otherwise to craue that my spéeches may bée buried in
silence.
                  
                     Egistus hauing ended his Oration, the Lordes not only gaue
their frée consent, but also sware to be secret, and to be ayders in
his defence, if any iniury should be offred for his enterprise: and
vpon this resolution they departed. Barmenissa (who all this
while held her self close in the Couert) hauing heard their determination,
was surprised with such sodaine ioy, that at last shée
burst foorth into these spéeches.
                  Now Bermenissa, thou séest that delay in reuenge is the best
Phisicke: that the Gods are iust and haue taken thy quarrel as
aduocates of thine iniury: now shalt thou sée wrong ouer ruled
with patience, and the iuyne of thine enemy with the safety of
thine owne honour▪ time is the discouerer of mishap, and Fortune
neuer ceaseth to stretch her strings til they cracke: shame is
the end of trechery, and dishonour euer forerunnes repentance,
Olinda hath soard with 
                        
                           •
                        ca
                           •
                        us, &amp; is like to fall with Phaeton:
sooner are bruses caught by reaching too hye, then by stooping too
low: Fortune g
                        •
                     udgeth not at them which fall, but enuy bytes
thē which climbes; now shall the Lords of Aegipt by reuenging

dound to both your contentments: and then she made manifest
the pretence of those Noble men.
                  
                     Olinda amazed at this sodaine newes (as base myndes are
euer fearefull) desired the Souldan that they might hye home,
least some treason in that place were intended: for (quoth she) I
knowe, whatsoeuer she saies, that Barmenissa was the author of
this treacherie, whose life, how long so euer it be, is ye continuance
of my sorrows. The Souldan whom cōscience began now
to sting at the very hart, turned his backe without farewell, and
no sooner came at the Court, but caused the Lords that were fauourers
of this treason to be apprehended, who willingly confessed
their intended determination, with resolution either to
die or to perform it. The King, perceiuing their obstinacie, cō
                     mitted
them to warde: and now to make proofe of Olyndas patience,
he counterfeated a more déeper affection then euer he did,
and for confirmation thereof, he gaue her free libertie to make
choise of thrée things without denyall whatsoeuer she would
craue: which Olynda taking kindly, desired this graunt to bee
sollemnely giuen before the Péers of Aegipt: Upon this request
the Souldan made Proclamation throughout all his Empyre,
that the Nobility should within fiftéene daies appeare at Memphis,
where then he kept his Court with notice also that vppon
that day the Quéene should fréely aske thrée things of the
Souldan without denyall. The commons greatly grudged at
this graunt, and began to mutinie, that a gracelesse Concubine
should reape such fauours without desart. The olde Empresse,
partaker also of this newes, willing to forwarne the Princesse
of ambition, determined with herselfe to send her certaine verses,
as a cauea
                        •
                     e for so warie a choyce. Wellleauing her to her
Poems: the Nobility and many of the Commons at the dated
tyme came, where in the Parliament house the Souldan reuealed
the cause of their comming: namely, to be witnesses of his
graunt and her demaund▪ 
                     Olynda fearing the worst, caused the
King sollemnely to sweare, that he should not reuoke whatsoeuer
he had promised. The Souldan taking aduice, made this
sollemne prostetation, and sware by the God of the Aegiptians,
                     
that whatsoeuer he had promised to the right and lawfull Quéene of AEgipt, he would performe. Olynda settling her selfe to vtter her mind, was interrupted by a messenger that came from Barmenissa with a scrole. The Shuldan understanding to what effect it tended, caused it openly to be read: the contents whereof were the verses following, ouer which was written this lattin sentence. Tempora mutantur, &amp; nos mutan
                           •
                        or in illis.
                  
                  
                     
                        Aspiring thoughts led Phaeton 
                           
                              〈◊〉
                           
                        
                        Proud Icarus did fall he sour'd so hye:
                        Seeke not to clymbe with fond Semyramis,
                        
                        Least Sonne reuenge the fathers iniury.
                        Take heede, Ambition is a 
                              〈◊〉
                            ill
                        That fortune layes, presumptuous minds to spill.
                     
                     
                        The bitter griefe that frets the quiet minde,
                        The sting that prickes the froward man to woe:
                        Is Enuy, which in honour seld we finde,
                        And yet to honour sworne a secret foe.
                        Learne this of me, enuy not others state,
                        The fruites of enuie is enuy and hate.
                     
                     
                        The misty cloude that so eclipseth fame,
                        That gets reward a Chaos of dispight,
                        Is blacke reuenge which euer winneth shame,
                        A fury vilde thats hatched in the night.
                        Beware, seeke not reuenge against thy foe,
                        Least once reuenge thy fortune ouergoe.
                     
                     
                        These blasing Commets doe foreshew mishap,
                        Let not the flaming lights offend thine eyes:
                        Looke ere thou leape, preuent an after clap:
                        These three forewarn'd well mayst thou flye.
                        If now by choyce though aymest at happy health, 
                        Eschew selfe-loue, choose for the Common Wealth.
                     
                  
                  
                     〈2… pages missing〉
                  
                  
                     
heard his melody &amp; diuers landed at Samos that sayles not to Corinth, 
                     
                        〈…〉
                      is not the discouerie of affection: neither to the talke of a husband the proofe of mariage: but feeling where your owne shooe 
                        〈◊〉
                      ye, you aime at the straightnesse of my last.
                  
                     Ismena hearing hir fellowes at such drye blowes, told them that how 
                        〈◊〉
                      so euer they made it, their s
                        •
                     ken throtes would easily digest such 
                        〈…〉
                      (quoth she I dare sweare the precisest of you both had rather a husbād thē heare of him, seeing your yeares are enough and your minds not vowed to Minerua.
                  
                  
                     Penelope could not but smile at the chollericke prattle of her mayds and yet for that the night was farre spent &amp; her Nurse in a sound sleepe, she tooke vp their controuersie, concluding wt the opiniō of her maid Ismenia, that they had rather follow Iuno to the Temple then Diana to the Woods: and rather sing with Himenius thē weepe with Vesta. Well, the maids whose conscience told them their Mistris propheste was truth, agréed to hir principles with silence: and Penelope waking her Nurse, mannerly foulding by her 
                        〈◊〉
                      went quietly to her rest.
               
            
            
               The second nights discourse.
               AFter that the day was come, &amp; the Sutors had filled the
stately Pallace of 
                     
                        •
                     enelope with their seuerall traynes,
ye Princesse put on hermourning attyre, which alwa
                     ••
                  s
she was accustomed to weare since the absence of Vlisses: shewing
her selfe (as Antisthenes commaunded) a good wi
                     •
                  e discontent
in her husbands absence, y• thereby she might both bewray
the perfection of her loue, and quallifie the passionate d
                     •
                  sires of
her Sutors: which séeing her dayly busie about her Web, and
yet her labour (like Belyde
                        •
                     
                   Daughters to powre water into
bottomelesse Tubs) endlesse, could not comprehend within the
compasse of their imagination▪ what the reason of this should be,
seeing so carefully shee endeuoured her selfe to bring her worke
to an end. Well, resting in hope y• time should ease their longing,

they spent the day in sundry pleasant pas
                     •
                  imes and seuerall
discourses, til the Sunne declining to the West, they departed.
               
                  Penelope glad of their absence, séeing that Phoebus had lodg
                  
                     •
                  d
himselfe with Ty
                        •
                     an, and Venus the swéet messenger of the
silent night appeared in the Skye, accompanied as before with
her Nurse and her maids, she went to her old talke, vntwisting
that in the night, which before she had wt great labor wrought
in the day. Sitting thus busily at their worke, the olde Nurse
(who by the last nights prattle had found the length of Penelopes
                  
                     •
                  oote) began to waken them out of their dumps in this maner.
I maruel, when I consider with my selfe that y• 
                  Romaines
who couetto surpasse the Gre
                        •
                     ians in all honorable &amp; vertuous
actions, did not sée into their owne follies, whē they erect 
                     •
                  ē
                  ples
vnto Flo
                        •
                     a, as a Goddesse worthy of deuine Sacrifice, appointing
in honour of her funeral day certain laiciuious sports
and pastimes, called after her name Floralia, she being a most
vile and infamous Courtizane, and discrediting y• state of their
Common wealth with her incontinencie: &amp; yet grudge to errect
an Image in the memorie of Lucrece, that with her inuiolable
chastitie, not onely honoured the Romaine vertue, but fréed y•
                  
                     •
                  ittie from the burthen of a Tyrant. The reason as I gesse
(quoth Penelope) is for that the nature of man is so corrupt &amp;
addicted too vice, that what vanity presents, they still (be if neuer
so had) kéep it as an obiect to their eyes: but what is veriously
performed they commit to obliuions charge to reward. In déed
(quoth Is
                        •
                     enia) now I perceiue y• my doubt is absolued, which
long hath holdē me in suspence: for long haue I mused why only
in all the whole world Diana hath a Temple in Ephesus, and
Venus is commonly honored as the household God 
                     
                        •
                     ar, that
hath a corner in euery mans kitchin: for in Paphos, Cipres, Athens,
Samos, Rome, and infinite other Citties, her Temples
stand in the streetes, di
                     •
                  couering the erecters deuotions by the
costly and sum
                     •
                  tuous buildings. And yet (quoth Eubula) the
Vestals in Rome, who were dedicated to virginitie, bare Palme
aboue the rest: for the Senators apparelled in their Robes of
Maiestie, neuer met any of thē in the streete but they gaue thē
                  
credit then voluptuousnesse, so nothing getteth more honour &amp;
glory then chastity. The consideration whereof, moued Iulius
Caesar rather to suffer a diuorce, thē an incōtinent wife, wishing
if Gracchus had liued in his daies, that he might haue made an
exchange of y• Empresse for his chast wife Cornelia so highly did
that Monarch estéeme of that vertue Chastity saith Epictetus
is the very faire and redolent blossomes that the trée of true and
perfect loue doth afford, yéelding so swéet and fragrant a 
                     ••
                  uour
that the most vicious and unbridled 
                     •
                  us
                     •
                   and 
                     〈…〉
                   by the
smell of such a deuine perfume. Euripedes entring into the consideration
of this vertue, crieth out, as wondring at the excellency
thereof. O how is chastity to be estéemed, that is the cause of
such great glory and honour amongst woman: for it sheweth
the feare she oweth to the Gods, the loue she beareth to her husband,
the care she hath of same, the small desire to inordinate affections,
and maketh her a woman, a very patterne of supernaturall
perfection. Hipsicratea being demaunded what was her
richest Iewel, answered chastity, alluding to the opinion of Crates
the Philosopher, who was wont to say: this 
                     〈◊〉
                  
ornament that adorneth, &amp; that thing adorneth a woman which maketh
her more honorable: and this is not done by Iewels of Golde,
Emeralds, Precious stones or sumptuous attyre, but by euery
thing that causeth her to be accounted honest, wise, humble and
chast. The Emperour Aurelius made certaine lawes to inhibite superfluity of attyre, affirming y
                     •
                   such y
                     •
                   curiously paint out
themselues with 
                     〈…〉
                  , swéete perfumes, and straunge
ornaments of pompe 
                     〈…〉
                   nobility of birth vrge them to such
brauery) make men most dissolute and subiect to folly: especially
if such sumptuous sh
                     •
                  ws be ayded with a rowling eye and vnchast
look wheras a wise woman through her honest behauior
and modest countenance, lead as many as cast their eyes vpon
her, to a continent reuerence of Chastity. Socrates was wont
to say, that when a maried wife holdeth her looking glasse in her
hand, she should speake thus to her self, if she be foule: what then
should become of me if I should be also wicked? &amp; if she be faire:
how shal my beauty be accounted of, if I continue wise and honest?

for a hard fauoured woman that is renouned for her chasti
                  
                     •
                  y,
is more honorable then she which is famous for her beauty:
The reco
                     •
                  ds that speake honorably of the Romaine Ladies, tel
vs that the wife of a poor Smith méeting the Empresse Faustina,
tooke the wall of her in the stréetes, whereat the Empresse
grudging, complained to the Senate, who sending for the poore
woman, &amp; demaunding of her if she committed the déed? she denyed
it not, and therefore her husband was condemned in a certaine
summe▪ vppon which sentence the woman appealed from
the Senate to the Emperour, who asked what she could say for
her self? As muchquoth she, as (if thou be iust and wise) may suffice.
For although I am not so honorable as thy wife, yet I am
more honest, and the Cittizens of Rome ought to es
                     •
                  éeme vertue
before dignity: the Emperour vpon this discharged the womā
of the sentence Alexander the great hauing at the conquest of
Babylon taken a very wel 
                     •
                  auoured Egiptian Lady, a widdow
whom for her beauty he did greatly affectionate, at night commaunded
one of his Captaines to bring her to his Tent, which
she boldly refused, willing him to say to the King, that captiuity
was no priuiledge to infringe chastily, and if he went about to
dishonor her, she would peruert such violence by death: this answere
returned 
                     •
                  o Alexander; he not onely moderated his desire,
but sent her his Signet, as a warrant of her safety▪ 
                  Portia
the wife of Brutus, was told by one of her seruants, that certaine
Embassadore of Samos were come, which were passing beautifull
and wel proportioned men: holde thy 
                     〈◊〉
                   foole quoth she,
wouldst thou haue ince prepare a poyson for mine honour by
the meanes of mine eye? Cyrus King of Pe
                        •
                     s
                        •
                     a making warres
against the Sythians, had for his Pryze of the triumph a very
faire woman called Panther, who being the wife of Ab
                        •
                     adatas
his enemy, being desired of Cirus for his concubine, she told him
that she was chast, the king little respecting this short answere,
demaunded a further resolution, why quoth Panther? can there
be any other answer, that is not cōprehended in this word, chastity?
héereby noting that the Antidote against, the enuenomed
thoughts of mens alluring intisements, and the surest corrosiue

to roote out such vnbridled desir
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   draw thē to in
                     •
                  rdin
                     •
                  te affecti
                     •
                  n
is this pretio
                     •
                  s Iewel of chastity, the which the more to
confirme, I will rehearse vnto you 
                     •
                   pleasant History, which
hapned not long since within our dominions of Ithaca.
               
            
            
               Penelopes second tale.
               IN this Countrey of Ithaca not long sin
                     •
                  e, there dwelled a
Nobleman called Calamus, of parentage honorable, as allyed
to the bloud Royall: of possessions rich, as one of the greatest
reuenewes in all the Country: but therwithall so wedded to the
vaine suppose of pleasure and delight, that his friends sorrowed
at the course of his vnbridled follies, &amp; his poor tennants groned
not vnder the burd
                     •
                  n of his 
                     •
                  ouetous desires, but were taxed wt 
the griefe of his voluptuous appetite, for such was the incontinēcy
of his life, as s
                     •
                  ciety of wāton aff
                     •
                  ctions neuer glutted his
mind with content: But as the Serpent Hida
                        •
                     pis, the more hée
drinketh the more he is 
                     •
                   thirst, &amp; as the Sala
                        •
                     and
                        •
                     r, th
                     •
                   more
he lyeth in the fire, 
                     ••
                  e more desirous he is of the flame, so Calamus,
the more he off
                     •
                  nded in this intemperate concupiscence, the
more his thoughts were adicted to y• vice, so as al his neighbors
did wish he might fall head-long into the Center of some déepe
misfortune. Wallowing thus in the sel
                     •
                   conceipt of his wickednes,
on a day as he rode on hunting with certaine of his gentlemen,
he stumbled by cha
                     •
                  nce at a 
                     •
                  armers house, whether as he
road to taste a cup of their smal wine, for y• the wel her was hot,
where he espied a woman homely attired, of modest coūtenance,
her face imported both loue and grau
                     •
                  ty, who séeing t
                     •
                  e Noble
man approch, dying her christal chéekes with a vermillion 
                     •
                  ue,
after humble salutations brought him in a country C
                     •
                  use such
drinke as their cottage did afford. Calamus narrowly marking
the proportion of this country huswife, courteously tooke his
leaue &amp; departed, but the sparkes of lust that had kindled a flame
of desire in his fancie, perplexed his minde with sundry passions:
For calling to mind not onely her exterior be auiy, adorned
with sundry and seueral graces, but also her inward perfection,

bewrayng that she was both wise and honest, he 
                     •
                  ell into this
conside
                     •
                  ation with himselfe: For shame (Calamus) let not thy
thoughts w
                     •
                  nder in a laborinth to be endlesse: Séeing y• flower
of thy youth hath 
                     〈◊〉
                   spent in vice, let the fruite of thyne age
on
                     •
                  ly 
                     〈◊〉
                   of 
                     〈◊〉
                   if the Gods had not the firstlings of thy
yeeres, yet let thē haue thy gray head in pawne of a Sacra
                     •
                  ice:
time is 
                     〈…〉
                   from vanity and vice: thy foot is stepping to
the graue, &amp; oport
                     •
                  nity 
                     •
                  ids thée tak hold of repentance. Venus
is printed without wrinc
                     ••
                  os, as signif
                     •
                  ing she is the Goddesse
of youth what of this, 
                     •
                  ond 
                     •
                  oole, suppose thou wert young, shalt
thou therfore 
                     〈…〉
                  : Doe not the Gods forbid
thée to craue y• y• i
                     •
                   another mans due: Are not volupiuous

                     〈◊〉
                   to be suppressed as well in the young 
                     〈◊〉
                   as in the old
trée: Is thy 
                     •
                  alloy so fickle as 
                     〈◊〉
                   must be vewed with affection:

                     〈◊〉
                   man, thinke this th
                     ••
                   the poore man maketh as
great account of his wife, as the greatest Monarch in y• world
both of an Empr
                     •
                  sse: that honesty harbors assoone in a cottage,
as in the Court
                     •
                   y• their minds oppressed with want, are fréed
from the 
                     〈◊〉
                   of loue▪ Then Cala
                        •
                     us, cease from these trinolus

                     〈◊〉
                  , and séeke no
                     •
                   so much as in thought to offer
wrōg to so modest a womā, whose honest behauiour foreshews
that she is poore, so she is chast, and holdeth as déere the price
of her same as the state of her life. No doubt Calamus, thou art
become a holy Prelate, that hast so many p
                     •
                  ecepts to re
                     •
                  ell that
thou hast alwaies followed: Is not loue a Lord as wel amōgst
Beggars as Kings▪ Cannot Cupid assoone hit a Shepheards
hooke as a Sc
                     •
                  pter: Doth not pouerty by natural insight yéeld
to the desires of Nobility: Are womens faces alwaies Kalenders
of truth: or are their 
                     •
                  ookes (as Ouid affirmeth) euermindglasses:
No, the thoughts of women hang not alwaies in their
eyes: dissimulation is sister to Ia
                        •
                     us, and wanton appetite oft

                     •
                  etteth vnder the Ma
                     •
                  ke of Chastitie: Hast thou he therto not
bin rep
                     •
                  lied with any resolute denya
                     •
                  s, and shalt thou now be
ouerthrowne with alooke? No, forward Calamus in thy purpose,
triumph man and say as Caesar did in his Conquests, veni,
vidi, vici: The Nobleman resting vpon this wicked resolutiō,

hearing of her husbands mishap, powred out such continuall
fountaines of teares, 
                     •
                  s not only Cala
                        •
                     us, but all men took pitty
of her plain
                     •
                  s. Bu
                     •
                   the vnbridled 
                     〈◊〉
                   of lust, that 
                     〈◊〉
                   it
runs headlong into a laborinth of mischefes feele
                     •
                  h no remorce,
had no consideration of hir daily sorrows, but resolued i
                     •
                   not by
intreaty, a
                     •
                   least by force to come to the end of his 
                     〈◊〉
                   desire.
Which resolution being knowne to Cratina: from prayers
she went to pollicy, and therefore on the sodaine became more
courteous, desiring Calamus that he would giue her some space
to forget her olde loue and entertaine a new choyse: He whose
fancy was some what appeased with this good spéech, granted
her the terme of a month▪ with free liberty to walke in the garden
and els where at her pleasure. Cratina enioying her wish so
fortunatly, taking time by the 
                     〈◊〉
                  , early in a morning stole
secretly from the Pallace and fled into the Country, where in
the day time hiding her amongst bushes, and in the night traueling
as fast as she could, at last she came to the place where her
husband was with the Collyeriand there changing her apparel
into the attire of a man, and her head brauely shorne, she became
a handsome stripling▪ The next day comming to the Colepits
she demaunded seruice. The Master Collyer séeing the youth
well faced, had pitty of his want, and entertained him: and for
that Lestio his man wanted one to driue his Cart, he appointed
Cratina to attend vpon him: She thanking the Gods that blest
her with so fauourable a seruice, was brought to the sight of Lestio
and committed to his charge. Lestio pittying the poore estate
of such a young youth, noting narrowly the lynamentes of her
face, fell into sighes, and from sighes to feares, for the remembrance
of his swéet Cratina: who indéede pittying her husbands
plaintes, in that she was a true de
                     •
                  iner of his thoughts,
could not (as womens secrets oft hang at the tip of their t
                     •
                  ngs)
but bewray to her husband what she was: who when he perfectly
knew his wife so straungely metamorphosed, what for ioye
of her presence, and sorrow that Fortune had made them both
thus vnhappy, he fell into déeper complaintes, till appeased by
his wife, they went merily to their worke.
               
                  
But Calamus missing Cratina, and after diligent search perceiuing
she was stole away, fel into such a melancholik humor,
that his seruants thought him half in a frenzie: He cōmanded
horse to be made out into euery hie way, al passages to be stopt,
euery womā to be examined, but in vain: which so increased his
furie, that taking his horse he rode vp and downe the Country
as one halfmad, but found not that which he sought for: at last
Fortune enuying the happines of Lestio and his wife, brought
him where the Col
                     ••
                  ars were at work, and a prety space before
hée came at the pitte hee met Cratyna: who séeing Cala
                        •
                     us, although
he had disguysed himselfe, because he would ride vnknowen,
yet perfectly perceiued what he was, and therefore would
willingly haue bene out of his companie: but he called vnto her,
and she hauing her lether Coate all dusty, &amp; her sweete face al
he smeared with coales, was the bolder to goe, and demaunded
of him what he wanted? Calamus inquired if such a woman past
not y• way: Yes mary (quoth Cratyna) there past such a one in
déede, who as she reported fled from Cala
                        •
                     us, for that the Noble
man would haue rest her of her chastitie. Canst thou tel my
friend (quoth he) whether is she gone? &amp; if I could (quoth Cratyna)
thinke 
                     〈◊〉
                   so little curtesie in me as to bewray her: for by
thy straigh
                     •
                   inquiry I perceiue thou art seruāt to that dishonorable

                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , that spareth neither wife nor widdow to satisfie
his vnbr
                     •
                  led lust. Calamus not brooking these hard spéeches allighted
from his horse, thinking to haue 
                     •
                  oel bū
                  
                     •
                  asled the boy:
who as falt as he could fled to the Colepit. The Colliars séeing
their boy (whō for his good behauiour they al generally loued)
to be misused by a seruingman, took their whips in their hands
and demaunded of Calamus what he ment to offer violence to
any of their companie: for y• (quoth he) the boy hath greatly abused
me. Crauna told thē at the whole matter: which knowne,
the Colliars wisht him if he were well to be packing, Calamus
séeing amongst such an vnruly cōpanie he could not mend himselfe,
went his way with a flea in his eare: and as he roade, perceiued
where Lestio lay a sleepe, who was not so disguised but
he knew him perfectly therfore thinking when he did wake to

learne some thing out of him, &amp; so turning his horse into a Close
hard by, rested himself behind a bush: Long he had not sitten before
Cra
                        •
                     ina came merily whistling with her Cart, &amp; tolde her
husband all what had happened, who both smiled that the Noble
man had such rough entertaynment, as also that she was so
cleane out of fauour. Calamus who ouerheard them, and perceiued
that the youth whome he tooke for a stripling was Cratyna
ye poore mans wife, felt such a remorce in his conscience for offering
violence to so vertuous and chast a mind, that assoone as
they were gene he posted as fast as he could to y• Court, where
Menon the Grandfather of my Lord Vlisses then raigned as
Prince, and reuealed vnto him the whole matter: who greatly
pleased with the discourse, desirous to sée so honest a wife, presently
dispatcht a Purseuāt to commaund the Colliar to bring
his man Lestio and his boy before the King. The Purseuant
sparing no horseflesh, came so fast from the Court that he found
thē all at dinner: who after they heard his message, were amazed,
especially poore Cratina, who feared some new misfortune:
yet chéering her selfe, the better to cōfort her husband, they wēt
with the Purseuant to the Court: where being brought before
Menon and Calamus, he there complained of the Collia
                     •
                   how
he had abused him in maintaining his boy to giue him ill
                     •
                  anguage.
The Colliar (as a man amazed) confessed his fault, but
vnwittingly, for that he knew him not: and therfore desired Calamus
to bee his good Lord and master. Menon, who all this
while had his eye on Cratina, ask
                     •
                  e her what he was: May it
please your grace (quoth she) I 
                     〈…〉
                   to this man who is
owner of the pit, but vnder this other who is ouers
                     ••
                  r of my
work: So then (quoth the King) you 
                     〈◊〉
                   two maisiers, y• one
by day, the other by night: Nay my 
                     〈…〉
                   but
one master, for we make smal account of any seruice y• is 
                     ••
                  ne
in the night. How say you 
                     〈◊〉
                   (quot
                     •
                   the 
                     •
                  ing to 
                     〈◊〉
                  ) is not
this boy your man: No my Lord (quoth he) only my 
                     〈◊〉
                  ,
and th
                     •
                  t is all the seruice I craue at 
                     〈◊〉
                  . At this answer
the King and Calamus smiled, and 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                   fearing she was
discouered began to blush: which Menon 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , dema
                     •
                  nded

of hir of what age she was? About eightéene my 
                     〈◊〉
                   (quoth
the) Menon willing to trye then what the euent would be: tolde
the Collyar that he and his man, for that their faults were shorow
ignoraunce, might get them home: but for your boy (quoth
the King) seeing he is so young and wel saced I meane to 
                     •
                  alie
him my page. The Collyar was glad he was so dispatcht, but
poore Lestio through aboundaunce of griefe was almost driuen
into anextasie, so y• changing colour he could scarce stand on his
legges: which Cratina perceiuing, seeing now Fortune had
done her worst, resolued to suffer all miseries whatsoeuer, f
                     •
                  ll
downe vpon her knées, and vnfolded to the King what she was,
and from point to point discoursed what had happened betwéen
her and Calamus, intermedling her spéeches with such a fountaine
of feares, as the king pittying her plaints, willed her to be
of good chéere: for none in all his kingdome should offer her any
vyolence. Calamus in the behal
                     •
                  e of Cratina thanked the King,
with promise before his Highnesse that the vertuous and chast
disposition of her minde had made such a met amorphosis of his
former thoughts, that not onely he was content to bridle his affections,
but to indow her with such sufficient lands and possessions,
as might very wel maintaine her in the state of a gentlewoman.
The King praising Calamus for his good minde, willing
to be an actor in this Comedy, commaunded his Steward
to furnish them with apparell, and afterward to conuey them to
Calamus Pallace, where they liued long after in presperous
and happy estate.
               The tale was long and the night was too far spent to run any
further descant onso good a playne song, and therefore Penelope
hauing finished her taske went to her lodging.
            
            
               The third nights discourse.
               THe day no sooner appeared, but according to their olde custome,
the Noble men of 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                   repaired to the Pa
                     •
                  lace of
Penelope, who fayning her selfe▪ not well, kept her Camber,
which her sonne▪ 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  spying, carried the Lords wt him

of certaine women washing of their clothes, where they talked
of a certaine place in the towne that was weake and worst defended.
Many inconueniences grow of the intemperancy of the
tongue, as discention and strife in a house, wheras contrariwise
nothing more appeaseth choller nor sheweth modesty then silence.
To confirme the which, I will rehearse a pleasant and
delightfull History.
            
            
               Penelopes third tale.
               THe Historiographers whose Annual Records makes mē
                  tion
of that auncient Citty of Delphos, where Apollo
deliuered his Oracles, sets downe as Chronicled for truth, that
sometime there raigned as chiefe and Gouernour of the Citty,
one Ariamenes, a Prince, wise, as seated in a place where the
meanest inhabitant was able to discourse of wisedome: rich, as
indewed with such and so large possessions that all his bordring
neighbors were inferiour to him in wealth and reuenews: and
fortunate, for that he had thrée Sonnes: honourable, as discended
from such parentage, and vertuous, as sauouring of their fathers
prudent education. Ariamenes blest thus euery way with
earthly fauours, séeing his gray hayres were summons vnto
death, and that olde age the true limiter of time, presented vnto
him the figure of his mortality, that he was come from the cradle
to the Crouch, and from the Crouch had one legge in the
graue: knowing that the kingdome of Delphos was not a Monarchy
that fell by inheritaunce, but that bee might as well appoint
his youngest sonne successor as his eldest, being affected to
them all alike: was perplexed with contrary passions, to which
of the three hee should bequeath such a Royall Leagacy, sith by
such an equall proportion Fortune had inriched them with fauours.
Nature, who is little partiall in such peculiar iudgements,
was by the seuerall thoughts that troubled Ariamenes
head, almost set at an non plus; insomuch that the olde King
driuen into a Dylemma, fell into this consideration.
               That all his sonnes were married to women descended from

honourable parents, and that sith his Sonnes were so equal in
their vertues, he was to measure his affection by the conditions
of their wiues: for he knew that kings in their gouernmēt proued
oft such Iusticiaries as ye good or il dispositiō of their wiues
did afford: for the greatest Monarches haue bene subiect to the
plausible perswasions of womē, and Princes thoughts are oft
tied to the wings of beautie. The Emperour Commodus had
neuer bin so hated in Rome for this tirannies, had he not bene
pricked forward to such wickednes by his wife. Ma
                        •
                     cus Aure
                     
                        •
                     us
the true &amp; perfect presidēt of a Prince, confessed, that hardly
he could with stand the allurements of Faustina. The enuie of
a woman hangs in the brow of her husband, and for ye reuenge
of an enemie the passeth not for ye losse of a friend. These things
considered, Ariamenes was thus resolued for himselfe, to bestowe
y• kingdome on that sonne whose wife was found to be
most vertuous Therefore after this determined resolution he
presently dispatched messengers to his sonnes in their seuerall
Prouinces, y• they particularly accompanied with their wiues
should méete him at Delphos, with generall commaund also y•
his Nobillitie should make hastie repaire to that Cittie. The
Kings commaund being put in execution, his sonnes to signifie
their duetifull obedience, sped them to y• Court, where being
come before their father, Ariamenes after he had sit a while in a
muse with himselfe, fell into these spéeches.
               Nature (Sonnes) the perfect mistris of affection tyeth the
father to his childrē with such a 
                     ••
                  rickt league, that loue admieteth
no partialitie, nor fancy brooketh any difference, but a 
                     •
                  ust
proportiō of good will is ministred if the parties haue 
                     〈◊〉
                  
in their vertues. Maicus Po
                        ••
                     i
                        •
                      Cato who was a father 
                     〈…〉
                  
childrē, was wont to say, that the loue of a father as it was
Royall, so it ought to be impartiall, neither declini
                     •
                  g to y• 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
nor to y• other, but as 
                     〈◊〉
                   doe merite. 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   who ha
                     •
                  
sixteene children of his owne bodie, at his de
                     •
                  th made equal distribution
both of goods &amp; lands alike to them 
                     〈◊〉
                   being dem
                     •
                  unded
why he did not giue his eldest Sonne y• greater portion,
made this answer. And is not the youngest also the sonne

eate. To auorde which, supposition, you referre his Highnesse
to the generall fame of the Countrey, y• aboue the rest you excéede
in obedience and chastitie: Take héede Sister, fame hath
two faces, and in that resembleth time, readie as well to backbite
as to flatter: therefore they which build their vertue vppon
report, doe alledge but a bad proofe. But leauing your reasōs to
his Highnesse consideration, thus for my self. I set not my good
name at so small a price, as to hazard it vpon the chaunce of the
tongue, that of al other members is most vncertaine: although
I am sure my bordring neighbours of estéeme of my doings, as
they take my vertues for a president of their actions: but I hope
your Highnes doth consider y• such trée such fruite, that ye liuely
pourtraiture of the parents is as in a Christall manifested in y•
children: that nature is the best touchstone of life: that educatiō
and nurture are as good as the Chrisocol to discerne Minerals:
so they of maners. Then right mightie Prince, I first for proofe
of my vertuous disposition lay downe the honorable &amp; happie
life of my Parents so wel ordred, that 
                     •
                  ame and enuie blusheth
to staine them with any spot of infamie: what care they had to
bring me vp in my youth, with what instructiōs they passed ouer
my tender yeares, I referre to your Maiestie, as by willing
your second sonne to match in so meane a famely: since the rites
of mariage were celebrated my husbands dispositiō shall manifest.
The eldest Sister hearing how cunningly &amp; yet crookedly
this prettie Oratresse aimed at the matter, could not suffer to
heare so long a tale without replye, and therefore went thus
roundly to the purpose.
               Sister ill might Phillis haue blamed Dido for her folly sith
she her self intertained stragling Demophon for a friend: The
Cynicks that inueighed against other mens faults were seldōe
culpable in the same crime: they which will haue their censures
peremptorie, must not build their reasons on vncertain principles
therefore wipe your nose on your owne sleeue, and if you
spie where my shooe wrings me, looke to the length of your own
last: for in obiecting selfeloue to me you fall a sléepe in the swéet
conceipt of your owne praise: which indéed wisely you frame to

hazard on the chance of fame, sith your deserts are so small as
report is blind on y• side which lookes to your vertues: the force
of your reasons drawne from the authority of propagation, alledging
nature and nurture for proofes of your vertues, are too
light to counterpaise wt a Crowne: for we oft sée that Natures
onely error is found in the dissimilitude of linage: so that the trée
bringing foorth faire blos
                     •
                  omes, yet the blomes may either hée
nipped in the bud with vntimely weather, or hindred with catterpillers,
that it neuer proue good &amp; perfect fruite. The Cedar
trée is faire of it self, but the fruite either none or very bad: Tis
no opinion to say a good father a good child, in that time oft maketh
an alteration of Nature. But your husband was cōmanded
to haue pleaded your interest: mary I feare his conscience
tels him the Crowne hangs too bye for his reach, sith he must
be faine to attaine to it by your vertues.
               The yongest Sister hearing how vnreuerently they brabled
before the King, began to blush: which Ariamenes espying, noting
in her face the very purtraiture of vertue, demanded of her
why hearing her sisters so hard by the eares for a Crowne shée
said nothing? her answere was thus briefe and pithy. He that
gaineth a Crowne getteth care, is it not folly then to hunt after
losse? The King looking for a longer discourse, and seeing contrary
to his expectation that she was onely short and swéete, prosecuted
still inquestioning, and demaunded what vertues she had
that might deserue so royall a benefit? This quoth she, that wh
                     ••
                  
others talke, yet being a woman I can hold my peace. Ariamenes
and all the Nobility of Delphos wondred at the modestie
of the young Lady, that contrary to her naturall disposition
could so well bridle her affections. Therfore dehating the matter
betwixt them which of the thrée were most vertuous: although
they found by proofe that the other Ladies were both obedient
and chast: yet for that they wanted silence, which (sayd
Ariamenes) comprehended in it all other vertues, they mist of
the cushion, and the King created his youngest Sonne heire apparant
to the Kingdome.
               
                  
                  PEnelope hauing ended her tale, the olde Nurse greatly commended
the discourse, and b
                     •
                  cause she wold be pleasant at the
parting blow, knowing that Isme
                        •
                     a was a quicke wench of her
tongue, tolde her that this tale was a good president for her to
direct her course, séeing silence was so profitable. Tush quoth Ismena,
feare not you Madame: for when I haue such a proffer
as a Crowne, I will gaze so fast at that, that I will forget my
prattle▪ but in saith my lippes are too course for such Lettice, and
so hye hangs the Grapes that the Foxe will eate none. Well
Madame, I know your meaning, but for all t
                     •
                  e cracke my penny
may be good siluer, sith silence is a vertue amongst women:
but yet I sée no reason of necessity, séeing nature hath béene so
niggardly in that 
                     •
                  auour. It may séeme quoth the Nurse, that
she hath béen rather too prodigall, for thy tung wants no mettall.
As thus they were about to part with these merry quips, a
messenger came hastily rushing in, who tolde Penelope that Vlisses,
was arriued that night within the port of Ithaca: This
word so amazed them all with sodaine ioy, that lea
                     •
                  ing the endlesse
Web, Penelope 
                  
                     ••
                  lled for her Sonne, and that night sent
him in post to the Sea: where what news he heard of his father
I know not. But thus abruptly this night was the discourse
broken off: but for that fell out after his home comming, I referre
you to the Paraphrase, which shortly shall be set out
vpon Homers Odissea: till when let vs leaue
Penelope attending the returne either
of her Husband, or Sonne,
or of both.
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

