
   
      
         
            A treatise of the great and generall daye of iudgement necessarie for euerie Christian that wisheth good successe to his soule, at that great and terirble day. By Henrie Greenwood, Master of Arts, and preacher of the word of God. With an addition of certaine godly prayers the contents appeare in the next page.
            Greenwood, Henry, b. 1544 or 5.
         
         
            
               1606
            
         
         Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02194
            STC 12337
            ESTC S119048
            99854255
            99854255
            19664
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02194)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19664)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1102:04)
         
         
            
               
                  A treatise of the great and generall daye of iudgement necessarie for euerie Christian that wisheth good successe to his soule, at that great and terirble day. By Henrie Greenwood, Master of Arts, and preacher of the word of God. With an addition of certaine godly prayers the contents appeare in the next page.
                  Greenwood, Henry, b. 1544 or 5.
               
               [102] p.   
               
                  By Richard Bradock for Henry Bell, dwelling on Holborn Hill: and are to be sold at his shop next the Crosse Keys,
                  Printed at London :
                  1606.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-F, G⁴ (-A1, blank?).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-02
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-02
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A TREATISE of the great and generall daye of Iudgement: Neceſſarie for euery Chriſtian that wiſheth good ſucceſſe to his Soule, at that great and terrible day.
            By Henrie Greenwood, Maſter of Arts, and Preacher of the word of God.
            With an addition of certaine godly prayers the contents appeare in the next page.
            But I ſay vnto you, that of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall giue account therof at the day of iudgement.

                  Mat. 12.36.
               
            
            
               
               
Printed at London by Richard Bradock for Henry Bell, dwelling on Holborn Hill: and are to be ſold at his ſhop next the Croſſe-Keys. 1606.
         
         
            
            The contents of the Praiers.
            
               A ſhort diſputation betweene the diuell and the poore ſoule of a chriſtian.
               A ſhort death-bed dialogue.
               A praier for the morning.
               A praier for the Euening.
               A thankſgiuing for our late deliuerance.
               A prayer comprehending the matter of the laſt iudgement.
               A ſhort prayer of purpoſe againſt Sathans aſſaults.
               A ſhort prayer at hand vpon all occaſions.
               A prayer for all ſorts.
            
         
         
            
            
               ❧ TO THE Right Worſhipfull, and my very good friends, LESTRANGE MORDAVNT of Maſsingham Hall, in the County of Norfolke Eſquire, and M• MARGARET MORDAVNT his louing bedfellow, Eternall welfare, and euerlaſting happines in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and Sauiour.
            
               BEeing earnestlye requeſted, and often intreated (Righte worſhippefull) by manye of my good friendes, to putte in printe this ſmall Treatiſe of the Generall day of doome, which I lately preached, and in publike place deliuered:

I haue (being ouercome with their perſwaſions) condeſcended to their earnest demaund, although very vnapt and exceedingly vnworthy for the penning of ſo worthy a matter. Wherefore I haue made choyſe (crauing pardō for my preſumption herein) of your well diſpoſed worſhip at this time (being the Alpha of my tender and ſlender endeuours) to ſound in your ſacred cares this laſt and generall trumpet, &amp; to dedicate to your worſhip the ſame: both in regard of the demonſtration of my true vnfamed, and laſting thankfulneſſe to your benigne worſhip, (for ſaith Seneca: Beneficium hominem gratū ſemper delectat, ingratum ſemel: id eſt: A thankfull man will alway remember a benefit, but an vnthankfull perſon wil ſoone forget it) for your extraordinary Kindneſſes beſtowed vpō me, Abſque vllo demerito, without any deſert in the world: as alſo in regard

of the greate
                  •
                affection, good deuotion, and thrice welcom entertainment you beare to diuine and ſpiritual tractates which appertain to the euerlaſting bliſſe of the ſoule, accounting thē bleſſed which bring glad tidings of ſaluation. I deſire therfore (idque more humillimo, in moſt ſubmiſſiue māner) this one thing at your worſhips hand, that you would (pardoning my boldneſſe) vouchſafe, aequi bonique conſulere, to take in good worth this ſimple and ſlender gift. Which thing if your worſhip ſhall vouchſafe to doe, it ſhall not onely be an incouragement to my future proceedings, but alſo it ſhall be vinculum in diſſolubile, an inuincible bond to tie me in all duty, &amp; in al loue to your worſhip: dum memor ipſe mei, dū ſpiritus hos regit artus: ſo lōg as life ſhal laſt. Thus hūbly taking my leaue of your good worſhips (nothing doubting of the goodnes of your natures

in the acceptāce of theſe my firſt preſē
               ted fruits) I cōmit you with yours to the ſafe protection of the almighty, alwaies begging before the throne of his moſte glorious Maieſty, that he would in this life, infuſe his holy ſpirit with all his graces into your heartes aboundantly, and in the worlde to come, crowne you with the crowne of immortall glory, &amp; that for Christ Ieſus his ſake, our Lord and only Sauiour, Amē. From Sampford Magna in Eſſex, this 30. of Aprill. 1606.
            
            
               Your Worſhips in all duty for euer to commaund. Henry Greenewood.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               A Treatiſe of the Great and general day of Iudgment: neceſſary for euery Chriſtian that wiſheth good ſucceſſe to his ſoule, at that great and terrible day.
            
               
                  But I ſay vnto you, that of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue an account thereof, at the day of 
                        •
                     udgement.
                  math. 12.36.
               
            
            
               MAn in regard of the corruption of his nature, through the fall of his greate Grandfather Adam (who was the foyle of Mankinde, the parent of ſinne, and the author of death

to all his poſteritie, foraſmuch as wee were all In Iumbis Adama, In his Ioynes)
                as hee is ſubiect to all ſinnes whatſoeuer,, ſo is hee eſpecially addicted to the ſinne of ſecuritie and careleſneſſe. Therefore as Adam ſleeping ſecurely in his tranſgreſſion, and hiding himſelfe from the preſence of the Lorde behinde the buſh, had greate neede of that watchbell from God (to rouſe him from the ſleepe of ſinne, and to call him againe vnto God, Adam vbi es? Adam where art thou?
               
               Gen. 3.9. So as neceſſary for euery ſinful Adamite (to raiſe him vp from the ſleepe of ſinne, wherein hee was borne) is this notable Memento, this worthy rehearſall of the great and terrible day of doome. But I ſay vnto you, &amp;c. which wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt, ſpoken to the ſcribes and phariſees (who would not beleeue that be wrought this miracles by the powrful ſpirit of God, but ſlanderouſly and contemptuouſly tolde him to his face▪ (that hee did caſt out diuels through Beelzebubs name.
               Mat. 12.24 are as much in effect, as if he had ſaid on this manner: It

account muſt be rendered at the daye of Iudgement of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, then much more of blaſpheamous wordes: But I ſay vnto you that of euery idle worde that men ſhal ſpeak, they ſhall giue account therof at the general day of Iudgement: Ergo
                much more of blaſphemous wordes as yours are, in ſaying, that I caſt out diuels through the name of Beelzebub.
               
            
            So that theſe words of our Sauiour are nothing elſe but a true propoſition and ſound argument drawne A minore ad maius, whereby Chriſt doth prooue the greatnes of puniſhment that ſhould befall the blaſpheamous Phariſees, in regarde of the greatneſſe of theyre ſinne.
            In which portion of Scripture, fowre things neceſſarily muſt be conſidered.
            
               1 The perſons that muſt giue account, who they bee.
               2 Of what things theſe perſons muſt giue an account.
               3 To whome muſt this account bee giuen.
               
                  4 When this account muſt bee giuen.
            
            
               The firſt part.1 The perſons that muſte giue an account, they are expreſſed in this text in general, to be mē. That men ſhall ſpeake. Men, yea all men muſt giue an account, as wee may reade in the Epiſtle of Saint Paule, to the Corinthians:
            
               2. c 1.5, 10
               VVee muſt all appeare before the tribunall ſeat of Chriſte, that euery man may receiue according to his works. All men none excepted, of euery age, of euery ſex, and of euery nation, ritch and poore, Princes and common people, noble and ignoble, all that haue beene from the beginning of the worlde, and ſhall bee to the end of the ſame, ſhall appeare before Chriſts Iudgement ſeat, and giue an account, euery one for himſelfe to God:Heb. 9.2
                     •
                  
                For; It it is appointed vnto men once to die, and after that commeth iudgment, As it is therfore moſt ſure, that al men muſt die ſo it is ſure, that all men moſt come to iudgment.
            
               Art. 7.This is the ſeuenth article of our faith to beleeue: that Chriſt ſhall come from heauen to iudge the quick and the dead:

by the deade, all thoſe are to bee vnderſtoode that ſhall bee found dead at the ſecond comming of Chriſt: by the quicke, all thoſe are to bee vnderſtoode, that ſhall bee found liuing at that his ſecond comming. Auguſtine in his Enchirioſon to Laurentius,
               Auguſt. 
               chapter 55. ſayth, that this article may bee expounded two wayes: eyther by the dead (ſayth be) may be meant thoſe that ſhall be found corporally dead: &amp; by the quicke, thoſe that ſhall be found corporally liuing at Chriſts comming: or (ſaith hee) by the dead may bee meant thoſe, that bee dead in ſinne, according to that in the Goſpell of Matthew:
               Mat. 8.22▪
                
               Let the dead bury their dead: and by the quicke, thoſe that be dead to ſinne, and liuing by faith, according to that of the Prophet Abacucke: the iuſt ſhall liue by faith.
               
               Hab
                     •
                  . 2.4. But this expoſition is not agreeable to the ſimplicity of the Creed: Yet notwithſtanding true it is, that both the godly and the wicked ſhall come to iudgement: for by the power of Chriſt all men ſhall be raiſed vp: the holy Angels with the greate ſound of a Trumpet ſhal be ſent forth into all the world,Mat. 24.31
               
and they ſhall gather togither the elect, from the fowre quarters of the earth, from one end of the heauen to the other: Then ſhall Chriſt ſeparate the electe from the reprobates,Mat 13.40 the wheate from the Tares, the come from the cheffe, the Lambes from the Contes, the iuſt from the vniuſt.
            So that you ſee that the godly and the wicked, yea all men whatſoeuer, ſhall appeare before Chriſts tribunall ſeate, and giue an accounte of themſelues, and for themſelues to the terrible Iudge.
            
               Obiect Ioh. 3.
                     •
                  8.
               Ob. Som not withſtanding may obiect againſt this doctrin deliuered, and ſay: as it to in Iohn, That bee that beleeueth in Chriſt, ſhall not be iudged, or ſhall not come into iudgement
               : and ſo by conſequence all men ſhall not bee iudged.
            
               Anſ. To which I anſwer, that iudgment in that place of Iohn,
               Anſwer. (as in many other places of ſacred ſcriptures) is taken for condemnation: in which ſenſe true it is, that bee that beleeueth in Chriſt Ieſus, he that is ingrafted

into Chriſt by a true and aliuely faith, he that is fleſh of his fleſh, &amp; bone of his bone, one with Chriſt, and Chriſt with him, by the ſpirituall coniunction of the Church with CHRIST, this party ſhall not come into iudgement, ſ
                     ••
                  l. Condemnationis, that is, of Condemnation, in iudgement he ſhall not bee confounded, condemned, or ouerthrowne: but he ſhall come in iudicium abſolutionis: that is, Into the iudgement of abſolution: In iudgement hee ſhall ſtand out, hauing on the white Robe of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, and beeing couered with the wedding garment of Regeneration. The trueth of which doctrine the Preacher affirmeth, ſaying: GOD will iudge the iuſt and the vniuſt.
               Eccle. 3.17 The iuſt vnto ſaluation, and the vniuſt to damnation.
            Seing then that all muſt be brought to iudgement, let no man thinke with himſelfe, that it may be poſſible for him to eſcape this dreadfull day:Pſal. 139
                     •
                   8.9. whither ſhall hee flie from the preſence of the Lord?
            
               If he aſcendeth vp to heauē, God is there:

if hee goe downe to hell, God is there alſo: if he take the wings of the morning, and ſhe to the vttermoſt parts of the ſea, God will finde him out there alſo: For God is euery where: hee is in heauen by his glory: hee is vppon the earth by his mercy, hee is in hell by his iuſtice: God is vbique &amp; nulquam: he is euery where by his power and wiſedome, but no where in reſpect of circumſcription of place, being a ſpirit. In earthly and terreſtriall courts, a man may haue his proctor; but then wee muſt (volentes nolentes, whether wee will or no)
                perſonally appeare and pleade for our ſelues.
            In terreſtriall courts, bribes many times blind the eyes of the wiſe, and for a little greaſing the fiſt of the Magiſtrate, many times ſmall faults, nay (by your leaue) greate and ſcandalous crimes may be winked at: but at this great court of heauen, the Iudge will not be partial to any: for God hath no reſpect of perſons:
               Rom 2▪11 Pſal. 98.9. hee will execute iuſt iudgement vpon all men: as the Pſalmographer ſpeaketh: VVith righteouſnes

will be iudge the world, and the people with equitle. Bribes, friends, intreaties, bowlings, cries, lamentations, nothing wil then preuaile, but a pure heart, and a ſpirits vpright: yea the damned in Hell confeſſe the ſame:a wiſd. 5, 8 
               quid profuit nobis ſuperbia? quid diuitiarū copia? what hath pride profited vs? or what hath the pomp of riches done vs good?
                alas theſe cannot ſaue our ſoules.
            Let the Atheiſt therfore mock God neuer to blaſphemouſly:b. Act. 23, 
                     •
                  
                let the Sadduces brag of no reſurrection, no Angel, no ſpirit, neuer ſo ſchiſmatically: let the Epicure ſlug that curſed Epitaph of Sardanapalus neuer ſo beaſtly, Ede, lude, bibe, charum, praeſētibus exple delicijs animū: poſt martem nulla voluptas: that is Eat, drink, play, be merry, live in al kind of pleſure, for after death there is no pleaſure. Yet notwithſtanding let all theſe miſerable wretches know, that there wil come a day, and ye a diſmal day, wherin they ſhall giue an account of euery idle word. Alas lamentable world, that men ſhoulde thus murther their deareſt darlings,

I meane their ſoules, which Chriſte hath holden ſo dear: that men ſhould with Eſau ſel their birthright,
               
               Gen 25.33. and heritage of heauē, for a meſſe of pottage of worldy pleaſure: that men ſhoulde delight in wallowing (with the ſow) in the myre of ſin,2, Pet. 2.22. and (with the dog) in ſwallowing the vomit of iniquity: &amp; ſo purchaſe to their ſouls and bodies euerlaſting torment in the lake vnquenchable: whereas they ſhould aboue all things ſeeke the kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe therof, that they mighte haue heauenly manſions at the great day of account.
            Let euery Chriſtian therfore bewayle the wickedneſſe of this world &amp; lament the iniquity of theſe dates: leaſt it bee ſaide of vs, as of the careleſſe and graceleſſe Chriſtian, Cadit afina, &amp; eſt qui ſublenet, perist anima, &amp; noneſt quirecogitat: If an aſſe falleth vnder his burthen, there be ſome that will diligently helpe it vp againe: but if a ſoule periſh, no man regardeth it.
                Men are like the horſe, aſſe, &amp; mule that haue no vnderſtanding: the more

is the good mans griefe. Dauid his eyes guſhed out into riuers of water,
               
               Pſal. 
                     •••
                  .
                     •
                  37. 
               becauſe men kept not gods law. The prophet Ieremy crieth out on this mā
               ner▪ 
               My belly, my belly, I am payned euen at the heart;
               Ierem. 4:19 
                     ••
                  
                
               I cannot be quiet becaus my people is a fooliſh people, they are wife to do euill, but to doe well, they haue no knowledge,
            
            That godly Matrone Monica ſai
                  •
                
               Auguſtine mother wayte daily,Monica and prayed for her ſonne a conuerſion; for hee was before his conuerſion a Manich
                  •
               e.
            So likewiſe it is the duty of euery Chriſtian to deſire the conuerſion of their brethren, and to bewaile their wretched eſtates.
            Sinne neuer more than in theſe our dais of the goſpel, aboūded: the greteſt part of the world at Sathauiſts diuels in conuerſation, worſhippers of ye vgly beaſt that hath ſeuē heads &amp; ten horns, whoſe badge is blaſphemy:Apo. 13.16 Eph. 
                     •
                  .2. of yt dāned ſerpēt, the prince of the air: the grād enemy of mankind, that goeth vp and down like a roaring lion ſeeking whom he may deuoure.1. Pet. 5.8. Yea

Saint Iohn ſaith, that Whatſoeuer is in the world,
               1. Iohn. 2.16. 
               is either the cōcupiſcence of the fleſh, or the concupiſcence of the eye, or the pride of life: hac tria pro trino numine mundus habet:
                this is The Trinity which the world doth worſhip: In ſtead of God the Father, God the Sonne, &amp; God the holy Ghoſt: the world doth worſhip the diuel, ye world and the fleſh: the concupiſcence of the fleſh, that is, carnall l
                  •
               turye: the concupiſcence of the eye, that is, worldly couetouſneſſe &amp; eche pri
                  •
                of life, that is, diueliſh ambition.
            The way to hell is abroad &amp; a wide way, &amp; whole multitudes walk in the ſame: but few there be that can finde out the narrow way of an
                  •
               m
                  •
               t of life: the Heathen man could ſay this: Plurima peſſima: the moſt are the worſt:
               
               Anſt. 
               precioſa non ſunt numer
                     •
                  ſa, good mē are od men:
                Waſps and hornets ſwarm, but few painfull bees are to be found, ye treaſure vp the hony of good works in the hiue of their hearts, and come laden home wt the ſame, as Virgil writeth of the Bees: At feſſamulta referuns ſe nocte minores, crura thymo plena.
               
No maruail therfore, if Dauid cried out to the Lord for help in his daies: ſaying: Helpe Lot
                     •
                  , helpe,
               
                  a pſal, 12, 1 
               for good and godly men decay. The world therfore may be compared to the earth.Compa.
            
            Aſke the earth, &amp; it will tell thee, that it doth affordé much matter for baſe pets, but very little ſtuffe for Golde: aſk the Gardner and he will tell thee that he hath more Nettles than Raſes, more Weeds than flowers, more 
                  •
               rambles than Vy
                  •
               : you aſke thine owne conſcience, and it will tell thee,Note. that there is Magna pl
                     •
                  itudo hominum, ſed magna ſolisudo homorum: id eſt, there is a great plenty of men, but there is a greate ſcarcity of goodmen.
                A good man is a Phenix, he is Rara anis in terris,
               Inuen. 
               nigro
                     •
                  ua 
                     •
                  llima cyg
                     •
                  i A rare bird, a blacke 
                        •
                     an.
                Wee haue many couetous Chur
                  •
               s that will (with the foole in the Goſpell) commend their ſoules to Plutus that was colled of the b
                  •
               athen, Deus diuitia
                     •
                  , The god of riches;
                but more 
                  •
               ly he is D
                     •
                  mon diuitiarum, the diuell 
                        •
                     f riches:
                and thinke themſelues ſafe when they haue ſpoken peace to their

ſouls on this manner:
                  
                     •
                  uk. 12.19 
               Soule take thy reſt, for thou haſt goods laid vp for many daies: making their cheſt their heauen, and their pictures their GOD. Wee haue many Achabs, Tyrannicall extortioners, deuourers of their brethren, eating them vp like bread. Many adulterers, as appereth by the great number of Baſtardes in this Realme.
            Many rebellious traytors and Antichriſtian conſpirators; as did appeare the laſt Nouember.
            Many conceyted Herodes, many proude Nebuchadne
                     •
                  rs, and many vaine glorious I
                     •
                  bels, many ſwearers, forſwearers, drunhardes, mocks-go
                  •
               s, many wee haue (in a worde) damned belboundes, curſed ce
                  •
               tifes, and moſt miſerable miſcre
               
                  •
               ts
            How little doe theſe lamentable wretches think of 
                  〈…〉
                of accoun
                  •
                how little do they imagin of that 
                  •
               ofull ſentence, Goe from me ye curſed &amp;c. the Lorde grant to all men (on
                  •
                with another) his grace, that they may haue this Scripture alway ſaſ
                  •
               
               ding

in their eares. Of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue an account thereof at the daye of iudgement.
            
            The conſideration of this laſt day made Ierome afraide to offend: Whether I eate or drinke (ſayth hee) or whatſoeuer I doe elſe,
               Iero. 
               me thinks I heare this ſaying ſounding in myne eares, Ariſe ye dead, and com to iudgement: The which when I conſider, it makes mee quake and ſhake, and not dare to committ ſinne, which otherwiſe I ſhoulde haue committed.
            O that men woulde remember their ende, then they ſhould neuer offend: O that men woulde alwayes ſet before their eyes the quatno
                     •
                   noniſſima: the day of death, the day of iudgement, the ioys of heauē and the torments of hel: then would not men liue ſo looſely, but they would with al diligence worke out their ſaluation with feare and exembling: the which care of godlineſſe the lord grant to al men Thus much ſhal ſuffice for this firſt part of this Scripture, namely,

for the parties that ſhall giue an account, who they be, namely all men whatſoeuer. But I ſay vnto you that of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they, &amp;c.
            
            
               The ſecōd part.
               2 Of what things muſt we giue an account.
            
            There muſt an account be made of many, yea of things innumerable, but eſpecially of theſe fiue.
            
               1 Of the thoughts of our hearts, according to that of Salomō,
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     wiſ, 1, 9 
               there ſhall inquiſition be made for the thoughts of the vngodly, there ſhall not a wicked thought paſſe in iudgement.
            
            If Adam had committed but one diſobedient thought in heart againſt Almighty God, with full conſent of will to haue performed the ſame, and though be had not actually broken Gods commaundement: it was neceſſarie that the ſe
                  •
                
               Adam (who is a rayſer of our ruins, the ranſom for our offences, and the reſtorer of life) ſhold come, and ſuffer the cortures of hel [as he did] or els we with Adam had gone the high way to eternall 
                  〈◊〉
               . No marualle therfore if our Sauiour

Chriſt accounted him an adulterer, that luſted after a woman, ſaying. VVhoſoeuer looketh on a woman to luſt after her,
               
                  Mat. 5, 28, 
               hath committed adultery with her already in his heart. It is the malicious nature of the diuel [as ſaith Barnard] to in
                        •
                     iſe mē to miſchiefe: Damorum eſt mala ſuggerere,
               Bernard. 
               nostrum eſt nō conſentire. It is the property of the diuel to intice and ſuggeſt men to euill, &amp; it is our partes, not to conſent to his inticements,
                but to reſiſt them māfully, according to that of Peter.
               1. Pc. 5.9 
               VVhō reſiſt ye ſtedfaſt in faith. The diuell outwardly by the world, and inwardly by the corruptiō of our nature, doth daily allure vs to ſinne: Now if we conſent to thoſe his wicked motions [whether wee performe them outwardly in art, yea or no] before God wee haue committed the ſinne: according to that of Iohn▪
                
               
                  Iob. 3.15
               He that hateth his brother is a manſlayer: becauſe in will, in wiſh, and in deſire be hath already ſlaine him, although be doth not bring it into outward act, either for feare of the lawe of man in that caſe, or for want of iuſt and 
                  •
               e oportunity for the effecting

therof. Yea the ſin of thought, the ſin conceiued in the heart of man, is not only a ſin, but it is the roote &amp; beginning of all ſins whatſoeuer: for it is not that which goeth into man,Mat. 15.11 that defileth him, but that which cōmeth out of him, that is, that which procedeth from the heart of man.
            The Diuell firſt ſuggeſteth after ſuggeſtion,The la
                     •
                  er of ſinne. commeth cogitatiō: after cogitation followeth affection: after affection, followeth delectation: after delectatiō followeth conſent: (Now is the ſin of thought fully cōmitted:) after conſent, followeth operation: after operation foloweth cuſtom after cuſtom followeth deſperation: after deſperation followeth defending of ſins committed after defending of ſinnes committed, followeth vaunting, boaſting, and glorying in ſinne, which is next to damnation it ſelfe: thus the heart is the fountain, from whence ſpringeth all ſinne whatſoeuer.
            Yet haue wee not many wicked ones in this world, that think the ſin of heart eye her to 
                  •
               ee no ſinne at all,

or elſe, but aſmall ſin, that ſhall neuer bee broughte in queſtion at the day of accoūt? But let al theſe know, that as of euery idle word, ſo of euery wicked and ſinful thought conceiued and nouriſhed within the hearte of man, with full conſent to the performance of the ſame (for there is no ſinne that can be committed without conſent had) men, yea all men muſt giue an account.
            I giue all men therefore (to the good of their ſoules) this good counſell of Salomon, Keepe thyne heart with all diligence,
               
               Prou. 4.23. 
               for thereout commeth life: if thou keepeſt it not diligently and warily, therout wil proceed death
               ▪ I meane, ſinne whoſe wages is death,
               om. 6 23 The heart is a mill, alwais grinding either good corne or bad, either good thoughts or bad: therefore keep it diligently for thy ſoules ſake; let it meditate in the law of god day &amp; night, abandon all wicked motions, that at the day of iudgement thou mayſt bee pure bread, and fine manches, for the bread of life, Chriſt Ieſus his table in heauē: the Lord grant this to me the

writer, thee the reader, and to euery hearer of it.
            
               2 We muſt giue an account of our words.
            
               Word.
               Of euery idle word that men ſhal ſpeak &amp;c. Diuers of the learned writers haue diuerſly commented of this idle word, what it ſhold be: one affirming one thing, another another thing. Therfore I wil (in a word) ſet down the opinions of ſome of thē, not incō
               gruent, neither diſagreeable to the holy Scripture.
            
               Greg.
               Gregory ſaith, that Verbum otioſum est, quod iuſta neceſſitate, &amp; pia v
                     ••
                  atate caret: That is (ſaith he) an idle word which is ſpokē eyther without iuſt neceſſity, or godly profit.
            
            
               Ierome 
                     •
                  
               
               Ierome ſaith, that Verbumotioſū est quod ſine v
                     •
                  elitate loquent
                     •
                   vel audiētis profertur, that is [ſaith he] an idle word which is ſpokē either without edification of the hearer; or ſpeaker.
            
            
               Baſil.
               Baſil. Omne verbū quod non cond
                     •
                  is ad propoſitam vtilitatem, vanū 
                  
                     •
                  ſt &amp; otioſum, that is, Euery word, which belō
                  geth not to an intended profit, is a vain and an idle word.
            
            
               Maiſter Iohn Caluin ſaith,Calv. that Sermo otioſus pro inutili ſumitur, qui nihil aedificationis vel fructus affert: id eſt, an idle word is takē for a word vnprofitable, for a word that bringeth with it no fruitful edification.
                So that frō theſe deſcriptions of holy men. I doe deſcribe an idle word on this manner.
            
               Verbum otioſum eſt, quod ad bonam rem non pertinet: quod non facit ad gloriā dei vinentis: quod mutile est &amp; infrugiferū: quod nec loquentē nec audientē aedificat: id eſt, An idle word is that which doth not appertaine to a propoſed profit; which tendeth not to the glory of the euerliuing God: which is vnprofitable &amp; vnfruitful: which edifieth neither the bearer, nor the ſpeaker.
                If then (good brethren in chriſt Ieſus) ſo great account muſt be giuen, of euery idle, vain, &amp; fruitles word; what account (thinke yee) ſhall be giuen for ſwearing, curſing, banning and blaſpheaming?
            What accoūt ſhal the ſwearer giue, that hath not one word in his mouth but it is guarded with an execrable oath?
            
               How common (alaſſe) this ſinne of ſwearing is, who knoweth not? for the ſmall infants and tender childrē in our ſtreetes haue curſed outhes Ad vnguem At their fingers end,
                yea at their tongues end too. What account ſhall the curſing and 
                  •
               anning tongue giue, that Cruelly, Diſdainfully,
               Pſal, 31.1
                     •
                  
                and Deſpightfully ſpeaketh againſt his neighbour? What account ſhall the blaſpheamous perſon giue, that ſpeaketh contemptuouſly of God, &amp; ſaith that Chriſt did caſt out Diuels throgh the name of Ecclzaeb
                     •
                  b?
               1. Pet 4.18. If the iuſt ſhall ſcarce be ſaued, where ſhall the ſinner appeare: If account muſt be made of euery idle word, Lord, what account ſhall they make, that rappe and vomiteous blaſphemies againſt the terrible Iudge of Heauen and Earth?
            As men thinke and fondly imagine, that the ſinne of thought (vnles it proceed into outward act) is but a ſmall ſinne: ſo likewiſe do they imagine of idle wordes, that they are but ſmall ſinnes, and a ſmall account for them ſhall be giuen.
            
               But let all the world knowe, that no ſinne can be ſaid to be ſmal in reſpect of it owne nature: for the leaſt ſinne that can bee committed in the world, is ſo weightie as, without repentance had, it will ſink the ſinner downe to the bottomleſſe pitt of Hel. Yet not withſtanding an idle worde in reſpect of other ſinnes, maye bee ſaid to be a ſmal ſinne: yet as ſmal as it is, it is able to damme the ſoul for euer.
            Wel therfore ſaith Petrus Damianus ſermone ſecūdo de vitio linguae:
               Pet. Dami 
               Audiut lingua vaniloqua, audiat otioſa linguae, au diat &amp; paneſcat, intelligat &amp; pethorreſcat ſententiā horribilem, extremique iudicis terrorem &amp;c. that is, Hear o vain babling tongue, heare 
                     •
                  o idle tongue, heare and tremble, vnderſtand, and quake, at the hearing of the terrible day of iudgement: he that hath hands to ſlay, hath hee not cates to heare
                     •
                  
                he ſaith, that of euery idle worde that men ſhall ſpeak; they ſhall giue an account therof at the day of iudgement:
            
            Although an idle word be a ſmall ſinne in reſpect of greater ſinnes, yet

neuertheles an innumerable company of idle words, cōgeſted, accumulated, and heaped vp together, they wil make a nighty ſinne. Quid peuna lenius? quid milt
                     •
                   breuius? What is lighter then a feather? and what is ſhorter thā the ſeed 
                        •
                     ill?
                Yet notwithſtāding an innumerable company of feathers truffed vp together, wil break ye po
                  •
               
               ters back.Exo. 8, 2.4. Smal wer the gnats that troubled Pharao, yet they being innumerable ouer came proud Pharao and all the power of Egypt. An hour is but a ſhort time, but D
                     •
                  m horae horae cōtinua ſucceſſiona congeritur: While on houre by continual ſucceſſion is added to another, the whole cours of our liues is finiſhed Quid ſax
                     •
                   durius, quid aqua liquidius? What is harder then a ſtone, and what is ſofter then the water?
                Yet a wiſe man ſaith,Poet. 
               
                  
                     •
                  ita cauat lapidem, conſimitur an
                     •
                  us vſu: that is, Water by continuall droppes doth eate vp the ſtone, and a Ring by continuall vſe is worne in pocces. So an idle word, although it be but a ſmall ſin, yet many a little makes a mickle, many of them heaped vp together make an intolerable

lump.
            At hath beene, is, and euer will bee the fond nature of man, to imagine ſinne a greate deale leſſer than indeed it is. A man would thinke that Adam (through the diuels ſuggeſtion,Gen. 3.6. and through the abuſe of his own free wil) Eating of the forbidden fruite, had committed but a ſmall treſpaſſe: yet hee was guilty of euerlaſting torment for the ſame. A man would thinke,Nu. 15.36. that that poore man had committed but a ſmall ſin in gathering chips (of meere neceſſitie) on a Sabbath day: yet hee was by the law ſtoned for his labour. A man would think that Peter had giuen his maiſter good counſell,Mat. 16.22 23. (when as Chriſt told him that he muſt goe to Ieruſalem, &amp; there ſuffer many things:) ſaying, Maiſter fauour thy ſelfe, and goe not: yet he was called Sathan for his labour.Act. 5.35. A man would thinke that Ananias and Saphira had committed but a ſmall ſinne, when as they did detaine parte of the Apoſtles money, for feare of afterclaps, and proteſted the contrary with a lye: yet they died both ſuddenly at the feete of Peter. So

a man would thinke, that an idle word were but a ſmal ſinne yet Chriſt ſaith heere, that a great account muſte bee made for the ſame; For by thy words thou ſhalt bee iuſtified, and by thy wordes thou ſhalt bee condemned.
               Ma. 11.3.5 Seeing this is true, it behooueth euerie man to ſet a watch before the doore of his lippes, and to keepe his tongue from idle and euill words, that he may obtaine that bleſſedneſſe:Eccl. 14.8 
               bleſſed is he that hath not fallen by the words of his mouth.
            
            
               
               3 We muſt giue an account of our workes:Works. 1. cor. 5.10 Ecle. 12.14 as it appeareth to the Corinthians: Wee muſte all appeare before the iudgement ſeat of Chriſte, and there receiue according to our works. Againe the Preacher ſaith: that God will bring to iudgement, euery worke, with euery ſecret thing, whether it bee good or euill. Hee that hath liued in ſinne ſhall receiue the reward of ſinne, which is death and damnation; and he that hath liued in faith and amendment of life, ſhal receiue a crowne of glory, whi
                     •
                  h the Lord will giue him at that day.
            
            
               It is the duty therefore of euery Chriſtian to labour and endeauour with all diligent carefulneſſe to liue toell, that at the day of iudgement, he may ſpeed well. 
                  〈◊〉
                
               bene vmore, that is, liue well, ſhoulde bee the delightſome poeſie, &amp; ſweete perfumed Noſegay of euery chriſtian: thus liue wel, that thou maieſt die wel, and after death eternally ſpeed well, obtayning that bleſſedneſſe, Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord.
            
            
               4 Wee muſt giue an account of our  temporall goods.Goods. howe wee haue gotten them whether iuſtly, or vniuſtly: how we haue ſpent them, whether we haue cloathed the naked with them, or whether we haue made naked the cloathed for them. howe wee haue diſpoſed them, leaſt there bee any debate for them after wee bee gone: therefore Eſay telling Ezekia that hee ſhould not liue but die, ſaith:Eſay. 38.1 
               Diſpone domum tuam, &amp;c. Set thine houſe in order, for thou muſt not liue but die.
                Howe then ſhall thoſe griping vultures make an account, that haue by oppreſſion vndone their brethren? The worlde is

grown ſo hard bearted, that men will rather ſuffer their brethren to ſtarue in the ſtreets, than to ſuccour or relieue them: the dogs ſhall haue the remnant of the ritch mans Table,Iuk 16 21. before poore Lazarus ſhall haue one crumme that falleth from the ſame. How ſhall theſe flinty heartes looke for one dramme of mercy at the daye of iudgement? Let thē look with what meaſure they haue meaſured to others, it ſhall be meaſured to them againe: let them know that it they will ſtoppe their ears at the cry of the poore, they ſhall crie themſelues, and ſhall not bee heard: if they will bee partakers with the Saints of the ioys of heauen, their brethren muſt be partakers with them of their wealth on earth: for this is to treaſure vp treaſures in heauen, to layout their treaſures on earth.
            Let men therefore ſo vſe their temporall goods, and worldly ritches, as they may at the daye of account receiue a crowne of immortall glory.
            
               
               5 We muſt giue an account of the time wherein wee liue,Time. and of our ſeuerall vocations, how wee haue imployed

our ſelues in the ſame.
            Saith Bernard: Omne tempus tibi impenſum requiretur á te,
               Ber. 
               qualiter fuerit expenſum: id eſt. All the time that God hath giuen thee, ſhall bee required at thy hands, how thou haſt ſpent it:
                Whether in the ſeruice of God or in the ſeruice of Sathan.
            The Prince muſt giue an account, how hee hath gouerned his kingdome: whether hee hath (as it becommeth Gods vicegerent) mildly, louingly, and carefully trained his ſubiects vp in the worſhip of GOD: or as a bloodie Nero, and hard-hearted Tyrant cruelly oppreſſed them. The miniſters of the word of God (who haue taken vppon them curam animarum, the charge of ſoules
               ) muſt giue an account, how they haue be haued themſelues in their miniſterie: whether they haue preached Chriſt for Chriſt, that is, for the conuerſion of ſinners to Chriſt, or (as hirelings) for lucre and gaine of worldlye traſh: whether they haue fedde their flocks carefully, or fed vpon their flocks couetouſly. The Magiſtrate muſt giue an account, how he hath behaued himſelfe

in his magiſtracy: whether hee hath ſought the maintenāce of vertue, and the confuſion of vice: or hath (his eyes beeing blinded with ſiluer ſcales) maintained iniquity, and oppreſſed the innocent. The houſholder, how hee hath gouerne
                  •
                his family: whether in reading of holy Scriptures, and prayer, to the praiſe and glory of God; or in reading of fooliſh fables, in gaming, dicing, playing, ſwearing and ſuch like. Yea euery man muſt giue an accounte of the time ſpent in his ſeueral calling, from the highſt to the loweſt. Let euery Chriſtian therefore beware of miſpend
                  •
               ng his time, liuing in ſecurity looſly, and of looſing his time ſecurely, &amp; careleſly: for there will come a day when for euery houre of thy life thou ſhalt giue an account, how thou haſt ſpent it: according as Salomon telleth the careleſſe liuer: Reioyce O young man in thy youth, cheere thy hearte in the dayes of thy youth, and walke in the wayes of thine hearte, and in the ſighte of thyne eyes: but know that for all theſe thinges GOD will bring thee to iudgement. Time loſt can neuer bee recouered,

the houre paſt cannot bee recalled: time is painted like an olde man hauing a locke of hayre on the former parte of his head, but balde on the hinder part; to ſignifie, that men ſhould lay hold of time comming, and make much of it when they haue it: for being once gone, it can neuer bee recouered.Aug. 
               Augustine confeſſeth that hee ſpent his time idlely when hee ſtoode gazing and looking on a Spider, howe thee catcht a flye in her net: But alas, men in theſe daies do not onely ſpend their time in idlenes (which is a ſhamefull fault amongſt Chriſtians) but alſo in all manner of euill:Amos 6.
                     •
                  
                
               They put off from them the euill day, namely the day of death and iudgement, and boldly approach to the ſeate of iniquity: a matter much to be lamented.
            Let euery Chriſtian therefore haue a care of the expence of time, leaſt (had I wiſt) comes too too late: for the damned in hell if they had this fauoure of God, to liue on the earth againe, and to haue hell broken looſe (which they ſhal neuer haue granted) they would liue ſo ſtrictly, as they might bee Chronicled

for admirable ſpectators to the whole world.Exemp. It is the duty therfore of euery man, to imitate that perſon, that vigilant perſon, that carried alwaies about with him in his pocket a little clocke, and when hee heard it ſound, hee would inſtantly examine himſelfe how he had ſpent that houre: thus ſhould Chriſtians examine themſelues, that they may neuer bee examined of the Lord, iudge themſelues that they may neuer be iudged of the Lord, and account with themſelues, that they may neuer be brought to an account of the Lord. Thus much for the ſecond part of this text, namely, of what thinges we muſt giue an account.
            
               But I ſay vnto you, of euery idle worde, &amp;c. Before I ſpeak of the third parts of this text, namely of the Iudge, to whom wee muſt giue an account, I thinkeſt very neceſſary to ſpeake of a few things, which beeing wel conſidered, wee may bee able to abſtaine from idle words, and ſhall haue the leſſe account to make at that day. Three things therefore there are, which being performed, we ſhall abſtaine from

idle words.
            
               
                  1 A man muſt cōſider what he ſpeaketh
               
                  2 To whom he ſpeaketh.
               
                  3 When he ſpeaketh.
            
            
               1 What hee ſpeaketh:Quid 
               Peter telleth vs what we ought to ſpeak in his firſt Epiſtle:1. Pc. 4.11 
               Jf any man ſpeak let him ſpeak as the words of God. Againe Paule to the Epheſians ſaith:Epeſ. 4.29 
               Let no corrupt communication proceede out of your mouth, but that which is good to the vſe of edifiing, that it may miniſter grace to the hearer. So that we ought to ſpeake aboue all things of God and his word, of good and honeſt matters, if wee will ſhew our ſelues to be true Chriſtians, and abſtinent from idle words. Wee ſhoulde ſay with Dauid,
               Pſal. 34.1. 
               I will alwaye giue thanks to the Lord, his praiſe ſhall be in my mouth continually.
               Iob. 27.4. We ſhould reſolue with Iob and ſay: My lippes ſurely ſhall ſpeak no wickedneſſe, and my tongue ſhall vtter forth no deceipte: then ſhall we vſe our tongues to that purpoſe, to which they were created.
            The tongue in Hebrew is called: Kebod: id eſt, gloria Glory; becauſe it

is an inſtrument to ſing forth the glory of God vpon earth. If wee vſe our tongues to this purpoſe, then may wee truely ſay with the Poet, Lingua quid melius?
               Poet. 
               What is better then the tongue? But if it bee abuſed to the diſhonour of Almighty God, if it bee an vntamed member, vttering out idle, and euill words: then may wee conclude with the Poet, and ſay, Lingua quid p
                     •
                  es eadem? What is worſe than the tongue?
               
            
            Let euery Chriſtian therefore ſhew himſelfe (as hee profeſſeth) a Chriſtian in his ſpeeche:Mat. 12.3
                     •
                  
                
               For out of the aboundance of the heart, the mouth ſpeaketh. Euen as the heart ſtandeth affected, ſo is the ſpeach of euery man: For Lingua eſt mentis interpres: the tongue is the interpreter of the mind:
                the chaſte man ſpeaketh chaſtly and honeſtly, the wanton ſpeaketh lewdely and luxuriouſly: the enuious perſon ſpeaketh bitingly and bitterly. Euen as by his ſpeeche a man may bee knowne what countriman hee is: ſo a man by his ſpeeche may bee knowne to what kingdome he belongeth.
            
               There are three kingdoms &amp; men by their talke may be known to which of theſe they belong. There is, 1.
               Three kingdoms. 
               Prouincia coeleſtis, the kingdome of heauen:
                and the ſpeach of this country is praiſing of God, talking of his worde, giuing of thankes for the greate benefits wee haue receiued, and ſpeaking of diuine and heauenly matters: hee therefore that ſpeaketh on this maner (Id que non hypocritice that is, Not hipocritically. For Simulata ſanctitas, duplex inquitas: counterfeit holineſſe is double vngodlines
               ) ſurely appertaineth to the kingdome of heauen.
            
               2 There is prouincia terreſtris: the  kingdome of earth,
                and the ſp
                  •
               ach of this country is talking of terrene end earthly matters 
                  ••
               ozling with ye mole in the Cranies terrarumque poris, and in the pores of the earth,
                quite contrary to the nature of man:Ouid. for Os homini ſublime dedit (ſaith the Poet) coelumque tueri inſſit: God gaue man a lofty face, and bad him looke aloft, and hold vp his head toward heauen.
                According to that of Iohn: Qu
                     •
                  de terra eſt, de terra loquitur: He that is of the earth, ſpeaketh of

the earth.
               
               Iob. 3.31. 1. Iohn. 4.5 And againe, They are of the world, therfore ſpeak they of the world.
            
            
               
               3 There is prouincia infernalis: The kingdome of Hell
               : and the language of this countrey is, ſwearing, forſwearing, curſing, banning &amp; blaſpheming: if therfore thou ſeeſt ſuch a one, it is to be feared that he belongeth to the prouince of hell. Thou therefore that wouldeſt belong to Gods thrice bleſſed kingdome, thou that wouldeſt abſtaine from idle words, &amp; ſo haue the leſſe account to make; thou muſt beware what thou ſpeakeſt, thou muſt talk of God &amp; of his word, of holy &amp; heauēly matters.
            
               2 He that would abſtaine from idle words, muſt conſider, to whom he ſpeaketh: if hee ſpeaketh to a foole, be muſt vſe fewe wordes, for hee ſpendeth his breath in vaine: if he ſpeaketh to a froward and contentious perſon, hee muſt vſe mild and gentle words: or elſe bee taketh the bellows to quench the fire: if he ſpeaketh to a wiſe man, hee muſt vſe no vaine Cautologies, or needleſſe repetitions: for fruſtrà fit per plura, quod fiers poteſt per paucior
                     •
                  t. It is in vaine to vſe many words, whē we may as wel be conceiued

in few.
                If theſe things be not cō
               ſidered, we may (yea ſpeaking of diuine and holy matters) offend in idle words.
            
               3 If wee would abſtaine from idle words, wee muſt alſo conſider when to  ſpeake: ſaith Salomon:
               Eccleſ. 3.
                     •
                  
                
               There is a time to ſpeake, and a time to hold ones peace. Saith one: there is a time when ſomething may be ſpoken, &amp; there is a time when nothing may be ſpoken, but there is no time when all things may be ſpoken. Theſe three things wel conſidered of vs, we ſhal abſtaine from idle words, and haue the leſſe accounte to make at the day of iudgement. Againe euery Chriſtian, as he ought to imitate Chriſt in al things, ſo he ought to imitate him in his words: Gregorie ſaieth, that Omnis Chriſti actio noſtra debet eſſe instructio, id eſt, Euery action of Chriſt ought to be to vs an exāple of imitation.
               
               Greg. Chriſt had three things in his wordes worthy of conſideration, which wee muſt likewiſe labor to haue, if we will abſtaine from idle words.
            
               1 He had veritatem in verbis: trueth  in his words:
                yea he reporteth of himſelfe in John: that he is, via, voritas,
               Iohn. 14.6 
               &amp;



vita: the way, the truth, and the life.
                He therefore that ſpeaketh truth to his neighbour, ſheweth himſelfe to bee the child of Chriſt Ieſus, the fountaine and origo of al truth: but he that ſpeaketh 
                  •
               aſings: and vttereth forth lies, ſheweth himſelfe to be the childe of the diuel, the author &amp; originall of all lies.  2 Chriſt had vt in verbis: profit in his words:
                as he ſpake truly, ſo he ſpake profitably: he neuer ſpake one idle or vnprofitable word throughout ye whole courſe of his life, which was aboue 32 years. 3 Chriſt had moderamē in verbis 
                  A mean in his word
                        •
                     
                  
                the neuer was in words exceſſi
                  •
               e, and when iuſt and neceſſarie occaſion was offered, hee was neuer deficient, but Ladie meane I meane golden vertu
                  •
                drew forth his well contriued wordes out of the rich content of his euer-flowing heart, He fulfilled that ſaying of Ieſus the ſon of 
                  
                     •
                  h: the wordes of the wiſe are weighed in a ballance.
               
               
                  
                     •
                  ccleſiaſti 21.25.
            
            In theſe three thinges ſhould euerie one imitate Chriſt Ieſus, and then wee ſhould abſtaine (as hee did) from idle, vaine, friuolous, and vnprofitable

words, for which a great account muſt be giuē: the which imitation of Chriſt, the Lord for Chriſt his ſake, graunt to all men, that they being like vnto him may bee receiued to reigne with him, and his holy Angels in the thrice happie heauens at that day, Amen.
            
               But I ſay vnto you,
               Text 
               that of euery idle word that men ſhall, &amp;c.
            
            
               3 To whome this account muſt bee giuen:The third part. although in this ſcripture the Iudge is not expreſly mentioned, yet notwithſtanding quod ſubintelligitur non d
                     •
                  est: that which is vnderſtoode is not wanting
               : and therefore not to bee omitted.
            This Iudge therefore before whoſe tribunall ſeat all mankinde muſt appeare, it is Chriſt: for he was annointed of his father into a triple office: to be a Prieſt after the order of Melchiſedech. to be a Prophet after the order of Dauid: to be a King after the order of Salomon. Therfore Chriſt, as hee is king ouer all in heauen and earth, is this iudge before whome wee muſte all appeare: the truth of this is euident in the Epiſtle of Saint Paule to the Corinthians:

VVe muſt all appeare before the tribunall ſeate of Chriſte,
               2. Cor. 5.10 
               &amp;c. Wee read alſo in Iohn, that the father iudgeeth no man, but hee hath committed all iudgement to his ſonne. And in Mathew it is written, that all power is giuen to Chriſte in heauen and in earth.
               Iohn. 5, 22 Math. 28.18. Pſ. 2.7.8.9 This was prophecied of him in the Pſalme. Thou art my ſonne, this day haue I begotten thee: aske of mee, and I wil giue thee the heathen for thine inheritance, and the ends of the earth for thy poſſeſſion: thou ſhalt cruſh them with a Scepter of iron, and breake them in peeces like a potters veſſel. And againe in another place: Sit thou at my righte hand,
               Pſal. 110, 1 
               vntill I make thine enemies thy footſtoole. Yea, it is an article of our faith, to beleeue that Chriſt ſhall come againe to iudge the quicke and the dead.
            
               Iudge,Chriſt is therfore the iudge: yea he is the vorus Index, a righte Iudge: for this word Index, that is Iudge, is as much as ius dicens: id eſt One that ſpeaketh iuſtice
               : and Iudice: that is, to iudge, is as much as, ius dice: to ſpeak iuſtice,
                and iudicium, that is, iudgement
               
is as much as iuriſdicium, if I may ſo terme it, that is a iuſt and righte ſpeech.
            
            So Chriſt being an vprighte iudge maintaineth iuſtice in iudgement: hee is a iudge that will vſe no partialitie, but will reward euery man according to his works: he is a iudge that hath no reſpecte of perſons.Rom▪ 2, 
                     •
                  
                Men in this world may fitly be compared to actors of a Comedie vpon a ſtage: Whereto one acteth yt part of a Prince, another of a Duke, another of an Earl, another of a noble man, another of a Gentlemā, another of a Magiſtrate, another of a merchant, another of a countrimā, another of a ſeruāt: one acteth one part, one another; &amp; ſo long as they are vpon the ſtage, ſo long there is reſpect [according to their parts] one of another amongſt them: but when the Comedie is ended, and the ſtage pulled downe, then there is no ſuch reſpect amongſt them: yea many times he that played the baſeſt part, is the beſt man.
            So likewiſe, ſo long as men art ſūdry parts vpon the ſtage of this earth, that

is, ſo long as men doe liue in ſeuerall vocations, ſo long there is reſpect amongſt men, and that worthily: but when as the Come die ſhall bee ended, that, is, the day of doome ſhal come vpon all men, when as the ſtage ſhall be pulled downe, that is, the earth ſhall bee chaunged (for the earth ſhall neuer bee brought ad non ens, to nothing; but onely the corruptiue qualities ſhall bee conſumed:] then ſhall there bee no reſpecte of perſons amongeſt men: yea it may bee that the poore man ſhall be greater before God than the rich man. Yea and Beſides all this, vpon the earth GOD hath no reſpecte of perſons [although there bee reſpecte amongeſt men) but euery man ſhall receiue according to his workes, the Prince as wel as the ſubiecte, the rich as well as the poore.
            If a Iudge then ſhould come into a citie, &amp; ſhould iudge the greateſt part of the citty to death, ſparing no man, nec precio, nec prece, neither by bribes nor intreaties,
                would not euery man in that Citty be in great perplexity and feare?

ſo feare this Iudge, who ſhall come with thouſandes of Angels in greate Pompe, Maieſtie, and Glorie, into the citty of this world, and iudge the greateſt part of mankinde to death, and damnation, ſparing no man, neither pretto, nor prece, neyther by bribes, nor yet by intreaties, a Iudge that wil vſe no partiality, A Iudge that is able to deſtroy both bodie and ſoule in hell are for euermore: feare this iudge,Iam. 4.12. this terrible Iudge, this iuſt Iudge, this ſtrict Iudge, that wil not ſuffer one idle word to eſcape in iudgement: thou that haſt offended this Iudge by thy manifolde tranſgreſſions, thou that haſt deſerued for them euerlaſting torments in the pit of hell, feare him: quake and tremble before him at the hearing of this hard ſaying: But I ſay vnto you, that of euery idle words that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue account thereof at the day of iudgement.
            If Paule a choſen veſſel, and a faithful ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt, was afraide of this iudgement: if the iuſt and vprighte man Iob cried out and

ſaid:Iob. 31.14 
               Quid agam, quò me conuertam cum venerit dominus ad iudicandum? What ſhall I doe, O whither ſhall I tu
                        •
                     ne me, when the Lord commeth to iudgement?
               
               Hil
                     •
                  ion. If bleſſed Hilary (who from the fourteenth yeere of his age ſerued the Lord in ſingleneſſe of heart, and in ſincerity of life to his liues end) was afraid of this day: as it appeareth by his ſpeach vpon his death-bed: Egredere anima, agredere: quid times? quid dubitas? that is, Goe forth O ſoule, goe forth, why art thou afraid? why doubteſt thou? thou haſt ſerued Chriſt theſe ſeuentie yeares, &amp; art afraid now to depart? If theſe holy men were afraide of this terrible day: how oughteſt thou (O ſinner) that art defiled with ſinne from top to toe, that haſt not ſerued thy God (as thou oughteſt) one daye in 70. yeares, how oughteſt thou to quake and tremble?1 Pc. 4.18 if the iuſt ſhall ſcarce bee ſaued, where ſhalte thou (poore wretch) appeare?
            
               Ex. 16.18.If the people of Iſraell trembled at the preſence of God on mount Sinai, when the Lorde gaue vnto them his lawe, and (as a Scheolemaiſter,) read

a lecture to all the world: how terrible will his preſence bee when hee ſhall come and exact this lecture at thy handes, howe thou haſt conned the ſame?Apo. 1.17 Dan. 8.17
            
            If Iohn and Daniel, at the ſight of a mild Angel, fel vpon the earth as dead: how ſhalt thou (poore ſinner) indure the preſence of this terrible iudge? If Haman could not abide the angrie countenance of King Ahaſueroſh: how ſhalt thou (O wicked man) abide the angrie countenance of this frowning iudge? If Adam,
               Heſt. 7.6. Gen. 3.8. for the commiſſion of one ſinne, ranne from god in greate feare, and hid himſelfe behinde the buſh: whither ſhalt thou (O ſinfull Adamite that haſte committed as many ſinnes as ſtarres in ſkye, as haires on head and ſands by ſea. Immò horum numerus numero non clauditur vllo: Yea the number of them is not to bee numbred
               ) whither (I ſay) ſhalte thou deſire to runne? and where ſhalte thou wiſh to hide thy ſelfe from this terrible iudge? O (ſaith Auguſtine) mallent impii eſſe in inferno, quàm videre faciem irati indicis; The wicked had rather be

tormented in hell, than ſee the face of this feareful iudge.
               Aug. Then ſhalt thou cry to the mountaines: Cadite ſuper me: Fall vpon mee:
               
               Apoc. 6.16 and to the hilles: Abſcondite me à facis ſedentis ſuper thronum, &amp; ab ir a agni: id eſt, Hide mee from the face of him that ſitteth vppon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb.
               
            
            Then ſhall the booke bee opened, videlicet, the euidence of thy workes in this life, recorded freſhly in the teſtimonye of thyne owne conſcience, and in the true and infallible memory of Gods eternall wiſedome: then ſhall thy ſinnes bee ſett in order before thyne eyes:Pſal. 50.21 Pſal. 50.4. Rom. 2.15. heauen and earth ſhall witneſſe, againſt thee, yea thyne owne conſcience ſhall condemne thee: and conſcientia eſt mille teſtes: Thy conſcience is a thouſand witneſſes to condemne thee.
                The Diuell ſhall pleade hard (moſt pitifull wretche) for thy ſoule and body, accuſing thee on this manner: O iudex iuſtiſſime, O moſt iuſt iudge,
                thou haſt in the aboundaunce of thy loue ſuffered many tormentes of hell vpon the Croſſe at Golgotha, for

the redemption of this wretche: thou haſt offered him (times innumerable) redemption, iuſtification, and endleſſe happineſſe: yet neuertheleſſe hee hath deſpiſed thee, and hated thy inſtruction, and hath choſen rather to followe mee, then thee, rather to walke in iniquity after my example, then in holyneſſe of life after thyne, hee hath choſen to bee my ſeruant, rather than thyne: therefore what remayneth, but that thou ſhouldeſt refuſe him, that refuſed thee, and that I ſhould receiue him to euerlaſting torments, that hath hitherto ſerued mee.
            When thou (poore ſoule) ſhalte heere this pitifull Plea, and confeſſe the ſame to bee too true, what ſhall become of thee, or whither ſhalt thou turne thee for comfort? Alacke, alacke, thou ſhalt haue no hope of ſaluation: for aboue thee, thou ſhalt ſee the iudge angry with thee for thy ſinnes, and the bleſſed Angels reioycing and laughing at thy deſtruction: benethe thee, thou ſhalt ſee hell open, and the fierye fornace ready to receiue thee to torment: on thy right hand ſhall bee thy ſinnes

accuſing thee: on thy left hand the diuells readye to execute Gods iudgements vpon thee: within thee ſhall lye thy conſcience gnawing: without thee the damned crue bewatling: on euery ſide fire burning: and then ſhalt thou receiue this lamentable ſentence: Goe from mee ye curſed into euerlaſting fire,
               Mat, 25 41 
               which is prepared for the diuell and his Angels:
               Goc▪
                Euery one of theſe wordes are able to cut thy heart a ſunder. Go from me: hitherto I haue beene a Father to thee: I haue beſtowed many comfortable benefits vppon thee: I haue had great care of thee: but now goe from mee into torments inexpreſſible: where thou ſhalt cry vnto mee, but I will not beere thee: in torment ſhalt thou lye comfortleſſe: in hell thy torment ſhall bee endleſſe: I will put a gulfe betweene thee and mee, to make thy torments remedileſſe: thou ſhalt bee dying alwaies, yet neuer dead: thou ſhalt ſeeke death,Apoc. 9.6. Luk. 6.25. but neuer finde it: thou ſhalt bee burning alwaies, yet neuer burnt to death: thy meate ſhall bee griping hunger, and famine intollerable:Pſal. 11.6. Mat. 13.4
                     •
                  
                thy drinke ſhall bee lakes of

fire and brimſtone: thy muſicke ſhall bee howling and roaring of crying Diuels, and weeping, wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth.
            
               Yee curſed:
               Yee Cur
                     •
                  
                thou haſt beene called hitherto by renowned and glorious titles: as Prince, Duke, Noble, Reuerend, Maiſter, &amp;c.
            but now thou ſhalt haue an other title: thou ſhalt be called curſed: curſed ſhalt thou be of God, whoſe curſe is panarum inflictio: id eſt puniſhment:
                curſed ſhalt thou be of all the bleſſed Angels in heauen: whoſe curſe is conſcientiae cruciamen, id eſt vexation of thy conſcience;
                curſed ſhalt thou bee of all the diuels in hell, whoſe curſe is poenarum executio, id eſt: the execution of thy puniſhment preſcribed;
                according to that of the poet; Minos examen, Radamanthus dat cruciamen; tertius heu frater tertia iura tenet: id eſt, One diuell rippeth vp thy examination, another diuell tormenteth thee, the third is not behinde to adde one torment to another vppon thee.
                Curſed moreouer ſhalte thou bee of all the damned crue, whoſe curſe, is poenarum aggrauatio, id eſt: the augmentation

of thy torment:
                thus curſed ſhalt thou bee of all thinges for euermore. Jnto euerlaſting fire: O miſerable torment! there were ſome comforte to the damned ſoule, if theſe torments ſhould haue end: but that ſhall neuer bee: O miſerable wretche, thou ſhalt bee bound hand and foote, and caſt into this euerlaſting fire,
               Into euerl. fire. Mat. 22.13 in reſpect of which fire, all earthlye elementall fire is but as fire painted on a wall; thy tormentes ſhall be endleſſe, eaſeleſſe and remedileſſe.
            
               Which is prepared.
               Which is prepared for the diuell and his Angells: Heauen was prepared for thee, and not Hell: thou wert borne to glory, and not to torment; but becauſe thou haſt choſen to followe the Diuell and not mee, therefore, Goe from mee yee curſed into euerlaſting fire which is prepared for the diuell, and thee his wicked Angell; where thou ſhalt lye weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of thy teeth for euermore.
            The conſideration of theſe things ſhoulde ſtirre vp euerye Chriſtian to looke about him, to bee carefull and circumſpect to all his wayes, that hee treade not his ſhooe awry at any time,

that he offend not this fearefull iudge, in any thing: that at this day of iudgment hee may finde him a gentle and louing Lambe, and not a Lyon of Iuda: for as to the wicked this iudge is terrible, ſo to the godly hee is a friendly and a welcome Iudge: as to the wicked the day of iudgement is a daye of deſolation, a day of cloudes and blackneſſe; ſo to the godly,Zeph, 1.15 it is a day of redemption, yea the godly ſhall leape for ioy at that day, and for the comming of that eternall daye,Apoc. 6.9 10. the bleſſed ſpirits in heauen cry out ſaying: how long Lord? and the bleſſed ones vpon earth deſiring the comming of this day alſo; ſaying with Paule, Cupimus diſſolui &amp; eſſe cum Chriſto, id eſt,
               Phil. 1.23. Apoc. 22. 
               Wee deſire to bee diſſolued, and to bee with Chriſt; and praying with Iohn, Veni Domine Ieſu; Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.
               
            
            Let euery Chriſtian therefore ſo lead his life, that it may goe well with him at that day; What if J haue all the world,
               Math. 
               and looſe my ſoule at that day, what doth it profit me.
            
            If a man be called to appeare before ſome earthly iudge, hee will haue an eſpecial

care to array himſelf in the beſt manner hee may, and to be haue himſelfe accordingly, that hee may bee the better accepted of him: So euery Chriſtian againſt the daye of iudgement, when hee muſt appeare before the king of Kings, and iudge of all the worlde, muſt haue an eſpeciall care to put on the wedding garment of Chriſts righteouſneſſe and regeneration, leaſt hee bee ſent packing to Hell with the wicked and all thoſe that forget God.
            
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   2.
               Mordecay, becauſe he went baſely in ſackcloth, could not bee permitted to come into the Kings pallace: and doeſt thou thinke (whatſoeuer thou art) that thou ſhalt be admitted into ye glorious Pallace of the King of heauen, hauing on the ſtinking, defiled, &amp; abhominable garment of impurity, and the menſtruous cloath of iniquity? no, no, the Lord will ſpue thee out of his mouthe a ſtinking carkas ſtinketh not to before men, as a polluted ſinner in the noſtrells of almighty God.
            
               Nebuchadnezzar woulde haue no children in his Pallace, but thoſe that were wiſe and beautifull:Dan. 4. and doeſt

thou think, that the King of heauē and earth will haue any fooles, that is ſinners (for the ſinner is called a foole in the Scripture: the foo
                     •
                  e 
                     •
                  ath ſaid in his heart,
               Pſal. 14.1. 
               there is no God) to dwell with him in his Pallace? or doeſt thou think that any vgly perſon ſhall bee ſuffered there? that is any ſinner (for the ſinner is an vglye and abhominable thing in the ſight of God), no: the Lord will entertaine none into his kingdome, but ſuch as are beautifull, ſhining in holineſſe, purity, and righteouſneſſe, as the portalls of the burniſht ſunne: ſuch as are without ſpot or wrinckle, Omnino ad imaginem ſuam: altogither like vnto him:
                holy as hee is holy, pure as hee is pure: ſuch will the Lord haue in his kingdome to ſing Halleluiah: Saluation and glory, and honor,
               Apo. 19.1. 
               and power be to the Lord our God.
            
            Therefore as the theefe is exceeding prouident, and very carefull how hee may aunſwere the Iudge at the barre: and as in earthlye courtes men will be very carefull to prouide an anſwere againſt they bee called: yea and will make ſome friende to the iudge,

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
that they may ſpeede the better: So likewiſe euery Chriſtian ſoule ſhoulde carefully prouide a good aunſwere againſte hee bee cited by the Apparitour death, to appeare before Chriſte at the generall Courte of Heauen: And that then it may goe well with him, let him get ſome friend to mooue the iudge in his behalfe, as he tendereth the welfare of his deare ſoule: and who muſt that friende bee? Not Mary, nor Peter, but it muſte be Chriſt Ieſus, that ſitteth at the right hand of his father in glory, and maketh daily interceſſion for the ſinnes of the whole worlde. Get him for thy Proctour (who offereth himſelfe to al) and then happie ſhalt thou bee: the diuel ſhall not preuaile againſt thee: for Chriſt hath broken his head: the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt thee, for Chriſt hath conquered them: and death ſhall not bolde thee captiue, for chriſt hath ouercome it:P. 44.15. 
               Happy art thou that art in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed arte thou, if thou haſt the Lord for thy God:
            
            Thus much for the third pare of this Text namely, of the iudge, to whome

we muſt giue an account.Text.
            
            
               But I ſay vnto you, that of euery idle word, &amp;c.
            
            
               4 When we ſhall giue an account: it is ſaid heer: at the day of iudgement:
            The time, whē this great &amp; generall day ſhal be, cannot be known of mortal mā: yea it is not for mā to know of it: as we may read in ye 
               Acts: It is not for you to know the times &amp; ſeaſons,
               Act. 1, 7. Marke, 13 
               which God hath put in his owne power: yea Chriſte himſelfe knoweth not of this day:
               32. 
               But of that day and houre (ſaith Marke] knoweth no man, no, not the Angels which are in heauen, neither the Sonne himlelfe, ſaue the Father: id eſt
               : Chriſte according to his humane nature knoweth not of it, but according to his diuine nature, he knoweth of it, as well as God the Father: for he is coequall with God the Father in knowledge, wiſedome, and in all thinges whatſoeuer: yea hee knewe of this daye before the foundation of the world was laide, yea he himſelfe ſhal ſit iudge at ye day.
            God will not haue vs know of this daye, when it ſhall bee, for theſe three cauſes,
            
               
               
               1 To prooue and trie our patience, faith, and other vertues: to ſee whether wee will put our whole truſt and affiance in him, although wee 
                  ••••…
               e not the time of our diſſolution.
            
               
               2 To bridle our curioſitie and peeuiſh inquiſition after ſuch (too high) matters:Ariſt. 
               qua ſupra nos, nihil ad nos: that which is aboue our capacitie, wee ought not to meddle withall.
               
            
            
               
               3 To keepe vs in continuall watchfulneſſe: for if wee knew certainely the day of death and iudgement, ſurely it would be a greate and forcible motiue to drawe vs to a looſe, negligent, and ſecure kind of life.Mat. 24.42. 
               Watch therfore (ſaith the Euangeliſt) becauſe yee know not when your Maiſter will come. For theſe three cauſes the Lord will not haue vs know of the time of iudgement,
            Although (my beloued in Chriſte) we know not the certainetie of the time of this day: yet neuertheleſſe wee muſte knowe, that this great and general day cannot bee farre off, both according to the propheſies of holy Fathers, as alſo to the truth of holy Scriptures.
            
               Auguſtine, in his booke vpon Geneſis
               
againſt the Manichees, ſaith, that the worlde ſhoulde laſte ſixe ages: the firſt from Adam to Noah: the ſecond from Noah to Abraham: the third from Abraham to Dauid: the fourth frō 
               Dauid to the tranſmigration of Babilon: the fifth frō the tranſmigration of Babilon, to the comming of Chriſt in the fl
                  •
               ſh: the ſixth from the comming of Chriſte in the fleſh to his comming againe to iudgement. So that according to his prophecie wee liue in the laſt age, which laſt age,1 Ioh. 2.28 
               
                  •
                called of Iohn hora extrema
                or hora nouiſſima the laſte hour
                        •
                     :
                but how lōg this laſt houre doth laſt, he yt is α and ω the firſt &amp; the laſt, the euerlaſting God alone doth know.
            The Hebrewes they boaſt of the prophecie of Eliah,
               Eliah. a great man in thoſe da
                  •
               e
                  •
                hee prophecied that the worlde ſhould laſt 6000, year
                  •
               s 2000, before the law 2000, vnder the law: and 2000 from Chriſt to Chriſte.
            If this his prophecie holdes true, the world cannot laſt 400 yeares for ſince Chriſte his comming in the fleſh, it was 1606. at Chriſtes tide laſt haſt, according to the computation of the Church from time to time. But leauing men

and comming to the Scripturs, which cannot erre, for Humanū eſt errare: Man may, yea and doth many times erre.
               
            
            
               1. Co. 10.11Sainte Paule ſaith, to the Corinthians: Wee are they vpon whome the ends of the world are come. If therefore the ends of the worlde were come vpon thē that liued aboue 1560. yeares ago, then ſurely doomes day cānot now poſſibly be far off.
            
               Iam. 5.9.
               Iames likewiſe ſaith: Behold the Iudge ſtandeth before the doore.
            
            
               Mat. 3.2
               Iohn Baptiſt preached repentance to the Iewes, ſaying: repent for the kingdome of heauen is at hand.
            
            So that by theſe places of Scripture it is euident, that the generall day of Iudgement is at hand: as alſo by the ſignes &amp; tokens which ſhould goe before this day immediatly, of which many, yea almoſt all are already fulfilled.
            Moreouer we muſt (deare brethren] know that there is a twofolde iudgement: the one called a particuler iudgment the other called a generall iudgment.
            
               
               Death what
               1 The particular iudgemente is exerciſed and executed vpon euery man immediatly after death, which is ſegregatio

anima a corpore: a ſeparation of the ſoule from the bodie.
               
            
            Of this particuler iudgemente wee may reade in the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes: It is appointed vnto men, that they ſhall once die,
               Heb. 9.27. 2 Eſ. 14.25 
               and after that commeth iudgemente. And though the generall Iudgement commeth not theſe 4000. years, yet particular iudgment cōmeth at the day of our death: &amp; look as we at the day of our death ſhal be found, ſo ſhall we bee iudged: and as we then ſhal be iudged, ſo ſhall wee bee iudged at the general iudgement.
            
               2 The generall iudgement
                  •
                (of which this Scripture ſpeaketh) is exerciſed and executed vpon all men together by Chriſte: who ſhall by his power raiſe all thoſe vp againe that haue beene dead from the beginning of the world, to that time: and they ſhall bee preſented all together (being againe vnited to theire ſoules] before Chriſtes tribunall ſeate, who ſhall come downe in a cloude from heauen, in greate maieſty and glory, with thouſands of bleſſed Angels attending vpon him: and hee ſhall giue ſentence vpon all in generall: the wicked

ſhall be caſt into euerlaſting fire, &amp; the godly he ſhall carry vp with him into caelum Empiraeum, the third and higheſt heauen, (where he nowe in bodie reigneth &amp; remaineth) there to reape ioyes vnſpeakable for euermore,
            But ſome man may obiecte and ſay, why (I pray you) ſhall there bee a generall iudgement, when as all are iudged in the particuler iudgement? what ſhall thee be two iudgements executed? There ſhal notwithſtanding the particul
                  •
               r) be a generall iudgemente,Anſ. and that for three cauſes.
            
                1 Becauſe in the particuler iudgemēt the faule of man is iudged onely, but then both ſoule &amp; bodie ſhall be iudged
            
               
               2 In the particuler iudgemēt, ye ſoule onely is either rewarded or puniſhed: but then both ſoule &amp; bodie either ſhal be rewarded with ioyes, or puniſhed with torments.
            
               
               3 There ſhall be a generall iudgmēt. to declare to all the worlde aſſembled then together, the iuſte iudgemente of god: that he hath iuſtly ſaued the godly▪ &amp; iu
                  •
               ly condēned the wicked: yea the uery wicked themſelues ſhal confes no leſſe.
            
               By reaſon of this generall iudgement, ſome light braine hereticks their bee ye ſay, that ther is no particular iudgmēt at al, &amp; that the ſoul immediatl
                  •
                after death is not iudged: for wheras it is ſaid hodie mecūeris in paradiſo,
               Luke. 23.43. 
               to day ſhalte thou be with me in paradiſe, the ſpeech of our ſauiour to the theef they take that word hodie id eſt, to day
                for 1000 years; &amp; bring for proofe hereof that place of ye 
               Pſalmiſt A thouſand yeeres in thy ſighte are as yeſterday,
               Pſal. 90.4.
            
            But to anſwere them: this place of Scripture is not ſo to bee vnderſtood,Anſ. as that a thouſand yeares ſhoulde bee taken for a day; or a day for a thouſand yeares: for hee ſaith not: a thouſand yeares are a daye: but a thouſand yeares in the ſighte of God, that is, in reſpecte of the eternity and euerlaſtingneſſe of god, are as a day: It is therefore ſpoken on this manner to expreſſe the eternitie of God, as if hee ſhould ſay: a thouſand yeares with man in reſpect of the eternity of God, are but as a daye: for as many as are, haue beene, and euer ſhall bee the daies of man, ſo many thouſand, yea ſo many thouſand thouſands yeeres is the eternity of

God: he is-and-the firſt and the laſt, before all beginnings, and ſhall neuer haue ending.
            
               Gen. 
                     •
                  .17:Againe, they alledge that place of Geneſis; In that day that thou eateſt therof
                (namely of the forbidden fruite) thou ſhalt die the death.
            
            Now (ſaith the heretique) that day they died not,Ob. but liued many hundred yeers after: therfore by a day is vnderſtood many hundred yeers.
            
               Anſ.But I anſwer that, that day (wherin Adam did eat of the forbidden fruit) euen that day did hee dye: that is, that day by ſinne hee was ſeparated from God: then the which ſeparation no death is greater;Aug. for Vt vita corporis eſt anima, ita vita animae eſt deus; tolle animā, perit corpus: tolle deū, moritur animae; id eſt, As the ſoule is the life of the body, ſo God is the life of the ſoule; take away the ſoule, the body dieth; take away God, the ſoule is dead;
                So that Adam that day died in ſoule, being ſeparated from the Lord; yea that day Adam was made ſubiect to death in this life, and in the life to come; that day he had the beginnings of death ſeaſing vppon him, for hee was preſently caſt out of Paradiſe

into the ragged world, he was curſed and all his poſterity, yea hee ſhould haue gone to hell, had not the ſecond Adam broken the head of the ſubtile ſerpent that inticed him to ſin. Yea, the thiefe vpon the croſſe had Paradiſe that day in ſoule, in which he ſuffered in body; although he had it not in ſo full meaſure, as hee ſhall at the generall day, when his ſoule ſhall take vnto it the body againe; hodie, to daie
                thy ſoule with my ſoule ſhall be in Paradiſe, that is, in my fathers kingdome. Where is now the heretique that confoundeth particular iudgement?
            Where is now the Epicure, that thinketh there is no iudgment at all?
            Where is now the ignorant Papiſt that dreameth of Purgatory? and hee that fondly thinketh that there is Limbus patrum, and Lymbus puerorum? and where are theſe that imagin of a place of ab
                  •
               ade, betweene Heauen and Hell? I turne them all together to the Hebrewes for Wiſedome in this point:Heb. 9.27: where they ſhall finde that after death the ſoule of man is iudged.
            
               Phil. 1.23:Would Paul haue ſo earneſtly deſired

to haue beene diſſolued, if hee ſhould not preſently haue bin wt Chriſt He ſaith, that in this world wee ſee in a glaſſe darkly:
               1 Co. 13.11 Exo. 33.23 We ſee but Gods backe ports as Moſes did, that is, but a little of the ſailour of God: But then that is, after this life ended we ſhal ſee god face to face: that is, we ſhall haue the full fruition of him.
            
               Luk. 16.22We read of Diues and Lazarus, that after death the one was iudged to heauen, the other to hell: which is a Parable to ſignifie the trueth of this particular iudgement.
            
               Eccle. 12.7And (to conclade this poynt) we read in Salomon: that the duſt returneth to the earth from whence it came, and the ſpirit to God 
                  •
               h
                  •
                gaue it.
            So that wee may learne from hence the vncertainty of the day of iudgment. Wel ſaith Bernard:
               The vſe: hereof, Ber. 
               Nihil certius morte, hora mortis nihil inocentius: that is, Nothing is more certayn than death, &amp; there is nothing more vncertaine than the houre of death.
            Let euery Chriſtian therefore (that wiſheth the ſaluation of his ſoule at the day of death and iudgement) beware of ſecurity and careleſſe liuing: let no

man deferre repentance, and amendement of life, leaſt death come when he i
                  •
               d
                  •
               eth not for it, and ſo (being vnprepared he be caſt into hell fire.
            The olde world had 120.
               Gen. 6.3. Ion
                     •
                  s 1.4 Pl. 95.10. yeares to repent in: N
                     •
                  n
                     •
                  e had 40. dayes to repent in: Iſraell had 40. yeares to repent in; but thou (O mā) knoweſt not how long thou haſt to liue: thou haſte no leaſe o
                  •
                thy life: thou art heere to day, and gon
                  •
                to morrow: when the houres of thy life bee ended, and the glaſſe outrunne, thou muſt awaye: death waſteth for thee in euery place, and at all times: therefore waſte thou for it plaing as the fiue wiſe virgins,Mat. 25.4 that had the candle of faith burning in the lamps of their harts, nouriſhed wc the oyle of loue and workes,
            
               Ieruſalem, becauſe ſhee could not bee brought to repentance, ſhee was deſtroyed: many hundred thouſandes of her children were famiſh
                  •
               e to death:Ioſephu. and many hundred thouſands taken captiue by Titus Veſpatian the Roman Emperour: many caſt to wilde beaſtes and deuoured,
            The children of Iſraell, becauſe they were a ſtiffenecked people, and a froward

generation, and woulde not bee brought to repentance: how many thouſands of them lay ſlaine in the wilderneſſe? 600000. males; except Ioſhua and Caleb.
            
            The old world, becauſe they would take no warning,Gen. 7.23. and could not bee brought to amendment of life: the floud drowned them all, except faithfull Noah and his godly family. And except thou repenteſt, thou likewiſe ſhall periſh: according to that of Luks: Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh
               : beware therefore and repent betimes: Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum, Happy is he,
               
               Luke 13, 3 
               whome other mens harmes do make to beware.
            
            Refuſe no good motions knocking at the doore of thy heart, but entertaine them willingly; according to the counſell of Auguſtine;Aug. If hee offereth thee grace to day (ſaith hee) take it, make much of it: for thou knoweſt not whether he will offer the ſame to morrow: Make no long tarrying to turne to the Lord,
               Eccleſiaſticus. Poet. 
               and put not off from day to day; the longer thou remaineſt in thy ſinne, the harder it is for thee to repent: for Qui non eſt hedie, cras minùs aptus erit:

                  If thou beeſt not fit to amendement to day, thou wilt bee leſſe fit to morrow.
                Therfore while ye lord ſpeaketh to thee, make him anſwer: while hee calleth vnto thee, let there be an eccho in thine heart, as was in the heart of Dauid: ſeek ye my face: thy face Lord will ſeek:
                and while it is ſaid to day,Pſal. 27.9. 
               harden not thine heart. In no caſe therefore defer thy repentance: for the day of death and iudgement is vncertain; as ſaith Chriſoſtome: Poenitenti veniam ſpoſpondit, ſed viuendi in craſtinū non ſpoſpondit:Chryſoſt. that is, the Lord hath promiſed pardon to him that repenteth, but to liue till tomorrow, he hath not promiſed.
            
            But ſome there be in the world, that will ſay;Obiect. (the more it is to be lamented) I am young. I will liue a while after my hearts deſire, and in my olde age I will repent mee of my ſinnes; for God hath promiſed (who will be as good as his word.Eze. 18.21 22.) At what time ſoeuer a ſinner doeth repente him of his ſinnes from the bottom of his heart, J will put all his wickednes out of my remembrance, ſaith the Lord.
            
            And will pray to the Lord for forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes,Aug. as Auguſtine
               
ſaid before his conuerſion: Ignoſce (pacer) ignoſce mihi: at noli modo: Forgiue mee my ſinnes, but not now: let me ſinne in my youth, &amp; pardon me in myne age:
                thus they would deſire to die the death of the righteous: but they would not liue ye life of the righteous: but let theſe graceleſſe perſons (that thus deferre repentance) beware of two things.
            
               1 Let them beware of ſodaine death: Let them take heede, leaſt they bee cut off in the middeſt of their ſinnes, as Iobs children in the middeſt of their bauquetting and ryoting were ſoddaynely ſlayne by the fall of the houſe:Iob. 1.18. and as the floud came vnlooked for, and drowned the old world.
            
               Liuis reporteth a fearefull example of ſodaine death:Liuie. ſaith hee, there were two olde men that frequented two harlots, and preſently vppon the face committed they both died ſodainely: the one was thruſt thorow with a dagger: the other died ſodainely of an Apoplerie: which is a diſeaſe ingendered of aboundance of groſſe humors, which do fill thoſe veſſels and receptories of the head, from whence commeth feeling &amp; moouing of the body,Galen. as ſaith Galene,
               
and therefore they that haue this diſeaſe, are depriued of all ſence, feeling &amp; moouing.
            Let euery Iuſtie yonker and deſperate ruffian ſet this fearefull example before his eyes.
            Againe, the young man dieth, as ſoone as the olde: the Lambs ſkinne is brought to the market, as well as the old
                  •
                crones:Auguſt. true is that ſaying of Auguſtine: vita dum creſcit, decreſcit: vita mortalis, &amp; mors vitalis: id eſt life while it increaſeth, decreaſeth: life is dying, and death is liuing.
               
            
            
               2 Let all men that refuſe the mercy of GOD, and deferre their repentance know; that repentance is not theirs at command: but it is the great mercy of GOD: and it is to be feared, that they that haue refuſed it offered, when they would haue it, they ſhall goe without: according to that country Prouerbe: If you will not when you may; when you will, you ſhall haue nay: And it is commonly ſeene, that qualis vita, finis eta: as a man liueth, commonly be dieth: he that will liue without repentance, muſt look to die without repentance.
            
               Though God ſpared the thiefe at the laſte gaſpe, yet ſet no man preſume of that: for that was a medicine againſt deſperation, and not a matter of imitation: ſaith one: God ſpared one, that no man mighte deſpayre: he ſpared but one, that no man might preſume.
            
            Let euery man therefore (in the feare of God) without all delay, ſeeke for amendmente of life: Let them as (Gregory wiſheth) Plangere plangenda Bewaile their ſinnes that ought to be lamented:
               
               Rom, 6, 13. 
               and as they haue giuen their members, as weapons of vnrighteouſnes to iniquity: ſo let them now giue them as weapons of righteouſneſſe to holines. Repent (dear brethren) betimes; Viue de
                     •
                   gratus,
               Poet. 
               tote mundo tumulatus: crimine mundat us ſemper tranſire paratus; that is Liue vnto God a thankfull wight, &amp; to the world die; clenſe thy ſelfe frō wickedns, alwaies ready hence to fly.
            
            Play the wiſe ſteward, lay vp treaſures in heauen for thy ſoul: imitate the Piſmire which gathers in Sommer, wherby ſhe may liue in winter.
            
               Demaſc.
               Damaſcene reporteth an excellent Hiſtorie touching this purpoſe: ſaith he There was a country where they

choſe their king of the pooreſt and baſeſt ſort of the people, and vpon any diſlikement taken, they would depoſe him from his throne, and exile him into an Iland, where hee ſhould bee ſtarued to death: Now one wiſe fellow (cōſidering hereof) ſent mony before into that Ilād, into which he ſhould be baniſhed, and when he was baniſhed, he was receiued into ye iland with greate triumph. So againſt thou be baniſhed by death from this world, without penny or farthing, (for naked thou cameſt, &amp; naked thou muſt go) thou muſt prouide whils thou art in this life, whereby thou maieſt liue in heauen hereafter,
            Let nothing therfore make thee deferre thy amendment, but whileſt Chriſt calleth thee, run vnto him. Put on Ieromes reſolution who ſaid: If my mother wete hanging about my neck,
               Ieromes 
               if my brethren were on euery ſide, howling and crying, and if my father were on his bare knees, kneeling before me to detaine mee in their wicked and ſinfull courſe of life, what woulde J doe? I would ſhake off my mother to the groūd I woulde deſpiſe and hate all my kindred and kinſfolkes, and I would tread

and trample my Father vnder my feete, thereby to flie to Chriſt when he calleth me.
            
            So ſhouldeſt thou reſolue the amendment of life. The Lord of Heauen for his ſweet Sonne Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, graune to th
                  •
               r (deere Reader) and me, to both of vs, his holy Spirit that we may ſtand vnblameable before the Iudge, at that great and generall day: that we (beeing clothed with the long white Robes of righteouſneſſe,) may be in the number of thoſe to whom it ſhall be ſaid then: Come yee bleſſed children of my father, inherite the kingdome which was prepared for you from the beginning of the world. Grant this 
                  •
               eer father for thy deere ſonnes ſake, Chriſt Ieſus our onely Lorde and Sauiour: To whom with thee and the holy ſpirit we aſcribe all power, glory, and dominion, and ſtag Halleluiah to thee, (O bleſſed Trinitie) for euer and euer. Amen.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A ſhorte diſputation betweene the deuill and the poore ſoule of a Chriſtian.
            
               Sathan.
               
                  THou haſt beene a greate Sinner.
            
            
               Soule.
               Yes: but I am not ſoe.
            
            
               Sathan.
               Thou art damned for that thou haſte done.
            
            
               Soule.
               No: thou lyeſt Sathā: God hath promiſed otherwiſe to all that beleeue, repent, and amend.
            
            
               Sathan.
               Thou beleeueſt not, as thou ſayeſt thy ſelfe.
            
            
               Soule.
               
                  Yes, I beleeue, and I deſire to beleeue bettter: holineſſe of deſire doth ſeale Gods fauour to me.
            
            
               Sathan.
               Thy hearte is hard, and ſo are al theirs whome god hath reiected.
            
            
               Soule.
               No ſathan, make the worſte of it thou canſt, it is but a ſoule trance for a time; the holy ghoſt remaineth; for I feele him ſtill.
            
            
               Sathan.
               Doeſt not thou ſee that god hath taken thee in hand, and hath laide a heauie iudgement vpon thee?
            
            
               Soule.
               God indeede hath like a mercifull father taken me in hande, to make mee a newe creature: and like a louing father to correcte me: but his mercy will he neuer take from me, and no wrathful Iudgment ſhall be towardes me.
            
            
               Sathan.
               Euery Pulpit rings of thee, and euery parte of ſcripture proclaimes thee to bee myne,
            
            
               Soule.
               The Lord reprooue thee, ſathan, for this

Slaunder: for all ſcriptures and Pulpits tell me, I am gods dearely bought
            
            
               Sathan.
               Shewe me Gods ſeale for that, or els thou art mine.
            
            
               Soule.
               I can weepe for ſinne, and I hate ſinne in my ſelfe and others; and I loue vertue and the vertuous: which are the Armes of Chriſte in his ſeale, and I find my hart formoſt in his place marching on to heauen.
            
            
               Sathan.
               This thou didſt, but nowe thou haſte left thy firſt loue.
            
            
               Soule.
               Thou haſte ſaide ynough for mee, the loue of God is like himſelfe vnchangeable, his guiftes and calling are without repentance, once Loue and neuer hate, as once Loued and neuer hated.
            
            
               Sathan.
               Thou haſt confeſſed, that thou haſte no ſuch feeling in Prayer and Sermons, as in times paſt.
            
            
               Soule.
               What gayneſt thou by that? for in Chriſts wooing dayes I was ſhewed

the riches of his grace, but though I ſee not that dayly, ſo highly to inflame me; yet Chriſt is neuer the poorer, neither do I ceaſe to loue him: ſhew me any one of gods elect, that feeleth his loue at al tymes alike: it is not the manner of graces working, thou haſt no ſkill in graces affaires.
            
            
               Sathan,
               There is ſome matter I warrant thee againſt thee, that God heares not thy prayer when thou calleſt vppon him, as thou confeſſeſt.
            
            
               Soule.
               I know thou markeſt my confeſſion, but the more I confeſſe againſte my ſelfe, the more I magnifie Gods mercy.
            
            
               Sathan,
               But tell mee, why God will not heare the prayer?
            
            
               Soule.
               Sathan God hears my prayer: but his delight is to heare the prayers of his Children often, therefore he doth delay.
            
            
               Sathan.
               God careth not for ſuch a wretch as thou art.
            
            
               Soule.
               
                  The more wretch I am in thy ſighte, and alſo in mine owne, the more amiable I am to him; and ſo auoyd ſathan, and ſpeake no more.
            
            
               A ſhort death-bed Dialogue.
               
                  Sathan,
                  DEath is come, and I muſt haue thee
               
               
                  Soule.
                  Death is welcome, but thou ſhalt goe without mee: heere are others to carry me, Chriſt my redeemer hath ſent his Angels for me.
               
               
                  Sathan.
                  Death will carrie thee to Hell.
               
               
                  Soule.
                  No: he muſt carry me no whither, but end me: the Angells muſt carrie mee to mine owne place. I haue euidence to ſhewe, which I will not vouchſafe to ſhewe thee: therefore auoyde. Lord Ieſus that haſt bought me, take me; I doe heere ſurrender my ſelfe to thee, Amen. Speake not a worde more but let thine eies be cloſed vp in ſilence.
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            Morning prayer.
            
               O Lord, That bleſſeſt thy ſeruice to thy ſeruaunts: Bleſſe vs in this part of thy ſeruice, prayer and thankſgiuing to thee: and Becauſe none are to meddle with anie part of thy ſeruice but thy called ſeruants, good Lord beſtow that grace vpon vs that we feele more and more our effectuall Calling, before wee preſume to come neer thee &amp; becaus each duty is to be done, by, and in the name of thy ſonne: we confeſſe that till our ingraftment into him by grace &amp; the apprehēſion of faith through thy ſpirit our effectuall calling doth not appeare, ſo that if we wāt faith, thy ſpirit we muſt not intrude our ſelues into thy ſight, but our attendāce is vpon the diuell, and thou wilte not part ſeruice with him.
            O Lord in the weaknes of faith we preſume, accept of vs, be in the middeſt of vs thou haſt ſtrongly vs called to obedience,

in this and all other things by worde and worke it is a dept therefore to be rendered heare of vs: Lord receiue it; we confeſſe our ſinns haue driuen vs far awaie, they are many and great, thy Curſe is the due of them: to our ſhame we confeſſe, we haue beene warned, and yet ſince warning, againſt our knowledge and conſcience, of forgetfullnes weaknes, and ſometime of frowardneſſe, we haue of our naturall inclination as lightly eſteeming thee, &amp; thy law tranſgreſſed &amp; offēded Nowe Lord, albeit wee can deſtroy our ſelues, yet we Cannot ſaue our ſelues; wee intreat thy Ritch mercy for our pardon, &amp; our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt for our ful ſatiſfactiō. Lord in that mercy pardon vs, &amp; in Ieſus chriſt be cōtented &amp; wel ple-wt vs: &amp; for former conceiued diſpleſurs forget thē, &amp; in the multitude of thy cō
               paſſions remoue thē, with ſin of al kinds ye cauſe of them; and ſo iuſtice being anſwered, thy wrath appeaſed, &amp; hel gates ſhut, &amp; a conqueſt aſſured; Let vs walke in ye cōfort of this peace, yea in holines &amp; aſſurāce of it: &amp; as we haue loſt all by yt life &amp; rule of ſin, ſo we pray yt let vs find our ſelues reſtored by the death and

captiuity of ſinne, let our vnderſtanding be lightned: let our memory be ſound; let our wills be holy: let our affection be honeſt, let our conſcience be tender and ready to euery good exhortation: let our apetites be ſober: let vs be free from bondage to prophanenes, in al our faculties, in all our liues, at all times, and in all places: let vs perſeuer, ſtriue and ouercome. Let vs be armed and watch, let vs heare, read, and pray; let vs meditate and ſtudy in thy loue: let all ſad motions and paſſions be examined, and if ill ſuppreſſed: let vs reſigne al our bodies and ſoules holineſſe vnto thy ſeruice. Let vs not want that we ought to haue: let vs not haue yt we ought to wāt, or that is good to be wanting. Lord let vs ſhew mortification in al our behauiour. Let ye life of righteouſnes appeare in all our actions, inward and outward, ſecret &amp; open. Let vs Regard our callings, &amp; the duties belonging to the ſame. Let vs haue grace to finde out all the ſound and peculiar Euidence of thy kingdome: let vs determine to keepe thy word, let vs vowe it, whatſoeuer ſtandeth in the waie: O

Lord be our keeper in our waies, this day and for euer: looke from heauen vpon thy whole Church, &amp; euery member of it militant, that hath neede of the prayers of thy ſaintes, eſpecially this part of it where we liue: and aboue euery particular member, Lorde let it pleaſe thee to regard our Soueraigne Lord the Kings Maieſty, wt his Queen, the noble Prince of Wales their Son, with the reſidue of that Royall iſſue: haue an eie deare Father to his Maieſties honorable priuy Councell, to councell them, and to the truſty nobility to ſanctifie them: and to all ſubordinate maieſtrates of City and Cuntry, to be the God of gods among them, and to ſtir them vp to ſtand in the gap, and to take thy part againſt the Diuell and his; and to animate them &amp; bleſſe them hereunto, and to guide them. Let thy word haue a free paſſage: let all lets be remooued, let the piller and cloude of protection further it night and day·Act. 16. Let all that are able and willing to help in Macedonia be called in, and countenā
               ced: let knowledge heale painfulnes, &amp; a godly life appear in all thy miniſters.

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
Let hearing and obedience meet in all thy people, becaus few preferred by thee doe prefer thee before their chiefe ioyes O Lord turn their harts as they belōg to thee, let generall conſideration hee had of the beneāts thou beſtoweſt, to mooue the hearts of al high and low, to put to hand to help thee againſt Anti-chriſte and the diuell: and let the corrections of thy hande, eſpecially that heauy rod and ſtroke of the peſtilence, continued and greatly ſpread through the kingdome this foure yeares, be ſtayed; let there be an humiliation proportionable, generall &amp; earneſt, true &amp; vnfained, &amp; without delay; Leaſt thy angell, haue his commiſſion inlarged, not onely to kill hundreds, but thouſands; as not long ſince, not onely thouſands, but millions: O Lorde ſtop yet the mouth of our cheefe crying ſins: in the howſe of Dauid, in the houſe of Nathā, in the houſe of Leuie, in all the howſes of Iudah, let a ſearch bee made good Lord for Achan &amp; for Ionas: that our ſtate may be calme, and the Epha ſent into Shinnar. Lord help thy church in all places, and in all things: let Babilon

fall, let the Iewes come on, let all them be as Meroz that haue ill will, and no good will to Sion, Amen.
         
         
            Euening Prayer.
            
               O Rich God, infinite in all goodneſſe; we preſume again to reſort to that ouerflowing fountain: Lord turn vs not awaie, though we be fools, like thy ſeruant Gedeons Armie, that we cannot tell the fitteſt way to take in the ſweetnes of thy goodnes; yet accepte of our weaknes, becauſe that good minde and harte we haue, thou art the author of it: thou haſt called and beckned vs to thee, now we are come to know thy good pleſure, &amp; to beg from thy liberality what ſhall pleaſe thee: thy do
                  •
               e of mercy is euer open to thy ſaintes, and thou fitteſt as Abraham at the dore, to entertaine poore, weary, and heauy loaden ones: and we know thou haſteſt to meet vs, to do vs good, like a good God according to thy accuſtomed goodnes: we are therfore confidently comforted yt in

this, that the leaſt ſoule-whiſpering of an adopted child, is as odours to thee, though it be ſilly and as the chattering of Ezechiah. O Lord we willingly confeſſe to thy praiſe, that thou haſt hearde our praiers offered to thee in the morning, we haue through thy mercy fared well this day in ſoule and body, not withſtanding the ſpight of Satan, the malice of our ſinne, the peſtilent enmity of corrupt nature, and the enuy of the world, and the deceits of others among whom we dwell: O prouident &amp; kind Lord and Father, we haue brought thee for it, the beſt Lamb of our flock, euen all hearty praiſe and thanks, &amp; purpoſe of better ſeruice that we can, and this dipped and drenſhed in heartmelting, and in Ieſus Chriſts merit and reconcilement: we beſeeche thee, teſtifie thy acceptance by addition of mercy in detraction and multiplication of it: and let vs obteine the taſt &amp; feeling of this, this nighte following, and all our life time repent thee not: go forward with vs for Chriſts ſake, regard not the outſtartings of ſoule or body againſt thy mind, in thy preſence: but let thy righte

hand of infinite compaſſion caſt them (as a milſtone) into the deepes of our Chriſts ſatiſfaction, and attonemente, and let our euidence be alwais kept by grace from dimneſſe or blurres of our weaknes, that our ſaluations enemies may not ſo much as dare to diſpute with vs, about our pardon and election. O Lord let thy ſpirit watch within vs: let thy miniſtring ſpirits attend without and about vs, being poore heyrs of ſaluation. What Sathan hath purpoſed. confound it, what ſin hath deſerued, preuent it: what thy mercifull maieſty ſees to be good, let vs haue it for Chriſtes ſake: let our ſleepe be quiet and not exceſſiue; let our health be continued, hold thy hand ouer vs, let no commiſſion bee granted againſt vs, let euery thing bee ſet in order, becauſe our date is vncertain, &amp; the place of our ende vnknown, if our leaſe of life laſt till morning: in that ſhall appeere to vs that thou wilt beſtow another day of grace vppon vs. O Lord wee promiſe before thy Maieſty, that wee will by thy grace ſtriue to the vttermoſt period of our ſtrength to ſerue thee Lord; remember vs, let vs ſee

a beſome, made &amp; put in a ſtrong hand for the wicked and wickednes, and let vs ſee ſtill the vine planted by thy own hand to flouriſh, and all the walls of it to ſtand, and not to fall, nor the leaſte breache to be made: let it not be ſaid that the Fore ſhall with going vpon it curſh it. O Lord to this end preſerue our captain the Kings maieſty, and all about him for euer; and keep his heart in thy hand, &amp; the hearts of all Chriſtian Kings, gouernors &amp; people, that a ioyfull ſucces may be ſeen to thy true religion &amp; church among vs, &amp; in all the world: and ſo with humble thanks we ceaſe. To thee be all honor and glory for euermore. Amen. Amen.
            
               A thanksgiuing for our late deliuerance.
               
                  O Lord, it is good to giue praiſes vnto thy name, prayſe is comly, but thou art ſo infinite in deſeets, that our praiſes are all ſhort; yet being true, and new according to freſh and admirable benefits receiued, they are as incenſe to thee: but when praiſes are not rendered in the due place, it prouoketh thee to fury, yea to ſweare, that we ſhal periſh for

all them hereafter: and in wrath thou wilt ſay, that which periſheth let it periſh: I will neuer put to hand to helpe: O Lord iuſtly mayſt thou ſay ſo to vs, for we haue him wōderfuly preſerued by thee, as Iſrael in Pihahiroth, as Dauid in the Prophets ſchoole, as Daniell in the Lions denne, wee haue ſeene the axe lie at the roote of our greateſt Cedars, as thou woldeſt haue them no couering for vs any longer: but let the ſunne and ſtars to pearce with vs as by withering Ionas Gourd: O Lord often haſt thou bewrayd the malice of the popiſh crue, &amp; the venō of all that brood, that for the time we haue been ſwallowed vp with thy goodnes, &amp; in ye ſoul rauiſhment we haue promiſed, but after not paying our vows for ſinne, thou haſt bin wors combred wt vs then before: good Lord vpon our confeſſion grant vs remiſſiō, &amp; mercifull acceptation; if thou ſtudeſt true thankfulnes but in ten or a few. Lord receiue it, and regard not the reſt: let the righteous deliuer the reſt, &amp; ſo take all glory that can be giuen thee from al the brāds that haue bin pulled out of ye fire, &amp; let al addreſſe thēſelues to bring preſents to thee that art to be feares, &amp;

ſo let our king be kept with his &amp; thine.
            
            
               A praier comprehending the matter of the laſt iudgement.
               
                  O Bleſſed Chriſt Ieſus, haſten to the laſt worke of thy mediation, to iudgement, yea the laſt iudgement: and becauſe that cannot bee till thou haſte ſealed all thy elect, with the ſeale of Gods iron; O Lord haſten that worke: and to this end powr thy ſpirit plentifully vpon miniſters and people, worke euery good worke that may further the building of thy Church, let all Chriſtian Kings caſt their crownes before the Lamb, and bee willing to lick the duſt of thy ſaints ſeet: let them be deuoured with a zeale of thy glory, let thy word ſpreade into more countries and nations; let Babilon fall, let it be a cage of vncleane birds, let not the noyſe of a mil be heard any more in her. Let ye Iewes be graffed in again, as thou haſt promiſed, euen all thy elect among them, let prayers be made for them: Lord heare thou in heauen, the place of thy habitation, and let all thyne haue grace to thinke of the laſt trumpet, ſounded to

wake the dead: Let vs remēber the chāge of heauen &amp; earth, &amp; that fire ſhall conſume them. Let vs Reſolue, here is no place of any lōg abode: Lord let vs not defer &amp; put of our repentance; for thou wilt come &amp; wilte not carry: and as a theef wilt thou ſteal vpon the reprobates, when they are either 
                     •
                  leeping or beating their fellows. O Lord, let it pleaſe thee that we may take heede of the company and conuerſation of the vngodly, or of any neuer ſo neerely vnited vnto vs in the fleſh: Becaus lord thou knoweſt, that then two ſhal be in a bed, one taken and another refuſed, and that thou haſt ſaide, that it ſhall be then a bleſſed ſtate to be found dooing our duties: bleſſed chriſt that ſhalt come in glory, to iudge both quick &amp; dead, at thy appearance and in thy comming: thy ſeat is ſaid to be great, to containe ſuch a perſonage of Maieſty; no greatnes ſhall appeare to be comparable to thine: and as thou art greate, ſo thy throne is white; for euery one ſhall haue iuſtice of thee. O Lord let vs take mercy while the date of it laſteth: for then the da
                     •
                  e of it will be out, &amp; Iuſtice without partiality muſt take place: O Lord arme vs in the time of mercy, that wee may ſtand in ye day of Iuſtice, when the wicked yt now 
                     •
                  augh, ſhal too late weep: whē the heauen &amp;

earth in their preſent but ſhall run away, &amp; neuer be foūd again in ye faſhiō: O good lord what wretches are wee then to ſtand vpon merit, when as the ſun is not clear in thy ſight, eſpecially conſidering no Euaſion can be made from thy preſence without chāge, which ſhall be to late: &amp; our merciful chriſt, our greatnes now if we be foūd ill, will not profit vs, but hurt vs &amp; increaſe our iudgment: neither our ſmalnes will excuſe vs, or accuſe vs to harme vs; but we muſt all, of al ſorts, and degrees and ſexes ſtand &amp; hould vp hand at thy hat: O ſweet Ieſus let it pleaſe thee, that we may vſe our greatnes to thy glory, to good and not to harme; our ſmalnes with comfort, and contentednes. O lord though we may couer our ſins before men, and finde a friend in court: yet we pray thee good Ieſus, let vs remember yt we muſt anſwere in thy courte, when it ſhall be too late to intreat. O Lord awake vs and make vs mindfull of our account before that wee be called for, and ſeeing moſt greate god al ſeſecrets muſt then be known or pronounced pardoned, O good lord let vs haue grace frō thee to confes our ſecret ſins, &amp; to take heed of ſuch: for thou keepeſt a depte book. Lord let vs find ſpeedily thy depe book Raſed, thy word anſwered, &amp; the book of life to haue our

names; that when they ſhal be opened in the great day of thy iudgement, they may bee no terror to vs. Good Chriſt let vs prepare our witneſſes, and make ready our anſwere without delay, for we know not what wil be to morrow. O lord we confes, we cā haue no leſſe then 4 ſufficient witneſſes, thy word, thy ſpirit, our conſcience, and the conſcience of our neighbours iointlie. Let vs be ſure of theſe, to ſtop the mouth of all helliſh Enimity, and to ſeale vp to vs pardon and recō
                  ciliation in Ieſus Chriſt: Let vs iudge our ſelues, that our Iudgement may quickly be paſſed ouer; that after we may iudge, &amp; not be iudged. O lord we know before, that we muſt heare iuſtice mercileſly, if we repēt not: if we turne not, we muſt be turned out, if we wil not come in time, we muſt fearfully go wt out time, O Lord let vs bethink vs of our eſtate, &amp; be ſure of our peace with thee; els our doting will quickly appeare; for we are euery moment within the compas of death, &amp; the priſon of hell. O Lord, happy are toades before Reprobates, for death fully ends thē: but death doth keepe the wicked, to reſtore them and bring them out againe to iudgemente, O Lord let vs ſee thee angrie, let vs ſee thee pleaſed; and ſo let not thy wrath, death, nor

the laſt iudgemēt terrifie vs. Let thy church our king and ſtate be bleſsed: Let Sions ilwillers be either conuerted, or confoūded: ſend out in thy bottomles mercies a reuocation of the commiſſion gone out againſt the people of this nation: By vertue whereof many die, &amp; many poor widdows, &amp; poore orphans cry: lord work what thou wilt, &amp; take what thou wol
                     •
                  eſt, &amp; be pacified. Lord al thy afflicted ſeruants make mone to thee, Lord hear in heauen, and ſend comfort to the earth and it ſhal bring vp hearty praiſe to thee by Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.
            
         
         
            A ſhort prayer of purpoſe againſt Sathans aſſaults.
            
               MY louing and moſt pitifull father, who in Ieſus Chriſt &amp; for his ſake haſt called me to thee, &amp; by grace I am come to thee, Now bleſſed father I finde ſtronger enmity then before, and finde ſuch a combination betweene Sathan and my nature, with the worlde againſt me, that my weaknes is ready to yeelde: good father ſeing that nowe this rage of aſſault ſeems to bee for thy ſake: I thy poore child doe beſeech thee to manage thy owne cauſe, and make thy part good againſt theſe enemies

of thine in all theire forcible aſſaults, &amp; let them all know, they haue to deal with thee, &amp; ſo defend thy glory and this poore ſoule of myne that commeth trembling to creep vnder thy wings, and deſireth to caſt liuely thy ſweet fauour, and neuer to be drawne from thee: ſhe we thy ſelfe for Chriſts ſake, and let me not be blinded in iudgement, nor ſo weak in faith, that I ſhould be deluded, thy Maieſty diſhonored, the enemy incoraged, or thy little ones diſmaied; free me therefore good father from all theſe daungerous perplexities, that in patience, faith, and true Godlines I may runne my race, and fighte a good fight &amp; conquer, that I loſe not my Crowne for Ieſus Chriſts ſake. Amen.
         
         
            A ſhort prayer at hand vpon all occaſions.
            
               O Chriſte, I beleeue, helpe my vnbeleefe: I am tolde from thee, that Sathan is conquered, ſinne is killed, hell is ſhut; thys wrath is pacified, curſe and law are fully anſwered, and no perill can poſſibly befal me: Good Chriſt let me not onely ſee it, but liuely and ioyfully apprehend it, and ſo ſtabliſh me and mortiſſe

me into thy ſelf vnchangeably, againſt winde and ſtorme, and all that the Dragon can caſt out of his mouth: and ſo I the leaſt of thine, with many thy deare children, will praiſe thee for euer. Amen.
         
         
            A prayer for all ſorts.
            
               O Lord heare vs, &amp; looke mercifully vpon vs, thou haſt promiſed it, &amp; commaunded vs to aſk it: performe thy promiſe, and helpe vs in aſking for thy ſons ſake: Thou haſt been gratious, and thy mercy endures, we haue been vngracious, &amp; our ſinnes continue, let thy wrath prouoked be pacified, let thy iuſtice ſtirred be ſtayed, and ſatiſfied, in Ieſus Chriſte our mediatour: Pitty vs, and pardon vs: we beleeue, helpe our vnbeleefe: reſolue vs, and peſwade vs, remoue all dangerous doubts from vs, as olde Adam liued and ruled when thou wert prouoked, ſo let it die and be ſubiecte, nowe thou art pacified: let vs be lightned by thy word, let vs be affected wt it, let vs haue it in high eſtimation, and let vs follow it in our conuerſation, let it be our ſword againſt the deuils temptation, let vs conquer in

Chriſt Ieſu, let a god conſcience Iudge vs, Let a continuall watch keepe vs, Let the power of thy ſpirit arme vs: Let our weaknes neuer grow to wilfulneſſe, let thy ſpirit neuer forſake vs, leaue vs not ouerlong, though thou tri'ſt vs, ſet ſecurity aſide, ſhake of our drowſineſſe, quicken our deadneſſe, ſoften our hardneſſe, quenche all the fiery dartes of Satan in vs, let vs looke back to our former ſtate, and to our preſent ſtate: let our heart grieue that it can bee no more grieued, let our ſouls ioy be in Chriſt thy ſon let vs glad our ſelues in the holy ghoſt. let vs be giuen to reading, hearing and meditation, let vs reſorte to the company of thy ſaints, let vs loath the companie of the wicked, let vs be lowly conceited in our ſelues, let vs think reuerendly of al thy children, let vs reſt in thee, our good father-watch vs by night, guide vs by day, bleſſe vs in both wt al ours, publikly and priuately: protect thy goſpell and church, preuent thy foes at home and abroad for Ieſus ſake: amen.
            Finis.
         
      
   

