
   
      
         
            The honorable historie of Frier Bacon, and Frier Bongay As it was lately plaid by the Prince Palatine his Seruants. Made by Robert Greene, Master of Arts.
            Friar Bacon and Friar Bungay
            Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
         
         
            
               1630
            
         
         Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02128
            STC 12268
            ESTC S103422
            99839176
            99839176
            3577
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02128)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3577)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1380:16)
         
         
            
               
                  The honorable historie of Frier Bacon, and Frier Bongay As it was lately plaid by the Prince Palatine his Seruants. Made by Robert Greene, Master of Arts.
                  Friar Bacon and Friar Bungay
                  Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
               
               [64] p.   
               
                  Printed by Elizabeth Allde dwelling neere Christ-Church,
                  London :
                  1630.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-H⁴.
                  With a title-page woodcut.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  Running title reads: The honorable historie of Fryer Bacon.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2007-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-09
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2008-09
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
HONORABLE
HISTORIE OF
FRIER BACON, AND
FRIER BONGAY.
            
            As it was lately plaid by the Prince Palatine his Seruants.
            Made by Robert Greene, Maſter of Arts.
            
            LONDON,
Printed by ELIZABETH ALLDE dwelling
neere Chriſt-Church. 1630.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE
HONORABLE HISTORY
OF FRYER BACON.
            Enter Edward the firſt, male contented with Lacy Earle of Lincolne,
Iohn Warren Earle of Suſſex, and Ermsby Gentleman:
Raph Simnell the Kings foole.
            
               Lacie.
               VVHY lookes my Lord like to a troubled skie,
               When heauens bright ſhine, is ſhadowed with a fog:
               Alate we ran the Deere and through the Iawnds
               Stript with our Nagges the lofty frolicke Bucks,
               That ſcudded fore the teiſers like the wind,
               Nere was the Deere of merry Freſingfield,
               
               So luſtily pull'd downe by iolly mates,
               Nor ſharde the Farmers ſuch fat venizon,
               So frankly dealt this hundred yeeres before:
               Nor haue I ſeene my Lord more frolicke in the chace,
               And now chang'd to a melancholy dumpe.
            
            
               Warren.
               After the Prince got to the Keepers lodge
               And had bin incond in the houſe a while:
               Toſſing of Ale and milke in countrie cannes,
               Whether it was the Countries ſweet content,
               Or elſe the bonny Damſell fil'd vs drinke
               That ſeem'd ſo ſtately in her ſtammell red:
               Or that a qualme did croſſe his ſtomacke then,
               But ſtraight he fell into his paſſions.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Sirra Raphe, what ſay you to your maſter,
               Shall he thus all amort liue malecontent?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Heareſt thou Ned? nay looke if he will ſpeake to me.
            
            
               
               Edward.
               What ſaiſt thou to me, Foole?
            
            
               Raphe.
               I pree thee tell me Ned, art thou in loue with the
Keepers daughter?
            
            
               Edward.
               How if I be, what then?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Why then ſirra, Ile teach thee how to deceiue Loue.
            
            
               Edward.
               How Raphe.
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               Marry ſirra Ned, thou ſhalt put on my cap, and my
coat, and my dagger, and I will put on thy cloaths, and thy
ſword, and ſo thou ſhalt be my foole.
            
            
               Edward.
               And what of this?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Why ſo thou ſhalt beguile Loue, for Loue is ſuch a
proud ſcab, that he will neuer meddle with fooles nor children.
Is not Raphes counſell good, Ned.
               
            
            
               Edward.
               Tell me Ned Lacie, didſt thou marke the mayd,
               How liuely in her country weedes ſhe look't?
               A bonier wench all Suffolke cannot yeeld,
               All Suffolke, nay all England holds none ſuch.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Sirra, Will Ermsby, Ned is deceiued.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Why Raphe?
               
            
            
               Rarhe.
               He ſayes all England hath no ſuch, and I ſay, and
Ile ſtand to it, there is one better in Warwickeſhire.
            
            
               Warren.
               How proueſt thou that Raphe?
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               Why is the Abbot a learned man, and hath he read
many bookes, and thinkeſt thou he hath not more learning then
thou to chooſe a bonny wench, yes warrant I thee by his whole
Grammar.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               A good reaſon Raphe.
               
            
            
               Edward.
               I tell thee Lacie, that her ſparkling eyes
               Doe lighten forth ſweet Loues alluring fire:
               And in her treſſes ſhe doth fold the lookes
               Of ſuch a gaze vpon her golden haire,
               Her baſhfull white mixt with the mornings red,
               Luna doth boaſt vpon her louely cheekes,
               Her front is beauties table wherr ſhe paints
               The glories of her gorgious excellence:
               Her teeth are ſhelues of precious Margarites,
               Richly encloſed with ruddie curroll cleues.
               Tuſh Lacie, ſhe is beauties ouermatch,
               
                  
If thou ſuruaiſt her curious imagerie.
            
            
               Lacie.
               I grant (my Lord) the Damſell is as faire,
               As ſimple Suffolks homely townes can yeeld:
               But in the Court be qainter Dames then ſhe,
               Whoſe faces are enricht with honors taint,
               Whoſe beauties ſtand vpon the ſtage of fame,
               And vaunt their trophies in the Court of Loue.
            
            
               Edw.
               Ah Ned, but hadſt thou watcht her as my ſelfe,
               And ſeene the ſecret beauties of the maid,
               Their courtly coineſſe were but foolery.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Why how watcht you her my Lord?
            
            
               Edward.
               When as ſhe ſwept like Venus through the houſe,
               And in her ſhape faſt foulded vp my thoughts:
               Into the Milk chouſe went I with the maid,
               And there amongſt the cream-boles ſhe did ſhine,
               As Pallas, mongſt her Princely huſwiferie:
               She turnd her ſmocke ouer her lilly armes,
               And diued them into milke to run her cheeſe:
               But whiter then the milke her criſtall skin,
               Checked with lines of Azur made her bluſh,
               That Art or Nature durſt bring for compare,
               
                  Ermsby if thou hadſt ſeene as I did note it well,
               How beauty plaid the huſwife, how this girle
               Like Lucrece laid her fingers to the worke,
               Thou wouldſt with Tarquine hazard Rome and all
               To win the louely maid of Freſingfield.
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               Sirra Ned, wouldſt faine haue her?
            
            
               Edward.
               I Raphe.
               
            
            
               Raphe,
               Why Ned I haue laid the plot in my head, thou
ſhalt haue her already.
            
            
               Edward.
               Ile giue thee a new coat and learne me that.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Why ſirra Ned, weell ride to Oxford to Fryer Bacon, oh
hee is a braue ſcholler ſirra, they ſay he is a braue Nigromancer,
that he can make women of diuells, and he can iuggle cats into
Coſtermongers.
            
            
               Edward.
               And how then Raphe?
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               Mary ſirra, thou ſhalt goe to him, and becauſe thy father
Harry ſhall not miſſe thee, he ſhall turne me to thee; and

Ile to the Court, and Ile Prince it out, and he ſhall make thee either
a ſilken purſe, full of gold, or elſe a fine wrought ſmocke.
            
            
               Edward.
               But how ſhall I haue the mayd?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Marry ſirra, if thou be'ſt a ſilken purſe full of gold,
then on Sundayes ſhe'le hang thee by her ſide, and you muſt not
ſay a word. Now ſir when ſhe comes into a great preſſe of people,
for feare of the Cut-purſe on a ſuddē ſhe'l ſwap thee into her
plackerd, then ſirra being there, you may plead for your ſelfe.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Excellent policy.
            
            
               Edward.
               But how if I be a wrought ſmocke?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Then ſhe'le put thee into her cheſt and lay thee into
Lauender, and vpon ſome good day ſhe'le put thee on, and at
night when you goe to bed, then being turn'd from a ſmocke to
a man, you may make vp the match.
            
            
               Lacie.
               Wonderfully wiſely counſelled, Raphe.
               
            
            
               Edward.
               
                  Raphe ſhall haue a new Coate.
            
            
               Raphe.
               God thanke you when I haue it on my backe, Ned.
               
            
            
               Edward.
               
                  Lacie the foole hath laid a perfect plot,
               For why our Country Margret is ſo coy,
               And ſtands ſo much vpon her honeſt points,
               That marriage or no market with the mayd:
               
                  Ermsby, it muſt be nigromanticke ſpels,
               And charmes of Art that muſt inchaine her loue,
               Or elſe ſhall Edward neuer win the girle,
               Therefore my wags we'le horſe vs in the morne,
               And poaſt to Oxford to this iolly Fryer,
               
                  Bacon ſhall by his magicke doe this deed.
            
            
               Warren.
               Content my Lord, and thats a ſpeedy way
               To weane theſe head-ſtrong puppies from the teat.
            
            
               Edward.
               I am vnknowne, not taken for the Prince,
               They onely deeme vs frolicke Courtiers,
               That reuell thus among our Lieges game:
               Therefore I haue deuiſed a policy,
               
                  Lacie, thou knowſt next Friday is St. Iames,
               
               And then the Country flockes to Harlſton faire,
               Then will the Keepers daughter frolicke there,
               And ouer-ſhine the troupe of all the maides,
               That come to ſee, and to be ſeene that day.
               
                  
Haunt thee diſguis'd among the Countrie ſwaines,
               Faine th'art a Farmers ſonne, not farre from thence,
               Eſpie her loues, and who ſhe liketh beſt:
               Coat him, and court her to controle the clowne,
               Say that the Courtier tyred all in greene,
               That helpt her handſomly to run her cheeſe,
               And fild her fathers lodge with veniſon,
               Commends him, and ſends fairings to her ſelfe,
               Buy ſomething worthy of her parentage,
               Not worth her beauty, for Lacie, then the Faire
               Affords no Iewell ſitting for the mayd:
               And when thou talkeſt of me, note if ſhe bluſh,
               Oh then ſhe loues, but if her cheekes waxe pale,
               Diſdaine it is. Lacie, ſend how ſhe fares,
               And ſpare no time nor coſt to win her loues.
            
            
               Lacie.
               I will, my Lord, ſo execute this charge,
               As if that Lacie were in loue with her.
            
            
               Edward.
               Send letters ſpeedily to Oxford of the newes.
            
            
               Raphe.
               And ſirra Lacie, buy me a thouſand thouſand million
of fine bells.
            
            
               Lacie.
               What wilt thou doe with them, Raphe?
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               Mary euery time that Ned ſighs for the Keepers
daughter, Ile tye a bell about him, ſo within three or foure
dayes I will ſend word to his father Harry, that his ſonne and
my maſter Ned is become Loues Morris dance.
            
            
               Edward.
               Well, Lacie, looke with care vnto thy charge,
               And I will haſte to Oxford to the Fryer,
               That he by Art, and thou by ſecret gifts,
               Maiſt make me Lord of merry Freſingfield.
               
            
            
               Lacie.
               God ſend your Honour your hearts deſire.
            
            Exeunt.
            Enter Fryer Bacon, with Miles his poore ſcholer with bookes vnder his
arme, with them Burden, Maſon, Clement, three Doctors.
            
               Bacon.
               
                  Miles, where are you?
            
            
               Miles.
               Hic ſum doctiſſime &amp; reuerendiſſime Doctor.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Attuliſti nos libros meos de Necromantia.
            
            
               Miles.
               Ecce quam bonum &amp; quam incundum habitare libros in
vnum.
            
            
               
               Bacon.
               Now Maſters of our Academick State,
               That rule in Oxford Vice-roies in your place,
               Whoſe heads containe Maps of the liberall Arts,
               Spending your time in depth of learned skill,
               Why flocke you thus to Bacons ſecret Cell,
               A Fryer newly ſtalde in Brazennoſe,
               Say whats your minde, that I may make reply.
            
            
               Burden.
               
                  Bacon, we heare, that ſong we haue ſuſpect,
               That thou art read in Magicks myſtery,
               In Piromancy, to diuine by flames,
               To tell by Hadromaticke, ebbes and tides,
               By Aeromancy, to diſcouer doubts,
               To plaine out queſtions, as Apollo did.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Well Maſter Burden, what of all this?
            
            
               Miles.
               Mary ſir, he doth but fulfill by rehearſing of theſe
names, the Fable of the Fox &amp; the Grapes, that which is aboue
vs, pertaines nothing to vs.
            
            
               Burden.
               I tell thee Bacon, Oxford makes report,
               Nay England, and the Court of Henry ſayes,
               Thart making of a brazen head by Art,
               Which ſhall vnfold ſtrange doubts and Aphoriſmes,
               And read a Lecture in Philoſophy,
               And by the helpe of Deuils and ghaſtly fiends,
               Thou meanſt ere many yeeres or dayes be paſt,
               To compaſſe England with a wall of braſſe.
            
            
               Bacon.
               And what of this?
            
            
               Miles.
               What of this, Maſter? why he doth ſpeake myſtically,
for he knowes if your skill faile to make a brazen head, yet
Mother Waters ſtrong Ale will fit his turne to make him haue
a copper noſe.
            
            
               Clement.
               
                  Bacon, we come not greeuing at thy skill,
               But ioying that our Academy yeelds
               A man ſuppos'd the wonder of the world,
               For if thy cunning worke theſe miracles,
               
                  England and Europe ſhall admire thy fame,
               And Oxford ſhall in characters of braſſe,
               And ſtatues, ſuch as were built vp in Rome,
               
               Eternize Fryer Bacon for his Art.
            
            
               
               Maſon.
               Then gentle Fryer, tell vs thy intent.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Seeing you come as friends vnto the Fryer,
               Reſolue you Doctors, Bacon can by bookes,
               Make ſtorming Boreas thunder from his caue,
               And dimme faire Luna to a darke Eclipſe,
               The great Arch-ruler, potentate of hell,
               Trembles, when Bacon bids him, or his fiends,
               Bow to the force of his Pentageron.
               What Art can worke, the frolicke Fryer knowes,
               And therefore will I turne my Magicke bookes,
               And ſtraine out Nigromancie to the deepe,
               I haue contriu'd and fram'd a head of braſſe,
               (I made Belcephon hammer out the ſtuffe)
               And that by Art ſhall read Philoſophy,
               And I will ſtrengthen England by my skill,
               That if ten Caeſars liu'd and raign'd in Rome.
               With all the Legions Europe doth containe,
               They ſhould not touch a graſſe of Engliſh ground,
               The worke that Ninus reard at Babylon,
               The brazen walls fram'd by Semiramis,
               
               Carued out like to the portall of the Sunne,
               Shall not be ſuch as rings the Engliſh ſtrond:
               From Douer to the market place of Rye.
            
            
               Burden.
               Is this poſſible?
            
            
               Miles.
               Ile bring ye two or three witneſſes.
            
            
               Burden.
               What be thoſe?
            
            
               Miles.
               Marry ſir, three or foure as honeſt Deuils, and good
companions as any be in hell.
            
            
               Maſon.
               No doubt but Magicke may doe much in this,
               For he that reads but Mathemoticke rules,
               Shall finde concluſions, that auaile to worke
               Wonders that paſſe the common ſence of men.
            
            
               Burden.
               But Bacon roues a bow beyond his reach,
               And tels of more then Magicke can performe:
               Thinking to get a fame by fooleries,
               Haue I not paſt as farre in ſtate of ſchooles,
               
                  
And read of many ſecrets? yet to thinke.
               That heads of braſſe can vtter any voyce,
               Or more to tell of deepe Philoſophy,
               This is a Fable Aeſope had forgot.
            
            
               Bacon.
               
                  Burden, thou wrongſt me in detracting thus,
               
                  Bacon loues not to ſtuffe himſelfe with lyes:
               But tell me fore theſe Doctors if thou date,
               Of certaine queſtions I ſhall moue to thee.
            
            
               Burden.
               I will, aske what thou can.
            
            
               Miles.
               Mary ſir, hee'le ſtraight bee on your pick packe to
know whether the feminine or the maſculine gender be moſt
worthy.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Were you not yeſterday Maſter Burden at Henly vpon
Themes?
            
            
               Burden.
               I was, what then?
            
            
               Bacon
               What booke ſtudyed you thereon all night?
            
            
               Burden.
               I, none at all, I read not there a line.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Then Doctors, Fryer Bacons Art knowes nought.
            
            
               Clement.
               What ſay you to this, Maſter Burden, doth hee not
touch you?
            
            
               Burden.
               I paſſe not of his friuolous ſpeeches.
            
            
               Miles.
               Nay Maſter Burden, my maſter ere hee hath done
with you, will turne you from a Doctor to a dunce, and ſhake
you ſo ſmall, that he will leaue you no more learning in you then
is in Balams Aſſe.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Maſters, for that learned Burdens skill is deepe,
               And ſore he doubts of Bacons Cabaliſme:
               Ile ſhew you why he haunts to Henly oft,
               Not Doctors for to taſte the fragrant aire:
               But there to ſpend the night in Al
                     •
                  umy,
               To multiply with ſecret ſpels of Art.
               Thus priuat ſteales he learning from vs all,
               To proue my ſaying true, Ile ſhew you ſtraight,
               The booke he keepes at Henly for himſelfe.
            
            
               Miles.
               Nay, now my maſter goes to coniuration, take heede.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Maſters, ſtand ſtill, feare not, Ile ſhewe you but his
booke.
               
                  
Here hee coniures.
               
                  Per omnes deos infernales Belcephon.
               
            
            Enter a woman with a ſhoulder of mutton on a ſpit, and a Deuid.
            
               Miles.
               Oh maſter ceaſe your coniuration, or you ſpoile all,
for her's a ſhe deuill come with a ſhoulder of mutton on a ſpit,
you haue marde the deuils ſupper, but no doubt he thinkes our
Colledge fare is ſlender, and ſo hath ſent you his cooke with a
ſhoulder of mutton to make it exceed.
            
            
               Hoſteſſe.
               Oh where am I, or whats become of me?
            
            
               Bacon.
               What art thou?
            
            
               Hoſteſſe.
               Hoſteſſe at Henly, miſtreſſe of the Bell.
            
            
               Bacon.
               How cameſt thou here?
            
            
               Hoſteſſe.
               As I was in the kitchen mongſt the maids,
               Spitting the meate againſt ſupper for my gueſſe:
               A motion moued me to looke forth of dore,
               No ſooner had I pryed into the yard.
               But ſtraight a whirlewind hoiſted me from thence,
               And mounted me aloft vnto the cloudes:
               As in a trance I thought nor feared nought,
               Nor know I where or whither I was tane:
               Nor where I am, nor what theſe perſons be.
            
            
               Bacon.
               No, know you not maſter Burden?
               
            
            
               Hoſteſſe.
               Oh yes good ſir, he is my daily gueſt.
               What, maſter Burden, 'twas but yeſternight,
               That you and I at Henly plaid at cardes.
            
            
               Burden.
               I know not what we did, a poxe of all coniuring
Fryers.
            
            
               Clement.
               Now iolly Fryer tell vs, is this the booke
that Burden is ſo carefull to looke on?
            
            
               Bacon.
               It is, but Burden, tell me now,
               Thinkeſt thou that Bacons Nicromanticke skill
               Cannot performe his head and wall of braſſe,
               When he can fetch thine hoſteſſe in ſuch poſte?
            
            
               
               Miles.
               Ile warrant you, Maſter, if Maſter Burden could coniure
as well as you, he would haue his booke euery night from
Henly to ſtudy on at Oxford.
               
            
            
               Maſon.
               
                  Burden, what are you mated by this frolicke Fryer?
               Looke how he droops, his guilty conſcience
               Driues him to baſh and makes his hoſteſſe bluſh.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Well Miſtris for I will not haue you miſt,
               You ſhall to Henly to cheere vp your gueſts
               Fore ſupper ginne. Burden, bid her adew,
               Say farewell to your hoſteſſe fore ſhe goes,
               Sirra away, and ſet her ſafe at home.
            
            
               Hoſteſſe.
               Maſter Burden, when ſhall we ſee you at Henly?
               
            
            Exeunt Hoſteſſe and the Deuill.
            
               Burden.
               The Deuill take thee and Henly too.
            
            
               Miles.
               Maſter, ſhall I make a good motion?
            
            
               Bacon.
               Whats that?
            
            
               Miles.
               Mary ſir, now that my hoſteſſe is gone to prouide
ſupper, coniure another ſpirit, and ſend Doctor Burden flying
after.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Thus Rulers of our Academicke State,
               You haue ſeene the Fryer frame his Art by proofe:
               And as the Colledge called Brazen-noſe,
               Is vnder him, and the Maſter there:
               So ſurely ſhall this head of braſſe be fram'd,
               And yeeld forth ſtrange and vncoth Aphoriſmes:
               And Hell and Heccate ſhall faile the Fryer,
               But I will circle England round with braſſe.
            
            
               Miles.
               So be it, &amp; nunc &amp; ſemper, Amen.
            
            Exeunt omnes.
            Enter Margaret the faire mayd of Freſingfield, with Thomas and
Ione, and other clownes: Lacie diſguiſed in Country apparell.
            
               Thomas.
               By my troth, Margret, here's a wether is able to
make a man call his father whorſon, if this wether hold, we ſhall

haue hay good chape, and butter and cheeſe at Harlſton will
beare no price.
            
            
               Margret.
               
                  Thomas, maids when they come to ſee the faire
               Count not to make a cope for dearth of hay,
               When we haue turn'd our butter to the ſalt,
               And ſet our cheeſe vpon the rackes.
               Then let our fathers priſe it as they pleaſe,
               We Countrie ſluts of merry Freſingfield,
               Come to buy needleſſe noughts to make vs fine,
               And looke that young-men ſhould be francke this day,
               And court vs with ſuch fairings as they can.
               
                  Phoebus is blithe and, frolicke, lookes from heauen,
               As when he courted louely Semele:
               
               Swearing the Pedlers ſhall haue empty packs,
               If that faire weather may make chapmen buy.
            
            
               Lacie.
               But louely Peggy Semele is dead,
               And therefore Phoebus from his Palace pries,
               And ſeeing ſuch a ſweet and ſeemely ſaint,
               Shewes all his glory for to court your ſelfe.
            
            
               Margret.
               This is a fairing gentle ſir indeed,
               To ſooth me vp with ſuch ſmooth flatterie,
               But learne of me, your ſcoffe's to broad before:
               Well Ione, our beauties muſt abide their ieſts,
               We ſerue the turne in iolly Freſingfield.
            
            
               Ione.
               
                  Margret, a Farmers daughter for a Farmers ſonne,
               I warrant you the meaneſt of vs both,
               Shall haue a mate to leade vs from the Church:
               But Thomas, whats the newes? what in a dumpe?
               Giue me your hand, we are neere a Pedlers ſhop,
               Out with your purſe, we muſt haue fairings now.
            
            
               Thomas.
               Faith Ione and ſhall, Ile beſtow a fairing on you, and
then we will to the Tauern, and ſnap off a pint of wine or two.
            
            All this while Lacie whiſpers Margret in the eare.
            
               Margret.
               Whence are you ſir, of Suffolke? for your tearmes
are finer then the common ſort of men.
            
            
               
               Lacy.
               Faith louely girle, I am of Beckles by,
               Your neighbour not aboue ſix miles from hence,
               A Famers ſonne that neuer was ſo quaint,
               But that he could doe courteſie to ſuch Dames:
               But truſt me Margret I am ſent in charge,
               From him that reueld in your fathers houſe,
               And fild his Lodge with cheere and veniſon,
               Tyred in greene, he ſent you this rich purſe:
               His token that he helpt you run your cheeſe,
               And in the milkehouſe chatted with your ſelfe.
            
            
               Margret.
               To me? you forget your ſelfe.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Women are often weake in memory.
            
            
               Margret.
               Oh pardon ſir, I call to minde the man,
               Twere little manners to refuſe his gift,
               And yet I hope he ſends it not for loue:
               For we haue little leiſure to debate of that.
            
            
               Ione.
               What, Margret, bluſh not, maides muſt haue their
loues.
            
            
               Thomas.
               Nay by the maſſe ſhe lookes pale as if ſhe were
angrie.
            
            
               Richard.
               Sirra are you of Beckles? I pray how doth goodman
Cob? my father bought a horſe of him, Ile tell you Margret, a
were good to be a Gentlemans iade, for of all things the foule
hilding could not abide a dung-cart.
            
            
               Margret.
               How different is this Farmer from the reſt,
               That carſt as yet hath pleas'd my wandring ſight
               His words are witty, quickened with a ſmile,
               His courteſie gentle, ſmelling of the Court,
               Facill and debonaire in all his deeds,
               Proportion'd as was Paris, when in gray,
               He courted Aenon in the vale by Troy.
               
               Great Lords haue come and pleaded for my loue,
               Who but the Keepers Laſſe of Freſingfield?
               
               And yet me thinkes this Farmers ioylly ſonne,
               Paſſeth the proudeſt that hath pleas'd mine eye.
               But Peg diſcloſe not that thou art in loue,
               
                  
And ſhew as yet no ſigne of loue to him,
               Although thou well wouldſt wiſh him for thy loue:
               Keepe that to thee till time doth ſerue thy turne,
               To ſhew the griefe wherein they heart doth burne.
               Come Ione and Thomas, ſhall we to the Faire,
               You Beckles man will not forſake vs now.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Not whilſt I may haue ſuch quaint girles as you.
            
            
               Margret.
               Well if you chance to come by Freſingfield,
               Make but a ſtept into the Keepers Lodge,
               And ſuch poore fare as Woodmen can affoord,
               Butter and cheeſe, creame, and fat venizon,
               You ſhall haue ſtore, and welcome therewithall.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Gramarcies Peggie, looke for me ere long.
            
            Exeunt omnes.
            Enter Henry the third, the Emperour, the King of Caſtile, Elinor his
daughter, Iaques Vandermaſt a Germane.
            
               Henry.
               Great men of Europe, Monarkes of the Weſt,
               Ring'd with the walls of old Oceanus,
               
               Whoſe lofty ſurges like the battlements,
               That compaſt high built Babell in with Towres,
               Welcome my Lords, welcome braue weſterne Kings,
               To Englands ſhore, whoſe promontory cleeues,
               Shewes Albion is another little world,
               Welcome ſayes Engliſh Henry to you all,
               Chiefly vnto the louely Eleonor,
               
               Who darde for Edwards ſake cut through the ſeas,
               And venture as Agenors Damſell through the deepe,
               To get the loue of Henries wanton ſon.
            
            
               Caſtile.
               
                  Englands rich Monarke braue Plantagenet,
               
               The Pyren mounts ſwelling aboue the clouds,
               That ward the wealthy Caſtile in with walls,
               Could not detaine the beautious Eleanor,
               
               But hearing of the ſame of Edwards youth,
               She darde to brooke Neptunus haughty pride,
               And bide the brunt of froward Eolus,
               
               
                  
Then may faire England welcome her the more.
            
            
               Elinor.
               After that Engliſh Henry by his Lords,
               Had ſent Prince Edwards louely counterfeit,
               A preſent to the Caſtile Elinor,
               
               The comly pourtrait of ſo braue a man,
               The vertuous fame diſcourſed of his deeds,
               
                  Edwards couragious reſolution,
               Done at the holy Land fore Damas walls,
               Led both mine eye and thoughts in equall links,
               To like ſo of the Engliſh Monarchs ſonne,
               That I attempted perils for his ſake.
            
            
               Emperour.
               Where is the Prince, my Lord?
            
            
               Henrie.
               He poſted downe, not long ſince from the Court,
               To Suffolke ſide, to merry Fremingham,
               To ſport himſelfe amongſt my fallow Deere,
               From thence by packets ſent to Hampton houſe,
               We heare the Prince is ridden with his Lords,
               To Oxford in the Academy there,
               To heare diſpute amongſt the learned men:
               But we will ſend forth letters for my ſonne,
               To will him come from Oxford to the Court.
            
            
               Emp.
               Nay rather Henry, let vs as we be,
               Ride for to viſit Oxford with our traine,
               Faine would I ſee your Vniuerſities,
               And what learned men your Academy yeelds,
               From Haspurg haue I brought a learned Clerke,
               To hold diſpute with Engliſh Orators.
               This Doctor ſurnam'd Iaques Vandermaſt,
               
               A Germane borne, paſt into Padua,
               
               To Florence, and to faire Bolonia,
               
               To Paris, Rheims, and ſtately Orleans,
               
               And talking there with men of Art, put downe
               The chiefeſt of them all in Aphoriſmes,
               In Magicke, and the Mathematike rules,
               Now let vs Henry trie him in your Schooles.
            
            
               Henry.
               He ſhall my Lord, this motion likes me well,
               
                  
Weele progreſſe ſtraight to Oxford with our traines,
               And ſee what men our Academy brings.
               And wonder 
                     Ʋandermaſt welcome to me,
               In Oxford ſhalt thou finde a iolly Fryer,
               Cald Fryer Bacon, Englands only flowre,
               Set him but Non-plus in his magicke ſpels,
               And make him yeeld in Mathematicke rules,
               And for thy glory I will bind thy browes,
               Not with a Poets Garland made of Bayes,
               But with a Coronet of choiceſt gold,
               Whilſt then we ſit to Oxford with our troupes,
               Lets in and banquet in our Engliſh Court.
            
            Exit.
            
               Enter Raphe Simnell in Edwards apparell, Edward,
Warren, Ermsby, diſguiſed.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Where be theſe vagabond knaues, that they attend
no better on their maſter?
            
            
               Edward.
               If it pleaſe your Honour, we are ready at an inch.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Sirra Ned, Ile haue no more poſte-horſe to ride on,
               Ile haue another fetch.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               I pray you how is that, my Lord?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Mary ſir, Ile ſend to the Ile of Eely for foure or fiue
dozen of Geeſe, and Ile haue them tide ſixe and ſixe together
with whip-cord. Now vpon their backs will I haue a faire
field bed, with a Canopy, and ſo when it is my pleaſure, Ile ſlee
into what place I pleaſe; this will be eaſie.
            
            
               Warren.
               Your honour hath ſaid well, but ſhall we to Brazennoſe
Colledge before we pull off our bootes.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               
                  Warren, well motioned, we will to the Fryer
               Before we reuell it within the towne.
               
                  Raphe, ſee you keepe your countenance like a Prince.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Wherefore haue I ſuch a company of cutting knaues
to wait vpon me, but to keepe &amp; defend my countenance againſt
all mine enemies? haue you not good ſwords and bucklers?
            
            
               Enter Bacon and Miles.
            
               Ermsby.
               Stay, who comes here?
            
            
               
               Warren.
               Some Scholer, and we'le aske him where Fryer Bacon
is.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Why thou arrant dunce, ſhall I neuer make thee good
ſcholer, doth not all the Towne crie out, and ſay, Fryer Bacons
ſubſiſer is the greateſt block-head in all Oxford? why thou canſt
not ſpeake one word of true Latine.
            
            
               Miles.
               No ſir, yes what is this elſe; Ego ſum tuiu homo, I am
your man, I warrant you ſir, as good Tullies phraſe as any is in
Oxford.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Come ſirra, what patt of ſpeech is Ego.
               
            
            
               Miles.
               
                  Ego, that is I, mary nomen ſubſtantino.
               
            
            
               Bacon.
               How proue you that?
            
            
               Miles.
               Why ſir, let him proue himſelfe and a will, I can be
heard felt and vnderſtood.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Oh groſſe dunce.
            
            Here beate him.
            
               Edward.
               Come let vs breake off this diſpute between theſe
two. Sirra, where is Brazen-noſe Colledge?
            
            
               Miles.
               Not farre from Copper-ſmiths hall.
            
            
               Edward.
               What doeſt thou mocke me?
            
            
               Miles.
               Nor I ſir, but what would you at Brazen-noſe?
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Mary we would ſpeake with Fryer Bacon.
               
            
            
               Miles.
               Whoſe men be you?
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Mary ſcholler, here's our maſter.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Sirra, I am the maſter of theſe good-fellowes, maiſt
thou not know me to be a Lord by my reparrell?
            
            
               Miles.
               Then here's good game for the hawke, for here's the
maſter foole, and a couie of Cockscombes, one wiſe man I think
would ſpring you all.
            
            
               Edward.
               Gogs wounds Warren kill him.
            
            
               Warren.
               Why Ned, I thinke the deuill be in my ſheath, I cannot
get out my dagger.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Nor I mine, Swones Ned, I thinke I am bewitcht.
            
            
               Miles.
               A company of Scabbes, the proudeſt of you all draw
your weapon if he can.
               
                  
See how boldly I ſpeake now my maſter is by.
            
            
               Edward.
               I ſtriue in vaine, but if my ſword by ſhut,
               And coniured faſt by magicke in my ſheath,
               Villaine here is my fiſt.
            
            Strike him a boxe on the eare.
            
               Miles.
               Oh I beſeech you coniure his hand too, that he may
not lift his armes to his head, for he is light-finger'd.
            
            
               Raphe.
               
                  Ned ſtrike him, Ile warrant thee by mine honour.
            
            
               Bacon.
               What meanes the Engliſh Prince to wrong my man?
            
            
               Edward.
               To whom ſpeakeſt thou?
            
            
               Bacon.
               To thee.
            
            
               Edward.
               Who art thou?
            
            
               Bacon.
               Could you not iudge when all your ſwords grew faſt,
               That Fryer Bacon was not farre from hence,
               
                  Edward King Henries ſonne, and Prince of Wales,
               Thy foole diſguis'd cannot conceale thy ſelfe,
               I know both Ermsby and the Suſſex Earle,
               Elſe Fryer Bacon had but little skill.
               Thou comeſt in poaſt from merry Freſingfield,
               Faſt fancied to the Keepers bonny Laſſe,
               To craue ſome ſuccour of the iolly Fryer,
               And Lacy Earle of Lincolne haſt thou left,
               To treat faire Margret to allow thy loues:
               But friends are men, and Loue can baffle Lords.
               The Earle both wooes and courts her for himſelfe.
            
            
               Warren.
               
                  Ned, this is ſtrange, the Fryer knoweth all.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               
                  Apollo could not vtter more then this.
            
            
               Edward.
               I ſtand amazed to heare this iolly Fryer,
               Tell euen the very ſecrets of my thoughts:
               But learned Bacon ſince thou knoweſt the cauſe,
               Why I did poaſt ſo faſt from Freſingfield,
               Helpe Fryer at a pinch, that I may haue
               The loue of louely Margret to my ſelfe,
               And as I am true Prince of Wales, Ile giue
               Liuing and lands to ſtrength thy Colledge ſtate.
            
            
               
               Warren.
               Good Fryer helpe the Prince in this.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Why ſeruant Ned, will not the Fryer doe it? Were
not my ſword glued to my ſcabberd by coniuration, I would
cut off his head and make him doe it by force.
            
            
               Miles.
               In faith my Lord, your manhood and your ſword is all
alike, they are ſo faſt coniured that we ſhall neuer ſee them.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               What Doctor in a dumpe? tuſh helpe the Prince,
               And thou ſhalt ſee how liberall he will proue,
            
            
               Bacon.
               Craue not ſuch actions, greater dumps then theſe,
               I will my Lord ſtraine out my magicke ſpels,
               For this day comes the Earle of Freſingfield;
               And fore that night ſhuts in the day with darke,
               They 'le be betrothed each to other faſt:
               But come with me, weele to my ſtudy ſtraight,
               And in a glaſſe proſpectiue I will ſhew
               What's done this day in merry Freſingfield.
            
            
               Edward.
               Gramercies Bacon, I will quite thy paine.
            
            
               Bacon.
               But ſend your traine, my Lord, into the Towne,
               My ſcholler ſhall goe bring them to their Inne:
               Meane while weele ſee the knauery of the Earle.
            
            
               Edward.
               
                  Warren, leaue me and Ermsby, take the foole,
               Let him be maſter, and goe reuell it,
               Till I and Fryer Bacon talke a while.
            
            
               Warren.
               We will, my Lord.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Faith Ned, and Ile Lord it out till thou commeſt, Ile
be Prince of Wales ouer all the blacke pots in Oxford.
               
            
            Exeunt.
            
               Bacon and Edward gos into the ſtudy.
            
               Bacon.
               Now frolicke Edward, welcome to my Cell,
               Here tempers Fryer Bacon many toyes:
               And hold this place his Conſiſtory Court,
               Wherein the deuils pleade homage to his words,
               Within this glaſſe proſpectiue thou ſhalt ſee
               This day what's done in merry Freſingfield,
               Tvvixt louely Peggis and the Lincolne Earle.
            
            
               
               Edward.
               Fryer, thou gladſt me, now ſhall Edward trie,
               How Lacy meaneth to his Soueraigne Lord.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Stand there and looke directly in the glaſſe.
            
            Enter Margret and Fryer Bungay.
            
            
               Bacon.
               What ſees my Lord?
            
            
               Edward.
               I ſee the Keepers louely laſſe appeare,
               As bright-ſunne as the Paramour of Mars,
               
               Onely attended by a iolly Fryer.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Sit ſtill and keepe the criſtall in your eye.
            
            
               Margret.
               But tell me Fryer Bungay, is it true,
               That this faire courteous Country Swaine,
               Who ſayes his father is a Farmer nye,
               Can be Lord Lacy Earle of Lincolnſhire.
            
            
               Bungay.
               
                  Peggie 'tis true, 'tis Lacy for my life:
               Or elſe mine Art and cunning both doe faile,
               Left by Prince Edward to procure his loues:
               For he in greene that holpe to run your cheeſe,
               Is ſonne to Henry, and the Prince of Wales.
            
            
               Margret.
               Be what he will, his lure is but for luſt.
               But did Lord Lacie like poore Margret,
               
               Or would he daine to wed a Countrie Laſſe?
               Fryer, I would his humble hand-maid be,
               And for great wealth, quite him with courteſie.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Why Margret doſt loue him?
            
            
               Margret.
               His perſonage like the pride of vaunting Troy,
               Might well auouch to ſhadow Hellens cape:
               His wit is quicke and ready in conceit,
               As Greece affoorded in her chiefeſt prime
               Courteous, ah Fryer full of pleaſing ſmiles,
               Truſt me I loue too much; to tell thee more,
               Suffice to me he is Englands Paramour.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Hath not each eye that viewd thy pleaſing face,
               Surnamed thee faire mayd of Freſingfield?
            
            
               Margret
               Yes Bungay, and would God the louely Earle
               
                  
Had that in eſſe, that ſo many ſought.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Feare not, the Fryer will not be behind,
               To ſhew his cunning to entangle Loue.
            
            
               Edward.
               I thinke the Fryer courts the bonny wench,
               
                  Bacon, me thinkes he is a luſtie churle.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Now looke, my Lord.
            
            
               Enter Lacy.
            
               Edwards.
               Gogs wounds Bacon, here comes Lacy.
               
            
            
               Bacon.
               Sit ſtill my Lord, and marke the Comedy.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Here's Lacy, Margret, ſtep aſide a while.
            
            
               Lacy.
               
                  Daphne the Damſell, that caught Phoebus faſt,
               And lockt him in the brightneſſe of her lookes,
               Was not ſo beautious in Apollo's eyes,
               As is faire Margret to the Lincolne Earle,
               Recant thee: Lacy, thou art put in truſt,
               
                  Edward thy Soueraignes ſon hath choſen thee
               A ſecret friend to court her for himſelfe:
               And dareſt thou wrong thy Prince with trecherie▪
               
               
                  Lacy, Loue makes no exception of a friend,
               Nor deemes it of a Prince, but as a man:
               Honour bids me controll him in his luſt,
               His wooing is not for to wed the girle,
               But to intrap her and beguile the laſſe:
               
                  Lacy, thou loueſt, then brooke not ſuch abuſe,
               But wed her, and abide thy Princes frowne:
               For dye, then ſee her liue diſgrac'd.
            
            
               Margret.
               Come, Fryer, I will ſhake him from his dumpes,
               How cheere you ſir, a penny for your thought:
               Your early vp, pray God it be the neere,
               What 'are come from Beckles in a morne ſo ſoone?
            
            
               Lacy.
               Thus watchfull are ſuch men as liue in loue,
               Whoſe eyes brooke broken ſlumbers for their ſleepe.
               I tell thee, Peggie, ſince laſt Harlſton faire,
               My minde hath felt a heape of paſſions.
            
            
               
               Margret.
               A truſty man that court it for your friend,
               Woo you ſtill for the Courtier all in greene?
               I maruell that he ſues not for himſelfe.
            
            
               Lacy.
               
                  Peggie, I pleaded firſt to get your grace for him:
               But when mine eyes ſuruaid your beautious lookes,
               Loue like a wagge, ſtraight dined into my heart,
               And there did ſhrine the Idea of your ſelfe:
               Pittie me though I be a Farmers ſonne,
               And meaſure not my riches, but my loue.
            
            
               Margret.
               You are very haſty for to garden well,
               Seeds muſt haue time to ſprout before they ſpring,
               Loue ought to creepe as doth the dyals ſhade,
               For timely ripe, is rotten too too ſoone.
            
            
               Bungay.
               
                  Deus hic, roome for a merry Fryer,
               What, youth of Beckles, with the Keepers Laſſe?
               'Tis well, but tell me here you any newes,
            
            
               Margret.
               No, Fryer, what newes.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Heare you not how the Purſeuants doe poaſt,
               With Proclamations through each Country towne?
            
            
               Lacy.
               For what, gentle Fryer? tell the newes.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Dwelſt thou in Beckles, &amp; hear'ſt not theſe newes?
               
                  Lacy the Earle of Lincolne is late fled
               From Windſor Court, diſguiſed like a Swaine,
               And lurkes about the Country here vnknowne.
               
                  Henry ſuſpects him of ſome treachery,
               And therefore doth proclaime in euery way,
               That who can take the Lincolne Earle, ſhall haue
               Paid in the Exchequer twenty thouſand Crownes.
            
            
               Lacy.
               The Earle of Lin
                     •
                  olne? Fryer, thou art mad,
               It was ſome other, thou miſtakeſt the man:
               The Earle of Lincolne? why it cannot be.
            
            
               Margret.
               Yes, very well my Lord, for you are he,
               The Keepers daughter tooke you priſoner,
               Lord Lacy yeeld, Ile be your gailor once.
            
            
               Edward.
               How familiar they be, Bacon.
               
            
            
               Bacon.
               Sit ſtill, and marke the ſequell of their loues.
            
            
               
               Lacie.
               Then am I double priſoner to thy ſelfe,
               
                  Peggie, I yeeld, but are theſe newes in ieſt?
            
            
               Margret.
               In ieſt with you, but earneſt vnto me:
               For why, theſe wrongs doe wring me at the heart,
               Ah how theſe Earles and Noble-men of birth,
               Flatter and faine to forge poore womens ill!
            
            
               Lacie.
               Beleeue me, Laſſe, I am the Lincolne Earle,
               I not deny, but tyred thus in rags,
               I liued diſguiſd to win faire Peggies loue.
            
            
               Margret.
               What loue is there where wedding ends not loue?
            
            
               Lacie.
               I meant, faire girle, to make thee Lacies wife.
            
            
               Margret.
               I little thinke that Earles will ſtoop ſo low.
            
            
               Lacie.
               Say, ſhall I make thee Counteſſe ere I ſleepe?
            
            
               Margret.
               Handmaid vnto the Earle ſo pleaſe himſelfe:
               A wife in name, but ſeruant in obedience.
            
            
               Lacie.
               The Lincolne Counteſſe, for it ſhall be ſo,
               Ile plight the bands and ſeale it with a kiſſe.
            
            
               Edward.
               Gogs wounds, Bacon, they kiſſe, Ile ſtab them.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Oh hold your hands (my Lord) it is the glaſſe.
            
            
               Edward.
               Coller to ſee the traitors gree ſo well,
               Made me thinke the ſhadowes ſubſtances.
            
            
               Bacon.
               'Twere a long Poinard, my Lord, to reach betweene
               Oxford and 
                     •
                  reſingfield, but ſit ſtill and ſee more.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Well, Lord of Lincolne, if your loues be knit,
               And that your tongues and thoughts doe both agree:
               To auoid inſuing iarres, Ile hamper vp the match,
               Ile take my Portace forth, and wed you here,
               Then goe to bed and ſcale vp your deſires.
            
            
               Lacie.
               Fryer, content, Peggie how like you this?
            
            
               Margret.
               What likes my Lord, is pleaſing vnto me.
            
            
               Bungay.
               Then hand-faſt hand, and I will to my booke.
            
            
               Bacon.
               What ſees my Lord now?
            
            
               Edward.
               
                  Bacon, I ſee the Louers hand in hand,
               The Fryer ready with his Portace there,
               To wed them both, then am I quite vndone,
               
                  Bacon, helpe now, if ere thy magicke ſeru'd,
               
                  
                  Bacon, helpe now, if ere thy magicke ſeru'd,
               Helpe, Bacon, ſtop the marriage now,
               If Deuils or Nigromancie may ſuffice,
               And I will giue thee fortie thouſand Crownes.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Feare not, my Lord, Ile ſtop the iolly Frier,
               For mumbling vp his oriſons this day.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Why ſpeak'ſt not Bungay? Frier, to thy booke.
            
            
               Bungay is mute, crying, Hud, hud.
            
               Margret.
               How lookeſt thou, Frier, as a man diſtraught,
               Reft of thy ſences, Bungay? ſhew by ſignes
               If thou be dumbe, what paſſion holdeth thee.
            
            
               Lacy.
               He's dumbe indeed: Bacon hath with his Deuils
               Inchanted him, or elſe ſome ſtrange diſeaſe,
               Or Apoplexie hath poſſeſt his lungs:
               But, Peggie, what he cannot with his booke,
               We'le twixt vs both vnite it vp in heart.
            
            
               Margret.
               Elſe let me die (my Lord) a miſcreant.
            
            
               Edward.
               Why ſtands Frier Bacon ſo amaz'd?
            
            
               Bacon.
               I haue ſtruk him dumb, my Lord, &amp; if your honor pleaſe:
               Ile fetch this Bungay ſtraightway from Freſingfield,
               And he ſhall dine with vs is Oxford here.
            
            
               Edward.
               
                  Bacon, doe that, and thou contenteſt me.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Of courteſie, Margret, let vs lead the Frier
               Vnto thy fathers lodge, to comfort him
               With broths to bring him from this hapleſſe trance.
            
            
               Margret.
               Or elſe my Lord, we were paſſing vnkinde
               To leaue the Frier ſo in his diſtreſſe.
            
            Enter a Deuill, and carry Bungay on his backe.
            
               Margret.
               O helpe, my Lord, a Deuill, a Deuill, my Lord,
               Looke how he carries Bungay on his backe:
               Let's hence, for Bacons ſpirits be abroad.
            
            Exeunt.
            
               
               Edward.
               
                  Bacon, I laugh to ſee the iolly Fryer
               Mounted vpon the Deuill, and how the Earle
               Flees with his bonny laſſe for feare.
               Aſſoone as Bungay is at Brazen-noſe,
               I will in poaſt hie me to Freſingfield,
               And quite theſe wrongs on Lacy ere it be long.
            
            
               Bacon.
               So be it, my Lord, but let vs to our dinner:
               For ere we haue taken our repaſt awhile,
               We ſhall haue Bungay brought to Brazen-noſe.
            
            Exeunt.
            
               Enter three Doctors, Burden, Maſon, Clement.
            
               Maſon.
               Now that we are gathered in the Regent houſe,
               It ſits vs talke about the long repaire,
               For he troop't with all the Weſterne Kings,
               That lye alongſt the Danſick Seas by Eaſt,
               North by the clime of froſtie Germany,
               The Almaine Monarke, and the Scocon Duke,
               Caſtile, and louely Ellinor, with him,
               Haue in their ieſts reſolued for Oxford Towne.
            
            
               Burden.
               We muſt lay plots for ſtately Tragedies,
               Strange Comicke ſhowes, ſuch as proud Roſſius
               
               Vaunted before the Romane Emperours.
            
            
               Clement.
               To welcome all the Weſterne Potentates,
               But more the King by letters hath fore-told,
               That Fredericke the Almaine Emperour,
               Hath brought with him a Germane of eſteeme,
               Whoſe ſurname is Don Iaques Ʋandermaſt,
               
               Skilfull in Magicke and thoſe ſecret arts.
            
            
               Maſon.
               Then muſt we all make ſute vnto the Fryer,
               To Frier Bacon, that he vouch this taske,
               And vndertake to counteruaile in skill
               The Germane, elſe there's none in Oxford can
               Match and diſpute with learned 
                     Ʋandermaſt.
               
            
            
               Burden.
               
                  Bacon, if he will hold the German play,
               
                  
We'le teach him what an Engliſh Frier can doe:
               The Deuill I thinke dare not diſpute with him.
            
            
               Clement.
               Indeed mas Doctor, he pleaſured you,
               In that he brought your hoſteſſe with her ſpit,
               From Henly, poſting vnto Brazen-noſe.
            
            
               Burden.
               A vengeance on the Frier for his paines,
               But leauing that, let's to Bacon ſtraight,
               To ſee if he will take this taske in hand.
            
            
               Clement.
               Stay! what rumour is this? The towne is vp in a
mutiny, what hurly burly is this?
            
            Enter a Conſtable, with Raphe, Warren, Ermsby, and Miles.
            
            
               Conſtable.
               Nay maſters, if you were ne'r ſo good, you ſhall
before the Doctors to anſwer your miſdemeanour.
            
            
               Burden.
               Whats the matter, fellow?
            
            
               Conſtable.
               Mary ſir, here's a company of Rufflers, that drinking
in the Tauerne, haue made a great brawle, and almoſt kild
the Vintner.
            
            
               Miles.
               
                  Salue, Doctor Burden, this lubberly Lurden,
               Ill ſhapt and ill faced, diſdain'd and diſgraced,
               What he tels vnto vobis, mentitur de nobis.
               
            
            
               Burden.
               Who is the maſter and chiefe of this crue?
            
            
               Miles.
               Ecce aſinum mundi, figura retundi,
               Neat, ſheat and ſine, as briske as a cup of wine.
            
            
               Burden.
               What are you?
            
            
               Raphe.
               I am, father Doctor, as a man would ſay, the Belweather
of this company, theſe are my Lords, and I the Prince of
Wales.
            
            
               Clement.
               Are you Edward the Kings ſonne?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Sirra Miles, bring hither the Tapſter that drew the
wine, &amp; I warrant when they ſee how ſoundly I haue broke his
head, thei'le ſay 'twas done by no leſſe man then a Prince.
            
            
               Maſon.
               I cannot beleeue that this is the Prince of Wales.
            
            
               Warren.
               And why ſo, ſir?
            
            
               Maſon.
               For they ſay the Prince is a braue &amp; a wiſe Gentleman.
            
            
               Warren.
               Why, and thinkeſt thou, Doctor, that he is not ſo?
               
                  
Dar'ſt thou detract and derogate from him,
               Being ſo louely and ſo braue a Youth?
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Whoſe face ſhining with many a ſugred ſmile,
               Bewrayes that he is bred of princely race.
            
            
               Miles.
               And yet, maſter Doctor, to ſpeake like a Proctor,
               And tell vnto you, what is veriment and true,
               To ceaſe off this quarrell; looke but on his apparell,
               Then marke but my talis, he is great Prince of Walis,
               The cheefe of our gregis, and filius Regis,
               
               Then ware what is done, for he is Henries white ſonne.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Doctors, whoſe doting night-caps are not capable of
my ingenious dignity, know that I am Edward Plantagenet,
whom if you diſpleaſe, will make a ſhip that ſhall hold all your
Colleges, and ſo carry away the Niniuerſity with a faire wind,
to the Bankeſide in Southwarke, how ſaiſt thou Ned Warraine,
ſhall I not doe it?
            
            
               Warren.
               Yes my good Lord, and if it pleaſe your Lordſhip,
I will gather vp all your old pantophles, and with the corke,
make you a Pinnis of fiue hundred tunne, that ſhall ſerue the
turne maruellous well, my Lord.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               And I my Lord will haue Pioners to vndermine the
Towne, that the very Gardens and Orchards be carryed away
for your Summer walkes.
            
            
               Miles.
               And with ſcientia and great diligentia,
               
               Will coniure and charme, to keepe you from harme,
               That vtrum horum manis, your very great nauis,
               
               Like Bartlets ſhip, from Oxford doe skip,
               With Colledges and ſchooles, full loaden with fooles,
               Quid dices ad hoc, worſhipfull Domine Dawcocke?
            
            
               Clement.
               Why harebraind Courtiers, are you drunke or mad,
               To taunt vs vp with ſuch ſcurrilitie?
               Deeme you vs men of baſe and light eſteeme,
               To bring vs ſuch a fop for Henries ſonne?
               Call out the Beadles and conuay them hence
               Straight to Bocardo, let the Roiſters lie
               Cloſe clapt in bolts, vntill their wits be tame.
            
            
               
               Ermsby.
               Why, ſhall we to priſon my Lord?
            
            
               Raphe.
               What ſaiſt, Miles, ſhall I honour the priſon with my preſence?
            
            
               Miles.
               No, no, out with your blades, and hamper theſe Iades,
               Haue a fiurt and a craſh, now reuell daſh,
               And teach theſe Sacerdos, that the Bocardos,
               Like Pezzants and clues, are meet for themſelues.
            
            
               Maſon.
               To the priſon with them, Conſtable.
            
            
               Warren.
               Well (Doctors) ſeeing I haue ſported me,
               With laughing at theſe mad and merry wagges,
               Know that Prince Edward is at Brazen-noſe,
               And this, attired like the Prince of Wales,
               Is Raphe, King Henries only loued foole,
               I, Earle of Eſſex, and this Ermsby,
               
               One of the priuie Chamber to the King,
               Who while the Prince with Frier Bacon ſtaies,
               Haue reuel'd in Oxford as you ſee.
            
            
               Maſon.
               My Lord, pardon vs, we knew not what you were▪
               
               But Courtiers may make greater ſcapes then theſe,
               Wilt pleaſe your Honour dine with me to day?
            
            
               Warren.
               I will, maſter Doctor, and ſatisfie the Vintner for
his hurt; only I muſt deſire you to imagine him all this forenoone
the Prince of Wales.
            
            
               Maſon.
               I will, ſir.
            
            
               Raphe.
               And vpon that I will lead the way, onely I will haue
Miles goe before me, becauſe I haue heard Henry ſay, that wiſedome
muſt goe before Maieſtie.
            
            Exeunt omnes.
            Enter Prince Edward with his poinard in his hand, Lacy
and Margret.
            
               Edward.
               
                  Lacie, thou canſt not ſhroud thy traitrous thoughts,
               Nor couer, as did Caſſius, all his wiles,
               For Edward hath an eye that lookes as farre,
               As Lincaeus from the ſhores of Grecia.
               Did not I ſit in Oxford by the Fryer,
               And ſee thee court the maid of Freſingfield,
               
                  
Sealing thy flattering fancies with a kiſſe?
               Did not proud Bungay draw his portaſſe forth,
               And ioyning hand in hand, had married you,
               If Frier Bacon had not ſtrooke him dumbe,
               And mounted him vpon a ſpirits backe,
               That we might chat at Oxford with the Frier?
               Traytor, what anſwer'ſt? Is not all this true?
            
            
               Lacy.
               Truth all, my Lord, and thus I make reply,
               At Harlſtone Faire there courting for your Grace,
               When as mine eye ſuruaid her curious ſhape,
               And drew the beautious glory of her lookes,
               To diue into the center of my heart,
               Loue taught me that your Honour did but ieſt,
               That Princes were in fancy but as men,
               How that the louely maid of Freſingfield
               Was fitter to be Lacies wedded wife,
               Then Concubine vnto the Prince of Wales.
            
            
               Edward.
               Iniurious Lacy, did I loue thee more
               Then Alexander his Hepheſtion?
               
               Did I vnfold the paſſions of my loue,
               And locke them in the clozet of thy thoughts?
               Wert thou to Edward ſecond to himſelfe,
               Sole friend, and partner of his ſecret loues;
               And could a glaunce of fading beauty breake
               Th'inchained fetters of ſuch priuat friends?
               Baſe coward, falſe, and too effeminate,
               To be corriuall with a Prince in thoughts!
               From Oxford haue I poſted ſince I dinde,
               To quite a Traitor 'fore that Edward ſleepe?
            
            
               Margret.
               'Twas I, my Lord, not Lacy ſtept awry:
               For oft he ſued and courted for your ſelfe,
               And ſtill woo'd for the Courtier all in greene:
               But I, whom fancy made but ouer-fond,
               Pleaded my ſelfe with lookes as if lou'd,
               I fed mine eye with gazing on his face,
               And ſtill bewitcht lou'd Lacie with my lookes,
               
                  
My heart with ſighes, mine eyes pleaded with teares,
               My face held pitty and content at once,
               And more I could not cypher out by ſignes,
               But that I lou'd Lord Lacy with my heart:
               Then worthy Edward, meaſure with thy minde,
               If womens fauours will not force men fall,
               If beauty, and if darts of piercing loue,
               Is not of force to bury thoughts of friends.
            
            
               Edward.
               I tell thee, Peggie, I will haue thy loues,
               
                  Edward, or none ſhall conquer Margret;
               
               In Frigats bottom'd with rich S
                     •
                  thin planks,
               Topt with the lofty Firs of Libanon,
               Stem'd and incaſt with burniſht Iuory,
               And ouer-laid with plates of Perſian wealth,
               Like Thetis ſhalt thou wanton on the waues,
               And draw the Dolphins to thy louely eyes,
               To dance Lauoltas in the purple ſtreames,
               Sirens with harpes and ſiluer Pſalteries,
               Shall wait with muſicke at thy Frigots ſtem,
               And entertaine faire Margret with her layes;
               England and Englands wealth ſhall wait on thee,
               Brittaine ſhall bend vnto her Princes loue,
               And doe due homage to thine Excellence,
               If thou wilt be but Edwards Margret.
               
            
            
               Margret.
               Pardon, my Lord, if Ioues great Royalty
               Sent me ſuch preſents as to Danae,
               
               If Phoebus tyed in Latonas webs,
               Come courting from the beauty of his lodge,
               The dulcet tunes of frolicke Mercurie,
               
               Not all the wealth heauens treaſury affords,
               Should make me leaue Lord Lacy, or his loue.
            
            
               Edward.
               I haue learn'd at Oxford then this point of ſchooles,
               Ablata cauſa, tollitur effectus.
               
                  Lacy, the cauſe, that Margret cannot loue,
               Nor fixe her liking on the Engliſh Prince.
               Take him away, and then the effects will faile.
               
                  
Villaine, prepare thy ſelfe: for I will bathe
               My poinard in the boſome of an Earle.
            
            
               Lacie.
               Rather then liue, and miſſe faire Margrets loue,
               Prince Edward, ſtop not at the fatall doome,
               But ſtab it home, end both my loues and life.
            
            
               Marg.
               Braue Prince of Wales, honour'd for Royall deeds,
               Twere ſinne to ſtaine faire Venus courts with blood,
               Loues conqueſt ends, my Lord, in courteſie,
               Spare Lacy, gentle Edward, let me dye,
               For ſo both you and he doe ceaſe your loues.
            
            
               Edward.
               
                  Lacie ſhall die as Traitor to his Lord.
            
            
               Lacy.
               I haue deſerued it, Edward, act it well.
            
            
               Marg.
               What hopes the Prince to gaine by Lacies death?
            
            
               Edward.
               To end the loues 'twixt him and Margaret.
               
            
            
               Marg.
               Why, thinks King Henries ſon that Margrets loue
               Hangs in th' vncertaine ballance of proud Time,
               That death ſhall make a diſcord of our thoughts?
               No, ſtab the Earle, and 'fore the morning Sun
               Shall vaunt him thrice ouer the lofty Eaſt,
               
                  Margret will meet her Lacy in the heauens.
            
            
               Lacy.
               If ought betides to louely Margret,
               
               That wrongs or wrings her honour from content,
               Europes rich wealth, nor Englands Monarchie,
               Should not allure Lacy to ouer-liue.
               Then Edward, ſhort my life, and end her loues.
            
            
               Marg.
               Rid me, and keepe a friend worth many loues.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Nay, Edward, keepe a loue worth many friends.
            
            
               Marg.
               And if thy mind be ſuch as fame hath blaz'd,
               Then Princely Edward, let vs both abide
               The fatall reſolution of thy rage,
               Baniſh thou fancie, and imbrace reuenge,
               And in one toombe knit both our carkaſes,
               Whoſe hearts were linked in one perfect loue,
            
            
               Edward.
               
                  Edward, art thou that famous Prince of Wales,
               Who at Damaſco beat the Sarazens,
               And broughtſt home triumph on thy Lances point?
               
                  
And ſhall thy plumes be puld by 
                     Ʋenus downe?
               Is't princely to diſſeuer Louers loues?
               Leaue, Ned, and make a vertue of this fault,
               And further Peg and Lacy in their loues;
               So in ſubduing fancies paſſion,
               Conquering thy ſelfe, thou get'ſt the richeſt ſpoile.
               
                  Lacy, riſe vp. Faire Peggis, here's my hand,
               The Prince of Wales hath conquered all his thoughts,
               And all his loues he yeelds vnto the Earle.
               
                  Lacy, enioy the maid of Freſingfield,
               Make her thy Lincolne Counteſſe at the Church.
               And Ned, as he is true Plantagenet,
               
               Will giue her to thee frankly for thy wife.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Humbly I take her of my Soueraigne,
               As if that Edward gaue me Englands right,
               And rich't me with the Albion Diadem.
            
            
               Margret.
               And doth the Engliſh Prince meane true?
               Will he vouchſafe to ceaſe his former loues,
               And yeeld the title of a Country maid,
               Vnto Lord Lacy?
               
            
            
               Edward.
               I will, faire Peggie, as I am true Lord.
            
            
               Margret.
               Then Lordly Sir, whoſe conqueſt is as great,
               In conquering loue, as Caſars victories,
               
                  Margret as milde and humble in her thoughts,
               As was Aſpatia vnto Cyrus ſelfe,
               Yeelds thanks, and next Lord Lacy, doth inſhrine
               
                  Edward the ſecond ſecret in her heart.
            
            
               Edward.
               Gramercy, Peggie, now that vowes are paſt,
               And that your loues are not to be reuolt:
               Once, Lacy, friends againe, come, we will poaſt
               To Oxford: for this day the King is there,
               And brings for Edward Caſtile Ellinor.
               
               
                  Peggie, I muſt goe ſee and view my wife;
               I pray God I like her as I loued thee.
               Beſide, Lord Lincolne, we ſhall heare diſpute,
               Twixt Fryer Bacon, and learned Vandermaſt,
               
               
                  
                  Peggy, we'le leaue you for a weeke or two.
            
            
               Margret.
               As it pleaſe Lord Lacy: but loues fooliſh looks
               Thinke footſteps miles, and minutes to be houres.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Ile haſten, Peggie, to make ſhort returne.
               But pleaſe your Honour goe vnto the Lodge,
               We ſhall haue Butter, Cheeſe, and Veniſon.
               And yeſterday I brought for Margret,
               
               A luſty bottle of neat Clarret wine:
               Thus can we feaſt and entertaine your Grace.
            
            
               Edward.
               'Tis cheere, Lord Lacy, for an Emperour,
               If he reſpect the perſon and the place.
               Come, let vs in, for I will all this night
               Ride poaſt vntill I come to Bacons cell.
            
            Exeunt.
            
               Enter Henry, Emperour, Caſtile, Ellinor, Vandermaſt,
Bungay.
            
               Emperour.
               Truſt me, Plantagenet, theſe Oxford Schooles
               Are richly ſeated neere the Riuer ſide:
               The mountaines full of fat and fallow Deere,
               The battling paſtures laid with Kine and Flocks,
               The Towne gorgeous with high built Colledges,
               And Schollers ſeemely in their graue attire,
               Learned in ſearching the principles of Art.
               What is thy iudgement, Iaques Ʋandermaſt?
               
            
            
               Vander.
               That Lordly are the buildings of the Towne,
               Spatious the roomes, and full of pleaſant walkes:
               But for the Doctors, how that they be learned,
               It may be meanely, for ought I can heare.
            
            
               Bungay.
               I tell thee, Germane, Haſpurge holds none ſuch,
               None read ſo deepe, as Oxenford containes,
               There are within our Academicke ſtate,
               Men that may lecture it in Germany,
               To all the Doctors of your Belgicke Scholes.
            
            
               Henry.
               Stand to him, Bungay, charme this Vandermaſt,
               
               And I will vſe thee as a Royall King.
            
            
               
               Vandermaſt.
               Wherein dareſt thou diſpute with me?
            
            
               Bungay.
               In what a Doctor and a Fryer can.
            
            
               Vandermaſt.
               Before rich Europes Worthies put thou forth
               The doubtfull queſtion vnto 
                     Ʋandermaſt.
               
            
            
               Bungay.
               Let it be this, Whether the ſpirits of Piromancy or
               Geomancy, be moſt predominant in Magicke?
            
            
               Vander.
               I ſay, of Piromancy.
            
            
               Bungay.
               And I of Geomancy.
            
            
               Vander.
               The Cabbaliſts that write of Magicke ſpels,
               
                  As Hermes, Melchre, and Pythagoras,
               Affirme that 'mongſt the quadruplicity
               Of elementall eſſence, Terra is but thought,
               To be a punctum ſquared to the reſt:
               And that the compaſſe of aſcending elements
               Exceed in bigneſſe as they doe in height;
               Iudging the concaue Circle of the Sunne,
               To hold the reſt in his Circumference;
               If then, as Hermes ſayes, the fire be great'ſt,
               Pureſt, and onely giueth ſhapes to ſpirits:
               Then muſt theſe Demones that haunt that place,
               Be euery way ſuperiour to the reſt.
            
            
               Bungay.
               I reaſon not of elementall ſhapes,
               Nor tell I of the concaue latitudes,
               Noting their eſſence, nor their quality,
               But of the ſpirits that Piromancy calls,
               And of the vigour of the Geomanticke Fiends.
               I tell thee, Germane, Magicke hants the grounds,
               And thoſe ſtrange Negromanticke ſpels,
               That worke ſuch ſhewes and wondring in the world,
               Are acted by thoſe Geomanticke ſprites,
               
                  That Hermes calleth Terrae ſilij.
               The fierie ſpirits are but tranſparent ſhades,
               That lightly paſſe as Heralds to beare newes,
               But earthly Fiends cloz'd in the loweſt deepe,
               Diſſeuer mountaines, if they be but char'd,
               Being more groſſe and maſſie in their power.
            
            
               
               Vandermaſt.
               Rather theſe earthly Geomantike ſpirits,
               Are dull and like the place where they remaine:
               For when proud Lucifer fell from the heauens,
               The ſpirits and Angels that did ſin with him,
               Retain'd their locall eſſence as their faults,
               All ſubiects vnder Lunas Continent,
               The which offended leſſe, hang in the fire,
               And ſecond faults did reſt within the aire,
               But Lucifer and his proud-hearted fiends,
               Were throwne into the Center of the earth,
               Hauing leſſe vnderſtanding then the reſt,
               As hauing greater ſinne, and leſſer grace.
               Therefore ſuch groſſe and earthly ſpirits doe ſerue,
               For Iuglers, Witches, and vild Sorcerers,
               Whereas the Piromanticke Genij,
               Are mighty, ſwift, and of farre reaching power.
               But grant that Geomancie hath moſt force,
               
                  Bungay, to pleaſe theſe mighty Potentates,
               Proue by ſome inſtance what thy Art can doe.
            
            
               Bungay.
               I will.
            
            
               Emper.
               Now Engliſh Harry, here begins the game,
               We ſhall ſee ſport betweene theſe learned men.
            
            
               
                  Ʋandermaſt.
               What wilt thou doe?
            
            
               Bungay.
               Shew thee the Tree leau'd with refined gold,
               Whereon the fearefull Dragon held his ſeate,
               That watcht the Garden cald Heſperides,
               Subdued and wonne by conquering Hercules.
               
            
            
               
                  Ʋandermaſt.
               Well done.
            
            Here Bungay coniures, and the Tree appeares with the
Dragon ſhooting fire.
            
               Henrie.
               What ſay you Royall Lordlings to my Fryer?
               Hath he not done a point of cunning skill?
            
            
               Vander.
               Ech Scholler in the Negromanticke ſpels
               Can doe as much as Bungay hath perform'd.
               
                  
But as Alemenas baſtard rais'd this Tree,
               So will I raiſe him vp as when he liued,
               And cauſe him pull the Dragon from his ſeate,
               And teare the branches piecemeale from the roote,
               Hercules, Prodi, Prodi, Hercules.
            
            
               Hercules appeares in his Lyous skin.
            
               Hercules.
               Quis me vult?
            
            
               
                  Ʋandermaſt.
               
                  Ioues baſtard ſonne, thou Libian Heroules,
               
               Pull off the ſprigs from off the Heſperian Tree,
               As once thou didſt to win the golden fruit.
               Hercules. Fiat.
            
            Here he begins to breake the branches.
            
               Vander.
               Now Bungay, if thon canſt by Magicke charme
               The Fiend, appearing like great Hercules,
               
               From pulling downe the branches of the Tree,
               Then art thou worthy to be counted learned.
            
            
               Bungay.
               I cannot.
            
            
               Vander.
               Ceaſe Hercules, vntill I giue thee charge.
               Mighty Commander of this Engliſh Ile,
               
                  Henrie, come from the ſtout Plantagenets,
               
               
                  Bungay is learned enough to be a Fryer:
               But to compare with Iaques Vandermaſt,
               
               Oxford and Cambridge muſt goe ſeeke their Celles,
               To find a man to match him in his Art.
               I haue giuen non-plus to the Paduans,
               To them of Sien, Florence, and Bologna,
               Rheims, Louain, and faire Roterdam,
               Franckford, Lutrech, and Orleance:
               And now muſt Henrie, if he doe me right,
               Crowne me with Lawrell, as they all haue done.
            
            
               Enter Bacon.
            
               Bacon.
               All haile to this Royall Company,
               
                  
That ſit to heare and ſee this ſtrange diſpute:
               
                  Bungay, how ſtandſt thou as a man amaz'd?
               What, hath the Germane acted more then thou?
            
            
               
                  Ʋandermaſt.
               What art thou that queſtionſt thus?
            
            
               Bacon.
               Men call me Bacon.
               
            
            
               
                  Ʋander.
               Lordly thou look'ſt, as if that thou wert learn'd?
               Thy countenance, as if ſcience held her ſeate
               Betweene the circled arches of thy browes.
            
            
               Henry.
               Now Monarks, hath the Germane found his match?
            
            
               Emperour.
               Beſtirre thee Iaques, take not now the foile,
               Leſt thou doeſt loſe, what foretime thou didſt gaine.
            
            
               
                  Ʋandermaſt.
               
                  Bacon, wilt thou diſpute?
            
            
               Bacon.
               No, vnleſſe he were more learn'd then Vandermaſt.
               
               For yet tell me, what haſt thou done?
            
            
               
                  Ʋandermaſt.
               Rais'd Hercules to ruinate that tree,
               That Bungay mounted by his Magicke ſpels.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Set Hercules to worke.
            
            
               Vander.
               Now Hercules, I charge thee to thy taske,
               Pull off the golden branches from the roote.
            
            
               Hercules.
               I dare not. Seeſt thou not great Bacon here,
               Whoſe frowne doth act more then thy Magicke can?
            
            
               
                  Ʋandermaſt.
               By all the Thrones, and Dominations,
               Vertues, Powers, and mightie Hierarchies,
               I charge thee to obey to Vandermaſt.
               
            
            
               Hercules.
               
                  Bacon, that bridles headſtrong Belzephon,
               And rules Aſmenoth guider of the North:
               Binds me from yeelding vnto Vandermaſt.
               
            
            
               Hen.
               How now, 
                     Ʋandermaſt, haue you met with your match?
            
            
               Vander.
               Neuer before was't knowne to 
                     Ʋandermaſt,
               
               That men held Deuils in ſuch obedient awe.
               
                  Bacon doth more then Art, or elſe I faile.
            
            
               Emperour.
               Why, Vandermaſt, art thou ouercome?
               
                  Bacon diſpute with him, and try his skill;
            
            
               Bacon.
               I come not, Monarks, for to hold diſpute
               With ſuch a Nouice as is Vandermaſt;
               
               I came to haue your Royalties to dine
               
                  
With Fryer Bacon here in Brazen-noſe;
               And, for this Germane troubles but the place,
               And holds the Audience with a long ſuſpence,
               Ile ſend him to his Academie hence.
               Thou Hercules, whom Vandermaſt did raiſe,
               Tranſport the Germane vnto Haſpurge ſtraight,
               That he may learne by trauell 'gainſt the Springs,
               More ſecret doomes and Aphoriſmes of Art,
               Vaniſh the Tree, and thou away with him.
            
            Exit the spirit with Vandermaſt, and the Tree.
            
               Emperour.
               Why, Bacon, whither doeſt thou ſend him?
            
            
               Bacon.
               To Haſpurge, there your Highneſſe at returne,
               Shall finde the Germane in his Study ſafe.
            
            
               Henry.
               
                  Bacon, thou haſt honoured England with thy skill,
               And made faire Oxford famous by thine Art,
               I will be Engliſh Henry to thy ſelfe.
               But tell me, ſhall we dine with thee to day?
            
            
               Bacon.
               With me, my Lord; and while I fit my cheere,
               See where Prince Edward comes to welcome you:
               Gracious as the morning-ſtarre of heauen.
            
            Exit.
            
               Enter Edward, Lacie, Warren, Ermsby.
            
            
               Emperour.
               Is this Prince Edward, Henries Royall ſonne?
               How martiall is the figure of his face!
               Yet louely and beſet with Amorets.
            
            
               Henry.
               
                  Ned, where haſt thou beene?
            
            
               Edward.
               At Framingham, my Lord, to trye your Buckes,
               If they could ſcape the teiſers or the toile:
               But hearing of theſe Lordly Potentates
               Landed, and progreſt vp to Oxford towne,
               I poſted to giue entertaine to them,
               Cheefe to the Almaine Monarke, next to him,
               And ioynt with him, Caſtile, and Saxonie,
               
                  
Are welcome as they may be to the Engliſh Court.
               Thus for the men. But ſee, 
                     Ʋenus appeares,
               Or one that ouermatcheth 
                     Ʋenus in her ſhape,
               Sweet Ellinor, beauties high-ſwelling pride,
               Rich natures glorie, and her wealth at once:
               Faire of all faires, welcome to Albion,
               Welcome to me, and welcome to thine owne,
               If that thou dain'ſt the welcome from my ſelfe.
            
            
               Ellinor.
               Martiall Plantagenet, Henries high-minded ſonne,
               The marke that Ellinor did count her aime,
               I lik't thee 'fore I ſaw thee; now I loue,
               And ſo as in ſo ſhort time I may:
               Yet ſo, as time ſhall neuer breake that ſo,
               And therefore ſo accept of Ellinor.
               
            
            
               Caſtile.
               Feare not, my Lord, this couple will agree,
               If loue may creepe into their wanton eyes:
               And therefore, Edward, I accept thee here,
               Without ſuſpence, as my adopted ſonne.
            
            
               Henry.
               Let me that ioy in theſe conſorting greets,
               And glory in theſe honours done to Ned,
               
               Yeeld thankes for all theſe fauours to my ſonne,
               And reſt a true Plantagenet to all.
            
            Enter Miles with a cloth and trenchers, and ſalt.
            
               Miles.
               
                  Saluete omnes Reges, that gouerne your Greges, in
Saxony, and Spaine, in England, and in Almaine: for all this
frolicke rable muſt I couer the table, with trenchers, ſalt, and
cloth, and then looke for your broth.
            
            
               Emperour.
               What pleaſant fellow is this?
            
            
               Henry.
               Tis, my Lord, Doctor Bacons poore Scholler.
            
            
               Miles.
               My maſter hath made me ſewer of theſe great Lords,
and (God knowes) I am as ſeruiceable at a table, as a Sow is
vnder an Apple tree: 'tis no matter, their cheere ſhall not be
great, and therefore what skils where the ſalt ſtand before or
behinde?
            
            
               
               Caſtile.
               Theſe Schollers know more skill in Axiomes,
               How to vſe quips and ſleights of Sophiſtrie,
               Then for to couer courtly for a King.
            
            Enter Miles with a meſſe of pottage and broth, and
after him Bacon.
            
            
               Miles.
               Spill, ſir? why, doe you thinke I neuer carried
two-penny chop before in my life? By your leaue, Nobile decus,
for here comes Doctor Bacons pecus, being in his full age, to carry
a meſſe of pottage.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Lordlings, admire not if your cheere be this,
               For we muſt keepe our Academicke fare,
               No riot where Philoſophy doth raigne:
               And therefore, Henry, place theſe Potentates,
               And bid them fall vnto their frugall cates.
            
            
               Emp.
               Preſumptuous Fryer, what, ſcoft'ſt thou at a King?
               What, doeſt thou taunt vs with thy peazants fare,
               And giues vs cates fit for Country Swaines?
               
                  Henrie, proceeds this ieſt of thy conſent,
               To twit vs with a pittance of ſuch price?
               Tell me, and Fredericke will not grieue thee long.
            
            
               Henrie.
               By Henries honour and the Royall faith
               The Engliſh Monarke beareth to his friend,
               I knew not of the Fryers feeble fare,
               Nor am I pleas'd he entertaines you thus.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Content thee, Frederick, for I ſhewd thee cates,
               To let thee ſee how ſchollers vſe to feede:
               How little meate refines our Engliſh wits.
               
                  Miles take away, and let it be thy dinner.
            
            
               Miles.
               Mary ſir, I will, this day ſhall be a feſtiuall day with me:
               For I ſhall exceed in the higheſt degree.
            
            Exit Miles.
            
               Bacon.
               I tell thee, Monarke, all the Germane Peeres
               Could not afford thy entertainment ſuch,
               So Royall and ſo full of Maieſtie,
               
                  
As Bacon will preſent to Fredericke,
               
               The Baſeſt waiter that attends thy cups,
               Shall be in honours greater then thy ſelfe:
               And for thy cates rich Alexandria drugges,
               Fetcht by Carueils from Aegypts richeſt ſtraights:
               Found in the wealthy ſtrond of Affrica,
               Shall Royallize the table of my King,
               Wines richer then the Gyprian Courtiſan
               Quaft to Auguſtus Kingly countermatch,
               Shalbe carrowſt in Engliſh Henries feaſts:
               Candy ſhall yeeld the richeſt of her canes,
               Perſia downe her Volga by Canows,
               Send downe the ſecrets of her ſpicerie.
               The Africke Dates, mirabiles of Spaine,
               Conſerues, and Suckets from Tiberias,
               Cates from Iudea choiſer then the lampe
               That ſiered Rome with ſparkes of gluttony,
               Shall beautifie the boord for Fredericke,
               
               And therefore grudge not at a Fryers feaſt.
            
            Enter two Gentlemen, Lambert, and Serlsby,
with the Keeper.
            
               Lambert.
               Come frolicke, Keeper of our Lieges game,
               Whoſe table ſpred hath euer Veniſon,
               And lacks of wine to welcome paſſengers.
               Know I am in loue with iolly Margret,
               
               That ouer-ſhines our Damſels, as the Moone
               Darkneth the brighteſt ſparkles of the night,
               In Laxfield here my land and liuing lies,
               Ile make thy daughter ioynter of it all,
               So thou conſent to giue her to my wife,
               And I can ſpend fiue hundred markes a yeere.
            
            
               Serlsby.
               I am the Lands-lord Keeper of thy holds,
               By coppy all thy liuing lies in me.
               Laxfield did neuer ſee me raiſe my due,
               I will infeoffe Margret in all,
               
                  
So ſhe will take her to a luſty Squire.
               
                  
                     ••
                   
                  Keeper. Now courteous Gentles, if the Keepers girle
               Hath pleas'd the liking fancy of you both,
               And with her beauty hath ſubdued your thoughts,
               'Tis doubtfull to decide the queſtion.
               It ioyes me that ſuch men of great eſteeme,
               Should lay their liking on this baſe eſtate,
               And that her ſtate ſhould grow ſo fortunate,
               To be a wife to meaner men then you.
               But ſith ſuch Squires will ſtoope to Keepers fee,
               I will t'auoyd diſpleaſure of you both,
               Call Margret forth, and ſhe ſhall make her choiſe.
            
            Exit.
            
               Lambert.
               Content, Keeper, ſend her vnto vs.
               Why, Serlsby, is thy wife ſo lately dead?
               Are all thy loues ſo lightly paſſed ouer,
               As thou canſt wed before the yeere be out?
            
            
               Serlsby.
               I liue not, Lambert, to content the dead,
               Nor was I wedded but for life to her,
               The graue ends, and begins a married ſtate.
            
            Enter Margret.
            
               Lambert.
               
                  Peggie, the louely flowers of all townes,
               Suffolks faire Hellen, and rich Englands ſtar,
               Whoſe beauty tempered with her huſwifrie,
               Makes England talke of merry Freſingfield.
            
            
               Serlsby.
               I cannot tricke it vp with poeſies,
               Nor paint my paſſions with compariſons,
               Nor tell a tale of Phoebus and his loues,
               But this beleeue me, Laxfield here is mine,
               Of ancient rent ſeuen hundred pounds a yeere,
               And if thou canſt but loue a Country Squire,
               I will infeoffe thee, Margret, in all,
               I cannot ſlatter, trie me if thou pleaſe.
            
            
               Mar.
               Braue neighb'ring Squires, the ſtay of Suffolks clime,
               A Keepers daughter is too baſe in gree
               
                  
To match with men accounted of ſuch worth:
               But might I not diſpleaſe, I would reply.
               
                  Lambert. Say, Peggie, nought ſhall make vs diſcontent.
            
            
               Margret.
               Then Gentiles, note that loue hath little ſtay,
               Nor can the flames that 
                     Ʋenus ſets on fire,
               Be kindled but by fancies motion,
               Then pardon, Gentiles, if a maids reply
               Be doubtfull, while I haue debated with my ſelfe,
               Who, or of whom loue ſhall conſtraine me like.
            
            
               Serlsby.
               Let it be me, and truſt me, Margret,
               
               The meads inuironed with ſiluer ſtreames,
               Whoſe battling paſtures fatten all my flockes,
               Yeelding forth fleeces ſtapled with ſuch wooll,
               As Lempſter cannot yeeld more finer ſtuffe,
               And forty kine with faire and burniſht heads,
               With ſtrouting dugs that puggle to the ground,
               Shall ſerue thy dary if thou wed with me.
            
            
               Lambert.
               Let paſſe the Country wealth, as flocks and kine,
               And lands that waue with Ceres golden ſheaues,
               Filling my barnes with plenty of the fields:
               But, Peggie, if thou wed thy ſelfe to me,
               Thou ſhalt haue garments of imbrodred ſilke,
               Lawnes, and rich net-works for thy head attire,
               Coſtly ſhall be thy faire habilliments,
               If thou wilt be but Lamberts louing wife.
            
            
               Margret.
               Content you, Gentles, you haue proffered faire,
               And more then fits a Country maids degree:
               But giue me leaue to counſaile me a time,
               For fancie bloomes not at the firſt aſſault;
               Giue me but ten dayes reſpit, and I will reply,
               Which or to whom my ſelfe affectionates.
            
            
               Serlsby.
               
                  Lambert, I tell thee, thou art importunate,
               Such beauty fits not ſuch a baſe Eſquire:
               It is for Serlsby to haue Margret.
               
            
            
               Lamb.
               Thinkſt thou with wealth to ouer-reach me,
               
                  Serlsby? I ſcorne to brooke thy Country braues.
               
                  
I dare thee, Coward, to maintaine this wrong,
               At dint of Rapier ſingle in the field
            
            
               Serlsby.
               Ile anſwere Lambert what I haue auoucht.
               
                  Margret, farewell, another time ſhall ſerue.
            
            Exit Serlsby.
            
               Lambert.
               Ile follow. Peggie, farewell to thy ſelfe,
               Liſten how well Ile anſwer for thy loue.
            
            Exit Lambert.
            
               Margret.
               How Fortune tempers lucky happes with frownes,
               And wrongs me with the ſweets of my delight!
               Loue is my bliſſe, and loue is now my bale.
               Shall I be Hellen in my forward fates,
               As I am Hellen in my matchleſſe hue,
               And ſet rich Suffolke with my face a fire?
               If louely Lacy were but with his Peggie,
               
               The cloudy darkeneſſe of his bitter frowne
               Would checke the pride of theſe aſpiring Squires,
               Before the terme of ten dayes be expired,
               When as they looke for anſwer of their loues,
               My Lord will come to merry Freſingfield,
               And end their fancies, and their follies both;
               Till when, Peggie be blithe and of good cheere.
            
            Enter a Poaſt with a letter and a bag of gold.
            
               Poaſt.
               Faire louely Damſell, which way leads this path?
               How might I poaſt me vnto Freſingfield?
               Which footpath leadeth to the Keepers Lodge?
            
            
               Margret.
               Your way is ready, and this path is right,
               My ſelfe doe dwell hereby in Freſingfield;
               And if the Keeper be the man you ſeeke,
               I am his daughter: may I know the cauſe?
            
            
               Poaſt.
               Louely and once beloued of my Lord,
               No maruell if his eye was lodg'd ſo low,
               When brighter beauty is not in the heauens,
               The Lincolne Earle hath ſent you Letters here,
               And with them, iuſt an hundred pounds in gold.
               Sweet bonny wench, read them, and make reply.
            
            
               
               Margret.
               The ſcrowles that loue ſent Danaë,
               
               Wrapt in rich cloſures of fine burniſht gold,
               Were not more welcome then theſe lines to me.
               Tell me, whilſt that I doe vnrip the ſcales,
               Liues Lacy well, how fares my louely Lord?
            
            
               Poaſt.
               Well, if that wealth may make men to liue well.
            
            The letter, and Margret reades it.
            THe bloomes of the Almond tree grow in a night, &amp; vaniſh
in a morne, the flies Haemerae (faire Peggie) take life with
the Sunne, and die with the dew, fancy that ſlippeth in with a
gaze, goeth out with a winke; and too timely loues, haue euer
the ſhorteſt length. I write this as thy greife, and my folly,
who at Freſingfield lou'd that which time hath taught me to
be but meane dainties, eyes are diſſemblers, and fancie is but
queaſie, therefore know, Margret, I haue choſen a Spaniſh Lady
to be my wife, chiefe wayting-woman to the Princeſſe Ellinor,
a Lady faire, and no leſſe faire then thy ſelfe, honorable and
wealthy, in that I forſake thee, I leaue thee to thine owne liking,
and for thy dowry I haue ſent thee an hundred pounds, &amp;
euer aſſure thee of my fauour, which ſhall auaile thee and thine
much. Farewell. Not thine, nor his owne.
            Edward Lacy.
            
               Margret.
               Fond Atae, doomer of bad boaſting fates,
               That wraps proud Fortune in thy ſnaky locks,
               Didſt thou inchant my birth-day with ſuch ſtars,
               As lightned miſchiefe from their infancy?
               If heauens had vowd, if ſtars had made decree,
               To ſhew in me their froward influence,
               If Lacy had but lou'd, heauens, hell and all,
               Could not haue wrong'd the patience of my minde.
            
            
               Poaſt.
               It grieues me, Damſell, but the Earle is forſt
               To loue the Lady, by the Kings command.
            
            
               Margret.
               The wealth combinde within the Engliſh ſhelues,
               
                  
Europes Commander, nor the Engliſh King,
               Should not haue mou'd the loue of Peggie from her Lord.
            
            
               Poaſt.
               What anſwere ſhall I returne to my Lord?
            
            
               Margret.
               Firſt, for thou camſt from Lacy whom I lou'd,
               Ah, giue me leaue to ſigh at euery thought,
               Take thou, my friend, the hundred pound he ſent:
               For Margrets reſolution craues no dower;
               The world ſhall be to her as vanity,
               Wealth, traſh; loue, hate; pleaſure, de ſpaire:
               For I will ſtraight to ſtately Fremingham,
               And in the Abby there be ſhorne a Nun,
               And yeeld my loues and liberty to God.
               Fellow, I giue thee this, not for the newes,
               For thoſe be hatefull vnto Margret,
               
               But for th'art Lacees man, once Margrets loue.
            
            
               Poaſt.
               What I haue heard, what paſſions I haue ſeene,
               Ile make report of them vnto the Earle.
            
            Exit Poaſt.
            
               Margret.
               Say, that ſhe ioyes his fancies be at reſt,
               And prayes that his misfortunes may be hers.
            
            Exit.
            Enter Fryer Bacon drawing the courtaines with a white ſticke, a booke
in his hand, and a lampe lighted by him, and the brazen head, and
Miles, with weapons by him.
            
               Bacon.
               
                  Miles, where are you?
            
            
               Miles.
               Here, ſir.
            
            
               Bacon.
               How chance you tarry ſo long?
            
            
               Miles.
               Thinke you that the watching of the brazen head
craues no furniture? I warrant you, ſir, I haue ſo armed my ſelfe,
that if all your deuils doe come, I will not feare them an inch.
            
            
               Bacon.
               
                  Miles, thou knowſt that I haue diued into hell,
               And ſought the darkeſt palaces of the Fiends,
               That with my Magicke ſpels great Belzephon
               Hath left his lodge and kneeled at my cell,
               The rafters of the earth rent from the poles,
               And three-form'd L
                     ••
                  a hid her ſiluer lookes;
               
                  
Trembling vpon her concaue continent,
               When Bacon read vpon his Magicke booke,
               With ſeuen yeeres toſſing Nigromanticke charmes,
               Poring vpon darke Hecats principles,
               I haue fram'd out a monſtrous head of braſſe,
               That by th'inchanting forces of the Deuill,
               Shall tell out ſtrange and vncoth Aphoriſmes,
               And girt faire England with a wall of braſſe.
               
                  Bungay and I haue watcht theſe threeſcore dayes,
               And now our vitall ſpirits craue ſome reſt,
               If Argos liu'd and had his hundred eyes,
               They could not ouer-watch Phobeters night,
               Now Miles, in thee reſts Fryers Bacons weale,
               The honour and renowne of all his life,
               Hangs in the watching of this brazen-head;
               Therefore I charge thee by the immortall God,
               That holds the ſoules of men within his fiſt,
               This night thou watch; for ere the morning ſtarre
               Sends out his glorious gliſter on the North,
               The head will ſpeake; then (Miles) vpon thy life,
               Wake me: for then by Magicke Art Ile worke,
               To end my ſeuen yeeres taske with excellence,
               If that a winke but ſhut thy watchfull eye,
               Then farewell Bacons glory and his fame,
               Draw cloſe the curtaines, Miles, now for thy life,
               Be watchfull and
            
            Here he falleth aſleepe.
            
               Miles.
               So, I thought you would talke your ſelfe aſleepe anon,
and 'tis no maruell, for Bungay on the dayes, and hee on the
nights, haue watcht iuſt theſe ten and fifty dayes, now this is
the night, and 'tis my taske and no more. Now Ieſus bleſſe me,
what a goodly head it is, &amp; a noſe! You talke of nos autem glorificare;
but here's a noſe, that I warrant may be cal'd nos autem popelares
for the people of the pariſh. Well I am furniſhed with
weapons, now ſir, I will ſet me downe by a poſt, and make it as
good as a watch-man to wake me if I chance to ſlumber.
               
                  
I thought, goodman head, I would call you out of your moment
                        •
                     
                  
paſſion a God, I haue almoſt broke my pate: Vp, Milet, to your
taske, take your browne bill in your hand, heres ſome of your
maſters Hobgoblins abroad. With this, a great noise.
               
            
            The Head speakes.
            
               Head.
               Time is.
            
            
               Miles.
               Time is. Why, Maſter Brazen-head, haue you ſuch
a capitall noſe, and anſwer you with ſillables, Time is? is this
all my maſters cunning, to ſpend ſeuen yeeres ſtudie about
Time is? Well, ſir, it may be, we ſhall haue ſome orations of it
anon; well, Ile watch you as narrowly as euer you were watcht,
and Ile play with you as the Nightingale with the Slow-worme,
Ile ſet a pricke againſt my breſt; now reſt there,
Miles, Lord haue mercy vpon me, I haue almoſt kild my
ſelfe: vp, Miles, liſt how they rumble.
            
            
               Head.
               Time was.
            
            
               Miles.
               Well, Frier Bacon, you haue ſpent your ſeuen yeeres
ſtudy well, that can make your Head ſpeake but two words at
once, Time was: yea mary, time was when my Maſter was
a wiſe man, but that was before he began to make the Brazen-head.
You ſhall lye while you arſe ake, and your Head ſpeake
no better: well, I will watch and walke vp and downe, and be
a Peripatetian and a Philoſopher of Ariſtotles ſtampe. What,
a freſh noyſe? Take thy Piſtols in hand, Miles.
               
            
            Here the Head ſpeakes, and a lightning flaſheth forth and
a hand appeares that breaketh downe the
Head with a hammer.
            
               Head.
               Time is paſt.
            
            
               Miles.
               Maſter, maſter, vp, hell's broken looſe, your head
ſpeakes, and there's ſuch a thunder and lightning, that I warrant,
all Oxford is vp in armes; out of your bed, take a browne
bill in your hand, the latter day is come.
            
            
               
               Bacon.
               
                  Miles, I come. O paſſing warily watcht;
               
                  Bacon will make thee next himſelfe in loue.
               When ſpake the Head?
            
            
               Miles.
               When ſpake the Head? did not you ſay that he ſhould
tell ſtrange principles of Philoſophy? Why ſir, it ſpeakes but
two words at a time.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Why villaine, hath it ſpoken oft?
            
            
               Miles.
               Oft, I mary hath it thrice: but in all thoſe three times
it hath vttered but ſeuen words.
            
            
               Bacon.
               As how?
            
            
               Miles.
               Mary ſir, the firſ time he ſaid, Time is, as if Fabuis
Commentator ſhould haue pronounſt a ſentence: he ſaid, Time
was: and the third time with thunder and lightning, as in great
choler, he ſaid, Time is paſt.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Tis paſt indeed. A villaine, time is paſt:
               My life, my fame, my glory, all are paſt:
               
                  Bacon, the turrets of thy hope are ruin'd downe,
               Thy ſeuen yeeres ſtudy lieth in the duſt:
               Thy Brazen-head lies broken through a ſlaue
               That watcht, and would not when the Head did will.
               What ſaid the Head firſt?
            
            
               Miles.
               Euen, Time is.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Villaine, if thou hadſt cald to Bacon then,
               If thou hadſt watcht and wakte the ſleepy Fryer,
               The Brazen-head had vttered Aphoriſmes,
               And England had beene circled round with braſſe:
               But proud Aſtmeroth, ruler of the North,
               And Demegorgon, maſter of the Fates,
               Grudge that a mortall man ſhould doe ſo much.
               Hell trembled at my deepe commanding ſpels,
               Fiends frownd to ſee a man their ouer-match,
               
                  Bacon might boaſt more then a man might boaſt:
               But now the braues of Bacon haue an end,
               Europes conceit of Bacon hath an end:
               His ſeuen yeeres practice ſorteth to ill end:
               And villaine, ſith my glorie hath an end,
               
                  
I will appoint thee fatall to ſome end.
               Villaine, auoid, get thee from Bacons ſight:
               Vagrant, goe rome and range about the world,
               And periſh as a vagabond on earth.
            
            
               Miles.
               Why then, ſir, you forbid me your ſeruice.
            
            
               Bacon.
               My ſeruice, villaine? with a fatall curſe,
               That dire full plagues and miſchiefe fall on thee.
            
            
               Miles.
               Tis no matter, I am againſt you with the old prouerb,
The more the Foxe is curſt, the better he fares. God be with
you, ſir, Ile take but a booke in my hand, a wide ſleeued gowne
on my backe, and a crowned cap on my head, and ſee If I can
want promotion.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Some fiend or ghoſt haunt on thy weary ſteps,
               Vntill they doe tranſport thee quicke to hell:
               For Bacon ſhall haue neuer merry day,
               To loſe the ſame and honour of his Head.
            
            Exit.
            
               Enter Emperour, Caſtile, Henry, Ellinor, Edward,
Lacie, Raphe.
            
               Emper.
               Now louely Prince, the Prince of Albions wealth,
               How fares the Lady Ellinor and you?
               What, haue you courted and found Caſtile fit,
               To anſwere England in equiuolence?
               Wilt be a match twixt bonny Nell and thee?
            
            
               Edward.
               Should Paris enter in the courts of Greece,
               And not lye fettered in faire Hellens lookes?
               Or Phoebus ſcape thoſe piercing amorits,
               That Daphne glanced at his deitie?
               Can Edward then ſit by a flame and freeze,
               Whoſe heat puts Hellen and faire Daphne downe?
               Now Monarks, aske the Lady if we gree
            
            
               Henry.
               What, Madam, hath my ſonne found grace or no?
            
            
               Ellinor.
               Seeing my Lord his louely counterfeit,
               And hearing how his minde and ſhape agreed,
               I come not, troopt with all this warlike traine,
               
                  
Doubting of loue, but ſo affectionate,
               As Edward hath in England what he wonne in Spaine.
            
            
               Caſtile.
               A match, my Lord, theſe wantons needs muſt loue:
               Men muſt haue wiues, and women muſt be wed,
               Let's haſte the day to honour vp the rites.
            
            
               Raphe.
               Sirra Harry, ſhall Ned marry Nell?
               
            
            
               Henry.
               I, Raphe, how then?
            
            
               Raphe.
               Mary Harry, follow my counſell, ſend for Fryer Bacon
to marry them, for heele ſo coniure him and her with his
Nigromancy, that they ſhall loue together like Pigge &amp; Lambe
whileſt they liue.
            
            
               Caſtile.
               But hearſt thou, Raphe, art thou content to haue Ellinor
to thy Lady?
            
            
               Raphe.
               I, ſo ſhe will promiſe me two things.
            
            
               Caſtile.
               Whats that, Raphe?
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               That ſhe will neuer ſcold with Ned, nor ſight with
me, Sirra Harry, I haue put her downe with a thing vnpoſſible.
            
            
               Henry.
               Whats that, Raphe?
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               Why Harry, didſt thou euer ſee that a woman could
both hold her tongue and her hands? no: but when egge-pyes
grow on Apple-trees, then will thy gray Mare proue a Bag-piper.
            
            
               Emperour.
               What ſayes the Lord of Caſtile and the Earle of
Lincolne, that they are in ſuch earneſt and ſecret talke?
            
            
               Caſtile.
               I ſtand, my Lord, amazed at his talke?
               How he diſcourſeth of the conſtancy
               Of one ſurnam'd for beauties excellence,
               The faire maid of Freſingfield.
            
            
               Henry.
               Tis true, my Lord, tis wondrous for to heare,
               Her beautie paſſing Marſes Paramour:
               Her virgins right as rich as 
                     Ʋeſtas was,
               
                  Lacy and Ned haue told me miracles.
            
            
               Caſtile.
               What ſayes Lord Lacy? ſhall ſhe be his wife?
            
            
               Lacy.
               Or elſe Lord Lacy is vnfit to liue.
               May it pleaſe your Highneſſe giue me leaue to poaſt
               To Freſingfield, Ile fetch the bonny girle,
               
                  
And proue in true apparance at the Court,
               What I haue vouched often with my tongue.
            
            
               Henry.
               
                  Lacy, goe to the Quiry of my Stable,
               And take ſuch Courſers as ſhall fit thy turne,
               Hie thee to Freſingfield, and bring home the Laſſe,
               And, for her fame flies through the Engliſh coaſt,
               If it may pleaſe the Lady Ellinor,
               
               One day ſhall match your Excellence and her.
            
            
               Ellinor.
               We Caſtile Ladies are not very coy,
               Your Highneſſe may command a greater boone:
               And glad were I to grace the Lincolne Earle
               With being partner of his marriage day.
            
            
               Edward.
               Gramercy, Nell, for I doe loue the Lord,
               As he that's ſecond to my ſelfe in loue.
            
            
               Raphe.
               You loue her? Madam Nell, neuer beleeue him you,
though he ſweares he loues you.
            
            
               Ellinor.
               Why Raphe?
               
            
            
               Raphe.
               Why, his loue is like vnto a Tapſters glaſſe that is
broken with euery tutch; for he loued the faire maid of Freſingfield
once out of all hoe; nay Ned, neuer winke vpon me,
I care not, I.
            
            
               Hen.
               
                  Raphe tels all, you ſhall haue a good Secretary of him.
               But, Lacy, haſte thee poaſt to Freſingfield:
               For ere thou haſt fitted all things for her ſtate,
               The ſolemne marriage day will be at hand.
            
            
               Lacy.
               I goe, my Lord.
               Exit Lacy.
            
            
               Emperour.
               How ſhall we paſſe this day, my Lord?
            
            
               Henry.
               To horſe, my Lord, the day is paſſing faire,
               Weele flie the Partridge, or goe rouze the Deere.
               Follow, my Lords, you ſhall not want for ſport.
            
            Exeunt.
            Enter Fryer Bacon with Fryer Bungay, to his Cell.
            
               Bungay.
               What meanes the Fryer that frolickt it of late,
               To ſit as melancholy in his Cell,
               
                  
As if he had neither loſt nor wonne to day?
            
            
               Bacon.
               Ah Bungay, my brazen-head is ſpoil'd,
               My glory gone, my ſeuen yeeres ſtudy loſt:
               The fame of Bacon bruted through the world,
               Shall end and periſh with this deepe diſgrace.
            
            
               Bungay.
               
                  Bacon hath built foundation on his fame,
               So ſurely on the wings of true report,
               With acting ſtrange and vncoth miracles,
               As this cannot infringe what he deſerues.
            
            
               Bacon.
               
                  Bungay, ſit downe, for by proſpectiue skill,
               I find this day ſhall fall out ominous,
               Some deadly act ſhall betide me ere I ſleepe:
               But what and wherein little can I geſſe.
            
            
               Bungay.
               My minde is heauy whatſoere ſhall hap.
            
            Enter two Schollers, ſonnes to Lambert and Serlsby.
Knocke.
            
               Bacon.
               Who's that knockes?
            
            
               Bungay.
               Two Schollers that deſire to ſpeake with you.
            
            
               Bac.
               Bid thē come in. Now, my youths, what would you haue?
            
            
               1. Scholler.
               Sir, we are Suffolke men &amp; neighbouring friends,
               Our fathers in their Countries luſty Squires,
               Their lands adioyne, in Crack field mine doth dwell,
               And his in Laxfield, we are Colledge mates,
               Sworne brothers; as our fathers liue as friends.
            
            
               Bacon.
               To what end is all this?
            
            
               2. Scholler.
               Hearing your worſhip kept within your Cell
               A glaſſe proſpectiue wherein men might ſee,
               What ſo their thoughts or hearts deſire could wiſh,
               We come to know how that our fathers fare.
            
            
               Bacon.
               My glaſſe is free for euery honeſt man.
               Sit downe, and you ſhall ſee ere long,
               How or in what ſtate your friendly fathers liue,
               Meane while tell me your names.
            
            
               Lambert.
               Mine Lambert.
               
            
            
               3. Scholler.
               And mine Serlsby.
               
            
            
               
               Bacon.
               
                  Bungay, I ſmell there will be a Tragedy.
            
            Enter Lambert and Serlsby, with Rapiers and Daggers.
            
            
               Lambert.
               
                  Serlsby, thou haſt kept thine houre like a man,
               Th'art worthy of the title of a Squire:
               That durſt for proofe of thy affection,
               And for thy miſtreſſe fauour prize thy blood;
               Thou knowſt what words did paſſe at Freſingfield,
               Such ſhameleſſe braues as manhood cannot brooke:
               I, for I skorne to beare ſuch pearcing taunts,
               Prepare thee, Serlsby, one of vs will die.
            
            
               Serlsby.
               Thou ſeeſt I ſingle thee the field,
               And what I ſpake, Ile maintaine with my ſword:
               Stand on thy guard, I cannot ſcold it out.
               And if thou kill me, thinke I haue a ſonne,
               That liues in Oxford in the Brodgates hall,
               Who will reuenge his fathers blood with blood.
            
            
               Lambert.
               And Serlsby, I haue there a luſty boy,
               That dares at weapon buckle with thy ſonne,
               And liues in Brodgates too as well as thine;
               But draw thy Rapier: for weele haue a bout.
            
            
               Bacon.
               Now luſty yonkers, looke within the glaſſe,
               And tell me if you can diſcerne your ſires.
            
            
               1. Schol.
               
                  Serlsby, tis hard, thy father offers wrong,
               To combat with my father in the field.
            
            
               2. Schol.
               
                  Lambert, thou lieſt, my fathers is the abuſe,
               And thou ſhalt finde it, if my father haue harme.
            
            
               Bungay.
               How goes it, ſirs?
            
            
               1. Schol.
               Our fathers are in combat hard by Freſingfield.
            
            
               Bacon,
               Sit ſtill, my friends, and ſee the euent.
            
            
               Lambert.
               Why ſtandſt thou, Serlsby, doubtſt thou of thy life?
               A veny, man, faire Margret craues ſo much.
            
            
               Serlsby.
               Then this for her.
            
            
               1. Scholler.
               Ah, well thruſt.
            
            
               2. Scholler.
               But marke the ward.
            
            
               
               Lambert.
               Oh, I am ſlaine.
            
            
               Serlsby.
               And I, Lord haue mercy on me.
            
            
               1. Scholler.
               My father ſlaine, Serlsby ward that.
            
            The two Schollers ſtab one another.
            
               2. Scholler.
               And ſo is mine, Lambert, Ile quite thee well.
            
            
               Bungay.
               O ſtrange ſtratagem!
            
            
               Bacon.
               See, Fryer, where the fathers both lye dead.
               
                  Bacon, thy magicke doth effect this maſſacre:
               This glaſſe proſpectiue worketh many woes,
               And therefore ſeeing theſe luſty Brutes,
               Theſe friendly youths did periſh by thine Art.
               End all thy magicke and thine Art at once:
               The poniard that did end the fatall liues,
               Shall breake the cauſe efficiat of their woes,
               So fade the glaſſe, and end with it the ſhowes,
               That Nigromancy did infuſe the chriſtall with.
            
            He breakes the glaſſe.
            
               Bung.
               What meanes learned Bacon thus to breake his glaſſe?
            
            
               Bacon.
               I tell thee, Bungay, it repeuts me ſore,
               That euer Bacon meddled in this Art,
               The houres I haue ſpent in Piromanticke ſpels,
               The fearefull toſſing in the lateſt night,
               Of papers full of Nigromanticke charmes,
               Coniuring and adiuring Deuils and Fiends,
               With Stole and Albe, and ſtrange Pentaganon,
               The wreſting of the holy Name of God,
               
                  As Sother, Eloim, and Adonai,
               Alpha, Manoth, and Tetragrammaton,
               With praying to the fiue-fold powers of heauen,
               Are inſtances that Bacon muſt be damn'd,
               For vſing Deuils to counteruaile his God.
               
                  
Yet, Bacon, cheere thee, drowne not in deſpaire,
               Sinnes haue their ſalues, repentance can doe much:
               Thinke mercy ſits where Iuſtice holds her ſeate,
               And from thoſe wounds thoſe bloody Iewes did pierce▪
               
               Which by thy magicke oft did bleed afreſh,
               From thence for thee the dew of mercy drops,
               To waſh the wrath of hie Iehouahs ire,
               And make thee as a new-borne babe from ſinne.
               
                  Bungay, Ile ſpend the remnant of my life
               In pure deuotion, praying to my God,
               That he would ſaue what Bacon vainly loſt.
            
            Exit.
            Enter Margret in Nuns apparell, Keeper, her father, and
their friend.
            
               Keeper.
               
                  Margret, be not ſo head-ſtrong in theſe vowes.
               Oh bury not ſuch beauty in a Cell:
               That England hath held famous for the hue.
               Thy fathers haire like to the ſiluer bloomes:
               That beautifies the ſhrubs of Affrica
               Shall fall before the dated time of death,
               Thus to forgoe his louely Margret.
               
            
            
               Margret.
               A father, when the harmony of heauen
               Soundeth the meaſures of a liuely faith:
               The vaine Illuſions of this flattering world,
               Seeme odious to the thoughts of Margret.
               
               I loued once, Lord Lacy was my loue,
               And now I hate my ſelfe for that I lou'd,
               And doated more on him than on my God:
               For this I ſcourge my ſelfe with ſharpe repents;
               But now the touch of ſuch a ſpiring ſinnes
               Tels me, all loue is luſt, but loue of heauens:
               That beauty vſde for loue is vanity,
               The world containes nought but alluring baites:
               Pride, flattery, and inconſtant thoughts,
               To ſhun the pricks of death, I leaue the world,
               
                  
And vow to meditate on heauenly bliſſe,
               To liue in Fremingham a holy Nunne,
               Holy and pure in conſcience and in deed:
               And for to wiſh all maides to learne of me,
               To ſeeke heauens ioy before earths vanity.
            
            
               Friend.
               And will you then, Margret, be ſhorne a Nunne, and
ſo leaue vs all?
            
            
               Margret.
               Now farewell world, the engin of all woe,
               Farewell to friends and father, welcome Chriſt:
               Adieu to dainty robes, this baſe attire
               Better befits an humble minde to God,
               Then all the ſhew of rich habilliments.
               Loue, oh Loue, and with fond Loue farewell,
               Sweet Lacy, whom I loued once ſo deare,
               Euer be well, but neuer in my thoughts,
               Leſt I offend to thinke on Lacies loue:
               But euen to that as to the reſt, farewell.
            
            Enter Lacy, Warrain, Ermsby, booted and spurd.
            
               Lacy.
               Come on my wags, we're neere the Keepers Lodge,
               Here haue I oft walkt in the watry Meades,
               And chatted with my louely Margret.
               
            
            
               Warraine.
               Sirra Ned, is not this the Keeper?
            
            
               Lacy.
               Tis the ſame,
            
            
               Ermsby.
               The old lecher hath gotten holy mutton to him,
a Nunne, my Lord.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Keeper, how fareſt thou holla man, what cheere,
               How doth Peggie thy daughter and my loue?
            
            
               Keeper.
               Ah, good my Lord! oh, woe is me for Pegge,
               
               See where ſhe ſtands clad in her Nunnes attire,
               Ready for to be ſhorne in Fremigham:
               She leaues the world, becauſe ſhe left your loue,
               Oh good my Lord, perſwade her if you can.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Why how now Margret, what a malecontent,
               A Nunne? what holy father taught you this,
               To taske your ſelfe to ſuch a tedious life,
               
                  
As dye a maid? 'twere iniury to me,
               To ſmother vp ſuch beauty in a Cell.
            
            
               Margret.
               Lord Lacy, thinking of thy forme miſſe,
               How fond the prime of wanton yeeres were ſpent
               In loue, Oh fie vpon that fond conceite,
               Whoſe hap and eſſence hangeth in the eye,
               I leaue both loue and loues content at once,
               Betaking me to him that is true loue,
               And leauing all the world for loue of him.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Whence, Peggie, comes this Metamorphoſis?
               What, ſhorne a Nunne, and I haue from the Court
               Poaſted with courſers to conuay thee hence,
               To Windſore, where our marriage ſhall be kept?
               Thy wedding robes are in the Taylors hands.
               Come, Peggie, leaue theſe peremptory vowes.
            
            
               Margret.
               Did not my Lord reſigne his intereſt,
               And make diuorce twixt Margret and him?
            
            
               Lacy.
               'Twas but to trye ſweet Peggies conſtancy:
               But will faire Margret leaue her loue and Lord?
            
            
               Margret.
               Is not heauens ioy before earths fading bliſſe?
               And life aboue ſweeter then life in loue?
            
            
               Lacy.
               Why then, Margret will be ſhorne a Nun.
            
            
               Marg.
               
                  Margret hath made a vow, which may not be reuokt.
            
            
               Warraine.
               We cannot ſtay, my Lord, and if ſhe be ſo ſtrict,
               Our leiſure graunts vs not to woo afreſh.
            
            
               Ermsby.
               Chooſe you, faire Damſell, yet the choiſe is yours,
               Either a ſolemne Nunnery, or the Court,
               God, or Lord Lacy, which contents you beſt,
               To be a Nun, or elſe Lord Lacies wife?
            
            
               Lacy.
               A good motion. Peggie, your anſwere muſt be ſhort.
            
            
               Marg.
               The fleſh is frayle, my Lord doth know it well,
               That when he comes with his inchanting face,
               Whatſoere betide, I cannot ſay him nay.
               Off goes the habit of a maidens heart,
               And ſeeing fortune will, faire Fremingham,
               And all the ſhew of holy Nuns, farewell,
               
                  
                  Lacy for me, if he will be my Lord.
            
            
               Lacy.
               
                  Peggie, thy Lord, thy loue, thy husband,
               Truſt me, by truth of Knighthood, that the King
               Stayes for to marry matchleſſe Ellinor,
               
               Vntill I bring thee richly to the Court,
               That one day may both marry her and thee.
               How ſaiſt thou Keeper, art thou glad of this?
            
            
               Keeper.
               As if the Engliſh King had giuen
               The Parke and Deere of Freſingfield to me.
            
            
               Ermesby.
               I pray thee my Lord of Suſſex, why art thou in a
browne ſtudy?
            
            
               Warraine.
               To ſee the nature of women, that be they neuer ſo
neere God, yet they loue to dye in a mans armes.
            
            
               Lacy.
               What haue you fit for breakefaſt? we haue hied and
poaſted all this night to Freſingfield.
            
            
               Margret.
               Butter and cheeſe, and humbles of a Deere,
               Such as poore Keepers haue within their Lodge.
            
            
               Lacy.
               And not a bottle of wine?
            
            
               Margret.
               Weele find one for my Lord.
            
            
               Lacy.
               Come, Suſſex, let's in, wee ſhall haue more, for ſhee
ſpeakes leaſt, to hold her promiſe ſure.
            
            Exeunt.
            Enter a Deuill to ſeeke Miles.
            
            
               Deuill.
               How reſtleſſe are the ghoſts of helliſh ſprites,
               When euery Charmer with his Magicke ſpels
               Cals vs from nine-fold trenched Phlegiton,
               To ſcud and ouer-ſcoure the earth in poaſt,
               Vpon the ſpeedy wings of ſwifteſt winds?
               Now Bacon hath raiſd me from the darkeſt deepe,
               To ſearch about the world for Miles his man,
               For Miles, and to torment his lazy bones,
               For careleſſe watching of his brazen-head.
               See where he comes: Oh he is mine.
            
            Enter Miles with a gowne and a corner cap.
            
               Miles.
               A Scholler, quoth you, mary ſir, I would I had been

made a bottle-maker, when I was made a ſcholler; for I can
get neither to be a Deacon, Reader, nor Schoole-maſter; no,
not the Clarke of a Pariſh; ſome call me dunce: another ſaith,
my head is as full of Latine, as an eg's full of oate-meale: thus
I am tormented, that the Deuill and Frier Bacon haunts me.
Good Lord, here's one of my maſters Deuils▪ Ile goe ſpeake to
him: what maſter Plutus, how cheere you?
            
            
               Deuill.
               Dooſt thou know me?
            
            
               Miles.
               Know you, ſir, why are not you one of my maſters
Deuils, that were wont to come to my maſter Doctor Bacon, at
Brazen-noſe?
            
            
               Deuill.
               Yes mary am I.
            
            
               Miles.
               Good Lord, M. Plutus, I haue ſeene you a thouſand
times at my maſters, and yet I had neuer the manners to make
you drinke; but ſir, I am glad to ſee how conformable you are
to the ſtate; I warrant you, he's as yeomanly a man, as you ſhall
ſee, marke you maſters, here's a plain honeſt man, without welt
or gard; but I pray you ſir, doe you come lately from hell?
            
            
               Deuill.
               I mary, how then?
            
            
               Miles.
               Faith, tis a place I haue deſired long to ſee, haue you
not good tippling houſes there? may not a man haue a luſty fire
there, a pot of good Ale, a paire of cardes, a ſwinging peece of
chalke, and a browne toaſt that will clap a white waſtcoat on a
cup of good drinke?
            
            
               Deuill.
               All this you may haue there.
            
            
               Miles.
               You are for me, friend, and I am for you: but I pray
you, may I not haue an office there?
            
            
               Deuill.
               Yes, a thouſand: what wouldſt thou be?
            
            
               Miles.
               By my troth, ſir, in a place, where I may profit my
ſelfe. I know hell is a hot place, and men are maruellous dry,
and much drinke is ſpent there; I would be a Tapſter.
            
            
               Deuill.
               Thou ſhalt,
            
            
               Miles.
               There's nothing lets me from going with you, but
that tis a long iourney, and I haue neuer a horſe.
            
            
               Deuill.
               Thou ſhalt ride on my backe.
            
            
               Miles.
               Now ſurely here's a courteous deuill, that for to pleaſure

his friend, will not ſticke to make a Iade of himſelfe: but
I pray you goodman friend, let me moue a queſtion to you.
            
            
               Deuill.
               What's that?
            
            
               Miles.
               I pray you, whether is your pace a trot or an amble?
            
            
               Deuill.
               An amble.
            
            
               Miles.
               Tis well, but take heed it be not a trot,
               But tis no matter, Ile preuent it.
            
            
               Deuill.
               What doeſt?
            
            
               Miles.
               Mary, friend, I put on my ſpurs: for if I find your
pace either a trot, or elſe vneaſie, Ile put you to a falſe gallop,
Ile make you feele the benefit of my ſpurs.
            
            
               Deuill.
               Get vp vpon my backe.
            
            
               Miles.
               Oh Lord, here's euen a goodly maruell, when a man
rides to hell on the Deuils backe.
            
            Exeunt roaring.
            Enter the Emperour with a pointleſſe ſword, next, the King of Caſtile,
carrying a ſword with a point, Lacy carrying the Globe, Edward
Warraine carrying a rod of gold with a Doue on it, Ermsby with
a Crowne and Scepter, the Queene with the faire maide of Freſing field
on her left hand, Henry, Bacon, with other Lords attending.
            
               Edward.
               Great Potentates, earths miracles for ſtate,
               Thinke that Prince Edward humbles at your feet,
               And for theſe fauours on his martiall ſword,
               He vowes perpetuall homage to your ſelues,
               Yeelding theſe honours vnto Ellinour.
               
            
            
               Henrie.
               Gramercies, Lordings, old Plantagenet,
               
               That rules and ſwayes the Albion Diademe,
               With teares diſcouers theſe conceiued ioyes,
               And vowes requitall, if his men at armes,
               The wealth of England, or due honours done
               To Ellinor, may quite his Fauorites.
               But all this while what ſay you to the Dames,
               That ſhine like to the chriſtall lampes of heauen?
            
            
               Emperour.
               If but a third were added to theſe two,
               
                  
They did ſurpaſſe thoſe gorgeous Images,
               That gloried Ida with rich beauties wealth.
            
            
               Margret.
               Tis I, my Lords, who humbly on my knee,
               Muſt yeeld her horiſons to mighty Ioue,
               For lifting vp his handmaide to this ſtate,
               Brought from her homely cottage to the Court,
               And graſte with Kings, Princes and Emperours,
               To whom (next to the noble Lincolne Earle)
               I vow obedience, and ſuch humble loue,
               As may a handmaid to ſuch mighty men.
            
            
               Ellinor.
               Thou martiall man, that weares the Almaine Crown,
               And you the Weſterne Potentates of might,
               The Albian Princeſſe
                     •
                   Engliſh Edwards wife,
               Proud that the louely ſtar of Freſingfield,
               Faire Margret, Counteſſe to the Lincolne Earle,
               Attends on Ellinour: gramercies, Lord, for her▪
               
               Tis I giue thankes for Margret to you all,
               And reſt for her due bounden to your ſelues.
            
            
               Henrie.
               Seeing the marriage is ſolemnized,
               Let's march in triumph to the Royall feaſt.
               But why ſtands Fryer Bacon here ſo mute?
            
            
               Bacon.
               Repentant for the follies of my youth,
               That Magicks ſecret myſteries miſled,
               And ioyfull that this Royall marriage
               Portends ſuch bliſſe vnto this matchleſſe Realme.
            
            
               Hen.
               Why, Bacon, what ſtrange euent ſhall happē to this Lād?
               Or what ſhall grow from Edward and his Queene?
            
            
               Bacon.
               I find by deepe praeſcience of mine Art,
               Which once I tempred in my ſecret Cell,
               That here where Brute did build his Troynouant,
               From forth the Royall Garden of a King,
               Shall flouriſh out ſo rich and faire a bud,
               Whoſe brightneſſe ſhall deface proud Phoebus flowre,
               And ouer-ſhadow Albion with her leaues.
               Till then, Mars ſhall be maſter of the field,
               But then the ſtormy threats of wars ſhall ceaſe,
               
                  
The horſe ſhall ſtampe as careleſſe of the pike,
               Drums ſhall be turn'd to timbrels of delight,
               With wealthy fauours, plenty ſhall enrich
               The ſtrond that gladded wandring 
                     〈◊〉
                   to ſee,
               And peace from heauen ſhall harbour in theſe leaues,
               That gorgeous beautifies this matchleſſe flower,
               
                  Apollos Hellitropian then ſhall ſtoope,
               And 
                     Ʋenus hyacinth ſhall vaile her top,
               
                  Iuno ſhall ſhut her Gilliflowers vp,
               And Pallas Bay ſhall baſh her brighteſt greene▪
               
               
                  Ceres carnation in confort with thoſe,
               Shall ſtoope and wonder at Diana's Roſe.
            
            
               Henrie.
               This Propheſie is myſticall,
               But glorious Commanders of Europa's loue,
               That makes faire England like that wealthy Ile,
               Circled with Gihen▪ and firſt Euphrates,
               In Royallizing Henries Albion,
               With preſence of your prin
                     •
                  ely mightineſſe,
               Let's march, the tables all are ſpred,
               And viandes ſuch as Englands wealth affords,
               Are ready ſet to furniſh out the bords,
               You ſhall haue welcome, mighty Potentates,
               It reſts to furniſh vp this Royall Feaſt,
               Only your hearts be frolicke: for the time
               Craues that we taſte of nought but iouyſance.
               Thus glories England ouer all the Weſt.
            
            Exeunt omnes.
            Omne tulit punctum qui miſcuit vtile dulci.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

