
   
      
         
            Greenes carde of fancie Wherein the folly of those carpet knights is deciphered, which guiding their course by the compass of Cupid, either dash their ship against most dangerous rocks, or else attaine the haven with pain and perill. Wherein also is described in the person of Gwydonius a cruell combate between nature and necessitie. By Robert Green, Master of Art, in Cambridge.
            Gwydonius
            Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
         
         
            
               1608
            
         
         Approx. 316 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02124
            STC 12264
            ESTC S105823
            99841549
            99841549
            6139
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02124)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6139)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1205:07)
         
         
            
               
                  Greenes carde of fancie Wherein the folly of those carpet knights is deciphered, which guiding their course by the compass of Cupid, either dash their ship against most dangerous rocks, or else attaine the haven with pain and perill. Wherein also is described in the person of Gwydonius a cruell combate between nature and necessitie. By Robert Green, Master of Art, in Cambridge.
                  Gwydonius
                  Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
                  Labé, Louise, 1526?-1566. Debat de folie et d'amour.
               
               [152] p.   
               
                  Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes] for Mathewe Lownes, and are to be solde at his shop in Paules-churchyard,
                  At London :
                  1608.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-T⁴.
                  Includes Louise Labé's "The debate betweene follie and loue, translated out of French [from 'Le debat de folie et d'amour'] by Robert Greene", beginning on K3.
                  Running title reads: The carde of fancie.
                  Originally published in 1584 as: Gwydonius.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            GREENES CARDE OF FANCIE.
            Wherein the Folly of thoſe carpet Knights is deciphered, which guiding their courſe by the compaſs of Cupid, either daſh their ſhip againſt moſt dangerous Rocks, or elſe attaine the haven with pain and perill.
            Wherein alſo is deſcribed in the perſon of Gwydonius a cruell Combate between Nature and Neceſſitie.
            
               By ROBERT GREEN, Maſter of Art, in Cambridge.
            
            At London Printed by H. L. for Mathewe Lownes, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Paules-churchyard 1608.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONOrable, Edward de Ʋere Earle of Oxenford, Vicount Bulbeck, Lord of Eſcales and Badleſmire, and Lord great Chamberlain of England: Robert Green wi
               ſheth long life with increaſe of Honour.
            
            
               THat poor Caſtilian Frontino (Right Honourable) being a very vnskilfull Painter, preſented Alphonſus, the Prince of Aragon, with a moſt imperfect picture, which the king thankfully accepted, not that hee liked the work, but that he loved the art. The paltering Poet Cherillus, dedicated his duncing Poems to that mightie Monarch Alexander, ſaying that he knew aſſuredly if Alexander would not accept them in that they were not pithie, yet he would not vtterly reject them, in that they had a ſhewe of Poetrie. Caeſar oft times praiſed his ſouldiers for their wil, although they wanted skil: and Cicero as well commended ſtammering Lentulus for his paynfull induſtrie, as learned Laelius for his paſſing eloquence. Which conſidered (although wiſdom did wil me not to

ſtraine further then my ſleeue would ſtretch) I thought good to preſent this imperfect Pamphlet to your Honours protection; hoping your Lordſhip will deigne to accept the matter in that it ſeemeth to be proſe, though ſomething vnſauorie for want of skill, and take my well meaning for an excuſe of my boldneſſe, in that my poore will is not in the wane, whatſoever this imperfect work do want. The Emperour Traian was never without ſuters, becauſe ſo curteouſly hee would heare every complaint. The Lapidaries continually frequēted the Court of Adobr indinus, becauſe it was his chief ſtudie to ſearch out the nature of ſtones. All that courted Atlanta were hunters, and none ſued to Sapho but Poets. Wherſoeuer Mecaenas lodgeth, thither no doubt will ſchollers flocke. And your Honour being a worthie fauourer and foſterer of Learning, hath forced manie through your exquiſite vertue, to offer the firſt fruits of their ſtudie at the ſhrine of your Lordſhips curteſie. But though they have waded farre and found mines, and I gadded abroad to get nothing but Mites, yet this I aſſure my ſelf, that they neuer preſented vnto your honor their treaſure with a more willing minde, than I do this ſimple traſh: which I hope your Lord hip wil ſo accept. Reſting therfore vppon your Honours wonted clemencie, I commit your Lordſhip to the Almightie. *⁎*
            
            
               Your Lordſhips moſt dutifully to command,
ROBERT GREENE.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE GENTLEMEN Readers, health.
            
               
                  
                     •
                  
               AN blowing vpon an Oten pipe a little homely Muſick, and hearing no man diſpraiſe his ſmall cunning, began both to plaie ſo loud, and ſo long, that they were more wearie in hearing his muſick, than he in ſhewing his skill; till at laſt to clawe him and excuſe themſelues, they ſaid his pipe was out of tune: So Gentlemen, becauſe I haue before time raſhly reacht above my pitch, and yet your curteſie ſuch as no man hath accuſed me, I haue once again aduentured vppon your patience; but (I doubt) ſo farre, as to be rid of my follie, you will at the laſt ſay, as Auguſtus ſayde to the Grecian, that gave him oft times many rude verſes: Thou haſt need (quoth hee) reward mee well; for I take more paines to read thy works, than thou to write them. But yet willing to abide this quip, becauſe I may counteruaile it with your former curteſie, I put my ſelfe to your patience, and commit you to the Almighty. Farewell. *⁎*
            
            
               Robert Greene.
            
         
         
            
            AD LECTOREM in laudem Authoris.
            PVllulaten ſtirpi ſimilis ſpecioſa propago
            Aureoluſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                novo revireſcit ramus amoris
            Vere: (tuo verèiam VERE dicandus honori:)
            Iſta ſalus Iuueni, Comiti ſit gloria noſſe,
            Accepiſſe decus: Comites vbi paſſibus aequis
            Ales amor virtuſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſagax decurrere nôrunt.
            Ventilat iſte faces, reſtinguit at illa furentes
            Taedas. Nec taedet Pueriſic taedia caeci
            Fallere, qui caecis conuoluit viſcera flammis.
            Ergo refer grates qui deuitare cupiſti
            Spumoſos Veneris fluctus, ſcopuloſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                minaces
            Qui fragilem tumidis cymbam merſiſſe procellis
            Poſſent. Hàc iter eſt, hàc dirige, tutior ibis.
            
               Richardus Portingtonus.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE CARDE OF FANCIE.
            
               THere dwelled in the City of Mitylene, a certaine Duke called Clerophontes, who through his proweſſe in all martial exploits wared ſo proud and tyrannous, vſing ſuch mercileſſe crueltie to his forraigne enemies, and ſuch moodleſſe rigor to his natiue Citizens, that it was doubtfull whether hée was more feared of his foes for his crueltie, or hated of his friends for his tyrannie: yet as the worſt weed ſpringeth vp more brauely then the wholſommeſt hearbe, and as the crookedſt trée is commonly laden with moſt fruite, ſo this rigorous duke was ſo fauoured and foſtered vp by fortune, his eſtate being ſo eſtabliſhed with honor, &amp; ſo beautified with wealth, ſo deckt with the Diadem of dignity, and endued with fortunate proſperity, hauing in warres ſuch happie ſucceſſe againſt his foes, and in peace ſuch dutifull renerence of his friends, (although more for feare than fauour) as he ſéemed to want nothing that either fortune or the fates coulde allow him, if one onely ſore which bred his ſorrowe, coulde haue béen ſalued. But this griefe ſo galled his conſcience, and this curſed care ſo cumbred his minde, that his happineſſe was greatly ſurcharged with heauineſſe, to ſée the cauſe of his care could by no meanes be cured. For this Clerophontes, was indued with two children, the one a daughter named Lewcippa, and the other a ſonne called Gwydonius: this Lewcippa, was ſo perfect in the complexion

of her bodie, and ſo pure in the conſtitution of her minde, ſo adorned with outward beautie, and endued with inward bountie, ſo poliſhed with rare vertues and exquiſite qualities, as ſhée ſéemed a ſéemly Venus for her beauty, and a ſecond Veſta, for her virginite: yea, Nature and the gods had ſo beuntifully beſtowed their gifts vpon her, as ſame herſelfe was doubtful whether ſhe ſhould make greater report of her excellent vertue, or exquiſite beautie. But his ſonne Gwydonius, was ſo contrarie to his ſiſter Lewcippa, (though not in the ſtate of his bodie, yet in the ſtaie of his mind) as it made al men maruaile how two ſuch contrarie ſtemmes could ſpring out of the ſelf ſame ſtock: His perſonage indéed was ſo comely, his feature ſo wel framed, each limb ſo perfectly couched, his face ſo fair, and his countenance ſo amiable, as he ſéemed a heauenly creature in a mortall carcaſſe.
            But his minde was ſo blemiſhed with deteſtable qualities, and ſo ſpotted with the ſtaine of voluptuouſneſſe, that hee was not ſomuch to bee commended for the proportion of his bodie, as to bee condemned for the imperfection of his minde. Hee was ſo endued with vanitie, and ſo imbrued with vice, ſo nurſed vp in wantonneſſe, and ſo nulled vp in wilfulneſſe, ſo careleſſe to obſerue his fathers commaund, and ſo retchleſſe to regard his counſell, that neither the dread of Gods wrath, nor the feare of his fathers diſpleaſure, coulde driue him to deſiſt from his deteſtable kinde of liuing. Nay, there was no fact ſo filchy, which hée would not commit, no miſchiefe ſo monſtrous, which hée would not enterprſſe: no danger ſo deſperate, which hée woulde not aduenture: no perill ſo fearefull, which hée would not performe: nor no action ſo diueliſh, which hée would not execute. So immodeſt in his manners, ſo rude in his geſtures, yea and ſo prodigall in his expences, as mines of golde were not able to maintaine ſuch witleſſe prodigalitie. This loathſom life of Gwydonius, was ſuch a cutting coraſiue to his Fathers carefull conſcience,

and ſuch a hapleſſe clog to his heauic hart, that no ioy could make him enioy any ioy, no mirth could make him merry, no proſperity could make him pleaſant: but abandoning all delight, &amp; auoiding all companie, he ſpent his doleful daies in dumps and dolors, which he vttered in theſe words.
            NOw (quoth hée) I proue by experience, the ſaying of Sophocles to be true, that the man which hath many children ſhall neuer liue without ſome mirth, nor die without ſome ſorrow: for if they be vertuous, he ſhal haue cauſe whereof to reioyce, if vicious, wherefore to be ſad: which ſaying I trie performed in myſelfe: for as I haue one child which delights me with her vertue, ſo I haue another that deſpights me with his vanity, as the one by dutie brings me ioy, ſo the other by diſobedience bréeds my anoy: yea as the one is a comfort to my minde, ſo the other is a fretting coraſiue to my heart: for what griefe is there more griping, what pain more pinching, what croſſe more comberſome, what plagne more pernitious, yea, what trouble can torment me worle, then to ſée my ſonne, mine heir, the inheritor of my Dukedom, which ſhould be the pillex of my parentage, to conſume his time in royſting and ryot, in ſpending and ſpoiling, in ſwearing and ſwaſhing, &amp; in following wilfully the furie of his own frantike fancie. Alas, moſt miſerable and lamentable caſe, would to God the deſtinies had decreed his death in the ſwadling cloutes, or that the fates had preſcribed his death in his infancie. Oh that the daie of his birth had béen the daie of his buriall, or that by ſome ſiniſter ſtorme of fortune he had béen ſtifled on his mothers knées, ſo that his vntimely death might haue preuented my enſuing ſorrowes, and his future calamities: for I ſie that the young frie will alwaies proue olde frogs, that the crooked twig will proue a crabbed trée, that the ſower bud will neuer be ſwéet bloſſome, how that which is bred in the bone will not eaſily out of the fleſh, that he which is careleſſe in youth, will be leſſe carefull in age, that where in prime of

yéeres vice raigneth, there in ripe age vanity remaineth. Why Clerophontes, if thou ſéeſt the ſore, why doeſt thou not apply the ſalue? and if thou doeſt perceiue the miſchief, why dooſt not preuent it with medicine? take away the cauſe &amp; the effect faileth: if Gwydonius be the cauſe of thy ruth, cut him off betimes, leaſt hee bring thee to ruine: better hadſt thou want a Son then neuer want ſorrow. Perhaps thou wilt ſuffer him ſo long, til he fall ſick of the Father, and then hée wil not only ſéek thy lands and liuing, but life and all, if thou preuent not his purpoſe: yea, and after thy death he will be through his laſciuious life the ouer throw of thy houſe, the conſumer of thy Dukedome, the wracke of thy Commonweale, and the very man that ſhall bring the ſtate of Mitylene to miſchief &amp; miſerie. Sith then thy Son is ſuch a ſink of ſorrowes, in whoſe life lies hid a loathſome maſſe of wretched miſhaps, cut him off as a graceleſſe graft, vnworthy to grow out of ſuch a ſtock. Alas Clerophontes, ſhalt thou be ſo vnnaturall as to ſeek the ſpoile of thine owne childe, wilt thou bee more ſauage then the brute Beaſtes in committing ſuch crueltie? no, alas, the leaſt miſfortune of our children dooth ſo mooue vs, that as the Spider féeleth if her web bee prickt but with the point of a pinne, ſo if they bée toucht but with the leaſt trouble, we féele the paines thereof with pricking grief to pinch vs. Why hath not Nature then cauſed loue to aſcend as well as to deſcend, and placed as dutifull obedience in the childe, as louing affection in the father: and with that he fetcht ſuch a deep ſigh, that it was a ſigne of the extreame ſorrowe he conceiued for his ſonnes witleſſe folly. But as hée was readie againe to enter into his dolefull diſcourſe, to aggranate his griefe the more, and increaſe his care, certaine complaints were brought him by ſundry Citizens, of the outragious behauiour of his Sonne Gwydonius, which béeing attentiuely heard he in great choller called for his ſonne, againſt whom hée thundred out ſuch threatning reproaches, laying before his face the miſery that would enſue of ſuch reckleſſe miſchiefes,

and promiſing that if hee directed not his courſe by a new compaſſe, and leuelled his life by a new line, hee would not onely repay his folly with the penalty of the law, but alſo by conſent of his commons, diſinherite him of his Dukedome: that Gwydonius, greatly incenſed with the ſeuere cenſure of his father, broyling with furious rage, ſturdily burſt forth into theſe ſtubborne tearmes.
            SIr, (quoth hée) if Terence his Menedemus were aliue, and heard theſe your fond and fantaſticall reaſons, hee would as readily condemn you of crabbedneſſe, as he accuſed Chremes of curriſhneſſe: for as he by too much auſteritie procured his ſonnes miſhap, ſo you by too much ſeueritie ſéeke to bréed my miſfortune. You olde men moſt iniuſtly, or rather iniuriouſly, meaſure our ſtayleſſe moode by your ſtayed minds, our yoong yeares by your hoary haires, our floriſhing youth by your withered age, thinking to direct our doings by your doatings, our wils by your wits, our youthfull fancies by your aged affections, &amp; to quench our fierie flames by your dead coales and cinders: yea, ſuppoſing that the Leueret ſhould be as skilfull in making of a head, as the olde Hare, that the yoong Cubs ſhould aſſoon tapiſh, as the old Fox, that the yoong Frie ſhould as well auoid the net as the old Fiſh, and that the yoong wantons ſhould be as warie as the olde wiſards. But this ſir, is to make fire froſt, to chaunge heate to colde, mirth to mourning, ſinging to ſadneſſe, pleaſure to paine, and to tye the Ape and the Bear in one tedder. Sith then young ſtemmes will not bee ſet on a withered ſtocke, that the yoong twig lieth not vnder ye old trée, that the toyiſh conceits of youth are vnfit for the teſtie cogitations of age: I mean for your ſatiſfaction and my ſolace, to depart fram the Court, and to ſpend my dayes in trauell.
            
               Clerophontes no ſooner heard this determination of his ſonne Gwydonius, but his ſorrowe was halfe ſalued, and his care almoſt cured, thinking that by trauell hée

ſhould eyther end his life, or amend his lewdneſſe, &amp; therefore both heartned and haſtened his ſonne in this his new courſe, leaſt delay might bréed danger, or time by ſome toy cauſe him turn his tippet, furniſhing &amp; finiſhing all things neceſſarie for his ſonnes iournie: who readie to goe (more willing to trauell, than his father to intreate him) had this friendly farewell giuen him by Clerophontes.
            
            SOnne (quoth hee) there is no greater doubt which doth more déeply diſtreſſe the minde of a young man, then to determine with himſelfe what courſe of life is beſt to take: for there is ſuch a confuſed Chaos of contrarie conceits in yong wits, that whiles they look for that they cannot like, they are loſt in ſuch an endleſſe labyrinth, as neither choice nor chance can drawe them out to their wiſhed deſires: for ſo many vaines ſo manie vanities: if vertue draweth one way, vice driueth another way: as profit perſwades them, ſo pleaſure prouokes them: as wit weigheth, will wreſteth, if friendes counſell them to take this, fancie forceth them to chooſe that: ſo that deſire ſo long hanges in doubt, as either they chooſe none, or elſe chance on the worſt. But in my opinion, the fitteſt kind of life for a young gentleman to take (who as yet hath not ſubdued the youthfull conceits of fancie, nor made a conqueſt of his wil by wit) is to ſpend his time in trauell, whearin hee ſhall finde both pleaſure and profite: yea, and buy that by experience, which otherwiſe with all the treaſure in the world he cannot purchaſe. For what changeth vanity to vertue, ſtayleſſe wit to ſtayed wiſedome, fond fantaſies to firme affections, but trauell: what repreſſeth the rage of youth, and redreſſeth the witleſſe furie of wanton yéeres, but trauell: what turneth a ſecure life to a carefull liuing, what maketh the fooliſh wiſe, yea, what increaſeth wit and augmenteth skill, but trauell? inſomuch that the fame Vlyſſes wonne, was not by the tenne yéeres he late at Troy, but by the time he ſpent in trauell. But there is nothing Gwydonius, ſo precious,

which in ſome reſpect is not perilous, nor nothing ſo pleaſant which may not be painfull: The fineſt Golde hath his droſſe, the pureſt wine his lees, the braueſt Roſe his prickles, each ſweete hath his ſower, each ioy his annoy, each weale his woe, and cuerie delight his danger.
            So trauaile, Gwydonius, is a courſe of life verie pleaſant, and yet very perillous, wherein thou maieſt practice vertue if thou take heed, or purchaſe diſcredit if thou béeſt careleſſe: where thou maieſt reape renowne if thou béeſt vertuous, and gaint reproach if thou be vicious: whereout do ſpring wiſedome and folly, fréedome and bondage, treaſure and traſh, fame and diſcredit, honour and ſhame, according to the diſpoſition of him which either vſeth it to his profit, or abuſeth it to his diſcemmoditie. Sith then thou ſhalt beare ſaile in ſuch perillous Straightes, take heede leſt thou daſh thy Ship againſt moſt dangerous Rockes. It is a ſaying Gwydonius, not ſo common as true, that he which will heare the Syrens ſing, muſt with Vlyſles, tye himſelfe to the maſt of the ſhip, leaſt happily he be drowned. Whoſo means to be a ſuter to Circes, muſt take a Preſeruatine, vnleſſe he will be inchanted.
            He that will fiſh for the Torpedo, muſt annoint his hand with the oyls of Nemiphar, leaſt he be charmed, and whoſo meaneth to enter combat with vanitie, muſt firſt ſurelie defence himſelfe with the target of vertue, vnleſſe he meane to be a captiue to care or calamitie. I ſpeake this Gwydonius by experience, which afterward thou ſhalt know by proofe: for in trauell thou ſhalt finde ſuch ſubtill Syrens, as will indanger thée, ſuch ſorcering Circes, as will inchaunt thée, ſuch poyſoned Torpedos, as will not only charme thy hand, but thy heart, if by my experience and other mens perils thou learne not to be ware. Firſt Gwydonius, be not too ſumptuous, leaſt thou ſéem prodigall, nor to couetous, leaſt they count thee a niggard: for by ſpending in exceſſe, thou ſhalt be thought a vaine glorious foole, &amp; by too much ſparing, a couetous pelant. Be not wilfull in thy doings,

that they count thée not witleſſe; nor too raſh, that they think thée not deuoid of reaſon: be not too merry, that they count thée not immodeſt; nor too ſober, leaſt they call thée ſullen, but ſhew thy ſelf to be an old man for thy grauitie, and a yoong youth for thy actiuitie: ſo ſhall all men haue cauſe to praiſe thee for thy manners, and commend thee for thy modeſty. Be not too curious Gwydonius, yt they déem thée not proud, nor too curteous, leaſt they call thée counterfaite. Be a friend to all, and a foe to none, and yet truſt not without tryall, nor commit anie ſecret to a friendly ſtranger, leaſt in too much truſt lie treaſon, &amp; thou be forced by repentance to crie Peccaui. The ſwéeteſt Muſke is ſower to be taſted, the fineſt Pilles moſt bitter to be chewed, and the flattering friend moſt tickle being tryed: then beware leaſt faire wordes makes fooles fayne, and glozing ſpéeches cauſe Had I wiſt to come too late. Lend not, Gwydonius, a liſtning ear to the alarums of Loue, nor yield not thy fréedome to the aſſault of luſt, be not dazeled with the beames of ſading beautie, nor daunted with the deſire of eeuery delicate damſell: for in time ſuch bliſſe will proue but bane, and ſuch delightfull ioy, but deſpightfull annoie. Luſt Gwydonins will prooue an enemy to thy purſe, and a foe to thy perſon, a canker to thy minde, and a coraſiue to thy conſcience, a weakner of thy wit, a moleſter of thy minde, a beſofter of thy ſenſes, and finally, a mortall bane to all thy body; ſo that thou ſhalt finde pleaſure the pathway to perdition, &amp; luſting Loue the load ſtone to ruth and ruine. Séek not then Gwydonius, gréedily to deuoure that bait, wherein thou knoweſt a hurtfull hooke to bee hidden: frequent not that pleaſure which will turne ſo thy poyſon, nor couet that companie which will conuert to thy confuſion, leaſt through ſuch folly thou haue cauſe in time to be ſad, and I to beſorrowfull. Now Gwydonius that thou haſt heard the aduertiſment of a louing Father, follow my aduiſe as a dutiful childe: and the more to bind thée to perform my former precepts, that this my counſaile

be not drowned in obliuion, I giue thée this ring of golde wherein is written this ſentence, Praemonitus, Praemunitus. A poeſie pretie for the words, and pithie for the matter, ſhort to be rehearſed, and long to be related; inferring this ſenſe, that he which is forewarned by friendly counſaile of imminent dangers, is forearmed againſt all future miſhap and calamitie, ſo that he may by forewarning prenent perils if it bee poſſible, or if by ſiniſter fortune hee cannot eſehew them, yet hée may beare the Croſſe with more patience and leſſe griefe. Keepe this King Gwydonius carefully, that thou mayeſt ſhew thy ſelfe to reſpect thy owne caſe, and regard my counſaile: and in ſo dooing thou ſhalt pleaſe me, and pleaſure thy ſelfe.
            
               CLerophontes, hauing thus ended his diſcourſe, embracing his ſonne with fatherly affection, and giuing him his bleſſing, went ſecretly into his Chamber, the more to couer his griefe which hée conceiued for his ſonnes departure: vnwilling his ſonne ſhould perceiue by his ſorrow how vnfeinedly he both liked and loued him.
            VVEll: Gwydonius, hauing taken his leaue of his Father, furniſhed both with counſaile and coine, with aduiſe of wiſedome and ayde of wealth, paſſed on his iourney very ſolemnly, vntill hee was paſt the boundes of his Fathers Dukedome: and then as merry as might be, he trauelled by the ſpace of ſeauen weekes without anie reſidence, vntill he came to a Cittie called Barutta, where (whether hee were delighted with the ſituation of the place, or deluded with the perſwaſion of ſome Paraſiticall perſons) hée ſecurely ſettled himſelfe by the ſpace of a whole yeare: in which time he ſo careleſly floated in the ſeas of voluptuouſneſſe, and ſo reckleſly raunged in licentious and laweleſſe libertie, thinking himſelfe a peaſant if he were not prodigall, counting nothing comely, if not coſtly, nothing ſeemely if not ſumptuogs, vſing ſuch

monſtrons exceſſe in all his actions, that the Citizens of Barutta noted him for a myrrour of immoderate life, and a very patterne of witleſſe prodigalitie: yea, his exceſſiue expences daily ſo mercaſed, that mines of gold had not bin ſufficient to maintaine his pompons magnificence; inſomuch, that the Magiſtrate of Barutta. not only maruelled where hee had coine to counteruaile his expenſes, but alſo began to ſuſpect him eyther for ſome skilfull Alcumiſt, or that he had ſome large commiſſion to take vp thoſe purles that fell into lapſe, for want of ſufficient defence: whervpon béeing called before the Magiſtrates and ſtrictly examined what trade hee vſed, why he ſtayed ſo long in the Citie, and how hee was able to maintaine ſo princely a port as he carried: Gwydonius, vnwilling to haue them priuie to his parentage, began to coine a ſcuſe, yet not ſo cunningly but hee was trapt in his own talk, and ſo caſt in priſon, where he lay clogged with care and deuoid of comfort, hauing not ſo much as one truſtie friend, amongſt all thoſe trothleſſe flatterers which in proſperitie had ſo frequented his companie: the ingratitude of whom ſo perplered his moleſted mind, as ſurcharged with ſorrow, he burſt forth into theſe tearms.
            ALas (quoth hee) now haue I bought that by hapleſſe experience, which if I had béen wiſe, I might haue got by happy counſell: Now am I taught that with pain and peril, which if ſelfeloue had not beſotted my ſenſes, I might haue learned with profit and pleaſure, that in the faireſt Sandes is moſt fickleneſſe, out of the braueſt Bloſſome moſt commonly ſpringeth the worſt fruite, that the fineſt floure ſeldome hath the beſt ſmell, that the moſt gliſtering ſtone hath oftentimes the leaſt vertue, and that in the greateſt ſhew of good will, lyes oft times the ſmalleſt effect of friendſhip, in moſt flatterie leaſt faith, in the faireſt face the falſeſt heart, in the ſmootheſt tale the ſmalleſt truth, &amp; in the ſwéeteſt gloſes, moſt lower ingratitude: Yea, I ſée

now (quoth he) yt in truſt lies treaſon, that fair words make fools fain, and that the ſtate of theſe fained friends are like to the Marie-gold, which as long as the Sunne ſhineth openeth her leaues, but with the leaſt cloud beginneth to cloſe, like the Violets in America, which in ſommer yéeld an odoriferous ſmell, and in winter a moſt peſtilent fauour: ſo theſe Paraſites in proſperitie profeſſe moſt, but in aduerſitie performe leaſt: when Fortune fauoureth, they laugh, when ſhee frowneth, they lowre; at eueryfull ſea they flouriſh, but at euery dead Neape they fade: like to the fiſh Palerna, which being perfectly white in the calme, yet turneth paſſing black at euery ſtorm: to the trées in yt deſarts of Affrica, that flouriſh but while the South winde bleweth, or to the Celedonie ſtone, which retaineth his vertue no longer than it is rubbed with gold.
            Sith then Gwydonius (quoth hée) thou findes ſuch falſehood in friendſhip, and ſuch faithleſſe déedes in ſuch paynted ſpéeches, ſhake off theſe fawning curs with the flag of defiance, and from henceforth trie ere thou truſt I, but (quoth he) it is too late to apply the ſalue when the ſore is incurable, to crie alarum when the Citie is ouerrunne, to ſéeke for couert when the ſtorme is paſt, and to take héede of ſuch flattering mates, when alreadie thou art deceiued by ſuch fawning merchaunts: now thou wilt crie Cave when thy coin is conſumed, and beware when thy wealth is wracked: when thou haſt nothing wherof to take charge, thou wilt be charie, and when follie hath alreadie giuen thee a mate. thou wilt by wiſedome ſéeke to auoide the check: but now thou tryeſt it true that thy father foretolde thee, that ſo long thou wouldeſt be careleſſe, as at laſt repentance would pull thee by the ſléeue, and then Had I wiſt would come too late.
            Well Gwydonius, ſith that which is once paſt can neuer be recalled againe, if thou haſt by folly made a fault, ſéek by wiſedome to make amendes, and heap not care vppon care, nor adde not griefe to ſorrowe, by theſe pitifull complaintes,

but chéere vp thy ſelfe and take heart at graſſe, for the ende of woe is the beginning of weale, and after miſerie alwaies inſueth moſt happie felicity.
            
               Gwydonius hauing thus dolorouſly diſcourſed with himſelfe, remained not aboue ten dayes in priſon, but that the Senate taking pittie of his caſe, and ſéeing no accuſations were inferred againſt him, ſet him frée from his purgatory, and gaue him good counſel, that hereafter hée ſhould beware by ſuch witleſſe prodigalitie to incurre ſuch ſuſpicion. Theſeus neuer triumphed more after he had eſcaped the danger of the perillous Labyrinth, than poore Gwydonius did when he was ſet frée from this pernitious Limbo: now the bitterneſſe of bondage made his fréedome ſéeme farre more ſweete, and his danger ſo happily eſcaped, cauſed his deliuery ſéem farre more delightfull. Yet he conceiued ſuch diſcurteſie againſt the Citizens, for repaying his liberal good will with ſuch loathſome ingratitude, that the next morning he departed frō 
               Barutta, not ſtored with too much mony for moleſting his minde, nor ouercharged with coine for cumbering his cōſcience with too much care: but hauing remaining of all his treaſure onely that ring which his father gaue him, trauelled very ſolemnely toward Alexandria.
            
            Where at that time ther raigned a certaine Duke named Orlanio, who was ſo famous and fortunate, for the peaceable gouernment of his Dukedome, adminiſtering iuſtice with ſuch ſinceritie, and yet tempering the extreamitie of the law with ſuch lenitie, as hee both gayned the good will of ſtrangers in hearing his vertue, and wonne the harts of his ſubiects in féeling his bounty, counting him vnworthy to hear the name of a Soueraigne, which knew not according to deſert, both to cheriſh and chaſtiſe his ſubiects.
            Fortune and the fates willing to place him in the palace of earthly proſperity, endowed him with two children,

the one a ſonne named Therſandro, and the other a daughter called Caſtania, either of them ſo adorned with the gifts of Nature, and be antifled with good nurture, as it was hard to knowe whether beautie or vertue helde the ſupremacie. But leaſt by this happie eſtate Orlanio ſhould be too much puffed vp with proſperitie, Fortune ſparing him the mate, yet gaue him a ſlender checke, to warne him from ſecuritie: for before his daughter came to the age of fouretéene yeares, his wife dyed, leauing him not more ſorrowfull for the loſſe of her whom he moſt intirely loued, than carefull for the well bringing vp of her whom hee ſo dearely liked: Knowing that as his Court was a ſchoole of vertue to ſuch as bridled their mindes with diſcretion, ſo it was a nurſs of vice to thoſe tender yeares that meaſured their willes with witleſſe affection, eſteeming libertie as perillous to the ſtaie of youth, as precious to the ſtate of age, and that nothing ſo ſoone allureth the minde of a young maide to vanity, and to paſſe her youth without feare in ſecurity. Feared with the conſideration of theſe premiſſes, to auoyde the inconueniences that might happen by ſuffering Caſtania to leade her life in lawleſſe libertie, hee thought it beſt to chooſe out ſome vertuous Ladie to kéepe her companie, who might direct her courſe by ſo true a compaſſe, and leuel her life by ſo right a line, that although her young years were verie apt to be intangled in the ſnares of vanity, yet by her counſaile and companie, ſhee might ſteadily tread her ſteps in the trace of vertue: and none he could find more fit for the purpoſe, than a certain olde widow, called Madame Melytta, honoured for her vertuous life throughout all Alexandria, who being ſent for to the Court, he ſaluted on this manner.
            MAdame Melytta (quoth hée) the report of thy honeſt conditions, and the renoume of thy vertuons qualities are ſuch, as thereby thou haſt not onelie purchaſed great praiſe, but wonne great credit throughout all

the Countrie. In ſomuch that, incenſed by this thy ſingular commendation, I haue ſelected thée as the onely woman to whome I meane to commit my chiefeſt treaſure: I mean, Melytta, my daughter Caſtania, to whom I will haue thee bee both a companion and a counſellour, haping thou wilt take ſuch care to traine her vp in vertue, &amp; trace her quite from vice, to winne her minde to honeſtie, and weane her quite from vanitie, that ſhe in her ripe yeares ſhall haue cauſe to thanke thee for thy paines, and I occaſian to regard thée as a friend, and reward thee for thy diligence.
            FIrſt Melytta, ſee that ſhe leade her life both charily and chaſtly. Let her not haue her owne will, leaſt ſhee proue too wilfull: or too much libertie, leaſt ſhee become too light. The palme tree preſſed downe, groweth notwithſtanding but too faſt. The heath Spattania, though troden on, groweth verie tall: and youth although ſtrictly reſtrained, will proue but too ſtubburne.
            The veſſell ſauoureth alwayes of that licour wherwith it was firſt ſeaſoned and the minde retaineth thoſe qualities in age wherein it was trained vp in youth. The tender twig is ſonner broken than the ſtrong branch, the yong ſtem more brittle than the old ſtocke, the weake bramble ſhaken with euerie wind, and the wanering will of youth toſſed with euerie paſte of vanitie, readie to bee wracked in the waues of wantonneſſe, vnleſſe it be cunningly guided by ſome wiſe and warie Pilot.
            Then Melytta, ſith youth is ſo eaſily entrapped with the alluring traine of fooliſh delights, and ſo ſoone entangled with the traſh of pernitions pleaſure, ſuffer not my daughter to paſſe her time in idleneſſe, leaſt happily being taken at diſcouert, ſhee become a careleſſe captiue to ſecuritie: for whan the minde once floateth in the ſurging ſeas of idle conceits, then the puffes of voluptuous pleaſures and the ſtifling ſtormes of vnbrideled fancy, the raging

blaſtes of alluring beautie, and the ſturdie gale of glozing vanitie, ſo ſhake the Shippe of reckleſſe youth, that it is dayly in doubt to ſuffer moſt dangerous ſhipwracke. But let her ſpend her time in reading ſuch auncient authors as may ſharpen her wit by their pithie ſayings, and learne her wiſedome by their perfect ſentences. For where nature is vicious, by learning it is amended, and where it is vertuous by skill it is augmented. The ſtone of ſecret vertue is of greater price if it be brauely poliſhed, the gold though neuer ſo pure of it ſelfe hath the better colour if it be burniſhed, and the minde though neuer ſo vertuous, is more noble if it be enriched with the gifts of learning. And Melytta, for recreation ſake, let her vſe ſuch honeſt ſports as may drine away dumps, leaſt ſhe be too penſiue, and free her minde from fooliſh conceits, that ſhee bee not too wanton.
            Thus (Madame) as you haue heard my fatherly aduiſe, ſo I pray you giue my daughter the like friendly aduertiſement; that hereafter ſhe may haue both cauſe to reuerence me, and to reward thee.
            
               Melytta hauing heard with attentiue héed the minde of Orlanio, conceiued ſuch ioy in this new charge, and ſuch delight in this happy chance, as with cheerefull countenance ſhe repayed him this anſwere.
            SIr (quoth ſhe) although in the largeſt ſeas are the foreſt tempeſts in the broadeſt waies moſt boiſterous windes, in the higheſt hilles, moſt dangerous happes, and in the greateſt charge the greateſt care: yet the dutie which I owe you as my Soueraigne, and the loue I beare you as a ſubiect, the care I haue to pleaſe you as my Prince, and to pleaſure you as a Potentate, the truſt you repoſe in my trueth without ſufficient tryall, the confidence you put in my conſcience without ſure proofe, the curteſie your Grace doth ſhewe me without anie deſert, haue ſo inflamed the forepaſſed fire of dutifull affection, and ſo incouraged

me to encounter your Graces curteſie, with willing conſtancie, that there is no hap ſo hard which I woulde not hazard, no danger ſo deſperate which I woulde not aduenture, no burthen ſo heauie which I would not beare, no perill ſo huge which I would not paſſe, no charge ſo great, which both willingly and warily I woulde not performe. For, ſince it hath pleaſed your Grace to vouchſafe ſo much of my ſimple calling, as to aſſigne me for a companion for your daughter Caſtania, I will take ſuch care in the charie performance of my charge, and indenour with ſuch diligence both to counſaile &amp; comfort Caſtania, as your Grace ſhall perceiue my dutie in pleaſing you, and my diligence in pleaſuring her.
            THe Duke hearing the friendly &amp; faithfull proteſtation of the good Lady Melytta, tolde her that although it were great trouble for one of her age to frame her ſelf as a companiō to ſuch yong youth, and that ſome care belonged to ſuch a charge, yet hee would ſo counternalle her painful labour with princely liberalitie, that both ſhe and all Alexandria ſhould haue cauſe to ſpeak of his bountie.
            
               MElytta, thanking the Duke for ſuch vndeſerued curteſie, ſetting her houſhold affaires in good order, repayred to the Court as ſpéedily as might be. But leauing her with Caſtania, again to Gwydonius: who now being arriued in Alexandria, pinched with pouerty, &amp; diſtreſſed with want, hauing no coine left wherewith to counteruaile his expences, thought it his beſt courſe, if it were poſſible, to compaſſe the Dukes ſeruice: repairing therfore to the court hée had not ſtaied there thrée dayes before he found fit oportunitie to offer his ſeruice to Orlanio, whom very dutifully he ſaluted in this manner.
            THe report (right worthie Prince) of your incomparable curteſie and pearleſſe magnanimity is ſo blazed abroad

throughout all Countries, by the golden trumpe of Fame, that your Grace is not more loued of your ſubiects which taſt of your liberall bountie, than honoured of ſtrangers, which only heare of your princely vertue. Inſomuch that it hath forced me to leaue my natiue ſoile, my parents, kindred, and familiar friends, and pilgrimlike to paſſe into a ſtrange Country, to try that by experience héer, which I haue heard by report at home. For it is not (right worthy Sir) the ſtate of your Country that hath altured me (for I deeme Bohemia, wherof I am, no leſſe pleaſant than Alexandria) neither hath want of liuing or hope of gain intiſed me, for I am by birth a Gentleman, and iſſued of ſuch parents as are able with ſufficient patrimonie to maintaine my eſtate: but the deſire, not onely to ſée, but alſo to learne ſuch rare curteſie and vertuous qualities as fame hath reported to be put in practice in your Court, is the onely occaſion of this my iourny. Now if in recompenee of this mytrauaile, it ſhal pleaſe your Grace to vouchſafe of my ſeruice, I ſhall think my ſelf fully ſatiſfied, and my pains ſufficiently requited.
            
               Orlanio, hearing this dutifull diſcourſe of Gwydonius, marking his manners, and muſing at his modeſtie, noting both his excellent courteſie, and exquiſite beautie, was ſo inflamed with friendly affection toward this yoong youth, that not only hee accepted of his ſeruice, but alſo preferred him as a companion to his ſonne Therſandro, promiſing that ſince hee had left his Country and Parents for this cauſe, he would ſo counteruaile his dutifull deſert with fauour and friendſhip, as he ſhould neuer haue cauſe to accuſe him of ingratitude.
            
               Gwydonius repaying heartie thankes to the Duke for his vndeſerued curteſie, being now brought from woe to weale, from deſpaire to hope, from bale to bliſſe, from care to ſecuritie, from want to wealth, yea, from helliſh miſery, to heauenly proſperitie, behaued himſelfe ſo wiſely and warily with ſuch curteſie in conuerſation, and modeſtie in

manners, that in ſhort time hee not onely purchaſed credit and countenance with Orlanio, but was moſt intirely liked and loued of Therſando.
            
            Now, there remained in the Court a young knight, called Signior Valericus, who by chance caſting his glancing eies on the glittering beautie of Caſtania, was ſo fettered in the ſnare of fancie, and ſo entangled with the trap of affection, ſo perplered in the Labyrinth of pinching loue, and ſo inchanted with the charme of Venus Sorcerie, that as the Elephant reioiceth greatly at the ſight of a Roſe, as the Bird Halciones delighteth to view the feathers of ye 
               Phoenix, and as nothing better contenteth a Ro-Buck, than to gaze at a red cloth; ſo there was no obiect that could allurc the wauering eyes of Valericus, as the ſurpaſſing beautie of Caſtania: yea, his only bliſſe, pleaſure, ioy, &amp; delight, was in féeding his fancy with ſtaring on yt Heauenly face of his goddeſſe. But alas her beautie bred his bane, her lookes his loſſe, her ſight is ſorrow, her exquiſite perfections, his extreame paſſions, that as the Ape by ſéeing the Snaile is infected, as the Leopard falleth in a traunce at the ſight of the Locuſt, as the Cockatrice dyeth with beholding the Chriſolito, ſo poore Valericus was pinched to the heart with viewing her comely countenance, was griped with galling griefe, and tortured with inſupportable torments, by gazing vpon the gallant beauty of ſo gorgeous a dame: yea, he ſo framed in his fancie the forme of her face, and ſo imprinted in his hart the perfection of her perſon, that the remembrance therof would ſuffer him to take no reſt, but he paſſed the day in dolour, the night in ſorrow, no minute without mourning, no houre without heauineſſe, that falling into penſiue paſſions hee began thus to parle with himſelfe.
            Why how now Valericus (quoth hée) art thou haunted with ſome helliſh hagge, or paſſeſſed with ſome frantike furie? art thou inchaunted with ſome magicall charme, or charmed with ſome bewitching Sorcerie, that ſo ſodainly

thy minde is perplexed with a thouſand ſundry paſſions, alate frée, and now fettered, alate ſwimming in reſt, and now ſinking in care, erewhile in ſecuritie, and now in captiuitie, yea turned from mirth to mourning, from pleaſure to paine, from delight to deſpight, hating thy ſelfe, and louing her who is the chiefe cauſe of this thy calamitie. Ah Valericus, haſt thou forgot the ſaying of Propertius, that to loue, howſoeuer it be, is to loſe; and to fancie, how charie ſo euer thy choice be, is to haue an ill chance? for Loue though neuer ſo fickle is but a Chaos of care; and fancie, though neuer ſo fortunate, is but a maſſe of miſerie: for if thou enioy the beautie of Venus, thou ſhalt finde it ſmall vantage: if thou get one as wiſe as Minerua, thou maieſt put thy winnings in thine eye, if as gorgious as Iuno, thy accounts being caſt, thy gain ſhalbe but loſſe: yea, be ſhe vertuous 
                  •
               e ſhe chaſt, be ſhe curteous, be ſhe conſtant, be ſhee rich, be ſhe renowmed, be ſhee honeſt, be ſhee honourable, yet if thou be wedded to a woman, thinke thou ſhalt finde in her ſufficient vanitie to counteruaile her vertue, that thy happineſſe will bée matcht with heauineſſe, thy quiet with care, thy contentation with vexation: that thou ſhalt ſowe ſeede with ſorrowe, and reape thy corne with ſadneſſe, that thou ſhalt neuer liue without griefe, nor die without Repentance: for in matching with a Wife there are ſuch miſchiefes, and in marriage ſuch miſeries, that Craterus the Emperour wiſhing ſome ſiniſter fortune to happen vpon one of his foes, prayed vnto the gods that hée might hée married in his youth, and die without iſſue in his age, counting marriage ſuch a cumberſome croſſe, and a Wife ſuch a pleaſant plague, that he thought his foe could haue no worſe torment, than to bée troubled with ſuch noyſome traſh. Oh Valericus, if the conſideration of theſe premiſſes bée not ſufficient to perſwade thee: if the ſentence of Propertius cannot quench thy flame, nor the ſaying of Craterus coole thy fancie, call to minde what miſeries, what miſchiefes, what woes, what wailings,

what miſhaps, what murthers, what care, what calamities haue happened to ſuch, as haue béell beſotted with the balefull beautie of women, enioying more care than commoditie, more paine than profite, more coſt man comfort, more griefe than good: yea, reaping a tunne of droſſe for euery dramm of perfect gold.
            What careleſſe inconſtancie ruled Eriphila? What curriſh crueltie raigned in Philomela? How inceſtuous a life led Aeuropa? and how miſerable was that man that married Sthuolea? VVhat gaines got Tereus in winning Progne, but a loathſome death for a little delight. Agamemnon in poſſeſſing the beautie of Creſida, cauſed the Greeian armie moſt grieuouſly to be plagued. Candaules was ſlaine by his murthering wife, whom ſo intirely hée loued. Who was thought more happie than the husband of Helena, and yet who in time leſſe fortunate? What hapleſſe chaunces inſued of the chaſtitie of Penelope? What broiles in Rome by the vertue of Lucretia? The one cauſed her ſutors moſt horribly to bée ſlaine, and the other that Tarquine and all his poſteritie were rooted out of their regall dignities. Phaedra in louing killed her hapleſſe ſonne Hippolitus, and Clitemneſtra in hating ſlewe her louing husband Agamemnon. Alas Valericus, how dangerous is it then to deale with ſuch dames, which if they loue, they procure thy fatall care: and if they hate thee, thy finall calamitie?
            But ah blaſphemous beaſt that I am! thus reckleſly to raile and rage without reaſon, thus curriſhly to exclaime againſt thoſe, without whom our life though neuer ſo luckie, ſhould ſéem moſt loathſome? thus Tymon like, to condemne thoſe heauenly creatures, whoſe only ſight is a ſufficient ſalue againſt all helliſh ſorrowes: Is this right, to conclude generally of particular premiſes? Is it iuſtice to accuſe all for the fault of ſome? Is it equitie to blame the ſtaie of vertuous women, for the ſtate of vicious wantons? Doeſt thou thinke Valericus to ſhake off the ſhackles of

fancie with this follie? Or to eſchue the baite of beautie, by breathing out ſuch blaſphemie? No, no, aſſure thy ſelf, that theſe thy raging reaſons, will in time be moſt rigerouſly renenged, that the gods themſelues will plague thée for braying out ſuch iniurious ſpéeches. Alas, Loue wanting deſire, maketh the minde deſperate: and fixed fancie bereaued of loue turneth into furie. The loyall faith I beare to Caſtania, and the loathſome feare of her ingratitude, the déep deſire which inforceth my hope, &amp; the deadly deſpaire which infringeth my hap, ſo toſſeth my minde with contrarie cogitations, that I neither regard what I ſay, to my harme; nor reſpect what I doo, to my own hurt: yea, my ſenſes are ſo belotted with pinching loue, and my minde ſo fretted with frying fancie, that death were thrice more welcome, than thus to linger in deſpairing hope.
            And with that to paſſe away thoſe penſiue paſſions, hée flung out of his chamber with his Hawke on his fiſt, thinking by ſuch ſport to driue away this melanchollie humor, which ſo moleſted his minde.
            But as hée was paſſing through the Court, hee was luckilie encountred by Melytta and Caſtania, who minding to haue ſome ſport with Valericus before hée did paſſe: had the onſet thus pleaſantly giuen him by Caſtania.
            
            II is hard Signor Valericus (quoth ſhee) to take you eyther without your Hawke on your fiſt, or your heart on your halfepenie: for if for recreation you bee not retriuing the Partridge with dogges, you are in ſolemne meditation driuing awaie the time with dumpes, neyther caring for companie to ſolace your ſadneſſe, norpleaſantlie diſcourſing of ſome amorous Parle: which makes the Gentlewomen of this Court thinke, that you are either an Apoſtata to loue, as was Narciſſus, or haue diſplayed the flagge of deffance againſt Fancie, as did Tyanaeus. If theſe their ſurmiſed coniectures bèe true,

               Valericus, I warne thée as a friend to beware by other mens harmes, leaſt if thou imitate their actions, thou bée mangled with the like miſerie, or maimed with the like miſfortune.
            
               Valericus hearing his Saint pronouncing this ſugered harmonie, feeling himſelfe ſomewhat toucht with this quipping talke, was ſo rapt in admiration of her eloquence, and ſo rauiſht in the contemplation of hir beautie, that hée ſtood in a maze not able to vtter one word, vntill at laſt gathering his wits together, hée burſt forth in theſe ſpéeches.
            MAdame (quoth he) what it pleaſeth the gentle women of this court to ſormiſe of my ſolitarines I know not: but if they attribute it to curiouſnes, or coineſſe, to ſtrangeneſſe or ſtatelineſſe, either that I am an enemy to loue, or a foe to fancie, that I deteſt their bountie with Narciſſus, or contemne their beautie with Tiancus, they offer me great iniurie ſo raſhly to coniecture of my diſeaſe, before rightly they haue caſt my water. But to put your Ladiſhip out of doubt what is the cauſe of my dumpes, ſo it is, that of late raunging the fieldes, my heart (my hawke I ſhould ſaie Madame) houered at ſuch a princely praie, and yet miſt of her flight, that ſince ſhee hath neither pruned her ſelfe, nor I taken anie pleaſure. Marie if the fates ſhould ſo fauour mee, or fortune ſo ſhroud me vp in proſperitie, that my deſire might obtaine her wiſh, I would not onely change my mourning to mirth, my dolor to delight, and my care to ſecurity, but I would thinke to haue gotten as rich a praie as euer Caeſar gayned by conqueſt.
            SVrely Signor Valericus (quoth Melytta) no doubt the praie is p
                  •••
               ing princely, ſince the value thereof is rated at ſo preciou
                  •
                a price, and therfore we haue neither cauſe to condemn your hawk of haggardnes, for want of pruning,

nor you of fooliſhneſſe for want of pleaſure. And if your heart (your Hawke I ſhould ſay, Signior Valericus) hath reacht farther with her eye, than ſhe is able to mount with her wing, although I am no skilfull Fawlkner, yet I think you had better kéep her on the fiſt ſtil, and ſo féede her with hope, than let her miſſe againe of her flight, and ſo ſhe turnetaile and be foiled.
            Indeede Madame (quoth Valericus) your counſaile is very good, for as there is no better confect to a crazed mind, than hope, ſo there is no greater coraſiue to a careful man, than deſpaire, and the Falkners alſo iumpe with you in the ſame verdite, that the Hawke which miſſeth her pray, is doubtfull to foare aloofe and proue haggard. Yet if ſhe were ſo tickle, as ſhe would take no ſtand, ſo ramage as ſhe would be reclaimed with no lure, I had rather happely hazarde her for the gayning of ſo péerleſſe a pray, though I both loſt her, and wanted of my wiſh, than by keeping her ſtill in the Bines, to proue her a kite, or mee a coward.
            Indéed Sir (quoth Caſtania) Fortune euer fauoureth them that are valiant: and things the more hard, the more haughtie, high and heauenly: neither is any thing hard to bee accompliſht, by him that hardily enterpriſeth it. But yet take heede that you fiſh not ſo faire, that at length you catch a Frogge, and then repentance make you mumble vp a maſſe with Miſerere.
            
            No Madame (quoth he) it is neuer ſéene that hée which is contented with his chance, ſhould euer haue cauſe to repent him of his choice.
            And yet (quoth ſhe) he that buies a thing too deare, may be content with his chaffer, and yet wiſh he had been more charie.
            Trueth Madame (quoth Valericus) but then it is traſh and no treaſure, for that which is pretious is neuer ouerpriſed, and a bad thing though neuer ſo cheap, is thought too chargeable.
            
               
Oh Sir (quoth Melytta) and is it not an olde ſaying, that a man may buy golde too deare, and that iewels though neuer ſo pretious, may be ſet at too high a price? I ſee if you had no better skill in manning of a Hawke, than in making of a bargaine, you would proue but an ill Faulkner. But ſince we haue ſo long troubled you with our talk, we will nowe leaue you to your ſport, and ſo bid you farewell.
            
               Valericus with a courteous Conge, repaying their curteſie, and with a glauncing eye giuing his goddeſſe the dolefull A dio, went ſolitarilie into the ſecret woodes, where laying him downe in the ſhade, he fell into theſe muſing meditations:
            VVHat greater proſperitie (quoth he) can happē vnto any earthly wight, than if he be croſſed with care, to finde a confect to cure his calamity: than if he be pinched with pains, to get a plaiſter for his paſſions: if hée bée drenched in diſtreſſs, to finde a means to mitigate his miſerie? which I ſée by proofe performed in my ſéelie ſelfe: for the ſight of my goddeſſe haue ſo ſalued my forepaſſed ſorrowes, hir ſweet words hath ſo healed my heauie wounds, that where before I was plunged in perplexitie, I am now placed in felicitie: where before I was oppreſſed with care, I am now refreſhed with comfort. O friendly fortune, if from henceforth thou furiouſly frowne vpon mee, if thou daunt mee with diſaſter miſhappe, or croſſe mée with perpetuall care, yet thus thy friendly courteſie ſhall bee ſufficient to counteruaile all future enormities.
            But alas, I ſee euery proſperous puffe hath his boyſterous blaſte, euery ſwéete hath his ſower, euery weale his woe, euery gale of good lucke, his ſtorme of ſiniſter fortune: yea, euery commoditie his diſcommoditie annexed: the bloud of the Viper is moſt healthfull for the ſight, and moſt hurtfull for the ſtomacke, the ſtone Celonites is

very precious for the back, and very perilous to the braine: the flower of India pleaſant to be ſéene, but whoſo ſmelleth to it, féeleth preſent ſmart: ſo as the ioy of her preſence procureth my delight, the annoy of her abſence bréedeth my deſpight: yea, the feare that ſhe will not repay my loue with liking, and my fancie with affection, that ſhe wil not conſent to my requeſt, but rather meanes to ſtifle mee with the raging ſtormes of repulſe, and daunt me with the doome of deadly dentals, ſo fretteth my hapleſſe minde with helliſh furie, that no plague, no paine, no torment, no torture can worſe moleſt me, than to be diſtreſſed with this dreadfull deſpaire.
            Alas, her calling is too high for mée to climbe vnto, her royall ſtate is farre aboue my reach, her haughtie minde is too loftie for mée to aſpire: no doubt if I offer my ſute vnto her, ſhée will proue like the ſtone of Silicia, which the more it is beaten, the harder it is: or like the ſpices of Ionia, which the more they are pounded the leſſe ſauour they yield; like to the Iſiphilon, which yieldeth forth no iuice though neuer ſo well bruſed: ſo, though I ſhould with neuer ſo great deuotion offer vp at her Shrine, prayers, promiſes, ſighes, ſobs, teares, troth, faith, fréedom, yea, and my heart it ſelfe, as a pledge to plead for pittie, yet ſhe would make ſo ſmall account of theſe my cares, and as little regard my ruth and ruine, as Eriphila did her faithfull friend Infortunio.
            
            But oh vile wretch that I am! why doo I thus without cauſe condemne Caſtania? Why do I accuſe her of crueltie, in whom raigneth nothing but curteſie? Why doe I appeach her of coineſſe, in whom bountie ſheweth ſmall curiouſneſſe?
            How friendly, how familiarly, yea, how faithfully did ſhe talke with me, what a chéerefull countenance did ſhée carry towards mee, what ſodaine glaunces, what louely lookes? which no doubt are ſignes, that though ſhee repulſe meat the firſt, ſhee will not refuſe mée at the laſt:

though ſhe be ſtraight in words, ſhée will not bée ſtrange in minde: though ſhe giue me ſome bitter pilles of denyall, it ſhall bée but for the better tryall. And ſhall I then béeing fed with this hope proue ſuch a mecocke, or a milkeſop, as to be feared with the tempeſtuous ſeas of aduerſitie, when as at length I ſhal arriue at the hauen of happy eſtate? ſhall I dread to haue my ſhip ſhaken with ſome angrie blaſtes, hoping to bee ſafely landed on the ſhoare, and ſo haue my ſhare of that, which the ſhowers of ſhrewd Fortune for a time haue denyed mee? No, no,
            
               Dulcia non meruit, qui non guſtavit amara.
            
            Hée is not worthy to ſucke the ſwéete, which hath not firſt ſauoured the ſowre: hee is not worthy to eate the kernell which hath not crackt the ſhel, he deſerueth not to haue the crown of victorie, which hath not abid the brunt of the battaile: hee meriteth not to poſſeſſe the pray, which will not willingly take ſome part of the pains: Neither is he worthy of ſo heauenly a Dame as Caſtania, that would not ſpend the moſt preti
                  •
               us bloud in his body, in the purſuite of ſo peereleſſe a piece.
            
               VAlericus thus mitigating his paine with the milde medicine of hope, and rooting out the dead fleſh of deſpaire with the playſter of truſt, determined to ſtrike on the Stith while the yron was hot, and ſo purſue his purpoſe while his miſtreſſe was in her good moode. And therfore leauing his ſport for this time, highed him to the court in haſte: where inſinuating himſelf into the ſocietie of the Ladies and Gentlewomen, hee ſhewed himſelfe in ſport ſo pleaſant, in talk ſo witty, in manners ſo modeſt, in conceits ſo cunning, in parle ſo pithie, and in all his conuerſation ſo comely, that wheras before he was ſpecially loued of none, now he was generally liked of all: inſomuch that for a time there was no talk in the Court but of the Metamorphoſ
                  •
               s of Valericus minde. Who oftentimes determining in plain tearms to preſent his ſuits to Caſtania, when he came to the

point, fear of offence, and dread of deniall, diſappointed his purpoſe, that hée remained mute in the matter: but at laſt perceiuing delay bred danger, ſéeing his miſtris ſit alone in his preſence, houering betwéen fear and hope, he began the aſſault with this march.
            MAdame (quoth hee) for that I ſée you ſitting thus ſolitarie in dumps, I am the bolder to preaſe in place, although the moſt vnworthy man to ſupply it. Hoping you will pardon my rudeneſſe for troubling thus raſhly your muſing meditations, and count my company the leſſe offenſiue in that I ſée you buſied with no ſuch ſerious matters whereunto my preſence may be greatly preiudiciall. Cyneas the Philoſopher, Madam, was of this minde, that when the gods made beautie, they skipt beyond their skill, in that they framed it of greater force than they themſelues were able toreſiſt. If then there is none ſo wiſe or worthy whom beauty cannot wrack, nor none iſſued of ſuch princely birth whom beauty cannot bend, though I haue béene intangled with the ſnare of fancie, and haue liſtned to the lure of beauty, I am the more to be borne with, and the leſſe to be blamed. For I muſt of force confeſſe Madame, that the gifts of nature ſo aboundantly beſtowed vpō you, your excellent beauty and exquiſite vertue, haue ſo ſcaled the walls of my fancie, and ſacked the fort of my fréedom, that for my laſt refuge I am forced to appeale vnto your curteſie, as the onely medicine which may cure my intolerable diſeaſe. Nay incurable I may well call it, for (I ſpeake with teares outwardly, and drops of blood inwardly) vnleſſe the mizling ſhowers of your mercie mittigate the fire of my fancie, the droppes of your princely fauour quench the flame of my affection, and the guerdon of your good will giue a ſoueraigne plaiſtor for my ſecret ſore, I am like to paſſe my life in more miſerie, than if I had taken the internall torments. But I hope it is not poſſible, that out of a ſugered Fount would diſtill a bitter ſtreame,

out of a fragrant flower a filthhy ſap, and from ſuch diuine beautie ſhould procéed hate and helliſh crueltie.
            It is Madame, your beautie which hath wrought my wo, and it is your bountie which muſt work my weale. It is your heauenly face which hath depriued me of libertie, and your curteous conſent muſt bee the meanes to redéeme me from captiuitie: for as he that eateth of the Brain leaſe, and is infected, can by no meanes be cured, vnleſſe he taſts of the ſame roote: as hée which is wounded of the Porcupins, can neuer bee healed vnleſſe his wounds bée waſht with the bloud of the ſame beaſt: as there is nothing better againſt the ſtinging of a Snake, than to be rubbed with an Adders ſlough, and as he which is hurt of the Scorpion ſéekes a ſalue from whom he receiued the ſore, ſo loue onely is remedied by loue, and fancie by mutuall affection: you Madame, muſt miniſter the medicine, which procured the maladie, and it onely lies in your power to applie the playſter which inferred the paine.
            Therfore I appeale to your good grace and fauour, and at the barre of your beautie I humbly holde vp my hands, reſting to abide your ſentence, either of conſent vnto life, or deniall vnto death.
            CAſtania hearing this ſolemne diſcourſe of Valericus, was driuen into a maze with this vnlookt for motion, muſing that hee would ſo farre ouerſhoote himſelfe, as to attempt ſo vnlikely a match, and therefore with diſdainfull countenance ſhe gaue him this daunt:
            AS your preſent arriuall Signor Valericus dooth not greatly preindice my muſes, ſo I think it will as litle profit your motion: and as your company pleaſeth mée regarding the perſon, ſo it much miſliketh me, reſpecting the Parle: that your counts being once caſt you ſhall find your abſence might haue more pleaſured you, and better contented me. For tis vnpoſſible Valericus, to call the Fawlcon

to that Lure wherin the pens of a Chameleon are pricked, becauſe ſhe doth deadly deteſt them, it is hard to traine the Lyon to that trappe which ſauoureth of Diagredium, becauſe he loatheth it. And it is as impoſſible to perſwade me to enter league with fancie, which am a mortall foe to affection, and to vow my ſeruice to Venus, which am alreadie addicted to Diana. No, no ſir, I mean not to loue, leaſt I liue by the loſſe, nor to chooſe, leaſt my skill being ſmall, I repent my chance. Shee that is frée and willingly runneth into fetters is a foole, and whoſo becommeth captiue without conſtraint, may be either thought wilfull or witleſſe. It is good by other mens harmes to learn to beware, and to looke before a man doth leaps, leaſt in skipping beyond his skill, he light in the mire. Whoſo conſidereth the fickleneſſe of mens affections, and the fléeting fondneſſe of their fading fancie, who carefully looketh at the lightneſſe of their loue, and marketh the inconſtancie of their wauering minde, who readeth the records which make mention of their deepe diſſembling, faithleſſe proteſtations, falſe vowes, periured promiſes, fayned loue, and forged flattery: how poore Ariadne was abuſed, how Medea was mocked, how Dido was deceiued, how Oenone was reiected, and how Phyllis was forſaken, and yet would be allured to the traine with ſuch filthie ſcraps, I would count her chaunce too good, were her choice neuer ſo bad. But leauing theſe neceſſarie doubts, Valericus, I tel you for troth, if I meant to loue, it is not you I mean to like: if affection forced me, it is not your perſon I mean to fancie, your patrimony is not ſufficient to counteruaile my parentage, nor your bringing vp my birth, and therfore I would wiſh you to ſow the ſéede of your ſute in a more fertile ſoile, for in me you ſhall finde no grafts of grant to growe, nor no conſent to be cropped, for I neither like of your vnlikely loue, nor mean not to be framed to your fancie.
            
               Valericus beeing puſhed with this pike, thought it a ſigne of ſmall courage to yeeld at the firſt foyne, and therefore

looking more narrowly to his ward, and gathering himſelfe within his weapon, he ſtood to his tackling with this reply:
            MAdame (quoth he) if you condenm me of folly for climbing a ſtaffe too high, or accuſe me of fondneſſe far laying my loue on a perſon of ſuch princely parentage, it I ſeeme to make an ill market in cheaping ſuch precious chaffer, as the price thereof is far aboue my reach, yet my offence is too ſmall to beare anie waightie penance, ſith where the fault proceedeth of loue, there the pardon inſueth of courſe, but your beautie ſhall beare all the blame, as the onely ſpurre of this my raſh enterpriſe. For as it is impoſſible for the yron to reſiſt the operation of the Adamant, or the ſilly ſtrawe the vertue of the ſucking teat, ſo as impoſſible it is for a louer to withſtand the brunt of beautie, to freeze if he ſtand by the flame, or to peruert the lawes of Nature. So that Madame if you knew what a breache your beautie hath made into my breaſt, and bow déepely I haue ſhrined the idoll of your perſon in my hapleſſe heart, I aſſure my ſelf though my perſon and parentage, my birth and bringing vp be far vnfit for ſuch a mate yet you would deeme my loue and loyaltie to deſerue no leſſe. Loyaltie I call it Madam; for as all things are not made of one mould, ſo all men are not of one minde: as the Serpentine powder is quickly kindled, and quickly out, ſo the Salamander ſtone once ſet on fire can neuer bee quenched: as the ſoft ware is apt to receiue euerie impreſſion, ſo the hard metall neuer changeth form without melting. Iaſon was neuer ſo tr
                  •
               uthleſſe as Troylus was truſtie: Paris was neuer more fickle then Pyramus was faithfull: Aeneas was neuer ſo light as Leander was faithfull And ſure Madame, I call the gods to witneſſe, I ſpeake without faining, that ſith your beautie and vertue eyther by fate or for time is ſo déeply ſhrined in my heart, if it pleaſe you to accept mée for your ſlaue or ſeruant, and admit

mée ſo farre into your fauour, as that I may fréely enioie the ſight of your ſweet face, and féed my fancie in the contemplation of your beautie; in liewe therof, I will repaie ſuch dutifull ſeruice, as the betrothed faith of Eraſta to his Perſida, ſhall not compare with the loue of Valericus and Caſtania.
            
            
               CAſtania hearing theſe perplexed paſſions proceed from wofull Valericus, pricked forwarde to take ſome remorſe of his torments, felt within her minde a carefull conflict betwéen fancie and the fates, loue &amp; the deſtinies: fancy perſwaded her to take pittie of his paines, the fates forced her to giue him the repulſe: loue wiſht her to return his goodwil with gaine, the deſtinies draue her to deny his requeſt: toſſed thus with contrary cogitations, at laſt ſhe burſt forth into theſe doubtfull ſpéeches.
            
               VAlericus, as I am not altogether to reward thy goodwill with hate, ſo I cannot repaie it with loue, becauſe fancie denies me to like: to marry I meane not, to retaine ſeruants I may not. Marie, to let thee eyther to loue, or looke, take this for an anſwere, I neyther can nor will.
            And with that ſhée went her way, leauing Valericus greatly daunted with this doubtfull anſwere, with feare and hope ſo fiercely aſſayled, that being left alone, he began thus to conſider of his amorous conceits.
            IF euer wofull creature had cauſe to complain his wofull eaſe, then vndoubtedly may I preace for the formoſt place: for there is no ſorrow more ſower, no torment more terrible, no grief more grieuous, no heauineſſe more hurtfull, than to haue deſire requited with deſpight, and good will with hate, then to like vpon hope of curteſſe, and to finde nothing but hate and helliſh crueltie.
            Alas poore Valericus, is thy true loue thus triflingly

accounted of, is this the guerdon for thy good will? Deoth thy deepe deſire merite no better deſert, then haſt thou no choice, but eyther to dye deſperately, or elſe to liue loathſomly? Why fond foole doeſt thou count her cruell, that at the firſt giues not a frée conſent? Doeſt thou think her coie that commeth not at the firſt call, wouldeſt thou haue the match made at the firſt motion? She that is wonne with a word will bee loſt with a winde, the Hawke that bates at euery caſt of the Lure, will neuer bee ſtedfaſt on the ſtonde, the woman that frameth her will to euery wiſh will proue but a wilde wanten. No, no, Valericus, let not her denials daunt thée, let not the ſower taſte of her talke quat thy queaſte ſtomacke, conſter all things at the beſt, though her cenſure was very ſeuere, yet ſhee knit vp her talke with a curteous cloſe. The hound which at the firſt default giueth ouer the chaſe, is called but a curre. The Knight that finding the firſt encounter comberſom, giueth ouer the queſt, is counted but a coward, and the louer that at the firſt denyall is daunted with deſpayre, is neyther worthy to obtaine his deſire, nor to enioy his deſert. And with that he flung out of his Chamber, both to auoid the melancholy which tormented his minde, and ſée if he could haue a ſight of his goddeſſe.
            But Caſtania altogether vnwilling to parle with her new patient, kept herſelfe out of his ſight: which Valericus eſpying, was no whit amazed, but like a valiant ſouldiour gaue the fort a freſh aſſault with a new kinde of batterie, ſéeking to obtaine that with writing, which he could not gaine with words, and therefore ſpéedily framed a letter to this effect.
            
               
                  Seignor Valericus, to the Lady Caſtania, health.
                  THere is no creature (Madame Caſtania) ſo bereaued of reaſon, or depriued of ſenſe, which being oppreſſed with direfull calamities, findeth not by méere inſtinct of

nature, a preſent medicine for his maladie, man onely excepted, who by reaſon of this want, may iuſtly accuſe the iniurious gods of iniuſtice. The Tiger though neuer ſo deadly wounded, taſteth the roote of Tamariſke, and is preſently cured: The Deare being ſtrooken, though neuer ſo déep, féedeth on the hearb Dictamnum, and forthwith is bealed: the Lyon ſalueth his ſickneſſe by eating the Sea Woolfe, and the Vnicorne recouereth his health by ſwallowing vp the buds of a Date trée. But man being croſſed with care, or oppreſſed with griefe, pinched with fancie, or perplexed with loue, findeth no hearbe ſo wholeſome, nor medicine ſo milde, no plaiſter ſo perfect, nor no ſalue ſo ſoueraigne, which by their ſecrete vertues can appeaſe his paſſions. Which Madame, I know by proofe, &amp; now ſpeak by experience: for your diuine beautie and ſecret vertue, the perfection of your bodie and the bountie of your minde, hath kindled ſuch a flaming fire in my hapleſſe heart; that by no meanes it may be quenched, but will turne my body into drie earth and cinders, vnleſſe by the droppes of your pittie it bee ſpéedily redreſſed. Then Madame, ſith your beautie is my bale, let it be my bliſſe: ſince it hath wrought my woe, let it worke my weale, and let not my faithfull ſeruice and loyall loue be recompenced with ſuch rigerous refuſals. Striue not for my life, ſince you haue my libertie, ſéeke not my death, ſince you are the Saint to whom I offer vp my deuotion. But good Madame, let the ſwéete Balme of your beneuolence ſalue the ſore which ſo painfully afflicteth my carefull conſcience, and with the deawe of your grace redéeme him from moſt helliſh miſerie, whoſe life and death ſtandeth in your anſwere, which I hope ſhall be ſuch as belongeth to the deſert of my loue, and the ſhew of your beautie.
                  
                     Yours, if he be
Don Valericus.
                  
               
            
            
               
               Valericus hauing thus finiſhed his Letter, ſent it with as much ſpéede as might be by his Page to Caſtania, who finding her at conuenient leaſure, with moſt reuerent dutie deliuered it. Caſtania at the firſt ſight coniecturing the contents, with ſcornful looks and diſdainfull countenance vnripped the ſeales, where ſéeing and reading his déep deuotion ſhee perceiued that his affection was no leſſe in déede, than he profeſſed in word: ſhe notwithſtanding would take no remorſe of his torment, but to driue him more into dolefull dumpes, ſhe returned him this damp.
            
               
                  Caſtania, to Signior Valericus.
                  AS it is impoſſible (Signor Valericus) to ſtraine moiſt licour out of the drie flint, to procure ſlaming heate in that which alreadie is nipped with chilling colde, to force the ſturdie ſtreames to run againſt their common courſe, ſo as hard it is to win vnwilling loue, eyther with teares or truth. For if thy birth and patrimony could counteruaile my parentage, if my Father were content to knit vp the knot, yet neither his commaund nor thy intreaty ſhould make mee to chooſe without my owne loue and liking. Sith then thou art the man whome I rather loathe than like, ceaſe from thy ſute, make a vertue of neceſſitie, and aſſwage the flame thy ſelf which no other will quench. By importunate perſiſting in thy purpoſe where no hope is, thou proueſt thy ſelfe rather a deſperate ſot than a diſcréete ſouldſour. To hop againſt the hill is extreame fondneſſe, to ſtriue againſt the ſtreame, méere folly: then Valericus, auoyde the one, and eſchew the other, for if thou wilt ſeeke to gayne my good will, thou ſhalt turne the endleſſe ſtone with Siſiphus, and therefore take my naye for anſwere. For if I would I cannot, and if I could I will not. And ſo farewell.
                  
                     No way yours,
Caſtania.
                  
               
            
            
               
               VAlericus hauing receiued this rigorous Letter from ruthleſſe Caſtania, ſéeing with what great diſdain ſhe reiected his dutifull deuotion, and how with coy countenance and lowring lookes, ſhe rewarded his loyall loue, hée began with reaſon ſome what to repreſſe his rage, and with wiſedome to redreſſe his witleſſe folly: for comparing her crueltie with his owne curteſie, and her wilfull diſdaine with his willing duty, his diſordinate deſire began not only to decay, but his extreame loue turned to extream hate, inſomuch that forced with deſpight, he ſent her (in reuenge) theſe raging lines.
            
               
                  Valericus the deſpiſed, to deſpightfull Caſtania.
                  
                     DIogenes being demanded why ſo extreamly hee hated women, anſwered, becauſe (quoth hée) they be women: ſo if thou aske of mée why ſo rudely I raile againſt thy reckleſſe folly, I anſwere, becauſe thou art Caſtania, whoſe mercileſſe mind is ſo miſledde with ingratitude, &amp; whoſe curriſh nature is foyled with careleſſe inconſtancie, that like Menechmus Subreptus his wi
                        •
                     e, thou doeſt not begin to loue ere againe thou ſéekeſt to hate. Thou plaieſt, Caſtania, like the yong Eagles, which being hatched vp by the bird Oſyphaga, neuer ſéek to peark on loftie Mounts, but to ſit in durtie Dales, and like the gréedie kite which leaueth the ſwéete fleſh, to praie on the ſtinking carrion. But why do I ſo farre forget my ſelfe? Is ſhe to be blamed that leaueth her choyce to haue a better chaunce? or is the Faulcon to bee accuſed of baſtardie, that leaueth the ſtarling to pray on the Larke? No: and no doubt ſuch is thy caſe: for if it be true that all ſpeaketh, or at the leaſt ſuſpecteth, thou art like by thy louers parentage to become a great Potentate: for if armes be the bewrayer of auncient deſcents, no doubt he is come of an olde houſe. Yea,

thy father Orlanio may roioyce if hée liue to ſée the day that his daughter ſhall bee ſo well wedded as to ſuch a wrangling wiſard. But Paſiphae preferred a Bull before a King, and Venus a ſmeared Smith before Mars the god of battaile. Tuſh, Pſomneticus was father to Rhodopes children, whoſoeuer begat them: and that cloake is of a courſe ſpinning, that cannot kéep off the raine. Farewell.
                  
                     Liuing he hopes to reuenge thy iniuries.
Wofull Valericus.
                  
               
            
            
               CAſtania no ſooner had read theſe deſpitefull lines of Valericus, but her minde ſried with the flames of furie, and her breaſt broyled with raging wrath, in ſuch ſort, that ſhe could not be in quiet nor take any reſt, ſhée buſied her ſelfe ſo carefully in ſtudying with what kinde of reuenge ſhée might beſt wreake her wrath vpon him, and requite his ſpitefull ſpéeches. At laſt womanlike, ſhee found her tongue the beſt weapon, and with that ſhe plagued him in this ſort.
            
               
                  Caſtania, to Valericus, neither health nor good hap.
                  THe Maſtiffe Dogge (Valericus) can neuer queſt like a Spaniell, but he muſt alwaies barke like a Curre: it is natural for the Pie to chatter, for the Iaye to iangle, and for thee to raile and rage like a frantike foole. Dooeſt thou think (Valericus) by brawling like a beggar to become a King, or by thy moodleſſe folly to obtaine my fauour? no, as I know thy knauery, ſo I paſſe not for thy brauery: neyther can thoſe vaunts ſtand for payment, where the partie is prickt for a péeuiſh paltering patch. It is no maruaile if thy doggiſh Letters ſauour of Diogenes doctrine: for in troth thou art ſuch a Cinicall kind of dunce,

that thy fonde felicitie is in biting bitterly thoſe, whome otherwiſe thou canſt not reuenge. Indéede, gentle Balaams Aſ
                        •
                     e, if I had béene ſo light as to haue loued you, I might iuſtly haue béene accuſed to haue béene a curre or a Kiſtrell: for in faith ſhee that féedes her fancy on thy face, may onely reape this profite, to fill her eyes full with the figure of a foole. For my louers arms, Valericus, they are imblazed in ſuch a coate, as it is hard for thée to controll. But, I know thou boaſteſt that thou haſt gotten thy antiquitie by conqueſt, and kéepeſt thy Letters patents in the beggers boxe. Thus adieu ſir dunce: the more you miſlike me, the better I loue my ſelfe.
                  
                     Thy deteſted foe,
Caſtania.
                  
               
            
            
               VAlericus his heart was ſo hardened with hate, as he was nothing diſmaied with this rigorous reply, but thought himſelfe halfe ſatiſfied, that hee had thus kindly toucht her to the quicke, praying the gods, that ſith it was not in his poſſibilitie to make any ſufficient reuenge, they would by ſome ſiniſter meanes requite her cruelty. But leauing him to his dumps, at laſt to Gwydonius, who beſides the beautie of his body, and the bounty of his minde (wherat all Alexandria wondered) had by good gouernment and perfect practice, obtained ſuch a dexterity in all things, as in feates of arms no man more forward, in exerciſe none more actiue, in play none more politicke, in parle none more pleaſant: amongſt the Auncients verie wiſe, amongſt the youthfull who more merry? ſo that there was no time, perſon, nor place, whereto aptly hee applyed not himſelfe: inſomuch that hee entred into ſuch fauour and familiarity with Therſandro &amp; Caſtania, that he was the onely man whoſe company they deſired to enioy. But eſpecially Caſtania, who by caſting a gazing glaunce ſometime vppon the beautie of Gwydonius,
               
felt a certaine reſtraint of libertie in her affections, an alteration of minde, and as it were a ciuile aſſault within her ſelfe: but hauing ſmall practice in the panges of loue, ſhe could not coniecture the ſecret cauſe of theſe her ſodain paſſions, thinking that as it was a toye lightly taken, ſo it would as lightly be left: and vpon this, ſtill ſhee reſted, conceiuing onely an ordinary kinde of liking towardes Gwydonius.
            
            Who bathing thus in the ſtreames of bliſſe, and ſafely harboured in the hauen of happineſſe, wanting nothing which might content his minde, eyther for pleaſure or profit, thought it a point of mecre folly eyther to ſéeke or wiſh for more than inough, knowing that to ſtraine further than the ſléeue would ſtretch, was but to make the arme bare, and to skippe beyond a mans skill, was to leape, but not to knew where to light: to auoide therfore haſtineſſe in hazarding, he fell a ſlumbering in the careleſſe ſeat of ſecuritie.
            But as it is impoſſible for a man to ſléepe by the Viper and not bée inuenomed, to gaze vpon the Cockatrice and not be infected, to ſtare vpon the Sunne and not bee dazeled, to looke vpon Meduſas head and not be tranſformed, to wade in the waues and not be drenched, to handle coalss and not be ſcorched: ſo it was as impoſſible for yong Gwydonius to gaze vpon the beauty of Caſtania and not be galled, to ſixe his eyes vpon her feature and not be fettered, to ſée her vertuous qualities and not be inueigled: for her curteſie had ſo encountred him, her modeſty had ſo amazed him, and her chary chaſtity ſo inchaunted him, that whereas he came to Orlanio his Court frée from affection, he was now become a ſeruile ſlaue to fancie; before a foe to luſt, now a friend to loue; yes, he felt ſuch an alienation of his ſenſes, and ſuch a ſtrange Metamorphoſis of his minde, as reaſon was turned to rage, mirth to mourning, ioy to annoy, delight to deſpight, weale to woe, bliſſe to hale: in fine, ſuch contrary paſſions ſo perplexed this doubtfull

Patient, as maugre his face hée yéelded the forte to fancie, and puld in the former flagge of defiance, intreated for truce, and began to enter parle with Cupide on this manner.
            
               O Gwydonius (quoth hée) what ſtrange chaunce, nay what rare chaunge, what ſolemne motion, nay, what ſodaine madneſſe, what fooliſh frenzie, or rather what frautike affection hath poſſeſſed thee? Is thy lawleſſe liberty turned to a ſlauiſh captiuitie? Is thy fréedome fettered? Are thy ſenſes beſotted? Is thy wit inueigled? Wert thou of late a defier of Venus, and art thou now a defender of vanity? Didſt thou of late renounce beauty as a foe, and wilt thou now embrace her as a friend? Is this the carefull kéeping of thy fathers commaundement? Or is this thy diligent duty in obſeruing the counſaile of thy olde ſire Clerophontes? Haſt thou ſo ſoon forgot his fatherly precepts, or committed to obliuion his friendly aduertiſement? Did hee carefully warne ſhee to beware of loue, and wilt thou careleſly wed thy ſelfe to luſt? Did hee ſhewe thee what poyſoned bane is hidden vnder the painted baytes of beauty, and wilt thou bee haled to the hooke?
            O hapleſſe caſe: nay rather, if the chary charge thy father gaue thee, will bée no conſtraint, if his counſaile will not commaund thée, if his warning will not make thee wary, nor his aduiſe be thy aduiſement: yet let imminent perils, and inſuing dangers be a precious preſeruatiue againſt future calamities. Cōſider with thy ſelfe Gwydonius, what difference is betwéen fréedom and bondage, betwéene liberty and captiuitie, mirth and mourning, pleaſure and paine, reſt and care, happineſſe and heauineſſe: and ſo far doth hee which is frée from affection, differ from him which is fettered in fancie.
            Why but Gwydonius, why doeſt thou thus reckleſly rage, againſt reaſon? Why dooeſt thou thus fondly exclaime

againſt thine owne welfare? Why dooeſt thou condemne thy ſelfe of that crime whereof thou art not guiltie?
            Thy Father warned thee to beware of ſickle fancie: but this thy liking is firm affection. His counſaile was to perſwade thee from lewd luſt, but not from lawfull loue, from vanitie, not from vertue: yea, his will was to wiſhe thée from liking ſuch a lewd miniō, who had neither birth, wealth, nor vertue, but a little fading beauty to be either her credite or thy countenance, not to warne thee from louing ſuch a chaſt maiden, nay, a péerleſſe Princeſſe, whoſe birth may countenance thy calling, whoſe power may promote thee, whoſe liuinges may inrich thée, whoſe vertue may aduance thée: yea, in obtaining whom, thou ſhalt gain both honour, and perhappes the inheritance of a Dukedome.
            Doeſt thou thinke then Gwydonius, in winning ſo worthy a péece, to purchace thy fathers diſpleaſure? nay aſſure thy ſelfe hee will not onely be content with thy chance, but hee will thinke thou haſt runne a happier race, than Hyppomanes did in winning Atlante. Content thée wc thy chance. Why Gwydonius, art thou ſo fond a foole, as to count the Caſtle conquered, that as yet thou haſt not compaſſed: to ſuppoſe the Citie ſacked, which thou haſt not beſieged: to think the Bulwarke beaten, which as yet thou haſt not battered: or to count the Lady wonne, whome as yet thou haſt not wooed? Nay Gwydonius, if thou weigh thy caſe in the equal ballance, thou haſt more cauſe of feare than of hope; of doubt than of aſſurance, of miſſing thy pretence, than of obtayning thy purpoſe.
            The Faulkon (Gwydonius) ſeldome pearketh with the Merline, the Lyon ſeldome lodgeth with the Mouſe, the Hart ſeldome féedeth with the Pricket, Aquila non capit Muſcas, and a Dame indued with Nobilitie, vouchſafeth not to match with a man of meane gentility. Of meane gentilitie Gwydonius? Yea truely, for Caſtania rather

thinketh thee ſprong of ſome poore peaſant, than of anyprincely perſonage.
            Beſides, alas, Fortune her ſelfe denieth me any ſuch fauour: my good will as yet hath deſerued no ſuch guerdon, my deſire is farre aboue my deſertes, my ambition aboue my condition, and the poor ſtay of wandering Gwydonius, farre vnfit for the princely ſtate of worthy Caſtania. But put caſe ſhe did will as I did, wiſh that ſhee were pricked in the ſame veine, caught in the ſame ſnare, trapped with the like traine, and fired with the like fancy, yet the Duke her father will neither condeſcend to her minde, nor conſent to my motion, neither thinke well of her liking nor of my loue: nay if he ſhould but once heare of ſuch reckleſſe folly, as he hath wrought my promotion, ſo he would work my confuſion, as he hath béen my friend, ſo he woulde bée my foe, and in troth Gwydonius, not without cauſe. For art thou ſo voyd of vertue, or vowed to vice, ſo nurſed vp in vanity, or nulled vp in villany, as to require his liberalitie with ſuch diſloyaltie, to returne the truſt which he repoſeth in thée, with ſuch treaſon. Tuſh, Loue is aboue Lord or Lawe, friend or faith. Where Loue leadeth, no maiſter is made account of, no king cared for, no friend forced of, no duty reſpected, but all things done according to the qualitie that is predominant. Why Gwydonius, what doubts are theſe that thou thus dreameſt on? Why doeſt thou caſt beyonde the Moon, and fear before thou art in daunger to fall? knowing that Loue and fortune deſireth not them that are daſtards, nor careth for them that are cowardes. The Captaine that retyreth from the walles before hée hath the repulſe, ſhall neuer returne a conquerour, the Souldiour that fainteth before the battaile be fought, ſhall neuer vaunt himſelfe of victorie. Hée that feareth euery tempeſt is not fit to be a trauailer. Hée that doubteth euery waue ſhall neuer proue a perfect Pilot, and he that in loue dreadeth euery chip of miſchaunce, may well encoounter, but neuer obtaine the conqueſt.

Sith then Gwydonius, hardy venturing is a ſigne of happy victory, ſound out the march with the trumpet of truſt, begin the aſſault, giue the onſet. Laie the battering péeces of Loue, againſt the bulwarke of beautie, and no doubt thy ſucceſſe ſhall be ſuch as thou ſhalt triumph with Caeſar and ſay, Veni, Vidi, Vici. And art thou ſo preſumptuous fond foole, as to promiſe thy ſelfe the conqueſt? knoweſt thou not that the path of loue is perilous? And with that he fell into ſuch melancholie paſſions, ſuch contrary cogitations, ſuch doubtfull thoughts, ſuch fearefull ſuppoſes, that as hée which eateth of the Goorde roote loſeth his memorie, and as the Elephant when he eateth of the Helitropion leafe, is then very ſléepie; ſo Gwydonius was ſo perplexed with theſe vnacquainted paſſions, that contrarie to his cuſtome he had driuen myrth into mourning, pleaſant conceits into painfull cares, laughing into lowring, ſinging into ſorrow: and being thus beſotted, to ſolace himſelf he went into a Parke adioyning to the Dukes Palace, where ſitting vnder the ſhade of a Béech trée, leaning his head on his hand, he lay as one in a ſlumber. But Fortune willing ſomewhat to fauour this young nouice, brought it to paſſe, that Therſandro, Valericus, Caſtania, and Melytta, with diuerſe other Gentlemen, were for recreation ſake ranging in the ſame Park: who eſpying ghoſtly Gwydonius, ſitting as one in a trance, Caſtania paſſing before the reſt, pulling him by the ſléeue, draue him thus out of his dump.
            VVHy how now Gwydonius (quoth ſhee) are you dreaming or doubting, or is your mind muſing vpō ſom metaphyſicall motions, that you ſit thus as a man half mortified? Your ſolemn geſture makes me remember the picture of Pigmalion, which once I ſawe portraied out by a ſkilfull Painter, who leaning his head on his Marble miſtres (that ſo vnfainedly he loued) ſat with his eies as one in a ſlumber, hauing his face notwithſtanding ſo bedewed

with brutiſh teares, as his outward plaints did ſufficiently bewray his inward paſſions. In truth Gwydonius, I had taken thee for Pigmalion, if thou hadſt had tears, as thou wert in a trance; for thou doeſt not greatly differ from him neither in countenance nor colour: well if it were but a dreame Gwydonius, that thus cumbred thy conſcience, or a doubt that made thée thus dumpith, I will diuine the one if it be not too dark, or decide the other if it be not too ſecret: marry if the caſe bee cumberſome, I leaue it to the iudgement of theſe Gentlemen.
            
               GWydonius, wakened out of his muſing ſlumber with this ſugred harmony, ſéeing before his eyes his gorgeous goddeſſe, the very ſaint, at whoſe ſhrine hee was offering vp ſcalding ſighes, far fetcht ſobs, plaints, prayers, and proteſtations, was ſo appald with her preſence, that as the Baſiliſk loſeth his ſenſes with the ſight of a naked man, as the Toretoiſe ſéeing yt North ſtar is benummed, &amp; as the Hermeline looking on the ſtone Echites is greatly amazed; ſo Gwydonius ſéeing the incomparable beauty of his beſt beloued Caſtania, was ſo aſtoniſhed, yea ſo inchanted with the rare perfectiō of this heauenly Pallas, that as one beſotted he ſate ſenſeleſſe, not being able to vtter one word; vntil at length reuiued with the view of hir chéerful countenance he repaid her with this pleaſant anſwere.
            MAdame (quoth hee) whereas ieſtingly you ſay, that at the firſt ſight you had taken me for perplexed Pigmalion by my pittifull plaints and carefull countenance, but that I wanted trickling tears to decipher my ſorrow; I anſwer, that wo may very well be without watry waylings: for when the ſtone Garatides fryeth without, it fréezeth within, the Germander leafe when it is moſt full of moyſture, looketh then moſt drie, where the ſtreame is moſt déepe there it is moſt ſtill, and where is the ſmalleſt ſhewe of teares, there is the greateſt ſigne of ſorrowe. And alſo

I call the heauens to witneſſe, that when you wakened me out of my dreame by your diuine eloquence, I took you either for beauty to bée Venus, for comelineſſe to bee Pallas, or for port and honour to be Iuno, ſo that both your preſence and curteſie daunted my minde; your preſence in dazeling my eyes ſo ſodainly with ſo ſolemn a ſight, your curteſie, in that your Ladiſhip without curioſitie would vouchſafe to talk with ſo meane a Gentleman. But Madame, ſith that I perceiue your skill in diuination to bée great, in that you made ſo cunning a coniecture, and without anie great ayming, ſo rightly hitte the marke; to put you out of doubt, I confeſſe I was both in a dreame and a doubt, wherein ſith it pleaſeth your honour to take ſo much paine, I will craue your ayde to diuine the one, and decide the other.
            
               
                  
                     
                        The Dreame.
                        I Was walking (Madame Caſtania) in my dreame (as I ſuppoſed) ſolitarily by the Sea ſide, wheras I tooke delight to ſée the Dolphines leape, (which as the Mariners ſay, is a ſigne of imminent tempeſt) I forth with eſpied a rocke in the Sea, whereupon ſtood a Lady arrayed with roabes of burniſht golde, ſo formed and framed, ſo adorned and decked with the gifts of Nature, as at the firſt I took her to be Thetis, that had ſo gorgeouſly clad her ſelfe, to welcome home her louer and Lord Neptunus. But viewing her countenance more narrowly, I perceiued her to be a mortall creature (though vnworthie ſuch diuine beautie ſhould be ſhrouded in the ſubſtance of an earthly carcaſſe) which ſo inflamed my affection, ſo fired my fancy, and ſo kindled my deſire, that the torments of Tantaius, the torture of Ixion, the ſorrow of Siſyphus, were not halfe comparable to the perplered paſſions that pinched my hapleſſe heart, when I ſawe all hope cut away from inioying this

earthly goddeſſe, the ſea which compaſſed the rocke was ſo déepe and dangerous, the cliffes ſo ſtéep-down and fearfull, as to deſcend was no leſſe daunger then death it ſelfe: thus as I ſurged in griefe, and wandred vp and downe in woe, I ſpied a bridge afarre off, whereby was a paſſage to the rocke: which ſight ſo ſalued my forepaſſed ſorrow, and ſo reuiued my daunted minde, as I was driuen into an extaſte for ioy, to ſee ſo good meanes to enioy my wiſhed deſire. Comming to the bridge, I found it built of glaſſe ſo cunningly &amp; ſo curiouſly, as if nature her ſelf had ſought to purchaſe credit by framing ſo curious a péece of workmā
                           ſhip. But yet ſo ſlēderly, as ye leaſt waight was able to paſh it into innumerable péeces, and vnderneath the bridge did runne ſo terrible a ſea, ſuch bouncing billowes, ſuch tumbling waues, ſuch fearefull ſurges, ſuch roaring ſtreames, ſuch hideous gulfes, as it made the paſſage ſéeme a thouſand times more perilous. This terrible ſight was ſuch a cooling card to my former conceits, as hope was turned to feare, bliſſe to bale, and ſuppoſed happineſſe to aſſured heauineſſe. And yet my fancy was not quenched, but rather far the more inflamed, my deſire was not diminiſhed, but augmented, and my liking no leſſe, but rather inlarged; ſo that to liue in loue without hope was loathſome: to ſéek redreſſe was loſſe of life: to want my wiſh, was horror: to inioy my wil, was hel
                              •
                            to liue in care without cōfort, was calamity: to ſéek for cure, was more than miſery: not to poſſeſſe the pray, was helliſh danger: to venture for the prize, was haples death. Thus croſſed with cares, &amp; daūted with ſuch diuers doubts, deſperate hope ſo repulſed direful feare, that encouraged by ventrous deſire, I had either obtained my wiſh, or wanted of my wil, if your Ladiſhip had not ſo ſodainly wakened me out of my ſlūber. Thus Madame Caſtania, you haue heard my dreame: now the doubt is, whether it had been better to haue ventured vppon the brittle bridge, and ſo either deſperately to haue ended cares with death, or elſe valtantly to haue enioyed deſire with

renowne, or ſtill like a fearefull daſtard to haue ended my dayes in lingering loue with miſery.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               Caſtania, hearing the ſurmized dreame of Gwydonius, both ſmelled the fetch, and ſmiled at the folly of this young youth, knowing that theſe fantaſticall viſions and preſuppoſed paſſions, would in time (if hée tooke not héed) proue but too true: to preuent therfore ſuch imminent perils, ſhée nipt her yong nouice on the pate with this parle.
            
            
               GGydoniu
                     •
                  
                (quoth ſhee) I haue liſtened to thy drouſie dream, with déep deuotion; by ſo much the more deſirous atttentiuely to heare it, by how much the more I find it ſtrange and wonderfull: yea, ſo ſtrange, as if I my ſelfe had not wakened thee out of thy ſlumber, I would eyther haue thought it a fained viſion, or a fantaſticall inuention: but ſith theſe Gentlemen here preſent, and mine owne eyes are witneſſes, and thine owne tongue a teſtimony of thy talk; ſuffice I beléeue it, though I cannot diuine it: to giue a verdite where the euidence is not vnderſtood, is vanity: to yéeld a reaſon of an vnknowne caſe, is meere folly: and to interpret ſo ſtrange a dreame without great practice, is but to skip beyond my skill, and to lie faſt in the mire. Yet, leaſt I might ſéeme to promiſe much &amp; perform nothing, I wil decide your doubt, if you pleaſe to take my doom for a cenſure.
            It is a ſaying Gwydonius, not ſo common as true, that the haſty man neuer wants woe, and that hee which is raſh without reaſon, ſeldome or neuer ſloepeth without repentance. To venture amidſt the Pikes when perilles cannot bée eſchewed, is not fortitude but folly: to hazarde in daungers, when death inſueth, is not to bee worthily minded, but wilfully mooued. Vertue alwaies conſiſteth betwéen extreamities, that as too much fearefulneſſe is the ſigne of a quaking coward, ſo too much raſhnes be tokeneth a deſperate Ruffian. Manhood Gwydonius conſiſteth in meaſure &amp; worthineſſe, in fearing to hazard without hope.

But to giue a verdit by thine owne voyce, I perceiue thou art guilty of the ſame crime: for when the brittleneſſe of the bridge portended, and the ſurging ſeas inferred loſſe of life, yet deſire draue thée to aduenture ſo deſperate a danger.
            Better it is Gwydonius, to liue in griefe, then to dye deſperately without grace: better to chooſe a lingering life in miſery, then a ſpéedy death without mercie: better to be tormented with hapleſſe fancy, then with helliſh fiends: for in life it is poſſible to repreſſe calamity, but after death neuer to redreſſe miſery. Tully Gwydonius in his Tuſculans queſtions, diſcourſing of the happineſſe of life and heauineſſe of death, ſayth, that to liue we obtaine it of the louing gods, but to dye, of the vnlucky deſtinies: meaning hereby, that life though neuer ſo loathſome, is better then death, though neuer ſo welcome: whereby I conclude Gwydonius, that to liue earefully, is better then to die deſperately.
            
               Gwydonius perceiuing that Caſtanias parle was nothing to the purpoſe, and that ſhée toucht not that point wherof he deſired moſt to be abſolued, but meant to ſhake him off with a ſléeueleſſe anſwere, began to drawe her to the Trap with this traine.
            MAdame Caſtania (quoth hée) I confeſſe that raſhneſſe neuer raigneth without repentance, nor haſtie hazarding without hapleſſe harmes, that hée which aduentureth deſperate dangers is a foole, and he that paſſeth ineuitable perils is worſe then an Aſſe: yet from theſe ſo generall rules, Madame, I exempt theſe particular exceptions, namely Loue and Neceſſitie, which two are tyed within no bounds, nor limited within no law, for whom the diuell driues hée muſt néedes runne, be the paſſage neuer ſo perillous: and whom Loue or Neceſſity forceth, hee muſt venture bee the daunger neuer ſo deſperate: for as there is no enterpriſe ſo eaſie, which to an vnwilling man ſeemeth not

very hard to be atchieued, ſo there is no encounter ſo cumberſome where will wiſheth, that ſéemeth not paſſing eaſie to bee performed: now this will is with nothing ſooner pricked forward, than eyther with the force of loue, or ſting of neceſſity. So that whoſoeuer aduentureth in a daunger, though neuer ſo deſperate, is not to be blamed, if inforced by fancy, or incouraged by affection; and eſpecially where the perill is in poſſibility to bee paſſed without death, and in the performance thereof, the poſſeſſion of ſuch a prize as the paſſionate perſon more eſtéemeth than lands, limbs, or life it ſelfe, be it neuer ſo ſwéet. In which caſe (Madame) my cauſe conſiſteth. For the Lady who was an heauenly obiect to my gazing eyes, was ſo beautified with the giftes of nature, and ſo perfectly poliſhed with more than naturall perfection, that with the onelie view of ſuch diuine beautie, my ſenſes were ſo beſotted, my wit and will ſo inueigled, my affection ſo inflamed, and my fréedome ſo fettered: yea, loue alreadie hath made ſo great a breach into the bulwarke of my breaſt, that to obtaine ſo gorgious a Goddeſſe, I thought death no daunger, though neuer ſo direfull, nor loſſe of life no torment, though neuer ſo terrible.
            Indéed Gwydonius, (quoth Therſandro) I agrée with thée in this point, that there is no carpet Knight ſo cowardly, that would not paſſe more perillous pikes to poſſeſſe ſo liuely a Dame as thou doeſt decipher, nor no daſtarde ſo daunted with dreade, which woulde not greatly indanger himſelfe to enioy ſo louely a damſell, in the fruition of whome conſiſteth nothing but ioy, bliſſe, reſt, contentation of minde, delight, happineſſe, yea, all earchly felicity.
            And yet Sir (quoth Gwydonius) your Siſter Caſtania condemnes me of folly, in venturing for ſo precious a prize; when as hope perſwaded me, that no hazard could be hapleſſe, and aſſured me that Loue and Fortune fauoureth them that are bolde: that the gods themſelues ſeeing

my perplexed paſſions, wold of pitty defend me from thoſe perilous daungers. For if Theſeus by Diuine power, were ayded againſt the force of the monſtrous Minotaure; or if Iaſon, who conſtrayned with a couetous deſire to obtaine the golden Fléece, arriuing at Colchos, was preſerued by the gods, from the dint of the deadly Dragons, no doubt Iupiter himſelfe would eyther haue made the flaggering bridge more ſtrong (conſidering that no hope of wealth, no deſire of riches, no gréedineſſe of gaine, no loue of luere, but beauty her ſelfe was the victorie I meant to vaunt off) or elſe if I had ſowled in the roaring Seas, hee would haue prouided ſom happy Dolphin, that Arion like, I might arriue at the deſired Rock: and then my daungers ſhould haue béene turned into delight, my perils into pleaſures, my hazarding into happineſſe: yea, I ſhould haue poſſeſſed that heauenly paragon, and enioyed the loue of that louely Venus, whoſe onely ſight were a ſufficient ſalue againſt all forepaſſed ſorrowes.
            Stay there, Maſter Gwydonius, quoth the Lady Melytta: for I ſée, to graunt one falſe propoſition, is to open a doore to innumerable abſurdities, and that by ſuffring you too long, of theſe ſuppoſed premiſes you will inferre ſome cauilling concluſion to your former reaſons: thus I reply, That I confeſſe neceſſity to haue no law, but I grant not the ſame of Loue: for if it be lawleſſe, it is lewde: if without limits, laſciuious: if contained within no boundes, beaſtly: if obſerued with no order, odious: ſo that lawleſſe Loue without reaſon, is the very Load ſtone to ruth and ruine.
            Sith then Maſter Gwydonius, as your ſelfe affirme, this was the pricke that puſht you into perill, how can the effect be good, when the cauſe was naught? or how can you clarkely defend your deſperate motion, proceeding of ſuch a fond and fooliſh occaſion. But it was the perfection of her comely perſon, her exquiſite feature, and rare beautie, that ſo kindled thy deſire, and ſo bewitched thy ſenſes: for who

is ſo fearefull, that beautie will not make bolde? who ſo doubtfull, that beauty will not make deſperat? yea, what ſo hard that a man will not hazard, to obtaine ſo diuine a thing, as beauty.
            Oh Gwydonius, haſt thou not heard that the Fiſh Remor
                     •
                  
                liſtening to the ſound of a Trumpet is caught of the Fiſhers, that while the Porcupine ſtandeth ſtaring at the glimmering of the ſtarres, hée is ouertaken with dogges, that the Deere gazing at the bowe is ſtriken with the bolt, that the Leopard looking at the Panthers painted skinne, is taken as a praie, and that hee which taketh too much delight to gaze vpon beauty, is oftentimes galled with griefe and miſery? Yea, his pleaſure ſhall inferre ſuch profit, and his good will ſuch gain, as if he reapt the beautifull apples of Tantalus, which are no ſooner toucht, but they turne to aſhes.
            Beauty, Gwydonius, no ſooner flouriſheth but it fadeth, and it is not fully ripe before it begin to rot: it no ſooner bloſſometh, but it withereth, and ſcarcely being toucht it ſtaineth, like to the Guyacum leafe, that hath the one halfe parched, before the other halfe be perfect: to the bird Acanthis, which hatched white, yet turneth blacke at the firſt ſtorm: or like to the ſtone Aſtites, that chaungeth colour with the onely breath of a man.
            If then Gwydonius, beautie bée ſo fading, ſo fickle, ſo momentary, ſo mouing, ſo withering, ſo waning, ſo ſoone paſſed, and ſo ſoone parched: is this the Iewell, which you count more deare than life? and the Gemme which you think worthy to bée purchaſed with the danger of death? No doubt Gwydonius, if you won the victory, you might vaunt of a great conqueſt, and if your long hope were repayed with a great hap, it ſhould be much like to his, which thinking to embrace Iuno, caught nothing but a vaniſhing cloude.
            You do well Madame (quoth Caſtania) to put an If, in it, becauſe he that vaunteth of victory before he hath wonne

fielde, may proue himſelfe a foole: hee that brags of gaines before the accounts be caſt, may perhappes put his winnings in his eies: and he that bloweth the Mort before the fall of the Buck, may verie well miſſe of his ſées: ſo he that countes himſelfe a ſpéeder before hee be a wooer, ſheweth himſelfe a vaine perſon or a vaunting patch.
            Might it not be I pray you Maſter Gwydonius, that paſſing the bridge, ſcaping the dangerous ſeas; and happily arriuing at the deſired Rocke, yet you might miſſe of your purpoſe? Yes forſooth: for many a man bendeth his bowe, that neuer killeth his game, layeth the ſtrap that neuer catcheth the fowle, pitcheth the Net that neuer getteth the fiſh, and long time are heauie wooers that neuer proue happie ſpéeders.
            So perhaps Gwydonius, you might be croſſed with a chip of the ſame miſchance, and the gorgious Dame whom you adore for a Goddeſſe, might repaie your liking with loathing, your loue with hate, your good will with deſpite, and your fixed fancie with ſmall affection, either that ſhee liked you too little, or loued another too much. All theſe doubtes Gwydonius, are carefully to be caſt, &amp; wiſedome it is to feare the worſt, and finde the beſt: but you ſir, like a luſtie champion, thinke a Ladie wonne at the firſt looke, and the good wil of women gained at the firſt glance, thinking the Gods themſelues are to be accuſed of iniuſtice, if they be not ayders to your enterpriſe, inſomuch that if in ventring ouer the perillous paſſage, you had by diſaſter Fortune fallen into the dangerous Seas, you doubtes not but that Iupiter would haue ſent a Dolphin; that Arion like, you might eſcape the fearefull ſurges: but Gwydonius be not ſo ventrous, leaſt though you harpe verie long, you get not the like hap. Theſe premiſſes conſidered, if my cenſure might ſtande for a ſentence, I déeme it better to be counted a daſtardly coward, than a deſperate caitife, better to forſake your Goddeſſe, than your God, better to liue pinched with a fewe momentarie paſſions, than with

deſperate death to deſtroy both ſoule and bodie: for there is no ſore ſuch, which in time may not be ſalued, no care ſuch which cannot be cured, no fire ſo great which may not be quenched, no loue, liking, fancie, or affection, which in time may not either be repreſſed, or redreſſed.
            
               Valericus hearing this rough reply of Caſtania, ſuppoſed that although ſhe leuelied at Gwydonius, yet ſhe ſhot at him: and ſcaring the fort ſhould be too much ſhaken with this fierce aſſault, hee ſtifly deſended the walles with this freſh alarum.
            Madame (quoth he) I ſée you will ſit nigh the walles creyou be thruſt out for a wrangler, and that you will ſpeake againſt your owne conſcience, but you will haue the conqueſt: for my owne part Madame, howſoeuer I ſéeme to like it, I will not ſaie I miſlike it, but I am ſorie you Madame Melytta ſhould ſo blaſphemouſly imblaze the armes of beautie, and ſo reckleſly raile againſt the ſacred lawes of loue: take héed for croſſing Cupid ſo crabbedly; for thogh he forgiue and forget, Venus is a woman, and will ſeeke reuenge.
            
               Valericus (quoth ſhée) take no care what daunger I incurre for ſpeaking the trueth. If I chaunce to bee harmed, it is mine owne miſhappe, and for Venus reuenge I care for it the leſſe, becauſe I feare it not: if I ſpeake againſt my ſelfe, you may ſée I am the fitter to be a Iudge, becauſe I am not partiall, nor haue any reſpect of perſons.
            Theſe quips Madame (quoth Gvvydonius) are nothing to the purpoſe: therfore in the behalfe of my ſelfe and beautie, thus I anſwere; That as there is nothing that ſo ſoone procureth a man to loath, as deformitie, ſo there is nothing which ſooner procureth a man to loue than beautie: for the moſt precious ſtone is choſen by the moſt gliſtring hew, the pureſt gold by the moſt perfect colour, the beſt fruit by the braueſt bloſſomes, and the beſt conditions by the ſwéeteſt

countenance: ſo that where beautie raigneth, there vertue remaineth, and vnder a faire face reſteth a faithfull heart▪ Sith then beautie and bountie cannot bee parted, what man is he ſo brutiſh, whom the leaſt of theſe will not breake or bend?
            And whereas you condemne me of vanitie in vaunting before the victorie, I ſaie, that if Fortune had ſo fauoured me, that I had gained the preſence of my Goddeſſe, I wold neuer haue doubted to haue obtained my deſire: for if ſhee had ſéene the deſperate daunger which I aduentured, and the fearefull perils which I paſſed for her ſake, ſhee could not but of conſcience, repaie my loue with vnfained loyaltie, and my good will with trobble gaine. And in troth I thinke it vnpoſſible, that ſuch heauenly beautie ſhould bée eclipſed with crueltie, and ſuch perfect comelineſſe bee blemiſht with curious coyneſſe.
            Why Gwydonius (quoth ſhe) doeſt thou call it crueltie not to condeſcend to the requeſt of euerie one that wooeth? or doeſt thou tearme it coyneſſe, not to yéeld to the aſſault of euerie flattering louer? Then in my iudgment, it were good for euerie woman to be both cruell and coie, that by crueltie ſhe might auoide the traine of trothleſſe wooers, &amp; by coyneſſe eſchue the troupe of faithleſſe ſutors.
            And ſo Madame (quoth Valericus) ſhe ſhould reape ſmall comfort and leſſe credit.
            Tuſh Signor Valericus (quoth Gwydonius) it pleaſeth her thus merilie to ieſt, whereas I know ſhe doth account more of a curteous dame, than of a curious damſell, and that her Ladiſhip ſo deteſſeth the name of crueltie, that ſhe would be loth to be thought to haue a mind deuoid of mercie. And in troth to leaue theſe particular inſtances, women in generall, or for the moſt part, are bountifull, curteous, ſober, chaſte, demure, not imbrued with vice, but indued with vertue: ſo that by how much womens bodies are weaker than mens, by ſo much their mindes are more ſtrong and vertuous.
            
               
What Gwydonius, (quoth ſhee) doe you thinke to be a frée man in Wales. for affering a Léeke to Saint Dauie, or to bring PAN into a fooles Paradiſe by prayſing his Pipe?
            Not ſo Madame (quoth hee) but I hope in extolling a ſouldiours life to haue Saint George to my friend, and in giuing verdit with Venus, to gaine her good will, and to reape the reward that Paris had for his cenſure.
            Mary ſir (quoth Caſtania) if you haue no better gettings you may gaine long inough, and yet liue by the loſſe: for in obtaining one friend, you ſhall reape two foes, as Paris did, who was more plagued by Pallas and Luno, than pleaſured by flattering Venus.
            
            And yet Madame (quoth hée) his miſhap ſhall not make mée to beware: for if Venus would grant me but one Lady in the world, whom moſt intirely I loue, I would neyther reſpect Pallas, luno, nor Diana her ſelfe, were ſhee neuer ſo deſpitefull.
            Yes but you would (quoth ſhée) if ſhe pinched you but with Acteons plague, to peſter your head with as many horns as a Hart: It would cauſe you coniecture your new miſtreſſe were too much giuen to the game, or that you were come from Cornet
                     •
                  o by deſcent.
            Tuſh Madame (quoth hée) doe you count Acteons hap ſuch a great harme? ſhe onely ſight in ſéeing Diana naked, was a recompence for all his inſuing ſorrowes: and if my ſelfe might inioy my wiſh, and obtaine the heauenly dame that ſo heartily I deſire, the plague of Acteon, nay, the griping griefes the ghoſtly ſpirites doe ſuffer, ſhould not counteruaile the ioy I ſhould conceiue in inioying ſo péerleſſe a iewell.
            Truly (quoth Therſandro) thou art worthy Gwydonius, to bée a Chapman, that thou bidſt ſo well for thy chaffer: and in my mind ſhee is not in Alexandria, who for her beautie is ſo to bee loued, or at the leaſt would déeme thee not worthy to be liked. But leauing theſe amorous

diſcourſes, let vs hie vs in haſt to the Court, leaſt in tarying, Orlanio miſſe vs, and ſo we bée ſhent. The company obeyi
                  ••
                the minde of Therſandro, paſſed as ſpéedily as might be to the Palace, were being arriued, they departed euery man to his own lodging.
            
               Caſtania had no ſooner conuried her ſelfe cloſely into her chamber, but her mind was moued with a thouſand ſundry motions, and ſhe felt ſuch a cruell conflict in her happeleſſe heart by the aſſault of diuers contrary paſſions, that how ſtoutly ſoeuer ſhée defended the walls, ſhée found her force too weake to reſiſt the rage of ſo reckleſſe a tyrant. Nowe the prayers Valericus powred forth came to effect, nowe Venus meant to be reuenged for the cruelty ſhe vſed to hir valiant captaine Valericus, who ſo valiantly had fought vnder the flagge of affection, &amp; yet could by no meanes preuaile. For Caſtania hearing the ſugred eloquence, which ſo ſwéetly flowed from the ſappie wit of Gwydonius, framing in her fancie the form of his face, and printing in her heart the perfection of his perſon, was ſo intangled in the ſnares of loue, as ſhe could by no reaſon redreſſe her miſerie, but wil ſhe, nil ſhe, fell into theſe bitter complaints.
            ALas witleſſe wretch (quoth ſhée) that I am, what flry flames of fancie doo frie within mée? VVhat deſire, what luſt, what hope, what truſt, what care, what deſpair, what feare, what furie? That to be pained with theſe perplexed paſſions, to me that neuer felt the force of them before, is no leſſe dolour than death it ſelf, be it neuer ſo direfull. O gods, where are now become thoſe lofty lookes I vſed to Valericus? Where is the diſdainfull dealings, the coy countenances, the curious congies, the cauſeleſſe cruelty, yea the hard heart, which ſo rigorouſly reiected the loue of him, which ſo intirely liked mée? Coulde I fond foole that I am, valiantly withſtand the aſſaultes of a worthie Gentleman, and ſhall I cowardly yeeld to an vnknowne ſtranger? Did I loath him, whoſe parentage was

little inferiour to mine, and ſhall I loue another of baſe and vile birth? Did I diſdaine to looke at the lure, and ſhall I now ſtoope without ſtall, come without call, yea and to ſuch an emptie fiſt▪ O lawleſſe Loue, O witleſſe will, O fancie, fraught full of frenzie and furie! Alas if I ſhould be ſo careleſſe as to conſent to this frantike toie, what will they ſay, that praiſed me for my vertue? Will they not as faſt diſpraiſe me for my vanitie? Will not my father fret, my kinsfolkes crie out, my friends be ſorrie, my foes and eſpecially Valericus, laugh me to ſcorne, and triumph of this my miſhappe? Yea, will not all the world wonder to ſée me alate giuen to chaſtitie, and now ſhake hands with virginitie, to yéeld my deareſt iewell and chiefeſt treaſure into the hands of a ſtragling ſtranger, who came to my fathers court without countenance or coine, wealth or worſhip, credit or calling: yea, who by his owne report is but a perſon of ſmall parentage, Seek then Caſtania to aſſwage this flame, and to quench this fire, which as it commeth wthout cauſe ſo it will conſume without reaſon. For the greateſt flowe hath the ſooneſt ebbe, the ſoreſt tempeſt hath the moſt ſodaine calme, the hotteſt loue hath his coldeſt end, and of the deepeſt deſire oft times inſueth the deadlieſt hate: ſo that ſhee which ſettles her affection with ſuch ſpeede as ſhe makes her choiſe without diſcretion, may caſt her corne ſhe knowes not where, and reapes ſhe wot not what, and for her haſtie chooſing, may perhaps get a heauy bargaine. Alas, I know this counſaile is good, but what then? Can I deny that which the deſtinies haue decréed? Is it in my power to peruert that which ye Planets haue placed? Can I reſiſt that which is ſtirred vp by the Starres? No: what neede I then make this exclamation? ſich I am not the firſt nor ſhall not bee the laſt, whome the frantike frenzy of flickering fancy, hath with more wrōg &amp; greater vantage pitiouſly oppreſſed. What though Gvvydonius be not wealthy, yet hée is wiſe: though hee be not of great parentage, yet he is of comely perſonage. It is not his

coine that hath conquered me, but his countenance: not his vading riches, but his renowmed vertues, and I far more eſtéeme a man than mony. I, but the Duke my father is not ſo baſe minded, as to beſtow me vpon ſo meane a gentleman, he neuer will conſent that poore Gwydonius ſhold inioy that which he hopeth ſome péereleſſe Prince ſhall poſſeſſe. What then? Shall I preferre my Fathers will before mine owne will, his liking before mine owne loue? no, no, I will chooſe for my ſelfe whatſoeuer my choiſe be. Why but perchance Gwydonius wil no more eſtéeme thee than thou didſt Valericus, and repay thee with as ſmall fancie, as thou him with affection. Tuſh, doubt it not Caſtania, thou art the dame which hee ſo deciphered in his dreame, thou art that Venus which hee ſaw in his viſion, thou art that Goddeſſe, whoſe beautie hath ſo bewitched him thou art that iewell to poſſeſſe, the which there is no hap ſo hard which he would not hazard, no danger ſo deſperate which he would not aduenture, no burthen ſo heauy which he would not beare, nor no perill ſo huge which hée would not paſſe. And ſhall not then Gwydonius be my ſeruant, ſith I am his Saint? ſhal not I like him which loueth me? ſith he is my ioy, ſhal I not inioy him? yes, Gwydonius is mine, and ſhall be mine in deſpite of the fales &amp; fortune.
            
               Caſtania hauing thus pitifully powred out her plaints, would gladly haue giuen Gwydonius intelligence (with modeſtie if ſhe might) of her good will towards him, and God knowes how fain Gwydonius wold haue diſcouered his feruēt affectiō, if too much feare had not aſtoniſhed him, and too great baſhfulnes ſtaied her. She therfore honering betwéen feare &amp; hope, perſeuered ſo long in her penſiue paſſions 
                  •
               nd carefull cogitatiōs, that by couert concealing of her inward ſorrow, the flame ſo furiouſly fried wthin her, yt ſhe was conſtrained to kéep her bed. Whereupon, Melytta coniecturing the cauſe of her care by the colour of her coū
               tenance, thought to fift out the occaſion of her ſorrow, that by this meanes ſhe might apply a medicine to her malady,

and finding fit opportunitie, ſhée brake with her in this wiſe.
            Madams Caſtania (quoth ſhée) ſince I haue by the Duke your father béen aſſigned to you as a companion, I haue in ſuch louing wiſe both comforted me counſailed you, as I hope you haue iuſt cauſe to ſay, that I haue moſt carefullie tendered your eſtate: for perceiuing how willing you were to follow my direction▪ I counted your wealth my weale, your pleaſure my profite, your happineſſe my ioy, and your proſperitie my felicitie. Which freindly care if it were not to be conſidered if I ſhould ſhew you what great ſorrow I ſuſtaine by your heauineſſe, you would iudge my wordes to procéed either of folly or flattery: but if your ſore be ſuch as it may be ſalued, if your care may bee cured, if your grief may be redreſſed, or your maladie mitigated by my meanes, commaund me good Caſtania, in what I may to pleaſure thee, &amp; thou ſhalt find me ſo charily to perform my charge, as my willing minde ſhall euidently bewray my well meaning. I ſee Caſtania, of late, ſuch a ſtrange metamorphoſis in thy minde, as for pleaſant conceites thou doeſt vſe penſiue cogitations, thy chéerfull countenance is chāged into lowring looks, thy merry deuiſes into mournfull dumps, and yet I cannot cōiecture the cauſe of this ſodain alteration. If want of riches ſhould worke thy woe, why, thou ſwimſt in wealth: if loſſe of friends, thou baſt infinite of noble parentage, which loues thée moſt intirely. If thou meaneſt no longer to leade a ſingle life, no doubt thy father will prouide thee of ſuch a princely match, as ſhall content thee for his perſon, &amp; countenance thee with his parentage. But if in all theſe ſuppoſes I haue miſſ ſhe marke, and haue not toucht the caſe of thy calamitie, vnfold vnto me Caſtania, what the paine is that thus doth pinch thee, and aſſure thy ſelfe I will be ſo ſecret in thy affaires, as euer Lampana was to her Ladie Cleophila.
            
            
               Caſtania hearing this friendly diſcourſe of Melytta, thought for all this faire gloſe, the text might hee too intricate,

and that theſe painted ſpéeches would proue but rotten pillers: fearing therfore the fetch, and doubting yt worſt, if ſhe bewray her mind, ſhe framed her this anſwere.
            MAdame (quoth ſhe) the incomparable curteſie and vnfained friendſhip which ſince your firſt comming I haue found in you by experience, will neither ſuffer mée to ſuſpect your Ladiſhip of flattery, nor my ſelfe willingly to be accuſed of ingratitude: for your diligence hath béene ſo great, and my deſertes ſo ſmall, that if I might but liue to requite ſome part of your good will, it were the ſecond felicitie I looke for in this life. But touching the penſiue paſſions which thus diuerſly perplexed me, I anſwer that as he which is wounded of the Bores tusk, if his ſores take aire is very hardly healed, as hee which is ſtriken with a Scorpion, if his wound take wind can neuer be cured: ſo Madam many inward maladies carry this nature, that if they bee once diſcouered, they are far ye more hardly recouered, that it is better to conceale them with griefe, than reueale them in hope of releefe.
            Not ſo Caſtania, your principle is not true: for if your paſſions procéeded of loue, which of all other inward ſores requireth greateſt ſecrecie, yet vndoubtedly the more it is diſcouered, the ſooner it is cured. For as the ſtone of Armenia being couered with Sand, burneth moſt extreamely, and no ſooner taketh aire, but it cooleth: ſo the firie flames of loue raked vp in ſilence, fry moſt ſuriouſly; but being by diſcourſe diſcloſed, they ſoone conuert from flame to fume and ſmoke. Wherfore good Caſtania impart vnto mée the matter which doth import thée ſo néere, and I ſweare vnto thee by the ſacred rites of Ceres, which is ſo honoured in Alexandria, that if thou doeſt loue where thy friends doe not like, and thy wiſh be contrary to their will, yet I will ſake all meanes poſſible to redreſſe thy ſorrowe.
            Alas good Madame, rather than you ſhould thinke mee ſo incredulous or ſuſpicious, as not to beléeue your oath, or

doubt of your ſecret dealing, I will without delay make you priuy to the cauſe of my paine, what perill ſoeuer I incurre by reuealing it. So it is Melytta, that the perfection of Gwydonius, his exquiſite qualities, &amp; excellent vertues, haue ſo fiercely aſſaulted the fort of my fancy, as I am perforce conſtrained to reſigne my liberty captiue vnto his curteſie, &amp; to make his perſon the priſon of my heart. This luckleſſe &amp; vnlikely loue, Madam, is the cauſe of my care, &amp; the ſum of my ſorrow, this frantike affection hath driuen my drooping heart to ſhew forth theſe drouſie leekes, this is it which hath made me an enemy to myſelfe, a foe to all good company, and to delight in nothing but ſorrow and ſolitarineſſe: yea, this is the ſore, which if in time it be not ſalued, will preuent by death all other miſeries.
            And is this (quoth Melytta) the pain that ſo greatly perplexeth you? Is this the care that ſo cumbers your conſcience? Is this the danger which driues you into ſuch déepe diſtreſſe? Do you think ſo ſuperſtitiouſly of Gwydonius, or ſo abiectly of your ſelfe, that you déem this matter impoſſible to be brought to paſſe? no, no, doubt not Caſtania, I my ſelfe dare abſolutely promiſe thee, that thy loue ſhall ſort to ſuch happie ſucceſſe, as thou thy ſelfe doeſt ſéeke for.
            And with that Melytta ſtayed by a ſodaine ſight ſhe had of that Saint that Caſtania ſo hartily ſerued: for Gwydonius was entring in at the chamber deere with a diſh of delicates, which Orlanio hearing his Daughter was ſo ſick, had ſent her. Melytta ſéeing that Cupid began to ſauor the cauſe of his Clients, in giuing them ſuch fit opportunitie to diſcouer their cares, went her waie, leauing Gwydonius the firſt man to play his part in this tragicall comedy, who ſéeing his goddeſſe thus ſurpriſed with ſickneſſe, was ſo gallen with griefe, ſo pinched with helliſh paſſions, and ſo tortured with extreame torments, that his colour began to change, &amp; he fetcht a déep ſigh or two, which Caſtania hearing, ſhe perceiued without touching his pulſes, the cauſe of theſe his ſodain paſſions. In fine, ſuch melancholike motions

ſo amazed his minde, that he was almoſt mute in his meſſage, yet at length incouraging himſelfe, hée preſented it vnto her in this wiſe.
            Madame (quoth he) the Duke your Father hearing of your ſodaine ſickneſſe, in token of his fatherly affection, amongſt all his dainties, hath ſent you this diſh, which hee thinks moſt méet for your diet, wiſhing your Ladiſhip to let no doubtfull motions diſtreſſe your minde, nor no carefull thoughts cumber your conſcience: for you ſhall lacks nothing if you reueale to him your want, which either your will or wiſh can deſire. And truly Madame, to manifeſt my willing duety (if the praiers of a poore Gentleman may be heard of the heauenly Gods) I wiſh that before you taſte of this feede it may turne to Nectar, whereby not only your ſickneſſe ſhould be ſalued, but your diuine beautie and vertue according to deſert ſhould be crowned with immortalitie.
            
               Caſtania perceiuing with what fernent affection Gwydonius vttered thoſe wordes, began to chéere vp her ſelfe, in hope that her good will ſhould not be repaied with ingratitude: taking therefore the preſent at his handes, and liking it neuer the worſe for his ſake that brought it, ſhe returned him this replie.
            
               Gwydonius (quoth ſhe) as I haue cauſe moſt reuerently to accept of my fathers louing curteſie, and to repay his naturall affection with moſt dutifull obedience, ſo I haue cauſe to thanke thee for thy paines, and to thinke well of thée for thy wiſh, promiſing in recompence of thy good wil, if in any reſpect I may pleaſure thee, to ſéeke and ſue to my father for preferment.
            Madame, I account the performance of my meſſage no paine, but pleaſure, and I thinke my ſelfe as much honored by this office, &amp; thrice more happy than if I ſhould in Ganimedes place preſent yt cup to Iupiter. But Madame, ſith yt to ſtop the ſtreame, is to make the floud flow more fiercelie, to repreſſe the fire, is to make it flame more furiouſly,

and to reſtraine the force of loue, is to kindle a greater flame, leaſt too long delaie ſhould bréede too great daunger, and by concealing my ſorrow I ſhould make the ſore incurable, I thought good either preſently to heare the curteous ſentence of my life, or the cruell doome of my death. So it is Madame, that too long gazing vppon the beames of your heauenly beautie, and too narrowly conſtruing ouer your vertuous conditions, I remaine ſo caught in ye ſnare of your bountie, and ſo thralled in the thréede of your vertue, that the ſtaie of my life hangeth in your hands, either to driue mee downe to helliſh miſcrie, or to boiſt mee vp to heauenly felicity. For although I haue not heretofore by dutifull ſeruice made manifeſt the loyaltie of my loue, yet ſince I firſt framed in my fancie (as in a mirrour) the ſhape of your ſurpaſſing beautie, my heart hath béene croſſed with ſuch cruell Camizados for your ſake, as if with the Target of hope I had not wi
                  •
               hſt ſtood the furious force of ſuch raging furies, I had by deſpaire béene daſhed againſt moſt dangerous rockes. Sith then Madame, the ſight of your ſwéete face hath faſt fettered my fancie in the links of loue, ſo as without your means I can neither be redreſſed nor releaſed: I humbly deſire you neither to reſiſt the motion of my well meaning, nor to reiect the deuotion of my good will, but to accept your poore Gwydonius as a faithfull ſeruant.
            
               Caſtania hearing diligentlie the faithfull diſcourſe of diſtreſſed Gwydonius, perceiuing by his ſighs the pinching ſorrow of his thoughts, and ſéeing him ſo faſt fettered in follie, on a ſodaine to giue her the ſlip had that ſhee deſired: and now her louing lookes were turned to lowring glances, her delightfull curteſie, to diſdainfull coineſſe, and ſhe thought to repaie the ſwéete meate wherewith before ſhe fed him, with moſt ſowre ſauee: not that ſhe miſliked of his loue, for it was the onelie thing ſhe deſired, but to make him the more feruent in affection, vttering theſe or ſuch like words to her ſelfe ſecretly.
            
               
And is not (Caſtania) the victorie moſt accounted of, where the conqueſt is moſt doubtfull? Is not the Caſtle which abideth the longeſt batterie, thought the richeſt bootie? Are not thoſe pearles which are ſcarcely founde and hardly gotten, euer of greateſt value: whatſo is gained by perill, is thought alwaies precious, hardly come by, warily kept. The maide that by long ſute and much trauell is obtained, by how much the more ſhe was hard in the winning, by ſo much the more ſhe will be ſwéet in the wearing: ſhe which in her virginitie is charie of her chaſtitie, in her mariage wil be as warie of her honeſtie: therfore I wil qualifie the hotloue of Gwydonius with a colde potion, and with that ſhe made him this waſpiſh anſwere.
            Why Gwydonius, ſhall the old Prouerbe be verified in thee, that the Prieſt forgets himſelfe that euer hee was a clarke, that too much familiaritie bréedes contempt? I ſée well if Apelles that cunning painter ſuffer the greaſie Souter to take a view of his curious worke, he will grow ſo malapert, as to meddle with his picture: if the proude Centaure Ixion be bidden to the feaſt of the Gods, no leſſe than Iuno her ſelfe will ſuffice him for his choiſe.
            Set a beggar on horſebacke they ſaie, and he will neuer alight. Extoll one of baſe ſtocke to any degrée of dignity, 
                  ••
               d who ſo proude and haughtie? I ſpeake this Gwydonius to thy reproofe: is thy ſtomake alate waxen ſo queaſie, that no dyet will downe but my fathers owne diſh? Wil no meaner mate ſuffice thee, vnleſſe thou match with a Princeſs? Is there no Ladie wil like thee, but my loue? Is there no courſer Dame to couet, vnleſſe thou court vnto me? Did my father promote thée to this thou art, from the ſtate of a beggar, and wilt thou now preſume to be my better? Haue my lookes béene ſo louing, my countenance ſo curteous, my glaunces ſo full of good will, as to promiſe ſo much as thou doeſt preſume? No: but one onely countenaunce in a ſeruile minde is too much incouragement. Doeſt thou thinke Gwydonius, that I account ſo meanly

of my perſon, as to match with a man of thy pitch? Shall I ſo far cracke my credit, as to cumber my ſelfe with one of thy calling? Shall I ſo ſtraine my ſtate, as to ſtoope to thy lure? No. Where is thy coine to maintaine my countenance? Where is thy wealth to vpholde my worſhip? Where is thy patrimonie to counteruaile my perſonage? But put caſe I accepted of thy ſute doeſt thou thinke euer to gaine my fathers good will? Doeſt thou thinke it is poſſible to compaſſe his conſent? Doeſt thou hope euer to take him in ſuch a vaine, as he will bee willing to giue his verdite on thy ſide? No Gvvydonius: but if he were priuie to this thy preſumption, he would repaie thy follie with too much furie, he would vnplume thee of all his feathers, that like Aeſops Crow thou mighteſt receiue the reward of thy raſhneſſe. If therefore thou loue thine owne welfare, kéep thy ſelfe within thy boundes, and ſtriue not farther than thy ſléeue will ſtretch, leaſt in climing too high, thou catch the ſorer fall.
            
               Caſtania hauing thus ſharply ſhaken vp my yong youth Gwydonius, thought ſhe had giuen him a ſufficient cooling Card: but he no whit diſmaied with this deniall, like a luſty champion entered pell-mell with her in this wiſe.
            Madame (quoth he) the poore ſhoomaker was not blamed for viewing Apelles picture, but becauſe in finding fault he went beyond his ſhooe: the Centaure Ixion was not reproued for his familiaritie with Iuno as he was a gueſt, but in that his ſute tended to the ſacking of her honeſtie: familiaritie neuer bréeds contempt in a good mind, neither am I to be accuſed of that crime: for the moſt ſeruile ſlaue in Alexandria (I call the heauens as witneſſes of my words) doth not with more louing dutie reuerence &amp; honor your perſon &amp; parentage, than doth your poore ſeruāt Gwydonius. Well Madame, though my nature and nurture be ſuch in your ſight, as they bewray my bringing vp and birth to be ſo baſe, as if I meane to drawe my deſcent, I muſt (as you ſay) imblaze mine armes in the beggars coat,

yet thus much I anſwere in reſpecte of my Parents, and without arrogancie thus farre I ſtand on my pantofles, that the credite I haue in your fathers Court, is not coequall with the calling I haue in mine owne Countrie, if I did not count it more greater credite and honour, in that I haue ſometime enioyed a curteous countenance of your ſwéete ſelfe ſince my comming. But it I were the moſt famous Prince in the world, I ſo eſtéeme your diuine beauty and exquiſite vertue, as I would thinke my ſelfe farre vnworthy to poſſeſſe ſuch heauenly perfection: which if I could obtain, the diſpleaſure of your Father could no whit diſcourage mee, his thundering threats coulde no whit amaze mée: no, death it ſelfe could neuer daunt my minde, were it neuer ſo deſpightfull. But who (ſay you) can lay their loue where is no deſert, and where want breedes a flat deniall?
            Ah Caſtania, Nature by her ſecret motion hath indued all creatures with ſome perfect qualities, to ſupply yt want which bréeds miſliking. The Moule depriued of ſight hath a wonderful hearing: the Hare being very fearefull is moſt ſwift: the Fiſh hauing no eares, hath moſt cleare eyes: ſo though want of dignitie diſgrace me, though want of coin diſcountenance me, though lacke of wealth impaires my credit, yet Nature hath giuen me ſuch a loyall and louing heart, as I hope in the perfection of that, ſhee hath ſupplyed the want of all the reſt: So that Madam though I want coine, I do not want conſtancy, though I haue no lands, yet I lack not loyaltie, though I want wealth yet I want not will to end my life to do you good, or ſpende my time to do you ſeruice.
            
               GWydonius hauing thus pithily replyed, draue Caſtania into a great doubt, whether ſhee ſhould preſently conſent to his demand, or ſtill driue him off with delayes, whether ſhee ſhould yeelde the fort at the firſt skirmiſh, or ſtand to the doubtfull euent of battayle: at length leaſt ſhee

ſhould digreſſe from the courſe of woman kind, ſhe thought beſt to deuie that ſhee moſt of all deſired, and therefore then gaue him this anſwere.
            
               GWydonius (quoth ſhée) in what ſtate you came to my fathers Court I knowe, what you are by diſcent I knowe not, nor I care not, and if I did it auaileth not: but this I ſay, that it is hard taking of Fowle, when the net is deſcried, and il catching of fiſh, when the hook is bare: impoſſible it is Gwydonius, to infer beléefe, when no credit will be giuen, and to deceiue her that ſpieth thy fetch: when the ſtring is broken, it is hard to hit the white, and when a mans credit is called in queſtion, perſwaſions can little preuatle. It is a religion amongſt louers to ſweare and forſweare, to promiſe mountains, and to perform moule hils, to be ripe without and rotten within, to carrie a ruſty blade in a veluet ſcabberd, and a ſiluer bell with a leaden clapper. Therfore Gwydonius, I had rather miſtruſt too ſoone, than miſtike too late, I had rather feare my choice than rue my chance, I had rather ſtop at the brim, than at the bottom: for the ſignet being ſet, it is too late to break the bargain, and fancy being once fixt it is too late to reclaime affection. For the loue of a woman is like the Oyle of Flint, which being once congealed will neuer be diſſolued: like the Diamond, being once rubbed with the gum of a Pine trée, will neuer be broken: ſo if I fancy any, ſith I mean not to fléete, it ſhall be ſuch a one, as I néed not repent mée.
            And whereas you ſay, Gwydonius, that in deſpight of Fortune, Nature hath giuen you a louing heart, I my ſelf ſurely did neuer déem any leſſe, but thought you of the crue of thoſe louers that loue too much, hauing as manie Ladies as they haue wits, and that is not a fewe, who count that euery face muſt haue a newe fancie, and if they ſée a thouſand they muſt be all viewed with a ſigh: which conſidered Gwydonius, I mean not to like nor to loue neither you nor any other.
            
               
ANd ſhall theu Madame (quoth hée) my merite bée repayed with no meede? Shall my good wil be requited with no gaine? ſhall I haue in lieu of my life no liking? will you ſo ſwaru
                  •
                from iuſtice, as not to giue euery one according to his deſert? at the leaſt, recompence not deſire with deſpight; and hearty loue, with loathing hate: for as the Poet ſaith: Quis 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſuccenſet amanti?
            
            Well Gwydonius, as I will not be thy priuie friend, ſo I will not be thine open foe, and as I cannot be ſo curteous as to requite thee for thy pains, ſo I will not be ſo cruell as to deſpight thee for thy preſumption, and where as thou craueſt gaines for thy good will, I am content to remaine thy unwilling debter.
            Yet Madame (quoth hée) where ſhe debt is confeſt, there remaineth ſome hope of recouery: for though the creditor bee neuer ſo vnwilling to pay the debt being due, hée ſhall by conſtraint of law and his own confeſſion, (maugre his face) be forced to make reſtitution.
            Truth Gwydonius (quoth ſhée) if he commence his action in a right caſe, and the plea he puts in, proue not imperfect. But yet take this by the waie, it is hard for that plaintife to recouer his coſtes, where the defendant béeing Iudge, ſetsdowne the ſentence.
            
               Gwydonius féeling himſelfe pincht to the quicke with this prettie quip, made no further reply: but leaſt his long tarrying might bréed ſuſpicion, wiſhing his Miſtris welfare, tooke his leaue very ſolemnly and ſorrowfully, of Caſtania, who ſéeing him gone and her ſelfe alone, began thus to muſe and meditate vpon the ſharpe anſweres ſhee had giuen her beſt beloned Guydonius.
            
            VVHy Caſtania, what franlike fully hath made thée thus far to forget thy ſelfe? Is ſhe 
                  •
               ird inti
                  ••
               d to the ſtrap by the ſhewe of the nets, is the For allured to the train by the view of the trap? wil the Mauſe march vnder

that Enſigne, where the Catte proclaimeth her ſelfe Captaine? will the ſiltie Doue laie her Egges in the Fawlcons neaſt? or is it the meanes to haue him to thy friend, whom with bitter blowes thou doeſt rebuke? is there no other call for curteſie, but crueltie? doeſt thou finde no fitter meanes to obtaine a ceaſonable requeſt, but by a rigorous repulſe? or is it the nature of women to defie that outwardly which they moſt deſire inwardly, to loath that in their mouth, which they loue in their minde, to reiect that with their hand, which they moſt willingly would receiue in their heart? Doeſt thou thinke Caſtania, to drawe Gwydonius to thy deſire, by deteſting him? Doeſt thou think to allure him to thy loue, by loathing him? Doeſt thou ſuppoſe to win him to thy will by theſe waſpiſh anſweres? No: and what, doeſt thou know what perill will enſue of this repulſe, what daunger will follow of this deniall? Is it like he will put it vp patiently? No ſure, either looke to haue his extreame loue turned to extreame hate, or that he will perſiſt no longer in the purſute of his purpoſe. Oh would to God Gwydonius, thou wert againe to begin thy demaund, and I to frame mine anſwere: then would I ſalue thy ſores with ſwéete ſtrops, not with cutting coraſiues: then would I mitigate thy maladie with eaſie medicines, not with pinching plaiſters: then would I comfort thee with conſent, not daunt thee with denials. But alas, Had I wiſt now comes too late: and therefore Caſtania, if thou haſt made a faulte, ſeeke to make amendes, and recompence this his iniurie with moſt friendly curteſie.
            And with that came Melytta: who comforting Caſtania, paſſed away the reſt of the day in parle.
            
            But Gwydonius, who all this while had a flea in his eare, was dr
                  ••
               en into aquandarie with the tauting qu
                  •
               p
                  •
                of his miſtreſſe, fearing that although his accounts were great, his gaines ſhould be little; and though he made a verie long harueſt, yet he ſhould reape but a very ſmal crop,

thinking that vnder ſuch ſowre ſpéeches, a ſugred minde could not bée contayned: yet at laſt entering into deeper conſideration with himſelfe, hee fell into theſe tearmes.
            But by the ſweete (quoth hée) how ſhould we knowe the ſower? but by the blacke, how ſhould wée knowe the white? hée neuer greatly accounteth of proſperitie which hath not béen before pinched with aduerſitie: which perchaunce Caſtania meanes to make me trie by experience, thinking to féede mee firſt with bitter broaths, that hereafter dainty fare may more delight mee: to daunt mée with the raging ſtormes of deniall, that the calme of her conſent may more content mée: to make mée taſte the bitter pilles of annoy, that hereafter I may inioy the greater ioy: for the chilling colde of winter makes the ſprowting ſpring time ſéeme farre more pleaſant, the parching heate of ſommer, makes the coole ſhade more delightfull, and the frowning looks of Caſtania, will make her ſmiling countenāce ſéeme more chéerful. Then ceaſe not Gwydonius, to purſue thy ſuite with endleſſe paine, eyther to enioy her curteſie or taſte of her cruelty, to thy great happineſs or extream heauineſſe.
            
               GWydonius thus like a valiant Champion, neuer amazed with any chip of miſfortune, neuer feared to giue the aſſault for all the firſt repulſe, but onely ſought opportunity how he might in cloſe combate once again incounter with Caſtania; vowing eyther to returne with ſome ſigne of victory, or elſe to put limme and life in hazard. But fortune meaning pleaſantly to ſport with this yoong nouice, would neuer miniſter ſuch fit occaſion, yt he might haue ſolitary acceſſe to his goddeſſe. For, Caſtania of pretē
               ded purpoſe ſo warily auoyded his company, and with ſuch diſdainfull lookes ſo reiected his dutie, as Gwydonius was conſtrained to ſéek his courſe by a new compaſſe, deliuering vnto one of her maids a friendly Letter, to this effect.
            
               
                  
                  Diſdained Gwydonius to his deſired Caſtania, health.
                  WHoſo taſteth (Madam Caſtania) of the riuer Licos in India, féeleth ſuch a continual flame to frie &amp; fret his entrailes, as it is more torture than to bée tormented with the helliſh furies, and this griefe can neuer bee redreſſed, but with drinking the bloud of his déereſt friend. And as he that is venomed with the Phalanga, féeleth ſuch painful paſſions, as he runneth mad, and is onely cured by means of moſt harmonious Muſicke: So Madame, the furious heate of fancy, doth ſo ſcorch and ſcalde my hapleſſe heart, and doth perplexe me wiſh ſuch helliſh pangues, as death it ſelfe were thrice more deſired, than thus to driue my dayes in dolour. And I haue ſo gréedily ſwallowed vp the ſugred poyſon of yourdinine beautie, as through the extremity of pinching griefe, which ſo direfully diſtreſſeth mee, I reſt as one diſtract from his ſenſes, not poſſible to obtain a cure for this my calamitie, vnleſſe with the deawe of mutuall affection you mitigate my maladie, or with the pleaſant harmonie of your muſicall conſent, you appeaſe my miſery.
                  Sith then Madam, my care procéedeth from your beautie, let my ſore be cared by your bounty: ſith the perfection of your perſon hath wrought my bane, let the effect of your courteſte procure my bliſſe, and reiect him not ſo rigorouſly which reſpecteth you ſo reuerently: loath him not ſo hatefully, which loueth you ſo heartily: nor repay not his dutifull amity, with ſuch deadly enmitie. The pike fatally proſecuteth the fiſh Ma
                           •
                        gra, as his mortall foe, and yet ſéeing him ſnared on the fiſhers hooke, he ſpéedily ſhreddeth the line in ſunder, to deliuer him: the Snake moſt deadly deteſteth the field mouſe, and yet ſhe heapeth vp in her hole ſtore of prouiſion to preuent her enemies penurie: and ſhall then Madame, your crueltie ſo farre excéede

theſe ſenſeleſſe creatures? ſhall your rigour be ſo voyd of reaſon, as to requite your friend with paine, when they repaie their foes with pleaſure? to driue your friends into diſtreſſe, when they redéeme their foes from danger? no Madame, I hope you will not counteruaile my conſtancy with ſuch diſcurteſie, nor ſo reckleſly regarde your poore Gwydonius, whoſe loue and loyalty is ſo great, that as the ſtones which are found in the Riuer Lynceſtis, the lowder the winde bloweth, and the déeper they are drencht in the water, the more they burne and blaze: ſo the more you ſéek to coole my fancy with diſdaine, the more my affection is kindled with deſire: the more you loath, the more I like: the greater deſpayre you driue me into by denials, yt greater hope, (incouraged by conſtancie) I haue to obtain my requeſt: in which feruent affection, I meane to remayne without chaunge, crauing in liewe of this my loyaltie, that you will ſpéedily fend the meſſenger of preſent conſolation, to him which pineth away, and is yours onely and euer.
                  
                     Still in hope, Gwydonius.
                  
               
            
            
               CAſtania hauing receiued this Letter from her aſſured friend Gwydonius, although ſhe perceiued by the cō
               tents that his loue was not counterfait, but conſtant: not light, but loyall: not floting, but faithfull: and that ſhee ſhould not finde him immutable in proſperitie, which was ſo permanent in aduerſity; Yet (whether it were for coyneſſe in conſent, or charineſſe of choyſe I know not) ſhee once againe thought to ſound him more déeper, to kéep out ſtill the flagge of deſtance, and to ſpend one Vollee of ſhot in the face of her enemy, to ſee if a hot skirmiſh woulde make him flie the fielde. And if like a valiant ſouldier hee did manfully march on, and not refuſe the brunt of the battaile, ſhe would then reſigne the fort of her freedome into his hands, and yéeld vp the bulwarke of her breaſt, which

ſo long he had battered, that triumphantly he might ſet vp Trophees in ſigne of moſt victorious conqueſt. To put therefore the matter in queſtion, ſhee returned him this anſwere.
            
               
                  Caſtania to Gwydonius, which hopeth in vaine, health.
                  MAſter Gwydonius, you Letter being more haſtily receiued then heartily read, I perceiue by the contents that you are ſtill perplexed with your pen-ſicke paſſions, and that your diſeaſe is incurable: for if your paines may bes appeaſed, or your maladie mitigated by no medicine but by my means, you are like either to pay your due vnto death, or ſtil to linger in diſtreſſe. My cunning is too ſmall to enterpriſe the compoſition of any ſecret ſimples, and my calling too great to become a Phyſition to ſuch a paltering patient, ſo that I neyther can nor wil cure another mans harm by mine owne miſhap. To loue him whom I cannot like, were but to wreſtle againſt mine owne will, to flatter him whom I mean not to fancie, is but a méere tricke of extream folly. What the cauſe is Gwydonius, that thy good will reaps ſo ſmall gain, and that ſo rigorouſly I repaie thy loue with hate, I know not, vnleſſe the conſtellation of the Starres by ſome ſecret influence haue ſo appointed it in the calculation of our natiuety. But this I am ſure, that as no Serpent can abide the ſmell of a Harts horne, as the Panther eſcheweth the companie of the Ownce, as the Vulture is mortall enemy to the Eele, and as it is impoſſible to hatch vp a Swan in an Eagles neaſt, to temper Oyle and Pitch together in one veſſell, to mixe the bloud of a Lyon and a Woolfe in one bowle, and to procure amitie betwéene the Fawlcon called Tilo, and the Foxe, ſo hard is it to procure mee by ruthfull requeſt to be thy friend, which am by inſtinct of nature thy profeſſed foe; and as hard to winne me to thy Wife, who ſo little

likes of thy loue, that the verie remembrance of thy perſon makes me fall into moſt hatefull paſſions. Ceaſe then Gwydonius, to condemne me of crueltie, and leaue off at laſt to appeale to my curteſie: for thou ſhalt alwaies be ſure to féele the one, and neuer to finde the other. Yet leaſt thou ſhouldeſt accuſe me of ingratitude, though I cānot inwardly mitigate thy miſerie, yet I will outwardly teach thee to apply ſuch plaiſters (as if the experience of them proue true) ſhall greatly appeaſe thy paine. Plinie, Gwydonius, reporteth, that he which drinketh of the riuer Aucrna, cooleth and mortifieth his affections; but if the water be toucht by any meanes before it be drunke, the vertue thereof is of no value. He that weareth the feathers of the bird Ezalon about him, ſhall euer be fortunate in his loue, but if they be not puld when the Sunne is eclipſed, they are of no forer: and to conclude, there is nothing that ſooner driueth away amorous conceites, then to rub the temples of thy head with the ſweat of an aſſe: which if you can performe if, as no doubt you may put it in practice, I hope you ſhalbe redreſſed from your intolerable griefe, and I releaſed from ſuch an importunate ſute.
                  
                     Forced by the deſtinies ſtill to denie thee, Caſtania.
                  
               
            
            
               GWydonius hauing viewed &amp; reuſewed ouer this Letter, ſéeing the rigorous reſolutiō of his miſtreſſe couldby no meanes be remoued, and that a moſt ſeuere ſentence was pronounced againſt him by a moſt iniurious Iudge, was driuen into a doubt whether he ſhould ſtill wt plaints ſue for pittie, or elſe blaſphemouſly exclaime againſt her brutiſh crueltie, whether he ſhold bewray his parents and parentage to the Duke and her, or ſtill ſtand to the doubtfull chance of fortune, to purſue his purpoſe ſtill wt plaints: her helliſh crueltie perſwaded him to blaſpheme againſt her: the ſinceritie of his loue, would not let him to bewray

his birth: diuers dangers might inſue: to ſtand to the chance of Fortune, was ſtill to hazard without hope: combred thus with diuers cogitations, at laſt he determined to breake vp the batterie, and to lay too an inuincible hold, and to returne with as much ſpéed, as might be to his father Clerophontes Court, there by abſence to mitigate the malady which ſo grieuouſly moleſted him: yet he thought before his departure to giue her a friendly farewell, that might both confirme his conſtancy, and condemne her cruelty, which he framed to this effect.
            
               
                  Guydonius to Caſtania, proſperous ſucceſſe in all her affaires.
                  I Meane not, moſt mercileſſe miſtreſſe, any longer to ſuefor mercie, nor with pittifull plaints to trouble your patience, ſith to ſtirre that which the Starres hath ſtayed, is to ſtriue againſt the ſtreame, and to force that which the Fates haue framed, is to couet to bee counted a foole: but as one whom Fortune meanes to make a myrrour of miſery, and ouer whom Venus herſelfe meanes to vaunt as of a moſt hapleſſe vaſſall, I ſorrowfully ſend you this fainting farewell, as a faithfull token of my feruent affection: for ſéeing neither my perſon cā pleaſe, nor my liuing like you, nor my baſe calling content you, nor I myſelfe reape anie guerdon for my good will; to auoide the remembraunce of theſe paſſions, which renue my paines, and to aſſwage the rigour of my raging loue, I purpoſe as ſpéedily as winde and weather will permit mee, to abandon the place of your abode, not incenſed by furie, as one in deſpight, but inforced by the rage of fancis, to depriue myſelfe of all delight, either to conſume in ſolitary cares without compaſſion, or by abſence to mitigate ſome part of my martyrdome: for to hope ſtill, I ſée is but to heape woe vpon wretchedneſſe, and care vpō calamity. Yet Madame, thus much I ſay, that Dido Quéene of Carthage loued Aeneas, a baniſhed exile,

and a ſtragling ſtranger. Euphinia daughter to the king of Corinth, and heire apparant to his crowne, who for her feature was famous throughout all the Eaſt Countries, vouchſafed to apply a ſouereigne plaiſter to the furious paſſion of Achariſto, her fathers bondman. The dutcheſſe of Malphey choſe for her husband her ſeruant Vlrico: and Venus, who for her ſurpaſſing beautie was canonized for a goddeſſe, diſdained not the loue of limping Vulcan. They madame, reſpected the man, &amp; not their money, their wils, and not their wealth: their loue, not their liuings: their cō
                     ſtancy, not their coine: their perſon, not their parentage: &amp; the inward vertue, not the outward value. But you are ſo addicted to toy• opinion of Danae, that vnleſſe Iupiter himſelfe be ſhrouded in your lap, vnder the ſhape of a ſhower of gold, he ſhall haue the repulſe, for all his deitie: ſéeing then it is not in my poore power, eyther to performe or practiſe it, I ceaſe off to ſéeke for impoſſibilities: promiſing in what coaſt or Country ſo euer I ſhall remain, to haue my heart wholly dedicated to your diuine beautie and vertue, both by dutie and ſeruice, and ſo commending my health to the gods, I bid you farewell.
                  
                     Yours, while he is Gwydonius,
ſans eſpoier.
                  
               
            
            
               CAſtania hauing receiued this letter from Gwydonius, perceiuing the conſtant mind of the yong Gentleman, that theſe his proteſtations were not vanitie, but veritie: not trifling, but troth: no ſignes of fléeting fancie, but of a firme affection: ſtanding a while in a dumpe, at laſt ſhe fel into this diſcourſe.
            I now (quoth ſhée) both ſée and trie by experience, that there is no fiſh to fickle, but will come to the bayt: no Doe ſo wild, but will ſtand at the gaze: no Hawke ſo haggard, but will ſtoope at the lure: no Nieſſe ſo ramage, but wil be reclaimed to the Lunes: no fruite ſo fine, but the Caterpiller

will conſume it: no Adamant ſo hard but will yéeld to the file, no metall ſo ſtrong, but will bende to the ſtampe: no mayd ſo frée, but loue will bring her to bondage and thraldome. And doo I call it bondage, fond foole, to be bound vnto beauty? is it ſlauery to bee ſubiect vnto vertue? is it thraldome to liue in league with him who will like mee in my youth, and loue me in my age, in whom I ſhall find nothing but pleaſure and contentation? who will be the hauen of my happineſſe, wherein I may reſt: &amp; the port of my proſperity wherein I may bee ſafe harboured from the tempeſts of froward fortune, and ſhroud meee from the bitter blaſts of bale? Shal I repent me, ſith my bargain is good? or complaine of the loſſe of libertie, ſith I haue a chaunge for farre more worthy chaffer? Shall I grudge when the gods are agréed? or deferre it, when the deſtinies driue it? or frowne at it, ſith fortune frames it? No: Gwydonius, is my Saint, and him will I ſerue; hee is my ioy, and him will I inioy. He hath laid the ſiege, and hee ſhall ſacke the Citie: he hath abode the batterie, and he ſhall haue the bulwarke of my breaſt: he hath fought the combat, and he ſhall be victor in the conqueſt. For I cannot be ſo vnnaturall, to reward his loue with loathing: ſo without reaſon, to defraud him of his right: ſo diueliſh, for his déepe deſire to giue him a dolefull diſh of deſpaire. No, no, I haue ſettled with my ſelfe, that if euer I marry, Gwydonius ſhalbe the man I will match with. And therefore as I haue driuen him off with delayes, and fed him with folly, ſo nowe I wil ſend him a ſettled anſwere of my good will and fauour: as I haue giuen him cutting corraſiues, ſo I will ſend him confects of comfort. As I haue béene fearefull to ſhewe my liking for the better tryall: ſo now I will be bolde to ſhewe my loue in token of a better truſt. And with that ſhe wrote him a Letter to this effect.
            
               
                  
                  Caſtania to Gwydonius, wiſhing him ſuch happie ſucceſſe, as either fortune or the fates can allow him.
                  
                     PLato, Gvvidonius, being demanded why hée would neuer condeſcend to requeſts of his moſt deareſt friends, without great entreatie and long ſuite, anſwered, ye things lightly granted (though neuer ſo coſtly) are ſmally accounted of: which ſaying Gvvidonius, I take as a ſufficient excuſe for my folly: for my ſtraightneſſe in wordes was no ſtraungeneſſe in minde, my bitter ſpéeches were written with my hand, not wrought with my heart, my deniall was onely for thy better tryall, and thoſe rigorous repulſes were either to rip vp thy fained fancie, or ſeruent affection: for if thou hadſt retired at the firſt foyle, I woulde haue thought thy fancie but a flaſh, ready to be quenched with the leaſt miſling deaw of miſfortune. But ſince thou haſt kept thy courſe ſo rightly by thy compaſſe, amidſt moſt daungerous rockes, and haſt ſtoode to thy tackling againſt all the bluſtering blaſtes of Fortune; Aſſure thy ſelfe, in lieu of this thy loue, thou haſt not héeretofore found mée ſo diſdainfull, as hèereafter thou ſhalt finde me dutifull, neither did I euer reiect thée ſo curriſhly, as I will accept thée curteouſly, béeing ready to reſtore the iniury I haue offered thée, with any curteſie that thou mayeſt either honeſtly require, or I iuſtly affoord. But alaſſe Gwydonius, what curteſie ſhall I euer be able to ſhew thée, that may counteruaile thy kindneſſe? How entirely ſhall I loue thée to requite thy loyaltie? What duetie can bee a due recompence to this thy good will? yea, if by any meanes I can quit this thy loue, I neuer doubt to bee déemed ingratefull while I liue. Thy worthy conſtancie (Gvvidonius) hath won the caſtle which many haue beſieged, and thou haſt obteined that which diuerſe haue ſought to gaine: yet it is not the ſhape of thy beautie, but the hope of thy loyaltie,

which entiſeth me: not thy faire face, but thy faithfull heart: not thy comly countenance, but thy modeſt curteſie: not thy wordes, but thy vertues: not thy wealth, but thy wit: for ſhe that builds her fancy vpon ſuch fading ſubiects, tieth her loue to the incōſtant whéele of Fortune. And what though the duke my father bee incenſed againſt me, for making (in his mind) ſo careleſſe a choiſe? What care I for his friendſhip, ſo I haue thy fauour? let him fret, let my friends frowne, let liuings be loſt, hap what hap will, no miſling ſhowers of miſchāce, no bayſterous blaſts of aduerſitie, no terrible tempeſt of diſaſter fortune, ſhall make my conſtant minde in any reſpect to mooue: no torments, no trauaile, no care, no calamitie, no penurie, no pouertie, no, onely the loſſe of life, ſhal diminiſh my loue: in lieu wherof remaine thou but conſtant, and in pledge of my proteſted good wil, haue héere my heart and hand, to be thine in duſt and aſhes.
                  
                     Thine, though the Gods ſay no, Caſtania.
                  
               
            
            THis Letter béeing moſt luckily deliuered into the hands of Gwydonius, I leaue you to iudge Gentlemen into what a quandarie this yong youth was brought, to ſée ſuch a ſodaine change, and ſo happie a chaunce, as to haue his helliſh bale requited with heauenly bliſſe, his deſpightfull annoy, with delightfull ioy: his heauineſſe with happineſſe, and doubtfull deſpaire turned to aſſured hope: to ſée Fortune which of late deffed him as a foe, nowe to imbrace him as a friend, and to will that hee did wiſh: to ſée his miſtreſſe crueltie turned to curteſie, her diſdaine to deſire, her bitter pilles to ſugered potions, her ſtormie repulſes to calme conſent, and her contemptuous proteſtations, to moſt conſtant promiſes. For if the carefull captiue, who by the doome of the Iudge expecteth each houre to die, reioyceth when he heareth his pardon pronoūced, no doubt

               Gwydonius ioy could be no leſſe, ſith denial was his death, and conſent the conſerue to heale his woundes: the greater care, the greater ioy: the more paine, the greater pleaſure: the more helliſh miſerie, the more heauenly felicitie. Yea, Gwydonius was driuen into ſuch an extaſie for ioy, that he was in doubt, whether this Letter was preferred to him indéede, or preſented to him in a viſion: whether he were rapt into a traunce, or rauiſhed with ſome drowſie ſlumber: but at laſt perceiuing it to be no fained fantaſie, ſuch a déep deſire inforced his affection, as he thought euerie moment a moneth, euerie houre a yeare, euerie day a thouſand, vntill he might fréely enioy the preſence &amp; ſight of his loue and Ladie Caſtania. Fortune meaning to aduance him to the toppe of her inconſtant whéele, brought it ſo to paſſe, that before the wéeke was ended, he ſpied Caſtania walking alone in the garden: which ſodain ſight ſo reuiued his ſenſes, that without any dread or doubt, he mā
               fully marcht on towards her, and was as haſtily and hartily incountred by Caſtania: who embracing Gwydonius in her armes, welcommed him with this ſalutation:
            As the Whale (Gwydonius) maketh alwaies ſigne of great ioy at the ſight of the fiſh called Talpa Marina, as yt Hinde greatly delighteth to ſée the Leopard, as the Lyon fawneth at the view of the Vnicorne, &amp; as he which drinketh of the Fountaine Hipenis in Scythia, féeleth his mind ſo drowned in delight, that no griefe thogh neuer ſo great, is able to aſſwage it: ſo Gwydonius I conceiue ſuch ſurpaſſing pleaſure in thy preſence, and ſuch heauenly felicitie in the ſight of thy perfection, that no miſerie though neuer ſo monſtrous, is able to amaze mée, no dolour though neuer ſo direfull, is able to daunt mée, nor no miſhappe though neuer ſo perillous, is able to make me ſinke in ſorrow, as long as I enioy thy preſence, which I count a ſoueraine preſeruatiue againſt all carefull calamities. That

as he which taſteth of the hearb Hyacinthus is neuer combred with care, and as he that weareth the ſtone Agathes about him, is ſurely defenced againſt all enſuing ſorrows: ſo enioying the ſight of thy ſéemely ſelfe, and féeding mine eyes with the forme of thy feature, I thinke my ſelfe ſufficiently ſhrowded againſt all the tempeſtuous ſhowers of ſiniſter fortune. And to proue theſe my promiſes to bee no fained vanities but faithfull veritie, I commit my ſelfe, my ſtaie, and ſtate into thy handes, to diſpoſe of me at thy pleaſure, wiſhing rather to liue with thee in moſt diſtreſſed penurie, than to linger héere in moſt fortunate proſpeperitie.
            
               Gwydonius liſtening attentiuely to this ſugred harmonie, was ſo rauiſhed with the ſight of her ſwéete face, and ſo rapt into a traunce with the contemplation of her beauty, that as the Lyon taſting of the gumme Arabicke becommeth ſenſeleſſe, as the Bull by browſing on the barke of a Iuniper trée falleth aſléepe, as the Camell ſtandeth aſtoniſhed at y• ſight of a Rat: ſo Gwydonius ſéeing in his armes the Saint whome in heart he did honour, and imbracing y• Goddeſſe whom with moſt déep deuotion he did adore, was ſo amazed, that he was not able to vtter one word, as witneſſe of his happineſſe, vntill at laſt gathering his wits together, he began thus to reply:
            
               CAſtania (quoth he) it is an axiome in Philoſophie, that the colour ioyned hard to the ſight, hindreth the ſenſe: the flower put into the noſethrill, ſtoppeth the ſmelling: the Wine veſſell being full, lettes paſſe no Wine, though neuer ſo well vented: the waterpot being filled to the brim yéeldes forth no licour, though hauing a thouſand holes: ſo where the minde is ſurcharged with ouermuch ioy, or too much pleaſure, there the tongue is both tyed, and the ſenſes ſo reſtrained, that the heart is neither able to conceiue the ioy, nor the tongue able to expreſſe the pleaſure.

Which, Caſtania, I now ſpeak by proofe, and know by experience: for I am ſo drowned in delight by enioying that Princely Gemme, which I eſtéeme the rareſt and richeſt Iewell, not onely in Alexandria, but in all the world, and ſo puffed vp in pleaſure by thy diuine preſence: Yea, thy faithfull and vnfeined affection, the promiſe of thy conſtancy, and the hope of thy loyaltie, the report of thy chaſtitie, and the renowme of thy modeſtie, the force of thy beautie, and the fame of thy vertue: But aboue all thy prodigall bounty, in beſtowing theſe heauenly perfections on thy poore Gwydonius, béeing by perſon and parentage moſt vnworthy to poſſeſſe them, ſo ſurchargeth my ſillie heart with exceſſiue ioie; that my tongue not being able in part to expreſſe the extreame pleaſure of my minde, I am with Philiſtion the comicall Poet, conſtrayned by ſilence to vnfolde that affection, which in words the filed phraſe of Demoſthenes were not able to decipher. But this aſſure thy ſelfe Caſtania, that if Iuno would aduaunce me to hée Monarch of the worlde, if Pallas would preferre mée to excéede hautie Hercules in valour, if Venus would preſent me with ſome princely peece of heauenly perfection, yet would I not ſo gladly receiue their proffers, as I do gratefully accept the promiſe of thy loue and loyaltie. No: I account the treaſure of Cioeſus but traſhe, in reſpect of the guerdon of thy good will: I account the fortune of Caeſar but follie, reſpecting the fruites of thy fauour: I eſtéeme the dignities of Priamus as dregges, in reſpect of thy diuine perfection. Yea, Caſtania, I am ſo ſnared with thy beautie, and ſo intangled in the trappe of thy bountie, as I ſhall neuer leaue to loue thée, nor euer begin to like anie other.
            IT is eaſie Gwydonius (quoth Caſtania) to purchaſe credite, where the partie is alreadie perſwaded, and to infer beléefe, where euerie word is counted an Oracle. Therefore omitting theſe frinolous proteſtations, thus much I

ſay touching the purpoſe. Cecillius Metellus was wont to ſay, that as it was neceſſary that old men ſhould be graue in counſaile, ſo it was expedient yong men ſhould be ſecret in loue: and therfore when the contract was made betwéene Fuluius and his daughter, hée ſealed vp their lips with his ſignet, meaning that to violate the ſecret conference of loners, was to commit a ſecond ſacriledge. I ſpeak this Gwydonius, as one careful of thy ſtaie, and my ſtate: for if Orlanio my father ſhould but once heare of our loue, or ſuſpect our liking, it would bréed thy miſhap and my miſerie: yea, no doubt hee woulde ſpéedily preuent our pretence, which would be thy care and my calamity. Diſpoſe our affaires at thy pleaſure, but diſouer not our purpoſe: if thou haſt wonne the Caſtle, vaunt not of the conqueſt: if thou haſt made a good market, bragge not of thy gaines: leaſt by boaſting of thy bootie, thou looſe thy preie, &amp; be thought a pratler. And Gwydonius, aboue all men beware of Valericus, leaſt vnder the ſhape of a friend, he proue in time thy mortall foe, leaſt his fained amitie prooue faithleſſe enmitie: that in truſting too much without tryall, thou finde not treaſon: and then though thou repent, yet Had I wiſt commeth too late, and ſo thou wiſh thou hadſt neuer loued, and I neuer liked.
            TVſh Caſtania, (quoth Gwydonius) he that is afraide to venture on the Buck, becauſe he is tapiſht in the briers, ſhall neuer haue hunters happe, and hée that puttes his doubt in loue for euery chaunce, ſhall neuer haue louers lucke. Cannot the Catte catch Mice, without ſhee haue a bell hanging at her eare? Cannot the Habbie ſeize on his preie, but hee muſt checke? Cannot the Spaniell retriue the Partridge, but hee muſt queſt? And cannot wée deale ſo warily but all the world muſt wonder as it? Yes, it is a ſubtile bird that bréedes among the aerin of Hawkes, and a ſhifting ſhéepe that lambes in the Foxes denne, and be ſhall looke narrowly that ſpies me halting.

Let Orlanio not onely weigh our workes, but our words, and let Valericus both deeme our déedes and diuine our thoughts, and yet we hope I will dealt ſo ſecretly in our affaires, as neither the one ſhall haue cauſe to ſuſpect our familiaritie, nor the other to detect our affection. And therfore Caſtania, leaſt (if we be ſpied) the time and place giue occaſion of miſtruſt, I will leaue you as I found you, and ſo farewell.
            VVEll, theſe two louers placed thus by Fortune in the palace of earthly proſperitie, floated ſo ſecurely in the ſtreames of bliſſe, as they thought no chippes of milchance might change their preſent happineſſe to future heauineſſe, as long as their priuy contract was kept ſo ſecret to thēſelues. But as they which cannot ſée fire in the ſtrawe are ſtone blinde: ſo hee that cannot ſée the flame of fancie is a foole. It is hard to couer ſmoake, but more hard to conceale loue: which theſe two louers in tract of time tried true. Who as cloſely as they kept their cloake, yet it was moſt eaſie to eſpie the lining: for fancie ſecretly reſtrained, is like the ſparke couered with aſhes, which at length bruſteth into a great flame. For there paſſed betweene Gwydonius ſuch amorous glaunces, ſuch louing lookes, ſuch curteous congies, ſuch countenances, and ſuch friendly familiaritie, ſuch often meetings, ſuch open greetings, ſuch ſighes, ſuch ſobs, and ſuch ſtrange paſſions, as not onele Valericus, but all the Court (though they poore ſoules thought to daunce in a Net and not be ſéene) perceiued how entirely they loued and liked each other. Which as it did not diſpleaſe many which loued Gwydonius as their friend, ſo it greatly deſpighted Valericus which was his foe, to ſée one of ſmall countenance preferred before one of his calling, that Guydonius ſhould win the bulwarke which he ſo long had battered: that hee pitching the fielde, another ſhould obtaine the conqueſt: that hee laying the ſiege, another ſhould vaunt of the victorie: that while hee

beate the buſh, another ſhould catch the birds, and that the méede of his merite, ſhould be giuen to one of ſmall deſert. Being cumbred with theſe cholericke cogitations, and perplexed with theſe deſpightfull paſſions, inflamed wt wrathfull furie, he fell into theſe tearmes:
            O Gods (quoth he) what curteſie is there to be found in ſuch Kites of Creſſids kinde? Or what conſtancie is there to bee hoped for in ſuch daintie diſdaining Dames? Whoſe wauering willes and ſtaileſſe wittes both waxe and wane with the Moone, whoſe lunatike minds change with euerie ſodaine motion: yea, whoſe lightneſſe and leaudneſſe is ſuch, as they delight with the Rauen to féede on the moſt loathſome fleſh, with the ſhee Woolfe to chooſe the ſonieſt Make, with Aeſops Cocke to prefer the Barly Corne before a moſt precious Pearle, and with Glaucus to make a chaunge of his golden armour for braſen Harneſſe.
            Did not Euphinia forſake moſt famous Princes, and embrace a moſt infamous bondſlaue? Did not Sirithia the Princeſſe of Denmarke reiect a poore peaſant? Yea, did not Venus her ſelfe, with the Béetle, diſdaine all day to light on the moſt fragrant flowers, and at night voutchſafeth to lodge in a filthie cowſheard: I meane, did ſhee not refuſe the renowmed Gods, and chooſe a moſt deformed Smith?
            Why, but Valericus, is it fancie that forceth them to follie? Doth loue leade them? Do the deſtinies driue them? Doth beautie allure them? Is it their countenance that conſtraineth them? No, they are clownes: Is it their perſon or parentage that perſwadeth them? No, they are peaſants. But like craftie Calipſos, they thinke by theſe vnequall matches to rule the roaſt after their owne diet, to be ſoueraigne miſtreſſes of their owne mindes, with Venus to let Vulcan poſſeſſe the trée, &amp; Mars enioy the fruit, to haue their huſbands ſéed the ſhéep, and ſome other reape

the fléece: vnder the ſhadowe of his head, to defend themſelues from ſuch heate as woulde otherwiſe greatly ſcorch their credite, to make him follow the bent of their bowe, although hée ſet the Cuckoldes end vpwarde. It is a ſimple cloake that cannot couer one from a ſhower of raine, and a ſilly husban
                  •
                that is not able to father that another dooth beget. But to ſée how theſe gallant girles if they like not the partie, what ſhewe of ſhame faſtneſſe they will make, how they will vale their face with the viſour of Virginitie, how they will cloke themſelues with the colour of continency, how chary they will be of their chaſtitie: whereas if they fancy, who ſo looſe of their lips, and frée of their fleſhe as they? But Valericus, why doeſt thou thus reckleſly raile and rage againſt womankinde? It is not Caſtania that thus croſſeth thée with care, but Gwydonius that bréedeth thy griefe. Is it not ſhée that inferreth thy ſore, but he that procureth thy ſickneſſe. She is not the meanes of thy maladie, but he the hinderer of thy medicine. Shee is not the worker of thy woe, but he is the ſower of thy ſorrowe. And ſhall hée bée puffed vp with proſperity, and I preſſed downe with miſerie? Shall he ſwim in wealth, and I ſinke in want? Shall he bathe in bliſſe, &amp; I waile in woe? Shall he be pampered vp with pleaſure, and I pinde away with penury? No, I will eyther ſpoyle him, or ſpill my ſelfe, in deſpite of the fates and fortune.
            VVHile thus Valericus ſought opportunity to reuenge his wrath vpō guiltleſſe Gwydonius, fortune minding to bewray her mutability, brought it ſo to paſſe, that wheras Orlanio was accuſtomed to pay a yéerly tribute to the Duke of Mitylene, which ſurmounted to the ſum of 30000. Duckets, eyther wilfully or willingly hée withhelde this debt, which Clerophontes claymed as his due, inſomuch that being demanded by Embaſſage for the payment of this tribute, he flatly anſwered, that he would not from henceforth diſburſe one denyer, and hee was

ſorrie that in paying it heretofore hée prooued himſelfe ſuch a foole. Whereupon Clerophontes being fraught with raging fury, was ſo incenſed againſt Orlanio, that taking counſell of his Nobility, he determined with as much ſpéed as might be, to wage battaile againſt him, and to obtaine y• by cōſtraint, which he denied him of curteſie. As thus he was muſing with himſelf whom he ſhould appoint captain generall of his army, becauſe he meant not in proper perſon to abide the hazard of the battell, the remembrance of his ſonne Gwydonius came into his minde, which not only amazed him, but ſo moleſted him, as he was driuen into moſt diſtreſſed dolor: now he called to mind his mercileſſe cruelty in correcting his faultes, and his moodleſſe rigour in rebuking his folly: now he bewailed his long abſence, and wiſhed his ſpéedie preſence: yea, hee was ſo diuerſly perplexed, as hée began thus dolorouſly to diſcourſe with himſelfe:
            ALas (quoth hee) now I ſée the ſaying of Cicero to be true, that who ſo wilfully peruerteth the lawes of nature, ſéemeth to proclaime himſelfe an enemy to the gods, for that Nature neuer framed any thing amiſſe, wherein I haue moſt gréeuouſly offended: for in beaſtly rage I haue ſurpaſſed the bruite beaſtes and in crueltie, the ſenſeleſſe creatures: I haue beene more deuoyd of pitie than the Fowles of the ayre, and more vnnatural than the Fiſhes of the ſea. The Bird called Apis Indica, ſéeing the venimous Viper readie to deuoure her yong ones in the neaſt, preſenteth her ſelf to death, to preſerue them from deſtruction The Eagle is ſo carefull ouer her yoong, that if it hap by her default one of them doo periſh, ſhe willingly woundeth her ſelfe in many places with her owne beake. The Lyon ſo louingly foſtereth vp her whelpes, that ſhee neuer faſteth of the preie vntill they bee fully ſatiſfied. The Foxe is ſo carefull ouer her cubbes, that ſhee willingly falleth into the Hunters handes to defend her yoong from harme.

But I vile wretch, as though I had drunke of the Riuer Lincellis in Bohemia, which preſently turneth whatſoeuer it toucheth, into ſtones. In ſteade of friendly courteſie haue abuſed mine own ſon with frowning cruelty, in lieu of mercy I haue brought him to miſery: the fatherly affection I haue ſhewed him, hath béen raging furie: yea, my rigorous nature, nay rather my vnnaturall rage hath béene ſuch towardes him, as hee liueth a baniſhed exile in a ſtraunge Countrie, perhappes pinched with penurie, oppreſſed with pouertie, wandering in the wilde deſartes, in daunger of deuouring, in perill of ſpoyling, afflicted not onely with the maladie of the body, but the miſerie of the minde: ſo that no doubt he wiſheth that I had neuer béene Father to ſuch a ſonne, or hée neuer ſonne to ſuch a Father.
            Alas what ioy can I now inioy when I want mine onely ioy? What comfort can I haue to ſée my childe in calamitie? What pleaſure can I take while he toyleth in penury, who now in mine age ſhould be the ſtaffe whereon to ſtaie, that by his valiant courage and warlike proweſſe (wherwith from his infancie hée hath béen indewed) might defend me from mine enimies, and reuenge me of my foes. But alas, I lament too late: the calme commeth out of time, when the Shippe hath ſuffered already Stipwrack, and the pittifull plaintes little preuaile, where the Patient is already puſhed into perill. No, no, my rage hath béene too great to heare of his haſty returne, my peruerſe furie hath béen ſuch, as hée dare not abide my preſence: and ſurely my ſorrow is too great euer to be ſalued.
            And with that Clerophontes ſtart vppe, minding to reuenge theſe his cholericke cogitations by bloudy battaile vpon the confines of Alexandria, and therfore in great haſt muſtered all his men, made great prouiſion for the warre, and cauſed his Nauie to be rigged, for that he meant to cō
               ney his army by ſea into Alexandria.
            
            VVhile thus there was no worde through the whole

Dukedome of Mitylene, but warre, warre, and no newes but of the cruell conflict that ſhould inſue betwéene the two Dukes; certaine Merchantes of Alexandria, which then roade in the Hauen durſt not goe a ſhoare to ſell their commodities, but as faſt as winde and weather woulde ſerue them, highed them out of the harbour, and coaſted ſpeedily into their owne Countrie: where they no ſooner arriued, but they made report thereof to Orlanio, who driuen into a dumpe with this noyſome newes, whether he doubted of the puiſſant power of Clerophontes, who was ſuch a worthy warriour, and in battaile ſo bold, that no man durſt abide him, or whether he feared his owne force was not able to reſiſt the furie of his raging enemy; Hee preſently ſummoned all his Lords to a Parliament, where after ſome conference, it was cōcluded that Therſandro ſhould bee ſent Embaſſadour to Mitylene to parle of peace with Clerophontes: which determination was no whit deferred, but with as much ſpéed as might be, the Bark wherein hée ſhould paſſe was prouided, the charge of the Embaſſage was giuen him, and he accompanied with a traine of braue Gentlemen, departed.
            But if this newes was dolefull to Orlanio, no doubt it was death it ſelfe to Gwydonius, who hearing that his father woulde bend his force againſt the place, wherein hee was, ſawe all poſſibilitie taken away from obtayning his purpoſe, for he feared death if he were knowen to Orlanio, and hée doubted deſpightfull hate at the leaſt, if he bewrayed himſelfe to Caſtania. Which double dolour ſo diſtreſſed him, as hée felt himſelfe diuerſly perplexed with dumpiſh paſſions, his myrth was turned to mourning, his pleaſant conceits, to painefull cogitations: his wanton toyes, to wayling thoughtes: now he abandoned all good companie, and delighted onely in ſolitary life, the wildeſome woodes were his walkes, and the ſecret ſhades the couert he chiefly coueted. In fine, hée ſéemed rather a Tymon of Athens, than a Gentleman of Alexandria, ſo that all the Court

marueiled at this ſo ſodaine a chaunge, but eſpecially Caſtania, who coniecturing his dolefull heart by his drouſie lookes, was aſtoniſhed at this ſtrange ſtate, caſting in her minde whether ſhe had giuen him anie cauſe of this care, or whether by her occaſion he was croſſed with this calamitie. But alas poore ſoule, howſoeuer ſhe aymed, ſhe miſt the marke, for Gwydonius kept his diſeaſe ſo ſecret, as he knew none could but himſelfe diuine the cauſe of his maladie: which no doubt was ſuch, that it would haue inferred preſent death, if hee had not hoped for ſome happie newes by Therſandro:
            
            Who no ſooner luckely arriued at Mitylene, but Clerophōtes was certified that the Dukes ſonne of Alexandria was come to impart with his Grace, ſome waightie matters of importance. Now at this inſtant when the meſſage was brought him, his daughter Lewcippa was by, who (as the nature of women is, deſirous to ſee and bee ſéene) thought ſhe ſhould both heare the parle, &amp; view the perſon of this young Embaſſadour, and therefore found fiſh on her fingers, that ſhe might ſtay ſtill in the chamber of preſence, whither preſently Therſandro was ſent for, who curteouſly and curiouſly doing his obeylance to the Duke, deliuered his Embaſſage in this maner:
            VVHereas (right worthy ſir) Orlanio, the Duke of Alexandria, more vnwittingly then wilfully denied certaine tribute, which he confeſſeth both hee and his predeceſſours haue payd to you and your aunceſtors: Hearing that héereupon your Grace meaneth rather to wage battaile, then to loſe any part of your due, although he feareth not your force, as one able euery way to withſtand it, nor paſſeth of your puiſſance, as a Potentate ſufficient to reſiſt your power: Yet, the care he hath of his ſubiects ſafetie, and the loue he hath to preſerue the life of his Commons, the regard he hath to pay and performe yt which conſciēce and cuſtome requireth: and laſtly meaning with

               Tully, Iniquiſſimam pacem iuſtiſſimo bello anteponere. He hath ſent me both to ſue for conditions of peace, and to paie the tribute: which if your Grace ſhall refuſe, of force he muſt put his hope in the hazard of Fortune.
            
               THerſandro hauing thus pithily performed his charge, Clerophontes tolde him that vpon a ſodaine he wold not diſpatch ſo waightie a matter, but meant firſt both to conſult and take counſaile of his Nobles: which done, within thrée dayes he ſhoulde haue an anſwere. In the meane time he commanded Lucianus the Steward of his houſe, verie courteouſly to entreate both Therſandro and his traine, and to feaſt them with ſuch ſumptuous fare, as they might haue cauſe moſt highly to extoll his magnificence.
            But leauing Clerophontes, to conſult with his learned counſailours, and Therſandro to accompanie with the luſtie Courtiers, againe to Lewcippa, who while this yong youth was telling of his tale, neuer markt the matter, but the man: nor regarded not the parle, but reſpected yt perſon: neuer noted the contentes, but viewed his countenance: In ſuch ſort, that ſhe was ſo ſcorched with the fire of fancie, and ſo ſcalded with the flame of affection, ſo bewitched with his beautie, and ſo inueigled with his bountie, as he was the onely man that made her checke at the pray, bate at the lure, and willingly yeelde to the firſt aſſault of fancie. And on the other ſide, Fortune ſo fauoured, that Therſandro printing in his heart the perfection of Lewcippas perſon, felt his fredome ſo fettered by yt view of her heauenly face, and ſo ſnared in the beames of her amorous glaunces, that he wiſht that either this diſſenſion had neuer growen, or that he had not béene the deliuerer of the meſſage: for hee felt his heart alreadie ſo ouergrowen with good will, towardes this young Princeſſe, as no ſalue but her ſelfe was able to mitigate his ſorrow, no medicine but her curteſie was able to cure his calamitie,

and he thought to preferre his ſute to his profeſſed foe, was folly: to linger ſtill in loue, was death and miſery: to ſéeke for helpe at her hands, neither would the preſent ſtate permit him, nor time ſuffer him to proſecute his purpoſe: daunted with theſe diuerſe doubtes, to auoyde the melancholike motions that moleſted his mind, he preſently went from his lodging to the Court, that by company hée might driue away theſe dumpes: where, hee founde in the great Chamber diuerſe Ladies &amp; Gentlewomen, paſſing away the time in pleaſant parle, amongſt whom was that peerleſſe Paragon, princely Lewcippa: who (after due reuerence done to the Gentlewomen in generall) was ſingled out by Therſandro, and courted in this wiſe.
            MAdam (quoth he) if any creature hath iuſt occaſion to accuſe eyther nature or the gods of iniuſtice, man only hath the greateſt cauſe to make this complaint: for there is none other ſo depriued of reaſon, or deuoyde of ſenſe, which by ſome naturall inſtinct dooth not skilfully preſage of perils before they come, and warily preuent ere they bée paſt.
            The Goates of Lybia, know certainly when the Canicular dayes beginne, wherein commonly they fall blinde, and therefore by eating the hearbe Polypodium, they prouidently preuent their diſeaſe. When the Lyon leaueth his Lawnes, and raungeth in forraigne deſartes, hée alwaies foreſheweth a drouth. When the Fiſh called Vranoſcopos ſinketh downe to the bottome of the Sea, hée bewrayeth great tempeſtes to bee imminent. But man is ſo farre from this ſecret foreſight, that not onely hee cannot diuine of theſe enſuing daungers, but rather wilfully or willingly, puſheth himſelf into moſt manifeſt perils: which Madame, I ſpeake, as féeling my ſelfe diſtreſſed with this want. For if I had béen indued with this ſacred preſcience, perfectly to preſage of inſuing perils, I had not béen croſſed with ſuch cares as I am like to incurre, nor had cauſe to repent

this my preſent arriuall. But ſith lacke of ſuch skill hath procured my loſſe, and that when the hurt is had it is too late to take héed, though reuealing of my miſhap cannot heale my miſery, nor repeating of my paines redreſſe my ſorrow, yet I mean to participate my paſſions to your good grace, that though you cannot or will not mitigate my maladie, yet you may pitie my eſtate, which wil ſome what eaſe my heauineſſe. I came to your Fathers Court Madam, a free man of Alexandria, and am like to return a captiue of Mitylene: I arriued deuoyd of care, and am like to depart drenched with calamity: I landed frée from affectiō, but fear to paſſe hence fraught with fancy: my charge was only to parle of peace, but my chance is to diſcourſe of paſſions. Yea, your beauty hath ſo fettered my fréedom &amp; ſo ſnared my heart in the linkes of your loue, that it ſhall neuer be raced out by any ſiniſter means of Fortune, although I ſée it is almoſt impoſſible to obtain it.
            For I doubt, our Parents are like to proclaime themſelues profeſſed foes, and the vrgent neceſſitie of my affaires forceth mée to depart ſo ſpéedily, as want of time wil not ſuffiſe to make triall of my loue, whereby I might claim a ſufficient guerdon for my good will: yet howſoeuer the matter ſhall hap, whether my hope bée voyde, or my hap be vaine, I meane Madame to remaine yours for euer.
            
               Lewcippa took ſuch delight in hearing Therſandro diſcourſe ſo louingly, as ſhée could ſcarcely kéepe her countenance from bewraying the pleaſure ſhe conceiued in this parle, ſéeing that her loue was requited with liking, and hir fancie incountred with the like affection. Yet, leaſt Therſandro ſhould think her too courteous if ſhée ſhould come at the firſt call, and very light of loue, to like at the firſt looke, ſhée framed him this anſwere:
            SIR (quoth ſhee) if of your ſute for Conditions of peace there inſue no better ſucceſſe than the reuealing of

your paſſions ſhall reape pittie at my handes, or if the intreatie for truce be as lightly reſpected by my Father, as either your perſon or petition is regarded by me, you are like to carrie home colde newes to your countrey, and to vaunt that you bad faire, but bought little, that your Harueſt was long, but your corne not worth the cropping: that your venture was much, but your gaines ſuch, as if your winning proue no better, you are like to liue by the loſſe. For ſir, do you ſuppoſe mee ſo ſottiſh, as to thinke euerie one that flatters doeth fancie, or ſo addicted to ſelfe loue, as by a few filed phraſes to be brought into a fooles Paradiſe? knowing that it is the faſhion of men by their fained ſubtiltie to deceiue our fathfull ſimplicitie? No, for if you meane to counterfaite, take this for a rule, it is ill halting before a créeple. But ſir, this your ſodaine liking bewraies the lightneſſe of your loue: this your fond affection, importes the ſickleneſſe of your fancie: for ſoone hote, ſoone colde: eaſilie inflamed, as quickly quenched: like to the Apples of Arabia, which beginne to rot, ere they behalfe ripe. And if I meant to loue, had I none to like but my Fathers foe? ſhould I deſire him whome my Father doth deteſt? And if I ſhould ſo farre forget mine owne ſtay, or my Fathers ſtate, as to conſent, it were impoſſible either to appeaſe his wrath, or to get the grant of his good will. So that to deſire that which I can neuer inioy, were to driue my ſelfe whollie into deſpaire, which would ſmally profite you, and greatly diſpleaſure me: and therefore ceaſe to ſue for that, which may well be wiſht, but neuer obtained.
            
               Therſandro although hée heard Lewcippa decide the caſe ſufficiently, yet hee was ſo wilfull that hee would not take her doome for a verdite, but returned her this replie.
            MAdame (quoth hee) where in lieu of hate there inſueth loue, it is alwaies the ſigne of the greater

affection: and that it is a thing either confirmed by the Fates, or appointed by the Gods. Tereus the Prince of Thrace, being ſent by his father to defie Pandion the king of Athens, was enamoured of his daughter Progne, wherby betwéene the Parentes in ſtéede of fatall enmitie, there inſued friendly amitie. When as the bloudie warre betwéene Atis the king of Libia, and Lycabas the Prince of Aſſur, was moſt hot, young Admetus, béeing ſent Embaſſadour into Libia, was ſo ſtroken in loue with Alceſt, onelie Daughter to his fathers foe, and ſhee repayed his liking with ſuch loialtie as death it ſelfe could neuer diſſolue their amitie. If Madame, theſe premiſes may perſwade you to take pittie of my paſſions, or theſe examples induce you, not to let the hatred of our parentes, bée a hinderance of our loue, whether your father reiect mee as a foe, or accept mée as a friend, I doubt not but the deſtinies will drine the bargaine through, in deſpight of them and fortune.
            Sir (quoth ſhée) I confeſſe, Progne poore wench loued Tereus, but how wretchedly did hee reward her loyaltie? and Scilla was enamoured of Minos her Fathers foe, but howe tyrannouſly did hee repay her loue with trecherie? Tarpeia betraied ye Tower of Rome to one of the Sabines whom ſhe moſt entirely loued, but the méede of her merite was extreame miſerie. Shall I then Therſandro ſée the traine and yet fall into the trap? ſhall I ſpie the nettes, and yet ſtrike at the ſtale? ſhall I ſée the miſhap, and yet wilfully incurre the miſchance? no, I meane not for an inch of ioy, to reape an ell of annoy, for a momēt of mirth, a month of miſerie: for a dramme of pleaſure, a whole pounde of paine, and by procuring mine owne delight, to purchaſe my fathers death and deſtruction. But let this ſuffice Therſandro to ſignifie howe I pittie thy paſſions, and thinke well of thy perſon, that if my Fathers will might bee framed to my wiſhe, if hee woulde condeſcend as I would conſent, thou onely art the man who in the way of

marriage ſhould diſpoſe of me at thy pleaſure. But ſith the frowning ſtate of Fortune denies our loue to haue ſuch happie ſucceſſe, hope well, and reſt vpon this point, that I will alwaies like thée as a friend, though not loue thée as my phéere.
            As Therſandro was ready to replie, and to ſeale vp the bargaine of their loue vpon her ſwéete lips, Clerophō
                  tes came in, who marred all their market, and turned their ſwéet to ſowre: for he gaue Therſandro his anſwere before Lewcippa, which was this; That he neither meant to accept of the conditions of peace, nor to receiue the tribute, but to claime his due by the doubtfull euent of battaile: That he ſhortly pretended in perſon, to viſite Orlanio, and within the walles of Alexandria to demand his debt, and that he would beſtow his fathers Dukedome vpon a Lord of his called Lucianus, in dowrie with his daughter Lewcippa.
            
            
               Therſandro was nothing amazed with the firſt part of the meſſage: but when he heard how Clerophontes meant preſumptuouſly both to depraue him of his liuing, and depriue him of his loue, hee was ſo puffed vp with wrath and choler, as happe what happe would, he fell into theſe tearmes.
            I remember (quoth he) that Caligula the Emperour, prouiding a mightie armie to ſubdue great Britaine, when hée was come to the ſea, ready to poſte ouer his ſouldiers in his Nauie, he left off his endleſſe enterpriſe, and ſet them to gather Cockles. Siphax boldly boaſting that hee would beſtow the kingdome of Numidia vpon his ſecond ſonne, was by Maſſiniſ
                     •
                  a ouerthrowne, and ſold as captiue to the Romanes. I dare not ſir inferre compariſons, becauſe they be odious, nor apply the examples, ſith time and place forbids mee: but this I ſay, that to fiſh before the net, is alwaies counted folly, and to vaunt before the victorie, is but

vanitie. Yea, and if I had as good right to your daughter Lewcippa, as I haue to the ſuppoſed dowrte which you aſſigne her, I would in deſpight of Lucianus and the diuell himſelfe, diſpoſe her at my pleaſure.
            
               Clerophontes hearing the cholerike concluſion of Therſandro, could ſcarcely bridle his frantike furie from raging without reaſon againſt this young youth: yet ſomewhat mitigating his moode, hee breathed out theſe cruell threatnings.
            IF the law of armes (quoth he) did not both ſafely protect thée, and ſurely forbid me to hurt thée in that thou art a meſſenger, I would with ſuch ſeueritie chaſtice theſe thy preſumptuous ſpéeches, as thou ſhouldeſt learne hereafter to anſwere with more reuerence: yet I wiſh thée not to ſtand too ſtiffe vpon this point, leaſt if thou bee ſo reckleſſe as to breake the bondes of reaſon, I be ſo forgetfull as to paſſe the limits of the law. Thou haſt receiued a determinate anſwer for the Embaſſe, and heere I charge thée this preſent day to depart out of my dominions.
            
               Therſandro fearing the tyrannie of this cruell Clerophontes, preſently paſſed out of the chamber of Preſence, taking his leaue of Ladie Lewcippa, onely with louing lookes, which ſhe requited with ſuch glaunces of good will, that they were ſufficient ſignes what inſupportable ſorrow ſhe receiued by his ſo ſodaine departure: yet knowing that her fancie was incountered with mutuall affection, ſhe draue away the myſtie cloudes of deſpaire, hoping that the Gods ſéeing their faithfull amitie, would take pittie of their paſſions, and in time redreſſe their miſerie.
            But Therſandro hauing with ſpéede diſpatcht his affaires (all his traine being ſet aboord, and they coaſting the ſtraights with a luckie gale) was ſo combered with care, and ſo ouer-growne with griefe, that he paſſed no houre, minute, nor moment, without wofull wailing, ſorrowfull ſobs, and far fetcht ſighs: ſo that the Gentlemen his companions,

ſuppoſing that hée was thus painfully perplexed for feare of Clerophontes puiſance, began both to comfort and incourage him, not to doubt or dreade the force of the enemie, ſith his father was able to repulſe him, without anie daunger to himſelfe, or anie great damage to his ſubiectes. But theſe their perſwaſions coulde no whit preuaile to aſſwage his paſſions, this their incoragement could not cure his care.
            But as there is no greater bane to the bodie, than trouble of the minde: ſo Therſandro ſo long continued in theſe penſiue paſſions and carefull cogitations, concealing his griefe ſo couertly, which ſo much the more furiouſly flamed within him, that he was conſtrained to kéep his Cabbin till his arriual at Alexandria. Where being ſet on ſhore, and preſently conueied to the Court, he remained for the ſpace of thrée dayes ſo ſtrangely perplexed, as he was not able to make report of his meſſage: which ſo griped Orlanio with ſuch inſpeakeable griefe, as he wiſhed rather to haue died valiantly with the force of his enemy, than to put the death of his ſonne in hazard by paſſing ſo perillous a iorney. But Therſandro ſéeing that ſorrowe would not ſalue his ſore, but rather increaſe his ſickneſſe: that mourning woulde not appeaſe his maladie, but rather augment his miſery: began to take heart at graſſe, and within fewe daies began to recouer his former health. And then hee declared to his father what he had in charge from Clerophontes, how hée meant ſpéedily to wage war againſt him, &amp; by force of arms to driue him out of his Dukedom, which he had already promiſed to one Lucianus in dowry with his daughter.
            
               Orlanio hearing this proude preſumption of this bragging Duke, thought ye greateſt barkers were not alwaies the ſoreſt biters, and that it was far more eaſie with wordes to obtaine the victorie, than with déeds to attaine the conqueſt. Yet, leaſt he might he taken at vnawares, he made a generall muſter throughout all his Dominions, prouiding in euerie place neceſſary munition for the defence

of his Countrie. And aſſembling his Nobility to giue their verdit, who were fitteſt to be Captains in this skirmiſh; after ſome conſultation had in this cauſe, they concluded, that ſince Clerophontes meant to ioyn battaile in his own perſon, that likewiſe he ſhould be Generall of the field, and Gwydonius who ſurpaſſed all the reſt in martiall exploits, ſhould be Lieutenant, and conduct the armie, which he no ſooner heard but he was tormented with inſpeakable grief, he began to pull downe his Peacockes feathers, to hang his wings, and crie creake: euerie man hoping to win fame was merry, but he alone mourning: euery man laughed and he alone lowred: inſomuch that he was generally ſuſpected to be a fearefull cowarde, and that dread of danger draue him into theſe dolefull dumps. But as they raſhly coniectured the cauſe of his ſorrowe, ſo they miſt the nature of his ſickneſſe: for Gwydonius ſéeing that of the cruel cō
               flict his calamity ſhould inſue, and that this bloudy broyle would bréed his bane, he fel into ſuch ſolitary ſurmiſes, and ſuch muſing meditations, that Valericus his opén friend, and yet his ſecret foe, ſought by ſundrie meanes to ſearch out the cauſe of his care: but not beeing able to wring out any thing, either by flattering promiſes, or fained proteſtations, he ceaſed from his importunate ſute. But froward fortune brought it ſo to paſſe, that Valericus comming by the chamber of Gwydonius, heard him thus deſperately diſcourſing with himſelfe.
            Alaſſe (quoth he) I ſée the Sunne being at the higheſt declineth, the Sea being at the full tide ebbeth: calme continueth not long without a ſtorme, neither is happineſſe had long without heauineſſe, bliſſe without bale, weale without woe, mirth without mourning. For who alate ſo floated in the flouds of felicitie as I, which now by the ſiniſter meanes of frowning fortune am ſowſed in the ſeas of ſorrow, eralted alate to the higheſt degrée of happines, am now driuen to the greateſt extremitie of euill: alate

puffed vp with proſperity, and now puſhed downe with aduerſitie: yea, alate placed in Paradiſe, and now plunged in perplexity.
            Oh Gwydonius, if thy Fathers friendly precepts might haue perſwaded thee, if his aduice had béene thy aduertiſement, and thou hadſt carefully kept his counſaile, then by his fore-warning, thou hadſt béene forearmed againſt all miſhap and miſerie, The force of fickle fancy had not then giuen thee the foyle, Loue had not ſo lightly procured thy loſſe, nor the painted ſhewe of beautie had not ſo ſoone procured thy bane. My bane? Why fond foole, beautie hath bred my bliſſe: fancie hath not giuen me the foile, but hath yéelded me the fort: Loue hath not wrought my loſſe, but requited me with treble gaine.
            Hath not Caſtania requited my loue with loyaltie, and repaied my good will with mutuall affection? Is ſhée not my Saint, and I her ſeruant? Are we not contracted together by loue, and ſhall continue together by law? May I not diſpoſe of her in the way of marriage at my pleaſure? Yes, but what then? The more is my griefe, and the greater my care. For if her preſence procureth my delight, will not her abſence bréed my deſpight? If her conſent preſerued my life, will not her contempt inferre my death? Yes. For alas, ſince the deſtinies meane to diſſolue that fancie hath decréed, ſince the frowning fates ſéeke to vnlooſe that which loue hath linked, ſince froward fortune meanes to breake the bonds wherein beautie hath bounde vs, ſince theſe bloudie broyles will cauſe Caſtania, (where before ſhe accepted me for a friend) now to reiect me for a foe: What better lucke can I looke for than a loathſome life, or what better hap can I hope for than horror and heauineſſe? Yea, which way ſo euer I turne mee I ſee nothing but woe and wretchedneſſe. For if Orlanio perceiued our liking, how would he ſtorme at our loue? If he knew my chance, how would he fret at his Daughters choice? Woulde hée euer conſent, that Caſtania ſhould match with ſo meane a mate,

that her Princely perſonage ſhould bee diſgraced with my baſe parentage, that her calling ſhould be crazed with my ſlender countenance: no, he would no doubt firſt baniſh me out of all his dominions. Tuſh Gwydonius, would God this were the worſt, and then thou mighteſt hope in time, by ſome means to redreſſe this doubt. But if Orlanio ſhuld know thou wert heire apparant to the Dukedome of Mitylene, and only ſonne to Clerophontes his fatall foe what torment were there ſo terrible, which thou ſhouldeſt not trie? What paine ſo pinching, which thou ſhouldeſt not paſſe? What hap ſo hard, which thou ſhouldeſt not hazard? Yea, what death ſo direfull, which at his cruell hands thou ſhouldeſt not ſuffer? And what if Caſtania were priuy to thy ſtate, doeſt thou thinke her ſo conſtant as to conſent to her Fathers foe? Doeſt thou thinke ſhee would wiſhe the ſonnes weale, when the Father wiſheth her miſhap? No, aſſure thy ſelfe if thy ſtate be once knowen, that Caſtania will moſt deadly deteſt thée, which will bee more gréeuous to thée than death it ſelfe, be it neuer ſo terrible. Sith then Gwydonius, thou muſt ſhortly either go in arms againſt thine owne Father, or elſe loſe both thy loue and thy life, let not delay bréede daunger, but ſtrike on the ſtith while the yron is hot. Caſtania hath promiſed to forſake both father, friends, and her owne Countrie, to paſſe where and whē it pleaſeth thée, ſhee doubteth no daungers, ſhe forceth of no miſfortune, ſhe careth for no calamity, ſhe paſſeth for no perils, ſo ſhe enioy thy deſired companie: and therefore as ſpéedily as may be, conuey her cloſely into the confines of Mitylene, before either ſhe know thy ſtaie or thy ſtate. And ſhall I ſo practice her with policies? Shall I ſo ſifte her with ſubtiltie? Shall I put ſo little truſt in her troth, and ſo ſmall confidence in her conſtancie, as to conceale frō her any ſecret? No, come woe, come wretchedneſſe, come death, come daunger, hap what hap will, I will preſentlie impart vnto her my preſent ſtate, and my pretended purpoſe.
            
               
               Valericus hearing this doubtfull diſcourſe of Gvvydonius, was driuen into an extaſie for ioy, to ſée that hee had found ſuch fit meanes, whereby hee might not onely purchaſe the Dukes fauour, aſpire vnto honour and dignitie, but alſo obtaine the loue of Caſtania: for he meant ſpéedily to preuent the pretence of Gwydonius, by vnfolding to the Duke the ſum of his ſecret purpoſe, aſſuring himſelfe, that after Orlanio knew his parents and parentage, that hée was ſonne and heire to Clerophontes, no price though neuer ſo precious, no ranſom though neuer ſo rich, might redéeme him from the moſt deſpitefull death that could be deuiſed. And of theſe premiſſes he inferd this concluſion, that if the cauſe be taken away, the effect faileth: that Gwydonius beeing reiected, hee ſhould be receiued: that he béeing deſpighted with hate, hee ſhould be requited with loue: and vpon this hope he went preſently to bewray this matter to Orlanio, whome hee found with his ſonne Therſandro, and diuerſe other noble men conſulting what courſe they had beſt take againſt Clerophontes, whoms Valericus ſaluted in this wiſe.
            
               PLato (right worthy Prince) that graue and wiſe Philoſopher, whoſe ſentences in all ages haue béene holden as moſt diuine Oracles, portraieth out in his bookes of his Common wealth, the picture of a perfect Citizen: whoſe liniaments béeing firſt leuelled, hée tricketh vp with theſe colours, that he loue his Prince loyallie, kéepe the lawes carefully, and defend his Country valiantly, in which thrée pointes (ſaith hée) conſiſteth the chiefeſt dutie of a truſty ſubiect: This ſaying of Plato throughly conſidered, and calling to minde the ſundrie good turnes which without deſert your Grace hath beſtowed vppon mee, I thought if I ſhoulde not repaie your fauour with faithfulneſſe, and your truſt you repoſe in mee with inuiolable troth, I might bee counted a vicious vaſſall deuoide of all vertues,

a trecherous citizen, rather then a truſty ſubiect, a careleſſe ſlaue, then a carefull gentleman: yea, a graceleſſe mō
               ſter, miſled wt ingratitude. I am come (right worthy ſir) not to betray my fo, but to bewray my frend, not to diſcouer ye falt of my enemy, but to diſcloſe his offence which liueth with me in perfect amitie, in whoſe company hitherto hath béene all my ioy, pleaſure and delight: but ſince his pretence is greatly preiudiciall to your Graces perſon, I thought to prefer your profit before mine own pleaſure, and the commoditie of my country, before mine owne priuate contentation. So it is, that Gwydonius, whom your Grace hath honoured, and all the Court eſtéemed, is ſonne and heire to Clerophontes the Duke of Mitylene. who by the péeuiſh policie of his Father, vnder the pretence of ſeruice, is purpoſed to procure your fatall death, and the finall deſtruction of your Dukedome. And the better to performe this diuelliſh practiſe, hée hath contracted himſelfe to my Lady Caſtania, who blinded with his beautie, and inueigled with his wit, hath conſented not onely to kéep his counſaile to your confuſion, but alſo cloſely to conuey her ſelfe with him into his Countrie. Which pretence if your Grace doth not ſpéedily preuent, you ſhall find that delay bréedes danger, &amp; that procraſtination in perils is but the mother of miſhap.
            And haue I (quoth Orlanio) brought vp the bird that wil picke out mine owne eies? Haue I foſtered vp the Serpent in my boſome that will bréede my bane? Haue I giuen her life, that ſéekes to yéeld me death? Haue I cheriſht her béeing young, and will ſhe conſume mee béeing older? Was there none to chooſe but Gwydonius, nor none to loue, but the ſonne of her fathers foe? Will ſhee preferre her luſt before my life? her priuate pleaſure, before the ſafetie of my perſon? Well, as ſhe forgets the duetie of a childe, ſo I wil forget the naturall affection of a father, and therefore Valericus goe ſpéedily with theſe noble men to Gvvydonius chamber, and apprehend him, that I may requite his hatefull trecherie with moſt helliſh torments. And Therſandro
               
ſée you that Caſtania be cloſely kept vntill we haue caught the traitour, leaſt ſhee vnderſtanding that their deuiſe is diſcloſed, ſhe ſaue her ſelfe by flight.
            
               Valericus hauing this commiſſion giuen him from the Duke, made no delay, but paſſed to Gvvidonius lodging with as much ſpéede as might be: but fortune who after euerie chip of miſchance, ſendeth ſome lot of good lucke, and after euerie ſtorme of aduerſitie, ſendeth a quiet calme of proſperitie, ſo carefully prouided to frée Gwydonius from miſhap, that he was newly gone towards Caſtania, to impart vnto her this his pretence: but before hee came to her chamber, he was encountered by Therſandro, who ſtearnly taking Gvvydonius by the boſome, pulling out his rapier commanded him as a traitour to ſtand, or elſe without any farther doome he ſhould féele the dint of death.
            
               Gvvydonius amazed with this ſodaine motion, ſtoode as one in a traunce, neither being able to defend himſelfe with worde or weapon, but yéelded himſelfe into the handes of Therſandro, who ſhakt him vp with theſe bitter ſpéeches.
            THou traiterous wretch (quoth he) as it is impoſſible for the flame ſo cloſely to be couered, but it will be ſpied: ſo it is impoſſible, but that treaſon, though neuer ſo ſecret, ſhould in tract of time be diſcloſed, which now by experience is verified in thee: for although thou haſt hetherto falſely fained thy ſelfe to be a ſtranger of a forraigne nation, thou art now known to be ſonne and heire to Clerophontes that cruell tyrant my Fathers foe, by whoſe péeuiſh policie thou hadſt not onely brought yt commō wealth to confuſion, but didſt pretend to be preiudiciall to my Fathers perſon, if thy deadly practiſe and diueliſh purpoſe had not by Valericus his meanes béen preuented. Haſt thou béene ſo trained vp in trecherie, or is thy minde ſo ſpotted with villanie, as to repay my fathers good will wc ſuch barbarous ingratitude, &amp; to deuiſe his deſtruction which ſimply foreſought thy preferment? Yea, to counſell my ſiſter

               Caſtania, not onely to conſent to thy deſire, but to my fathers death? Is this the maner of Mitylene, or the cuſtome of thy country, to be ſuch cooſening counterfaites? Well, ſince I haue happily attached thee as a traitour, and as a villanous rebell, both tranſgreſſing humaine and diuine lawes, thou ſhalt abide the paine and puniſhment due to ſuch diuelliſh offenders. Now let thy cruell ſire Clerophontes, free thee from thoſe torments which thou art like to ſuffer for thy trecherie, and let the Lordes of Mitylene deliuer thee from his handes, who meanes in moſt miſerable wiſe to martyr thee. Yea, let thy Concubine Caſtania, who is like for her graceleſſe diſobedience, to ſip of yt ſame ſorrow, ſée if her teares will now preuaile to mooue Orlanio to pittie. No, if Iupiter himſelfe ſent Mercurie to mitigate his moode, neither the authoritie of the one, nor the eloquence of the other might preuaile to pacifie his furie.
            
               GWydonius ſéeing that not onely his purpoſe was preuented, and his ſecrets diſcloſed, but that alſo Valericus moſt villanouſly had accuſed him and Caſtania of that which they neuer ſo much as once imagined, was ſo perplexed, and driuen into ſuch dumpes, as hee ſéemed by ſilence to auerre that which Therſandro had alleadged, yet at laſt he began thus to reply.
            
               THerſandro (quoth he) as I meane not to affirme that which is falſe, ſo I will not deny that which is true: but come dolor, come death, come miſerie, come martyrdome, come torture, come torments, I will neither accuſe myſelfe vniuſtly, nor excuſe myſelfe by periurie. I confeſſe Therſandro, that I am ſonne and heire to the Duke of Mitylene, and contracted to thy ſiſter Caſtania, that Clerophontes, is my father by the law of nature, and Caſtania my wife by the league of loue: but that I either pretended or purpoſed to be preiudiciall to Orlanios perſon, or that Caſtania was counſailed or euer conſented to her fathers

confuſion, I not onely deny, but I will proue by combats that Valericus moſt villanouſly doth accuſe vs of ye whereof we are altogether ſackleſſe.
            VVHy Gwydonius, (quoth hée) wilt thou ſéeke to proue thyſelfe loyall, when the hearers deeme ſhee a lyer? or to make a tryall of thy troth, when thy words can haue no truſt? Dooeſt thou think my fathers fury will ſuffer thée to fable? Dooeſt thou thinke his wrathfull rage wil abide thy reaſons, or that he wil be ſo patient as to hear thée plead thine owne cauſe? No, if thou wert as cléer from theſe crimes alleadged againſt thée by Valericus as I am: yet in that thou art ſon to Clerophontes, the coine of Croeſus, and Kingdoms of Caeſar, were not ſufficient ranſome to redéem thée frō death. But Gwydonius, ſince thy health hangeth in my hands, and thy life or death is in my power, I will neither bee ſo bloudy minded as to bréede thy bane, nor ſo cruell, as to be the cauſe of thy confuſion. The guerdon Gwydonius I craue of this my good will, and the recompence I claim for this curteſie, is that when thou commeſt to Mitylene, thou certifie thy ſiſter and my loue and Lady Lewcippa, that for her ſake I haue procured thy ſafety, that her perfection hath preſerued thée from perill, the loue I beare her hath ſaued thy life, the dutifull deuotion I owe vnto her, hath redéemed thée from death and daunger. And in token of this my vnfeined affection, I will lift my hand againſt none that commeth from Mitylene, but againſt Lucianus onely.
            Before Therſandro was able ſullie to vnfolde his mind, or that Gwydonius had time to yéelde him thankes for the ſafegard of his life, they heard a great noiſe, which made Gwydonius flie, and Therſandro hie him haſtily to Caſtanias lodging. Now the companie which came, was Orlanio himſelf, who certified by Valericus that Gwydonius could not be found, laid not only watch &amp; ward throughout all his Dukedom to attache him, but went in proper perſon

with his Gard to apprehend Caſtania, and lay her in cloſe priſon, whom he found all blubbered with teares, for that ſhe had vnderſtood the cauſe before of her brother Therſandro: Orlanio no ſooner ſpied her thus wéeping, but hée raged againſt her in this wiſe.
            HAth the force of lone, nay rather the furie of luſt (vile wretch) ſo blinded thine vnderſtanding, that to accompliſh it, thou paſſeſt not to peruert both humane and diuine lawes? Doth laſciuious affection and fleſhly fancy ſo furiouſly frie within thée, as thou wouldeſt procure thy fathers death to purchaſe thy diueliſh deſire? Could no rules of reaſon, no pricke of conſcience, no reſpect of honeſty, no feare of God, nor dread of man, prohibite thée from pretending ſuch a monſtrous miſchiefe, as to conclude with my mortall foe to worke my fatall confuſion? The yong Storkes ſo tender the olde ones in their age, as they will not ſuffer them ſo much as to flie to get their owne liuing. The bird called Apis Indica, being young, ſéeing yt olde ones through age growen ſo weake, as they are not able to waue their wings, carry them continually from place to place on their backs: theſe ſauage creatures haue but only ſenſe, and are obedient, thou haſt both reaſon and ſenſe, and art more vnnaturall: theſe brute beaſtes are moſt dutifull to their Parents, &amp; thou a reaſonable creature art moſt diſobedient to thy father: yea, contrarie both to the lawes of nature and nurture, thou ſéekeſt to bathe thy handes in his guiltleſſe bloud, &amp; without care or conſcience, to commit moſt cruell murther: which is ſo hatefull to all things, as the ſenſeleſſe plants and ſtones moſt deadly deteſt ſuch villanie. The Oliue trée ſo hatefully abhorreth a Paraſite, that who ſo being guiltie of that crime, attempteth to plant it, doth not onely himſelfe preſently periſh, but the tree forthwith waneth and withereth. The ſtone Epiſtrites, ſo loatheth this offence, coūting it a fact ſo repugnant to nature, that it wil not vouchſafe to be worne by a murtherer. And ſhall I then

lett thee liue, whome the ſenſeleſſe creatures doe ſo deadly leath? No, this hand which cheriſht thee béeing a child, ſhal now chaſtiſe thee being ſuch a curſed caitife. And with that he drew out his Fa
                  •
               ichon ready to haue ſtain her, but that Therſandro knéeling downe, deſired him that he would not ſo in his furie forget himſelfe, as without the ſentence of the law put her to death, but to commit her toward, vntill the wars betwéene him and Clerophontes, were happily ended; and then vppon more ſtraight examination, if ſhe were found faultie, to aſſigne her a puniſhment due for ſuch an offence. Orlanio, ſomwhat pacified with his ſons perſwaſion, commanded that preſently ſhe ſhould bee carried to priſon, and the Ladie Melytta with her, as an actor in this Tragedie. And that with all ſpéede they ſhould poſt the countrie for the attaching of the traytor Gwydonius. Who after that he parted from Therſandro, ſeeing before his eyes the terrour of torments, and the helliſh horrour of death, was driuen forward ſo with the dread of danger, and feare of imminēt perils, that knowing perfectly the coaſt of the Countrey, he paſſed ſo ſecretly and ſpéedily, as hee was not ſo much as once deſcried by the Poſts that purſued him, but ſcaped ſafely out of the Dukedom of Alexandria. Being now without the dint of the Dukes danger, ſéeing that although he had eſcaped himſelfe, yet hee had left his loue and ladie Caſtania in hazard of her life, he began thus to exclaime againſt his owne folly.
            AH Gvvidonius (quoth he) what foltie haſt thou committed by this fearefull flight, what carefull calamitie is like to inſue of this thy cowardiſe? in auoyding Scilla thou art fallen into Charibdis, in preuenting one danger, thou art like to be plagued with a thouſand diſcommodities. Had it not béen better for thee to haue died in Alexandria, with honor, than to liue heere with ſhame &amp; reproche, to haue ſuffered miſhappe with Caſtania, then to linger héere in miſeris? Doeſt thou thinke that ſhe wil euer count

of ſuch a prating Paraſite, as will loue her in proſperitie, and leaue her in aduerſitie, as preferreth his owne ſafetie before her ſecuritie, his life before her loue, and draweth himſelfe out of danger to leaue her in diſtreſſe? No, ſhe will contemne thee as a cowarde, more fit to be mate to ſome countrie ſlut, than a match for ſuch a courtly Princeſs, ſhe will thinke thy greateſt faith was but fained fickleneſſe, thy forged loue was but filthie luſt, thy promiſes were but periuries, and that thy greateſt amitie was but moſt diſſembled enmitie: ſo that of a profeſſed friend, ſhe will become thy profeſſed foe, her deſire will turne to deſpite, and her loue to moſt helliſh hate.
            Why, alas, would my paine haue pleaſed her, would my martyrdome haue contented her minde, had my perill procured her profite, or my care her commoditie? Nay, rather would not my danger haue béene her death, my miſhap her miſery, my torture her torments, and my fatall deſtiny her finall deſtruction. By ſauing my life in time wee may enioy our loue, but by death no hope had béene left for obtaining our deſire: ſo that I aſſure my ſelfe, Caſtania will rather allow of my policie by preuenting perills by flight, than miſlike of my practiſe in procuring mine owne ſafetie. And vppon this point I reſt, hoping that the Gods ſéeing how vniuſtly Valericus hath accuſed vs, will in tract of time rid vs from blame, and reward him with ſhame.
            
               Gwydonius was not more diſtreſſed with dolour, than poore Caſtania was combred with care, to ſée ſo ſtraunge a chaunce, and ſo ſodaine a change, that ſhe who of late was a royall Princeſſe, was now a ruthfull priſoner, that her fréedome was turned to fetters, her dignitie to miſerie, &amp; her happie ſtaie, to a moſt helliſh ſtate: that after flouds of teares which fell from her cryſtall eies, ſhe burſt forth into theſe tearmes.
            Alas (quoth ſhée) what poore Damoſell was euer driuen into ſuch doubtfull diſtreſſe? What Princeſs was

euer perplered with ſuch dolefull paſſions? what maid was euer croſſed with ſuch miſhappe? nay, what creature euer was clogged with the like calamitie? Haue the ſpightfull Deſtinies decréed my deſtruction, or the peruerſe Planets conſpired my bitter bane? Doth froward fortune mean to make mee a mirror of her mutabilitie, or is this the reward that Cupid beſtowes vpon his Clyents? Is euery one that doth fancie, maimed with the like miſfortune, or is Love alwaies accompanied with ſuch hapleſſe lucke? Alas no; for their loue is lawefull, and mine lewd and laſeiuious: their fancie is fixed vpon vertue, and mine vppon vanitie: they make their match with conſent of their Parents, and I my market without my Fathers counſaile? ſo that I am like in chooſing ſuch chaffer, to chop and change and liue by the loſſe: yea, to buy repentance at an vnreaſonable rate. Had it not been better for thée Callania, to haue condeſcended to ye requeſts of Valericus, than conſented to the ſuite of Gwydonius? to haue liked thine owne Countrey man, than loued a ſtraggling ſtranger: to haue ſatiſfied thy ſelfe with aſſurance, than vainley to fiſh for hope? Trueth, but what then? Can the ſtrawe reſiſt the vertue of the pure Ie
                  •
               ? Canth flaxe reſiſt the force of the fire? Can a louer withſtand the brunt of beautie? fréeze, if hée ſtand by the flame? peruert the lawes of Nature, or eſchue that which is framed by the fates, or flie from the force of fancie? No, for who ſo eſcapeth the deadly dartes of Cupid ſhall be ſcorched with his fire, and ſhée that with the dewe of chaſtitie quencheth his flame, ſhall be ouertaken with his winges: ſo that to ſéeke by flight to eſchue affection, is fooliſhly to enterpriſe that which can neuer be atchieued.
            But alas, If I muſt néedes lend a liſtening eare to the allurements of loue, was there none to like but thy Fathers foe? How, fond foole, couldeſt thou ſhew him curteſie, that intendes to repay thee with crueltie? How couldeſt thou chooſe the ſonne to thy mate, when the Father ſéekes

thy miſery. It is not poſſible to mixe the bloud of a Ball and a Beare, togither in one veſſell. The Lyons whelpes will neuer company with yong Woolues: the Faulcons called Pelagrae, will neuer fl
                  •
               e with the young 
                  •
               euerets: and if the Egges of a Crowe and a Curle we be put in one neſt, they both forthwith burſt in ſunder, becauſe there is ſuch ancient enmitie betwéen the olde ones. And wilt thou then be ſo wilfull to loue him whom thy father doth loath, or ſo peruerſe as to place thy ſelfe in that parentage, where there is ſuch mortall hatred betwéen the Parents? Wilt thou ſo farre forget the dutie of a childe, as more to reſpecte thy fatall enemy, than regard thy naturall Father? But why vile wretche doe I thus fondly fable? though Clerophontes be my Fathers ſo, yet Gwydonius is my faithful friend: though the one ſéeke to procure my paine, the other ſéekes to purchaſe my pleaſure: though the olde Sire ſtriues to ſubuert my Fathers ſtate, yet the ſonne neuer ſought to bee preiudiciall to his perſon, although that periured Paraſite Valericus hath moſt vniuſtly accuſed him of trecherie. Shall I then hate him who hath alwaies honored me? Shall I work his wo that wiſheth my weale? Shall I be his bane, who hath bred my bliſſe? Shall I deteſt him which ſerueth me with moſt déepe deuotion? No, I héere heartily powre out moſt pittifull playntes to the gods to preſerue my Gwydonius from perill, and that fortune may ſo fauor him as hée may paſſe out of Alexandria, without death or danger. What though I héere in pryſon pine in payne? VVhat though I ſink in ſorrow? What though I be diſtreſſed with griefe &amp; oppreſſed with miſery? What though I be croſſed with care, and cumbered with calamity? Tuſh, let my father fret and fume in his furie, let my brother rage and rayle, let that traitor Valericus triumph, and all the Countrie moſt bitterly curſe mee, yea, let them martyr mee moſt miſerably, let them torment mee moſt terribly, yet direfull death ſhall not feare mée, as long as I know Gwydonius is deuoyde of danger.

For I hope though Fortune frowne, though the deſtinies deny it, though the fates forſweare it, yea, though the gods themſelues ſay no, yet in time wee ſhall haue ſuch happie ſucceſſe, as the loyaltie of our loue, and the clearneſſe of our conſcience by the lawe of iuſtice do deſerue. And therefore Gwydonius ſhall be the Planet whereby to direct my dooings, hée ſhall be the ſtarre ſhall guide my compaſſe, he ſhal be the hauen to harbour in, and the Saint at whoſe ſhrine I meane to offer my deuotion.
            
               Caſtania hauing thus diſcourſed with her ſelfe, ſhe determined when the wars were ended, if ſhée could haue no hope to enioy the loue of Gwydonius, to confeſſe her falts and to ſue for mercy at the barre of her fathers curteſie: not that ſhe meant to liue without Gwydonius, or to loue or like any other, but to prolong her daies in dolour, that ſhée might moſt rigorouſly reuenge ye villany of Valericus, &amp; by bathing in his bloud ſhe might both ſatiſfie her ſelf, and ſignifie to Gwydonius how entirely ſhe loued and liked him. But leauing her perplexed with theſe paſſions, againe to Clerophontes.
            
            Who frying ſtill in his frantike fury, was not anie whit perſwaded to conclude peace with Orlanio, but hauing muſtered his men, as ſpéedily as might bée, imbarkt them, and with a lucky gale arriued at the coaſt of Alexandria, where the borderers not able to abide his forces, were conſtrayned to ſaue themſelues by flight. But he as a man hauing exiled from his heart both pietie and pitie, bathed his hands in guiltleſſe dloud, firing euery fort, battering downe euery bulwarke, ſacking each Citie, racing downe the wals to ye ground, and commanding his ſouldiors vpon pain of moſt grieuous puniſhment, not to haue any reſpect of perſons, neither to regard the hoarie hairs of the aged Cittizens, nor the tender yéeres of the ſucking infants, but to imbrue their blades with ye bloud of all men, of what degrée ſoeuer.
            
               Orlanio hearing how Clerophontes had inuaded his

dominions, and with what barbarous cruelty he had murthered his ſubiects, hauing alſo intellegence by his ſcowts, that his army was paſſing huge, the better to reſiſt the furious force of his enemy, hired out of other Countries a great multitude of mercenary Souldiours, ſo that he gathered a maruellous great hoaſt, wherein was an infinite number indued with great skill and long experience.
            Furniſhed thus ſufficiently both with men and munition; like a wiſe and warie Captaine, ſéeing that hée no waie elſe might reſiſt the puiſſant power of ſo mightie a Prince, determined without further delay to méet him and giue him preſent battaile, hauing maruellous affiance in the approoued manhoode and vertue of his ſouldiours.
            
               Clerophontes likewiſe béeing of ſuch a valiant and inuincible courage, as hée ſéemed from his infancy to be vowed to Mars and martiall affaires, manfully marched forward to méete with his enemies: which he performed ſo ſpéedily, that within few daies, both the armies were within view: which Clerophontes ſéeing, hée began to incourage his ſouldiours on this ſort.
            ALthough moſt truſty Subiectes (quoth hée) I neither doubt of your proweſſe, nor haue cauſe to feare your manhood, as hauing mine army fraught with the moſt couragious Captaines, and bouldeſt blouds of Mitylene, yet I with you to conſider how deſperately we haue aduentured vpon the conqueſt of this Dukedome, which if we atchieue, we ſhall not onely gaine perpetuall fame and renowme, but reap ſuch riches &amp; treaſure, as ſhal ſufficiently counteruaile our trauaile. But to obtaine this victory wée muſt behaue our ſelues valiantly, neyther dreading any danger though neuer ſo deſperate, nor doubting any perill though neuer ſo fearefull. Before our face we haue our enemie, behinde our backes the ſurging ſeas; ſo that fight

we muſt, but flie wée cannot: in being couragious wee winne the field and returne conquerours: in prouing cowards, wee both loſe our liues and the conqueſt: if wee foile our foes, wee returne with triumph: if we faint and flie, we haue no hope of ſafetie, but death and deſperation is imminent. Be then hardy to hazard, and valiant to venture amidſt the preaſe of your enemies, that daunted with your valour, they may be forced to fly, &amp; wee both triumph and enioy the treaſure.
            
               CLerophontes hauing thus louingly incouraged his ſouldiers, Orlanio on the other ſide ſéeing his men began to feare the force of the enemie, and were amazed wt ſuch a monſtrous multitude, prickt them forwarde with this parle.
            
            THat mightie Monarch Alexander ye great, who for his martiall exploites was a mirrour to all his poſteritie, whoſe proweſſe was ſuch, as he daūted Darius, and by his inuincible courage made a conqueſt of the whole worlde: hearing on a time one of his Captaines to demaund what multitude was in their enemies campe, anſwered, that it was not the point of a good ſouldier, to inquire how many the enemies were, but where they were: meaning that to feare the multitude is rather the ſigne of cowardiſe, than a token of courage. Which ſaying I wiſh you carefully to conſider; that ye huge armie of Clerophontes neither amaze your minds, nor abate your valour, ſith that the equitie of our cauſe doth more than counteruaile his companie. He inuadeth our realme without reaſon, &amp; wee defend but our owne right: he cruelly ſecketh to depriue vs of fréedome &amp; we lawfully do maintain our own libertie. He tyrannouſly ſtriueth to make vs bondſlaues, and we fight to frée our ſelues from captiuitie. If he preuaile let vs look for no pitty, but yt we ſhalbe murthered without mercy, we ſhall ſée before our face our wiues rauiſhed, our daughters defloured,

our parents put to death, our children ſlain, our goods ſpoiled, our Citie ſacked, and our ſelues brought to vtter ruthe and ruine. Sith then we are placed betwéen two extremities, either to poſſeſſe our own with plenty, or to paſſe our liues in penurie: let vs valiantly venture whatſoeuer wée gaine, let vs fight without feare: for better it is to die with honour, than to liue with ſhame.
            BY that time Orlanio had ended his Oration, the armies met in a plaine, within thirtie leagues of Alexandria. Where both of them ordering (as became good Captains) their people, there began in the breake of the daie the moſt cruell and terrible battaile that earſt was heard of, conſidering the number on both parts, their experience and policie, with the valiant proweſſe and courage of the captains. Thus continued they in fight, euen almoſt vntill Euen, with marueilous ſlaughter on both ſides, the victorie yet doubtfull, till in the end the Alexandrians began to faint and flie, more oppreſſed with the exceſſe of the multitude, than diſtreſſed for want of manhood: for there weretwo and fortie thouſand ſlaine, but not one taken priſoner, and of Clerophontes company eight and twenty thouſand flaine, and ſixe hundered mortallis wounded. This monſtrous maſſacre, and fearefull ſlaughter, ſo amazed the minds of theſe two Captaines, that for the better burying of ye dead, and healing of them which were hurt, they concluded a truce betwéene them for fiftéene daies, in which time Orlanio ſent Ambaſſadours to parle of peace with Clerophontes, but in vaine: for hee was reſolued either valiantly to die in the field with glorie, or to inioy the Dukedome of Alexandria with renowme. Yet as a worthy Prince preferring the ſecuritie of his ſouldiers before the ſafetie of his owne perſon, he offered them the combat, which Orlanio to auoyd the effuſion of blōud, moſt willingly accepted. Now it was agréed and concluded betwéene them, that two champions might be choſen, who by the dint of the

ſword ſhould ſtint the ſtrife betwéene theſe two armies. It he of Mitylene remained victor, then Orlanio ſhould not onely pay his former tribute, but deliuer vp his Dukedome into the hands of Clerophontes. But if the Alexandrian obtained the conqueſt, the Duke of Mitylene ſhould peaceably depart the Countrie, releaſe the tribute, and alſo reſigne his ſtate, and become a ſubiect to Orlanio. And for the better keeping and confirming of theſe conditions, they preſently diſpatcht Embaſſaders to Fernandus ye king of Bohemia, to intreat his Maieſtie that he would vouchſafe to become iudge in the combat: who for that hee wiſhed well to both theſe Dukes, graunted to their requeſts, and with as much ſpéedes might be, came to Alexandria. But in the meane time there was ſome difference about the champiōs: for Clerophontes ſaid, that ſith in loſing ye feld conſiſted the loſſe of liuing, life, and libertie, and in getting the victorie the gaine of a Dukedome, be would in proper perſon fight the combat, and trie the chaunce of Fortune, and therefore made a challenge to Orlanio. But her finding himſelfe faire vnfit to reſiſt his 
                  •
               uri
                  •
               us force, refuſed it. Yet premiſing, that none vnleſſe he were deſcended of Nobilitie, ſhould enter the l
                  •
               ſts, wherewith Clerophontes was very well contented. Now while this truce continued, which was prolonged for thirtie daies, it was lawfull for them of Alexandria to come and view the campe of Mitylene, and for the Mitylenes to goe and ſee the Cittie. Whereupon, Clerophontes deſirous to ſée Orlanio &amp; his Court, went onely accompanied with his guard to Alexandria, where he was moſt royally entertained, and ſumptuouſly feaſted by Orlanio, both of them remitting the rigour of their malice, till it ſhould be ſhewed in 
                  •
               ffect, by reaſon of their manhood. But as ſoone as Therſandro and the other Lordes ſawe Clerophontes, that he was rather a monſter than a man, hauing each limme ſo ſtrongly c
                  ••
               
               ched, each part ſo proportioned, ſo huge of ſtature. &amp; ſo fierce of countenance, they were ſo daunted with the ſight of his

perſon, as they almoſt feared to came in his preſence, ſaying: that thrée of the boldeſt bloudes in Alexandria were not able to abide the force of Clerophontes. Who now peaceablie departing to his hoaſt, left Orlanio as greatly perplexed for aſſembling his nobilitie together, amongſt whom he appointed the champion ſhould be choſen. They not onely with one conſent withſtood his command, but began to murmure and mutine againſt him, cōdemning him of follie that he would ſo vnaduiſedly commit his owne ſtate and their ſtaie to the doubtfull hazarde of one mans hap. Orlanio ſeeing that it was now no time to chaſtiſe this their preſumption, vnleſſe hee meant to raiſe ciuill diſſenſion in the cittie, which were the next way to confirme the enemie, and bréede his owne confuſion, he diſſembled his choler, and began to worke a newe way. For firſt he fréed Caſtania out of priſon, then made generall proclamation throughout his Dukedome, that what Lord ſo euer within his land would trie the combat with Clerophontes, if he remained victor in the conqueſt, hee would not onely giue him his daughter Caſtania to wife, let him poſſeſſe peaceably the Dukedome of Mitylene as her dowris, but be content to acknowledge him as his liege, &amp; pay him tribute, as he was wont to Clerophontes.
            
            While he lingred and liſtned how this proclamation would preuaile, Caſtania hearing this ſeuere ſentence, and dolefull doome pronounced, ſeeing that ſhe ſhould not onely be forced to forſake Gwydonius, but be conſtrained to match in mariage with one whom ſhe ſhould neither loue nor like, burſt forth into theſe bitter complaints.
            ALaſſe (quoth ſhe) how pinching a paine is it to be perplexed with diuerſe paſſions, what a noyſome care it is to be cumbred with ſundrie cogitations, what a woe it is to hang betwéene deſire a
                  ••
                deſpaire, and what a hell it is to houer betwéene feare and hope? For as to him which is aſſured to die, death is no dolour, in that he perfectly knows

there is no ſalue can cure his ſorow, ſo to him which feares to die, and yet hopes to liue, death were thrice more welcome than to linger in ſuch doubt. In which curſed caſe alas my care conſiſteth: for as out of the riuer Cea in Sicilia but fleſh moſt fearefull flames, and yet the ſtreame is paſſing colde, neither is ye water able to quench the fire, not the fire cauſe the water to be hot; ſo the heat of hope flameth out of the chilling fountain of feare, and yet the force of the one is not able to aſſwage the vehemency of the other, but ſtill my heauy heart is diuerſly aſſayled with them both.
            If my father Orlanio win yt conqueſt, I doubt my deſire ſhall reuer haue happy ſucceſſe: if Clerophontes triumph as victor, I greatly feare his cruelty is ſuch, as I ſhall not eſcape moſt hopleſſe death. And yet again, I hope that then my owne Gwydonius will accept me for his, and with triumphant armes embrace me. But alas, wil Clerophontes ſuffer him to match with his mortall foe, wil hée not rather preuent it by my perill? Yes no doubt: if he returne with triumph my father ſhall ſerue him as a ſubiect, my brother ſhall become his vaſſall, my friendes ſhall bee forelorne, my Citie ſackt, and my natiue Countrie brought to vtter confuſion. And ſhall I for the loue of a Stranger wiſh theſe ſtraunge Stratagems? Shall I to féede mine owne fancy, and content my luſting minde, wiſhe my Fathers death, my Brothers bane, my Friends miſhap, my Countries confuſion, and perhappes my owne miſerie? For though Gwydonius loued mée when our Parents were friendes, hée will not now like me being foes: but to reuenge the iniuries my Father offered him, will ſubtilly ſéeke to ſacke mine honour and honeſty, and ſo triumph of my ſhame and diſcredite. Had I not better pray my Father may winne the combate, and then ſhall I bathe in the ſtreames of bliſſe, and flowe in the flouds of felicitie, then ſhall I dread no daunger, no feare, no perills: then ſhall I ſée my father, friends, and Country, flouriſh in moſt happie proſperitie: then ſhall I enioy ſome iollie Gentleman,

who will loue mée being young; and cheriſh me being olde, and poſſeſſe the Dakedome of Mitylene for my downe. And canſt thou Caſtania be ſo ingratefull, as to will his woe which wiſheth thy weale? to deſire his deſtruction which prayeth for thy proſperity? Canſt thou be ſo couetous as to craue that for thy poſſeſſion, which is thy Gwydonius patrimonie? or ſo ſuſpicious, as to accuſe him of trechery, which hath bin but too truſty: to count him a counterfaite, which hath alwaies béene conſtant? No, come what come will, let froward Fortune fauour whom ſhée pleaſe, ſo I maie ioy and ſafely enioy my only ioy Gwydonius.
            
            As Caſtania had thus ended her complainte, Gwydonius who all this while lurked about the borders of Alexandria, heard what ſucceſſe Orlanio
                     •
                  
                affaires had with his Father Clerophontes, how varie fews or none at all durſt trie the combat with him, that his loue and Lady Caſtania was the priſe that hée ſhould get that gained the conqueſt. Which things conſidered, ſuppoſing that Caſtania had caſt him off, and that ſhe plaid, Out of ſight, out of mind, by a ſecret and truſty meſſenger, hee preſented her with this Letter.
            
               
                  Gwydonius to Caſtania, health.
                  THe pure ſpice, Caſtania, the more it is pounded, the ſwéeter ſmell it yéelds: the Camomill increaſeth moſt béeing troden on: the Palme tree the greater waight it beareth, the ſtraighter it groweth: the ſtone Terpiſtretes, the more it is beaten, the harder it is, and loyall loue is not weakened by the ſtormes of aduerſitie, but rather farre the more fortified by the frowarde ſtate of frowning Fortune: which Madame I ſpeake by proofe and experience:

for ſince I haue ſupped off the ſowre dregs of ſorrow, and béene peſtered with the bitten pills of penary, ſin or ſiniſter fortune hath croſſed me to the miſhaps, and diſaſter fates haue driuen mee downe to miſery, my fancy hath ſo furiouſly aſſaulted my minde, and affection hath ſo inceſſantly battered the bulwarke of my breſt, as the ſparkes of Ioue which kindled in mée in proſperity, are turned to fierce and fiery flames by adnorſitie. So that Madam, your preſence did not before procure me ſuch pleaſure, as your abſence doth paine, neither was I ſo drowned in delight, in frequenting your companie, as I am drenched with deſpight, by leading my life in ſorrowfull calamitie. Alaſſe Caſtania, what vnſpeakeable griefe hath tormented mée? what direfull dolour hath diſtreſſed mee? what helliſh horrour hath haunted mee? yea, what wee and wretchedneſſe hath wracked my wits, ſince thou laſt béen proclaimed a prey to him whoſoeuer winneth the priſe in the combate? How oft haue I wiſhed that I might bee the Champion to make the challenge, that I might venture my life to purchaſe thy liberty, that my death might redéem thée from danger?
                  But alas, I ſée to wiſh is in vaine: to craue of ye geds, that thy father ſhould vaunt of ye victory, is but to wiſh that our loue ſhould haue hapleſſe ſucceſſe: to pray that Clerophontes ſhould returne with conqueſt, thou wilt déeme I deſire thy friends miſfortune. Thus aſſayled with diuers doubts, I driue off my dayes in dolour: hoping howſoeuer fortune frowne, that the fates wil aſſigne vs a perfect calm of permanent felicity for this ſturdie ſtorme of pinching miſerie.
                  
                     Thine, euer exiled
Gwydonius.
                  
               
            
            
               
               CAſtania hauing receiued this Letter, ſéeing that no ſiniſter chaunce of fortune was able to change the fixed fancie of Gwydonius, conceiued ſuch aſſured hope in his conſtancie, as now ſhée thought his troth was filed with no ſpot of treachery, that his faith was quite deuoide of flatterie, &amp; that whatſoeuer chaunced, ſhe might ſafely repoſe hir ſtay and ſtate in his loyaltie. Inſomuch that to drine out the euill opinion which ſhe thought her brother Therſandro had conceiued of Gwydonius conſpiracie, ſhe ſecretly ſhewed him the Letter: which after he had read ouer, and carefully conſtrued euery clauſe, hee began both to detect and deteſt the villanie of Valericus, deſtring his ſiſter Caſtania that ſhee would earneſtly perſwade Gwydonius in diſguiſed apparel ſpéedily to repair to her ledging, promiſing with ſolemne vowes and ſacred oathes, not to be preiudiciall to his perſon: Caſtania affying greatly in her brothers faith, and deſtrous to haue a fight of her louing Gwydonius, returned him theſe few lines.
            
               
                  Caſtania, to Gwydonius, proſperity.
                  VVHoſo taſteth Gwydonius of the heard Mely Sophilos is neuer tormented with the ſting of aduerſttie, and ſhée that weareth the ſtone Mephites about her, neuer ſorroweth at ſiniſter fortune, who ſo fancieth without faining neuer proueth fickle, and ſhe that loueth loyally may well be croſſed with calamitie, but neuer iuſtly accuſed of incōſtancy. Account thy Caſtania good Gwydonius to be in ye ſame predicament: for let diſaſter miſhap driue me down to moſt deadly miſerie, let the cruell fates compaſſe me with curſed care, let fortune and the deſtinies conclude my confuſion, yet it ſhall not diminiſh my fancie, but rather increaſe my affection. I will ſtill in weale, in woe, in bale, in bliſſe, in mirth &amp; miſery, ſay I loue, and it is

onely Gvvidonius. For ſhall our fancie be ſuch as it ſhall be foiled with miſfortune? no, but as Thetis chaunging into many ſhapes, at laſt returned into her owne forme, ſo into what miſhap I be driuen by miſerie, yet I will ſtand in mine old ſtate in deſpight of the fates and fortune. Come therefore Gwydonius to the Court in diſguiſed apparell, but without care: for thou ſhalt finde me ſo truſtie, as my troth ſhalbe without ſpot, and thy health without hazard. Thus wiſhing thy curteſie to conſter well of my conſtancie, I bid thee farewell
                  
                     Thine, or not her owne,
conſtant Caſtania.
                  
               
            
            
               GWydonius hauing carefully conſtrued ouer the contents of this louing Letter, although the rigor of Orlanio might haue giuen him ſufficient cauſe of ſuſpicion, yet the cléereneſſe of his owne conſcience, and the loue he bare to Caſtania, would not ſuffer him either to ſuſpect any treaſon, or to doubt of any deceit, but determined without any delay to put the ſafetie of his perſon and the ſafegard of his life into her handes. But leauing him to bring his purpoſe luckily to paſſe, againe to Orlanio.
            
            Who ſéeing that his proclamation coulde not preuayle, and that his Nobles preferred their owne ſafetie before his ſecuritie, was perplexed with ſuch helliſh paſſions, &amp; griped with ſuch pinching griefe, as the Ghoſtes tormented with griſly fiends, felt no ſuch hapleſſe furie. To fight with Clerophōtes, hee felt his ſtrength farre vnfit to reſiſt his force: to denie the combat, he neither could nor would, although he brought himſelfe to confuſion, &amp; his children to captituitie: ſo yt howſoeuer he turned himſelf, he ſaw before his face death and deſpaire, woe and wretchedneſſe, miſhap and miſerie. Combred thus with this cureleſſe care, and ſitting ſolitarily in ſorrow, ſéeing the diſmall day drewe on, and hearing that Fernandus ye king of Bohemia was lately

landed, he fell into more furious paſſions, vntill he was driuen out of his dumpes by his ſonne Therſandro: who perceiuing his father thus dolefully daunted, he beganne moſt louingly to comfort him, promiſing that ſince none durſt venture to deale with Clerophontes, hée himſelfe would fight the combat, and either worthlly win the conqueſt with renowme, or manfully die in the fielde with honour.
            
               Orlanio hearing the bold courage of this newe champion, felt his ſorrow ſomewhat ſalued by this profer, perſwading himſelfe that his ſonne was better able to abide the brunt than he, and hoping that the Gods would fauour the equitie of the cauſe, and aſſuredly by iuſtice graunt him the victorie. Reſting I ſay, vpon this hope, and thanking Therſandro for his naturall affection, and prayſing him for his noble courage, he preſently went to méete Fernandus, whom he moſt princely entertained, conducting him very royally into Alexandria, where he moſt ſumptuouſly ſealled him and all his traine. But as they paſſed away the time in paſtime and pleaſure, ſo poore Therſandro ſpent the day in dolour, and the night in ſorrowe. For although to comfort his father hee made light of the combat, and valiantly offered himſelfe to trie the chaunce of fortune, yet ſeeing his enemies force far to excéed his féeble ſtrength, hee began to faint, although like a worthy Gentleman he couered his dreadfull courage with a deſperate countenance, raunging vp and downe the fields to driue away his melancholie: where by chance in diſguiſed apparell he met Gvvidonius, to whom after ſome parle paſt betwéene them, he bewrated the whole ſtate of the matter, how he was to enter combat with Clerophontes, and that he doubted greatly of the euent of the victorie, fearing the force of his Father, and fainting at his owne unbecillitie. Which Gwydonius hearing, hee made this ſhort anſwere.
            
               
               THerſandro (quoth hée) it is vaine with long talke to paſſe away the time when delay bréeds danger, and folly to hope for faire weather when the Aire is ouercaſt with cloudes: leauing off therofore all oathes to confirme my faith, thus much to the purpoſe. If it pleaſe thee to truſt me without tryall, and to giue any confidence to my words, I héere promiſe both to make manifeſt my loyall loue to Caſtania, and to repaie thy courteſie; that I wil, reſembling thy perſon, and diſguiſed in thy armour, enter combat with my father Clerophontes, eyther intending by winning the victorie to obtaine my will, or by loſing the conqueſt to want my wiſh: if this my profer pleaſe thée, I will paſſe priuily to the Court: if not, good Therſandro, let me go as I came.
            
               Therſandro, commending the ſubtill deuiſe of Gwydonius, carried him as couertly as coulde be to Caſtania, to whom hée was farre more welcome, than ſoone come, remayning cloſely in her cloſet til the next morning. Caſtania notwithſtanding knowing nothing of their pretence, Fernandus king of Bohemia, the next day being gone with al his Nobility to the place appointed for the combat; Orlanio, Caſtania, and all the Lords of Alexandria, clad in mourning attire followed him, thinking this diſmall daie ſhould bée the date of their deſtruction. And Clerophontes as a balefull wretch thirſting after bloud, and glorying in the hope of his ſuppoſed conqueſt, ſtoode in the liſtes, expecting his fatall foe. To whome Gwydonius his ſonns furniſhed with the armour of Therſandro, preſented himſelfe. Who ſéeing, that forced by the fond allurements of Loue, he was to fight, not with his mortall foe, but with his naturall father, he fell into theſe doubtfull dumps:
            Alas poore Gwydonius (quoth he) how art thou combred with diuerſe cogitations? what a cruell conflict doeſt thou finde in thy minde betwéene loue and loyaltie, nature and neceſſity? who euer was ſo wilfull, as willingly to wage

battaile againſt his owne father? who ſo cruell as to enter combat with his owne ſire? Alas, dutie perſwades mee not to practice ſo monſtrons a miſchiefe: but the deuotion I owe Caſtania, drines mee to performe the déede, were it thrice more dangerous or deſperate. The honour I owe to my father, makes mée faint for feare, but once to imagine ſo brutiſh a fact: the loue I owe to Caſtania, conſtrayneth me to defend the combat, if Iupiter himſelfe made the challenge. And is not (fond foole) neceſſitie aboue nature? is not the lawe of loue aboue King or Keyzar, Father or Friends, God or the diuell? Yes. And ſo I mean to take it: for either I will valiantly winne the conqueſt and my Caſtania, or loſe the victory, and ſo by death end my miſeries.
            With that the Trumpets ſound, and Gwydoniu; luſtily leaping into the liſts, fell preſently into furious fight with his Father, driuing not onely Fernandus and Orlanio but alſo both the armies into a great doubt. For although Clerophontes moſt cruelly proſecuted him, yet he alwaies receiued the ſtrokes, but neuer ſo much as once returned one blow: til at laſt looking aloft, &amp; ſpying Caſtania, his courage increaſed, that all feare ſet aſide, he careleſly ſlang away his ſword and ſhield, and ran vpon his Father, not only tearing from him his Target; but, violently caſting him vpon the ground and ſpéedily vnlacing his helmet, offered to cut off his head with his owne ſword: but Clerophontes crying out confeſſed himſelfe captiue, and graunted his enemy the conqueſt. Wherupon they of Alexandria, gaue a mighty ſhowt, and Fernandus and Orlanio came downe ready to carrie Clerophontes captiue to the Cittie. But Gwydonius firſt demaunded of Orlanio if he was content to perform that which he promiſed by proclamation: to whō 
               Fernandus anſwered, that both hee would and ſhould; or elſe as he was his friend, ſo he would be his fo. Gwydonius hearing this faithfull aſſertion of the King, pulling downe his heauer began to ſpeak in this manner.
            
               
I Let thee Orlanio (quoth hée) and the worthy king of Bohemia to know, that I am Gwydonius, ſonne and heire to this conquered Clerophontes, who for the loue of thy Daughter Caſtania, haue not ſpared contrary to the law of nature to fight with mine owne Father; hoping the deſtinies by my meanes haue decréed not onely of fatall foes to make you faithfull friends, but to finiſh vp your loue, which otherwiſe could not haue béen performed.
            I haue wonne Orlanio my Fathers Dukedome by victory, and thy daughter by conqueſt: the one I had before by inheritance, and the other by loue, yet I would willingly haue thy good will, which if thou grant, I hope my father wil both pardon my offence, and think well of my proffer.
            
               Clerophontes kiſſing and embracing Gwydonius, told him his care whas half cured, in that ſuch a good captain had wonne the conqueſt. Fernandus and Orlanio ſtoode aſtoniſhed at this ſtrange Tragedy, doubting whether they dreamt of ſuch a rare deuiſe, or ſaw it in effect. At laſt Orlanio, as one wakened out of a trance, with trickling tears imbraced Clerophontes, honoring him as his ſoueraigne, and promiſing not onely to giue Caſtania to Gwydonius, bus alſo halfe his Dukedome in dowrie. Clerophontes thanking him for his curteſie, conſented moſt willingly to this motion: ſo that before Fernandus departed, the marriage betwéen Gwydonius and Caſtania, Therſandro and Lewcippa was moſt ſumptuouſly ſolemnlzed.
            FINIS.
            
         
         
            
            The Debate betweene Follie and Loue, tranſlated out of French by ROBERT GREEN, Maiſter of Artes.
            
            
               The ARGVMENT.
               
                  IVpiter made a great Feaſt, at the which all the gods were commanded to be preſent. Loue and Folly arriue at one inſtant at the gate of the palace, which was ſhut hauing nothing open but the wicket. Folly ſeeing Loue readie to enter in, paſſeth before: which repulſe driueth Loue into choler. Folly auoucheth that of right ſhe ought to be the foremoſt. Whereupon they enter into diſputation of their power, dignity and ſuperioritie. But Loue not able to get the conqueſt by words, taketh his bowe in hand and ſhooteth at hir; but in vaine: for Folly became inuiſible, and in deſpight pulleth out Cupids eyes. And for to couer this deformity, ſhadoweth his face with a vaile, ſo framed by the Deſtinies, that is was not poſſible to take it away. Venus complayneth of Folly vnto Iupiter, who appointeth Apollo &amp; Mercury to pleade the caſe of theſe two Clients: whoſe diſcourſe being heard, hee pronounceth his ſentence.
            
            
               
                  FOLLIE.
                  
                     I Fear greatly that I ſhal be the laſt at yt feaſt of Iupiter, where all the gods (no doubt) do attend me. And yet me think I ſée the ſonne of Venus which is as late as I. I will paſſe before him, leaſt they call me ſluggiſh and ſlothfull.
               
               
                  
                  Loue.
                  VVHat ſoole, is this that repulſeth mee ſo rudely? Take héede leaſt haſte make waſte, and that thy raſhneſſe cauſe thée not to cry Peccaui.
                  
               
               
                  Folly.
                  Oh ſir, blame me not though I make haſte: for I go before, to tell the gods that you come at leiſure.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  Nay, that which is eaſily begun, is not alwaies lightly ended: for before you eſcape me, I wil reuenge this thy iniurious ieſting.
               
               
                  Follie.
                  Let mee goe fond Loue, and ſtate mée not: for as it is a ſhame to quarrell with a woman, ſo it is more diſcredit to take the foile.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  The foile? What boaſting brags be theſe? Who hath euer aduentured to deſpiſe me, much leſſe to defie me? But doeſt thou know what I am?
               
               
                  Folly.
                  Thou art Cupid, the Sonne of Venus.
                  
               
               
                  Loue.
                  How dareſt thou then vaunt thy ſelfe againſt mée? which how little ſo euer I bee, am the moſt redoubted of all the gods.
               
               
                  Folly.
                  Thy words are great whatſoeuer thy works be: but tell me, what or wherein lieth this thy great power?
               
               
                  Loue.
                  The heauens and the earth (fond foole) are witneſſes of my words, there is no place where I haue not left Trophées in ſigne of triumph. Looke into heauen, and demand if anie of the gods haue eſcaped my hands. Begin with olde Saturne, Iupiter, Mars, Apollo, and end with the demi gods, Satyres, Fawnes, and Syluans: Nay, the goddeſſes

themſelues will not ſhame to confeſſe ſomewhat. Looke vpon the earth, and ſée if thou canſt finde one which hath not béene foyled by my meanes. Behold in the furious Seas, how Neptune &amp; his Tritons doe pield me obeiſance. Yea, and laſtly looke into Hell it ſelfe, if I haue not forced Pluto that infernall Prince, to ſteale away Proſerpina the daughter of Ceres. And to yt end thou doubt not with what engines I haue atchieued theſe victories, behold this bowe and theſe arrowes only, which haue wonne me theſe worthie conqueſts. I haue no néede that Vulcan do temper my tooles. I am not accompanied with the Furies &amp; Harpies, to cauſe me to bée feared before the combat. I haue not to do with Chariots, Souldiours, Captaines, men of armes, nor great troupes of Horſmen, without the which mortall men cannot triumph. No, I haue no other counſaile, munition, nor aide, but my ſelfe. When I ſée mine enemies in the fielde, I preſent my ſelfe with my bowe, and let flie my boltes, and the victorie is alwaies gotten at the firſt ſtroke.
               
               
                  Folly.
                  I excuſe thy youthfull yéeres poore Cupide, or elſe I woulde blaze thée for the moſt preſumptuous patch in the world. It ſéemeth by thy vaine vaunting, that euery one holdeth his life of thy mercy, and that thou art the onely Lord and Soueraign both in Heauen, Earth, the Sea, and Hell. But many things are ſpoken which are neuer beléeued.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  And art thou ſo hard of beléefe, to deny that which euery one confeſſeth?
               
               
                  Folly.
                  I haue not to doo with other mens opinions: but this I am ſure: that it is not by thy force and proweſſe, that ſo many miracles are wrought in the world, but by my induſtry, by my meanes, and by my diligence, although thou knoweſt me not. But if thou doeſt cōtinue long in this thy

choler, I wil let thée vnderſt
                        •
                     nd, that thy bowe and thy arrowes wherof thou vaunteſt ſo much, are more weak than wax, if I bend not the one and temper the other.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  Doeſt thou thinke by this ſkoffing to pacifie mine anger, or by contemptuous threatning to qualifie my choler? Haſt thou euer (fond fool) handled my bowe, or directed my bolts? Is it thy proweſſe and not my force which performeth ſuch valiant conqueſts? But ſince thou regardeſt me, and reſpecteſt my force ſo little, thou ſhalt preſently féel the proofe thereof.
               
               Folly maketh her ſelfe inuiſible, ſo that Loue cannot hit her.
               
                  Loue.
                  But where art thou become? How haſt thou eſcaped mee? This onely is the ſtrangeſt caſe that euer chaunced vnto me. I had thought that amongſt all the gods I only could haue made my ſelfe inuiſible. But now I ſée I am deceiued.
               
               
                  Folly.
                  Did not I tell thee before, that thy bowe &amp; thy arrows are of no force, but when it pleaſeth me, and that by my means thou alwaies obtaineſt the conqueſt? Maruaile not if I be inuiſible: for if I lift the eyes of the Eagle or of the Serpent Epidaurus, cannot eſpie me; for Chameleon like, take the ſhape of them which whom I do remaine.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  Trulie as I coniecture, thou art ſome Sorcereſſe, or ſome Enchauntreſſe, ſome Circe, ſome Medea, or ſome Fairie.
               
               
                  Folly.
                  Wel, ſince, thou doeſt thus recleſly rail vpon me, know that I am a godeſſe as thou art a god: my name is Follie▪
                     
I am ſhe which raiſeth thee vp, and caſteth thee downe at my pleaſure. Thou vnlooſeſt thy bowe, &amp; lefteſt flie thine arrowes in the aire: but I place them where it pleaſeth me. Thou doeſt addreſſe thy ſelfe againſt Iupiter: but he is of ſuch puiſſance, that if I both guided not thy hand, &amp; tempered thy arrow, thy féeble force could little preuail againſt his proweſſe. Indéed thou diddeſt force Iupiter to loue, but I cauſed him to change himſelf into a Swan, into a Bull, into Gold, into an Eagle. Who cauſed Mars &amp; thy mother Venus to be taken in bed together by the limping cuckold Vulcan, but I? If Paris had done no other thing but loued Helena, Sparta had neuer reioyced, nor Troy béen brought to ruine. But did not I cauſe him to goe to Menelaus, vnder colour of Embaſſage, to Court vnto his wife, to leade her away by force, and after to defend his vniuſt quarrell againſt all Greece? Who had ſpoken of the loue of Dido, if he had not deuiſed to goe a hunting, that ſhe might haue the better opportunity to communicate with Aeneas, that by ſuch priuate familiaritie he might not be aſhamed to take from her that which long before moſt willinglie ſhée would haue giuen him. I beléeue no mention had beene made of Artemiſia, if I had not cauſed her drinke the cynders of her huſbāds dead carkaſſe: for els who had knowne whether ſhe had loued her huſbande more than other women? The effect and iſſues of things alwaies makes them to be praiſed or diſpraiſed. If thou makeſt men to loue, yet I am oft times the chiefeſt cauſe. But if any ſtraunge aduenture or great effect chanceth, in that thou haſt no part, but the onely honour belongeth vnto me. Thou ruleſt nothing but the heart, the reſt I gouerne: yea, I leade thee, I conduct thee, &amp; thine eies ſerue thée to no more vſe than the beames of the Sunne to a blinde man. But to the ende thou know me from henceforth and that thou maieſt giue me thankes for conducting thee carefully, behold now how greatly thine eies do profit thée.
               
               
                  Follie putteth out Cupids eyes.
               
                  Loue.
                  Alas Iupiter, O my mother Venus, what auaileth it to be thy ſonne ſo feared, ſo redoubted, both in heauen and in earth, if I be ſubiect to be iniured as the moſt vile ſlaue in the worlde? Alaſſe, haue I thus loſt mine eyes by an vnknowne woman?
               
               
                  Follie.
                  Take héede fond foole another time to raile vpon thoſe, who perhaps are of more force and puiſſaunce than thou. Thou haſt offended the Quéen of men, thou haſt outraged her, who gouerneth the heart, the braine, and the minde; vnder whoſe ſhadow euery one once in his life ſhrowdeth himſelfe, and there remaineth either long or ſhort time according to his merite: thou haſt diſpleaſed her who procureth thy renowme, thou haſt contemned her who hath aduanced thée, and therefore hath this miſfortune fallen vpon thy head.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  Alas! how is it poſſible for me to honour her whome I neuer knew, or to reuerence that perſon whome before I neuer ſawe: but if thou haſt borne mee ſuch great good will as then ſaieſt, pardon this my offence, and reſtore me my ſight.
               
               
                  Follie.
                  To reſtore thee thine eyes is not in my power: but I will couer the place, to hide the deformitie.
               
               Follie couereth Cupids face with a Scarfe, and giueth him winges.
               And in lieu of this hapleſſe lucke, thou ſhalt haue theſe wings which ſhall carrie thee whither thou wilt wiſh.
               
                  
                  Loue.
                  But where hadſt thou this vaile ſo readie to couer my deformitie?
               
               
                  Follie.
                  It was giuen me as I came hither by one of the Deſtinies: who tolde me it was of that nature, that if it were once faſtned, it could neuer be vnlooſed.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  How vnlooſed? Am I then blinde for euer? O vile and traiterous wretch, could it not ſuffice to put out mine eies, but to take away the meanes that the gods cannot reſtore them? Now I ſée the ſentence verified on my ſelfe, that it is not good to take a preſent at the hand of anenemy. O cruell deſtinies, O curſed daie! ſhall not the heauens, ye earth, and the ſeas haue cauſe to waile, ſith Loue is blinde? But why doe I complaine here in vaine? it is better for me to ſue to the Gods for reuengement.
               
            
            
               The ſecond Diſcourſe.
               Loue goeth from the palace of Iupiter, lamenting to himſelfe his miſchiefe.
               
                  Loue.
                  Alas in what miſerable caſe am I? what can either my bowe or mine arrows auaile me? now can I not cauſe whō I liſt to loue, but without reſpect of perſons, euerie one is in daunger of my dartes. Hitherto I haue onely cauſed daintie damſels, and yong youths to loue, I did chooſe out the braueſt blouds, and the faireſt and moſt well featured men: I did pardon vile and baſe perſons, I excuſed the deformed creatures, and let olde age remaine in peace. But now, thinking to hit a young gallant, I light vppon ſome olde doating lecher: in ſtead of ſome braue Gentleman, I ſtrike ſome filthie lurden. And it ſhall happen (I doubt) that they ſhalbe moſt fortunate in their loue; ſo yt by

patrimony, preſence, or wealth, they ſhall ſooneſt winne the fauour of women, and by this meanes my kingdome ſhall come to ruine, when men ſée in it ſuch diſorder and cuill gouernment.
               
               Venus hauing long ſought Cupid, now meeteth him.
               
                  I Haue carefully long ſought thée my déere ſonne, maruelling what the cauſe ſhould bee that thou haſt not béene preſent at the banket of Iupiter: Who is greatly incenſed againſt thée, not only for thy abſence, but for the cōplaints which are powred out againſt thée by ſundrie poore artificers, laboring men, peaſants, ſlaues, hand-maids, old men, and toothleſſe aged women, crying all vnto Iupiter, that they loue; thinking themſelues greatly iniured in this reſpect, that the paſſion which is proper to worthy and Noble men, ſhould be inflicted vpon them which are of the baſe and vileſt ſort.
               
               
                  Loue.
                  Had not the great miſfortune which is chaunced vnto me happened, I had neither béen abſent from the banquet, nor their gréeuous complaints had not béene inſerred againſt me.
               
               
                  Venus.
                  Why? And art thou hurt? Who hath thus vailed thine eyes?
               
               
                  Loue.
                  
                     Folly hath not onely pulled them out, but alſo hath put this band before mine eyes, which can neuer be taken away.
               
               
                  Venus.
                  O curſed enemy of all wiſedome, O hapleſſe wretch, vniuſtly called a goddeſſe, and more vnrightly tearmed immortal, haſt thou depriued me of my chiefeſt delight and felicity? O diſaſter loue, O diſſolute mother, O wofull

                     Venus, who ſéeſt thy ſonne, thy ioy, and only care, thus cruelly depriued of his ſight. Well, ſince thy miſhappe is ſo great, I vowe that euery one that ſhall loue (what fauour or happy ſucceſſe ſoeuer he ſhall haue) ſhall not be without ſome care, trouble, or calamitie, that he vaunt not himſelfe to be more happie than the ſonne of Venus.
                  
               
               
                  Loue.
                  Ceaſe off good mother from theſe ſorrowful complaints, and redouble not my griefe by theſe dolorous diſcourſes, ſuffer mee to beare mine owne miſfortune, and wiſh not euill vnto them which ſhall be my ſubiects.
               
               
                  Venus.
                  Well, let vs then go to Iupiter, and complaine of this curſed inchantreſſe.
               
            
            
               The third Diſcourſe.
               
                  Venus.
                  It euer thou haddeſt pittie of my plaintes, moſt iuſt Iupiter, when thou ſaweſt me labour to ſaue my ſonne Aeneas from the furie of the raging ſeas, and to defend him from other dangers, in the which hée was preſent at the ſiege of Troy: If my teares for the death of my deare Adonis moued thee to compaſſion: The ſurpaſſing ſorrow that I doe conceiue for the great iniurie offered to Cupid, I hope ſhall mooue thée to pittie. If teares wold ſuffer me, I would bewray the cauſe of my ſorrow: but behold my ſon in what plight hee is, and thou ſhalt eaſily perceiue the cauſe of my complaint.
               
               
                  Iupiter.
                  Alaſſe my béere daughter, what doe theſe teares preuaile? knoweſt thou not what fatherly affection I haue alwaies borne thee? what doeſt thou diſtruſt that I will not ſuccour thee, or that I cannot?
               
               
                  Venus.
                  No, I neither doubt the one, nor diſtruſt the other, only

demaund iuſtice againſt Follie, the moſt outragious Furie in the worlde, which hath thus grieuouſly abuted Cupid.
                  
               
               
                  Folly.
                  Moſt mightie and ſoueraigne Iupiter, behold I am here ready to anſwere to Venus complaints, and to debate my right againſt Cupid.
                  
               
               
                  Iupiter.
                  
                     Folly, I will neither accuſe nor excuſe thée, vntill I haue heard the defence of the one, as well as the plaint of the other, leaſt I ſhould be thought partiall: neither, for the more auoiding of iniuſtice in the matter, will I ſuffer you to pleade your owne cauſes, but Venus chooſe you one of the Gods, and Folly take you another.
               
               
                  Venus.
                  I chooſe Apollo to defend my cauſe.
               
               
                  Follie.
                  And I Mercurie, to maintaine my right.
               
               
                  Iupiter.
                  Then Apollo &amp; Mercurie prepare your ſelues to plead well in your clientes caſes: and Apollo ſince you take the plaintifes part, let vs heare what you can ſay.
               
               
                  Apollo.
                  THe common people, right ſoueraign Iupiter, although their minds be ſotted, and almoſt ſenſeleſſe, yet they haue alway had loue in ſuch ſacred eſtimation, that they haue carefully rewarded them with the titles of honor and dignitie, which haue excelled in that holy affection, eſtéeming this onely vertue (if ſo rightly it may bee tearmed) ſufficient, of a man to make one a God. The Scythians for this cauſe canonized Pilades and Oreſtes, erecting temples vnto them, and calling them the Gods of amitie. Caſtor and Pollux were made immortall by this meanes, not in that they were brothers, but in that (which is rare) their

loue was inuiolable. How hath ſame blazed abroad ye loue of Dauid and Ionathan, the amitie of Pythias and Damon, and of Titus and Giſippus? But the better to make manifeſt the force of loue and amitie, I will alledge the ſaying of Darius, who opening a Pomgranate, being demanded whereof hee would haue as manie as there were graines wtin, anſwered, of Zopyres: this Zopyrus was his faithful friend, by the meanes of whom he conquered Babylon. I remember alſo a certaine Syrian demaunding a mayd in mariage &amp; being willed to ſhewe of what wealth hee was, ſaid that he had no other riches, but two friendes; eſteeming himſelfe rich inough with ſuch poſſeſſions to craue the daughter of a great Lord in marriage. Did not loue cauſe Ariadne ſaue Theſeus life, Hypermineſtra redéeme Linceus frō danger, and Medea frée Iaſon from perill? Haue not many poore ſoldiers béen aduanced to high dignities by the meanes of loue? Yea, doth not all pleaſure and profit procéed to man by loue, cauſing him to looke with an amiable countenance, to ſpeake pleaſantly, and to bee curious in his geſtures, although by nature he be dull, ſottiſh, and of a fierce looke? What cauſeth a man to go braue and fine in his apparell, ſeeking euerie day new faſhions, but loue? What procureth Gentlewomen to haue their haire frizled, criſped, &amp; embrodered with gold, to be dreſſed after the Spaniſh, French, or Italian faſhion, but Loue? Painting their faces, if they be foule, with liuely colours. But if they be faire, they ſo carefully kéepe their beautie from the parching heate of ſummer, from the chilling cold of Win
                        •
                     
                     ter, from the winde, raine, and aire, as they remaine almoſt euer young, not ſo much as forgetting to haue theirſhooes made fine and neate (becauſe the curiouſneſſe of men is ſuch, as they leaue not to looke from the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foote) to haue their gemmes, iewels, ouches, rings, perfumed gloues, &amp; what not? In fine, what beautie or brauerie is in the apparell, either of man or woman, all procéedeth of Loue. Shall I ſay that Muſicke was

onely inuented by loue, yea truly: for either it mitigateth the paſſions wherewith men are perplexed, or elſe augmenteth their pleaſure, ſo that daily they inuent diuerſe kindes of inſtruments, as Lutes Citrons, Violls, Flutes, Cornets, Banderas, wheron they play Madrigalls, Sonnetts, Pauins, Meaſures, Galliardes, and all theſe in remembrance of Loue, as he for whom men doe more than for any other. What cauſeth men to iuſt, tourney, runne at tilt, and combat, but Loue? Who cauſed Comedies, ſhews Tragedies and Maſkes to be inuented, but Loue? Wherof commeth it that men delight to rehearſe their amorous chaunces and ſtraunge paſſions, and to relate them to their companions? ſome praiſing the curteſie of his Lady, another condemning his miſtreſſe cruelty: yea, recounting a thouſand miſhappes which happen in their Loues: as Letters diſcloſed, euill reports, ſuſpicious iealouſie, ſometimes the husband comming home ſooner than either the louer would, or the wife doeth wiſh: ſometimes coniecturing without cauſe, and otherwhiles beléeuing nothing, but truſting vpon his wines honeſty. To be ſhort, the greateſt pleaſure after Loue, is to tell what perillous dangers are paſſed. But what maketh ſo many Poets in the world, is it not Loue? The which ſéemeth to bee the plaine ſonge wheron all Poets doe deſcant: yea, there are fewe which write vppon any ſerious matter, but they cloſe vp their work with ſome amorous clauſe, or elſe they are the worſe accepted. Ouid hath celebrated ye fame of Cupid, Petrarke and Virgill, Homer and Liuius, Sappho, yea, &amp; that ſeuere Socrates wrote ſomewhat of his loue Aſpaſia. Tuſh, who rightly can denie, that Loue is not the cauſe of all the glory, honor, profit, and pleaſure which happeneth to man, and that without it hee cannot conueniently liue, but ſhall run into a thouſand enormities?
                  All this happy ſucceſſe came by Loue, aslong as hee had his eies: but now béeing depriued of his ſight, and accōpanied with Folly, it is to be feared, nay certainly to be

beléeued, that he ſhall be the cauſe of as many diſcommodities, miſchiefes and miſhaps, as hetherto he hath béen of honour, profite, and pleaſure. The noblemen which loued their inferiours, and the ſubiectes which dutifully ſerued their Lordes, ſhall be marueilouſly changed by the meanes of Follie: for the maiſter ſhall loue his ſeruant onely for his ſeruice, and the ſeruant his maiſter onely for commoditie. Yea, there is none ſo addicted vnto vertue, but if once he loue, he ſhall preſently commit ſome fooliſh touch: and the more ſtraight and firme Loue is, the greater diſorder there ſhall be by the meanes of Folly. There will returne into the world more than one Biblis, more than one Semyramis, than one Myrrha, than one Canace, than one Phaedra. There ſhall be no place in the world vnſpotted. The high walles and trelliſſed windowes ſhall not kéepe the Nunnes and Veſtall Virgins in ſafegard. Olde age ſhall turne her aged affections into fond fancies and wanton deſires. Shame ſhall liue as an exile. There ſhall be no difference betwéene the noble and peaſant, betwéene the Infidell and the Moore, the Turke and the Iewe: the Lady, the Miſtreſſe, and the handmayd. But there ſhall inſue ſuch a confuſed inequalitie, that the faire ſhall not be matched with the well featured, but ſhall bee oft times ioyned with foule and deformed perſons. Great Ladies and noble Dames ſhall fall in loue with them whome before they would diſdaine to accept as their ſeruants. And when the loiall and faithfull louers haue long languiſhed in the loue of ſome beautifull Dame, whoſe mutuall good will they haue gained by deſert; then Follie will cauſe ſome fickle and falſe flatterer to enioy that in one houre, which in all their life they could not attaine. I paſſe ouer the continuall debates and quarrels that ſhall inſue by Follie, whereof ſhall ſpring woundes, maſſacres, &amp; moſt fearefull murthers. And I greatly feare that whereas Loue hath inuented ſo many laudable ſciences, and brought foorth ſo many commodities, that now he will bring great idleneſſe, accompanied

with ignorance, that he will cauſe young Gentlemen to leaue feates of armes, to forſake the ſeruice of their Prince, to reiect honorable ſtudies, and to applie thē
                     ſelues to vain ſongs and ſonnets, to chambering and wantonneſſe, to banquetting and gluttony, bringing infinite diſeaſes to their bodies, and ſundry dangers and perils to their perſons: for there is no more dangerous company than of Folly.
                  Behold O ſoueraigne Iupiter, the miſchiefes and miſeries that are like to iuſue, if Folly be appointed companion to Loue. Wherfore I, in the perſon of all the gods, beſeech your Maieſtie to graunt that Loue may not bee ioined with her, and that Folly may grieuouſly be puniſhed for the outrage ſhe hath done to Cupid.
                  
               
               As ſoone as Apollo had ended his Oration, Mercurie in the defence of Folly began to ſpeake in this wiſe.
               
                  Mercurie.
                  VVHeras (right worthy Iupiter) Apollo hath with his painted eloquence ſet out the praiſes of loue. and hath ſought with his filed phraſes to diſcredit Folly, I hope when your Maieſty ſhall throughly heare the cauſe decided, you wil commend his eloquence more than his reaſons. For it is not vnknowen vnto you and all the gods, that Folly is no whit inferior vnto Loue, and that loue ſhould be of no force without her, neither coulde his Kingdome indure without her helpe, ayde, and counſaile. I pray you cal to remembrance how Folly incōtinently after man was placed in Paradiſe, began moſt imperiouſly to rule, and hath euer ſince continued in ſuch credite, as neuer any goddeſſe had the like; raigning and ruling amongeſt men, from time to time, from age to age, as the only princeſſe of the world: Inſomuch that who haue béen

more honoured than fooles? Who was more ſubiect vnto follie than Alexander the great: which féeling himſelfe to ſuffer hunger and thi
                        •
                     ſt, to be ſubiect to ſorrowe and ſickneſſe, not able to kéepe himſelfe from drunkenneſſe, yet would be honoured for a God.
                  What kinde of people hath béene in greater credit than Philoſophers, and who more fooles? Did not Ariſtotle moſt fooliſhly did for ſorrow, becauſe he know not the ebbing and flowing of the ſea? Did not Crates in caſting his treaſure into the Sea, commit a wiſe déede? What follie ſhewed Emped
                           •
                        cles, by his ſtrange coniectures? What ſay you to Diogenes tunne, and to Ariſtippus flatterie? Whoſo throughly conſidereth their opinions, ſhall finde them ſubiect to the ſtate of follie. How manie other ſciences are there in the worlde, which are altogether fooliſh? and yet the profeſſours of them had in high reputation amongeſt men. They which are Calculators of Natiuities, makers of Characters, caſters of figures, are they not fryers of this fraternitie. Is it not follie to be ſo curious, as to meaſure the heauen, the height of the ſtarres, the breadth of the earth, and the depth of the ſea? and yet yt profeſſors héereof are highly eſtéemed, and onely by the means of follie. Nay, how could the world continue, if the dangers, troubles, calamities, and diſcommodities of marriage were not couered by folly? Who would haue coaſted the ſeas if follie had not béen his guide? To commit himſelf to the mercy of the winde and the waues, to liue in danger of fearefull ſurges, and perilous rockes, to traffique with ſauage and barbarous people, onely incenſed by the meanes of Follie. And yet notwithſtanding, by this meanes the Common-wealth is maintayned, knowledge and learning augmented, the properties of hearbes, ſtones, Birdes, and beaſtes, perfectly ſearched out. What folly is it moſt daungerouſly to paſſe into the howels of the earth to digge for yron, and ſéeke for gold? How many artes and occupations ſhould bee driuen out of the

worlde if Follie were baniſhed? Truly the moſt part of men ſhould either beg for want, or die for hunger? How ſhould ſo many Aduocates, Procurators, Sergeants, Atturneis, Scriueners, Imbroderers, Painters, and Perfumers liue, if Ladie Follie were vtterly exiled? Hath not follie inuented a thouſād deuices to draw a man from idleneſſe, as Tragedies, Comedies Dancing ſchooles, fencing houſes, wraſtling places, &amp; a thouſand other fooliſh ſports?
                  Hath ſhe not made men hardie and venturous to fight with Lions, Bores, and Buls, onely to gaine honour and to paſſe other in follie? What did Antonie and Cleopatra when they ſtraue who ſhould ſpend moſt in beaſtly banquetting? What cauſed Caeſar lament that he had not begun to trouble the world in that age, wherein Alexander had conquered the greateſt part? Why did diuerſe ſéeke to fill vp the valleyes, to make plaine the mountaines, to dry vp Riuers, to make Bridges ouer the Sea, as Claudius the Emperour did? What made Rodope builde the Pyramides, and Artemiſia frame the ſumptuous ſepulchre, but Follie. In fine, without this Goddeſſe, man ſhoulde bee carefull, heauie, and whollie drowned in ſorrow: whereas Follie quickeneth his ſpirits, maketh him ſing, daunce, leape, and frame himſelfe altogether to pleaſure. It is not poſſible that loue ſhould bee without the daughter of youth, which is Follie. For Loue ſpringeth of ſedaine and ſundrie cauſes, by receiuing an apple, as Cidippe: by looking out at a windowe, as Scilla: by reading in a Booke, as the Ladie Francis Rimhi: ſome fall in loue by ſight, ſome by hearing, but all liuing in hope to obtaine their deſires. And yet ſome haue loued without anie naturall cauſe, as Pigmalion, who fell in loue with his Marble picture: and I pray you what Sympathie could there be betwéene a liuely youth and a dead ſtone? what was it then but follie that kindled this flame? What forced Narciſſus to fall in loue with his owne ſhaddowe, but Follie? Yea, what aduenture is paſſed in loue without Follie?

For the Philoſophers define Follie to be a depriuation of wiſedome, and wiſedome is altogether without paſſions: of the which when loue ſhall be voide, then no doubt, the Sea ſhall be without waues, and the fire without heats.
                  Conſider but a young man which onely placeth his delight in amorous conceites, decking, dreſſing, and perfuming himſelfe moſt delicately, who paſſeth out of his lodging fraught with a thouſand ſundrie fancies, accompanied with men and Pages, paſſing to the place where hee may haue a ſight of his Miſtreſſe, obtaining for his trauell no gaine but perhaps ſome amorous glance, making long ſutes, ſpending his time and his treaſure, conſuming his wit, and waſting his wealth, and yet reaping nothing but diſdaine and diſcredite. But if it chance that his Miſtreſſe condeſcend vnto his requeſts, ſhe appointeth him to come at ſome ſuſpicious houre, which he cannot performe without great perill. To come with company, were to bewraie his ſecrets: to go alone, moſt daungerous: to goe openly, too manifeſt: ſo that he muſt paſſe diſguiſed, ſometime like a woman, other times like a peaſant or ſome vile perſon, ſcaling the walles with ladders, climbing vp to the windowes by cordes: yea, continually in daunger of death, if Follie did not hold him vp by the hand. It is not alſo vnknowne vnto you how many ſundrie paſſions do perplexe the poore paſſionate Louers, all which procéed of Follie: as to haue ones heart ſeparated from himſelfe, to be now in peace and then in warre, now couering his dolour, bluſhing one while, and looking pale another, fraught whollie with feare, hope, &amp; ſhame, ſeeking that carefully which hée ſéemeth to flie, and yet doubtfully dreading not to finde it, to laugh ſildome, to ſigh often, to burne in colde, and freeze in heate, to be croſſed altogether with contraries, which be ſignes not onely of follie, but of phrenſie. Who ſhall excuſe Hercules, handling ſo carefully the diſtaſte of Omphale, or Salomon for combring himſelfe with ſo many Concubines, Anniball in ſubmitting himſelfe to his Loue,

                     Ariſtotle in obeying Hermia, and Socrates in yéelding to Aſpaſia, and many other which we ſée daily to bee ſo blinded, as they know not themſelues: and what is the cauſe hereof, but follie? ſo that we ſee that it is ſhe which maketh Loue to be ſo feared and redoubted, it is ſhe that honoureth him, exalteth his name, and cauſeth him to be counted as a God. Further, whoſoeuer loueth, muſt apply himſelfe to the affection of his miſtreſſe, although it be contrarie to his naturall conſtitution: if he be quiet, wiſe, and diſcréete, yet if his louer pleaſe to haue him chaunge his ſtate, he muſt turne his ſtearne, and hoiſe his ſaile, to goe with another winde. Zethius and Amphion could not agrée, for becauſe the delight of the one was a deſpight to the other, vntill Amphion left his Muſicke. If the Ladie whom thou loueſt be couetous, thou muſt chaunge thy ſelfe into golde, and ſo fall into her boſome: if ſhe be merrie, thou muſt bée pleaſant: if ſullen, thou muſt be ſad. All the ſeruants and ſutors to Atlanta were hunters, becauſe ſhe delighted in that ſport. Many Gentlewomen to pleaſe their louers which were Poets, left the rocke and the néedle, and tooke in hand pennes &amp; books: now tell mee if theſe ſtraunge Metamorphoſes be not méere points of follie? Doe you thinke that a Souldier which goeth to the aſſault, marketh the trenches, thinketh of his enemies, or of a thouſand harguebuſhes, wherof euerie one is ſufficient to deſtroy him? No, he onely hopeth to win the conqueſt, and doth not ſo much as once imagine the reſt. He which firſt inuented ſayling, doubted not of the perillous daungers: and hee that playeth, neuer thinketh to become a looſer, yet are they all thrée in daunger to be ſlaine, drowned, and vndone. But what then? they neither do ſee, nor will ſée what is hurtfull vnto them. So we muſt coniecture the like of louers: for if they did ſée the dreadfull dangers, and the fearefull perits wherein they are, how they be deceiued and beguiled, they would neuer honour loue as God, but deteſt him as a Diuell, and ſo ſhould the kingdom of loue be deſtroyed, which

now is gouerned by ignorance, careleſneſſe, hope &amp; blindeneſſe, which are all the handmaids of Folly. Remaine in peace then fond Loue, and ſéeke not to break the auncient league which is betwéen thée and Folly. For if then doeſt, thy bowe ſhal be broken, thy darts ſhal be of no force, Contemptęque iacent &amp; ſine luce faces.
                  
               
               ¶ When Mercury had finiſhed the defence of Follie, Iupiter ſeeing the gods to be diuerſly affected, that ſome held with Cupid, and ſome with Folly, to decide the doubt he pronounced this ſentence:
               
                  FOr the difficulty and importance of this difference and diuerſitie of opinions, we haue remitted the deciding of it vntill thrée times ſeuen times and nine ages be paſt: in the meane while wee ſtraightly commaund you to liue friendly together, without offering iniury one vnto another. And Folly ſhall guide and conduct blinde Loue whither ſhée ſéemeth beſt: and for the reſtoring of his eyes, after we haue ſpoken with the Deſtinies, it ſhall be decréede.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            AT LONDON, Printed for Mathew Lownes. 1608
            
            
         
      
   

