
   
      
         
            Greenes Orpharion VVherin is discouered a musicall concorde of pleasant histories, many sweet moodes graced vvith such harmonius discords, as agreeing in a delightfull closse, they sound both pleasure and profit to the eare. Heerein also as in a diateheron, the branches of vertue, ascending and descending by degrees: are covnited in the glorious praise of women-kind. VVith diuers tragicall and comicall histories presented by Orpheus and Arion, beeing as full of profit as of pleasure. Robertus Greene, in Artibus Magister.
            Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
         
         
            
               1599
            
         
         Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02120
            STC 12260
            ESTC S103410
            99839164
            99839164
            3564
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02120)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3564)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 298:07)
         
         
            
               
                  Greenes Orpharion VVherin is discouered a musicall concorde of pleasant histories, many sweet moodes graced vvith such harmonius discords, as agreeing in a delightfull closse, they sound both pleasure and profit to the eare. Heerein also as in a diateheron, the branches of vertue, ascending and descending by degrees: are covnited in the glorious praise of women-kind. VVith diuers tragicall and comicall histories presented by Orpheus and Arion, beeing as full of profit as of pleasure. Robertus Greene, in Artibus Magister.
                  Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.
               
               [6], 58 p.   
               
                  Printed [by J. Roberts] for Edward VVhite, dwelling at the little north doore of S. Paules Church: at the signe of the Gun,
                  At London :
                  1599.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2002-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-07
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2002-10
            AptaraRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2002-11
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2002-11
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               Greenes Orpharion.
Wherin is discouered
a musicall concorde of pleasant
Histories, many sweet moodes graced vvith
such harmonius discords, as agreeing in a delightfull
closse, they sound both pleasure and profit
to the eare. Heerein also as in a Diateheron, the branches
of Vertue, ascending and descending by degrees: are covnited in
the glorious praise of women-kind. VVith diuers Tragicall and Comicall Histories
presented by Orpheus and Arion, beeing as full of
profit as of pleasure.
            Omne tulit punctum, qui miscuit vtile dulci.
            
               Robertus Greene, in Artibus Magister.
            AT LONDON,
Printed for Edward VVhite, dwelling at the
little North doore of S. Paules Church: at the
signe of the Gun. 1599.
         
         
            
            
            To the Right Worshipfull Maister
Robert Carey Esquire, Robert Greene
vvisheth encrease of all honorable
vertues.
            
               ENnius (Right Worshipful) had
a Maecenas, though his verses
were rude, &amp; Hippocrates durst
present his pictures though they
were rough. The blindest Bayard
hath a reason to shadow his
presumption: for sayth hee, will
is aboue skill. Soothing my selfe
(right Worshipfull) with their
humours, hauing attempted to
frame out an ORPHARION, to harsh to make a
concord in any cunning eare: yet with old Ennius doating
in my youth as he did in his age: I doe presume to present
my rurall Instrument vnder the shadow of your patronage,
and the rather for that as the poore Cobler durst prefer his
chattring Pye to Augustus, for that the Emperour was affable

and curteous, so hearing your Worship to be indued
with such honourable vertues and plausible qualities, as
drawes men to admire and loue such vnited perfection: I
embolden my selfe to trust vpon your Worships curteous
acceptance, which if it be such as others haue founde and I
hoped for, &amp; that any way this Orpharion may agree with
the daintines of your touch and fingering, the end of my labours
and the summe of my desires consort in one
sympathie, and in that hope, I commit
your Worship to the
Almightie.
            
               Your VVorships humbly to commaund, Ro. Greene.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the Gentlemen Readers
Health.
            
               GEntlemen, I haue long promised
my Orpharion, and because
I would not frustrate your expectation:
at last it is leapt into
the Stacioners Shoppe, but not
from my Study, for then might
you thinke I had sweld with the
mountaines, and brought foorth
a Mouce, but the Printer had it
long since▪ marry whether his
presse were out of tune, Paper deere, or some other secret
delay driue it off, it hath line this twelue months in the suds.
Now at last it is crept forth in the Spring, a slender bud and
easily to be nipt with the least frost of Disdaine.
            Therfore doo I entreate whatsoeuer melody my Orpharion
yeeld: you would fauour the blossome with the Sunshine
of your curteous acceptance, else shall you discourage
a Gardener for grafting any more, and therefore
hoping to finde you as euer I haue
done, farwell.
            
               Rob. Greene.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Greenes Orpharion.
            
               
                  CVpid hauing taught me what
restlesse passions are in loue,
what continual perturbations
Fancy affoordes to such as account
beauty the principal end
of their affects: hauing receaued
the wound, I sought where
to find a salue fit for the easing
of my malady: Experience
willing that I should not tye
my thoughts on delay, told me that such as were enuenomed
with the Scorpion, must be healed by the Scorpion,
that the Tarantals sting could not be pulde out without
Musick, that he which was pierced with Achilles Launce
must be healed by his Speare, and they which were charmed
with Loue, must seeke to loue, or els lacke remedy:
Wherupon doubtfull what I should doo, I was willed to
sue to Venus as soueraigne Goddesse and patronesse of
such perplexed patients. I left my home and sayled to
Cipres, there found I men vnknowne, but not her whom
I lookt for: there might I sée Venus Pallace like the gorgious
Tower built by Semeramus. Sloth being Porter,
sléepy, and suffering frée passage to all, the gate of entrance
was not the way to returne: for at the other side was a
doore to depart, where Beggery stoode and threatned all,
but strooke some with his whip of repentance: within I
found Princes, great Lords and men of meane calling, al
prisoners, some fettered by the eyes, others by the eares,
some by the tong, as hauing more lust in their mouth then
loue in their mindes, none or fewe cheyned by the harts,
and such as were set inthroned in a secret Cell: those Venus
shrinde vp as wonders of the worlde, well: missing
what I came for, I past spéedily from thence to Paphos,
where Venus had onely a Temple, thither came multitudes
on Pilgrimage, making vowes, vttering oathes,

and protesting promises: if they might enioy the fruition
of their Ladyes, to be sworne votaries to the Goddesse:
Some were fauoured, others disgraced: some dispaired,
some hoped, but all found the ende of theyr pilgrimage
was to buy smoake with many perrills and daungers:
But all these instances were no arguments to diswade
me from my iourney: But as Medea though I saw the
best and allowed of it, yet I followed the néerest &amp; smarted
for it, for such as be in loue are like the Déere which
one while strike at the Tamarisk trée with their hornes,
and then gréedily burst on it with their mouthes, others
the people of Mamaca, that surfet on Dates, and yet dye
with them in their mawes. Louers exclaime agaynst
Cupid, and yet they goe on pylgrimage to Paphos, they
call Venus vniust, and yet offer her incense and sacrifice,
they fore-sée misery, and yet run headlong on their owne
misfortune. So fared it with mee, for seeing these men
thus deepely passionate, and yet so slenderly rewarded, as
who carried away the greatest trophe, had his ensigne
stamped with repentance: yet their mishaps could not
make me learne to beware, but from Paphos I went to
the fountaine of Alcidalion, where I heard Venus to auoyde
the heate of Sommer, was kept close Prisoner by
Mars in a Pauillion, but I found the rumour false, yet
did I not repent mee of my arriuall, for there I sawe sitting
about the bancks, infinite troupes of faire and beautifull
Ladyes, all votaries vnto Venus, smyling at the
fondnesse of men, and laughing at the passions of theyr
Louers, making true loue knots of rushes, that broke ere
they could be twisted: some séemed lyke Saintes, those
were subtill and peruerse: others fawned, and those were
flatterers: some wept, and they let fall teares of deceite:
some séemde to haue many eyes, and those had many fancies:
some two harts, and yet they were very chast: for
some had twenty measuring their Loues by their lookes:
gazing still vpon their countenance and gesture, I perceiued

hard by seperate from the rest a fewe Ladyes sitting
passing solitarie, their names were ingrauen in the trées,
but so long since as hardly I could read them, yet I found
out Hero, Penelope, Thisbe, Artemesia, alas a small number
and disdained by the rest, these had their eyes shut against
beauty, and their eares open to vertue, their harts
subiect to loue, but onely stamped with one Carracter, resembling
the Emeraulde, that neuer looseth the first impression
nor admitteth any other: well here I could neyther
finde Venus, nor heare of her, but scoffinglie those
girles told me, she was either in Ida or in Erecinus, desirous
to loose no time, I hasted from Alcydalion to Ida,
where I could see no steps of a Goddesse, but only the ancient
monument of Troy cōsumed to cinders, there I noted
the end of loue, the reward of lust, the trophes of Venus,
the follies of women in Helena, that brought Priamus
his sonnes, and so famous a Cittie to confusion. From
thence I posted to Erecinus, the Mountaine was greene
and pleasant to the eye, the stones that appeared higher
then the grasse séemed like Iacinthes, the mosse was flowers,
the very rubbish below pearles, so ye nature seemd
to haue conquered art, and art nature, and a supernaturall
glory both in musing at the gorgeous scituation of
this deuine Mount, looking if eyther there were Palace
or Temple dedicate to Venus, I sawe none, but casting
mine eye into the bordring vale, I saw a Shepheard grasing
of his flockes. Desirous to learne of the man any
newes of the Goddesse, pacing downe from the Hyll, I
went and saluted him in this manner.
            Shepheard, so I name thee for thy flockes, more maist
thou be, for Apollo kept Midas sheepe, and Mercury taken
the shape of a Heardman: but measuring thy degrée
as present thou seemest, I craue so much fauour at thy
hands, as to tell mee whether Venus is resident about
this mount of Erecinus, or no, I haue beene at all her places
of abode, and this is the last of all her earthly mansions:

This Shephearde hearing me salute him so curteouslie,
laying downe his pipe and his hooke aunswered
thus bluntly.
            Friend, what I am it little reckes thée, thou seest my
fouldes, and then why standest thou vpon higher titles:
In calling me shepheard or Swaine, thou giuest me my
due, if my degrée be greater, my sheepe may serue for thy
excuse, to thy question: as it sauours of folly, so I thinke
best to aunswer it with silence, yet for I see thy thoughts
to be full of passions, and thy face the map of sorrowes, the
two notes of a Louer, if I knew my counsaile might profite
thee, or my experience warne thee, I would bestow a
little wast time while my Sheepe grase so hard, to holde
thee chat.
            Hearing the Shepheard beginning so roughly, to conclude
so gently, willing to be auditor to his Country precepts,
I aunswered him thus.
            Shepheard, if thou be no better, (for thy talke makes
me suspect higher, Know that I haue tolde many cares,
numbred many passions, felt many sorrowes, vttred many
sighes, shed many teares since Venus entertained me,
with Roses at the first, &amp; afterwarde beate me with Nettles,
I haue found loue to be a Laborinth, a fury, a hell,
wherein men aliue féele worse paines then those ghostes
that pay Charon hier for his ferriboat: gréeued thus, yet
as one in a lunacie: I neuer fore-sawe my miseries. I
heard many counsailes, and read many preceps, but al in
vaine, yet for that time hath many chaunces, the Fates
their Canons tied to opportunitie. Fortune her decrées
variable, and loue, many accidents: I will humbly craue
what thou hast offered, promising to be attentiue and not
ingratefull, as farre as a strangers abilitie may gratifie.
            The Shephearde without further promising or longer
delay, began thus.
            Thou seest that I sitte heere féeding my flocks by Erecinus,
               
whether daily resorte multitudes of amorous Pilgrims
suing to Venus for releefe of their passions, but
how she vsed these fond and perplexed patients, as it pitties
mee to rehearse, so it wil grieue thee to heare. Those
youthes whose yeeres more then their mindes, are fryed
with a small flame of ordinarie fancie, rather inserted by
nature then inferred by loue, such she entertaineth most
sumptuously, as fittest obiects for her to worke vpon, putting
oyle in the flame, fire to flax, and beautie as the balefull
obiect to youth, for she knowing the olde verse to bee
too true for her to disproue, Quod latit ignotum est: ignoti
nulla Cupido, that, what is secret from vs we neuer desire
to inueagle them with her charmes, she present beutie
excellent by nature, yet far more gorgious by arte:
faire faces, smiling lookes, alluring gestures swéet spéeches,
these are the baites that she layes to intrap, &amp; youth
is so fond that he cannot but taste, resembling the poore
Mouse, that feedeth soonest on the most infectious Rosalger,
respecting the colour, not the confection, after once
shée hath gotten youth limed fast on her twigges, then
Cupid vseth them as marks, and at euery shoote galleth
to the quicke, that the woundes cannot be cured, till eyther
we finde remedie by repentance, which oft cōmeth
too late, or haue a quittance by death, which they thinke
commeth too soone. Others, that haue beene stale stayers
in her Court, spending their time in sighes, teares,
and many dispayring passions, such shée feedeth on with
delayes, giuing thē one day an incarnatiue to heale, and
the next day a contrary medicine to fester, choking theyr
sences with perfumes, and straight stifling them with
Hemlock, suffering theyr Ladies in the morning to wash
their temples with Rose-water, and at night to quaffe to
them gall and vinegar, shadowing smiles with frownes,
sower lookes with wanton actions, fettering them with
the wings of hope, but hanging dispaire at their heeles,
least soaring too hie, they should seaze &amp; catch their pray:

suppose she sets thē on the top of her whéele, where, poore
man I know thou desirest to be plaste, and for their long
trauell, she giues them with Ixion a clowde, a faire dame
I mean, as shee bestowed vpon Paris, yet shalt thou finde,
that she fetcheth all her virgins from the fountain of Alcydalion,
(beleeue me Pilgrim I will not warrant theyr
maidenheads) because thou seest they haue many eyes,
and many harts, which haue many fancies, and many
lures, and trust me Pilgrime, many causes must needes
bring out some effects: But leauing these doubts as may
not once haue entrance into Louers thoughts, and affirming
that all are virgins that come from Venus, for
Diana hath so few in her traine, that she marries not one
in seauen yéeres, whē the louer hath what he long sought
for, he findes not the fairest Christall but hath his staine,
the brightest topar but hath his spot, the richest Gold, but
hath his ore, and the purest creature feminine I meane:
but hath her common imperfection, either proud without
profite, and thats a purgation for the Purse, or fayre
without wit, and that is to marry a woodden picture
with a golden creast, full of fauour but flattering, and
so he may reape many kisses and little loue, shrewish, deceitfull,
wilfull, fond, new fangle, and what not: nay,
perhaps proue so light in the braines, that she make him
swell in the browes, that as he hath beene in his youth a
votary to Venus, so in his age he may proue a companion
to Vulcan, and Pilgrim quoth the Shepheard, this is to
sitte on the toppe of Venus wheele, these bitter sauces be
her cheefest delicates, and these painted Sepulchers her
richest trophies. Thou seest I sit neere Erecinus, and therfore
speake by experience, thou saiest to Venus thou art in
loue, thou wouldest faine haue a wife frō 
               Alcidalion, looke
before thou leape, pry into Venus Cofers, and sée what
chaffer she prouides for her chapmen, I haue counsayled,
now rests it in thee either to followe it with a momentary
sorrowing content, or to forsake it with a perpetuall

pleasing mislike.
            Hearing the cunning experienced swaine to discourse
so roundly of the matter, I imagined either he had beene
in loue, or an enemie to Venus, so that I demaunded of
him if he would not haue men loue at all?
            Yes quoth he, so they count Dianas virgins not Venus
wantons: I replied she had very few or none, hee aunswered,
had shée more suters, shee woulde prouide more
maydes, but Venus spying them passe towards her Pallace,
layeth such snares to intangle, such traps to intice,
such charmes to bewitch, such dangers to preiudice, that
none or very few ariue at Dianas mantion, and such as
doo: come thither halfe maimed.
            Then quoth I, you conclude peremptorily against Venus
and her crue, and very hardly against women. Hearing
me say so, he tooke me by the hande, &amp; softly whispering
in mine eare, Pilgrim I may say to thée, Wiues be
they neuer so watcht they will: Maides be they neuer so
bashfull they wish, and widdowes bee they neuer so coy,
they would, take me not generally Pilgrime quoth hée,
and with that sitting downe he tooke his pipe in his hand,
and plaid so sweetly, that like Argus at Mercuries melodie
I fell on sleepe.
            No sooner had Morpheus shut mine eyes, but I fell into
a dreame, mee thought I was ledde from Erecinus by
Mercury, alongst the galupin or siluer paued way of heauen
to the hie built house of Ioue, there woulde I haue
gazde at the gorgious buildings, but my guide was in
haste, and conducted me into the great Hall, wher Iupiter
and the rest of the Gods were at a banquet, no sooner was
I entred amongst them, but Mercury sprinkled me with
water, which made me capaple of their diuine presence,
so yt I sat stil looking on their persons, and listning to their
parle, at last me thought blunt Vulcan that sat at ye lower
end of the boord, although Venus aboue, sat opposite to
Mars, beganne thus roughly to breake silence: I cannot

mighty Gods but smile to thinke that when my wife and
her blind Sonne, the one with her boxe of beauties, the other
with his quiuer of Arrowes, passe abroade to shewe
their Deities: what number of poore perplexed men as
Patients come to haue cure of their hurts, some in their
eyes, that haue gazed with the Phylosopher agaynst too
bright a Sunne, and such are blind; some that with Vlisses
haue not stopped their eares, but haue listened the Syrens,
and they complaine of their hearing: some in their
harts, and those bewraies their passions by their grones:
none comes without gréefe, nor returne throughly cured,
so that I suppose either the wounds are very perilous, or
my wife a bad Surgion. Truth (quoth Iupiter) but what
number of women come hether: Multitudes (quoth Vulcan)
Apollo smoothly and yet with a smile, demaunded
if they were as bad to cure as men: No (quoth Vulcan)
for be the wound neuer so déepe, tis perfectly cured in
twelue houres, eyther my wife is more friendly to Women,
or their sores more easie to salue. No (quoth Mercury)
it is because their loues are like a mans breath against
bright stéele, which scarse lighteth on before it
leapeth off, or like wood wet in Allom water, which lieth
in the fire and waxeth hot, but neuer burneth: their harts
resemble a Pumice stone, light: &amp; which way soeuer you
turne it: full of starting holes, that if fancy steale in at the
one, he can step out at the other: or els quoth Iupiter, their
harts haue no holes at all, but as firme as flint, that neither
fancy nor loue can enter, for Venus teacheth them
extremities, eyther to fawne &amp; be too fond, or to be too coy
and too stubborne, which causeth so many to put vp inuertiues
against her. Least of all (quoth the Goddesse,) in a
great chafe hath Iupiter cause to accuse women of cruelty,
if not, I appeale to Iuno, at this all the company smiled
and Ioue was silent, well (quoth Apollo,) leauing these
quips seeing we haue met to be merry, if it please you to
allow of my motion, to make vs some musicke, I will

raise vp the Ghosts of Orpheus and Arion, two, famous
in their times for their instruments, and greatly experienced
in Loue, as béeing great trauailers, and with that
conuersing the greatest Potentates in the world, who
often are as full of loues as they are of dignities: these
shall please vs with harmony, and discourse either what
they thinke, or what they haue heard of womens Loues:
To this all the Gods gladly agréede, and Mercury was
sent in Post to Pluto for these two Musitians, scarse had
I thought Mercury had béene out of the Hall, before I
saw enter with this winged God the Ghosts of Orpheus
and Arion, so liuely to the eye, and so well trussed in their
apparell as they séemed perfectly such as they were when
they liued vpon earth: Orpheus after that he had doone
due reuerence to the Gods, especially to Apollo: tuning
his instrument without any more commaund, as if his
seruice should be saluery, hée daintily toucht the Cordes
with a sweete stroake, and to a melodious tune, sung this
Ditty.
            
               Orpheus Song.
               
                  HE that did sing the motions of the starres,
                  Pale colour'd Phaebus borrowing of her light:
                  Aspects of planets oft oppos'd in iarres,
                  Of Hesper Henchmen to the day and night.
                  Sings now of Loue as taugh by proofe to sing:
                  Women are false and loue a bitter thing.
               
               
                  I lou'd Euridicae the brightest Lasse,
                  More fond to like so faire a Nymph as she:
                  In Thefaly, so bright none euer was,
                  But faire and constant hardly may agree.
                  False harted wife to him that loued thee well:
                  To leaue thy loue and choose the Prince of hell.
               
               
                  
                  Theseus did helpe, and I in hast did hie,
                  To Pluto, for the Lasse I loued so:
                  The God made graunt, and who so glad as I,
                  I tunde my Harpe, and shee and I gan goe▪
                  
                  Glad that my loue was left to me alone.
                  I looked back, Euridicae was gone.
               
               
                  She slipt aside backe to her latest loue,
                  Vnkinde shee wrong'd her first and truest Feere,
                  Thus womens loues, delights as tryall proues,
                  By false Eurydycae I loued so deere.
                  To change, and fleete, and euery way to shrinke,
                  To take in loue, and lose it with a winke.
               
            
            SCarse had Orpheus ended his song, but Iupiter thinking
not to let so faire a ball fall to the grounde: tooke
opportunitie thus by the hand.
            This present Dittie of Orpheus tendeth to our forepassed
discourse, as though the Fates had forepointed our
talke, and this arriuall consequence of their infallible decrees:
sith then the vnkindnes of Euridicae discouers the
inconstancie of women, &amp; that Orpheus hath by his sundry
passions made an Anatomy of loue: let vs heare hys
opinion howe hee censures of beautie. Apollo at Iupiters
motion commaunded Orpheus, who not amased (as a
Ghost come from hell) began thus. The Question right
mighty Gods is easie, for that commonly all gaze at
beauty as at the fairest obiect that flattereth the eye, yet
a thing perilous, howsoeuer it seemes precious: seeing
the fairest Lawnes soonest take the déepest staines, the
brightest Beralles the greatest flawes, and oftentimes
the fairest faces with intollerable faults: Greece vaunted
not so much of her beautifull paragon, as Troy lamented
of their incestuous strumpet, men came to Rome to sée
Messalines beauty, but Rome sorrowed that shee was
counted a Harlot: Thessaly rung of Euridites proportion,

but Thessaly shamed and Orpheus grieued at her bad condition,
and yet forsooth though we find beauty thus preiudiciall,
yet we must leape at it, though to our vtter ruine
we light in the ditch: But as the fish Ramera listning to
the sound of the trumpet, is caught of the Fishers: as the
Porcupine standeth staring at the glimmering of the
Starres, and is ouertaken with dogges: as the Leopard
looking at the Panthers painted skinne, is caught as a
pray: so he which taketh too much delight to gaze vppon
beautie, is oft times galled with greefe and misery: yea,
his pleasure shall inferre such profite, and his good will
such gaines, as if hee reapt the beautifull Apples of Tantalus,
which are no sooner toucht, but they turne to ashes.
            Beautie no sooner flourisheth but it fadeth, and it is not
fully ripe, but it beginneth to rotte: it no sooner blossommeth,
but it withereth: and scarcely being toucht, it stayneth
like the Guiacum leafe, that hath the one halpe parched
before the other halfe be perfect, to the Birde Acauthis,
which hatched white, yet turneth blacke at the first
storme: Or like to the stone Astites, that changeth coulour
with the onely breath of a man: this (right mightie
Gods) is my censure of beautie, that vnlesse ioyned with
vertue, it is like the feathers of the Phenix, placed in the
carkasse of a Crow, but where faith and feature are Relatiues,
that beauty I call diuine and metaphisica, for because
gratior est pulchro veniens è corpore virtus. Thys
discourse of Orpheus all the Gods applauded except Venus,
Iuno brookt it as hauing lost the Ball, and Venus
thought it was best to pocket vp whatsoeuer a Ghost out
of hell did tattle, and so I would haue all faire Gentlewomen
to take it: well, so well did the Gods like and allow
of his talke, that Iupiter questioned him what hee thought
generally of women: Orpheus neither forcing Iuno nor
Venus, as one that could but goe to hell, boldly made answer,
that their generall sex stood vpon two extreames, either
too curteous or too cruell, and that he had made expeence

of both, and which quoth Iupiter are the worst? I
note (quoth Orpheus) if your question tendes towardes
men, because my particuler instance may be no generall
Example, but this well I wot, crueltie hath the greatest
punishment appointed for it in hell, which may it please
you and the rest of the Gods to be attentiue, I will proue
with a knowne history. The Gods setling themselues in
their seates, shewed by their silence how they lik'd of his
motion, whereupon Orpheus began thus.
            
               Orpheus Tale.
               SInce the mad frowes of Bacchus (in that I was sworn
an enemy to women through the vnkindnes of Euridicae,)
stoned me to death while I sate playing musicke to
the Rockes, which seemed to mooue at my melody: my
soule sent to Pluto, I founde fauour at his handes for that
he wronged me of my wife, that I had frée liberty to passe
into euery seuerall mancion: wherupon one day with my
Harpe I walked through seuerall places, and heard seuerall
complaints, but at the last I came to a thicke fogge,
the smoake and stench so deadly and pestilent, as all the
ghosts in hell, respecting this dungeon, seemed to liue in
Elisium, out of this mist I heard the voice of a woman, vttering
pittifull shrikes, hauing remorse of her passions, I
toucht my Harpe, and plaid, thinking while my musicke
lasted, to make her forget her torments, as I had done the
other ghosts in hell, but she told me all was in vaine, sith
as her faulte exceeded all, so her torture was more then
they all: for here quoth she I hang by the haire of ye heade
in so thicke a smoake and stinking a fog, as no tongue can
expresse, nor imagination conceiue it. Desirous to heare
the cause of this strange extreame, I askt her name, and
the offence, shee wisht mee 
                     •
                  alfe angerly to cease my fidling,
and she would discourse at large: I put vp my pipes

at such a dry blowe, and shee murmured out of the fogge
thus.
               I am Lidia that renowned Princesse, whose neuer
matched beauty seemed like the gorgious pompe of Phoebus,
too bright for the day: rung so strongly out of the
trumpe of Fame, as it filled euery eare with wonder:
Daughter to Astolpho, the King of Lydia: who thought
himselfe not so fortunate for his Diadem, sith other Kings
could boast of Crownes: nor for his great possessions, although
indued with large territories, as happy that hee
had a Daughter whose excellencie in fauour stained Venus,
whose austere chastitie set Diana to silence with a
blush: Know whatsoeuer thou art that standest attentiue
to my tale, that ye ruddiest Rose in all Damasco, the whitest
Lillies in the créeks of Danuby, might not if they had
vnited their natiue colours, but haue bashed at the vermilion
staine, flourisht vppon the pure Christall of my face:
the Marguerites of the westerne Indies counted more
bright and rich, then that which Cleopatra quaft to Anthonie,
the Corall highest in his pride vppon the Affricke
shoares, might well be graced to resemble my teeth and
lippes, but neuer honoured to ouerreach my purenes. Remaining
thus the mirrour of the Worlde, and natures
strangest miracle: there arriued in our Court a Thracian
Knight, of personage tall, proportioned in most exquisite
forme, his face but too faire for his qualities, for hee was
a braue and resolute Souldiour. This Caualier comming
amongst diuers others to sée the roiallie of the state
of Lidia, no sooner had a glaunce of my beautie, but he set
downe his staffe, resoluing either to perrish in so sweet a
Laborinth, or in time happily to stumble out with Theseus.
He had not staide long in my Fathers Court, but hee
shewed such Knightly deeds of chiualrie amongst the nobilitie,
lightned with the extraordinary sparkes of a couragious
minde, that not onely hee was liked and loued of
all the chéefe Péeres of the Realmes, but the report of his

valoure comming to my Fathers eares, hee was highly
honored of him, &amp; placed in short time as Generall of his
warlike forces by Land: resting in this estimation with
the King, preferment was no meanes to quiet his minde,
for loue had wounded so deepe, as honour by no meanes
might remedy, that as the Elephants can hardly bee haled
from the sight of the Wast, or the Roe buck from gazing
at red cloth, so there was no obiect that could so much
allure the wauering eyes of this Thracian called Acestes,
as the surpassing beautie of the Princesse Lydia, yea, so
déepely he doted, that as the Camelion gorgeth herselfe
with gazing into the ayre, so he fedde his fancie with staring
on the heauenly face of his Goddesse, so long dallying
in the flame, that he scorcht his wings, &amp; in time consumed
his whole body. Beeing thus passionate, hauing
none so familiar as he durst make, hee fell thus to debate
with himselfe.
               Is it Alcestes loue that troubles thee? why thou art a
Souldiour, sworne to armes, not to Armour: to incounter
foes in the féelde, not to courte Ladies in the Chamber:
Hercules had almost performed his twelue labours, ere
he durst find leysure to loue, and thou art scarse acquainted
with Mars, but thou seekest to be priuate friend to Venus:
away fond foole, to thy Speare and Shielde, manage
thy horse, though héere in a peaceable Countrey: let not
Bées hiue in thy Helmet, rust inblaze the figure of sloath
on thy Armour, or loue call thee her milksoppe, by whom
warre it selfe hath approoued martiall: hast thou forgotte
that which thou suckest out of thy Nurses teate, that to
loue is to loose, and fancie bee it neuer so charie, is meere
folly: for loue how soeuer it bee, is but a Chaos of cares:
and fancie though neuer so fortunate, hath her crosses: for
if thou inioy the beauty of Venus, thou shalt finde it small
vantage: if thou get one as nice as Minerua, thou mayst
put thy winnings in thine eye: if as gorgious as Iuno,
thy account being cast, thy sums will be rated with losse:

yea, be shée chast, be shée vertuous, be shée curteous, constant,
rich, renowned, honest, honourable, yet if thou be
wedded to a woman, thinke thou shalt finde in her sufficient
vanity to counteruaile her vertue: assure thy selfe neuer
to liue lesse without disquiet, nor die before thou haue
cause to repent: which Craterus the Emperour noted,
when wishing that some sinister misfortune might befall
his foe: he prayed vnto the Gods he might be married in
his youth, and dye without issue in his age: accounting
mariage by this wish, farre more full of preiudice, then of
pleasure. This, yea all this Acestes thou knowest to be
true: but suppose it were not, is there not sufficient to disswade?
beside, seest thou not? or hath fancy cast such a
maske before thine eyes, that thou wilt not sée? that her
beauty as it is excellent, so it is high seated: both in the
dignity of her parentage, &amp; the selfe conceite of her mind,
to be gazed at, and so honored: not to be reacht at and so
enioyed, thou séest she is little liberall of her lookes, much
lesse prodigall of her loue: she couets rather a God, then
a man: thē amongst men think she wil aime at the highest,
or sit still as she is: Pride in her greatest pompe sits
inthrond in her eyes, and disdaine in her lookes: that if
she glaunce to so low as Acestes, it is rather to grace him
with a smile then to shew him any fauour: beside, fortune
hath opposed her selfe to thy aspiring thoughts, in that
thy good will hath not yet deserued any such guerdon: thy
desire, is farre aboue thy desert: and the poore stay of a
wandring Knight, farre vnfitte for the Princely state of
worthy Lidia: But suppose she were pricked in the same
veine, and that Venus would friendly instill some drops
of her inchaunted water to mollifie her hart, yet ye Duke
her Father will neither condiscend to her mind, nor consent
to my motion: nay if he should but heare of such reckles
folly, as he hath wrought my promotion, so hee would
worke my confusion: and in troth Acestes, not without
cause: for art thou so voyde of vertue, or vowde to vice, as

to requite his liberality with such disloyalty: to returne
the trust which hee reposeth in thée with such treachery:
Tush, Loue is aboue Lord or law, friend or faith, where
Loue buddeth, no Maister is made account off, no King
cared for, no friend feared of, no duty respected: but all
things done according to the quality that is predominant.
Hast thou béene a Souldiour, and dreamest thou of such
doubts? are the courtings of Venus, more perrillous then
the incounters of Mars? or the deniall of a Lady, worse
then the daunt of a foe: no Acestes, be not faint harted as
the North Ilands, where the people Iberi dwell foster no
venemous beast, nor the Sea called Mare mortuum feedeth
no Fish, so are there no Cowards suffered to arriue
at Paphos, she is but a woman, and therefore to be wone:
Then sound on the march, aske not of what degrée she is,
but where she is: these words Acestes (carry emphasis)
and are more fit for a Souldier then for a Louer: for loue
is quesie, and if it be ouer-strained, cracketh at the first
wrest: enduring in this doubt, he sat downe déepely ouercharged
with melancholy passions; that as he which eateth
of the Goord Nutte, loseth his memory: and as the
Elephant féeding on the Helytropian becommeth sleepy:
so Acestes fell into a drowsie kind of contemplature, that
to auoide such cogitations as combred his minde, hee got
him selfe into a Gallery which was built betweene the
Turrets of the house, and there sette himselfe downe as
halfe in a traunce: Loue, that tooke pitty of this patient,
so fauourd him, that he had not sat long in his dumps but
that Lidia came thither all alone to be solitary, who séeing
Acestes sitting thus sadly slumbring, determined for her
owne recreation to be a little plesant with him, and therfore
awakened him thus.
               Why how now Acestes, is it your custome in Thracia
to vse slumbers after meat for Phisick? or is it some melancholy
impression that thus amateth your sences? trust
me at the first I called to remembrance the picture that

                  Zerxsis drew of Endimion, lying vpon the mount of Erecinus,
who leaning his head on his hand, his eyes shutte as
one in a dreame: yet had his face so bedued with distilling
teares, as his outward plaints did sufficiently bewray his
inward passions: and so Acestes, in this thy solitary dump?
didst thou resemble Endimion, both in countenance and
colour, that had teares fallen from thine eyes as thou
wert in a traunce? I had happily demaunded how Phebe
had vsed thee: So apalde was Acestes at this sodaine presence
of Lidia, that hee sat still as a man depriued of his
sences: till at the last gathering of his wittes together
he start vp, and his due reuerence done, he made this answere.
               I think Madam that melancholy is not particuler either
to person or place, but that being a complexion, it followeth
oft-times the quality of the affection: so that the
mind any way distrest, the body must yéeld in effect to the
most precious part: I confesse therefore, that being disquiet
at my hart, I felt mine eyes heauy, as they which
were the chéefest procurers of my malady: but when I
awoke and sawe your excellency, both your presence and
curtesie greatly daunted my mind: your presence, in dazeling
mine eyes so suddenly with so solemne an obiect:
your curtesie, in that your Ladyshippe without curiositie
would vouchsafe to talke with so mean a Gentleman: but
I sée the best fruite hath the brauest blossomes: the most
precious stone, is chosen by the most glistering hue, and
the best conditions, by the swéetest countenance: so that
where beauty raigneth, there vertue remaineth: and vnder
a faire face resteth a faithfull hart: But whereas you
say you had taken mee for Endimion by my penitrature
&amp; countenance, but that I wanted teares to decipher my
sorrow: I answer, that the hottest thunders are not euer
quenched with raine, nor the déepest gréefes euer discouered
by teares: the stone Garatides fryeth without and
is cold within, the Germander least when it is most full

of moisture, looketh then most dry: where the sea is most
déepe, there it is most calme: &amp; where is the smallest shew
of teares, there oft are the greatest effect of sorrow: For
trust me Madam, I thinke Endimion sighing for the absence
of his Lady Luna, neuer felt more bitter passions
on the mount Erecinus, then I suffered in this halfe waking
slumber: why (quoth Lidia) are you in loue? Acestes
at this question fetcht a déepe sigh, as it séemed his heart
strings should haue crackt in sunder, he stood as one in an
extasie, doubting whether nowe hee should take time by
the fore-head, or to defer it till afterward: well, séeing opportunity
so fit, he boldly tooke hart at grace, and began to
giue this encunter.
               They (Madame) that séeke to stop the swift running
Volgo, a Riuer that leadeth into Persia, by staying the
streame, maketh the flood flow more fiercely: to represse
the fier, is to encrease the flame: and to conceale loue, is
to smother smoake in the nosethrill, which either wil out,
or els stifleth: wounds fed of with delayes fester, and oft
prooue incurable: fancy long held in the grasse, seldome
prooues a timely Haruest: which makes me to set my hazard
on the Dice, and either presently to heare the curteous
sentence of my life▪ or the cruell doome of my death.
Since most excellent Princesse, I arriued at the Court
of Lidia, so hath mine eyes fed on the beauty of your face,
mine eares wrapt in admiration of your deuine wit, my
mind inchaunted with the consideration of your vertues,
and my hart as the receptacle of all these excellencies, so
deuoted to the substance that contriues such supernaturall
qualities, that the exceeding pleasure, which so long
luld mee in delight, at length suncke so déepe, that they
grew to gréeuous passions: to say all (what I could at
large discourse) in on worde, so long did I gaze at your
beauty, that I was snared, and so long did I admire your
vertue, that now I rest your Captiue: so farre Madame
entred the Laborinth, that either I must perrish with the

Minotaure, or els humbly craue your ayde, that the clue
of your mercy may hale me forth of such an intricate danger.
               
                  Lidia, who swelled in choller at these spéeches, coulde
not brooke to heare vp the ende of his discourse, but faring
like angry Ioue, who in his rage couereth the beautifull
Skye with a world of stormes, so she incensed with dysdaine,
filled her sweet countenaunce with a shaddowe of
bitter frownes, knitting her browes she beganne thus to
reply.
               Why gentle maister Knight, hath too much familiaritie
bredde contempt? are you such a good Phisiognomer,
that you haue insight into my wrincle in the browe and
dimple in the cheekes? I see well if Apelles that cunning
Painter, suffer the greasie Sowter to take a view of his
curious worke, hee will growe so malapart as to meddle
with his picture, that he must be thrust into his shop with
Nae sutor vltra crepidum, if the proude Centaur Ixion bee
bidden to the feast of the Gods, no lesse then Iuno herselfe
will suffice him for his choyce.
               Set a Begger on horsebacke, and they say he will neuer
light: extoll one of base stock to any degree of dignitie,
and who so proud and hautie: I speake this Acestes to
thy reproofe, for that my Father hath made thée generall
of his forces, seekest thou to maister him in fortune: will
no dyet downe but my Fathers owne Dish? no meaner
mate suffise vnlesse thou marry with a Prince? Dyd my
Father preferre thee, and now wilt thou presume to bee
his better? haue my lookes beene so louing, my glaunces
so full of good will, as to promise so much as thou doost presume?
no▪ but the least countenaunce of familiaritie to a
seruile minde, procureth great incouragement: hast thou
euer noted any of my actions so base, that thou mightest
think I would match with a man of thy calling? Haue I
wantond it so euer in thy sight, as thou mightst think mee
fit for Venus? But suppose my minde were so fonde, as I

would (soring so hie as euer I haue doone) stoope nowe so
low? thinkest thou my Father coulde affoorde thee hys
Daughter Lidia, whom he farre priseth aboue his crown?
hopest thou to compasse his consent? No, but if he knewe
of thy daring presumtion, he would repay thy follie with
such punishments, as thy aspiring thoughts doe merrit:
hée woulde vnplume thée of all thy feathers: and like Esops
Crowe turne thee naked to the worlde: that they
which grudged at thy hastie promotion, might laugh at
thy sudaine fall: if therfore thou loue thine own welfare,
kéepe thy selfe within thy bounds: least in soaring with
the Hobby, to fall to the geound with the Larke: and in
daring with Phaeton, thou fal headlong into such infirmities,
as thou shalt neuer be able to créepe out of: and with
that she flung away in a great rage, and left Acestes passing
passionate: so that hee sate him downe againe more
melancholie then he was before: musing aud meditating
vppon the cruell resolution of Lidia, slumbring thus on
his harde fortune, vppon a suddaine hee fell into these
tearmes.
               But by the swéete, how should wee know the sower:
the white séemeth most siluer hued when it is adioyned to
blacke: and prosperitie is most sweetest when it hath
beene fore-crossed with aduersity. This principle perhaps
Lidia meanes to make me try by experience, thinking to
féede mee first with bitter broathes, that after, dainty fare
may more delight me: for the childing colde of Winter,
makes the Sommers Sun more pleasant: and the frowning
lookes of Lidia, will cause her smiles to séeme more
cheerefull. Then Acestes cease not to pursue thy sute, vntill
thou finde her more curteous, or resolutely vowed to
remaine obstinate.
               Thus like a valiant Champion, Acestes neuer feared
that mislike hung in Womens browes, and into theyr
harts hee could not pry: but hoped the best, and sought for
opportunitie to iterate his sute in this distresse. But ForFortune

meaning plesantly to sport with this young nouice,
would not minister such fitte occasion that hee might
haue sole and solitary accesse to his Goddesse: for Lidia
vpon pretended purpose, so warily auoided his companie:
and with such disdainfull lookes rewarded his proffered
dutie, that Acestes was faine to aime his course by a new
compasse, and therefore getting into his Chamber, stepping
to his standish, he wrote her a Letter to this effect.
               
                  
                     Acestes to the beautifull Princesse
Lidia, wisheth what shee desires.
                     SUch as take surfeite by féeding too greedily on the Hony
combes of Hibla, seeke cure by tasting ouermuch of
the swéete suger Canes in Candi. The Phalanga stingeth
deadly, and his venome can bee drawne out onely by rubbing
ouer the place with golde. They which fall sicke of
Loue, must haue potions ministred by fancie &amp; charmes
from Venus to tie about their temples, or els come Apollo
with all his drugs: the patient will returne him thys
answer. Nullis amor est medicabilis Herbis. I speak thys
sweet Princesse, as a patient troubled with the same passions:
for so déeply haue I imprinted the rich Carracters
of your exquisite perfections, in the closet of my thoughts▪
that neither mine owne endeuour féeling I haue aspyred
too hie, nor your rigor checking me I am borne to lowe,
serueth any way to race out those Ideas which so firmelie
I haue conceiued: I seeke to suppresse loue with reason:
and I finde that I quench fire with Flaxe: I vse absence,
that is Oyle in the flame: I frequent cōpany, their talke
is tedious vnto mée: I séeke to be solitarie, oh then as in
visions your swéete selfe is present, as that celestiall obiect
whereon mine eye coueteth to gaze, and my minde to
meditate. Sith then Madame, your beautie hath made
me surfeit, let your curteous bountie cure my disease: reiect

him not so rigorously that regardeth you with such reuerence:
poore Knights haue their loues not in their own
willes, but as Loue and Fortune pleaseth to allot: some
gaze hie and stumble not, as Vulcan whē he courted Venus,
some looke low and gaine not, as Eumenides, that maried
a Farmers daughter that proued vnchast: sure I am
howsoeuer I shall speede, it will be more honor for mee to
perrish in her desires, then liue in base fortunes. Then
Madam, séeing my loue is like to ye stone Lincostis, which
the lowder the winde bloweth, and the déeper they are
drencht in the water, the more they burne &amp; blaze: so the
more you séeke to coole my fancie with disdaine, the more
my affection is kindled with desire: the greater dispayre
you driue mee into by denials, the greater hope incouraged
by cōstancie I haue to obtaine my requests? in which
feruent affection I meane to remaine without change,
crauing in liew of this my loialtie, that I may bee admitted
by degrées into your fauor, euen as my deserts in loue
shall merrit, which shall be as the blisse of heauen to him
that pineth away, and as yours onely and euer.
                     
                        Still in hope
Acestes.
                        
                     
                  
               
               THis Letter conueid with great spéede and no lesse secrecy
to Lidia beeing then solitary in her Chamber,
who receiuing them, vnripping the seales, sawe no sooner
the name of Acestes, but shee perceiued he was importunate
in his old sute: which droue her into such a fury, as
at the first shée flung away his Letter in great disdaine,
vpbrayding him of immoderate presumption, that durst
attempt the loue of such a Paragon: so that throughly inflamed
with choller, shée stept hastily to the Letter and
red it, which after shée had perused, falling into a satyricall
scoffing kinde of vaine, shee rudely returned him this
aunswere.
               
                  
                     
                     To her new found Louer Acestes,
the great Knight of Thracia,
Health.
                     SWéete Sir, I receiued your passionate Letters, and
pitty them as the inhabitants of Labia Laborinth doo
the passengers that perrish on their shelues, whom they
gaze on, but neuer releeue: your witty inuention tels me
that you are stung with the Phalanga, and so are in loue:
take it the more patiently, for no doubt the serpent was
Venus messenger, els had she not fancy in stéed of infection:
But alas, your malady cannot be cured but by my
meanes: know then braue Caualier of Thracia, that my
cunning is too small to enterprise the composition of any
secret simples, and my calling too great to become a
Phisition to such a paltring Patient: so that I neyther
can nor will cure any other mans disease by being preiudiciall
to mine owne safety, but gentle sir thinke me not
cruell: for it is the influence of the starres, &amp; the effectes
of nature that maketh these contrarieties, as hauing opposde
vs in the calculation of our natiuity, for as the
Panther cannot abide the company of the Ownce, as
the Uulture is mortall enemy to the Eagle, and the blood
of a Lyon &amp; a Woolfe can neuer be mixed in one bowle, so
as impossible it is by requests, be they neuer so ruthfull to
become thy friend, which by the destinies and instinct of
nature am thy mortall foe. Cease then to accuse mee of
cruelty, and leaue off to appeale to my curtesie, for thou
shalt alwayes be sure to finde the one, and neuer to feele
the other: yet least thou should condemne Lidia of ingratitude,
who euer was bountifull to her greatest foes,
though I cannot inwardly mittigate thy misery, yet I
wil outwardly teach thée to apply such playsters, as if
the experience of them approue true, shal greatly appease
thy paine: It is reported that he which drinketh of the riuer

                        Auerna, cooleth and mortifieth his affections, but if the
water be toucht by any meanes before it be drunke, the
vertue thereof is of no value. He that weareth the fethers
of the bird Ezalon about him, shal euer be fortunate in
his loue, but if they be not puld when the Sunne is eclipsed:
they are of no force, and to be briefe there is nothing
that sooner driueth away amorous conceits, thē to rub the
temples of thy head with the sweate of an Asse, which if
you can performe, as no doubt you may put in practise,
feare not but you shall count my Phisicke authenticall.
Thus gentle knight of Thracia, you haue heard my mind,
and so I warn you to wade no further, least I haue cause
to laugh and you to repent.
                     
                        
                           Lidia of Lidia resolued to mislike
of Acestes of Thracia.
                        
                     
                  
               
               THis Letter shee sent by one of her Gentlewomen to
Acestes, who no sooner read the contents, but the disdaine
of his Goddesse strooke such a colde dumpe to his
hart, that hee sat as the picture of Pigmalion, when the
poore caruer leaned with great passion on his marble mistresse:
his thoughts were on dispaire, his musings on
dispaire, the obiects to his eyes, sounded the vgly shadowe
of dispaire: that as one lunatick, he said: Venus was ths
strumpet of Mars, the baude of Iupiter, the Patronesse of
leachers: and that in all her Kingdome there was neyther
loue nor vertue, but lust and vanity: I graunt (quoth
he) she hath beauty to bestow, but so it is tempred with
pride, as hee that buyes it dooth penetentiam emere: shee
hath many such truls as Helena to sell, but they were either
so froward or so frolick, as feare may perswade them
from the one, or turne them from the other: shee is Goddesse
of womens hearts, but shee trickes them vp with
such false colours, and engraues so many principles of
her Philosophy, in the very center of it, that they are as

expert in coyning of deceites, forging of teares, feigning
of sighes, casting of lookes, lending of fauning smiles, and
such preiudiciall pollicies to bewitch men, as euer the
Caldees were in their diuinations, but this is, suffiseth not
to reuenge me on her words, would she were mortall, thē
would shee were Mars, that I might with my arming
Sworde pearce their disdaine and ingratitude in single
Combate.
               As thus hee was halfe in a frensie, one came to him
from the King with Letters, the contents whereof were,
that he should make him ready with all possible speede to
passe into Pamphilia, to make inuasion with fire &amp; sword:
This newes come to Acestes view, as a man reuiued frō
the dead, hee burst from his former plaints, and began
thus to frolicke with him selfe: Now despight of Venus
hath Fortune sworne to ioyne me in friendship with opportunity,
now time proffers the full cup, and the deuill
take me if I carowse it not: Now Lidia shall be mine if
euer she shalbe to any: women are wonne with honors:
the fame of Prowesse challengeth more then eloquence,
a Souldiers sword preuaileth more with a Princesse, thē
a Cowardes pen: when newes shall come to Lidia that
Acestes hath made a conquest of Pamphilia, whē he sends
the Kinges Crowne as a token to the faire and matchles
Lidia, thē no doubt but she wil be as curteous, as now she
is cruell: her lookes will lighten loue, where now they
drop hate: her words will be welcome, where now they
threten reuenge: Conquerers carry commaunds in their
foreheads, and loue kneeles to them where others bow to
loue? then Acestes ply thee, martiall thy Souldiours in
hast to Pamphilia, and there fight both for honor and loue,
which either resolue to get or to misse of both with death:
Hauing thus comforted him selfe, he prouided all things
necessary for his voiage into Pamphilia, both of souldiers,
money, victuals, and munition: which beeing ready:
taking his leaue onelie of the King (for Lidia would

                     〈1 page missing〉
                  
                  
                     〈1 page missing〉
                  
                  
and his Daughter on his right hand, were amazed, as
noting in his face some extraordinary sparkes of Chiualrie:
Acestes pacing vp to the steps that decended from the
Kings seate, placing on eyther hande a King, began thus
to deliuer his tale.
               Right mightie Soueraigne, executing the charge of
the Generall of thy forces against Pamphilia, as thy cō
                  maund
and my allegance bad me, I entred with fire and
sword, and by the helpe of Fortune made conquest of the
Countrey, the King is slaine, his Crowne I sent to thy
Daughter, the kingdom is garisond to thy vse: his confederates
these two Kings of Caria &amp; Cylicia, for that they
vnited their supplies to his forces, I inuaded, conquered,
and brought hither Captiues: their Crownes theyr kingdoms,
the treasure, the bondslaues, for that they were
without thy Commission, I not present to thee, but to the
Princesse Lidia, with all the honour I won in the fielde,
euer vowing to deuote all my thoughts, my actions, and
my Sword and life, as prest to execute her commaunde
and seruice: with that, rising vp, he led the Kinges to the
Princesse, and deliuered them her as her Captiues, shee
coulde not for shame in such a presence, but faine a good
countenaunce, and accept them gratefully: whom shee
forthwith presented to her Father, who entertaind them
as belonged to such Kingly prisoners: all the Nobles casting
their eyes on Acestes, as honouring the man for his
vertues: the King starting vp, gaue him great thanks,
and bad him demaunde some-what before that honorable
assemblie: with the gift whereof hee might gratifie him:
swearing whatsoeuer he craued, as he was true King hée
woulde performe it: Acestes hearing this happy motion,
casting his eye on the Lady Lidia, boldly beganne his request
thus.
               Although right mighty Soueraigne, Crownes and
Kingdoms be swéete, and your grace hath willed mee to
aske any thing without acception: yet for that I paunde

my life &amp; honor for the atchiuing of these conquests with
my blood, which a Souldiour holdeth far deerer then Diadems,
I little make account of such pelfe: but rather
make choise of that which I prefer before honour, life, and
land, or all the world, if it should be presented to me: and
that is, the faire and vertuous Princesse Lidia. Scarce
had Acestes vttered this worde Lidia, but the King starting
from his seat, turned to his daughter, and asked what
loue was passed betwixt her &amp; Acestes. Such (quoth shee)
with a frowning countenaunce, as past betwixt Iuno and
the Centaure Ixion: I not deny, but before his iourney to
Pamphilia, he courted and made great sute by worde, and
letters, but howe I disdained the motion of so base a companion,
let the aunswers of his Letters manifest: And
nowe before this royall &amp; honorable assembly I protest, if
Acestes were featurde like Narcissus, as couragious as
Hercules, hauing as many heroicall vertues as euer had
any, and could present me euery day two Kings for Captiues
till he made me Empresse of the World, yet woulde
I disdaine him, as one vnworthy the Princesse Lidia. At
this aunswere, all the assembly abashed, as counting the
Princesse discourteous and ingrate: the King as a man
inflamed with furie, began to prosecute his Daughters
speech in this manner: Presumptuous Thracian, vnfitte
with these late conquests, rather obtained by the ill fortune
of these Kings, then thy prowesse: for thou hast done
mee seruice, I graunt thee life, but for thyne aspyring
thoughts to demaunde the Princesse Lidia, I discharge
thée of thy Generalship, and absolutely of my seruice, cō
                  maunding
thee vpon paine of death, within ten dayes to
depart out of all my dominions, and neuer to approch my
Confines or land. This saide, the King in great choller
rose vp ready to depart, the Nobles were amazed and
greeued, yea, aud grudged secretly at Acestes wrong, but
for feare of the King were silent: Acestes howsoeuer inwardly
vexed, yet shewed no discontent in his countenance,

but with a Souldiers courage pulling of his Garland,
said: I am not dismaied at this doome, for that I neuer
greeued at the ouerthwarts of Fortune: what I haue
got in thy Court, I leaue, as disdaining ought yt is thine:
the honour I haue wonne, is mine owne, and that thou
canst not depriue me off, and so committing my fortunes
to my deserts, I leaue thee and thy Court: and so soone as
may be thy Country: where if euer I arriue, I dare thee
to doo thy worst: and with that Acestes went away, and
the King with the two Kings and the Lords, passed in to
dinner.
               No sooner was Acestes alone, but the ingratitude of
the King, the disdaine of his Daughter, the disgrace offered
by both, so pierst him to the hart, that as such as drink
of Lethe become obliuious: so he forgetting the beauty of
Lidia, fell to such déepe thoughts of hate and reuenge, that
he enioyned himselfe for a great space to be solitary, that
Nemesis and he might consult together how to bring both
the Father and the Daughter to confusion: at last hee resolued
to goe to Armenia to Sertorius, there great Potentate
of that Country, whom hée knew to be mortall enemie
to the King of Lidia, and in this resolution hée tooke
his iourney. No sooner was hee arriued in the Armenian
Court, but worde was brought to Sertorius that Acestes
the martiall Thracian, that conquered Pamphilia, Ca
                        •
                     ia,
and Cylicia, was come disguised, and as a stranger into
his Court: the King hearing this, tooke one or two of hys
chéefe Lords, and went to salute Acestes, and to giue him
honourable entertainement, such as belonged to so mightie
a Cōquerer: Acestes perceiuing himselfe to be known,
after due reuerence doone to the King, began at large to
discourse to him what seruice he had doone to the King of
Lidia, and how hee was rewarded, crauing succour and
supply of his Maiestie, that hee might reuenge with hys
Sworde. The King amazed at such monstrous ingratitude,
wondring how such base resolutions coulde harbour

in the hart of Prince, he promised Acestes not onely to
ayde him with an army of approoued Souldiers, but in
person to hazard him selfe, both to requite olde iniuries:
and to reprooue in iustice such an abuse offred without desert.
This answer of Sertorius so contented Acestes, that
after great thanks, hee rested in the Court, passing frolicke,
til the forces were furnishing: which no sooner were
ready, but without delay Sertorius and Acestes marched
merrily forwarde towardes the confines of Lidia, as soone
as Acestes had sette his foote within the ground of the ingratefull
King, drawing his Sword, hee swore not to
sheathe it, till hee had made it drunke with the blood of
Lidians, commaunding his Souldiers (for Sertorius had
giuen him the ordring of the battailes) that they should
vse all extremeties of martiall, burne, sack, spoile Citties,
Townes, and Castles, to cast all to the ground, to take
none Captiues of whatsoeuer degrée or sex, but to put all
to the Sword: men as they were subiects in Lidia, Women
as the wormes that he most hated: Children as the
issue of them both: the pillage of all should be theirs, only
the King of Armenia should haue the Kingdome, and he
would content him selfe with reuenge: this Oration ended,
he furiously marched forward, and where hee came,
left the Countrey desolate: The King of Lidia hearing
this, was driuen into a great agony, but dissembling his
gréefe for feare of discouraging his Souldiers, he leuied a
mighty army, and hasted forward to buckle with Acestes
whom he met halfe at aduantage, as hauing most of his
men at pillage: whereupon the Lidians taking oportunity
set vpon the Armenians, but Acestes so rangde those
that he had, in such warlike sort: that he not only aboade
the braue of his enemy, but entred his battaile, disordered
his ranckes, and put them to the flight: many were
slaine in that present place, such as escapt and fled, were
met by the Pillages and haruiers of the Armenians, and
all put to the sword, so that of forty thousand Lidians there

scarse remained thirty with the King, who passing vp into
the Country: insconst him-selfe within a strong Castel
with his Daughter Lidia, a few faint harted Souldiers,
and all the treasure hee could get: Acestes followed his
Fortunes, and leauing Sertorius behind with the mayne
battaile, tooke with him ten thousand Horse, and sixe thousand
foote, and made after the King of Lidia, as fast as his
men were able to march: comming at last to the Castell
weere he was insconst, first he intrencht a siege round about
and legard it on euery side, then he damd vp all such
springs, wels, and Conduits, as serued the Castell with
fresh water: this done, hee resolued not to loose a man at
the assault, but to make them yeeld by famine. The Princesse
Lidia looking ouer the walls, séeing how her mortall
enemy had girt the Castell with Souldiers, Armenians
men there thirsted after blood, and hated both her and her
Father, she fell from thoughts to passions, from passions
to teares: insomuch that she sat her downe, and wept bitterly:
her Father comming vp the batilments, séeing his
daughter in such perplexed estate, finding want of victuals,
and that of force he must be famished: gréefe stopping
his spéech, he sat him downe and bare her company in her
passions: and after consulted how to preuent ensuing misery,
many coniectures cast: at last they resolued to submit
themselues to his mercy, whereupon Lidia decking
her selfe in most gorgious attire, accompanied onely with
two of her Ladies, passed out of the Castell gate, &amp; went
toward the Legar: the Sentonell no sooner had them in
hold, but they were honourably conueyed to the Pauilion
of Acestes, who being certified that the Princesse Lidia
was attended to speake with him, leapt from his seate,
and went to entertaine her, Lidia no sooner saw him, but
she fell downe at his feete: Acestes curteeusly tooke her
vp, and setting her in his seate, demaunded her what shē
                  craued:
Lidia all blubbered with teares, falling downe
on her knées, began thus.
               
                  
Mighty Acestes, if repentance were any satisfaction
for offences, or sorrowe any salue to couer ingratitude, if
teares might wipe away disdaine, if a Uirgines blood
would pay raunsome for them which haue done amisse:
I would present all these to pacifie the fury of thy conquering
Sword: but I know such déepe hate of my Fathers
ingratitude, such desire to reuenge my rechlesse disdaine,
and the disgrace proffered by both: hath set a fire
the hart of Acestes, as nothing may serue to quench such
an ouer heated flame: Oh yet might I finde so much fauour,
that my death might redéeme the old man my Father,
if not for the losse of Kingdome, yet of life: and from
falling into the handes of his ancient enemy Sertorius, I
should account Acestes as mercifull as he is valiant: if
my treaties may not preuaile, as it little behooueth Acestes
any way to fauour Lidia, yet graunt me this, that I
may dye vpon thine owne Sworde, that my blood vanishing
on thy blade, thou mayst be satisfied, and I slaughtred:
by the hand of Acestes so braue a Souldier, might
dye contented.
               No sooner had shee vttered these words, but shee poured
foorth such streames of teares, as made the Armenians
to take pitty of the distressed Princesse: Acestes taking
her vp againe, called for his Sworde, and vnsheathing
falling downe at her feete, began thus to make
reply.
               Such déepe impression of gréefe swéete Goddesse, hath
pierced the heart of Acestes, in that hee hath lifted his
Sworde against the Lord that harboreth Lidia such sorrow,
such repentance, such remorce, in that I haue doone
any thing that might offend the Princesse Lidia, whose
deuine presence hath raced out all intent to reuenge: and
so captiuated againe her Acestes: that héere franckly he
offreth his conquering Sworde, (that hath atchiued so
many battailes) into the hand of his mistresse to chastice
eyther with death if she please, that daring Knight that

hath so déepely offended, and with that he sat as a man in
a traunce: Lidia séeing she had brought the Beare to the
stake, thought now so cunningly to muzzle, as she would
kéepe him heereafter for biting: following therefore her
inchauntment, shee fell about his necke, and wette his
chéekes with her teares in such sort, that at last from wéeping
they fell to kissing, yea so did Acestes comfort Lidia,
that from melancholy she grew to be somewhat plesant,
the Knight possessed thus of his Lady (as hee thought) after
he had banqueted her with such delicates as souldiers
can affoord, taking only her hand for pawne of his fafety,
he went with her to the Castell, where they were no sooner
entred, but the King of Lidia with his Crowne in his
hand met Acestes, and submitting him selfe, offered both
his diadem and daughter as due to so victorious a champion,
Acestes refused his dignities, but accepting of his
Daughter, embraced her, and entred into priuate and
familier parle: insomuch that choller past vppon both
sides, they began to treate of the marriage, which was
concluded: when the King of Armenia returned out of his
Kingdome: wherupon without delay (so feruent was the
loue of Acestes,) hee tooke leaue of Lidia and her Father,
and going downe to the Legar, raysed the siege, to the
great admiration of all his Souldiers, and from thence
marched to the Campe where Sertorius lay: to whom
Acestes reueled what had past, and craued that he would
depart out of Lidia with sufficient coyne answerable for
his costs: Sertorius with a frowning looke tolde him that
in battaile he neuer plaid in iest, and what he had wonne
with the blood of his Souldiers and danger of his owne
person, he would not deliuer vp but by battaile: Acestes
whose minde was too haughty to intreat, said nothing, but
secretly stole from the Campe, and trauersing through
Lidia, got vp of Horse and Footemen, the number of sixe
and thirty thousand, with whome trusting to his Fortunes,
hee marched closely and secretly to the Campe,

of Sertorius, where he arriued about midnight, vsing now
pollicy, that before had conquered with prowesse: so that
killing the watch and Sentonell, he past the Courte of
garde, and set vpon the Souldiers, making a great slaughter
of such men as were sleepie and amaz'd: yet Sertorius
escaped, but Acestes passed forward and followed him into
Armenia, where his fortunes so serued him, that hee
conquered Armenia, and brought the King himselfe captiue
to Lidia: comming thus in tryumph to my Fathers
court, seating him in greater pompe and possessions then
euer he had, he began to vse his late familiarity towards
me, but I as a woman changed in calling and condition,
shooke him off with more disdaine then before: hee challenged
my Fathers promise, who presently commaunded
he should be apprehended and put in close prison: wee hauing
thus cauhgt the Lyon in ye snare, my Father questioned
mee how I would haue him vsed. I would not resolue
on any lesse penaltie then death, my reason least in
letting him abroad, he should fal to his fortunes: the maner
of his martirdome I deuised to be famine, as hee intended
to vs by his leager: my Father yeelding him absolutely
into my hands: I prosecuted the matter, causing
euery day for his greater torment, a course or two of daintie
viands to be carried before the window that looked into
his Chamber, and my selfe to agrauate his sorrowes,
would passe often by his lodging in most pleasant humor.
Acestes séeing himselfe thus ouertaken in his own follie,
by trusting too much the teares of a woman, would not
exclaime against the sexe, but séeing no way but death, no
kinde but famine, he resolued to shew an honorable mind
in great patience, &amp; so remained their foure dayes, when,
pinched with extreame hunger almost euen to death: as
Lidia passed by, he fell into these passions.
               Meate, meate, oh for want of meate I perrish: Ah
hunger, hunger, the extreamest of all extremeties: were
I amongst men, men would pittie me: amongst beastes,

beastes should feede me or feede vpon me. Amidst ye pikes
would I venterously escape, or valiantly perrish: on the
land, I could shift: in the Sea, I could swimme: no place
so barren, no people so barberous that woulde not releeue
me or soone ridde mée: euery where more help, no where
lesse, hope, ah hunger, hunger, the extreamest of all extremities.
Thrice cruell Lidia, no worse I will tearme thée
for that once I loued thee: not suffering mee to liue, nor
simply to dye: my head is giddy, mine eyes dazell, fallen
are my cheekes, and my tonge die my words, my sinewes
shrinke, my blood consumeth, all my limmes fainte, and
my hart failes me: euery minute I die, and I with I dyd
but die: too long am I out of the way, to bee well out of
the way: Ah hunger, hunger, the extreamest of all extremities.
               Ah Liuia, haue I deserued thus to bee doone vnto, I
gaue thee Crownes, and thou wilt not giue mee a crum:
I bestowed Kingdoms on thy Father, aud hee presents
me with famine: thus Loue wrought the traine, and fortune,
nay mine owne folly performed the treason: yet
this hope I haue, that he hath found me, is hee that
hath fashioned mée, who though he scourge mee, will yet
saue me, how be it my God I cannot but cry, ah hunger,
hunger, the extreamest of all extremeties.
               What is it I would not rather be, then thus bee? then
thus, ah then thus in pined walles to attende so bitter a
death? I faint, alas I faint, my harts anguish commaundeth
my tongues silence: then Acestes silently be patient,
patiently be penitent, penitently perrish, and that last
martirdome will be thy least miserie, because longer thou
shalt not cry: ah hunger, hunger, the extreamest of all
extremeties.
               This complaint highly contented Lidia, so that shee
departed and tolde it to her Father, reioycing that her
deuised fourme of death sorted to so bitter euents: well
another day past, so hungry grew Acestes, that he greedely

fed on the flesh on his armes, spilling that bloode with
his own teeth, which before he had so prisde in many battailes:
which when hée had done, readie to giue vp the
ghost, seeing the bare bones of his armes, he fell into this
last complaint: Miserable wretch euen in the highest degrée,
miserably with my teeth haue I tyred on mine own
flesh, till now bloodlesse and famished, my latest gaspe
hardly giues passage to a few, and my farewell wordes,
Lidia, ah Lidia, wherof is thy hard hart formed? that the
sting of such diresse cannot peirce it, hast thou the eares of
a woman to heare my cries, and not the hart of a woman
to pitty my case? Ah Lidia, he that loued thee, for that hee
loued thee must die: he that sounded thy praises in sundry
Prouinces, him hast thou pinned and pined vp, till those
armes are bare from flesh, that in many battailes bruted
thy fame: I will not curse; thou art Lidia, nor exclaime
at my last date thou wert my loue: nor pray for reuenge,
sith at my death my patience shall giue my soule the better
passage. But fondly, how short a time haue I to speak
and yet how foolishly I speake, to name my earthly Goddesse
when I shoulde pray to my heauenly God: the one
hath consumed me, the other must saue mée: now comes
the touch, my hart yeeldes to him that framed it, now the
last bitter sweete pang of death endes what the malice of
man hath inflicted, and so falling downe, he died.
               As soone as I perceiued hee was dead, not yet content
with reuenge, I caused his body to be hang'd in chaynes,
that the world might see the trophée of my crueltie: The
manner of his death beeing knowne, the Nobles and specially
the Commans began to murmure that so braue a
warriour who had made foure Kingdoms tributories to
Lidia, shoulde so ingratefully perrish through ye malicious
disdaine of a woman, yea, so farre it pierced into the hart
of Selidon great Duke of our realme, that suddainly causing
a mutiny, he summond most of the Nobles, &amp; told thē
such a tirant was too heauy for them to beare, to be short,

the Nobles agréed, the Commons of their free will came
in flocks to reuenge, so that he had quickly leauied an Armie
of an hundred thousand men, and entred into the Castle,
tooke mée and my Father prisoners, whom hee commaunded
to be famished in the same place where Acestes
ended his life, there without remorse we dyed, they tooke
downe the body of Acestes, and buried him with princelie
funerals, and ouer his tomb, for that he attempted the reuenge:
they crowned Solydor King of Lidia.
               
               AS soone as she had ended her tale, she fell to her wonted
cryes and shrikes, not answering to any question,
so that I left the place and returned backe with my Harp:
Orpheus hauing thus discoursed, Iupiter asked Venus
how the liked of the tale: marry quoth shée, as of one that
Orpheus tells, comming out of Hell: nothing preiudicial
to my Dietie, sith shee was enemy to loue, and of so austere
chastitie: it rather toucheth Iuno or Diana, the one
stately in her lookes, the other too chary in her thoughts:
for my part so I dislike of her disdainfull crueltie, as if I
might haue censured, if possible it might haue béene, shee
shoulde haue had a more bitter death vppon earth, and a
more pinching paine in hell: Truth quoth Mercurie, for
perhaps the paine is not so great to remaine in the fogge,
as the remembrance how faire once shee was, and nowe
to haue all smeared with the smoake: I think when Venus
was a maid, she was more charie of her face then her
maidenhead: and more warie of her beauty then her honestie.
These quippes quoth Mars are digressions, but
leaue Venus and talke of Lidia, whose life was so strickt,
whose hart so opposde to loue, whose thoughtes so full of
pride and disdaine, as her instance serueth rather to bée
produced for a wonder, then for example to condemne
women, sith the world I thinke containes not one so bad:
Apollo smiling said, Well taken Mars for you owne aduantage,
women must be pleasde, and Venus will frowne

if she be not flattered: Vulcan sits fast a sléepe, or else I
would not haue spoake so broad before, but to drink down
all the frumps, Ganimede (quoth he) fill in Nectar, so the
Gods from disputing fel to carowsing, and then Arion tuning
his instrument, began to warble out this Ditty.
               
                  The Song of Arion.
                  
                     SEated vpon the crooked Dolphins back,
                     Scudding amidst the purple coloured waues:
                     Gazing aloofe for Land, Neptune in black,
                     attended with the Tritons as his slaues.
                     Threw forth such stormes as made the ayre thick▪
                     
                     For greefe his Lady Thetis was so sick.
                  
                  
                     Such plaints he throbd as made the Dolphin stay,
                     women (quoth he) are harbours of mans health:
                     Pleasures for night, and comforts for the day,
                     what are faire women but rich natures wealth.
                     Thetis is such, and more if more may be:
                     Thetis is sick, then what may comfort me.
                  
                  
                     Women are sweets that salue mens sowrest ills,
                     women are Saints, their vertues are so rare:
                     Obedient soules that seeke to please mens wills,
                     such loue with faith, such Iewels women are.
                     Thetis is such, and more if more may be:
                     Thetis is sick, then what may comfort me.
                  
                  
                     With that he diu'd into the Corall waues,
                     To see his loue, with all his watry slaues.
                     The Dolphin swam, yet this I learned then:
                     Faire women are rich Iewells vnto men.
                  
               
               
                  ARion hauing ended his Ditty, Apollo sayde, this
falls out fitte, for Orpheus hauing made the diuision
of a womans nature to be either too cruel, or too curteous:

                  Arion standeth in his song as well to defend, as he to oppose:
accounting women the wealth of nature, and farre
more profitable then Orpheus saies they are preiudiciall,
therfore if it please the rest of the Gods, we'le heare what
Arion censures of that sexe, they gladly agreed, and Apollo
commaunded him to shewe his opinion, where-vpon
Arion began thus.
               No sooner right mighty Gods, had nature in her curious
moulde formed the counterfeite of Beauty, but looking
vpon her workmanship, shee fell in loue with that
metaphysicall excellency, as Pigmalion did with the perfection
of his owne Art: which may assure vs, that it is
most exquisite, wherein curious nature taketh such extreame
delight: this glorious Idea drawne out from the
secret temper of the graces nature, bestowed more prodigally
vpon women then men, as creatures more worthy
and excellent: the richest gold hath the rarest colour, the
purest stones are most cleare, the sweetest Flowers most
pleasing to the eye: and women as the purest quintissence
circolated from all other liuing things, are therefore the
most beautifull and faire: yea in their own sex, beauty is
the touchstone of vertue, and ye fairer a woman is, the fuller
of good conditions: for such as nature hath either slipt
ouer with negligence, or made in her melancholy, so that
they are ill fauoured and deformed eyther in face or body:
such I holde as a principle to be counted stigmaticall, as
noted by nature to be of a bad constitution: then must we
confesse that beauty is excellent, as the pride of nature:
deuine, as fetcht from the Gods: glorious, as the delight
of the eye: pleasing, as the content of the hart: and to be
estéemed aboue all things, as the very couer and superficies
vnder which vertue lyes hid: if then men séeing such
heauenly obiects, such swéet Saints, haue their eyes fixed,
their minds fettered, their thoughts inchanted with their
loues, are they to be blamed or not? rather to be thought
of Heroicall conceite: that place their liking on the foundation

of beauty, and to be counted men of great iudgement,
that in their desires séeke to covnite themselues to
such an excellency: for may not he which enioyeth a beautifull
Lady, boast that he possesseth at command? by spending
a few yéeres in wooing, some part of his liuing in expences,
his dayes quiet in sighs, his nights sléep in teares,
by these toyes and a few other passions, he possesseth himselfe
of that creature which the graces and nature had
studied many ages to make excellent: yet there be some
such satiricall copes-mates▪ that spare not to raile against
them, calling them the imperfection of nature, saying
beauty is vanity, and the signe of little honesty, noting
women as waspish, froward, deceitful, toyish, light, sullen,
proud, inconstant, discurteous, cruell, and what not: such
as can afford them no better spéeches, I would haue either
made Euenuches or Esseni or plaine Asses, neuer to be
fauoured of women, but to be accounted as stoicall companions,
vnfit to attend on such beautifull and vertuous
creatures: for in my opinion swéete and simple soules:
they be pleasant, open harted, far from deceit God wote,
as bearing all their owne secrets both graue, and yet hauing
many mad and merry tricks to pleasure men, humble
&amp; lowly, submitting themselues to what their friends
will lay vpon them: constant, as neuer to be turnd from
their opinions: kind enough, and to be short, as full of excellent
qualities, as the precious stone Silex is full of secret
vertue, and this right mighty Gods is my opinion of
women: The Gods smiled at this censure of Arion, and
wished him if he could to proue it with an instance as Orpheus
did the contrary: Arion laying by his instrument,
and the Gods being silent, he told his tale to this effect.
            
            
               Arions Tale.
               AFter that Right mighty Gods, the Pirats had heaued
me ouer boord, &amp; that being receiued vpon a Dolphins
back, I was safely transported to Loyath, the King

glad of my arriuall, as honoring me for that I was counted
the most perfect musition in Thece, and musing at
the strangenes of my fortunes: to make his péeres and
princes of his land, partakers not only of my melody, but
of the wonder: he proclaimed a generall feast, not of volentary
but vpon commaund, that all Dukes, Earles,
Barrons, Knights, and other Gentlemen, should with
their wiues and children, for the more magnificence be
present: which strickt Edict, was so straightly obeyed of
all, that at the day appoynted, none failed to be present:
there appeard in the Kings Pallace such troups of Lords
and Ladies, as might with their glorious brauery ouercharge
the eye with pleasure. To these the King presented
me clad in my rich robe, with mine instrument euen
as I sate on the Dolphins back, with the whole discourse
of my fortunes: wherat they were all driuen into a wandring
admiration, after long gazing on me, as at a man
reserued to some higher or more hatefull destiny, they
sate downe in the great Hall to dinner: beeing placed by
the King him selfe and his Sonne, who then playde the
Marshall of the Hall: the yong Prince, whose name was
Philomenes, giuing greatest attendance where hee sawe
the fairest Ladies: as hauing his eye drawn rather with
beauty then chiualry, at last he espied a lampe that lightned
all the rest, or rather disgraced them: as Phebe dooth
the little fixed Starres: for so farre she surpast the other
Ladies in excellency, as she did in dignity: and by birth
she was daughter to Pelopidas the Duke, and great commaunder
in Corinth, this Lady whose name was Argentina
was so faire: as touching the faultles mixture of vermillion
flourisht vpon Iuory, &amp; so full of fauor for the perfect
proportion of the linaments, whereupon this natiue
colour was ouer-dasht, that nature had made beauty abcolute,
and beauty made Argentina the most excellent:
Philomenes séeing so heauenly a Nimph, stoode staring on
her face, as at a wonder, gazing so long, that Venus séeing

                  Ceres and Bacchus honored all the rest, thought to arrest
the yong Prince for her attendant, so that leuelling Cupids
arrow aright, and wishing the boy to draw home, she
pierst Philomenes so deepe, that hee shrunk &amp; start at the
suddaine prick which this inuenomed arrow had tainted
him with: feeding thus his eye, his fancy &amp; his thoughtes
with contemplation, hee lost his stomacke to gorge with
the Camelion on the ayre: sure was that messe where
Argentina sat, to haue what attendance the Prince could
grace them with: but their seruice was so broken and so
ill sewed, that either they must coniecture the Prince to
bee no cunning seruitor, or els that his hart was on his
halfe-penny: well, dinner beeing doone and the tables taken
vp, Arion fell to his musick, and the cheefe Ladies to
the measures, Philomenes ringleader of the rout, singled
out the Lady Argentina, who blushing to sée the young
Prince make choise of her aboue the rest, gaue such a glorie
to her face, that Philomenes all on fire at the sight, had
almost forgotte the time of the measure: but calling his
wits together, he led formost till the musick ceast, &amp; then
wringing her by the hand, he whisperd to her thus. I see
Madam that all these Lords and Ladies present, frolicke
themselues as fitting the time, and feeding my Fathers
delightful humor: my silly selfe onely excepted, who thys
day giuing mine eyes leaue to banquet on your beautie,
commanded my stomacke to fast and pray, that my heart
which had surfetted on the excellencie of loue, might finde
a curteous Phisition: now swéete saint it resteth in your
fauour, whether I shall triumph as the most happiest, or
sorrow as the most miserable. The musick called on to an
other measure, so that Philomenes was interrupted, &amp; forced
to tread his taske, but as soone as the musicke gaue
breathing time, Argentina beginning her exordium with
a blush, made Philomenes this aunswer.
               It seemeth sir, that tis a mery time, your honor is so well
disposed to bee pleasant, singling out a cunning musition.

the simplest plaine song, that your descant might séeme the
more refind. It behoueth such as my self to brook ye frumps
of a Prince, &amp; to take them for fauours, for Kings wordes
may not offend, if in wrath, much lesse in iest: might your
handmaide dare to reply, in my opinion howsoeuer your
eyes haue banquetted, your sight is neuer the worse, nor
they the more satisfied: for your harts surfeite I will bee
beadwoman, with your stomack not in fasting, but pray
that your Phisition may prooue such as would fit your desires:
but my Lorde to your last clause, it is vnlikely your
mirth dependeth of my fauour, whose fauour cannot profit
nor disfauour preiudice, but taking it in iest as your honor
profferd it, I pray you for my part my Lord to be as merry
as you please. The instruments sounded, and forward
must Philomenes, who wisht Arions strings might crack,
that his melody ended, he might proceed in his prattle. As
soone as the musick stopt againe, the Prince began thus.
               Beléeue me Lady, if you take my talk for a iest, you haue
a deeper insight in my thoughts then my self: for by your
diuine beauty, (the oath that for the whole world I would
not infringe) so déeply in earnest did I break into my first
passion, that my hart féeleth far more then my tongue vttered,
so strongly and strangly hath loue on a suddain vi et
armis as they say made entrance, there where fancie before
could haue no passage, so that rightly hast thou sayde
Argentina, that though mine eyes &amp; hart surfeited, yet they
are not satisfied: as vowing themselues euer deuoted to so
excellent a choyse: which if they may possesse as it lyes in
your power, nature by no meanes may minister thē greater
content: As Philomenes was ready to wade further in
his discourse, the daunce, I know not vpon what occasion,
brake of, and the old man calling his sonne, tolde the noble
men they should heare one of Arions schollers, whervpon
he commaunded his sonne to take the instrument in hys
hand, who very nie as skilfull as his Maister, obeyed his
Fathers charge, and glad that time had giuen him opportunitie

to shew his cunning before this Goddesse, hee began
to play, and sung a sonnet to this effect.
               
                  CVpid abroade was lated in the night,
                  his winges were wet with ranging in the raine,
                  Harbour he sought, to mee hee tooke his flight,
                  to dry his plumes I heard the boy complaine.
                  I opte the doore, and graunted his desire,
                  I rose my selfe, and made the wagge a fire.
               
               
                  Looking more narrow by the fiers flame,
                  I spied his quiuer hanging by his backe:
                  Doubting the boy might my misfortune frame,
                  I would haue gone for feare of further wrack.
                  But what I drad, did me poore wretch betide:
                  For forth he drew an arrow from his side.
               
               
                  He pierst the quick, and I began to start,
                  a pleasing wound but that it was too hie,
                  His shaft procurde a sharpe, yet sugred smart,
                  away he flewe, for why his winges were dry.
                  But left the arrow sticking in my brest:
                  That sore I greeude I welcomd such a guest.
               
               
                  PHilomenes hauing ended his song, they all generallie
commended the skil of the yong Prince, but especially
Argentina, who hearing him sing both swéetly and passionately,
was charmed as if she had heard the Sirens, that
while all the other walked abroad, shee fained herselfe not
well, and withdrew solitary into her Chamber, where alone,
she began to ruminate in her memory all the perfections
of Philomenes, as well the swéenes of his face, ye proportion
of his body, as the vertues &amp; qualities of the mind:
his courage, his comlines, his dignities, but there she stopt
&amp; gaue a sigh, as being a prince too high for her to gaze at,
meditating thus: shee so swallowed vp the potions yt 
                  Venus
                  
had tempred with her sorcery, as drunk with his beutie,
she began to fall with herselfe into this parle.
               Unhappy Argentina, whose youth vertue hath brideled
with chast thoughtes, whose yeeres beauty inchaunteth
with fond lookes, resembling the nettle, which may bee
handled in the bud, but stingeth in the flower: do thy vertues
increase like the pace of a Crab, backwarde? Hast
thou in thy cradle been continent, and wilt thou in thy sadle
be impudent? art thou come to this feast to buy follie?
knowst thou not that Venus stands by the wine-presse of
Bacchus, and breathes her venom vppon his liquor? satst
thou downe pleasant &amp; must thou rise passionate? I and
in loue Argentina? and why not in loue? was I not framed
for loue? are not Womens harts the Exchequour
where fancie yeelds vp his accounts: yes Argentina, and
feare not to loue, for if thy choyce be right made, there can
nothing come for marriage but honour: but with whom
art thou in loue? with Philomenes the Kings Sonne and
heire apparent to the Diadem of Corinth, a steppe higher
Argentina then it becommeth thee to tread a degrée farre
aboue thy fortunes, a star to high for thée to gaze at. Kings
as they are men before the gods, so are they gods before
men: such high personages as wee must honor with our
lookes, not attempt with our loues: Why but Argentina
he loues thee, he is inamored of thy beauty, hee sues with
wordes, and intreates with his eyes: What then: cannot
such great Princes be sooner pensick then passionate:
weare fauour in their mouthes, when they haue flatterie
in theyr harts: Dooth not loue hang in their eye-lyddes,
which as it is taken in with euery looke, so tis shaken off
with euery winke: is not their fancies like the Somers
dew, which scarce wetteth the grasse before it bee dryed
vp with the Sunne? take heed Aagentina, Princes haue
liberties and priuiledges, they can laugh out faultes,
which wee must pay with pennalties: Wee hold Venus
for a Goddesse, they neuer offer her incense nor sacrifice:

and yet they no sooner craue, but she is ready to graunt:
yea but hath sworne ah fond foole, Periuria ridet Amantum
Iupiter: Louers oaths are like fetters made of glasse that
glister faire, but couple in restraint: if swearing had made
loue perfect, Carthage had possest Eneas for their King:
Phillis had not hangd her selfe, nor Medea said Deteriora
sequor, yet men must be credited, els shall loue be a shadow:
talkt of, but not put in execution: all are not Sons
to Anchisis, nor brothers to Iason, nor traitors like Demophon:
Philomenes face bewraies his faith, &amp; me thinkes
his looks containe loyalty: Thus poore wench doo I perswade
my selfe to the best, whereas perhaps he meanes
but to sport with me to make triall of my wit, well if it be
so, I wil endeuor to loue him lesse thē I doo, but if he mean
truth, I will labour to loue him more then I haue done:
and with this she rested content, &amp; went abroad to find out
the rest of the Ladies. Argentina had not serued her selfe
thus in secret, but Philomenes was as solitary: for getting
himselfe vp into his Study, then setting down his head on
his hand, &amp; his elbow on his book, he began thus to debate
with himselfe. Philomenes thou hast read much &amp; reapt
litle, that at one look hast learnd more, thē in seauen yeres
study thou couldst discouer: Hermes told thée that beauty
was a star, whose influence had sundry effects, this was
Allegorical, &amp; thou didst only passe it ouer for a principle.
Auicen said that loue was a fury, how didst thou estéeme
of this but as an axiome: Epictetus called Venus the restlesse
planet, thou tookest this for a dart: &amp; Amphibological
Aphorisme comments thou hadst none, and conceiue thou
couldst not: but now if Hermes, Auicen, or Epictetus want
interpreters, let amorous Schollers be auditours to my
precepts: for I haue found beauty a star, and haue gazd against
it: Loue is a fury for it is full of passions, &amp; Venus
a restlesse starre, for since the Goddesse distilled into my
thoughts her precious Balms, the opperation hath béen so
mighty, as my greatest rest hath béene restlesse disquiet,

what néed these ambigues, this schollerisme, this foolery,
thou art in loue with Argentina, the cōmanders daughter
of Corinth, a Duke, but thy Subiect: why then doost thou
vse preambles &amp; protestations? canst thou not say flatly I
am in loue, Venus Cofers when they haue the greatest
found, are alwaies most empty: &amp; louers when they prattle
most, are thought either great talkers, or déepe flatterers:
then Philomenes discouer thy mind, Argentina is a
woman, &amp; therfore to be wooed, &amp; so to be won: Kings may
command, where poore men cannot intreat: tis better to
name a crowne then to write a Letter: an ounce of giue
me, is worth a pound of heare me: the name of Quéen is a
great argument, &amp; therfore feare not: thou hast as much to
be liked, as she to be loued. Thus far wel Philomenes, but
suppose she hath already setled her affection, &amp; hath made
choise of some other: séeke not to diuert her, for she that is
faithles to one, will be constant to none, if thou loue her,
wish her not to be disloyall, but rather paune thy life, then
disparage her honor, &amp; wrastle with Loue, whom if thou
subdue: thou extéemst a glorious conquest. In this resolution
he flung out of his chamber, and passing into the priuy
Garden, there he found all the Ladies sparfeled abroad in
sundry borders, som gathering flowers, others in discourses
of the excellency of the place, some in prattle with the
birds, all busie, none idle: taking thus a superficial view of
them all, as hauing his eye wandring for a fairer obiect:
he passed forward to finde out if it might be the Lody Argentina,
whom he spied with her mother in a shady walke
of the Garden: seeing non but thē two, thither went Philomenes
&amp; saluted them in this maner: Honorable Dutches,
well accompanied with your faire daughter, the Mother
happy for bearing so swéete a creature, &amp; Argentina fortunate
in cōming from such a parent: your walking in this
shady Arbour resembles Latona, tripping with her train,
Diana in the Lamns, where hauing her self tried the forwardnes
of Esculapius her husband: she schoold her daughter,

so that Diana vowed perpetual chastity: I hope Lady
that ye Duke Pelopidus, brooks not company with Esculaus,
&amp; therfore you néede not nusle vp your daughter in such
heresie: The Dutches hearing the yong Prince so plesant
being her selfe a Lady of merry disposition, made him this
answer. Lord Pilomenes, were I Latona indéed &amp; as waspish
in minde, as ready as she to reuenge: I would cause
Phebus to chastice your frumps as he did the sons of Mobae,
in loding my back with such reuerence, &amp; my daughter
with such beauty, to your strange supposition, as far as
Pelopides differs from Esculapius: so far was mine from
Latonas perswasion, so beléeue me sir, if Roses be not gathered
in the bud, they either wither or proue windfalls:
Maids must be married, least they be marred: if they be
coy &amp; sweare chastity, they oft wish and wil with secrecy,
youth is the subiect of loue, &amp; Siens that are grafted yong,
haue the surest ioynts, therefore so far am I from that austere
peruersnes of some mothers, that as yong as Argentine
is, if there were a man whom she could loue &amp; we like
of, they should neuer break off for yeeres. Philomenes hearing
how the Dutches desembled not, began thus to reply:
&amp; what manner of man should he be that might both
content you &amp; please your daughter? the one measuring by
age, the other be youth: I would haue him, quoth the Dutches,
to be of age answerable to my daughters yéeres, and
his parētage proportioned to his parentage, least inequality
of time or birth might bréed mischeefe, his personage
such as might féed her eye, his vertues such as might plese
vs both, his liuing answearable to all these, &amp; him would
I count a fit husband for Argentina. A right conclusion
quoth Philomenes, for there is no match yt is right made if
pelfe conclude not the premises: if he had ye age of Adon,
the honors of Hercules, ye proportiō of Theseus, the vertues
of yeboy, yet si nil attuleris ibis Homere foras, if he haue not
liuing, al his loue is laid in ye dust: but what say you Argē
                     tina,
in faith let me as your gostly father, haue you at shrift

before your mother, tel me were you neuer in loue: Argentina
blusht &amp; was silent, as one that durst not be bold
before her mother: whereupon Philomenes said, see Madam,
tis your presence makes your daughter so squemish,
I pray you pratle with some other of the Ladies, &amp; giue vs
leaue a litle to be secret héere in this walk, perhaps I wil
be a suter to your daughter, what say you Madam, shal I
haue your good wil? I, &amp; my good word my Lord quoth she,
if you meant earnestly: &amp; with that smiling she went her
way &amp; left them to thēselues: Philomenes seeing himselfe
thus alone with his Goddesse, thought to take hold of her
mothers last words &amp; frō thē to driue his insinuation thus.
               You heare swéet Saint how fauourably your Mother
speakes, now Madam what censure shall I haue at your
hands? I cānot paint out many passions, not tel tales with
such large periods as many vse to doo, but I wil court thée
and woo thée in one word, &amp; that is Argentina I loue thée,
more I cannot promise, and so much I will performe by
the faith of a Prince: Argentina séeing Philomenes speak
so plainly, &amp; therfore as she thought so faithfully made this
answer: my Lord, you take the antecedent of my mothers
answer for a fouor, but you leaue out the consequent: and
that is if you meane in earnest, for I cannot thinke youe
grace would look so low as vpō 
                  Argentina, but rather gaze
at some glorious princesse, whose Maiesty might match
Iuno, whose worthines Pallas, whose beauty venus, &amp; with
these might bring for her dowry a Diadem: but? &amp; with
that Argentina staid &amp; blusht: which Philomenes espied,
&amp; therfore wringing her by the hand said: but, what Madam,
nay forward with the rest or you proffer me great
wrong: why then my Lord, quoth she, and with that shee
gald him with a glance: but if your honor would vouchsafe
to fauor such a simple maid, as from a meane Lady to
make her a Quéene: for other thē mariage I dare sweare
your Lordship dooth not intend: your Father gracing our
loues with his Kingly consent, though I could not with

loue sufficient request loue: as in person &amp; parentage vnfit
for your highnes, yet would I with obedience and humility
make supply of these defects which otherwise were
wanting. This answer of Argentina so contented Philomenes,
as that hee stoode as a man in a trance, at last hee
tooke her hand in his, and swore, that before the feast were
ended he wold make her princesse of Corinth, let this suffise
Argentina, qd. he, &amp; with that he sealed vp the bargain
with a kisse, and walked towardes her Mother, to whom
he deliuered Argentina thus: Madam here I deliuer your
daughter as safe as I receiued in outwarde appearance,
but how I haue schoold her, time will make trial, perhaps
we haue strooke the match, and therfore let the Lorde Pelopidus
prouide a good dowrie, and with that he went his
way: when the matter comes to that effect my Lord, you
shall haue a dukedome with her: at that the Prince turnd
back and said, thats mine already, and her Father is like
to bee my subiect, and so to holde his liuing in cheefe: the
Dutchesse smilde, &amp; thus they parted. But leauing Philomenes
to the King his Father, who hauing noted as narrowly
as his sonne, the beauty of Argentina, had great lyking
of the Lady, so that he made inquirie of those which
were Pelopidus neerest neighbours, what disposition the
virgin was of, they all affirmed to the King that shee was
so vertuous, humble, curteous, and adorned with such excellent
qualities, as the fourme of her life was a methode
wherby other Gentlewomen did direct their actions. The
King hearing this, resolued in his minde there coulde not
be a fitter match for his Sonne, whervpon determining to
break with the yong Prince, as he was in this humor, hée
met Philomenes whom he tooke aside, and began to question
him as concerning Argentina, whether hee could fancy
the Lady or no. Philomenes afraide the King had espyed
their loues, made answer, that he neuer tooke such narrow
view of her that he could yéeld his iudgement with affection:
then doo qd. the King, and giue me within two daies
an answer, and so he departed. Philomenes ioyfull of this,

no sooner met Argentina, but he told what motion his Father
had made, but to make a smal haruest of a little crop:
Philomenes at the two daies end so answered his Father,
that the King breaking with the Duke, it was concluded
that the end of the feast should be the beginning of ye marriage,
which was such a ioy to the nobles to see their yong
Prince allied in his owne Land, that they deuised newe
Iustes and pastimes, continuing the feast many dayes to
their great ioy, and the Louers most happy content: The
mariage and the feast thus finished, the Nobles departed,
Pelopidus leauing his daughter thus honorably espoused,
took this leaue, the maried couple staying still with the old
King in his Court, who being of great age, liued not long
after, but paide his debt vnto nature, so that Philomenes
was crowned King of Corinth: Liuing thus happily with
his wife Argentina, thinking his degrée too high for Fortune
to preiudice, it so fell out, that Marcion the King of
Sycilia, hearing that his ancient enemy Philomenes father
was dead, thought to try what mettall was in the sonne,
to proue if he were as valiant and fortunate as his father,
therfore he leauied a great Army &amp; prouided a great fléete
to saile to Corinth, which was no sooner rigged but he imbarqued
his men, and as soone as wind &amp; weather woulde
permit, sailed towards Corinth, where arriuing in a Desert
place, as politick to land without any great resistāce:
he vnshipt his men, and all his furniture for war: and letting
his Nauie ride in the road, hee marched forward into
the maine land, vsing as one yt intended a conquest, fire &amp;
sword, Philomenes hearing by Postes how Marcion was
landed with a mighty Hoast, and had spoiled many of his
prouinces, started vp, &amp; summoning his Lords about him,
raised a mighty hoast, such as neuer King of Corinth dyd
before him, and with thē marched to meet with Marcion,
whom he incountred by the Riuer yt runneth by the great
plaines called the Corinth downes: then pitching his pauilion,
he intrenched his Army, and so had Marcion fortified
his: lying thus a while, at last by Heralts they resolued

vpon a day of battaile, which once come &amp; both the Armies
rangd: they ioynd battaile so furiously, the one to cō
                  quer,
the other to defend: Philomenes hart made one with
equitie, the other with dispaire, that a long while ye fight
was doubtfull, till at last fortune allotted the best to Marcion,
in such sort that the fielde was his, the Corinthians
most slaine, some fledde, the King valiantly fighting, taken
prisoner: Marcion triumphing in the victory, marched forwardes
to the Citty leading Philomenes as his Captiue:
comming to the gates, ye Cittizens yéelded vp the keyes, &amp;
he as a valiant conquerour entred, &amp; passing into the pallace,
found there the Queene all blubbred with feares, as
a woman almost sencelesse, whom he comforted and committed
to ye custodie of one of his Duke: seated thus victoriously
in Corinth, he not onely disgraded the King from
all dignitie, but disrobing him, commanded that he should
be turnd out of the pallace, and that he should not be reléeued
vpon paine of death, but if he would haue any thing to
satis-fie his thirst, he should gette it with his handythrift:
Philomenes not abashed at this doome, intreated the King
to be good to his wife, and so went and became a labourer
for day wages, contented with this fortune: Marcion the
next day sent for the Queene, who although forlorne with
teares, yet nothing her narrowly, hee found her the fayrest
creature that euer yet in his life he had viewed, so that hée
fell extreamly in loue with her, and offered her what lyberty
or pleasure shee would haue, courting her with many
faire promises and amorous conceits, but all in vaine,
for shee was resolued whatsoeuer fell, life or death, yt none
to her but her loue Philomenes: Marcion captiuated in her
beauty, was restlesse, féeling such strange &amp; vncouth passions,
that at last he fell into these termes.
               What fond motions Marcion are these that disturbe thy
mind? what childish thoughts vnfit for a king, a souldier,
nay for one that hath conquered both a Crowne and kingdom:
thou camst from Sycilia to be victor, &amp; heere thou art
arriued &amp; not vanquished, thou hast beaten Philomenes in

battaile, &amp; art brought vnder by his wife in loue, thy resolution
was to terrifie thy foes with thy sword, so thou hast
don, but faine to please a woman with thy tongue: by this
fond foolery I may note, yt 
                  Venus frowne is of more force
then the weapons of Mars, that affections are harder to be
supprest then enemies to subdue: that loue is aboue King
and keiser, where Cupid commaunds, there dignity hath
no priuiledge to withstand: then Marcion yéelde, sue and
intreat, but whom, the wife of Philomenes thy captiue, rather
commaund her, and what shee will not yeelde by intreaty,
take by constraint: in so dooing should I reape infamy,
and forced loue is neuer swéete: no Marcion allure
her with wealth, promise she shal be thy paramore, to seat
her next thy selfe in thy kingdome, women are won with
fauors, and there is none so chast but time and gifts may
intice. In this resolution he sent for Argentina, &amp; beganne
thus to deliuer his minde vnto her. Thus seest Argentina,
how I haue fauourd thée, no like a Princesse that were
captiue, but euen as a Quéene that is sole mistres and soueraigne
of my affections, thy beauty hath cōquered that
hart which had made conquest of thy Country, &amp; subdued
him who before, womans feature neuer vanquished: then
Argentina take pitty of him that for thy loue is so passionate,
consent that I may enjoy thée as my paramour, and
thou shalt be honourd as shée that is best loued of the King
of Sycilia, I could Argentina y• seest obtaine by force what
I sue for by intreatie: but I couet rather to possesse my
selfe of thy louely consent, then by constraint: yéeld therefore
what I request, and héere before the Lords of Sycilia,
I promise to grant whatsoeuer thou shall commaund, so it
touch not my Crowne nor thy Husbande, though to the
danger of my person, fréely without exception: Argentina
as one nothing dismaid, returnd him this answere: I not
deny Marcion thou hast subdued Corinth, and deposed the
King, which I attribute rather to his bad fortunes, then
thy prowesse or chiualrie, but in all thy conquest thou shalt
neuer boast thou hast conquered either Philomenes or hys

wife Argentina, séeing we are only ouercom, not vanquished:
in that both of vs remaine contented, and kéepe our
minds vntoucht: thou art inchaunted with my loue, no
Marcion, but perhaps thou art fed with lust, &amp; neuer hope
that Argentina will minister any meanes to appease the
flame: although thou shouldst inforce her to consent by the
most extreame torments: Philomenes liues, &amp; so long wil
&amp; loue: not thée, but him whom I vowed to be true vnto
for euer: yet thy last condition hath somwhat perswaded
me, that if thou graunt what I request, I will consent not
only to be thy paramour but thine for euer: the king was
so glad of this, that he iterated with an oath to performe
her demauud: then this it is quoth Argentina: Tomorrow
morning thou shalt shut thy selfe into a secret place,
wherof my selfe wil kéepe the key, &amp; there for thrée dayes
thou shalt fast, without tasting any thing so aslake hunger
or thirst: this time thou shalt pray to the Gods for the remission
of our sinns which we shal offend in by breach of
matrimony, then at the terme of thrée days thou shalt fréely
take the vse of my body before thou eat any meat, otherwise
if thou faile but as much as Proserpina to taste a
graine of the pomgranet, thou shalt neuer after question
me of loue: thus doo, and I grant to like thée, or els here is
my head, let that pay my raunsom: Marcion was so setted
in her beauty, that he thought it nothing to vndertake this
taske, and therfore promised before his Lords to fast three
daies, and then to lye with her before he eat any meat, or
els neuer to motion her any more of loue: whereupon the
next day the Princesse shut him vp till the date was expired,
in which thrée dayes he felt such torments, such pinching
hunger and extreme thirst, that he cursed loue, and
exclaimed against beauty as a charme yt made men senceles,
willing to giue for one crum the Diadem of Corinth▪
                  
well the terme expired, all the Nobles were assembled &amp;
sat in the great hall, expecting what euent shold fall either
of ye kings fast, or of Argentinas request: at last Argentina
sent the key to one of the Lords, that the king might come

into the Hall whether she presently would repaire: the
Lord went to the chamber doore and no sooner put the key
to the lock, but Marcion started vp and cryed for meat, the
Lord vnlockt and saw the king glance at him with such a
fierce looke, that he was afraid and started back: villaine
quoth Marcion, hast thou brought me any meat, and with
that running as a mad man into the hall, flinging in fury
among the Lords: Why Gentiles (quoth he) sit you héere
without meat? why are not the tables spread? doo I allow
such niggardly allowance, or wil you famish him that fostereth
you all? At this he was in a rage, Argentina apparailed
in her richest robes, came pacing, that she looked
more like an Angell, then a mortall creature, insomuch
that euery eye directed their glaunces at so heauenly an
obiect, except Marcion, who at her sight sat as a man greatly
amated: hauing her mayde followe her with a dish of
meat crumd: Argentina with a smiling countenance taking
him by the hand, sayd thus.
               Redoubted Conquerour, according to promise I am
come in the presence of these Lords to offer my self subiect
to your highnes plesure, ready to goe whither your grace
shal conduct me: Marcion at this cried out, &amp; thinkst thou
Argentina that famisht men haue minde on beauty, or is
hunger to be satisfied with loue? no, no, tis true Marcion,
Sine Cerere &amp; baco friget Venus, reason could not subdue
lust, but fasting hath set it on a non plus: but what is that
the mayde carries? meat my Lord quoth she for your honour
after, and with that she blusht: Marcion no sooner
heard her name meate, but he leapt to the mayde, puld away
the dish, saying: farwel fond loue, and welcome that
wherof one morsel is worth a monarchy, Argentina giue
me leaue to eate, for thou hast conquered Marcion in his
own folly, and with that he fell to his meat, wherwith after
he had somewhat appeased his hunger, sitting him in
his seat royal, he began to parle with his Lords of Argentinas
pollicy, highly extolling the constancy of so true a
wife, and so far entred into consideration of the chaunce of

fortune, and fall of Princes, that rising from his throne,
he went and embraced and kist Argentina, not only praising
her for her redy inuention to perswade him from his
vanity, but for her sake sent for her husband, and yéelded
him his Crowne and his Kingdome, and liuing his sworn
friend, returned home into Sycilia.
               
               NO sooner had Arion ended his tale, but Mars taking
opportunity, said: we sée by this euent, that as women
haue their vanities whereby to be checked, so they haue
their vertues redounding greatly to their praise: beeing
both affable and constant, although that single instance of
Orpheus his Lidia did inferre the contrary: And so quoth
Apollo would Venus serue for an instance if you mean of
constancy, for no doubt if you may be iudge, al beauty shal
be vertue, &amp; all women shal be Saints: &amp; now quoth Iupiter,
Apollo by your leaue to take Mars his part, we oft
rightly to think of women, seeing so oft we seeke their fauors,
&amp; speak to them by intreaties for their loues, otherwise
we should proue our selues very ingrate: to beat thē
with rods, that feast vs with banquets, to proffer them
Scorpions that giues vs no worse then their own selues:
Liuely spokē quoth Mercury, but Iuno likes you neuer the
better for this flattery, as supposing you haue sued to more
then contented her, or becommed you: but in my opinion,
Arions tale paints out a paragon, a matchles mirrour, as
wel for constancy, as the other for cruelty: these extremes
therfore infer no certain cōclusions, for they leaue a mean
betwéene both, wherein I think the nature of women doo
consist, neither so cruel but they wil grant, nor so constant
but they will yeeld, &amp; rather oft-times proue too curteous
then too vnkind: Sée quoth Mars how péeuishly you conclude,
to taunt them still of vnconstancy: well Mercury,
quoth he, thou art subtill, &amp; canst by thy fallacions prooue
what thou wilt: but yet this I set down for mine own opinion,
that women the more beautiful they are, the more
curteous, the more constant, ye fuller of excelent qualities:

and rather vertues, and by the Riuer of Stycks I swere,
and with that he rose in a choller, this I will approoue against
him that dare maintaine the contrary: though not
with my pen, yet my sword: at this the Gods smild, and
Mars in such a rage clapt his hand on the boord: that I awoke,
not knowing what became of the Gods or of Arions
soule, only I remembred their tales.
               BEing thus awakt, I lookt about mee, and still sate my
Shepheard: how now good fellow, quoth I, haue I not
taken a lusty nap? thy Pipe sounded so swéetly, and there
I had such a dreame as I would not haue lost for much,
for I hope it wil after more profit me then all my iourny,
I haue past to Erecinus: I am glad quoth the Shepheard,
my pipe did thée so much pleasure, and if thy slumber hath
presented thée any visions, note them, for al dreames that
men sée in Erecinus, prooue true: and with that standing
vp, me thought he had wings on his head, shoulders, and
féete: he bad me farwell, &amp; tooke his flight: then I knewe
it was Mercury. Whereupon, calling to mind the occasion
of my iourney: I found that either I had lost loue, or
loue lost me: for my passions were eased, I left Erecinus
and hasted away as fast as I could, glad that one dreame
had rid me of fancy, which so long had fettred me,
yet could I not hie so fast, but ere I could
get home, I was ouertaken
with repentance.
               FINIS.
               
                  Robert Greene.
               
               
            
         
      
   

