
   
      
         
            The burthen of tyre A sermon preach'd at Pauls Crosse, by Iohn Grent, then fellow of New Colledge in Oxford.
            Grent, John.
         
         
            
               1627
            
         
         Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02225
            STC 12360.3
            ESTC S118299
            99853506
            99853506
            18890
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02225)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18890)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 888:15)
         
         
            
               
                  The burthen of tyre A sermon preach'd at Pauls Crosse, by Iohn Grent, then fellow of New Colledge in Oxford.
                  Grent, John.
               
               [4], 44 p.   
               
                  Printed [by A. Mathewes] for Richard Royston,
                  London :
                  1627.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  A variant of the edition with Grismand's name in imprint.
                  Identified as STC 12360a on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-10
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-11
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE BVRTHEN OF TYRE.
A Sermon Preach'd at Pauls Croſſe, By IOHN GRENT, then Fellow of New-Colledge in Oxford.
            
            ISAI. 28. 1. 
            
               Woe to the Crowne of Pride,—
            
            
            LONDON, Printed for RICHARD ROYSTON.
            1627.
         
         
            
            
            TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED PATRON, SIR THOMAS HOLT, Knight and Baronet, the comforts of Grace here, and a Crowne of glory hereafter.
            
               SIR,
            
            
               THis diſcourſe preſumeth, now it aduentureth the Preſſe, on the Patronage it had, when it paſſed the Pen. The Author of it well knoweth, and euer will acknowledge, his deepe engagements for your many fauours: one principall, (a comfort to your ſoule, that conferr'd it, as to his, that receiu'd it,) the faire, and free entrance,

to the exerciſe of his Miniſtery. VVhich one, and the reſt, hee can no way anſwere, but by his Prayers to God, and hearty deſires, for the encreaſe of all happineſſe, and honour, to you, and yours; and this he will not ceaſe to doe, while hee remembreth himſelfe to be
            
               Your much bounden,
IOHN GRENT.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE BVRTHEN of TYRE.
            
               ISAI 23. 7. 8. 9.
               
                  7. Is this your ioyous Citie, whoſe Antiquitie is of ancient dayes? Her owne feete ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
                  8. Who hath taken this counſell againſt Tyre, the crowning City, whoſe Merchants are Princes, whoſe Traffiquers are the Honorable of the earth?
                  9. The Lord of Hoaſts hath purpoſed it, to ſtaine the pride of all glory, and to bring into contempt all the Honourable of the Earth.
               
            
            
               THe ſound of Warre in a time of peace is like a ſhowre of raine, when the Sunne ſhineth; mention of Feare in the height of fauour as the curſings of Mount Ebal among the bleſſings of mount Gerizim. Beſt ſuteable vnto theſe Halcyonian dayes would bee the

Oliue leafe of peace in the Doues mouth, and to men lull'd aſleepe in Securities lapp welcome ſoft Pillowes ſewen vnder their elbowes. But while Mercy is thus our deſire, Miſery may be our deſert; and when we looke for a Barnabas, a ſon of conſolation, we may meete with a Boanerges, a ſonne of Thunder. As we receiue good things at Gods hands, ſo we muſt euill; the acts of his Iustice ſhould no more diſcontent vs, then of his Mercy, for he is aequally glorified in them both: and therefore, if this be the Burthen of Tyre, for ought I know, theres no remedy, but Tyre muſt heare it, Tyre muſt beare it. Is this your ioyous Citie, whoſe Antiquity is of ancient dayes? her owne feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ioiourne, &amp;c.
            
            Loe heere

                  1 Tyres glory, and
                  
                  2 Her Iudgement.
               
Her glory lyeth
            Firſt, in her Antiquity, which was of auncient dayes.
            
            Secondly, in her preſent flouriſhing eſtate, a ioyous Citie, a crowning City, grac'd not onely with her owne, but alſo with Forraiue dignity, Chapmen as well as Merchants, her Merchants at home Princes, her Chapmen from abroad, The honorable of the earth.
            
            Her iudgement is ſet forth
            Firſt, by the forme and manner of it.
            Secondly, by its cauſes.
            The forme and manner of it in theſe words, Her owne feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne, Wherein three degrees:
            
               
               1 Baniſhment, ſhe ſhould be carried to ſoiourne.
               
               2 Pouertie, her owne feet ſhould carry her.
               
               3 Remoteneſſe of place, a farre off.
               
            
            The cauſes of this iudgement are three.
            
               1 The efficient cauſe.
               2 The impulſiue cauſe.
               3 The finall cauſe.
            
            Firſt, the efficient, or Author of it, The Lord of Hoaſts: Hee tooke this counſell againſt Tyre; Hee it was that purpoſed it.
            Secondly, the impulſiue, or that that mooued him to it, Pride and Glory.
            
            Thirdly, the finall, or ende wherefore he did it, to ſtaine the pride of that glory, and then (a degree farther) to bring into contempt all the Honorable of the earth.
            
            Theſe branches, and in this order, (with Gods gracious aſsiſtance) implore my paines and your patience, and in the firſt place, the former part of Tyres glory, her Antiquity, which was (ſaith my Prophet) of ancient dayes.
            
            So paſt the Records of memory was this Cities 
                  Tyres glory. 1 Her Antiquity. Original, that eitherlike, Fame,-Caput inter nubila condit, it ſeemes muffled and wrapt in the clouds, and you may as well find the head of Nilus fountaine, as of Tyres foundation; or els, you muſt needs make her one of the eldeſt daughters of the new World, euen the ſtructure and worke of Tyras, laphets ſonne. For whereas Ioſephus ſeemeth to giue her birth but 240. yeeres before Solomons Temple, to wit, in Gedeons time, and Iuſtin only before the ſacke of Troy, about Iepthas time, (both making Sidon the faire mother of Tyre a
               
farre fairer daughter) they are rather to be vnderſtood of her reaedifying and repayring, then of her firſt founding; for ſure, her Antiquity was of more ancient dayes. But though it were, yet it ill became her proudly to vaunt of it, and thereupon to contemne her bordering neighbours; as it would ill beſeeme this Famous Citie vainely to brag of her Antiquitie, or of her Founder Brute, father of Britany, who (tis thought) in olde Eli's time, was King in England, before there was any King in Iſrael. Indeed Antiquity, in ſome mens eyes, carries a very faire ſhew, and like a Perſpectiue, maketh the obiect ſeeme bigger then truly it is, hauing that to bragge off, they care for no more. If they can but ſay, Tyre the ancient City Tyre. Rome the ancient City Rome; they thinke, that muſt preſently ſweepe all away before it, as did Kiſhon, that ancient Riuer Kiſhon, Iudg. 5. 21. But in true iudgement, it little skils, how olde, how ancient a Citie is, rather how holy, how honeſt, how vpright, how iuſt, how pleaſing to God, and how profitable to men. Therefore, as Apollo being demanded by the Athenians, which Religion was the beſt? Anſwered, the ancienteſt; and a ſecond time, which was the ancienteſt? replyed that that was beſt? So ſay I of Cities, which is the beſt? the Ancienteſt: Which is the ancienteſt? the beſt: For antiquity, is to be meaſured by goodneſse, not goodneſse by antiquity, elſe might youthinke well of the Deuill, he can pleadage, an olde Serpent, a Lier from the beginning. Tis true, very ancient was Tyre, and long

was it, ere ſhe came to the height of her glory; but here was her miſery, her ſinne grew vp as faſt as her ſelfe; ſhe was no elder in age, then in euill: and therefore, the longer ſhee had ſetled, with Moab, on the lecs of wickedneſſe, the more need to be powred out from veſſell to veſſell; the longer the blade of her iniquitie had beene growing, the riper, and the readier to bee cut downe with the ſickle of vengeance. The harueſt of whoſe Woe, when our Prophet foreſawe, he laughs and ſcoffes at her, by way of deriſion, Is this your ioyous City? (not ſo much wondring at her ruine, or pitying her miſery, as indeed inſulting ouer her calamity, and vpbrayding her pride, the cauſe of her fall) Is this your tryumphing, glorying, flaunting, flouriſhine Citie? that ſo drew the worlds eyes to looke on her? that was ſo much admir'd by them that vſed Traffique with her? that ſo vaunted of her Antiquitie, as if the Rocke, on which ſhe had long ſtood, could neuer be moued? See, ſee, whither her glorying is now come, Her owne feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne. Tis not her ancientnes that can Patronize her from heauens vengeance, no nor yet her preſent flouriſhing eſtate, though a ioyous City, a crowning City; whoſe Merchants are Princes, and her Chapmen the Honourable of the Earth: the ſecond part of Tyres glory, and in the ſecond place ſaluteth your attention.
            2 Very excellent things are ſpoken of this renowned 2 Her preſent flour ſhing eſtate. City, and yet no more then her pompe and glory might ſometime iuſtly challenge; they

that dwelt in her, and that dealt in Traffique with her, were ſo enrich'd (ſaith my Prophet) by her Merchandiſe, that they came not behind the greateſt Perſonages of the earth, Kings, Princes, Nobles. Famous may be the Merchants of Venice, Florence, Antwerpe, but theſe of Tyre ſurpaſt them all; the admiration of whoſe wealth and glory brought forth the word Tyrant (King, then noting Maieſty, not cruelty) ſo that Cyneas Pyrrhus his Embaſſadour, might farre better haue call'd Tyre then Rome, Ciuitatem regum, A City of Kings. What place in the world could ſhow ſuch a Shop of Wares, as ſhee doth, Ezek. 27? Which the City that ſo had the harneſt of the Riuer for her reuenewe, and was her ſelfe a Mart of Nations, verſ. 3. of this Chap? Where, (ſince the Deluge) but in her, and Sodom could you ſee an Eden, and garden of God, as ſhee is called, Ezek. 28. 13? Whoſe Prince, but hers, was ſtiled The annointed Cherub, that couereth, that was vpon the holy Mountaine of God, and walked vp and downe in the midſt of the ſtones of fire? Ezek. 28, 14. What City, but this Tyre could haue ſo dazled the eyes of the Eaſterne World, as to put her owne name on a whole Region Tyria, or Syria? Once, what place, beſides her, could haue ſtood in aemulation with that Queene of Nations, and Lady of Kingdomes, the perfection of beauty, and ioy of the whole earth, Ieruſalem? and make her ſelfe, as much frequented for wealth, as Ieruſalem for religion? and yet all this, and more too; is true of that crowning Citie, whoſe Merchants

were Princes, and her Chapmen the honorable of the earth. Which gay trimming of Tyre, with ſo ſpecious priuiledges makes a man thinke her a peereleſſe Princeſſe, Paragon of beauty, faire Eſter; but loe, a Harlot dreſt in ſtrange apparell, by a flattering glaſſe, painted Iezabel: outward ornament enough, wealth, and glory, and pompe, and maieſtie, like the rayment of Needle worke the Kings Daughter wore; and like the Veſture of gold wrought about with diuers colours, but none of that which ſhould make her all glorious within, and cauſe his Maieſtie take pleaſure in her beauty, pure Religion, holines of life, practiſe of vertuous actions. Which Pearle of price (the one thing neceſſary) when our Prophet ſeeth neglected, and yet other ſeeming Iewels (of little or no value) much ſet by, he can tell Tyre, that her temporall bleſſings, without bleſſings ſpirituall, are but a faire preface to foule ruine; and therefore if hee can finde nothing elſe to commend her by, but that her Antiquity is of ancient dayes, &amp; that ſhe is a ioyous City, a crowning City, whoſe Merchants are Princes, and her Chapmen the Honourable of the earth, he will giue her anone a moſt heauie doome, her owne feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
            
            O conſider this, and lay it to heart, all ye that inhabite the like ioyous Citie, (for who, in this point of flouriſhing Eſtate, ſees not Londons face in Tyres looking glaſſe?) Flatter not your ſelues with your wealth and pompe, like her Merchants, as if you (forſooth) were Gods onely Fauourits, and your Fleece alone, like Gedeons,
               
wet with the dew of heauen, and all the ground drie round about. Dreame not of ſecure poſſeſſing the Fortunate Iſlands, nor of being begirt with the Sea, and hemmd in with watry walles from all danger; Think not by heaping togeather thicke clay, and therewith building your neſt on high; you ſhall eſcape wrath and iudgement to come. Know rather that the Chriſtian Armour, Faith and Rightcouſnes, and the Churches Weapons, Prayers and Teares, muſt be your beſt bulwarke againſt deſtruction. If you would bee couered with the defence of the moſt high, and be ſafe vnder the ſhadow of the Almighty, be ſure, ſuch ſhelter is not procur'd by your glorious pompe, and ruffling pride, but by your fearing God &amp; keeping his Cōmandements. Strangers eyes can witnes a daily increaſe of your outward glory, ô that wee could ſee in you the like growth of inward grace; we walk about your Siō, &amp; go round about her, we tel the towers therof, &amp; note her Temples, we mark wel her bulwarks, and ſet vp her houſes, that wee may acquaint them that ſhall come hereafter, and the children that are yet vnborne; but wee had farre rather take notice of your piety, charity, ſobriety toward God, your Neighbours, and your ſelues; without which, all your pomp in the ende, will proue but vanitie and vexation of ſpirit. You haue lately extended your Cities wings, as if you ment to make her fly ouer a good part of this Iſland, and by ſumptuous buildings haue perfected her beautie; you haue enlarg'd your roome, encreas'd your border, ioynd houſe to houſe at home, procur'd goodly Colonies abroad; you firſt

get the riches of the Kingdome, then her honors; long may you enioy both, if you be firme friends to God and goodnes. Your courſe of Trading is pleaſing to the Lord, and your Merchandiſe bleſt if you make not ſhipwracke of a good Conſcience. Not onely the Kingdome of heauen is like a Merchant man, ſeeking goodly pearles, Mat. 13. But euen the Church is a Ship of Merchants, fetching her food from far, Pro. 31. Buying and ſelling are the nerues and ſinewes of a Kingdome, exerciſes not misbeſeeming the Saints of God: Ioſeph was a Merchant of Corne; Lydia a ſeller of Purple, Dauid bought a floore, and Ieremy a field. But yet amids your great dealing, &amp; traffique in the world, let me put you in mind of two ſorts of Merchāts, moſt odious among you. Merchants of Time, and merchants of the Tēple: of Time, Vſurers; of the Temple, Church-robbers; Time &amp; Tēple are both Gods wares, therefore take heed ô man, of ſetting to ſale, what is none of thine own. Wilt thou, that canſt not, with all thy wealth purchaſe an houres additiō vnto thy life, yet offer to ſel a yere to thy neighbor for ten in the hūdred? wilt thou, whoſe own ſoule muſt be ſaued by the conſtant exerciſe of a painful Miniſtry, ſel thouſāds of ſouls to the deuil, by putting a hireling ouer the flock of Ch? Princes &amp; Nobles either ſhould not be ſuch broking merchants, or (I am ſure) ſuch broking merchāts are not Princes &amp; Nobles, but baſe degenerate perſons, that haue not the leaſt ſparke of true nobility in thē. He that is wiſe wil beware of ſuch trading for feare of the gold of Tolouſe, that will Aurum Tololoſanum. one day, bring ruine to him, and to his family.
            
               
From theſe ſacrilegious Merchants, tis but ſtepping a little aſide into the Shops of deceit, and a man meets with many others almoſt as pernicious: who ſucke ſuh ſweetnes of gaine, by vſing ſcant meaſure which is abominable, and wicked ballances, with the bag of falſe weights, Micah. 6. as alſo by vttering wares with oily words, and ſometime intermixing oathes and lyes, and aequiuocation about the prizes, that they will not be drawne from it, though (in moſt bargaines they make) they venture the wofull end of Ananias and Zaphira, Acts 5. (the firſt example of iudgement in the New Teſtament.) I can ſcarſe repeat it without trembling, Tell me, ſold you the Land for ſo much? Yea for ſo much. Doth your ware stand you in ſo much? Yea in ſo much. How is it that you haue conceiued this thing in your heart? you haue not lied vnto men, but vnto God; and you know what follow'd, both huſband and wife fell ſtraight way downe to the ground, and gaue vp the ghoſt. Tis to be hoped, there are not many Merchants, that deale in ſuch deceitfull manner, let thoſe that doe, take heede they, with their money, periſh not together. Howeuer, let the beſt, in the feare of God, examine their Trading, and in all bargaines they make, bee ſure to take Conſcience along with them. Let both Buyers and Sellers conſider, the ende of their commerce ſhould bee the vpholding one another, not the vndoing; therefore let theſe beware how and by what meanes, of Merchants, they make themſelues Princes, and thoſe how, and by what meanes of

               Chapmen they become the Honourable of the Earth. The riches of the Countrey (wee ſee) take the wings of the morning, and fly into the Citie: the whole Land emptieth her treaſure into your lapps, as all the Riuers doe their waters into the Sea: Looke therefore you vſe your abundance to Gods glory, and the aduancing of goodneſſe. The Metropolitan City is vſually the ſpleene of the Kingdome; the bigger the ſpleene, the leſſe and leaner all the body beſide; for the ones fulneſſe draweth the other to emptineſſe, which if it ſtill ſwell and ſwell, and purge not foorth (by good workes and almes-deedes) there muſt be ſome other remedy ſought; Leeches muſt be applied. You are but Stewards of the Riches you poſſeſſe, improue them therfore for your Maſters commodity, not for your owne pompe and brauery. Traffique hath brought you foorth Wealth, take heede Wealth bring not foorth Luxury; Luxury Pride, and Pride, Vengeance. Poore Tyre payeth for it; who, though when ſhe did wel, was accepted, yet afterward, when ſhe did ill, found iudgement lying at the doore. Her owne feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
            
            2 As while the Prophet continued piping, Tyre 
               2. Tyres iudgement. 1 The forme and manner of it. was content to daunce, ſo now hee beginns his mourning, ſhee may frame her ſelfe to weepe; It was ſweet Muſick in her eares to heare tell of her glory, it will be a ſharpe coraſiue, to her heart to heare mention of her iudgement. That diſtill'd downe like the hony, and the hony Combe, a ioyons City, a crowning City, whoſe Merchants are

Princes, and her Chapmen the Honourable of the earth; this goes downe like gall, and bitter Aloes. Her owne feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
            
            A ſharpe ſentence, and yet in its time ſeuerely put in execution; Twiſe was this Mother Citie in the power of the enemie; once layd waſt by Nebuchadnezzar, another time by Alezander: Tis the former blow that is here threatned, for Ezekiel who nameth Nebuchadnezzar, Ezekiel 26. Prophecieth there of the ſame thing, as heere doth Eſay. So it was, that that mighty Monarch hauing newly ſackt Ieruſalē, the crowning Citie of Iudea, ſoon ſet vpó her riual Tyre of the Tribe of Aſher: where after three yeares Siege, and ten months, (when Ithobalus was her King) at length killing, and carrying captiue Prince and people, hee aequall'd her to the ground, and ſo quite disfigured the face of a City, that for ſeuenty yeares together, ſhe was but a plaine for Fiſhermen to dry their Netts on. Till that time as Venice a Virgine City, becauſe neuer ouercome; euer after a Harlot, when her owne feete had once carried her a farre off to ſoiourne. And ſo iuſtly had ſhee deſerued ſuch her calamity, that God gaue Nebuchadnezzar a reward for inflicting it on her: Sonne of man, (ſaith he) Nebuchadnezzar, King of Babylon, cauſed his Army to ſerue a great ſeruice against Tyrus, yet had he no wages, nor his Army for Tyrus, for the ſeruice, that hee had ſerued againſt it; therefore (ſaith the Lord God) behold I will giue the Land of Egypt vnto Nebuchadnezzar King of Babylon, and hee

ſhall take her multitude, and take her ſpoyle, and take her prey, and it ſhall be the wages for his army, Eze. 29. 19. Thus when God puniſheth, he puniſheth to purpoſe; and yet the ſame GOD, before he puniſheth, vſeth to warne; Tyre ſhall downe becauſe ſhee will not repent, though hee hire Nebuchadnezzar to be the rod of his fury, and yet Tyre ſhall be warned, that ſhe may repent, many yeares before hand: in the one ſee Gods hate againſt ſinne, in the other his loue vnto the Sinner. The ſpeciall obiect of your thoughts, at this time, muſt be the latter, onely the warning, the thunder before the ſhowre, the threatning before the ſtroke, the ſhaking the rodd before the ſtripe; Tyres feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne; ſhall carry, haue not yet, but ſhall, if ſhee doe not repent. Repentance is a neceſſary Euangelicall condition, ſtill to be ſupplied, wheneuer God threatneth, and giueth ſpace for repentance. Suppoſe Nebuchadnezzar were already entred into Phoenicia, and euen now labouring to ioyne Tyre vnto the ſhore, from which it was diſtant ſeuen hundred paces, neuertheleſſe three yeares ſiedge, and ten moneths was (one would thinke) warning ſufficient, and yet Tyre had much more; for the Prophet dealeth not ſo roundly with her, as Ionas did with Niniue, Yet forty dayes and Niniue ſhall be deſtroid, but giueth her almoſt as much time to repent as Noah did the old world, well nigh a hundred yeares.
            O the patience and long ſuffering of the Almighty, ſo bearing with ſinners, and ſo willing

to ſpare, that hee would euen be glad to ſee his plagues preuented by our conuerſion; Thoſe hands of his that made the World, are not of a deſtructiue nature, deſirous to bring it to nought again, but ſtil labor to mend rather then to mar; and his heart is ſo enuironed with the bowels of compaſſion, that (as farre forth as Iuſtice will giue leaue) hee euer thinkes bloud better ſpard then ſpilt. When the Lord proceeds to mercy, he commeth forth merrily, as a Bridegroome out of his chamber, or as a Gyant that reioyceth to runne his courſe; Comfort yee, Comfort yee my people will your God ſay, ſpeake comfortably to Ieruſalem, Iſai. 40. 1. But when hee is forc't to take vengeance, he hangs backe, as vnwilling, and his ſoule ſeemes troubled within him, How ſhall I giue thee vp Ephraim? how ſhall I deliuer thee Iſrael? How ſhall I make thee as Admah? how ſhall I ſet thee as Zeboim? mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are rouled together. Hoſ. 11. 8. O that mercifull Father, with whom iudgement is a worke, but ſo ſtrange a worke, an act, but ſo ſtrange an act, Iſai. 28. 21 that hee can very hardly perſwade himſelfe to it! When hee was to Create, hee went about that moſt readily; Hee but ſpake, and things were done, hee but commanded, and they ſtood faſt; but, being to deſtroy, he deliberates, and he prepares, and he warnes, and hee threatens, and faine he would begin, but Mercy keeps him back; he holds vp his rod ready to ſtrike, and preſently flings it away from him; Hee now taketh vp the ſword into his hand, and by and by layeth

it downe againe; He drawes his arrrow to the head, and yet ſtopps before hee ſhootes: and though hee continually threaten vs from the skie with a bent bowe, yet tis ſuch a one (we ſee) as hath neuer a ſtring. Thus doth Mercy ouermaſter Iuſtice, and ſo works with the Almighty, that he ſeldome executes iudgement willingly; and when he doth, moſt leaſurely; he will haue more daies ſpent in the deſtruction of one Citie Ierico, then in the Creation of the whole World. If his iudgement, at any time, make toward vs, tis not with Iehu's furious March, 2 King. 9. but with an offer firſt of Peace, Deut. 20. 10. and if peace refuſed, force it the faſter on, yet his mercy ſteps forth, and ſoone gets before it, as Ahimaaz outran Cuſhi, and Iohn did Peter: and therefore neuer ſhall you finde that God is call'd a Father of iudgement: but 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , a Father of mercies. 2 Cor. 1. 3.
            O man endeauour to be like thy Maker, and bee thou mercifull, as thy heauenly Father is mercifull; there cannot bee ſuch diſproportion betweene any other and thee, as is between thee Poteſt poena dilata exigi, exacta non poteſt reuocari. and thy God: therefore, if he warne, ſo doe thou; in puniſhing be deliberate, and ſend not preſently from the barre to the blocke, but doe that vnto man, which thou wouldſt haue done vnto thee of God. Twas a worthy ſaying of Saint Cyprian, and ſuch as ſhewd him to haue the bowels of man in him, Remitto omnia, multa diſsimulo, delictis pluſquam oportet remittendis penè ipſe delinquo &amp;c. I remitt all things, of ſome I take no notice for Charities ſake, things committed

againſt God I examine not ſo ſtrickly as I might, and in pardoning offences more then I ſhould, my ſelfe almoſt offend. Thus doth the mercifull man on earth, ſtriue to imitate the God of heauen, and no other vertue can make him more like him. For with God tis ordinary, either to ſpare when he might deſtroy, or at leaſt, to ſhew ſome mercy, if it be but by delaying of miſery. Yet muſt not the deſperate ſinner preſume on his long ſuffering; his hand will reach him home at laſt, if he perſiſt in his wickedneſſe. Sera venit, ſed certa venit: though Gods vengeance haue leaden feet, and come but ſlowly, yet it hath iron hands, layeth on heauy ſtrokes: his Mills grind but ſeldome, but when they doe, they grinde to powder. God is prouoked euery day, and if a man will not turne, hee whets his Sword, bends his Bow, prepareth instruments of death, and ordaineth his Arrowes againſt the perſecutors. Pſal. 7. 13. Three, there are in his Quiuer moſt deadly, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Famine, Peſtilence, and the Sword; The laſt falls to Tyres lot, which when it ſhould firſt haue raged a while within her walles, and beene glutted with eating fleſh, and drunke with bloud, at length it ſhould yeeld the remainder of the people vnto Captiuity, and ſend them a wandring into a farre Country, Her owne feete ſhould carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
            
            And here we may take a ſuruey of the degrees 1. Degree, Baniſhment. in the burthen of Tyre, and in them ſee the wonderfull Wiſdome and Iustice of God; Wiſdome in ſo aptly fitting puniſhment vnto ſinne, and Iuſtice in appointing extreamity of puniſhment

to extreame ſinne. Tyre, at this time had goodly Buildings, ſtately Pallaces, but abuſed to Riot, and to Luxury; therefore tis threatned thoſe houſes ſhould ſhortly ſpew out their Inhabitants, and that is the firſt degree, Baniſhment; Shee ſhould bee carried to ſoiourne.
            
            
               Tyres niceneſſe was Sybariticall, her tender delicacie 2. Degree, Pouerty. would be rowed on the water in Boates and Barges, hurried vp and downe the ſtreers in Chariots and Coaches, therefore her Feete ſhould bee forced to the ground, and her dainty legges in ſpite of her, bee made beare the burthen of her body, and thats the ſecond degree, Pouerty; Her owne feete ſhould carry her to ſoiourne.
            Shee could not (forſooth) abide forraine 3. Degree, Remoteneſſe of place. ayre, the Countrey winde might not blow vpon her, wedded ſhee was to her owne Paradiſe, and out of her Eden ſhee would not goe, Therefore ſhee muſt into a ſtrange Land, as farre as Chaldaea, the third degree, Remoteneſſe of place; Her owne feete ſhould carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
            O take heede therefore (yee Daughters of Tyre) of turning the graces of GOD into wantonneſſe, and of abuſing thoſe mercies which he ſo ſweetly dropps downe vpon you. Make not Riches bring foorth Riot, and let not the meanes, allowed to maintaine life, yeeld you fuell for your Luxurie. If it doe, bee ſure, the ſame Lord that hath plentifully ſent his bleſsings will (for the abuſe

of them) as faſt ſhowre downe plagues, and inſteed of the full draughts of the Cup of Saluation, you ſhall drinke the dreggs of the Viols of Vengeance: the ſame hand that hath long bene wide open to fill you with good things, will (vpon iuſt occaſion) be as cloſe ſhut in withholding them; and thoſe louing armes which haue bene gently ſpread ouer you, for your protection, will bee ſtretched forth to reach you blowes of destruction. God will pay ſinne home, where euer he findes it, and (for the moſt part) will fit his puniſhment to the nature of the offence; The Daughters of Sion may be haughtie, and walke with ſtretched out necks, and with wandring eyes, walking and minciug as they goe, and making a tinckling with their feet; but mark whether the Lord meet not with them accordingly; after the taking away the whole Wardrope of their vanity; Hee will make their heads bald, and diſcouer their ſecret parts, inſteed of ſweet ſauour, there ſhall be ſtincke, inſteed of a girdle, a rent; inſtead of dreſsing the haire, baldneſſe; inſteed of a ſtomacher, a girding of ſackecloath; and burning inſtead of beauty. Iſai. 3. 24. In like manner, if Tyre will diſſolue and melt into pleaſure, if ſhe will needes giue her ſelfe ouer to niceneſſe and delicacie, let her be ſure, ſhe ſhall be fitted with paine, and haue hardneſſe enough prouided for her, Her owne feet ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
            
            From conſideration of which iudgement here threatned, ſome (neuer looking vnto Sinne the true cauſe of Tyres ſickneſſe,) will perhaps, tel you

of the reuolutions of times, and of fatall periods of ſtates, beyond which, Kingdomes and Cities cannot ſtand; As Phyſitians make the threeſcore and third yeere of mans life a dangerous Climactericall to the body naturall; ſo will Statiſts make the fiue hundreth yeere of a Citie, or Kingdome, as dangerous to the body politique. But I wonder, who hath euer felt a Cities languiſhing pulſe, who hath diſcerned her fatall diſeaſes? found her Criticall dayes? Doth ſhe waxe weake, and heauy, and olde, and ſhriueled, and pine away with yeeres, as the body of man? No, ſhee may flouriſh ſtill and grow greene, ſhe may continue as the dayes of heauen, and bee as the Sunne before the Almighty; if his wrath be not prouoked by her wickedneſſe. Tis ſinne, ſinne, that is both the chiefe cauſe, and the chiefe Symptome of a Cities ſickneſſe, and that, indeede, ſoone brings her to a fearefull end, and vtter deſolation; whereas Religion and honeſty would preſerue her flouriſhing eſtate beyond all fatall periods of time. What brought the deluge on the olde world? vvhat call'd for fire and brimſtone on Sodome and Gomorrah? What deſtroyed Ieruſalem, and her glorious, Temple (the vvonder of the earth?) What brought Niniue, and other famous Cities to ruine? Was it the power of numbers? Was it Plato's multiplying the Sunnes retrograde motion by twelue? Was it any dire aſpect of the heauens? any malignant coniunction of ſtarres and planets? No; but the peoples looſe manners, and their vngracious liues, and their enormous ſinnes. Which ſinnes (all Cities

Cankerwormes) if Tyre, forewarned by the Prophet, could haue ſhaken off, ſhe might haue ſtood in her glory vntill this day: but ſeeing ſhe choſe rather to flatter and ſooth vp her ſelfe in euill, ſo blindfolding her eyes with the veile of her wealth, that ſhe could not perceiue what God intended againſt her; words, at laſt, proceeded into workes, and the Prophets threatning ended in performance; no longer then menacing that God will ouerthrowe, ouerthrowe, ouerthrowe; but he doth it indeed; O thou that dwelleſt vpon many waters, aboundant in treaſures, thine end is come, and the meaſure of thy couetouſneſſe. Alas, alas, the great City, the mighty City, for in one houre is her deſtruction come: O therefore that my head were full of water, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe, day and night, for the ſlaine of the daughter of my people. For not onely her owne feete ſhall carry her a farre off to ſoiourne; but, at laſt, her owne feet did carry her a farre off to ſoiourne.
            Tis not (I hope) expected, that I ſhould here apply this point: tis a Prophecie, and I am neither Prophet, nor Prophets ſonne, therefore all I ſay vnto you, is what Daniel ſaid vnto Nebuchadnezzar, The dreame be to them that hate you, and the interpretation thereof to your enemies. But if (of your ſelues) you would meditate on Tyres iudgement, and that ſeriouſly; if in her ruine, you would but ſeeme to read your owne, that by others harmes you might learne to beware, twould be the happieſt application of a Text, that euer was made. You knowe that like ſinnes
               
draw down like puniſhmēts, &amp; that they who imitate the wicked in their doings, may iuſtly fear to be made partakers of their ſuffrings. Tis true you are yet at eaſe in Sion, and trust in the mountaine of Samaria; you lye vpon beds of luory, and ſtretch your ſelues on your beds; you eate the Lambes of the flocke, and Calues out of the ſtall; you ſing to the ſound of the Violl, and inuent to your ſelues inſtruments of Muſicke like Dauid; you drinke Wine in bowles, and annoint your ſelues with the chiefe oyntments, Amos 6. But are you certain of the continuance of this your happineſſe? Can you ſecure your ſelues to abide a ioyous City ſtill? Alas, you know not what may, at this time, be a prouiding for you, you knowe not what a day may bring foorth, you knowe not what may ſuddenly befall you, vnleſſe you breake off your ſinnes by repentance. I haue no commiſsion to terrifiey ou with warrs, nor rumors of wars; but your ſelues haue heard the ſound of the Trumpet, and the alarum of the Battell; A great part of the Chriſtian World is already vp in Armes, and the Sword hath already made many a mother childleſſe, many a wife a widdow; the Lord euer keepe it from Ieruſalem, &amp; repell it from the gates of Sion; the Lord guard her from his high heauen, &amp; ſend his own penſioners, the holy Angels, to defend her; Peace continue within her walles, and plenteouſnes within her Pallaces. Of the three moſt deadly arrowes in Gods quiuer, (Famine, Peſtilence, and the Sword) he hath ſhot two at you already, ôlet his mercy ſo hold his hād, that he neuer ſhoot the

third; you remember, when he gaue you cleanneſse of teeth in all your Cities, and ſcarceneſſe of bread in all places, when your children fainted and ſwooned, and languiſht away, when your wiues and yong men failed for hunger, and fell downe in the ſtreets of the Citie, and by the paſſages of the gates, and ther was no ſtrength in them. You remember when, after that, once and againe, the deſtroying Angell came among you, and by a grieuous peſtilence laid heapes vpon heapes; when he plac'd Solitarineſſe at your doores, hauing ſlaine thouſands, and ten thouſands in your ſtreets. O then the Lord drewe his Bow mightily, and made his venemous ſhafts enter into your ſoules, and though for all this, you would not turne vnto him, yet hath hee withheld his third arrowe, in hope of your amendment, and his mercy ſtill perſwades him, you will yet take that warning which Tyre would not. Whether your ſinnes bee the ſinnes of Sodome, Pride, Idleneſſe, and fulneſſe of bread, Ezek. 16. 49. or the ſinnes of Samaria, Pride, and Drunkenneſſe, Iſai. 28. 1. or the ſinnes of Tyre, Pride, and inſulting ouer Gods People. Ezek. 26. 2. or all theſe put together; yet may they be waſht away with vnfained teares of repentance, as Naaman the Syrians leproſie with the waters of Iordan; O therefore in the feare of God, bethinke your ſelues while you haue time, and while the acceptable day of the Lord doth laſt; yeeld while the white Flagge of Mercy hangs forth, before the red be diſplaied of bloud, Praemc
                     •••…
                  i. Pramuniti. or the blacke of death; Minae ſint Medicinae, bee

               taught before you bee toucht; take warning before the decree come forth, for if it bee once enacted in the high Court of heauen, twill bee like the Lawes of the Medes and Perſians, not to be repeal'd, not to be altered; It hath gone out heretofore againſt many famous Cities, and accordingly it hath bene executed; Where is now Tanis? and Dumah? and Babylon? and Niniue? and Moab? and Ieruſalem? and Carthage? and Corinth? and No? and Sydon? they are all aequall'd to the ground, and their honour lyeth in the duſt. Tyre her ſelfe, that crowning Citie, is now but onely a hauen vnder the Turks; Her own feet hath carried her a far off to ſoiourne. But who tooke this counſell againſt Tyre, and who purpoſed it,? euen the Lord of Hoaſts, to ſtaine the pride of all glory, and to bring into contempt all the Honourable of the earth: And ſo from the, forme and manner of Tyres iudgement, I paſſe vnto the cauſes of it, and they in number three.
            
               1 The Effficient or Autor of it, the Lord of 
                  2 The cauſes of Tyres iudgement. 
                  Hoaſts. Hee tooke this counſell againſt Tyre. Hee it was that purpoſed it.
               2 The Impulſine, or, that that moued him to it, Pride and glory.
               
               3 The Finall, or end, wherfore he did it, firſt, to ſtaine the pride of that glory, and then (a degree further) to bring into comtempt all the Honourable of the earth.
               
            
            
               Tyres deſtruction was foretold; a City, becauſe ſituate in the Sea, on a Rocke; therefore (in her conceit, and in the Worlds) thought impregnable; whereupon our Prophet (doubting

ſhe would not ſo much feare the iudgement denounc'd, as admire how it could be effected) guideth her eye to ſee the hand that ſhould giue the blowe, as plainely as Belſhazzar ſawe the fingers that wrot his ruine on the wall. Hee neuer mentions to her the arme of fleſh, ſhe would haue ſleighted that, but tells her of the Lord of Hoaſts. The Lord of Hoaſts, A name of power, yet not excluding prudence, a name of might yet not excluding mercy, for tis 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                The Lord of Hoaſts hath decreed it, did not headily and haſtily ruſh vpon it, but ſoberly conſult and deliberat about it: he whoſe word is all one with his work, and that can with the ſame facility doe a thing as determine it, yet 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               decreed before he executed; as he went downe to ſee whether Sodom had done according to the cry, before he decreed, Gen. 18. Now of all the ſinnes that vrge him to decree vengeance, and force down the Viols of his wrath, Pride and glory, ſeem the chiefe, therefore he neuer leaueth till his reuenging hand hath atcheiued thus much; euen, the ſtayning the pride of all glory, and the bringing into contempt all the Honourable of the earth.
            
            More diſtinctly thus; The three cauſes of Tyres iudgement, yeeld vs three concluſions.
            
               1 The Efficient (the Lord of hoasts) this; The inflicter of all puniſhments is the Lord of hoaſts.
               2 The Impulſiue (Pride and Glory) this; That which chiefely ſeemes to mooue him to inflict puniſhment is Pride and glory.
               3 The Finall (the ſtaining, the bringing into contempt) this; His puniſhment beats not the ayre,

but workes for ſome ende, and effects powerfully what it goes about: Twill ſtaine the Pride of all glory, and (as if that were to little) twill bring into contempt all the Honourable of the earth.
            
            Firſt, The inflicter of all puniſhment is the Lord 
               1 Efficient, Lord of hoaſts 
               of Hoaſts.
            
            The prophane Atheiſt may dreame (as the Epicure) that God ſits idle in the heauens, careleſſe of things belowe; letts men liue as they liſt, and if vengeance, at any time, doe ouertake the wicked, tis not long of him but of Chance or Fortune, or the counſell and power of man, or the like; Kingdomes may bee ouerthrowne, Cities ruined, and hee neuer meddle with them. But Can there bee euill in the Citie, and the Lord hath not done it? Amos 3. 6. Is it not Hee that formeth light, and createth darkeneſſe, maketh peace, and createth euill? Iſai. 45. 7. Surely yes; For tis not Chaunce that domineereth in this inferiour world, nor are things whirld about on Fortunes Weeele, but the Lord is hee that iudgeth the Earth, His owne Heritage, and His hand layeth the burthen on euery ſinners backe. Whether any euill befall a Priuate man (euill 
               Malum culpae, Malum poena. I meane ſtill of puniſhment, of which GOD is Author, not of fault, of which he is auenger.) Whether (I ſay) any euill befall Autor Vltor 
               a Priuate man, or a Publique perſon, or a Family, or a City, or a Kingdome, or the whole World, He, he, it is, euen the Lord of Hoaſts, that brings it on them.
            
               
1 On a priuate man. The arrowes of the Almighty (ſaith Iob) are in me, the poyſon of them drinke vp my Spirit; they be the terrors of God, that ſet themſelues in array againſt me. Iob 6. 4.
            2 On a publike perſon. Nebuchadnezzar muſt be driuen from men, and his dwelling, till ſeuen times paſſe ouer him, muſt be with the beaſts of the field, and (ſayth Daniel) O King, Tis the decree of the moſt high which is come vpon my Lord the King. Dan. 4. 24.
            3 On a Family. I will bring euill on thee (ſaith the Lord to Ahab) and I will take away thy Poſterity, and will cut off from Ahab him that piſſeth agaiſt the wall, and I will makethy houſe like the houſe of Ieroboam the Sonne of Nebat, and like the Sonne of Baaſha the Sonne of Ahiiah; 1 King. 21. 21.
            4 On a City. Twas the Lord that rained vpon Sodom, and vpon Gomorrah, brimſtone and fire from the Lord out of heauen, and ouerthrewe thoſe Cities, and all the plaine, and all the Inhabitants of the Cities, and that which grewe vpon the ground. Gen. 19. 24.
            5 On a Kingdome. Twas the Lord ſent a Peſtilence in Iſrael from the morning euen to the time appointed, and there dyed of the people, from Dan euen to Beerſheba 70000 men. 2 Sam. 24. 15.
            6 Laſtly, on the whole world. And I (ſaith the Lord) Behold I, will bring a flood of waters vpon the earth, to deſtroy all fleſh, wherein is the breath of life vnder the heauen, all that is in the earth ſhall periſh. Gen. 6. 17.
            
               
Thus is it he, who ſits on High, that puniſheth all vs here below. Therefore, if there bean end &amp; period ſet to Tyres floriſhing eſtate, you need not doubt but twas the Lord of Hoasts decreed it. As by him Kings and Princes raigne, ſo by him are their Scepters remoued; he was the Alpha and beginning of all rule, and likewife he will be the Omega and ending. Hee changeeh times and ſeaſous, he taketh away Kings, and he ſets vp Kings, Dan. 2. 21. The moſt high beareth rule ouer the Kingdomes of Men, and giueth them to whomſoeuer he will. Dan. 4. 25. Well may Salmanaſar, or Hazael, or Nebuchadnezzar, or ſome ſuch, put to their helping hands, but neither of them is more then the Hammer or the ſcourge, or the rod of the Almighty, only doing that inſtrumentally, which he himſelfe doth principally, O Aſhur the rod of my wrath, and the ſtaffe in their hands is mine indignation. Iſai. 10. 5.
            But what? Is God thus angry? or can hee poſsibly execute iudgement? Is he that (I told you) was ſo vnwilling to puniſh, become now the author of puniſhment? Is hee that ſhewd mercy to thouſands, content to ſee thouſands deſtroyd? Doth he, that would not the death of a finner, put his owne hands to the execution? and he whoſe compaſson flowed as the riuers of water; delight to ſee ſtreames of bloud? In a word, doth that Father of mercies pleaſe himſelfe with Wars? and Captiuities? and Wounds? and Slaughters? and Deathes? and Funerals? Are ſuch voyces as theſe befitting him? Slay euery man his brother, and euery man his companion,

and euery man his neighbour? Exod. 32. 27. Thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould raigne ouer them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me? Luke 19. 27. Is this the ſame God wee ſpake of before? and not rather ſome other? or is he turned on the ſudden from being mercifull to be cruell? Sure, there is not one God of mercy, another of iuſtice; one working good, another working euill: nor is the God of the olde Teſtament more cruell, then the God of the New (as ſome Heretiques blaſphemouſly affirmed) nor the ſame God at one time more cruell then at another; but he that warneth as a Father, is the ſame that decreeth as a Iudge. Cuius &amp; amanda bonitas (ſaith Saint Auguſtine) &amp; timenda ſeueritas, with whom there is mercie, but ſo that hee may be feared. 130. 4. Not altogether compoſed of Compaſſion, excluding Iuſtice, but ſo participating of either, that as we oft heare him promiſing, ſo ſometime threatning; as we oft ſee him pardoning, ſo ſometime puniſhing. Tyre was fairely warn'd, when the Lord ſent his Prophets vnto her, riſing vp earely, and ſending them, adding line vnto line, precept vnto precept, heere a little, and there a little; in this ſee we God as a kind Father ſhewing mercy; but Tyre would not take that warning, forcing him to decree, &amp; to purpoſe that Her owne feet ſhould carry her a far off to ſoiourne. In this wee ſee the ſame God as a iuſt Iudge, executing Iuſtice; there is mercy indeed in the one of his Acts, but there cannot be cruelty in the other. It belongs to the Iudge of heauen and earth to doe right; therefore tis

no more proper to him to ſhew compaſſion, then tis vpon (iuſt occaſion) to inflict puniſhment.
            Well then, if the Lord bee hee that puniſheth, beware, yee Sonnes of men, of offending, and beware in two reſpects.
            Firſt, in regard he is Omniſcient, can ſo eaſily find out what euer euill you doe: And ſecondly, in regard he is Omnipotent, can ſo eaſily punniſh, when he hath found out euill done. As for the former, truſt him, thou Adulterer if thou dare, get thee forth in the twilight, and in the blackneſſe of the night commit thy deedes of darkeneſſe, hope to walke in a cloude, and ſay in thy heart, tuſh, the Lord ſees it not. But marke, whether he doe not, one day, reproue thee, and ſet before thee the things that thou haſt done; aſſure thy ſelfe he ſees thy works, heareth thy words, vnderſtands thy thoughts long before; he is about thy pathes, and about thy bed, and ſpieth out all thy wayes: That which thou doſt in ſecret hee ſees openly, and what thou plotteſt, and contriueſt on thy bed by night, in the darke Cloſet and Cabinet of thy heart, is to him as cleare as the Sunne at nooue day, and as it were, apparently ſet vpon the Houſe top, the eye of heauen that neuer ſlumbreth nor ſleepeth, is ſtill waking, and waiting, and watching ouer thee, and when thou thinkeſt it cloſed vp and faſt, at moſt it doth but winke.
            And as the Lords eye is thus piercing to deſery thy wickedneſſe, ſo is his hand powerfull to take vengeance on thee for it, therefore in the ſecond place, beware, It is a fearefull thing to

fall into the hands of the liuing God. Heb. 10. 31. For if hee be once diſpleaſed with thee, he will muſter vp an Army, euen of the vnſenſible creatures, which ſhall fight againſt thee, Earth, Water, Fire, Sunne, Moone, Starres; the Earth opens her mouth, and ſwalloweth vp Korah, Dathan and Abiram. Num. 16. The Waters, that before ſtood on heapes, ruſh ſuddenly vpon Pharaoh, and drowne him with all his Hoaſt. Exod. 14. Fire commeth downe from heauen, and deuoureth the two Captaines with their fifties, 2 Kings 1. The Sunne ſtands ſtill in Gibeon and the Moone in the Valley of Aiialon, that vengeance may be taken on the Lords Enemies, Haileſtones alſo fight againſt the fiue Kings in the ſame Chapter. 
               Ioſh. 10. and they fight from heauen, euen the Starrs in their courſes fight againſt Siſera. Iudg. 5. How thē are we to deale with this Lord of Hoſts? and his ſo ſtrange Army? not reſiſt him by any meanes, but preſently yeeld, and turne vnto him, that ſo his hand like Achilles Speare, Vulnus opemque, as it wounds may bind vp, and as it ſmiteth, may alſo make whole. Iob 5. 18. Twas neuer ſo truely ſaid of the Kings of Iſrael that they were mercifull Kings, as tis of the God of heauen, that he is a mercifull God; if we come vnto him in all humility as Benhahads Seruants did vnto Ahab, with Sackcloath on our bones, and ropes about our heads, beyond all Peraduenture he will ſaue our liues, for he giueth grace vnto the humble, as he beholds the proud a farre off, and ſcatters them in the imaginations of their hearts; yea he ſo reſpects the meeke Spirit; that he can leaſt abide him of all other

that is moſt contrary to him, and therefore is haughtineſſe ſo the obiect of his furie; nor doth any ſinne more then it, prouoke him to take vengeance; the ſecond Concluſion ariſing from the Impulſiue cauſe of Tyres iudgement, Pride and glory.
            
            2 That that chiefly ſeemes to mooue God to 
               2. Impulſiue. Pride and glory. 
               inflict puniſhment is Pryde and Glory.
            
            Though I confeſſe there were other faults in Tyre as well as Pride, that moued the Lord to take vengeance on her; As firſt, a reioycing at Ieruſalems calamity, Ezek. 26. 2. (which ſhee 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . might haue forborne for that ancient league that was betweene King Solomon and Hiram King of Tyre, (King. 5.) Secondly, Imposture and iniquity in her Trafique Ezek. 28. 18. Thirdly, Deliuering the whole Captiuity to Edom, and not remembring the brotherly couenant, Amos 1. 9. Fourthly, Robbing God of his ſiluer and gold, Ioel 3. 5. and the like. Yet the chiefe and principall was Pride: as appeareth both by this my Text, and by the 28. of Ezekiel, Where the Prince of Tyre is challenged by God for hauing his heart lifted vp, and for being ſo proud, as that hee ſaid, hee was God, and ſate in the ſeat of God. Which Pride, (deſcribed to be, A peruerſe and inordinate deſire of a mans owne excellency) ſeemeth a thing wholly irregular, a breaker of all ranke and order, impatient of the ſtate and place wherein God hath ſet it, ſtill arrogating to its own glory, derogating from his. And it ſhews its ſelfe (ſaith Gregory the Great) foure manner of wayes.
            Firſt, when arrogant men thinke the good

they haue, proceeds from themſelues.
            Secondly, when they yeeld tis from aboue, but giuen for their owne merrits and deſerts.
            Thirdly when they vaunt, as if they had that, which they haue not.
            Fourthly, when deſpiſing others they would ſeeme to haue, what they haue in ſome ſingular manner.
            Now in which kinde ſoeuer of theſe, proud Tyre advanc'd her Peacock plumes, and gaue the Almighty an affront, ſhee could not chooſe but greatly prouoke his wrath and indignation againſt her; for ſo ſoone as euer ſhe came into the number of the haughty, ſhe was one of thoſe that are an abomination vnto him, Prou. 16. 9. and on whom his eyes are ſet to humble them, 2 Sam, 22. 28. As all ſinnes vrge him to take vengeance, ſo Pride (it ſeemeth) eſpecially; and that, probably, for theſe reaſons.
            
               Firſt, Becauſe tis a mother ſinne.
               
               Secondly, becauſe a notorious ſinne.
               
               Thirdly, becauſe the moſt haynous ſinne.
               
               Fourthly, becauſe a manifold ſinne.
               
            
            1 Tis a mother ſinne, in that all other offences ariſe out of it, as braunches from their roote, or ſtreames of water from their fountaine: and that two manner of wayes; directly, and indirectly; directly, all ſinnes ſpring from Pride, becauſe they all aime at the ſame ende at which Pride doth, mans owne excellency: and indirectly, all ſpring from Pride, becauſe ſhe contemneth, and trampleth vnder foot that diuine law, in which is the forbidding of them all.
            
               
2 Tis a notorious ſinne, becauſe it ſo impudently declareth it ſelfe: For whereas other offences couer their faces in darkneſſe, flye the preſence of God, deſiring to be hid from his eies; Pride, being brazen fac'd, walkes vp and downe the open ſtreets, taketh pleaſure in the light, and ſo ietts and ſtruts it before the Almighty, as if ſhee meant to outbraue him to his face.
            3 Tis the moſt hainous ſinne, in that, whereas in euery offence there is an Auerſion from the Creator, as the formality of it, and a Conuerſion to the Creature, as the materiality; though in reſpect of the latter, Pride be not the greateſt ſinne, becauſe height, the proud mans ayme, carrieth not the greateſt repugnancy vnto morall good; yet in reſpect of the former, to wit, the Auerſion from the Creator, tis; for whereas in other ſinnes a man turneth from GOD, either through ignorance, or infirmity, or deſire of ſome other good, or the like, Pride hath its auerſion from him, only becauſe twill not be ſubiect to him, and to his rule.
            4 Laſtly, tis Peccatum multiplex, a manifold ſinne, becauſe whereas other vices ſet onely vpon thoſe vertues, by which themſelues are deſtroyed, Luxury batters Chaſtitie; Anger, Patience, and the like; Pride rayſeth it ſelfe not againſt any one, but againſt all, and as a generall and peſtilent diſeaſe corrupts them all
            Theſe are the Diuelliſh qualities of damn'd Pride, and therefore where euer you finde it

in perſons, or in places, you may attribute their ruine to nothing more. If Moab bee as Sodom, and the children of Ammon as Gomorrah, euen a breeding of Nettles and Saltpits, and a perpetuall deſolation, that they haue for their Pride, Zeph. 2. 10. If Edom bee brought downe to the ground, tis becauſe ſhee hath exalted her ſelfe as the Eagle, and made her neſt among the Stars, Obed. 4. And if Capernaum be thruſt lowe into Hell, tis becauſe ſhe was lifted vp high vnto Heauen, Math. 11. 23. Twas this Pride was Lucifers ſinne, the Sonne of the Morning, which made him from prime of Angels become prince of Deuils; and therefore hee neuer doubted, if he once could but worke in Adam and Eue that proud conceit that they ſhould bee like gods, but twould bee enough to make them die like men. While Pride is climbing vp, it neuer thinks of comming downe, therefore Satan worketh that ſin in man of all other, that his ruine, as tis certaine, ſo it may be ſuddaine, and ſeize vpon him at vnawares; he knoweth they that ſwell with arrogance muſt burſt at laſt, and when they leaſt thinke of it; and that they (who ambitiouſly climbe ouer other mens heads, will ſoone fall, and breake their owne necks. To this ende hee puts a man into a vaine of exalting himſelfe as Haman; or of bragging, as Nebuchadnezzar; or of reuelling, as Belſhazzar, that preſently euen amids his Pride and Iolſitie hee may feele ſome ſtrange downefall; And feele it hee ſhall, little hope is there of eſcaping, for if there be any weapons in the Armory of heauen, any creatures

at Gods command on earth, any Viols of wrath to be powred forth, then looke to thy Crowne, Pride, for thou ſhalt bee ſure to haue thy hairy ſcalpe ſmitten. Though a man were as the Signet of Gods owne right hand, as a Frontlet betweene his eyes, as a Chaine about his necke, yet thence and thence will he ſoone plucke him, if he once begin to be proude, and with Ephraim to kicke with the heele; Pride ſhall haue a fall. Well therefore may it bee painted with a wry neck, not ſo much ſcornefull to looke on men ouer the ſhoulder; as indeede, to ſee how faſt ſhame and deſtruction commeth after.
            Now if ſuch be the danger of Pride, and if it ſo moue God to inflict puniſhment on it, how dareth it ſo frequently iett vp and downe the ſtreets, and not feare the heauy hand of heauen? How commeth it to paſſe there are ſuch troopes of Gallants, euery where met, ſo printed, powdred, perfum'd, ſo kemm'd and trimm'd that a haire may not ſtand awry? Who Abſalon-like are ſo curious of their beauty, that they will rather endure three diſorders in their liues, then one in their locks? How commeth it that they ſo ruffle it in their Silkes and Veluets? Cloath of Gold and Tiſſue? That they carry Houſes, and Lordſhips, Lands and Liuings, Yea ſometime Tythes and Offerings on their backs? And weare Cloathes to that value on one day, as was wont to to keepe good Hoſpitality a whole yeare? How commeth it that yong Landlords to maintaine their Pride here in the Citie, depopulate ſundry Villages in the Countrey? Turne many

ancient Tenants children a begging, and yet keepe no houſe to relieue them with a morſell of bread? How commeth it that where their Grandfathers gaue daily almes to the fatherleſſe and widdow? and were content to let poore families renue their States and Copy-holds, making the eye which ſaw them bleſſe them, and the eare which heard them giue witneſſe vnto them? How commeth it (I ſay) that there now the ſonnes of theſe men engroſſe all tenements into their owne hands, as faſt as they fall, and neuer care for being better members of the Common-weale, then to ſtarue others while they fare deliciouſly themſelues?
            Againe, if great be the danger of pride, and if it ſeeme chiefely to moue God to inflict puniſhment, how commeth it that our women build ſuch turrets and caſtles on their heads, with braided haire and gold put about? How commeth it that they ſo put down the wanton daughters of Syon for bonets, and cawles, and round-tires, and headbands, and veiles, and wimples, and criſping pinns, and tablets, and carerings, and rings, and mufflers, and ſweet balls, and bracelets, and glaſſes, and fine linnen, and hoodes, and lawnes, and ſuch like vanities, whereat diuels laugh, and good men bite the lip? I denie not but there is neceſsitas perſonae, as well as neceſsitas naturae, a rugge or a mantle doth not befit a Lady or a Princeſſe, though it couer nakedneſſe, and keepe away colde, as well as a gowne of Sattin, or Veluet; but yet the exceſſe of apparel euen in ſuch great perſonages (though it be farre more tolerable in them then in thoſe

of the lower ſort) is vnwarrantable; and the Lord will viſite them for it, though Princes and Kings children. Zeph. 18. But let mee farther queſtion, how commeth it that ſome women reſt not ſo in gay and gorgeous cloathing, but (as being weary of their ſexe) are ready to ſtep in to mans apparell, a thing (I dare ſay) neuer heard of in Tyre, and I am ſure, an abomination to the God of Iſrael, Deut. 22. 5. Againe, how commeth it that ſome painted Iezebels ſeeme diſcontent with Gods owne workmanſhip? and (being deſirous to mend what he hath made) put Art a plaiſter vpon Nature? What doe they with their oyles? and waters? and complexions? and colours? and perfumes? and powders? and ſuch like trumperies? The very thought of which may ſet a greater bluſh, and make more roſie cheekes in a modeſt face, then all theſe vnnaturall dawbings can, where the forehead is impudent. O the intolerable pride of theſe times, and of the age wherein wee liue! And when (I wonder) will theſe painted walls thinke of repenting, and ſorrow for ſinne? when with Mary Magdalen, will In fontē frontem, atque in flamina lumina vertit. they make their eyes their baſin, their teares the water, their haire the towell, to waſh and wipe their Sauiours feete? They may not enter into ſuch a mournfull exerciſe, twill preſently diſcolour their freſh varniſht countenance: therefore in their repentance, they (forſooth) will haue ſilkes for ſaceloath, oyles for teares, and ſweet powders for aſhes: but if there be a God in heauen, let them be ſure, he will viſite for theſe things. But (perhaps) you will ſay; theſe, all this while, are

the Chapmen of Tyre and their dainty minions, tis farre otherwiſe with her Merchants and the Citie Matrons, more humility is found in Citizens, and in their wiues more modeſty: God forbid elſe; and yet ſome of them haue their pride too, and ſuch as is not to be endured; for, are not ſome Merchants ready to kiſſe their owne hands, and to ſacrifice to their owne netts, when for their happy returne from ſome dangerous voyage, and for their proſperous encreaſe of wealth, they ſhould aſcribe all vnto the Lord? Againe, are not ſome Merchants in ſuch pompe and brauery, as exceedes their place, and ſo clad with riches, as is beyond their ranke and calling? Cannot we ſee pride peeping through their ruffes and ſetts, through their iaggs and cutts, as Diogenes ſawe Ariſtippus vanity through a gaſh of his cloake? Is there not pride in apparrell? pride in geſture? pride in gate? pride in ſpeech? in almoſt all their actions pride? And as for their wiues and daughters, haue not ſome of them forgot to attire themſelues as Sarah did, and other holy women, who truſted in God, hauing the hidden man of the hart vncorrupt, and a meeke and quiet Spirit which is before God, a thing much ſet by? 1 Pet. 3. 4. Nay, haue they not forgot, how that their owne mothers by being graue and ſtayd matrons, ſoberly and modeſtly attired, were once the ornament and renowne of this place, whereas themſelues by dawbing their faces &amp; dreſſing their heads, as Iezebel did, and then looking out of their windowes, or ſitting at their doores to entrap Solomons foole as he paſſeth by, become a

ſhame and diſhonour vnto the famous Citie that bred them? Yet ſo it is; but if there be a God in heauen: let them be ſure, hee will viſit for theſe things. And if he take the matter into his hand, His puniſhment ſhall not beate the ayre, but worke for ſome ende, and effect throughly what it goeth about, twill ſtaine the Pride of all their glory, and (if that be too little) twill bring all their honour into contempt, The third and laſt concluſion ariſing from the finall cauſe of Tyres Iudgement, (the 
               3. Finall cauſe. 
               ſtaining, the bringing into contempt.)
            
            
               Gods puniſhment beateth not the ayre, but &amp;c. Twill ſtaine) that is, prophane, violate, deſtroy, the pride of all glory) that is, the Pride of all Tyres glory, though ſhee be ſo proud, as if ſhee had the pride of al the world in her, and (becauſe the ſcorner muſt be paid in his own Coine, bee alſo ſcorned) this more; twill not barely ſtain, but bring into contempt,) that is, make vile, and deſpicable, All the honourable of the earth) that is, all the Honourable of the Land of the Tyrians, to wit, their Princely Merchants, and of the Land of her bordering neighbours too, her proud Chap men, if they imitate Tyre in her brauery.
            Tis very miſerable to bee but degraded, and throwne downe from a high conceit of ones owne excellency, but, ouer and aboue to haue ſcorne, and deriſion, and contempt added, is intollerable; yet thus, and thus far proceedes God in puniſhing, rather then his ſtroake ſhal fall light, and ſeeme to be idle. for when he once begins, he will alſo make an ende, though hee ſend plague vpon plague, affliction vpon affliction, as

he dealt with Pharaoh, and the Egyptians, till they ctied out, We dye all, Exod. 12. He firſt warneth, then threatneth; threatneth, then decreeth; decreeth, then puniſheth; puniſheth at firſt lightly, but afterward to purpoſe: Is he (thinke you) as man that hee ſhould lye? or as the Son of man that he ſhould goe backe? Hath he ſaid, and will he not performe? hath he determined, and ſhal it not come to paſſe? and when he brings it to paſſe, will he do it imperfectly, and to halfs? No, he goeth through with what hee enterpriſeth, not onely meetes with Prides perriwig, and haleth it from her crowne, but continueth tugging at her frizled Locks, till hee bring her to the ground, and to bee trampled vnder feete; Firſt, he will Staine the Pride of all glory, and then bring into contempt all the Honourable of the earth.
            
            I might here fairely fall into a point, which I touched vpon before, to wit, God ſo aptly fitting puniſhment vnto ſinne: For (as I told you) if Tyre taking vpon her to be a ioyous Citie, a crowning City, and therefore melting and diſſoluing into pleaſure, yeelding her ſelfe wholly ouer vnto niceneſſe and delicacy, (as thoſe that are in Kings houſes) ſhould for that her wantonneſſe be fitted with paine, and haue hardneſſe enough prouided for her, inſomuch that her owne feete ſhould carry her a farre off to ſoiourne: then no maruell if when ſhe groweth ſtately, and proud, ſcorning and contemning others, the Lord fitt her here in like manner for that too, euen Stayning the pride of all her glory, and bringing into 
                     〈◊◊〉
                   both be honourable, and all the honour 
                     •…
                   
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
                  
ſoiourne, the dainty City ſhall be carried on her owne feete to ſoiourne, the proud City ſhall haue the pride of all her glory stained, and the contemning City ſhall haue all her honourable brought into contempt: The medicine is rightly made for the malady, the ſalue excellently fitted for the ſoare. But I am loath to harpe twice on the ſame ſtring, and that the rather, becauſe I preſume, that whatſoeuer is wanting in the proſecution of this, or any other point, which I haue touch'd vpon, may ſufficiently be ſupplyed, by your more priuate and retyred Meditations. Well then; you ſee, what Pride muſt looke for, euen to be ſtained, what Glory and honour muſt expect, euen to bee brought into contempt; that painted Harlot ſhall be ſure, not onely to bee pull'd and hal'd out of her high throane, but ſo violently hurl'd out of it, that there ſhall bee no ſtay, nor footing for her, till ſhee come downe, downe, vnto the ground; let her carry the matter neuer ſo fairely, and ſooth vp her ſelfe, with neuer ſo many flatteries, yet ende ſhee muſt, in that which ſhee can leaſt abide, contempt.
            
            Wherefore (Beloued) in the feare of God, giue me leaue thus to beſpeake you; Yee Merchants of Tyre that are as ſo many Princes, and yee, her Chapmen, the Honourable of the earth, as you deſire this place, wherein you liue (whoſe antiquity is of ancient dayes) ſhould yet long abide a ioyous City, and a crowning Citie; as you deſire ſhe may ſtill flouriſh more and more heere at home, to the admiration of Strangers; and that her owne feet neuer carry her a far off to ſoiourne;
               
as you deſire the continuance of your own plenty, and proſperitie in her, and that you may bee able to hold vp your heads with credit in the world; as you deſire to auoyd diſgrace, (the ſtaining of your glory, and the bringing your honours into ſcorne and contempt) ſhun pride, &amp; arrogance, embrace humility and meekeneſſe. God hath bleſt you with riches, and honours, and friends, and with what not? and ſo hee did Tyre; With riches, She heaped vp Siluer as the duſt, and Gold as the mire of the ſtreets, Zech. 9. 3. With honours, her Merchants were Princes, and her Chapmen the honourable of the earth, the words of my Text; 
                  •
               aſtly, with friends, ſhe was confederate (by reaſon of her Traffique) almoſt with all Nations, Eeck. 27. But ſhe had a quallity that ſpoild all, (and I could wiſh twere not found in you) ſhe waxed Proud. God is exceedingly offended with Pride in whomſoeuer he findes it; but eſpecially (it ſeemeth) with Pride in Merchants; and that may be, becauſe hee cannot endure they ſhould ſo forget what they ſometime were, and from 
                  •
               ow meane place moſt of them haue bene raiſd. One (whoſe Family was poore in Manaſſes, and he the leaſt in his Fathers houſe) came vp hither villing to labour for his liuing, and began the world with a very little, roſe vp earely, went to bed late, and did eate the bread of carefulneſſe; now (perhaps) God hath giuen him a ſtately Houſe, and a Shop full of wares, diuers Tenements, and rich Reuenues, many Men-ſeruants, and Maid-ſeruants at his command, ſo that the lot ſeemes fallen to him in a faire ground, and he

hath a goodly Heritage; but ſhall hee therefore aduance his creſt, and growe proud? Another was once in as ill a caſe as his Sauiour Christ, though the Foxes haue holes, and the Birds of the ayre haue neſts, yet he had not ſo much as a houſe to put his head in; but ſince that time, perhaps, God hath enlarged his roome, encreaſed his border, giuen him a goodly habitation heere in the City, and Lordly Mannors in the Countrey, a Ship or two at Sea, and rich commodities on the Land, ſo that in peace and plenty he enioyeth whatſoeuer heart can wiſh; with his ſtaffe onely came hee ouer the Riuer, as Iacob; now God hath giuen him two Bands: But ſhall hee therefore aduance his Creſt, and grow proud? Nay rather, as Agathocles, who of a Potter was Fictilibus canâſſe ferunt Agathoclea Regem. made a Prince, ſtil remembred his former meane place: ſo ſhould you thinke of yours, and with all humility thanke God for ſo bettering your ſtates. As the Wiſeman bids you Remember your ende, ſo doe I your beginning, and you ſhall neuer doe amiſſe. The Philoſopher ſaith, rich men are naturally 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Louers of God, fearing to diſpleaſe, becauſe they haue ſomewhat to looſe: which Satan vnderſtood well enough, when hee ſaid, Iob feared not God for nought, but becauſe hee had made a hedge about him and bleſſed the workes of his hands, and increaſed his ſubstance in the Land, Iob 1. 10. O then ſhake not off your Natures you that are rich, and abound in wealth, but be yee louers of God ſtill, Though you lye where you may ſucke your fill at the ſweet dugs of a fruitfull Ile, though you inhabite a ſecond

               Paradiſe vpon earth; yet ſwell not with Pride, nor grow big, be not high minded but feare; and Diuituſque ſinum, deliciiſque larem. ſo the God of peace be with you all, and ſo proſper you in the way of life, that from this ioyous and crowning City below, you may be made free Denizens of the new Ieruſalem aboue, and from being princely Merchants and Chapmen on earth, you may be Kingly Saints ſitting on throanes in Heauen. To God the Father, God the Sonne, &amp;c.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

