
   
      
         
            Christs passion a tragedie, with annotations.
            Christus patiens. English
            Grotius, Hugo, 1583-1645.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02262
            STC 12397
            ESTC S4330
            24157689
            ocm 24157689
            27274
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02262)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27274)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1817:23)
         
         
            
               
                  Christs passion a tragedie, with annotations.
                  Christus patiens. English
                  Grotius, Hugo, 1583-1645.
                  Sandys, George, 1578-1644.
               
               [6], 123, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Legatt,
                  London :
                  M.D.C.XL. [1640]
               
               
                  Translation of Grotius' Christus patiens.--Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.
                  Translator's dedication signed: George Sandys.
                  Signatures: a⁴(-a1) A-G⁸ H⁶.
                  Item identified as STC 12397 on reel 1350 is actually STC 12397.5.--Cf. reel guide.
                  Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Jesus Christ --  Drama.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-06
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-07
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2005-07
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            CHRISTS PASSION. A TRAGEDIE. WITH ANNOTATIONS.
            LONDON, Printed by Iohn Legatt. M. D. C. XL.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTIE.
            
               SIR,
            
            I Am bold to preſent you with this Peece of the PASSION, the Originall deſigned by the curious Penſill of Grotius: whoſe former afflictions ſeeme to have taught him pliable paſsions, and art to rule the affections of others: cloathing the ſaddeſt of Subjects in the ſutable attire of Tragedy; not without the Example of two ancient Fathers of the Primitive Church, Apollinarius and Nazianzen. The Argument is

of both the Teſtaments a patheticall Abſtract. Thoſe formidable Wonders, effected by God in his owne Common-wealth; thoſe ſtupendious Miracles, for truth a Pattern to all Hiſtory, for ſtrangeneſſe to all Fables; here meet together to attend on CHRIST'S PASSION. The effects of his Power here ſweetly end in thoſe of his Mercy: and that terrible Lord of Hoſts, is now this meeke God of Peace; reconciling all to one another, and Man-kinde to Him-ſelfe. Sr. in this change of Language I am no punctuall Interpreter: a way as ſervill as ungracefull. Quintilian cenſures a Painter,

that he more affected Similitude then Beauty; who would have ſhown greater Skill, if leſſe of Reſemblance: the ſame in Poetry is condemned by Horace; of that Art the great Law-giver. Thus in the Shadow of your Abſence, diſmiſt from Arms by an Act of Time, have I, in what I was able, continued to ſerve you.
            
               The humbleſt of your Majeſties Servants, GEORGE SANDYS.
            
         
         
            
            THE PERSONS.
            
               JESUS.
               CHORUS OF JEWISH WOMEN.
               PETER.
               PONTIUS PILATE.
               CAIAPHAS.
               JUDAS.
               THE JEWS.
               FIRST NUNCIUS.
               SECOND NUNCIUS.
               CHORUS OF ROMANE SOULDIERS.
               JOSEPH OF ARIMATHEA.
               NICODEMUS.
               JOHN.
               MARY THE MOTHER OF JESUS.
            
         
         
            
               Imprimatur:
            
            
               Tho: Wykes.
               
                  September 17. 1639.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               THE FIRST ACT.
               
                  JESVS.
                  O Thou who govern'ſt what thou didſt create
                  With equall ſway, great Arbiter of Fate,
                  The Worlds Almighty Father; I, thy Son,
                  Though born in Time, before his Courſe begun;
                  Thus far my Deeds have anſwered thy Commands:
                  If more remain, my Zeale prepared ſtands
                  To execute thy Charge: all that I feare,
                  All that I hate, I ſhall with patience beare;
                  No miſery refuſe, no toile, nor ſhame:
                  I know for this into the world I came.
                  And yet how long ſhall theſe extreames indure!
                  What Day or Night have known my life ſecure!
                  My burthen, by induring, heavier grows;
                  And preſent ills a way to worſe diſcloſe.
                  My Kingdome, Heaven, I left, to viſit Earth;
                  And ſuffer'd baniſhment before my Birth.
                  An unknown Infant, in a ſtable born,
                  Lodg'd in a manger: little, poore, forlorn,
                  And miſerable: though ſo vile a Thing,
                  Yet worthy of the envy of a King.
                  Two yeers ſcarce yet compleat, too old was thought
                  By Herods fears: while I alone was ſought,
                  
                  The bloudy Sword Ephratian Dames deprives
                  Of their dear Babes; through wounds they exhal'd their lives.
                  Secur'd by flying to a forreign Clime,
                  The Tyrant through his Error loſt his Crime.
                  A Thouſand Miracles have made me known
                  Through all the World, and my extraction ſhown.
                  Envy againſt me raves: yet Vertue hath
                  More ſtorms of Miſchief raiſ'd, then Herods wrath.
                  It is decreed by thy unchanging Will,
                  I ſhould be acknowledg'd, and rejected ſtill?
                  Th'inſpired Magi from the Orient came,
                  Prefer'd my Starre before their Mithra's flame,
                  And at my infant feet devoutly fell:
                  But Abrahams Seed, the Houſe of Iſrael,
                  To thee ſequeſtred from Eternity,
                  Degenerate and ingrate! their God deny.
                  Behold the contumacious Phariſies,
                  Arm'd with diſſembled Zeale, againſt me riſe:
                  The bloudy Prieſts to their ſtern Party draw
                  The Doctors of their unobſerved law:
                  And impious Sadduces, to perpetrate
                  My intended Overthrow incenſe the State.
                  What reſts to quicken Faith? Even at my Nod
                  Nature ſubmits, acknowledging her God.
                  The Galilean Youth drink the pure bloud
                  Of generous Grapes, drawn from the Neighbor floud:
                  
                  I others famin cur'd, ſubdu'd my own;
                  Life-ſtrengthning food for fourty dayes unknown.
                  Twixt the Diſpenſers hands th'admired Bread
                  Increaſ'd, great multitudes of People fed,
                  Yet more then all remain'd. The Windes aſſwage
                  Their ſtormes; &amp; threatning Billows calme their rage.
                  The hardned Waves unſinking feet indure:
                  And pale Diſeaſes, which deſpiſe their cure,
                  My Voice ſubdues. Long Darkneſſe chac'd away,
                  To me the Blind by Birth now owes his Day.
                  He hears who never yet was heard; now ſpeaks,
                  And in my Praiſes firſt his ſilence breaks.
                  Thoſe damned Spirits of infernall Night,
                  Rebels to God, and to the Sonnes of Light
                  Inveterate foes; my Voice but heard, forſake
                  The long poſſeſt, and ſtruck with terror quake.
                  Nor was't enough for Chriſt, ſuch wonders done,
                  To profit thoſe alone who ſee the Sunne:
                  To vanquiſh Death my powerfull hand invades
                  His ſilent Regions and inferior Shades.
                  The Stars, the Earth, the Seas, my triumphs know:
                  VVhat reſts to conquer but the Deeps below?
                  Through op'ning Sepulchers, Nights gloomy Caves,
                  The violated priviledge of Graves,
                  I ſent my dread Commands: A heat new born
                  Reanimates the Dead, from funerals torn;
                  
                  And Deaths-numb Cold expulſt, inforc'd a way
                  For Soules departed to review the Day.
                  The Aſhes from their ranſackt Tombs receive
                  A ſecond life, and by my bounty breathe.
                  But Death, his late free Empire thus reſtrain'd,
                  Not uſed to reſtore his Spoyles, complain'd
                  That I ſhould thus unweave the web of Fate,
                  Decreaſe his Subjects, and ſubvert his State:
                  I, for ſo many ranſomed from Death,
                  Muſt to his anger ſacrifice my breath.
                  And now that horrid Houre is almoſt come,
                  When ſinfull Mortalls ſhall their Maker doom:
                  When I, the worlds great Lord, who life on all
                  Mankinde beſtow'd, muſt by their fury fall.
                  That Tragick Time to my laſt Period haſts;
                  And Night, who now on all her Shadows caſts,
                  While with the motion of the Heavens ſhe flies,
                  This ſhort delay of my ſad life envies.
                  Fate, be leſſe ſterne in thy intended Courſe;
                  Nor drag him who will follow without force!
                  After ſo many miſeries indur'd;
                  Cold, Heat, Thirſt, Famine, eyes to teares inur'd;
                  The end, yet worſt of ills, draws neare: their breath,
                  For whom I ſuffer, muſt procure my death.
                  The Innocent, made guilty by the foule
                  Defects of others, muſt his weary Soule
                  
                  Sigh into aire; and though of heavenly birth,
                  With his chaſte bloud diſtain th'ungratefull Earth.
                  They traffick for my Soule: my death, long ſought,
                  Is by the mitred Merchants faction bought;
                  And Treaſon findes reward. My travels draw
                  Neare their laſt end. Theſe practices I ſaw;
                  See what this Nights confederate Shadows hide:
                  My Minde before my Body crucifi'd.
                  Horrour ſhakes all my Powers: my entrailes beat,
                  And all my Body flowes with purple ſweat.
                  O whither is my ancient Courage fled,
                  And God-like Strength! by Anguiſh captive led.
                  O Death, how farre more cruell in thy kinde!
                  Th'anxiety and torment of the Minde!
                  Then muſt I be of all at once bereft?
                  Or is there any hope of ſafety left?
                  O might I to my heavenly Father pray,
                  So ſupple to my teares, to take away
                  Part of theſe ills! But his eternall Doome
                  Forbids, and ordered Courſe of things to come.
                  His purpoſe, fixt when yet the world was young,
                  And Oracles, ſo oft by Prophets ſung,
                  Now ruſhing on their deſtinated end,
                  No Oriſons, nor Sacrifice can bend.
                  Why ſtay I with triumphant feet to tread
                  Vpon th'infernall Serpents poyſnous Head,
                  
                  And break th' old Dragons jaws? The ſin of our
                  Firſt Parents muſt be cleanſed with a ſhowre
                  Of bloud, rain'd from my wounds: my death appeaſe,
                  And cure the venome of that dire Diſeaſe.
                  All you who live, rejoyce; all you who die:
                  You ſacred aſhes of the juſt which lie
                  In peacefull Vrnes, rejoyce in this my fall:
                  I for the living liv'd, but die for all.
                  My ſufferings are not loſt. To Earth I owe
                  Theſe promiſ'd ills: bonds, whips, and thorns to grow
                  About out bleeding brows; the Croſſe the ſcorn
                  Of a proud People, to deſtruction born.
                  O let my Fathers wrath through ſinged aire
                  On me in thunder dart, ſo mine it ſpare!
                  Leſt the World ſhould, I periſh
                        •
                     ; and muſt beare
                  The puniſhments of all that ever were.
                  You who inhabit, where the Sunne diſplaies
                  His earely light, or neer his ſetting Raies;
                  Who ſuffer by his perpendicular
                  Aſpect, or frieze beneath the Northerne ſtar;
                  Affect this ready Sacrifice, who am
                  A greater offering then the Paſchall Lamb.
                  My precious bloud alone the vertue hath
                  To purge your ſins, and quench my Fathers wrath.
                  Now the full Moone ſucceeds that Vernal light,
                  Which equally divides the Day and Night;
                  
                  Sacred to Feaſts. The next Sunne ſhall ſurvay
                  One brighter then himſelfe, and loſe his Day.
                  Falſe Traitor, through thy guilt ſo timerous growne,
                  Although thou lead'ſt an army againſt One,
                  Shrouded in Night; I am not taken by
                  Thy guile, but know thy'fraud, and haſt to die.
                  But you my choſen friends, who yet preſerve
                  Your faith intire, nor from your duty ſwerve;
                  Your Feſtivall, our waſhings paſt, reherſe
                  Your Makers excellence inſacred Verſe;
                  While I to thoſe frequented Shades repaire
                  Where the trees anſwer to the ſighing Aire.
                  Learn, as we walke along, unto what place
                  I ſhortly ſhall return; what heavenly Grace
                  Is to deſcend upon you from above;
                  What are the laws of Charity and Love.
                  While my laſt prayers ſolicit Heaven, to Sleep
                  Give no acceſſe: this Night my Vigil keep.
               
               
                  CHORVS OF JEWISH WOMEN.
                  THe rapid Motion of the Spheres
                  Old Night from our Horizon bears;
                  And now declining ſhades give way
                  To the return of chearefull Day.
                  
                  But Phoſphorus, who leads the Starres,
                  And Day's illuſtriou's Path prepares,
                  Who laſt of all the Hoaſt retires,
                  Not yet with-draws thoſe radiant Fires:
                  Nor have our Trumpets ſummoned
                  The Morning from her dewy Bed:
                  As yet her Roſes are unblown,
                  Nor by her purple Mantle known.
                  All night we in the Temple keep,
                  Not yeelding to the charmes of Sleep;
                  That ſo we might with zealous praier
                  Our thoughts and cleanſed hearts prepare
                  To celebrate th'inſuing Light,
                  When Phoebe ſhall her hornes unite.
                  This annuall Feaſt to Memory
                  Is ſacred, nor with us muſt die:
                  Thus by that dreadfull Exul taught,
                  When God his plagues on Aegypt brought.
                  Thoſe Cities theſe our Rites bereave
                  Of Citizens, and widdows leave,
                  Where Jordan from two bubling Heads
                  His oft-returning waters leads;
                  Till they their narrow bounds forſake,
                  And grow a Sea-reſembling Lake.
                  Thoſe Woods of Palme, producing Dates;
                  Of fragrant Balſamum, which hates
                  
                  The touch of Steele; where once the ſound
                  Of trumpets level'd with the ground
                  Vnbatter'd Wals; that Mount which ſhrouds
                  His aiëry head in hanging Clouds,
                  Where Death clos'd our loſt Prophets eies;
                  Admire to ſee their Colonies
                  Aſcend the hills of Solyma
                  In celebration of this Day.
                  Cephaeans, whoſe ſtrong Wals with-ſtood
                  The ruines of the Generall Flood,
                  To ſolemnize this Day forſake
                  Ador'd Dercetis, and her Lake.
                  Hither the Paleſtines from ſtrong
                  Azotus, both the Jamnes throng.
                  Not Lydda could her Own reſtraine;
                  Nor Caparorſa's wals containe
                  Her Edomites; Damaſcus could
                  Not hers, though ſhe ten Nations ruld:
                  Nor yet Sabaſte, long the Nurſe
                  Of impious Sons, ſprung from our Surſe.
                  Phoenicians, who did firſt produce
                  To Mortals letters, with their uſe;
                  Where Tyrus full of Luxury
                  With Mother Sidon, front the Sky,
                  Hither with haſty zeale repaire:
                  Among the Syrians, thoſe who dare
                  
                  Feed on forbidden fiſh; nor more
                  The Deitie of a Dove adore.
                  From Belus, whoſe ſlow waters paſſe
                  On glittering ſands, which turn to glaſſe:
                  From Arnons banks; thoſe Borderars
                  The ſubject of our ancient wars:
                  Whoſe ſulphurous Bitumen take
                  From ſalt Aſphaltis deadly lake.
                  No Tempeſt on that Sea provailes;
                  No ſhip upon her boſome ſailes;
                  Vnmov'd with oares: what over-flies,
                  Struck by her breath, fals down and dies:
                  Hates all that lives; in her Profound
                  None are receiv'd, but flore undrownd:
                  No Seas, by ſlymie fhores imbras't,
                  So peſtilent a vapor caſt:
                  This blaſts the corne before it bears,
                  And poyſons the declining Ears:
                  Sad Autumns fruits to cinders turn,
                  And all the fields in aſhes mourn:
                  Leſt time ſhould waſte the memory
                  Of thoſe revengefull flames, the sky
                  On Earth in melting ſulphur ſhowr'd,
                  Which that accurſed Race devour'd:
                  When ſhe who did commiſerate
                  With impious griefe her Cities fate,
                  
                  Grew, in the moment of her fault,
                  A Statue of congealed Salt.
                  Hither devout Eſſeans fly,
                  Who without iſſue multiply,
                  And Vertue onely propagate:
                  All ſenſuall loves, all lucre hate,
                  And equall Povertie imbrace:
                  Thrice happy, of a noble Race,
                  Who ſlight your own particular,
                  Tranſported with a publique care.
                  He flies a pitch above our woes,
                  Or crimes, who gladly undergoes
                  Their toile and want; nor would poſſeſſe
                  VVhat others miſcall Happineſſe.
                  VVhat numbers from the Suns up-riſe,
                  From where he leaves the mourning Skies,
                  Of our diſperſed Abrahamites,
                  This Veſper to their Homes invites!
                  Yet we, in yeerly triumph, ſtill
                  A Lamb for our deliverance kill.
                  Since Libertie our Confines fled,
                  Given with the firſt unleaven'd Bread,
                  She never would return; though bought
                  With wounds, and in deſtruction ſought.
                  Some ſtray to Lybia's ſcorched Sands,
                  Where horned Hammons Temple ſtands:
                  
                  To Nilus ſome, where Philips Son,
                  VVho all the rifled Orient won,
                  Built his proud City: others gon
                  To their old Priſon, Babylon:
                  A part to freezing Taurus fled;
                  And Tiber, now the Oceans Head.
                  Our Ruines all the world have fill'd:
                  But you, by uſe in ſufferings skill'd,
                  Forgetting in remoter Climes
                  Our vaniſht Glory; nor thoſe Times,
                  Thoſe happy Times, compare with theſe,
                  Your burdens may ſupport with eaſe.
                  More juſtly we of Fate complaine,
                  VVho Servitude at home ſuſtaine:
                  VVe, to perpetuall woes deſign'd,
                  In our owne Countrey Aegypt find.
               
            
            
               
               THE SECOND ACT.
               
                  PETER.
                  YOu Of-ſpring of bloud-thirſty Romulus,
                  
                  Foes to ſweet Peace, to our great God, and us,
                  And you prophaner Sacrificers, who
                  VVith ſubtil miſchiefe guiltleſſe bloud purſue;
                  Since you would not refuſe to binde the hands
                  Of Innocence, on me impoſe your bands:
                  Seize on the guilty; he who hath refus'd
                  His Lord and Maſter, by himſelfe accus'd.
                  The ills yet ſuffer'd, I deſerve to beare
                  For looking on; what follows, for my feare.
                  You need no torches to ſubdue the Night's
                  Dark Shades to finde me; no ſterne Satellites
                  Drawn from the Temple, nor with Romanes joyne
                  To act one Sin; nor ſpend your ſacred Coine
                  In ſalary to ſuch a Guide as may
                  VVith a perfidious kiſſe his Lord betray.
                  This Head I give you freely; hither haſt:
                  No ſudden hurl-windes ſhall your bodies caſt
                  On trembling Earth. Behold; I with my hands
                  Behinde me bound, implore your dire Commands;
                  And run to meet your ſtripes. Are you now prone
                  To melting pitty? will you puniſh none
                  
                  But with injuſtice? is your fury ſlow,
                  Vnleſſe to thoſe who no offences know?
                  We both alike have impiouſly tranſgreſt:
                  You in not puniſhing a fault confeſt;
                  And I who have the living Lord deni'd.
                  Juſt Jugdes of a life ſo ſanctified
                  To whom ſuborned Witneſſes have ſold
                  Their damned perjuries, a Wretch behold,
                  And heare his Crime: My Countrey Galile,
                  To follow Chriſt I left both Land and Sea:
                  Son to the Thunderer, his onely Heire;
                  From Heaven ſent by his Father to repaire
                  And rule th'affairs of Mortals. This is He,
                  VVhom you have bound, who muſt his Countrey free.
                  Rebellious Vaſſals, you have doom'd your King.
                  I know the impious Race from whence you ſpring,
                  Your ſavage manners, cruel Anceſtors,
                  VVhom Nature, as her greateſt curſe, abhors.
                  Such, when the trembling Boy his brethrens hands,
                  Their truculent aſpects, and ſervill bands
                  Beheld; though privy to a better fate,
                  Whoſe providence was to reward their hate:
                  Soon after, cal'd to Niles ſeven channel'd Flood,
                  He famine from both Lands expel'd with food.
                  So your ſeditious Fathers mutined
                  At Sina's rocks againſt their ſacred Head:
                  
                  And there the food of Angels loth'd, which fell
                  From Heaven in ſhowres: beſotted Iſrael
                  Aegypt and Servitude prefer'd above
                  The Tents of Moſes, and their Countries love.
                  What numbers, with prophetick Raptures fill'd,
                  Have you, and yet not unrevenged, kill'd!
                  Memphis, devouring Deſarts, Civill wars,
                  Oft forreign Yokes, Aſſyrian Conquerars,
                  Great Pompeys Eagles, ſacred Rites profan'd,
                  Your Temple ſackt, with ſlaughtered Levites ſtain'd;
                  Are all forgot? Yet worſe attend your Hate.
                  O that I were the Miniſter of Fate!
                  I then would teare your guilty buildings down,
                  And in a crimſon Sea their ruines drown.
                  Witneſſe you Groves, late conſcious to our cares,
                  Where Chriſt with tears pour'd forth his funeral praiers,
                  How I revenge purſu'd; and with their bloud
                  Would have augmented Cedrons murmuring Floud:
                  But he, for whom I ſtruck, reproov'd the blow;
                  And following his own Precept, cur'd his foe.
                  For Malchus, ruſhing on in front of all,
                  Perceiving part of his, with-out him, fall,
                  Searcht with his flaming brand: the bleeding eare
                  See on the earth, revenge ſubdu'd his feare;
                  Who lowdly roaring ſhook his threatned bands,
                  And ſtreight incountred thoſe all-healing hands:
                  
                     
They to his Head that Ornament reſtor'd,
                  And benefits for injuries affor'd.
                  But O blinde Miſchief! I, who gave the Wound,
                  Am left at large; and he, who heal'd it, bound.
                  O Peter, canſt thou yet forbeare to throw
                  Thy body on the weapons of the Foe!
                  If thou would'ſt vindicate thy Lord, begin
                  Firſt with thy ſelfe, and puniſh thy own Sin.
                  Thou that dar'ſt menace armies, thou that art
                  Fierce, as a Midian Tyger, of a heart
                  Invincible, nor knows what 'tis to dread;
                  VVith Fortune, at the firſt incounter, fled.
                  A Fugitive, a Rebel; one that hath
                  All crimes committed in this breach offaith.
                  VVho towring hopes on his own ſtrength erects,
                  Nor the ſelfe-flattering Mindes deceit ſuſpects,
                  But his vaine Vertue truſt; let him in me
                  The ſad example of his frailty ſee:
                  From ſlippery heights how pronely Mortals ſlide;
                  Their heady errors puniſhing their pride.
                  VVhat can I adde to theſe miſdeeds of mine!
                  VVho have defil'd the water, bread, and wine,
                  VVith my abhor'd defection! O, could I
                  Thoſe lips pollute with wilfull perjury,
                  But newly feaſted with that ſacred food,
                  Preſenting his torne fleſh, and powr'd-out blood!
                  
                  O Piety! for this, thou Renegate,
                  Did Jeſus waſh thy flying feet of late!
                  Not Jordan with two Heads, whoſe waters roule
                  From ſnow-top Libanus, can cleanſe thy Soule:
                  Not thou Callirhoe; nor that ample Lake,
                  From whoſe forſaken ſhore my birth I take,
                  Could'ſt thou blue Nereus, in whoſe troubled Deep
                  Niles ſeven large Mouthes their foming currents ſteep▪
                  
                  Or that red Sea, whoſe waves in Rampires ſtood
                  While our Fore-Fathers paſt the parted Flood?
                  Theſe purging ſtreames from thy own Springs muſt flow.
                  Repentance, why are thy complaints ſo ſlow!
                  Raiſe ſtormes of ſighes; let teares in torrentsfall,
                  And on thy bluſhing cheekes deep furrows gall.
                  O ſo! run freely: beat thy ſtubborn breaſt:
                  Here ſpend thy rage; theſe blowes become thee beſt.
                  This, wretched Cephas, for thy crimes I owe:
                  What can I for my injur'd Lord beſtow!
                  My deeds and ſufferings diſproportion'd are;
                  Nor muſt they in an equall ſorrow ſhare.
                  Should this Night ever laſt, to propagate
                  Increaſing ſorrowes, till ſubdn'd by Fate,
                  My penitent Soule this waſted fleſh forſake;
                  Yet can my guilt no reparation make.
                  Swoln eyes, now weep you? then you ſhould have wept,
                  Beſprinkled my devotion, and have kept
                  
                  That holy Watch, when interdicted Sleep
                  Your drowſie lids did in his Lethe ſteep.
                  You ſhould have dropt my brains into a Flood,
                  Before he at that dire Tribunall ſtood:
                  Ere thrice abjur'd, on me his looks he threw;
                  Or ere th'accuſing Bird of Dawning drew.
                  Where ſhall I hide me! in what Dungeon may
                  My troubled Soul avoid the wofull Day!
                  Fly quickly to ſome melancholy Cave,
                  In whoſe dark entrails thou maiſt finde a grave
                  To bury thee alive: there waſte thy yeares
                  In cheariſht Sorrow, and unwitneſt Tears.
               
               PONTIVS PILAT. CAIAPHAS.
               
                  TArpaean Jove; Mars, great Quirinus Sire;
                  You Houſhold gods, ſnatcht from Troys funerall Fire,
                  With greater Zeal ador'd; when ſhall I pay
                  My Vows! my Offerings on your Altars lay!
                  And ſee thoſe Roofs which top the Clouds! the Beams
                  With burniſht gold inchac'd, and blazing Gems.
                  Thoſe Theaters; which ring with their applauſe
                  Who on the conquered World impoſe their Lawes!
                  And thee, the triple Earths imperious Guide,
                  Great-Soul'd Tiberius! whether thou reſide
                  On Tibers banks, ador'd by gratefull Rome;
                  Ambitious of his reſidence, for whom
                  
                  She gave the World; or Caprae, much renown'd
                  For ſoft delights, impoveriſh the Long-gown'd!
                  Farre from my friends, farre from my native Soyl
                  I here in honourable Exile toyl,
                  To curb a People whom the Gods diſclaim:
                  Who cover under the uſurped Name
                  Of Piety, their hate to all Man-kinde;
                  Condemne the world; in their own vices blinde:
                  And with falſe grounded fear abjure for One,
                  All thoſe Immortalls which the Heavens inthrone.
                  Their onely Law is to renounce all Laws:
                  Their Error, which from others hatred draws,
                  Fomenting their own diſcord, ſtill provokes
                  Their Spirits to Rebellion, who their yokes
                  Have oft attempted to ſhake-off; though they
                  More eaſ'ly are ſubdu'd, then taught to obey.
                  Cleare Juſtice, ſincere Faith, bear witneſſe you
                  With how much grief our ſwords the Hebrews ſlew:
                  But ſuch as ſtubborn and inhumane are,
                  Vnleſſe they ſuffer, would inforce a War:
                  And Reaſon urgeth thoſe who Scepters bear,
                  Againſt their Nature, oft to prove ſevere.
                  I go to queſtion what theſe Prelates would:
                  Since they forbear to enter, leſt they ſhould
                  (Their Feaſt ſo neare) with my unhallowed Floore
                  Their feet pollute. Who's this, by ſuch a power
                  
                  In ſhackles led! How reverend his aſpect!
                  How full of awe! theſe Looks no guilt detect.
                  Thou, Caiaphas, of Solyma the Prime,
                  And Prince of Prieſts, relate th'imputed Crime.
               
               
                  CAIAPHAS.
                  Great Guardian of the Romane Peace, whom we
                  Next Caeſar honour; to be doom'd by thee
                  Our Senate brings th'Infection of theſe Times:
                  Whom we accuſe of no ſuggeſted crimes.
                  Thoſe holy Rites which grave Antiquity
                  Firſt introduced, ſince defended by
                  A long deſcent, this Innovator ſought
                  To aboliſh, and a new Religion taught.
                  Nor fearing the Receſſe of Gods own Seat,
                  The Temples ruine ſings, and Roof repleat
                  With the full Deitie: diſturbs the Feaſt
                  Of the ſeventh Day, deſign'd for ſacred Reſt.
                  Thoſe lawes rejects which Moſes pen reveal'd,
                  Even thoſe by God with dreadfull thunder ſeal'd.
                  Nor ſo content; with Heaven his furie warres,
                  Aſpires that Throne, and tramples on the Starres.
                  Who ſtiles himſelf, though of ignoble birth,
                  His onely ſonne, who made both Heaven and Earth.
                  This, Death muſt expiate; he hath judg'd his Cauſe,
                  Who writ in leaves of Marble our ten Lawes.
               
               
                  
                  PILAT.
                  When Wrath, the Nurſe of War, and thirſt of gold
                  Deſtructive Arts produc'd; the better Soul'd
                  No peace nor ſafety found, inforc't to bear:
                  Life, of it ſelf infirme, through common fear
                  Into Societies the ſcattered drew,
                  Who by united forces potent grew:
                  Intrenched Cities with high walls immur'd;
                  But more by well-digeſted Lawes ſecur'd:
                  The Crime and Puniſhment proportion kept;
                  And Wrongs, like Wolves, on their firſt Authors leapt:
                  Juſtice from each Offence example took;
                  And his own weapon the Delinquent ſtrook:
                  Spoil ſeaz'd on Rapine, Bloud drew bloud; deter'd
                  From doing that, which they to ſuffer fear'd.
                  But more then humane plagues attend on thoſe
                  Who God provoke: he proſecutes his foes
                  With ſure revenge. Why ſhould thoſe Hands which tear
                  The clouds with thunder, ſhake the World with fear;
                  Their wrath to Man reſigne? The impious finde
                  Their ſcourge: the terror of th'aſtoniſh'd Minde
                  Affrights their peace: who feel what they deny;
                  And fear an unbeleeved Deity.
                  One Day no period to his torment gives:
                  To tremble at the Name of Death he lives;
                  
                  Still apprehending what then death is worſe;
                  Long life awarded to prolong his curſe.
                  But if he have your laws infring'd, be you
                  Your ſelves the judges, and his guilt purſue.
               
               
                  CAIAPHAS.
                  Although thoſe ancient Laws, which now remain
                  Among us, we acknowledge to retain
                  From Romes free bounty; yet to you 'tis knowne,
                  Our curbed Power can death inflict on none.
                  You, to whom Caeſars Fortunes recommend
                  His Rods and Axes, ſacred Rule defend.
                  This guilty Wretch, whoſe practiſes we feare,
                  Of late his place of birth forſaking, where
                  The Sea is honour'd with Tiberius Name,
                  With troopes of Clients to this City came.
                  Who ſeeds of War among the Vulgarſowes:
                  With what injuſtice Romane Armes impoſe
                  Their Tribute on a Nation ever free.
                  With magick Charmes, and Stygian compact, he
                  Attracts beliefe: denies the dead their reſt,
                  Of thoſe un-envi'd Manſions diſpoſſeſt
                  By wicked Spels. Theſe prodigies delude
                  The novelty-affecting Multitude:
                  Whom for their Lord their loud Hoſannas greet;
                  And ſtrew the noble Palme beneath his ſeet.
                  
                  Imboldned by theſe Arts; He, as his own
                  By birth, aſpires to Davids ancient Throne.
                  When Rome, provok'd by his rebellion, ſhall
                  Arme her juſt Griefe; we by the ſword muſt fall,
                  Our City ſinke in flames, our Countrey lye
                  Depopulated. But ſince One muſt dye
                  To ſave the Generall; ſentenc'd by thy breath,
                  Let him redeeme his Nation with his death.
               
               
                  PILAT.
                  Such doubtfull cauſes grave advice require:
                  Here, if you pleaſe, attend; while I retire.
                  The Priſ'ner to the Souldiers care commit:
                  On whom this day we will in judgement fit.
               
               
                  CHORVS OF JEWISH WOMEN.
                  YOu lofty towers of Solyma,
                  Thou ancient Throne of Soveraign ſway:
                  To thee the conquered Tribute pay'd,
                  From th'Iſthmos, crown'd with Ebon ſhade,
                  To great Euphrates trembling Streames:
                  Arabians, ſcorch'd by Phoebus beames.
                  Th'admiring Queen, wing'd with thy Fame,
                  From her black-peopled Empire came.
                  
                  Great Kings, ambitious of thy love,
                  To joyne with thee in friendſhip ſtrove.
                  Thoſe who Canopus Scepter bore;
                  Thoſe Monarchs who the Sun adore,
                  And o're the wealthy Orient reigne:
                  Sarrana, Soveraigne of the Main.
                  Now, ah! a miſerable Thrall!
                  O, nothing, but a prey to all!
                  This Land, t'one God once chaſtly wed,
                  How often hath ſhe chang'd her Head,
                  Since they our Temples ruin'd pride
                  With bad preſage reedifi'd!
                  Since thoſe, in forrein bondage born,
                  Did with their ſervile Fates return!
                  On us Antiochus guilt reflects:
                  Our Fathers Sinnes ſit on our necks.
                  What durſt that wicked Age not do,
                  Which could thoſe Altars naked view,
                  Oft flaming with celeſtiall Fire!
                  Provoking Heavens deſerved ire
                  With their adult'rat Sacrifice!
                  For this did Ours ſo highly prize
                  Th'Iönian Gods, by mortals made,
                  And incenſe to thoſe Idols pay'd?
                  Since when th'Accurſt their brothers ſlew;
                  Wives, leſſe malitious poyſon brew;
                  
                  Sons fall by Mothers: we have known
                  That, which will be beleev'd by none.
                  Twice vanquiſhed by Romane Armes;
                  Twice have their Conquerours our harmes
                  Remov'd for greater: Fortunes change
                  To our proud Maſters prov'd as ſtrange.
                  Yet this no leſſe our grief provokes,
                  Our kindred beare divided yokes:
                  One part by Romane bondage wrung;
                  The other two by Brothers, ſprung
                  From Savage Idumaeans, whom
                  Our Fathers have ſo oft ore-come.
                  O thou the Hope, the onely One
                  Of our diſtreſſe, and ruin'd Throne;
                  Of whom, with a prophetick tongue,
                  To Judah dying Jacob ſung:
                  The crowned Muſe on ivory Lyre,
                  His breaſt inflam'd with holy Fire,
                  This oft fore-told; That thou ſhouldſt free
                  The People conſecrate to thee;
                  That thou, triumphing, ſhouldſt revoke
                  Sweet Peace, then never to be broke;
                  When free'd Judaea ſhould obey
                  One Lord, and all affect his Sway.
                  O when ſhall we behold thy Face,
                  So often promis'd to our Race!
                  
                  If Prophets, who have won belief
                  By our miſhaps and flowing grief,
                  Of joyfull change as truely ſung;
                  Thy abſence ſhould not now belong.
                  Thee, by thy Vertue, we intreat;
                  The Temples Vaile, the Mercies Seat;
                  That Name, by which our Fathers ſware,
                  Which in our vulgar Speech we dare
                  Not utter, to compaſſionate
                  Thy Kindreds Teares, and ruin'd State.
                  Haſt, to our great Redemption, haſt,
                  O thou moſt Holy! and at laſt
                  Bleſſe with thy Preſence; that we may
                  To thee our Vowes devoutly pay.
               
            
            
               
               THE THIRD ACT.
               JVDAS. CAIAPHAS.
               
                  YOu who preſerve your pure integrity;
                  O you whoſe crimes tranſcend not credit, fly
                  Farre from my preſence! whoſe invenom'd ſight
                  Pollutes the guilty. Thou, who wrong and right
                  Diſtinctly canſt diſcern; whoſe gentle breſt
                  All faith hath not abandon'd, but art bleſt
                  With children, brothers, friends; nor haſt declin'd
                  The ſweet affections of a pious Minde;
                  Shut up the winding entry of thine eare,
                  Nor let the world of ſuch a bargain heare.
                  A Sinne ſo horrible ſhould be to none
                  Beſides the deſperate Contractors known.
                  Wher's now that mitred Chief? where that dire Train
                  Of Sacrificers, worthy to be ſlain
                  On their own Altars? I have found my Curſe:
                  The Sun, except my ſelf, ſees nothing worſe.
                  Heare, without hire; O heare the too well known:
                  If you ſeek for a witneſſe; I am one
                  That can the truth reveal: Or would you finde
                  A Villain? Her's a ſelf-accuſing Minde.
                  That ſacred Life, O moſt immaculate!
                  More then my Maſters! to your deadly Hate
                  
                  Have I betrai'd: diſcharge my hands I may,
                  Although not of the Guilt, yet of the Prey.
                  Receive the gift you gave: a treachery
                  Second to mine, you may of others buy.
               
               
                  CAIAPHAS.
                  If thou accuſe thy ſelfe of ſuch a Sin
                  Deſervedly, thou haſt a Court with-in,
                  That will condemne thee. Thy offences be
                  No Crimes of ours: our conſciences are free.
                  Nor ſhall the ſacred Treaſury receive
                  The price of bloud. Thee to thy Fate we leave.
               
               
                  JVDAS.
                  Is this the doctrine of your piety
                  To approve the Crime, yet hate the Hire? O fly,
                  Fly, wretch, unto the Altar, and pollute
                  The Temple with thy Sins accurſed fruite.
                  Nor will I for my ſelfe with hopeleſſe praier
                  Solicit Heaven; loſt in my owne deſpaire;
                  But Gods ſterne Juſtice urge, that we, who were
                  Joyn'd in the guilt, may equall vengeance beare.
                  Nor ſhall I in my puniſhment proove ſlow:
                  Behold, your Leader will before you go;
                  'Tis fit you follow; to thoſe ſilent Deepes,
                  Thoſe horrid Shades, where Sorrow never fleepes.
                  
                  Thou great Director of the rouling Starres,
                  Vnleſſe thou idlely lookſt on mens affaires,
                  And vainely we thy brutiſh Thunder feare;
                  Why ſhould thy land ſo dire a Monſter beare?
                  Or the Sun not retire, and yet behold?
                  If thoſe thy fearefull puniſhments of old
                  Require beliefe, in one unite them all:
                  Let Seas in Cataracts from Meteors fall,
                  Afford no ſhore, but ſwallow in their Brine;
                  That ſo the Worlds firſt ruine may prove mine.
                  Let melting Stars their ſulphrous ſurfet ſhed,
                  And all the Heavenly Fires fall on my Head.
                  And thou, O injur'd Earth, thy jawes extend,
                  That I may to th'infernall Shades deſcend:
                  Leſſe cauſe had thy revenge, when ſhe the five
                  Inrag'd Conſpirators devour'd alive.
                  Thoſe evils which amaz'd the former-times,
                  Thy fury hath conſum'd on ſmaller Crimes.
                  O ſlow revenger of his injuries,
                  And he thy Son! ſome fearefull death devize;
                  Vnknowne, and horrid: Or ſhall I purſue
                  My owne offence, and act what thou ſhouldſt doe?
                  You Legions of Heavens Exuls, you who take
                  Revenge on Mortals for the crimes you make;
                  Why troope you thus about me? Or what need
                  Theſe terrors? Is my puniſhment decree'd
                  
                  In Hell already? Furies, now I come.
                  In your darke dungeons what more horrid Rome
                  Shall now devoure me? Muſt I to that Place,
                  Where the curs'd Father of a wicked Race
                  Your ſcourges feeles? who, when the world was new,
                  And but poſſeſt by foure, his brother ſlew.
                  Or where that faithleſſe Prince blaſphemes? then all
                  His Hoſt more eminent; who leſt his fall
                  Should honour to his enemies afford,
                  Made way for hated Life with his own ſword.
                  He moſt affects me, who his fathers Chaire
                  Vſurp'd; when caught by his revenging Haire,
                  He loſt the Earth and Life: the way he led
                  T'avoided Death, my willing feet ſhall tread.
                  Maſter, I fly to anticipate the event
                  Of my foule crime with equall puniſhment.
               
               PONTIVS PILAT. THE JEWS.
               
                  HOrror diſtracts my ſenſe: irreſolute
                  Whether I ſhould break ſilence, or ſit mute.
                  Envy th'accus'd condemnes, whom Juſtice cleares.
                  I muſt confeſſe, perſwaded by my Feares,
                  Leſt I this State and People ſhould inſence,
                  I wiſht they could have prov'd that great Offence.
                  
                  Yet whatſoever they inforc'd of late,
                  No fault of his reveal'd, but their own hate.
                  His ſilence was a vanquiſhing reply.
                  Who for detecting their falſe piety
                  (Whoſe ſupercilious looks, with faſting pale,
                  Cloſe avarice, and proud ambition vaile)
                  Is by their Arts made guilty: One that ſlights
                  The God they adore, and violates his Rites.
                  From hence thoſe many-nam'd Offences ſpring;
                  And his aſpiring to become their King.
                  Can thoſe poore Fiſhers of that In-land Sea,
                  And women, following him from Galile,
                  So great a Spirit in their Leader raiſe;
                  That Rome ſhould feare, whom all the World obayes.
                  Yet he avers his Kingdome is unknown,
                  Nor of this World; and bows to Caeſars Throne.
                  Prov'd by th'event: for when the Vulgar bound
                  His yeelding hands, they no reſiſtance found.
                  But his endowments, zealous in defence
                  Of clouded Truth, their mortall hate incenſe.
                  Follow'd by few, who like affections beare,
                  And with beliefe their Maſters doctrine heare.
                  If true, he may ſpeak freely; nor muſt dye
                  For Oſtentation, though he broach a lye.
                  But if diſtracted, that's a puniſhment
                  Even to it ſelfe, and Juſtice doth prevent.
                  
                  He, whom this Annual Solemnity
                  Hath now invited to the Temple by
                  His Father built, whoſe Kingdome borders on
                  The land innobled by Agenor's Throne,
                  Of theſe ſtupendious acts by Rumour ſpred
                  Could fixe no faith, though in his City bred.
                  To laughter doom'd, his Rivall Herod ſeorn'd;
                  And ſent him back, in purple robes adorn'd.
                  Th'implacable, now far more fiercely bent
                  To proſecute the twice-found innocent:
                  Perhaps afraid leſt they their owne ſhould looſe,
                  Vnleſſe they him of forged guilt accuſe.
                  But when Revenge doth once the Minde ingage;
                  O how it raves! loſt to all ſenſe but rage!
                  No Lioneſſe, late of her whelps bereft,
                  With wilder ſury proſecutes the Theft.
                  O Shame I through feare I ſought to ſhield the Right
                  VVith honeſt Fraud, and Juſtice ſteale by ſlight:
                  As when the labouring Bark, too weak to ſtem
                  The boyſterous Tide, obliquely cuts the ſtream.
                  They have an ancient Cuſtome, if we may
                  Believe the Jews, derived from that Day
                  When the delivered Sons of Iſrael
                  Fled from thoſe banks whoſe flouds in ſummer ſwel:
                  That ever when the Vernall Moone ſhall joyne
                  Her ſilver Orb, and in full luſtre ſhine,
                  
                  They ſhould ſome one releaſe, to gratifie
                  The People, by their Law condemn'd to die.
                  Now, hoping to have free'd the Innocent,
                  The violent Prieſts my Clemency prevent:
                  Who urge the heady Vulgar to demand
                  One Barrabas; a Thiefe, who had a hand
                  In every murther, hot with humane blood.
                  How little it avails us to be good!
                  Prepoſterous Favour! through the hate they heare
                  His guiltleſſe Soule, their Votes the guilty cleare.
                  And now my Wifes not idle dreames perplex
                  My ſtrugling thoughts, which all this night did vex
                  Her troubled ſlumbers: who conjures me by
                  All that is holy, all the Gods, that I
                  Should not the laws of Juſtice violate
                  To gratifie ſo undeſerv'd a hate.
                  For this ſhall I the Hebrew Fathers ſlight,
                  Th'indeavours of a Nation ſo unite,
                  Committed to my charge? Shall I for One
                  Poore Abject, forfeit all the good I have done?
                  Theſe peſter'd Wals all Jewry now infold;
                  The Houſes hardly can their Strangers hold,
                  Sent from all parts to this great Feſtivall:
                  What if the Vulgar to their weapons fall?
                  Who knows the end, if once the Storme begin?
                  Sure I, their Judge, egregious praiſe ſhould win
                  
                  By troubling of the publique Peace. Shall I
                  Then render him to death? Impiety!
                  For what offence? Is his offence not great,
                  Whoſe innovation may a warre beget?
                  Leſt Empire ſuffer, they who ſcepters beare
                  Oft make a Crime, and puniſh what they feare.
                  One hope remaines: Our Souldiers the Free-borne,
                  And yet by our command, with whips have torne.
                  A ſight ſo full of pitty may aſſwage
                  The ſwiftly-ſpreading fire of popular Rage.
                  Look on this Spectacle! his armes all o're
                  With laſhes gall'd, deep dy'd in their own gore!
                  His ſides exhauſted! all the reſt appeares
                  Like that Fictitious Scarlet which he weares!
                  And for a Crown, the wreathed Thornes infol'd
                  His bleeding browes! With griefe his griefe behold!
               
               
                  JEWES.
                  Away with him: from this Contagion free
                  Th'infected Earth, and naile him on a Tree.
               
               
                  PILAT.
                  What, crucifie your King?
               
               
                  JEWES.
                  Dominion can
                  No Rivall brook. His rule, a Law to Man,
                  
                  Whom Rome adores, we readily obay:
                  And will admit of none but Caeſars Sway.
                  He Caeſars right uſurps, who hopes to aſcend
                  The Hebrew Throne. Thy own affairs intend.
                  Doſt thou diſcharge thy Maſters truſt, if in
                  Thy government a preſident begin
                  So full of danger, tending to the rape
                  Of Majeſty? Shall treaſon thus eſcape?
               
               
                  PILAT.
                  The Tumult ſwels: the Vulgar and the Great,
                  Joyne in their Votes with contributed heat.
                  Whoſe whiſperings ſuch a change of murmur raiſe
                  As when the riſing Windes firſt Fury ſtrayes
                  'Mong wave-beat Rocks; when gathering Clouds deforme
                  The face of Heaven, whoſe Wrath begets a Storme:
                  The fearefull Pilot then diſtruſts the Skies;
                  And to the neereſt Port for refuge flies.
                  To theſe rude Clamours they mine eares inure:
                  Such ſharpe diſeaſes crave a ſudden cure.
                  You my Attendants, hither quickly bring
                  Spot-purging Water from the living Spring.
                  Thou liquid Chryſtall, from pollution cleare;
                  And you my innocent hands like record beare,
                  On whom theſe cleanſing ſtreames ſo purely runne;
                  I voluntarily have nothing done.
                  
                  Nor am I guilty, though he guiltleſſe die:
                  Yours is the Crime; his Blood upon you lie.
               
               
                  JEWES.
                  Reſt thou ſecure. If his deſtruction ſhall
                  Draw down celeſtiall Vengeance, letit fall
                  Thick on our heads, in puniſhment renew:
                  And ever our diſperſed Race purſue.
               
               
                  PILAT.
                  Then I, from this Tribunall, mounted on
                  Imbelliſh'd Marble, Judgements awfull Throne,
                  Thus cenſure: Lead him to the Croſſe; and by
                  A ſervil death let Judahs King there dye.
               
               CHORVS OF JEWISH WOMEN JESVS.
               
                  VVE all deplore thy miſeries;
                  For Thee we beat our breſts; our eyes
                  In bitter teares their moyſture ſhed:
                  If thou be he by Ravens fed,
                  Aloft on flaming Charriot born;
                  Yet wouldſt to cruell Lords return:
                  Or that ſad Bard, believ'd too late,
                  Who ſung his Countreys ſervil Fate;
                  
                  Now come to ſigh her deſtiny,
                  A like unhappy; twice to dye:
                  Or he, long nouriſh'd in the Wood,
                  Who late in Jordans cleanſing Flood
                  So many waſh'd; that durſt reprove
                  A King for his inceſtious love;
                  Slain for a Dancer. If the ſame,
                  Or other of an elder fame,
                  Sent back to Earth, in vices drown'd,
                  To raiſe it from that dark Profound;
                  'Tis ſure thy Sanctitie exceeds,
                  Blaz'd by thy Vertue and thy Deeds.
                  O never more, ring'd with a Throng
                  Of Followers, ſhall thy ſacred tongue
                  Informe our Actions; nor the way
                  To Heaven, and heavenly joyes, diſplay!
                  The Blind, who now the unknown light
                  Beholds, ſcarce truſting his own ſight,
                  Thy gift, ſhall not the Giver ſee.
                  Thoſe maladies, ſubdu'd by thee,
                  Which powerfull Art and Hearbs deſie,
                  No more thy ſoveraign Touch ſhall fly.
                  Nor Loaves, ſo tacidly increaſt,
                  Againe ſo many thouſands feaſt.
                  Thou Rule of Lifes Perfection,
                  By Practice, as by Precept, ſhown;
                  
                  Late hemb'd with Auditors, whoſe ſtore
                  Incumbred the too-narrow Shore,
                  The Mountains cover'd with their Preaſſe,
                  The Mountains then their People leſſe;
                  For whom our Youths their garments ſtrew,
                  Victorious Boughs before thee threw,
                  While thou in Triumph rid'ſt along,
                  Saluted with a joyfull Song:
                  Now, ſee what change from Fortune ſprings!
                  O dire Viciſſitude of Things!
                  Betray'd, abandon'd by thy owne;
                  Drag'd by thy Foes, oppoſ'd by none.
                  Thou hope of our afflicted ſtate,
                  Thou Balme of Life, and Lord of Fate;
                  Not erſt to ſuch unworthy bands
                  Did'ſt thou ſubmit thy powerfull Hands.
                  Lo, he who gave the dumbe a tongue,
                  With patient ſilence bears his wrong!
                  The Souldier, ah! renews his blows;
                  The whip new-op'ned furrows ſhows,
                  Which now in angry tumors ſwel:
                  To us their wrath the Romans ſel.
                  Lo, how his members flow! the ſmart
                  Confin'd to no particular part:
                  His ſtripes, which make all but one ſore,
                  Run in confuſed ſtreames of gore.
                  
                  Art thou the Slave of thy owne Fate,
                  To beare thy torments curſed waight?
                  What Arab, though he wildly ſtray
                  In wandring Tents, and live by prey;
                  Or Cyclop, who no pitty knowes,
                  Would ſuch a cruel task impoſe?
                  O that the fatall preſſure might
                  Sinke thee to Earth, nor weigh more light
                  Then Death upon thee; that thy weake
                  Vntwiſted thread of life might breake!
                  It were a bleſſing ſo to dye:
                  But O for how great cruelty
                  Art thou reſerv'd! the Croſſe thou now
                  Support'ſt, muſt with thy burden bow.
               
               
                  JESVS.
                  Daughters of Solyma, no more
                  My wrongs thus paſſionately deplore.
                  Theſe teares for future ſorrows keep:
                  Wives, for your ſelves and children weep.
                  That horrid day will ſhortly come,
                  When you ſhall bleſſe the barren Wombe,
                  And Breſt that never infant fed:
                  Then ſhall you wiſh the mountains head
                  Would from his trembling baſis ſlide,
                  And all in tomb's of ruins hide.
               
               
                  
                  CHORVS.
                  Alas! thou ſpotleſſe Sacrifice
                  To greedy Death! no more our eyes
                  Shall ſee thy Face! ah, never more
                  Shalt thou return from Deaths dark ſhore.
                  Though Lazarus, late at thy call,
                  Brake through the barrs of Funerall;
                  Raiſ'd from that Priſon to review
                  The World which then he hardly knew:
                  Who forth-with former ſenſe regains;
                  The bloud ſprung in his heated Veins;
                  His ſinews ſupple grew, yet were
                  Again almoſt conjeal'd with feare.
                  Thy followers, Sadock, now may know
                  Their Error from the Shades below.
                  A Few, belov'd by the Moſt High,
                  Through Vertue of the Deitie,
                  To others rarely rendred breath:
                  None ever raiſ'd himſelfe from death.
               
            
            
               
               THE FOVRTH ACT.
               FIRST NVNCIVS. CHORVS OF JEWISH WOMEN. SECOND NVNCIVS.
               
                  I From the horrid'ſt Act that ever fed
                  The fire of barbarous Rage, at length am fled:
                  Yet O too neare! The Object ſtill purſues;
                  Flotes in mine eyes, that ſad Scene renewes.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  Art thou a witneſſe of his miſerie?
                  Saw'ſt thou the Galilean Prophet die?
               
               
                  1. NVNCIVS.
                  
                  Thoſe Savages, to Scythian Rocks confin'd,
                  Who know no God, nor vertue of the Minde,
                  But onely Senſe purſue; who hunger tame
                  With ſlaughtered Lives; they, and their food, the ſame;
                  Would this deteſt.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  Vain Innocence! would none
                  Lend him a teare! were all tranſform'd to ſtone!
               
               
                  
                  1. NVNCIVS.
                  
                  No certainly: yet ſo commiſerate,
                  As Pittie prov'd more tyrannous then Hate.
                  The curſed Tree with too much weight oppreſt
                  His ſtooping ſhoulders: Death had now releaſt
                  His fainting Soul: but O, the Lenitie
                  Of Malice would not ſuffer him to die,
                  Part of the load impoſ'd with idle ſcorn
                  On Lybian Simon, in Cyrene born.
                  To whom th'affected quiet of the fields,
                  Secur'd by Poverty, no ſafety yeelds.
                  The Furies of the Citie him ſurpriſe,
                  Who from the vices of the Citie flies:
                  Who beares not his own burden, that none may
                  Miſdoubt, the Innocent became their prey.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  Forth-with unmask this wretched face of Wo:
                  All that he ſuffer'd, and the manner ſhow;
                  What words brake from his ſorrow; give thy tongue
                  A liberall ſcope: Our mindes not ſeldome long
                  To know what they abhorre: nor ſpare our eares;
                  What can be heard, is fancied by our feares.
               
               
                  
                  1. NVNCIVS.
                  
                  With-out the Citie, on that ſide which lies
                  Expoſed to the boyſterous injuries
                  Of the cold North, to War a fatall Way,
                  Infamous by our ſlaughters, Golgotha
                  Exalts his Rock. No flowers there paint the field,
                  Nor flouriſhing trees refreſhing ſhadowes yield:
                  The ground all white, with bones of mortalls ſpread,
                  Stencht with the putrefaction of the dead,
                  And reliques of unburied Carcaſes.
                  Who on his aged Fathers throat durſt ſeaſe,
                  Rip-up his mothers wombe; who poyſon dreſt
                  For his own brother; or his unknown Gueſt
                  Betray'd, and gave his mangled fleſh for food
                  Vnto the wild inhabitants of the Wood;
                  This Stage of Death deſerv'd: while every ſoule
                  Misdeed of theirs purſues the guilty Soule.
                  Now when the Nazarite at this diſmall place
                  Arrived, with a weak and tardy pace;
                  Leaſt he ſhould die too quickly, ſome preferre
                  Sweet wine, mixt with the bitter teares of Myrrhe.
                  He of the idle preſent hardly taſts;
                  But to incounter with his torments haſts.
                  The Steel now bor'd his feet, whoſe ſlit veines ſpout
                  Like pierced conduits; both his armes ſtrechtout.
                  
                  His hands fixt with two nailes. While his great Soule
                  Theſe tortures ſuffer'd, while the riſing Bole
                  Forſook the Earth, and crimſon Torrents ſprung
                  From his freſh wounds, he gave his Grief no tongue.
                  The Croſſe advanc'd and fixt; then, as more nigh
                  To his own Heaven, his eyes bent on the Skie,
                  Among ſuch never to be equal'd woes
                  (Who would beleeve it!) pities his ſtern foes;
                  And thinks thoſe falſe Contrivers, thoſe who gor'd
                  His fleſh with wounds, more fit to be deplor'd:
                  Who even their merited deſtruction feares;
                  And falſely judg'd, the truly guilty cleares.
                  Father, he cries, forgive this ſinne: they knew
                  Not what they did, nor know what now they do.
                  Mean-while the Souldiers, who in bloud delight,
                  With hearts more hard then Rocks, behold this ſight;
                  And ſavage Rigor never reconcil'd
                  To Pitty, all humanitie exil'd:
                  Who, uſ'd to pillage, now intend their prey;
                  Nor for his death, though then a dying, ſtay;
                  But he alive, and looking on, divide
                  The Spoil; yet more in the Spectatour joy'd.
                  Fury in trifles ſports: their ſcorn his poore,
                  Yet parted garments, diſtribute to foure.
                  His inward Robe, with one contexture knit,
                  Nor of the like diviſion would admit,
                  
                  Their votes to the diſpoſe of Lots referre,
                  Electing Chance for their blinde Arbiter.
                  Nor waſt the leaſt of evils to behold
                  Th' ignoble Partners of his pain; who old
                  In miſchief rob'd the murder'd Paſſengers;
                  Follow'd by Troops, that fill'd the Night with feares.
                  While thus they hung, none could the doubt explain,
                  VVhether He more had ſav'd then They had ſlain.
                  The numerous Index of each bloudy deed
                  Now brand their lives: when thoſe who could not read
                  At ſuch a diſtance, of the next inquire
                  For what they dy'd; who had the ſame deſire.
                  But above his declining Head they hung
                  A table in three Languages: the Tongue,
                  The firſt of tongues, which taught our Abrahamites
                  Thoſe heavenly Precepts, and myſterious Rites;
                  Next, that which to th'informed World imparts
                  The Grecian Induſtry, and learned Arts;
                  Then this, from whence the conquer'd Earth now takes
                  Her Lawes, and at the Romane Virtue quakes;
                  All of one ſenſe. His place of birth, his Name
                  Declare; and for the Hebrew King proclame.
                  After the bloudy Prieſts ſo long had fed
                  On this lov'd Spectacle; at length they read
                  The Title: and in ſuch a miſerie,
                  So full of ruth, found ſomething to envy.
                  
                  The Governour intreating to take down
                  That glorious Stile; leſt he the Hebrew Crown
                  Should vindicate in Death; and ſo deny
                  That Princes by Subordinates ſhould die.
                  But who that Day ſoreadily compli'd
                  To give a life, auſterely this deni'd.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  While lingring Death his ſad releaſe deferr'd,
                  How lookt the ſtanders by? what words were heard?
               
               
                  I. NVNCIVS.
                  Not all alike: diſcording murmurs riſe.
                  Some, with transfixed hearts, and wounded eyes,
                  Aſtoniſht ſtand: ſome joy in his ſlow fate,
                  And to the laſt extend their Barbarous hate.
                  Motion it ſelf variety begets,
                  And by a ſtrange viciſſitude regrets
                  What it affected, nor one poſture beares:
                  Teares ſcornfull laughter raiſe, and laughter teares.
                  Who to the Temple from th'impoveriſht ſhore
                  Of Galilee his followed ſteps adore,
                  And miniſtred to his life, now of his End
                  The Witneſſes; ſtill to their dying friend
                  Their faith preſerve: which, as they could, they ſhow
                  In all th'expreſſions of a perfect woe.
                  
                  One, from her panting breſt her garments tare;
                  Another, the bright treſſes of her haire;
                  This, with her naked armes her boſome beats;
                  The hollow rock Her fearfull ſhriekes repeat;
                  She, ſtiff with ſorrow. But what grief could vie
                  With that example of all piety,
                  His virgin Mothers! this affords no way
                  To leſſening teares; nor could it ſelf diſplay.
                  Where ſhould ſhe fix her looks! if on the ground;
                  She ſees that with her bloud, he bleeding, drown'd:
                  Or if ſhe raiſe her eyes; the killing ſight
                  Of her wombes tort'red Iſſue quencht their light.
                  Fearing to look on either, both diſcloſe
                  Their terrours; who now licences her woes.
                  Ready to have ſtept forward, and imbraſt
                  The bloudy Croſſe, her feeble lims ſtuck faſt:
                  Her feet their motion loſt; her voice in vain
                  A paſſage ſought: ſuch Grief could not complain.
                  Whoſe Soul almoſt as great a Sorrow ſtung,
                  As his, who on the Tree in torments hung.
                  That Youth, one of the Twelve, ſo dignifi'd
                  By his deare Maſters love, ſtood by her ſide.
                  Beholding this ſad Paire, thoſe Souls that were
                  To him then life, while life remain'd, more deare;
                  He found an other Croſſe: his ſpirits melt
                  More for the ſorrow ſeen, then torments felt.
                  
                  At length, in ſtrength tranſcending either, brake
                  The barres of his long ſilence, and thus ſpake:
                  A legacie to each of you I leave:
                  Mother, this ſonne in ſtead of me receave
                  By thy adoption: and thou gentle boy,
                  The ſeed of Zebedeus, late my joy,
                  Thy friend now for thy mother take. This ſaid,
                  Again he to his torments bow'd his Head.
                  The Vulgar with the Elders of our Race,
                  And Souldiers, ſhake their heads in his diſgrace:
                  Is this the man, ſaid they, whoſe hands can raiſe
                  The Temple, and rebuild it in three dayes?
                  Now ſhew thy ſtrength. Or if the Thunderer
                  Above the rank of Mortalls thee preferre,
                  Acknowledg'd for his Heir; let him deſcend,
                  Confirme thy hopes, and timely ſuccour lend.
                  Behold, the help thou gav'ſt to others, failes
                  The Authour. Break theſe Bonds, theſe ſtubborn Nails,
                  And from the Croſſe deſcend: then we will ſay
                  Thou art our King, and thy Commands obey.
                  Nor waſt enough that the ſurrounding Throng
                  Wound with reproches: Who beſides him hung,
                  Doth now again a murderers minde diſcloſe;
                  And in his puniſhment more wicked growes.
                  Who thus: If thou be he whom God did chooſe
                  To Govern the free'd Nation of the Jews,
                  
                  Thy ſelf, and us releaſe: thus honour win.
                  The Partner of his death, as of his ſinne,
                  Who had his fierceneſſe, with the thief, caſt-off,
                  Ill brookes, and thus reprooves, that impious ſcoff:
                  Haſt thou as yet not learnt to acknowledge God?
                  Nor ſacred Juſtice fear? who now the rod
                  Of vengeance feel'ſt? wilt thou again offend,
                  And to the jaws of Hell thy guilt extend?
                  This death we owe to our impiety:
                  But what are his miſdeeds? why ſhould he die?
                  Then looking on his face with dropping eyes:
                  Forgive me, O forgive a wretch, he cries:
                  And O my Lord, my King, when thou ſhalt be
                  Reſtor'd to thy own Heaven, remember me.
                  He mildly gives conſent; and from the barres
                  Of that ſad Croſſe, thus raiſ'd him to the Starres:
                  With me, a happy Gueſt, thou ſhalt injoy
                  Thoſe ſacred Orchards where no froſts deſtroy
                  The eternall Spring, before the Morne diſplay
                  The purple Enſigne of th' enſuing Day.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  What's this! the Centre pants with ſudden throwes!
                  And trembling Earth a ſad diſtemper ſhowes!
                  The Sun, affrighted, hides his golden Head;
                  From hence by an unknown Ecliptick fled!
                  
                  Irregular Heavens abortive ſhades diſplay;
                  And Night uſurpes the empty Throne of Day!
                  What threats do theſe dire Prodigies portend
                  To our offending Race! Thoſe ills tranſcend
                  All that can be imagin'd, which inforce
                  Diſturbed Nature to forget her Courſe.
                  I heare approaching feet: What ere thou art,
                  Whom darkneſſe from our ſight conceales, impart
                  All that thou know'ſt to our prepared eares:
                  Accompliſh, or diſſolve our preſſing feares.
               
               
                  II NVNCIVS.
                  Fury (from which, if looſe, the Earth had fled)
                  And fatall Starres have their event: He's dead.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  O Heaven! we pardon now Dayes haſty flight;
                  Nor will complain, ſince they have quencht this light.
                  Yet tell how he diſpoſ'd of his laſt breath;
                  The paſſages, and order of his death.
               
               
                  II NVNCIVS.
                  As the declining Sun the ſhades increaſt,
                  Reflecting on the more removed Eaſt,
                  His blazing haire grew black: no clouds obſcures
                  His vaniſht Light; this his own Orb immures.
                  
                  The Dayes fourth part as yet inveſts the Pole,
                  Were this a Day; when from the afflicted Soule
                  This voice was clearely heard, not like the breath
                  Of thoſe who labour between life and death;
                  My God, O why doſt thou thy own forſake!
                  VVhich purpoſely the Multitude miſtake,
                  But to prolong their cruel mirth; who ſaid,
                  He on the Thesbian Prophet calls for aid;
                  Now to return, and draw from Heaven again
                  Devouring Showres of Fire, or Flouds of Rain.
                  VVith ſilence this he indures. His body rent,
                  His bloud exhauſted, and his Spirits ſpent,
                  He cry'd; I Thirſt. As ſervants to his will,
                  The greedy hollowes of a ſpunge they fill
                  VVith vineger, which Hyſſops ſprigs combine,
                  And on a reed exalt the deadly Wine.
                  This ſcarcely taſted, his pale lips once more
                  He opens, and now lowder then before
                  Cry'd, All is finiſht; here my labours end:
                  To thee, O heavenly Father, I commend
                  My parting Soul. This ſaid, hung down his head;
                  And with his words his mixed Spirits fled:
                  Leaving his body, which again muſt bleed,
                  Now ſenſeleſſe of the Croſſe. From priſon freed,
                  Thoſe happy ſeats he injoyes, by God aſſign'd
                  To injur'd Vertue, and th'etheriall Minde.
                  
                  But Terrours, which with Nature war, affright
                  Our peaceleſſe Souls. The World hath loſt its Light:
                  Heaven, and the Deeps below, our Guilt purſue:
                  Pale troops of wandring Ghoſts now hurrie through
                  The holy Citie; whom, from her unknown
                  And ſecret Wombe, the trembling Earth hath thrown.
                  The cleaving Rocks their horrid jawes diſplay:
                  And yawning Tombes afford the dead a way
                  To thoſe that live. Heaven is the generall
                  And undiſtinguiſht Sepulcher to all.
                  Old Chaos now returnes. Ambitious Night
                  Impatient of alternate Rule, or Right,
                  Such as before the Dayes etheriall birth,
                  With her own ſhady People fills the Earth.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  How did the many-minded People look
                  At theſe Portents? with what affection ſtrook?
               
               
                  II. NVNCIVS.
                  The Lamentations, mixed with the cries
                  Of weeping Women, in low'd Vollies riſe.
                  Thoſe who had known him, who his followers were
                  While yet he liv'd, and did in death adhere,
                  In that new Night ſighs from their ſorrowes ſend;
                  And to thoſe Heavens they could not ſee, extend
                  
                  Their pious hands; complaining that the Sun
                  Would then appeare when this was to be done.
                  The ſafety of their lives the Vulgar dread:
                  Some for themſelves lament, ſome for the dead;
                  Others the ruine of the world bewaile.
                  Their Courages the cruel Romanes faile:
                  Thoſe hands, which knew no peace, now lazie grew;
                  And conquering Feare to earth their weapons threw.
                  Th'amaz'd Centurion with our thoughts compli'd;
                  And ſwore the Heros moſt unjuſtly dy'd:
                  Whoſe puniſhment the Earth could hardly brook,
                  But groaning, with a horrid motion ſhook.
                  Confirmed by the Dayes prodigious flight
                  To be a beame of the celeſtiall Light:
                  And ſo the mourning Heavens inverted face,
                  Showes to the Vnder world his Heavenly Race.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  Why flock the People to the Temple thus?
                  No cauſe, excepting piety, in us
                  Can want belief. Hope they to ſatisfie
                  With Sacrifice the Wrath of the moſt High?
               
               
                  II. NVNCIVS.
                  New prodigies, as horrid, thither hale
                  Th'aſtoniſht Multitude. The Temples Vale
                  
                  That hung on guilded Beames in purple dy'd,
                  Aſunder rent, and fell on either ſide.
                  The truſt of what was ſacred is betray'd;
                  And all the Hebrew Myſteries diſplay'd.
                  That fatall Ark, ſo terrible of old
                  To our palefoes, which Cherubins of Gold
                  Veil'd with their hovering wings; whoſe cloſure held
                  Thoſe two-leav'd Tables, wherein Godreveal'd
                  His ſacred Lawes; That Food which by a new
                  Example fell from Heaven in fruitfull Dew
                  About our Tents, and tacidly expreſt
                  By intermitted ſhowres the ſeventh Dayes reſt;
                  The Rod with never dying bloſſoms ſpread;
                  Which with a Miter honour Aarons Head:
                  Theſe, with th'old Temple periſht: Th'eye could reach
                  No object in this rupture, but the Breach.
                  What was from former Ageshid, is ſhown;
                  Which ſtruck ſo great a reverence when unknown.
                  The Temple ſhines with flames; and to the ſight
                  That fear'd Receſſe diſcloſ'd with its own Light.
                  Either Religion from their fury flies,
                  Leaving it naked to profaner eyes:
                  Or God doth this abhorred Seat reject,
                  And will his Temple in the Minde erect.
               
               
                  
                  CHORVS.
                  Shall Puniſhment in Death yet finde an end?
                  Shall his cold Corps to earth in peace deſcend?
                  Or naked hang, and with ſo dire a ſight
                  Profane the Vefper of the ſacred Night?
               
               
                  II. NVNCIVS.
                  Too late Religion warmes their ſavage breſts,
                  Leſt that neare Houre, which harbengers their Feaſt;
                  Should take them unprepar'd: to Pilat they
                  Repaire; intreat him that the Souldier may
                  From bloudy croſſes take their bodies down,
                  Before their Feſtivalls the Morning crown:
                  That no uncleanneſſe might from thence ariſe;
                  In memory of th' Aegyptian Sacrifice.
                  The leggs of the two Thieves, they brake, whoſe breath
                  Yet groan'd between the bounds of life and death.
                  The craſhing bones report a dreadfull ſound;
                  While both their ſouls at once a paſſage found.
                  Nor had the Cohortleſſe to Jeſus done,
                  Who now the Courſepreſcrib'd by Fate had runne:
                  But dead, deep in his ſide his trembling ſpeare
                  A Souldier ſtrake: his entrails bare appeare;
                  And from that wide-mouth'd Orifice, a floud
                  Of water guſht, mixt with a ſtream of bloud.
                  
                  The Croſſes now diſcharged of their fraught,
                  The People fled; not with one look or thought:
                  Part ſad, and part amaz'd. Spent Fury dies.
                  Whither ſo faſt? run you to ſacrifice
                  A ſilly Lambe? too mean an Offering
                  Is this for you, who have ſacrific'd your King.
               
               
                  CHORVS.
                  Either deceiv'd by the ambiguous Day,
                  Or troops of mourners to my eyes diſplay
                  A perfect Sorrow: Women with their bare
                  And bleeding breſts, drown'd cheeks, disſheveld haire.
                  The Souldiers ſlowly march, with knees that bend
                  Beneath their feares, and Pilats ſtaires aſcend.
               
               
                  CHORVS OF ROMANE SOVLDIERS.
                  O Thou who on thy flaming Charriot rid'ſt,
                  And with perpetuall Motion Time divid'ſt;
                  Great King of Day, from whoſe farre-darting Eye
                  Night-wandring Stars with fainting Splendor flie;
                  Whither, thus intercepted, doſt thou ſtray!
                  Through what an unknown darkneſſe lies thy way!
                  In Heaven, what new-born Night the Day invades!
                  The Mariner that ſails by Tyrian Gades,
                  
                  As yet ſees not thy panting Horſes ſteepe
                  Their fiery fet-locks in th'Heſperian Deep.
                  No pitchy ſtorme, wrapt up in ſwelling Clouds
                  By Earth exhal'd, thy golden Treſſes ſhrouds:
                  Nor thy pale Siſter in her wandring Race
                  With interpoſed wheeles obſcures thy Face;
                  But now farre-off retires with her ſtolne Light,
                  Till in a ſilver Orbe her hornes unite.
                  Hath ſome Theſſalian Witch with Charms unknown
                  Surpriz'd and bound thee! What new Phaëton
                  With feeble hands to guide thy Charriot ſtrives,
                  And farre from the deſerted Zodiack drives!
                  What horrid fact, before th' approach of Night.
                  Deſervedly deprives the World of Light!
                  As when ſtern Atreus to his Brother gave
                  His Childrens fleſh, who made his owne their grave:
                  Or when the Veſtall Ilia's God-like Sun,
                  Who our unbounded Monarchie begun,
                  Was in a hundred pieces cut; by theft
                  At once of Life and Funerals bereft.
                  Or hath that Day wherein the Gods were borne
                  Finiſh'd the Courſe of Heaven in its returne;
                  And now the aged Stars refuſe to run
                  Beyond that place from whence they firſt begun!
                  Nature, what plagues doſt thou to thine intend!
                  Whither ſhrinks this hugh Maſſe! what fatall end!
                  
                  If now the Generall Floud againe retire,
                  If the World periſh by licentious Fire,
                  What ſhall of thoſe devouring Seas become!
                  Where ſhall thoſe funerall Aſhes finde a Tomb!
                  What ever innovates the Courſe of Things,
                  To men alone, nor Nations, ruine brings:
                  Either the groaning Worlds diſordered Frame
                  Now ſuffers, or that Power which guides the ſame.
                  Doe proud Titanians with their impious War
                  Again provoke th' Olympian Thunderer?
                  Is there a miſchiefe extant, greater then
                  Dire Python, or the Snake of Lerna's Fen,
                  That poyſons the pure Heavens with Viperous breath?
                  What God, from Gods deriv'd, oppreſt by Death,
                  Is now in his own Heaven bewail'd? Divine
                  Lyeus gave to man leſſe precious Wine;
                  Not Hercules ſo many Monſters flew;
                  Vnſhorne Apollo leſſe in Phyſick knew.
                  Sure we with darkneſſe are invelloped
                  Becauſe that innocent bloud by Envy ſhed,
                  So deare unto the Gods, this place defam'd:
                  VVhich ſhook the Earth, and made the Day aſham'd.
                  Great Father of us all, whoſe Influence
                  Informes the World thou mad'ſt; though Sin incenſe
                  Thy juſt diſpleaſure, eaſie to forgive
                  Thoſe who confeſſe, and for their Vices grieve;
                  
                  Now to the deſperate Sons of men, who ſtray
                  In ſinnes dark Labyrinth, reſtore the Day.
                  One Sacrifice ſeek we to expiate
                  All our Offences, and appeaſe his hate.
                  VVhich the Religion of the Samian,
                  Nor Thracian Harpe, wild beaſts inſtructing, can;
                  Nor that Prophetick Boy, the Gleabs ſwart ſon,
                  VVho taught the Thuſcans Divination.
                  The Bloud, which from that mangled body bled,
                  Muſt purge our ſins, which we unjuſtly ſhed.
                  O ſmooth thy brows! Receive the innocence
                  Of one for all; and with our guilt diſpence.
                  For ſin, what greater Ranſome can we pay?
                  VVhat worthier Offering on thy Altar lay?
               
            
            
               
               THE FIFTH ACT.
               JOSEPH OF ARIMATHEA. NICODEMVS.
               
                  SEe, Citizens, we Pilats bounty beare:
                  With-out a ſuite men cannot man interre.
                  The Romane Progeny nor freely will
                  Doe what is good; nor, unrewarded ill.
                  Nothing is now in uſe but barbarous Vice:
                  They ſell our bloud, on graves they ſet a price.
               
               
                  NICODEMVS.
                  O Joſeph, theſe vaine extaſies refraine:
                  But if it ſeeme ſo pleaſant to Complaine,
                  Let Rome alone, and ſeek a neerer guilt:
                  His bloud not Romulus ſons, but Abrahams ſpilt.
                  VVho ſo the purer ſenſe ſincerely draws
                  From thoſe celeſtiall Oracles and Lawes,
                  By God above himſelfe inſpir'd, will ſay
                  None led to Eternitie a ſtraighter way.
                  VVhat's that to Pilat? fell the Innocent by
                  A Romane Oath? was't through the ſubtilty
                  Of Senators or Prieſts? The Doome diſplay'd
                  They Caeſarleſſe then Caiaphas obay'd.
                  
                  Let us transferre the fact; the impious Jew
                  VVith heart, with tongue and eyes, firſt Jeſus ſlew:
                  The Romans onely acted their Offence.
                  How well the Heavens with Hebrew hands diſpence!
                  For this the Jew th'Italians Crime envi'd,
                  And wiſh'd himſelfe the bloody Homicide.
                  Doe we as yet our ſervitude lament,
                  VVhen ſuch a murder meets no puniſhment?
                  This doe they, this command.
               
               
                  JOSEPH.
                  The Progeny
                  Of Romane Ilia, and of Sara, I
                  VVith equall deteſtation execrate.
                  O may they periſh by a fearefull Fate!
                  Juſt Heaven, why ſleepes thy Lightning! in a Showre
                  Of pitch deſcend: Let ſtenching Seas de youre
                  This curſed City. Sodome, thou art cleare,
                  Compar'd to ours. No more will I a teare
                  Shed for my Countrey. Let the Great in War,
                  VVorſe then the Babylonian Conquerar,
                  Enter her Breaches like a violent Floud,
                  Vntill the bloudy City ſwim in bloud.
                  Is this too little? Let Diſeaſes ſow
                  Their fruitfull Seed, and in deſtruction grow:
                  
                  Famine, in their dry entrailes take thy ſeat;
                  VVhat Nature moſt abhors, inforce to eat.
                  Let th' Infant tremble at his Fathers knife;
                  The Babe re-enter her who gave it Life.
                  VVhile yet the eager Foe inveſts the wall,
                  VVithin may they by their own weapons fall:
                  The Temple wrapt in flames. Let th' Enemy
                  Decide their Civill Diſcord, and deſtroy
                  VVith fire and ſword ungratefull Solyma:
                  The reliques of their ſlaughter drive away;
                  Nor ſeventy yeers diſſolve their ſervill bands;
                  Deſpiſ'd, and wretched, wander through all Lands:
                  Aboliſh'd be their Law; all forme of State:
                  No Day ſee their returne. Let ſudden Fate
                  Succeed my curſes. This infected Soyle
                  No more ſhall feed me. What unuſuall toyle
                  Shall my old feet refuſe, ſo they no more
                  Tread on this Earth! though to that unknown ſhore,
                  VVhich lyes beneath the ſlow Bootes VVaine,
                  Daſht by th' unconſtant billows of that Maine.
                  That Countrey ſhall be mine, where Juſtice ſwayes;
                  And bold Integrity the Truth obayes.
               
               
                  NICODEMVS.
                  This Error with a ſecret poyſon feeds
                  The minds Diſeaſe. VVho cenſures his own deeds?
                  
                  VVho not anothers? Theſe accuſing Times
                  Rather the men condemne, then taxe their Crimes.
                  Such is the Tyranny of Judgement; prone
                  To ſentence all Offences, but our owne.
                  Becauſe of late we cry'd not Crucifie,
                  Nor falſely doom'd the Innocent to die,
                  Our ſelves we pleaſe: as it a Vertue were;
                  And Great one, if from great Offences cleare.
                  Confeſſe; what Orator would plead his Cauſe?
                  To vindicate his truth who urg'd the Laws?
                  Or once accuſ'd their bloudy ſuffrages,
                  By Envy ſign'd? VVho durſt thoſe Lords diſpleaſe?
                  So Piety ſuffer'd, while by ſpeaking they,
                  And we by ſilence, did the Juſt betray.
                  VVhen women openly their zeale durſt ſhow,
                  VVe, in acknowledging our Maſter, ſlow,
                  Vnder the ſhady coverture of Night
                  Secur'd our feares, which would not brook the Light.
                  Joſeph, at length our faith it ſelfe expreſt;
                  But to the Dead.
               
               
                  JOSEPH.
                  This is a truth confeſt.
                  The Evening now reſtored Day ſubdues:
                  And lo, the Vigil with the Night enſeues.
                  
                  Not farre from Golgotha's in famous Rocks
                  A Cave there is, hid with the ſhady Locks
                  Of funerall Cypreſſe, hewne through living ſtone:
                  The houſe of Death; as yet poſſeſt by none.
                  My Age this choſe for her eternall reſt:
                  VVhich now ſhall entertaine a nobler Gueſt.
                  That ample Stone which ſhuts the Sepulcher,
                  Shall the inſcription of his Vertues beare.
                  VVho knows but ſoon a holier Age may come,
                  VVhen all the World ſhall celebrate this Tombe;
                  And Kings as in a Temple hereadore;
                  Through fire and ſword ſought from the fartheſt Shore?
               
               
                  NICODEMVS.
                  Pure water of the Spring, you precious Tears,
                  Perfumes which Odor-breathing Saba beares,
                  VVith your preſervatives his body lave,
                  Sinke through his pores, and from corruption ſave.
                  Nor God, nor Fate will ſuffer, that this pure,
                  This ſacred Corps, ſhould more then death indure.
                  Religion, if thou know'ſt the Shades below,
                  Let never filthy putrefaction flow
                  Through his uncover'd bones; nor waſt of Time
                  Reſolve this beavenly figure into ſlime.
               
               
               JOHN. MARY THE MOTHER OF JESVS.
               
                  THou reverent Virgin, of his royall Bloud,
                  Who all between the Erythrean Floud
                  And great Euphrates won by ſtrenuous Armes:
                  Aſſume his noble fortitude; thoſe harmes
                  Which preſſe thy Soul, ſubdue: ungentle Fate
                  Hath by undoing thee ſecur'd thy ſtate.
                  Fortune her ſtrength by her own blowes hath ſpent.
                  Judaea's kingdome from thy Fathers rent
                  By forrein hands; of ancient Wealth bereft;
                  Except thy Son, what was for danger left?
                  Theſe ſtormes by death diſperſt, ſerene appeare:
                  For what hath childleſſe Poverty to feare?
               
               
                  MARY.
                  O John, for thee in ſuch extreames to mourn
                  Perhaps is new: but I to grief was born.
                  With this have we convers't twice ſixteen yeares:
                  No form of ſorrow hath beguil'd our feares.
                  To me how ominouſly the Prophets ſung,
                  Even from the time that heavenly Infant ſprung
                  In my chaſte Wombe! Old Simeon this reveal'd;
                  And in my Soul the deadly wound beheld.
                  
                  When One, among ſo many Infants ſlain,
                  Was by the Tyrants Weapons ſought in vain,
                  No miracles had then his fame diſplaid,
                  Or him the object of their envy made.
                  Perfidious Fraud in Sanctities diſguiſe,
                  Nor the adulterated Phariſies,
                  By his detection had he yet inflam'd;
                  Nor for deſpiſing of their Rites defam'd;
                  A Trumpet of inteſtine Warre: the Earth
                  Of nothing then accuſ'd him, but his birth.
                  Not that fierce Prince, ſo cruell to his Own;
                  Nor his Succeſſour in that fatall Throne,
                  As high in vice, who with the Prophets Head
                  Suppli'd his Feaſt, and on the bloud he had ſhed
                  Fed his inceſtuous eyes, in dire delight
                  To highthen impious Love, could me affright:
                  Nor yet the vulgar, hating his free tongue;
                  And ſhowres of ſtones by a thouſand Furies flung.
                  I though no miſchief could our ſteps purſue,
                  That was more great; or to our ſufferings new.
                  What wants example, what no mother fear'd;
                  This, this alone my dying hopes inter'd.
                  Wretch, wilt thou ſeek for words t'expreſſe thy woes!
                  Or this ſo vaſt a grief in ſilence cloſe!
                  Great God (ſuch is my faith) why wouldſt thou come
                  To this inferiour Kingdome through my wombe!
                  
                  Why mad'ſt thou choice of me to bring thee forth
                  For puniſhment! unhappy in my worth!
                  No woman ever bare a Son, by touch
                  Of man conceiv'd, whoſe Soule indures ſo much:
                  No mother ſuch an iſſue better gain'd;
                  Nor loſt it worſe; by curſed Death profan'd.
               
               
                  JOHN.
                  What lowder grief with ſuch an emphaſis
                  Strikes through mine eares! What honour'd Corſe is this,
                  With Tyrian linen vail'd? What's he whoſe haires
                  Contend with ſnow, whoſe cies look through their tears,
                  Who on thoſe veins, yet bleeding, odors powres?
                  Or his aſſiſtant, crown'd with equall houres?
                  What troops of women hither throng! what ſtormes
                  Riſe in their looks! Grief wanders through all formes.
                  My eyes, ah! wound my Heart. This was thy ſon;
                  This is thy bloud, thy mangled fleſh. O run,
                  Take thy laſt kiſſes, ere of thoſe bereft
                  By funerall: What elſe of all is left?
               
               
                  MARY.
                  My Soul, tyr'd with long miſerie,
                  A midſt theſe greater Sorrows die;
                  While Grief at his ſad Exequies
                  Poures out her laſt Complaints in theſe.
                  
                  Let me this ſnowy Paul unfold,
                  Once more thoſe quickning looks behold.
                  O Son, born to a ſad event;
                  Thus, thus, to thy poore Mother ſent!
                  O Salem, was thy hatred ſuch,
                  To murder him who lov'd ſo much!
                  Ah ſee, his ſide gor'd with a ſpear!
                  Thoſe hands, that late ſo bounteous were,
                  Transfixt! his feet pierc'd with one wound!
                  The Sun had better never found
                  His loſſe, then with reſtored light
                  To ſhew the World ſo dire a ſight.
                  You Neighbours to the Suns up-riſe,
                  Who read their motions in the Skies;
                  O you in chief who found your Lord,
                  And with ſuch lively Zeal ador'd,
                  Now view the Heavens inverted laws:
                  With me bewail the wretched Cauſe.
                  His Birth a Starre, new kindled, ſign'd:
                  To ſee his Death the Sun grew blinde.
                  Thou hope of my afflicted State;
                  Thou living, I accus'd not Fate:
                  The Day again with light is crown'd,
                  But thou in Night for ever drown'd.
                  O could'ſt thou ſee my broken heart!
                  The flowing teares theſe ſprings impart!
                  
                  Thy mother, whom man never knew;
                  Who by the Word then fruitfull grew:
                  My Womb admir'd that unknown Gueſt,
                  Whoſe burden for nine Moones increaſt.
                  Thy Mother, to a Scepter borne,
                  With age and wrinkling ſorrow worne,
                  This Countrey ſees to get her bread
                  With labour, in an humble Shed.
                  Thy milk from theſe two fountaines ſprung:
                  Theſe armes about my neck have hung,
                  Coucht on the flowry bancks of Nile:
                  Aegypt, ſo juſt to thy exile,
                  Hath now redeem'd her former Curſe;
                  Our Jews then thoſe of Memphis worſe.
                  If his chaſt bloud at length aſſwage
                  The bitter tempeſt of your rage;
                  If you can pitty miſery,
                  O let me by your mercy dye:
                  Or, if not glutted with his bloud;
                  With mine increaſe this purple floud.
                  O my deare ſonne! what here our eyes behold,
                  What yonder hung, or what Death could infold
                  In endleſſe Night; is mine, and onely mine:
                  No mortall did in thy conception joyne,
                  Nor part of thee can challenge: Since the loſſe
                  Was onely ours, let us the griefe ingroſſe.
                  
                  Vngratefull Man! who his Protector ſlew:
                  Nor feels his Curſe, nor then his Bleſſing knew.
                  Poore wretch! no ſoule in thy defence durſt riſe:
                  And now the murdred unrevenged lies.
                  The Lame, who by thy powerfull Charmes were made
                  Sound and ſwift-footed, ran not to thy aide:
                  Thoſe Eies, which never ſaw the glorious Light
                  Before thy ſoveraign touch, avoid thy ſight:
                  And others, from Deaths ſilent manſion by
                  Thy Vertue raviſh'd, ſuffer'd thee to dye.
               
               
                  JOHN.
                  Too true is thy Complaint, too juſt thy Woes:
                  Such were his friends, whom from a World he choſe.
                  O deſperate Faith! from whence, from whom are we
                  Thus falne! our Soules from no defection free!
                  Some ſold, forſwore him; none from tainture cleare;
                  All from him fled to follow their owne feare.
                  Thou Oracle! a father in thy care,
                  In love a brother, the delinquent ſpare,
                  In thy divine affection ô too bleſt!
                  Whom Yeſter-night ſaw leaning on thy breſt:
                  If Love in death ſurvive, if yet as great;
                  Even by that Love thy pardon I intreat:
                  By this thy weeping Mother: I the Heire
                  By thee adopted to thy filiall care,
                  
                  Though alike wretched, and as comfortleſſe;
                  Yet, as I can, will comfort her diſtreſſe.
                  O Virgin-mother, favour thy Reliefe;
                  Though juſt, yet moderate thy flowing griefe:
                  Thy downe-caſt Minde by thy owne Vertue raiſe.
                  Th'old Prophets fill their Volumes with thy praiſe:
                  No Age but ſhall through all the round of Earth
                  Sing of that heavenly Love, and ſacred Birth.
                  What female glory parallels thy Worth!
                  So grew a Mother, ſuch a Son brought forth!
                  She who prov'd fruitfull in th'extreame of age,
                  And found the truth of that deſpiſ'd preſage:
                  She, whoſe ſweet Babe, expoſ'd among the reeds
                  Which ancient Nilus with his moiſture feeds,
                  Who then, a ſmiling Infant, overcame
                  The threatning floud; aſpir'd not to thy fame,
                  But theſe expreſſions are for thee too low;
                  The op'ning Heavens did their obſervance ſhow:
                  Thoſe radiant Troopes, which Darkneſſe put to flight,
                  Thy Throws aſliſted in that feſtive Night:
                  Who over thy adored Infant hung
                  With golden wings, and Allelu jah's ſung:
                  While the Old Sky, to imitate that birth,
                  Bare a new Starre to amaze the wondring Earth.
               
               
                  
                  MARY.
                  Sorrow is fled: Joy, a long baniſh'd Gueſt,
                  With heavenly rapture fill's my inlarged breſt:
                  More great then that in youth, when from the Sky
                  An Angel brought that bleſſed Embaſſy;
                  When Shame, not ſoon inſtructed, bluſh'd for feare,
                  How I a Son by ſuch a Fate ſhould beare.
                  I greater things fore-ſee: my eyes behold
                  What ever is by Deſtiny inrold.
                  With troops of pious Soules, more great then they,
                  Thou to felicity ſhalt lead the way.
                  A holy People ſhall obey thy Throne;
                  And Heaven it ſelfe ſurrender thee thy own.
                  Subjected Death thy Triumph now attends,
                  While thou from thy demoliſh'd Tombe aſcends.
                  Nor ſhalt thou long be ſeene by mortall eies,
                  But in perfection mount above the Skies;
                  Propitious ever, from that heighth ſhalt give
                  Peace to the World, inſtructed how to live.
                  A thouſand Languages ſhall thee adore:
                  Thy Empire know no bounds. The fartheſt Shore
                  Waſht by the Ocean, thoſe who Dayes bright Flame
                  Scarce warmes, ſhall heare the thunder of thy Name.
                  Licentious ſword, nor hoſtill Fury, ſhall
                  Prevaile againſt thee: thou, the Lord of all.
                  
                  Thoſe Tyrants, whom the vanquiſht Worlds obay,
                  Before thy feete ſhall Caeſars Scepter lay.
                  The Time draws on, in which it ſelfe muſt end,
                  When thou ſhalt in a Throne of Clouds deſcend
                  To judge the Earth. In that reformed World,
                  Thoſe by their ſins infected, ſhall be hurl'd
                  Downe under one perpetuall Night; while they
                  Whom thou haſt cleanſ'd, injoy perpetuall Day.
               
            
            The End.
         
         
            
            THe Tragedie of CHRIST'S PASSION was firſt written in Greek by Apollinarius of Laodicea,, Biſhop of Hieropolis: and after him by Gregory Nazianzen; though this, now extant in his Works, is by ſome aſcribed to the former: by others accounted ſuppoſititious, as not agreeing with his Strain in the reſt of his Poems; which might alter in that particular upon his imitation of Euripides. But Hugo Grotius, of late hath tranſcended all on this Argument: whoſe ſteps afar-off I follow.
            
               
               ANNOTATIONS VPON THE FIRST ACT.
               
                  VErſe 23. Ephratian Dames]
                  Of Ephrata, the ſame with Bethlehem.
                  
                  Ver. 33. Magi]
                  Tradition will have them three, of ſeverall Nations, and honour them with crownes. But the word delivers them for Perſians, for ſo they called their Philoſophers; ſuch as were skilfull in the Coeleſtiall Motions, from whence they drew their predictions: and with whom their Princes conſulted in all matters of moment. Some write that they were of the poſteritie of Balaam, by his Propheſies informed of the birth of Chriſt, and apparition of that narrative Starre: but more conſonant to the Truth, that they received it from divine inſpiration.
                  Ver. 34. My Starre]
                   None of thoſe which adorne the Firmament; nor Comet, proceeding from condenſed Vapors inflamed in the Aire; but above Nature, and meerely miraculous: which, as they write, not onely illuminated the eye, but the underſtanding; excited thereby to that heavenly inquiſition. Some will have it an Angel in that forme. The excellencie whereof is thus deſcribed by Prudentius.
                     
                     
                        This, which in Beames and Beauty far
                        Exceld the Sunnes flame-bearing Car,
                        Shew'd Gods deſcent from Heaven to Earth,
                        Accepting of a humane Birth.
                        No ſervant to the humerous Night,
                        Nor following Phoebe's changing Light;
                        But didſt thy ſingle Lamp diſplay
                        To guide the Motion of the Day.
                     
                     Hym Epiphaniae.
It is probable that this Starre continued not above thirteene dayes, if we may beleeve that Tradition, How the Magi were ſo long in travelling from their Countrey unto Bethlehem.
                  
                  Ver. 34. Mithra's flame]
                   
                     Mithra: the ſame with the Sunne, adored by the Perſians. His Image had the countenance of a Lion, with a Tiara on his head, depreſſing an Oxe by the hornes. Of this Statius
                     
                        Come, O remember thy owne Temple; prove
                        Propitious ſtill, and Juno's Citie love:
                        Whether we ſhould thee roſy Titan call;
                        Oſyris, Lord of Ceres feſtivall;
                        Or Mithra ſhrin'd in Perſian rocks, a Bull,
                        Subduing by the horror of his skull.
                     
                     Thebaid. l. 1.
And in a Cave his Rites were ſolemnized: from

whence they drew an Oxe by the hornes; which, after the ſinging of certaine Paeans, was ſacrificed to the Sun, Zoraſtes placeth him between Oremazes and Arimanius, the good and bad Daemon, from which he took that denomination.
                  Verſ. 39. Phariſees]
                  A preciſe Sect among the Iews, ſeparating themſelves from others in habit, manners, and converſation: from whence they had their Name; as their Originall from Antigonus Sochaeus, who was contemporary with Alexander the Great. Men full of appearing Sanctitie; obſervant to Traditions, and skilfull expoſitors of the Moyſaicall Law: wearing the Precepts thereof in Phylacters (narrow ſcroules of parchment) bound about their browes, and above their left elbowes: paſſing thorow the ſtreets with a ſlow motion, their eyes fixed on the ground, as if ever in divine contemplations: and wincking at the approach of women, by meanes whereof they not ſeldome met with churliſh incounters. Superſtitious in their often waſhing, keeping their bodies cleaner then their ſoules. They held that all was governed by God and Fate; yet that man had the power in himſelfe to doe good or evill: That his Soule was immortall; that after the death of the body, if good, it returned into an other more excellent; but if evill, condemned to perpetuall torments.
                  Verſ. 43. Sadduces]
                   Theſe derived the Sect and name from Sadock, the ſcholar of Antigonus
                     
Socaeus: as he his Hereſie by miſinterpreting the words of his Maſter; that we ſhould not ſerve God as ſervants, in hope of reward: concluding thereupon that in another World there was no reward for Pietie, and conſequently no reſurrection: holding the Soul to be annihilated after the death of the Body herein agreeing with the Stoicks.

                        As ſmoke from trembling flames aſcends, and there,
                        Loſt in its liberty, reſolves to aire;
                        As empty Clouds, which furious tempeſts chace,
                        Conſume and vaniſh in their aiery race;
                        So our commanding Souls fleet with our breath:
                        After Death nothing reſts; and nothing Death,
                        But of ſwift Life the Gole. Ambition lay
                        Thy hopes aſide; nor Care our peace betray.
                        Inquir'ſt thou to what place thou ſhalt return
                        VVhen dead? To that, where lie the yet Vnborn.
                     
                     Seneca in Troad.
They held that there was neither Spirits nor Angels; rejected all Traditions; and onely allowed of the five books of Moſes; that there was no ſuch thing as Fate; that no evil proceeded from God; and that Vertue and Vice were in our own Arbitrements. The Phariſees were ſociable among themſelves: but the Sadduces ever at diſcord, and as uncivill to their own Sect as to ſtrangers. This Hereſie infected not

a few of the High Prieſts: for Hircanus with his two Sons, Ariſtobulus and Alexander, were Sadduces; ſo was Auanus the younger.
                  Verſ. 151. Now the full Moon]
                  In the firſt full Moon after the Suns aſcending into the Equinoctiall, they celebrated the annuall Paſſeover, according to the poſitive Law of Moſes; eating the Lambe in the Evening at their private houſes, and lying about the table on beds, as the Romanes upon their Trielinium: never fewer then ten together; if they wanted of their owne Family, they ſupplied themſelves with their Neighbours; nor above the number of twenty. This Feaſt was onely to be kept at Ieruſalem: but thoſe that came ſhort of the Day by reaſon of the diſtance, or were defiled with the Dead, had a ſecond Paſſeover in the moneth following aſſigned.
                  Verſ. 161. Our waſhings paſt]
                  It was the Cuſtome as well of all the Eaſtern Nations, as of the Iewes, to waſh the feet of their Gueſts, though performed by inferior Servants; but here by Chriſt himſelf, to give an example of humilitie. They had veſſels ſtanding by, ready fill'd with water for that purpoſe. This, at this Feaſt, was obſerved between the firſt and ſecond lying down, by way of Purification:
                  Verſ. 175. Phoſphorus]
                   The ſame with Lucifer, which is a bringer in of Light; and therefore the Harbinger of the Day: ſaid to conduct and withdraw the Starres in that the laſt that ſhineth. This is the beautifull Planet of Venus; which when it riſeth

before the Sun is the Morning Starre; and ſetting after it, the Evening.

                        Now ſea-bath'd Heſperus, who brings
                        Night on, and firſt diſplayes his wings:
                        Now, radiant Lucifer; who Day
                        Exalting, chaceth Night away.
                     
In regard that her Courſe is ſometimes ſwifter then the Sun, and ſometimes ſlower: yet never farre off, and fulfilling the ſame period.
                  Verſ. 193. Thoſe Cities, &amp;c.]
                  The Cities which lie at the foot of Libanus, on the North of Galilee; whereof Ceſarea Philippi, the Seat of the Tetrarch, was the principall: where Iordan not farre above deſcends from Ior and Dan, two neighbouring Fountains.
                  Verſ 198. A Sea-reſembling Lake.]
                  The Lake of Geneſareth called alſo the Sea of Galilee, and of Tiberias; taking this name from that Citie there built by Antipas in honour of Tiberius. It extendeth forty fur-longs in breadth, and in length an hundred: the ſhore once inriched with the Cities of Capharnaum, Tiberias, Bethſaida, Bethſan, Gadra, Taricha, and Choroſaim.
                  
                  Verſ. 199. Thoſe VVoods of Palmes.]
                  In the Plaines adjoyning to Iericho: from theirabundance called the Citie of Palmes.
                  Verſ. 200. Of fragrant Balſamum, which &amp;c.]
                   As in

                     Engaddi, ſo Balſamum grew plentifully about Iericho. A plant onely proper to that Countrey: and from thence tranſported into Aegypt by Antonius, to gratifie Cleopatra. It dies, if it be toucht with iron: and therefore they lanch the rinde with ſharp ſtones, or knives of bone, from whence that precious liquour diſtilleth.
                  Verſ. 203. That mount]
                  Phaſga: from whence Moſes ſaw all the land of Promiſe from Dan to Berſheba; and there died: buried in an unknown Sepulcher by an Angel, leſt that ſhould have drawn the Iſraelites to Idolatry. Saint Hitrome writes, how the Devil, indeavouring to reveale the place, was reſiſted by Michael the Archangel.
                  Verſ 209. Cepheans, whoſe ſtrong walls, &amp;c,]
                   
                     Cepheus, the ſon of Phoenix, reigned in Ioppa: A citie built by Iaphet before the Floud, and rather covered then demoliſht by that Deluge. The Inhabitants, with their territories, took the name of their King: Who worſhipped Dercetis the Goddeſſe of the Aſcalonites their neighbours. She, as they fable, inflamed with the love of a beautifull Youth who ſacrific'd unto her, having by him a Daughter (who after, in that nouriſhed by Doves, was called Semiramis) aſhamed of her incontinency, put away the Youth, expoſed the childe to the mercie of the Deſerts; and diſtracted with ſorrow, threw her ſelf into a Lake neare

                     Aſcalon, and there was changed into a fiſh. Of which Ovid.
                     
                        —To inſiſt upon
                        The ſad Dercetis of great Babylon:
                        Who, as the Paleſtines beleeve, did take
                        A ſcaly form, inhabiting a Lake.
                     
To whom a magnificent Temple was erected, with her image in the likeneſſe of a fiſh from the navell downward. This was that Dagon, the Idol of the Aſcolonites, according to S. Hierome, (by interpretation the Fiſh of Sorrow) which fell before the Ark of God, when it was brought into her Temple.
                  Verſ. 214. Azotus, both the Jamnes]
                  
                     Maritim townes belonging to the Philiſtines: the latter ſo called of the flouriſhing Soyle.
                  Verſ. 215. Lydda]
                  A Citie ſeated in the valley above, and a little to the North of Ioppa: called after, the Citie of Iupiter: famous for the Allegoricall Combat of St 
                     George, and his Martyrdome.
                  Verſ. 216. Caparorſa]
                  A Citie of Iudaea according to Ptolomey; rather of Idumea, as here intimated by our Authour.
                  Verſ. 217. Damaſcus]
                  The regall Citie of Syria: as pleaſant as great; here ſaid to have commanded ten Nations. It lieth on the North of Galiee, in a valley beyond Antelibanus: ſix ſhort dayes journey from Ieruſalem.
                  
                  
                  Verſ. 219. Sabaſte]
                   
                     Samaria, the ſoveraigne Citie of thoſe ten Tribes which fell from the Houſe of Iudah: not much above a dayes journey from Ieruſalem. Built by Amri on the top of a Hill, preſenting an admirable Proſpect, which he bought of Samarus, of whom it was called Samaria. The Inhabitants infamous for their frequent falling from God to Idolatry.
                  Verſ. 221. Phoenicians, who]
                   The Inhabitants between the great Sea and Galilee (ſo called of Phoenix their king, the fifth in deſcent from Iupiter) honour'd for the invention of Letters.

                        Phoenicians firſt expreſt (if Fame be true)
                        The fixt voice in rude figures. Memphis knew
                        Not yet how ſtreame-lov'd Biblus to prepare:
                        But birds and beaſts, carv'd out in ſtone, declare
                        Their Hieroglyphick Wiſdomes.
                     
                     Lucan. l. 3.
Theſe Cadmus the ſonne of Agenor communicated to the Grecians.
                  
                  Verſ. 223. Tyrus, full of Luxury]
                  The Metropolis of Phoenicia; once ſoveraigne of the Sea, and of all the World: the greateſt Emporium: whoſe beauty, commerce, and riches, the parent of luxury, is by the Prophet Ezekiel moſt gloriouſly deſcribed.
                  Verſ. 224. Mother Sidon]
                   The ancienteſt Citie of Phoenicia built by Sida, the daughter of Belus, or rather

by Sidon the firſt-born of Canaan. The mother of Tyrus; for the Tyrians were a Colony of the Sidonians.
                  
                  Verſ. 226. Among the Syrians, thoſe, &amp;c.]
                  The Syrians would eat no fiſh; not onely in regard of the fabulous transformation of their Goddeſſe Dercetis; but that they held it injuſtice to kill thoſe Creatures which did them no harm, and were fed on, rather for luxury then neceſſity: Withall, conceiving the Sea to be the originall and father of all that had life, and that man was ingendred of a liquid ſubſtance, they adored fiſhes as being of their own generation and Subſiſtence. So did they a Dove; not onely becauſe their glorious Empreſſe Semiramis carried that name, and was after, as they fable, transformed into that creature: but expreſſing the Aire by the Dove, as by a fiſh the water; reverencing both, as compriſing the Nature of all things.
                  V. 229 From Belus, whoſe &amp;c.]
                   From certain mariſhes in the valley of Acre runs the River of Belus with a tardy pace, and exonerates it ſelf into the Sea hard by Ptolemais: whoſe ſand affordeth matter for glaſſe, becomming fuſible in the furnace. Strabo reports the like of divers places there about: and Ioſephus, ſpeaking of this, that there is an adjoyning Pit, an hundred cubits in circuit, covered with ſand that gliſtered like glaſſe; and when carried away (for therewith they accuſtomed to ballaſt their ſhips) it forth-with was filled again, borne thither by windes

from places adjacent. Moreover, that what minerall ſoever was contained therein converted into glaſſe; and glaſſe there laid, againe into ſand.
                  Verſ. 231. From Arnons bankes; thoſe, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Arnon riſeth in the mountaines of Arabia; and dividing the Countrey of the Moabites from the Ammonites, fals into the Dead Sea. By thoſe ancient Warres is meant the Overthrow which Moſes gave unto Og and Sehon.
                  
                  Verſ. 234. Aſphaltis]
                  The Dead Sea, or Lake of Sodome and Gomorrah; having no egreſſe, unleſſe under the Earth; Seventy miles in length, and ſixteen broad: here at large deſcribed by our Author.
                  Verſ. 237. VVhat over flies, &amp;c.]
                   The like is written of Avernus: whereof the poeticall Philoſopher

                        Avernus cald: a name impoſ'd of right,
                        In that ſo fatall to all Birds of flight.
                        VVhich when thoſe aiery Paſſengers o' re-fly,
                        Forgetfull of their wings, they fall from high
                        With ſtretcht out necks: on Earth, where Earth partakes
                        That killing propertie; where Lakes, on Lakes.
                     
                     Lucr. l. 6.
                  
                  Verſ. 215. VVhen ſhe, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Lots wife. Ioſephus writes that he himſelfe had ſeene that Statue of Salt: yet extant, if Brocardus and Saligniacus, profeſſed Eyewitneſſes, be to be beleeved.
                  
                  Verſ. 255. Devout Eſſeans]
                  A Sect among the Iews; ſtrictly preſerving the worſhip of God, the rules of Religion and Iuſtice: living on the common ſtock; never eating of fleſh, and wholly abſtaining from Wine and Women. They wore their apparell white and cleanly: pray'd before the riſing of the Sunne; laboured all day long for the publike utilitie; fed in the evening with a generall ſilence; and had their Sobriety rewarded with a life long and healthfull. Their chiefe ſtudy was the Bible; and next to that, Phyſick, taking their name from the cure of diſeaſes. All were ſervants one to an other. They never ſware an oath, nor offered any thing that had life in their ſacrifice: aſcribing all unto Fate, and nothing to free Will. They preſerved their Society by the adoption of children, inured to piety and labour. Their Sect, though ancient, hath no known Originall; yet much agreeing with the diſcipline of the Pythagoreans.
                  
                  Verſ. 274. The firſt unleaven'd Bread]
                  Eaten with the Paſchal Lambe at the Iſraelites departing out of Aegypt: the Ceremonies uſed therein are at large delivered by Moſes.
                  
                  Verſ. 275. She never would retaine]
                   The Libertie they loſt in the Babylonian Captivitie, was never abſolutely recovered: for the moſt part under the Perſians, Grecians, Aegyptians, or Syrians (although in the reigne of the Aſmones they had the face of a Kingdome, yet maintained with perpetuall bloudſhed)

after governed by the Idumeans, and laſtly by the Romanes: often rebelling, and as often ſuppreſſed.
                  Ver. 278. Horned Hammons Temple]
                  
                     Iupiter Hammon, which ſignifies Sand; becauſe his Temple ſtood in the Lybian Deſarts: with ſuch difficultie viſited by Alexander. Or rather being the ſame with Ham the ſonne of Noah; from whom Idolatry had her Originall: who uſually wore the carved head of a Ram on his Helmet; whereupon his Idol was ſo faſhioned. But Iupiter Hammon is alſo taken for the Sunne; Hammah ſignifying Heate in the Hebrew. And becauſe the Yeere beginneth at his entrance into Aries, he therefore was carved with Rams hornes.
                  Ver. 281. Built his proud City]
                  
                     Alexandria in Aegypt; built by Alexander the Great upon a Promentory neer the Iſle of Pharos: ſo directed, as they write, by Homer in a Viſion.
                  Verſ. 282. To their old priſon, Babylon]
                  Not all the Iews returned with Zorobbabel, but remained at Babylon, and by the favour of ſucceeding Princes planted thereabout their Colonies; grew a great Nation, obſerving their ancient Rites and Religion. Theſe were called Babylonian Iews: to whom not a few of their Countrey men fled from the troubles of their Countrey.
                  Verſ. 283. To freezing Taurus, &amp;c.]
                   The greateſt Mountaine of the World, which changeth its name

according to the countries through which it extendeth: that part properly ſo called, which divideth Pamphilia and Cilicia from the leſſer Armenia and Cappadocia: Whither many of the Iews were retired.
                  Verſ. 284. And Tiber now, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Rome, the Empreſſe of Cities adorning the bankes of Tiber, to which the Ocean then yeelded Obedience.
               
            
            
               
               ANNOTATIONS VPON THE SECOND ACT.
               
                  VErſe 1. Bloud-thirſty Romulus]
                  The Originall of the Race and Name of the Romanes: who laide the Wals of Rome in the bloud of his brother Remus.
                  
                  Verſ. 15. To ſuch a Guide, &amp;c.]
                  It was a Cuſtome among the Eaſterne Nations, and not relinquiſhed by many at this Day, for men to kiſſe one another in their ſalutations. So did the Romanes, untill interdicted by Tiberius. With the Iews it was a pledge of peace and amitie: uſed alſo to their Lords and Princes by way of homage and acknowledged ſubjection: as perfidious Iudas did here to his Maſter.
                  Verſ. 55. Memphis]
                  By this is meant the Aegyptian Servitude; Memphis of old the chiefe Citie in Aegypt.
                  
                  Verſ. 55. Devouring Deſarts]
                  All the Iſraelites, that came out of Aegypt, periſhed in the Deſarts, but Ioſhuah and Caleb.
                  
                  Verſ. 55. Civill warres]
                  As between the Tribe of Benjamin, and the reſt of the Tribes; the Iews and Iſraelites; Iſraelites againſt Iſraelites, and Iews againſt Iews. Diſcord threw her Snakes among the Aſmones, nor had Herods Poſteritie better ſucceſſe.
                  
                  Verſ. 56. Oft forreign yokes]
                  Often ſubdued by their Neighbours, and delivered by their Iudges and Princes.
                  Verſ. 56. Aſſyrian Conquerers]
                  Who ſackt Ieruſalem, deſtroyed the Temple which was built by Solomon, led their King captive, and their whole Nation, unto Babylon.
                  
                  Verſ. 57. Great Pompeys Eagles]
                  
                     Pompey, who bore the Romane Eagle on his Standard, took Ieruſalem and the Temple by force (yet would not meddle with the Treaſure, nor ſacred Vtenſils) ſubdued the Iews, and made them tributaries to the Romanes.
                  
                  Verſ. 57. Sacred Rites Profan'd]
                  Who entred the Sanctum Sanctorum with his followers, and prophaned the Religion of the place by beholding that which was to be ſeene but by the High Prieſt onely.
                  Verſ. 58. The Temple ſackt, with bloud, &amp;c.]
                  He ſlew twelve thouſand Iews within the wals of the Temple.
                  Verſ. 66. Cedron]
                  This Brook, or Torrent, runnes thorough the Vale of Iehoſaphat, between Mount Olivet and the City, cloſe by the Garden of Gethſemane, where Chriſt was betrayed.
                  Verſ. 103. Not Jordan with two, &amp;c.]
                  See the Note upon verſ. 195. Act. 1.
                  Verſ. 105. Callithoe]
                  A Citie in the Tribe of Ruben, ſo called of her beautifull Springs: where from a Rock two neighbour Fountaines guſh out as from the breſts of a woman: the one of hot, but ſweet

water; the other of cold and bitter; which joyning together make a pleaſant Bath, ſalubrious for many diſeaſes; and flowes from thence into the Lake of Aſphaltis. Herod in his ſickneſſe repaired to this place: but finding no help, and deſpairing of life, removed to Iericho; where he died.
                  Verſ. 105. That ample Lake]
                  The Sea of Galilee, by which Peter was borne.
                  Verſ. 107. Blew Nereus, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Nereus is taken for the Sea in generall, but here for the Aegyptian; into which Nilus diſchargeth his waters by ſeven currents; the freſh water keeping together, and changing the colour of the Salt, far further into the Sea, then the ſhore from thence can be diſcerned.
                  Verſ. 128. Lethe]
                   A River of Africa, paſſing by Bernice, and running into the Mediterranian Sea neere the Promontory of the Syrtes. It hath that name from Oblivion, becauſe thoſe, who drunk thereof, forgot whatſoever they had formerly done. Of this Lucan.
                     
                        Where ſilent Lethe glides: this (as they tell)
                        Draws her Oblivion from the veines of Hell.
                     
So feigned, becauſe of the oblivion which is in Death; as allegorically for that of Sleep.
                  Verſ. 139. Tarpean Jove]
                   
                     Tarpeus is a Mountaine in Rome, taking that name from the Veſtall Virgin Tarpea, who betrayed her Fathers Fort to the Sabines,
                     
upon promiſe to receive what they ware on their left armes for her reward; ſhe meaning their golden bracelets: which they not onely gave, but threw their ſhields upon her (a part of the bargaine) and ſo preſt her to death; who buried her in the Place: ſince called the Capitol, where Iupiter had his Temple.
                  Verſ. 139. Mars, great Quirinus Sire]
                  
                     Romulus was called Quirinus of his Speare; or for his uniting the two Nations of the Cures and Romanes: as the ſonne of Mars, in that ſo ſtrenuous a Souldier. Plutarch writes that he was begotten by his Vncle Aemulius, who counterfeiting Mars, diſguiſed in Armour, raviſhed his mother Ilia: not onely to ſatisfie his Luſt, but to procure her deſtruction, as the heire to his elder brother, the law condemning a defiled Veſtall to be buried alive.
                  Verſ. 140. You Houſhold Gods, ſnatcht, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Penates: which Aeneas ſaved from burning at the ſack of Troy, and brought them with him into Italy: ſuppoſing that from them they received their fleſh, their life, and underſtanding.
                  Verſ 151. Caprae]
                   A little Iland in the Tyrrhen Sea, and in the ſight of Naples, naturally walled about with up-right Cliffs, and having but one paſſage into it. Infamous for the Cruelties and Luſts of Tiberius; who retiring thither from the affairs of the Common-wealth, ſent from thence his Mandates of death; polluting the place with all varietie of uncleanneſſe;

whereupon it was called the Iland of ſecret luſts, and he Caprenius: converſing there with Magicians, and South-ſayers; whereof the Satyr ſpeaking of Sejanus:
                     
                        The Princes Tutor glorying to be nam'd;
                        Sitting in caves of Caprae with defam'd
                        Chaldeans.
                     
                     Iuv: Sat. 10.
                  
                  Ver. 152. The long-gown.]
                  The gowne was a garment peculiar to the Romanes, by which they were diſtinguiſhed from other Nations; as of what qualitie among themſelves by the wooll and colour, faſhion, and trimming. In ſo much as they were called Togati: Whereof Virgil in the perſon of Iupiter
                     
                        Curſt Juno, who Sea, Earth, and Heaven above,
                        With her diſtemper tires, ſhall friendly prove;
                        And joyne with us in gracing the Long-gownd
                        And Lordly Romanes, ſtill with conqueſt crown'd.
                     
                     Aen. l. 1.
                  
                  Verſ. 157. Their hate to all &amp;c]
                   The Iews with the hate of an enemy deteſted all other Nations: would neither eat with them, nor lodge in their houſes; but avoided the ſtranger as a pollution. Proud in their greateſt poverty: calling themſelves the elect of God: boaſting of their Countrey, their Religion,

and ancient Families: in their converſation auſtere and reſpectleſſe. So full of jealous envy, that by a Decree in the reigne of Hircanus and Ariſtobulus ſuch ſuffered the dreadfull cenſure of a Curſe, who inſtructed their ſons in the Grecian Diſciplines: and much regrated that the laws of Moſes was tranſlated into a profane language by the command of Philadelphus; expreſſing their grief by an annuall Faſt, which they kept on the Eighth day of the moneth Teveth.
                  
                  Verſ. 159. Abjure for one, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Pilat accuſeth them here for their piety: who after the Captivity, as much deteſted Idolatry as they affected it before: who could not be compelled by their Conquerours to worſhip the Images of Tiberius Caeſar, which Pilat brought into the Citie, but was forced to carry them away upon their refuſall. Caius not long after commanded that the Statues of the Gods ſhould be erected in their Temple; menacing, if they ſhould refuſe it, their utter ſubverſion. But his death prevented their ruine: who before had made their proteſtation, that they would rather ſuffer the generall deſtruction of themſelves, and their City, then ſuffer ſuch an abomination, ſo repugnant to their Law and Religion.
                  Verſ. 168. With how much grief our ſwords &amp;c.]
                   
                     Ioſephus mentions one ſlaughter onely, which Pilat, as then, had made of the Iews; and that about the drawing of water by conduits into the ſacred Treaſury;

which divers thouſands of the Iewes tumultuarily reſiſted. Pilat invironed them with his Souldiers, diſguiſed in popular garments; who privately armed, fell upon the naked People, and by the ſlaughter of a number appeaſed the mutiny.
                  Verſ. 234. Rods and Axes]
                  Borne before the Romane Conſuls, Pretors, and Governours of Provinces: bound together in bundles, to informe the Magiſtrate that he ſhould not be too ſwift in execution, nor unlimited: but that in the unbinding thereof he might have time to deliberate, and perhaps to alter his ſentence: that ſome are to be corrected with Rods, and others cut off with Axes, according to the quality of their offences.
                  Verſ. 254. Since one muſt die, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Caiaphas propheſied; being then the High Prieſt, though not of the Houſe of Aaron. He was thrown out of his Office by Lucius Vitellius, who ſucceeded Pilat, and Ionathan the ſonne of Annas placed in his room: when diſtracted with melancholy and deſperation, he received his death from his own hands.
                  Verſ. 242. Stygian]
                  
                     Styx is a Fountain of Arcadia, whoſe waters are ſo deadly, that they preſently kill whatſoever drinks thereof: ſo corrodiating that they can onely be contained in the hoof of a mule. This in regard of the dire effects, was feigned by the Poets to be a river in Hell.
                  Verſ. 361. Solyma]
                   So called by the Grecians; as by the Hebrews Salem; and when David had taken

it from the Iebuſites, Ieruſalem, which is as much as Jebuſalem, turning B into R for the better harmony: called after the building of the Temple Hieroſolyma by the Greeks, of Hieron which ſignifies a Temple in their language.
                  Verſ. 264. From th' Iſthmos]
                  This Iſthmos lies between Aegypt, and the bottom of the Red Sea, from whence to Euphrates David extended his conqueſts: inforcing all the Arabians to become his Tributaries. Who alſo overthrew the King of Sophona hard by the eruption of Tygris, overcame the Meſopotamians, the King of Damaſcus, and drew that City, with all Syria, under his obedience: having before ſubdued the neighbouring Nations.
                  Verſ. 267. Th'admiring Queen, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Joſephus makes her Queen of Aethiopia; and to have beſtowed on Solomon that pretious Plant of Balſamum, which he after planted in Engaddi: but this grew in Canaan in the dayes of Jacob, who ſent a Preſent thereof, among other fruits of that Countrey, into Aegypt. The Aethiopian Emperours glory in their deſcent from Solomon by this Queen; in regard whereof they greatly favour the Jewiſh nation. They have a Citie called Saba, which lies on the Weſt ſide of the Arabian Gulf. But by the preſents which ſhe brought, and vicinitie of the Countrey, it is more probable that ſhe came from Saba, the principall Citie of Arabia the Happy.
                  Verſ. 271. Canopus Scepter &amp;c.]
                   Kings of Aegypt, of

                     Canopus a principal Citie, which ſtood on that branch of Nilus which is next to Alexandria; taking that Name from Menelaus his Pilot, there buried by his ſhipwrackt maſter.
                  Verſ. 272. Thoſe Monarchs &amp;c.]
                  Chaldean Monarchs: Babylon, the ſeat of their Empire; who, as the Perſians, adored the Sun under the name of Mithra.
                  
                  Verſ. 274. Sarrana]
                   
                     Tyrus: ſo called in that it was built on a rock: the Arabians pronouncing Scar for Sar, from whence the Tyrian purple takes the name of Scarlet.

                        He Cities ſacks, and houſes fills with grones;
                        To lie on ſcarlet, drink in pretious ſtones.
                     
                     Virg. Geor. l. c.
Not onely Ioſephus, but the Scriptures, make often mention of the ancient amitie between the Iews and Tyrians.
                  
                  Verſ. 277. Ths land &amp;c.]
                  See the Note upon V. 275. Act. 1.
                  Verſ. 283. Antiochus guilt]
                  
                     Antiochus Epiphanes; who abrogated their Law, and by threatnings and tortures enforced the Iews to Idolatry: polluting their Altar with ſacrificed Swine.
                  Verſ. 291. Iönian Gods]
                  The Gods of Greece: Antiochus being of a Grecian Family, and zealous in their Superſtitions.
                  Verſ. 293. Their brothers ſlew, &amp;c.]
                   
                     Ariſtobulus, the

firſt that ware a Crown of the race of the Aſmones upon a falſe ſuſpicion, by the machination of Salome the Queen, cauſed his valiant and affectionate brother Antigonus to be treacherouſly murdred; who before had impriſoned the reſt of his brethren, and famiſhed his mother. After the deſperate death of Ariſtobulus, Alexander his brother was removed from a Priſon to a Throne: who ſlew his third brother out of a vain ſuſpicion of his aſpiring to the Kingdome. To conclude, from the firſt King of the Aſmones, to the laſt of the Herods, no hiſtory is ſo fruitfull in examples of unnaturall Cruelties.
                  Verſ. 297. Twice vanquiſhed &amp;c]
                  
                     Pompey was the firſt of the Romanes that ſubdued the Iews: neither were the Romanes expulſed by any forrein Prince; but untill this time maintained their Government. It muſt then be meant by their expulſion of one another in their Civill warres: Inlius Coeſar vanquiſhing Pompey: Mark Anthony being his Lieutenant in Syria (who gave a great part of the Territories of the Iews to Cleopatra) after abſolute Lord of the Eaſtern parts of the Romane Empire; in the end overthrown and deprived of all by Auguſtus.
                  
                  Verſ. 303. One part by Romane &amp;c.]
                  
                     Iudea reduced into a Romane Province by Pompey, and then governed by Pontius Pilat.
                  
                  Verſ. 304. The other two by brothers &amp;c.]
                   
                     Philip and Antipas (called alſo Herod) ſons to Herod the Great: the one Tetrarch of Iturea, a Countrey which lies at

the foot of Libanus; and the other of Galilee: to whōm Agrippa ſucceeded, the ſon of Ariſtobulus ſlain by his father Herod, with the title of a King beſtowed by Coeſar.
                  
                  Verſ 305. From ſavage Idumaeans]
                  
                     Antipater, the father of Herod, was an Idumoean; who in the contention between the two brethren Hircanus and Ariſtobulus, about the Kingdome, took part with Hircanus; and grew ſo powerfull, that he made a way for his ſon to the Soveraigntie, though he himſelf was prevented by poyſon.
                  Verſ. 327. That Name]
                  
                     Iehova.
                  
               
            
            
               
               ANNOTATIONS VPON THE THIRD ACT.
               
                  VErſe 47. Brutiſh Thunder]
                  The Philoſophers will have two ſorts of Lightning: calling the one fatall, that is, pre-appointed and mortall; the other Brutiſh, that is, accidentall, and flying at random.
                  Verſ. 119. He, whom &amp;c.]
                  
                     Herod Antipas; then Tetrarch of Galilee: whoſe father Herod the Great ſo magnificently reedified the Temple, that the glory of the latter exceeded that of the former.
                  Verſe 122. The land &amp;c.]
                  
                     Phoenicia; the ancient kingdome of Agenor, ſon to Belus Priſcus: who was reputed a God after his death, and honoured with Temples; called Bel by the Aſſyrians, and Baal by the Hebrews.
                  
                  Verſe 142. Whoſe flouds in Summer ſwell]
                   
                     Nilus, which conſtantly begins to riſe with the riſing Sunne on the ſeventeenth of Iune, increaſing by degrees, untill it make all the Land a Lake.

                        Not ty'd to laws of other Streams; the Sun
                        When furtheſt off, thy ſtreams then pooreſt run:
                        Intemperate heaven to temper, midſt of heat,
                        Vnder the burning Zone, bid to grow great.
                        
                        Then Nile aſſiſts the world; leſt fire ſhould quell
                        The Earth: and make his high-borne waters ſwell
                        Againſt the Lions flaming jaws.—
                     
                     Lucan. l. 10.
                  
                  Ver. 187. The free born]
                  It was the cuſtome of the Romanes to puniſh ſlaves onely with whips, but their children and the free, with rods.
                  Verſe 195. The wreathed Thorns]
                  in reverence of this crown of Thorns, which was platted about the brows of our Saviour, the Chriſtians forbare to wear any garlands on their heads in their Feſtivalls; although it were the cuſtome of thoſe Nations, among whom they lived.
                  Verſ. 221. Thou liquid chryſtall, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Pilat waſht not his hands to expreſſe his innocencie, as a Romane Cuſtome; but therein obſerving the Iewiſh Ceremony: which was, that he who would profeſſe himſelf guiltleſſe of a ſuſpected Man ſlaughter ſhould waſh his hands over a Heifer, with her head cut off.
                  Verſe 338. Let it fall &amp;c.]
                  This imprecation ſoon after fell upon them in all the fulneſſe of horrour; and throughout the world at this day purſues them.
                  Verſe 233. Drag him to the Croſſe, &amp;c.]
                   
                     Pilat not onely out of fear, and againſt his conſcience; but therein infringed a Law lately made by Tiberius, in the ſudden execution: for by the ſame no offendour was to ſuffer within ten dayes after his condemnation. But he met with a Nemeſis; ſoon after

turn'd out of his Government by Vitellius for his cruelty inflicted upon the Samaritanes, and ſent to Rome with his accuſers. But Tiberius dying before his arrivall, he was baniſhed the Citie by Caius: who troubled in minde, and deſperate of reſtitution, ſlew himſelf at Vienna in France within two yeares after.
                  Verſ. 238. If thou be he, &amp;c.]
                   By this place taken out of the Goſpel, it appeares that divers of the Iews were of the opinion of the Pythagoreans, or the Pythagoreans of theirs, concerning the tranſmigration of Soules into other bodies.

                        All alter, nothing finally decayes:
                        Hither and thither ſtill the Spirit ſtrayes;
                        Gueſt to all Bodies: out of beaſts it flies
                        To men, from men to beaſts, and never dies.
                        As pliant wax each new impreſſion takes;
                        Fixt to no forme, but ſtill the old forſakes;
                        Yet it the ſame: ſo Soules the ſame abide,
                        'Though various figures their reception hide.
                     
                     Ovid. Met. l. 15.
                     Herod conceived that the Soule of Iohn the Baptiſt, by him wickedly murdered, was entered into the body of our bleſſed Saviour: And Ioſephus in his Oration to his deſperate Companions in the Cave of Iotopata: Thoſe poore Soules which depart from this
                     
                     life by the law of Nature, and obediently render what from God they received, ſhall by him be placed in the higheſt Heavens; and from thence againe, after a certaine revolution of time, deſcend by command to dwell in chaſte bodies.
                  
                  Verſ. 249. Slaine for a dancer]
                  This daughter of Herodias, as Nicephorus writes, going over a River that was frozen, fell in all but the head, which was cut off with the yce, as her body waved up and downe underneath.
                  Verſ. 331. Sadock]
                  The Author of the Sect of the Sadduces. See the Note upon Verſ. 43. Act. 1.
               
            
            
               
               ANNOTATIONS VPON THE FOVRTH ACT.
               
                  VErſe 35. To Warre the fatall way]
                  The City of Ieruſalem is onely on that ſide aſſailable: there forced and entred by the Babylonians, and after by Pompey.
                  
                  Verſ. 36. Golgotha]
                  Mount Calvary: a rocky hill, neither high, nor ample, lying then without the North-Weſt wall of the City: the publique place of execution. Here they ſay that Abraham would have ſacrificed Iſaac; in memory whereof there now ſtandeth a Chappell: as an Altar, where the Head of Adam was found, which gave the name to that Mount: buried in that place that his bones might be ſprinkled with the reall bloud of our Saviour, which he knew would be there ſhed by a propheticall foreknowledge. It is ſaid to ſtand in the midſt of the Earth; which muſt needs be meant by the then habitable: for what middle can there be in a Sphericall Body?
                  V. 49. The Nazarite]
                  Not as Sampſon by vow, nor of that Sect: but ſo called of that City, wherein he was conceived, and where he inhabited after his returne out of Aegypt.
                  
                  
                  Verſ. 52. Mixt with the bitter tears of Myrrh]
                   Some ſuppoſe that this was proffered him by his friends, being of a ſtupifying qualitie, to make him leſſe ſenſible of his torments. But it appeares by Petronius and Pliny, that it was a mixture much uſed in their delights: Whereof Martial
                     
                        The teares of Myrrh in hot Falernum thaw:
                        From this the Wine a better taſte will draw.
                     
                     Epig. l. 14.
Strengthning the body, and refreſhing the Spirits; and therefore more likely proffered by his enemies to prolong his ſufferings.
                  Verſ. 81. His inward Robe]
                  There be, who write that this was woven by the Virgin Mary: and we reade in the Scriptures, as frequently in Homer and other Authors, that women, and thoſe of the higheſt qualitie, uſually wrought garments for their Children and Husbands.
                  Verſ. 203. The Center pants, &amp;c.]
                  This Earth-quake proceeded not from the Windes impriſoned in the bowels of the Earth, ſtrugling to break forth, or from any other naturall cauſe, but by the immediate ſinger of God.
                  Verſ. 205. The Sunne affrighted hides, &amp;c.]
                   Miraculous; without the interpoſition of the Moone, or palpable Vapours, was that defect of the Sunne, and unnaturall Darkneſſe, in the ſixth houre of the Day:

which appeareth by the Text to have cover'd all the World, and not Iudea alone, as ſome have conjectured. Divers Authours have recorded this in their Annals and Hiſtories: but none ſo exactly as Dionyſius Areopagita; who then reſided in Aegypt, and was an eye-witneſſe.
                  Verſ. 240. The greedy hollowes of a Spunge, &amp;c]
                  Phyſicians agree that Vineger being drunk, or held to the noſe, hath in it a naturall Vertue for the ſtenching of bloud. Pliny attributes the like to Hyſſop, and the better if joyned. Neither is it to be thought that the Iews offered this unto IESUS in humanity, but rather out of their hatred, that by prolonging his Life untill the Evening, his legges might have been broken to the increaſe of his torments.
                  Verſ. 256. Pale troopes of wandring Ghoſts]
                   Theſe were the reall bodies of the dead, which entred the City from their graves (for it was, as now, their Cuſtome to bury in the fields) and ſeen by day. Whereas deluding Spirits aſſume an Aery, thinne and fluxative Body, condenſed by cold, but diſſipated by heate, and therefore onely appeare in the Night time. Which Virgil intimates in the Ghoſt of Anchiſes:
                     
                        And now farewell: the humid Night deſcends;
                        I ſent Day's breath in his too-ſwift repaire.
                        This ſaid, like ſmoak, he vaniſneth to aire.
                     
                     Aen. l. 12.
                     
                  
                  Ver. 259 The cleaving Rocks]
                  The Rock of Mount Calvary was rent by that Earth-quake from the top to the bottome, which at this day is to be ſeene: the rupture ſuch as Art could have no hand in; each ſide anſwerable ragged, and there where unacceſſible to the workman.
                  Verſ 263. Old Chaos now returnes]
                   That confuſed Maſſe, out of which God created the beautifull World: into which it was imagined that it ſhould be againe reduced.

                        The aged World, diſſolved by the Laſt
                        And fatall Houre, ſhall to Old Chaos haſt.
                        Stars, juſtling Stars, ſhall in the Deepe confound
                        Their radiant fires: the Land ſhall give no bound
                        To ſwallowing Seas: the Moone ſhall croſſe the Sun,
                        With ſcorne that her ſwift wheeles obliquely run,
                        Dayes throne aſpiring. Diſcord then ſhall rend
                        The Worlds crackt Frame, and Natures Concord end.
                     
                     Lucan. l. 4.
But many of our Divines are of opinion, that the World ſhall neither be diſlolved nor anihilated: ſtrengthning their aſſertion out of the eighth of the Romanes, and other places of Scripture.
                  Ver. 238. Th'amaz'd Centurion]
                  To this Centurion, who profeſſed CHRIST to be the Sonne of God, they give the name of Longinus, and honour him with the crowne of Martyrdome.
                  
                  Verſ. 296. The Temples Veile]
                   Deſcribed by Ioſephus to conſiſt of Violet, Purple, and Scarlet Silke, cunningly mixt &amp; wrought by Babylonian Needles: the colours containing a myſticall ſenſe. Such was that of Solomons, and of the travelling Tabernacle; but that they were powdred with Cherubins. This, it ſhould ſeeme, was renewed by Herod, when he ſo magnificently repaired the Temple. It hung before the Sanctum Sanctorum; into which none but the High Prieſt, and that but once in the yeer, was to enter: violated by Pompey, purſued by a miſerable Deſtiny. There was an out-ward Veile, not unlike the other, which ſeparated the Prieſts from the People: this, contrary to the Opinion of our Authour, Baronius conceives to be that which then rent aſunder: interpreted to ſignifie the finall aboliſhing of the Law Ceremoniall. They write that at the tearing thereof a Dove was ſeene to flye out of the Temple.
                  Verſ. 319. Or God doth this abhorr'd &amp;c.]
                  
                     Euſebius, St. Ierome, and others report, that with this Earthquake at the Paſſion, the Doores of the Temple flew open, and that the Tutular Angels were heard to cry, Let us remove from this place: though Ioſephus referre it to the deſtruction of the Temple.
                  Verſ. 362. Tyrian Gades]
                  
                     Gades, now called Cales, an Iland lying on the South of Spaine without Hercules Pillars, held to be the uttermoſt Confines of the Weſtern World, was planted by a Colony of the Tyrians.
                  
                  Verſ. 363. As yet ſees not thy panting Horſes, &amp;c.]
                   A Charriot and Horſes were attributed to the Sunne, in regard of the ſwiftneſſe of his Motion; and to expreſſe what is beyond the object of the ſenſe by that which is ſubject unto it. Theſe alſo by the Idolatrous Iews were conſecrated unto him. The Sunne was feined to deſcend into the Sea, becauſe it ſo appeareth to the eye; the Horizon being there moſt perſpicuous.
                  Verſ. 371. Hath ſome Theſſalian Witch, &amp;c.]
                   The Theſſalian women were infamous for their inchantments: ſaid to have the power to darken the Sunne, and draw the Moone from her Spheare. Such Lucans Erictho:
                     
                        Her words to poyſon the bright Moone aſpire;
                        Firſt pale, then red, with darke and terrene fire:
                        As when deprived of her Brothers ſight,
                        Earth interpoſing his Coeleſtiall Light:
                        Perplext with tedious Charmes, and held below,
                        Till ſhe on under Hearbs her gelly throw.
                     
                     Pha
                           •
                        . l. 6.
The Author of this opinion was Aglonice the daughter of Hegaemon: who being skilfull in Aſtronomy, boaſted to the Theſſalian women (foreknowing the time of her Eclips) that ſhe would performe it at ſuch a ſeaſon: which hapning accordingly, and they beholding the diſtemper'd Moone, gave credit to her

deception. The like may ariſe from the Eclipſes of the Sunne,
                  Verſ. 372. What new Phaëton]
                  The fable of Phaëton, the ſonne of Phoebus, as the Allegory, is notorious; who by miſguiding the Charriot of the Sunne ſet all the World on a conflagration.
                  Verſ. 377. As when ſterne Atreus &amp;c.]
                  
                     Atreus, having had his bed diſhonored by his brother Thyeſtes, ſlew his children, and gave them for food to their father: when the Sunne, to avoid ſo horrid a ſight, fled back to the Orient. So fained in that Atreus firſt diſcovered the Annuall Courſe of the Sun, which is contrary to his Diurnall.
                  Verſ. 379. Ilia's god-like ſonne, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Romulus: cut into a hundred pieces by the hundred Lords of the Senate, for being ſo rigorous to them, and ſo indulgent to the People; every one carrying a piece away with him under his long Gowne to conceale the murder: when Iulius Proculus, to appeaſe the People, ſwore that he ſaw him aſcend into Heaven: whereupon they conſecrated Temples unto him, and gave him divine honours; changing his Name into Quirinus.
                  
                  Verſ. 383. Or hath that Day, &amp;c.]
                  The Great Yeere: when all the Planets (here called Gods becauſe they carry their Names) ſhall returne to that poſition which they were in at the beginning: Compriſing, according to Cicero's Hortenſius, the revolution of twelve thouſand nine hundreth and fifty yeers.
                  
                  Verſ. 390. If the World periſh by licentious fire]
                   The Romanes could not then have this from St. Peter; but rather from the Propheſies of the Sibyls:
                     
                        Theſe Signes the Worlds combuſtion ſhall fore-run:
                        Armes claſhing, Trumpets, from the riſing Sun
                        Horrible fragors, heard by all: this Frame
                        Of Nature then ſhall feed the greedy flame.
                        Men, Cities, Floods, and Seas, by rav'nous luſt
                        Of Fire devour'd, all ſhall reſolve to duſt.
                     
                     Orac. l. 4.
From hence perhaps the Ancient Philoſophers derived their opinions; as Seneca a Latter, The Stars ſhall incounter one another, and what now ſhines ſo orderly, ſhall burne in one Fire.
                  
                  Verſ. 395. Either the groaning world, &amp;c.
                   
                  Verſ. 397. Do proud Titanians &amp;c]
                  The Poets feigne that the angry Earth, to be revenged of the Gods, brought forth the Titans, as after the Gyants; who by throwing mountains upon mountains attempted to ſcale the Heavens, and diſinthrone Iupiter; who overthrew them with his Lightning, and caſt thoſe conjeſted Mountains upon them. Pherecydes the Syrian writes, how the Devils were caſt out of Heaven by Iupiter (this fall of the Giants perhaps alluding to that of the Angels:) The chief called Ophionius, which ſignifies Serpentine: having after made uſe of that Creature to poyſon Eve with a falſe ambition.
                  
                  Verſ. 400. Dire Python]
                   A prodigious Serpent, which after Deucalions Floud lay upon the Earth like a Mountain, and ſlain by Apollo: the ſenſe of the Fable being meerely Phyſicall; for Python born after the deluge of the humid Earth, was that great Exhalation, which roſe from the late drowned world; at length diſſipated by the fervour of the Sunne, or Apollo.
                     
                        The Earth then ſoak'd in ſhowres, yet hardly dry,
                        Threw up thick clouds, which darkned all the Sky:
                        This was that Python.
                     
                     Pont. Meteor.
The word ſignifies putrefaction: and becauſe the Sun conſumes the putrefaction of Earth, his beams darting from his Orb like arrows, with his arrows he is ſaid to have ſlain Python.
                  
                  Verſ. 400. Lerna's Fen]
                   In this lay that venemous Serpent Hydra; which is ſaid to have many Heads, whereof one being cut off, two roſe in the room more terrible then the former, and with her poyſnous breath to have infected all the Territories adjoyning. This Fable had a relation to that place, which through the eruption of waters annoyed the neighbouring Cities; when one being ſtopt many roſe in the room: this Hercules perceiving, burnt them with fire.

                        
                        Corruption boyls away with heat;
                        And forth ſuperfluous vapours ſweat.
                     
But Phyſically, Hydra ſignifies water, and Hercules according to Macrobius, preſenteth the Sunne, whoſe extraordinary fervour dried up thoſe noyſome and infectious vapours.
                  Verſ. 404. Lyaeus gave to man leſſe precious wine]
                  
                     Lyaeus is a name of Bacchus, becauſe wine refreſheth the Heart, and freeth it from ſorrow. Noah was he who immediately after the Floud firſt planted a Vineyard and ſhewed the uſe of wine unto man: wherefore ſome write that of Noachus he was called Boachus, and after Bacchus by the Ethnicks, either by contraction, or through ignorance of the etymologie. This compariſon hath relation to Chriſt's converſion of water into ſuch excellent wine at Cana in Galilee.
                  
                  Verſ. 405. Not Hercules ſo many Monſters ſlew]
                   Hercules, ſaith Seneca, travelled over the world, not to oppreſſe it, but to free it from Oppreſſours; and by killing of Tyrants and Monſters to preſerve it in tranquillitie. But how much more glorious were the victories of Chriſt; who by ſuffering for Sinne, ſubdued it; led Captivity captive, was the death of

Death; triumphing over Hell, and thoſe Spirits of Darkneſſe.
                  Verſ. 406. Vnſhorn Apollo deſſe in Phyſick knew]
                  
                     Apollo; to whom they attribute long yellow haire, in regard of his beautifull Beams, is ſaid to have invented the Art of Phyſick (his name importing a preſervation from evil) becauſe the Sunne is ſo powerfull in producing phyſicall Simples, and ſo ſalubrious to our bodies: when Chriſt by his own Vertue cured all diſeaſes; gave ſight to the blinde by birth, which ſurpaſleth the power of art; threw out wicked Spirits from the tortured bodies of the poſſeſſed; and called the Dead from their beds of death to converſe again with the Living.
                  Verſe 419. With the Religion of the Samean]
                   Of Pythagoras of Samos; who by his doctrine and example withdrew the Crotonians from luxury and idleneſſe to temperance and induſtry; calming the perturbations of the Minde with the muſick of his Harp: for he held that Vertue, Strength, all Good, and even God himſelf, conſiſted of Harmony: That God was the Soul of the World; from whence each creature received his life; &amp; dying, reſtored it. And leſt it might be doubted that the Souls of all had not one Originall, in regard of their different underſtandings, he alleadged how that proceeded from the naturall

complexion &amp; compoſition of the Body, as more or leſſe perfect: whoſe opinions are thus delivered by Virgil.
                     
                        The arched Heavens, round Earth, the liquid Plain,
                        The Moons bright Orb, and Starres Titanian,
                        A Soul with-in ſuſtaines; whoſe Vertues paſſe
                        Through every part, and mix that huge Maſſe.
                        Hence men, hence beaſts, what ever fly with wing,
                        And Monſters in the marble Ocean ſpring:
                        Of Seed divine, and fiery Vigour, full;
                        But what groſſe fleſh, and dying member dull.
                        Thence fear, deſire, grief, joy; nor more regard
                        Their heavenly Birth, in thoſe blinde Priſons barr'd.
                     
                     Aen. l. 6.
Moreover, he held that this viſible Soul or Godhead, diffuſed throughout all the world, got it ſelf ſuch diverſitie of Names, by the manifold operations which it effected in every part of the viſible Vniverſe.
                  Verſ. 420. Nor Thracian Harp, wilde Beaſts inſtructing, can]
                   
                     Orpheus of Thrace; who with the muſick of his Harp and voice attracted even beaſts and ſenceleſſe ſtones to heare him. The morall of which Fable may parallell with that of Amphion.
                     
                        
                        Orpheus the Gods Interpreter, from blood
                        Rude men at firſt deterr'd, and ſavage food:
                        Hence ſaid to have Tygers and fell Lions tam'd.
                        Amphion ſo, who Theban bulwarks fram'd,
                        T'have led the ſtones with muſick of his lute,
                        And milde requeſts. Of old in high repute:
                        Publick from Private, Sacred from Prophane,
                        To ſeparate; and wandring Luſt reſtrain
                        With matrimoniall ties; faire Cities raiſe,
                        Laws ſtamp in braſſe. This gave the honour'd Bayes
                        To ſacred Poets, and to verſe their praiſe.
                     
                     Horat. de Art. Poet.
It is apparent by his Teſtament to his Scholar Muſaeus (whereof certain verſes are recited by Iuſtin Martyr) that his opinion in divinitie was in the main agreeable with the ſacred Scriptures: As of one God, the Creator of Heaven and Earth, the Authour of all good, and puniſher of all evil; exhorting him to the hearing and underſtanding of that knowledge which was revealed from Heaven: meaning nothing elſe by thoſe various Names which he gives to the Gods, but divine and naturall Vertues: ſhadowing God himſelf under the Name of Iupiter to avoid the envy and danger of thoſe times; as is almoſt evident by theſe attributes.

                        
                        Omnipotent Jove; the Firſt, the Laſt of things;
                        The Head, the Midſt: all from Joves bounty ſprings:
                        Foundation of the Earth, and ſtarry Skie:
                        A Male, a Female; who can never die.
                        Spirit of all: the Force of awfull Fire;
                        Sourſe of the Sea; Sun, Moon, th'Originall,
                        The End of all things; and the King of all.
                        At firſt conceal'd, then by his wond'rous Might
                        And ſacred Goodneſſe, all produc'd to light.
                     
                  
                  Verſ. 421. Nor that prophetick Boy, &amp;c.]
                   Of whom Ovid.
                     
                        The Nymphs and Amazonian this amaz'd,
                        No leſſe then when the Tyrrhen Plow-man gaz'd
                        Vpon the fatall clod, that mov'd alone;
                        And, for a humane ſhape, exchang'd his own.
                        With infant lips, that were but earth of late,
                        Reveal'd the Myſteries of future Fate:
                        Whom Natives Tages call'd. He, firſt of all,
                        Th'Hetrurians taught to tell what would befall.
                     
                     Met. l. 15.
And Cicero, in his ſecond book of Divination: Tages, when the Earth was turned up, and the Plow had made a deeper impreſſion, aſcended (as they ſay) in the Tarquinian fields, and ſpake to
                     
                     the Tiller. It is written in the Hetrurian Records that he was ſeen in the form of a Boy, although old in wiſdome. The Husband-man amazed, and exalting his voice, drew thither a great concourſe of People; and with-in awhile all Thuſcany: who ſpake many things in that populous audience; by them remembred, and committed to writing. His oration onely contained the diſcipline of Divination by the entrails of beaſts: which after increaſed by experience, but is referred to this Originall. A deluſion of the Devils to introduce that Superſtition.
                  
               
            
            
               
               ANNOTATIONS VPON THE FIFTH ACT.
               
                  VErſe 30. O may they periſh, &amp;c.]
                  This imprecation comprehends thoſe following calamities which the Divine Vengeance inflicted on the Iews: more, and more horrid, then ever befell any other Nation.
                  Verſ. 35. Let the great in Warre, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Titus Veſpaſian: who beſieged Ieruſalem when almoſt all the Iewiſh Nation was within the Walles, there met to celebrate the Paſſeover: who took it by force, conſumed the Temple with fire, (which fell on that day in which it was formerly burnt by the Chaldeans) and levelled the City with the ground: eleven hundred thouſand Iewes there periſhing by famine, peſtilence, and the ſword: another hundred thouſand Captives were publikely ſold, for a Romane penny a Iew; and ſixteene thouſand ſent to Alexandria for ſervill imployments: two thouſand of the moſt beautifull and perſonable young men reſerved to attend on his Triumph, who after, to delight the Spectators, were torne in pieces by wild beaſts in the Amphitheater.
                  
                  
                  Verſ. 26. Let Diſeaſes ſow, &amp;c.]
                   During the ſiege the Peſtilence violently raged, proceeding from the ſtench of dead bodies, to whom they afforded no buriall, but piled them up in their houſes, or threw them over the Wall of the City.
                  Verſ. 41. Famine, in their dry entrailes, &amp;c.]
                  Vnexpreſſible was the Famine they indured; and pittifull, if they themſelves had had any pitty: enforced to ſeeth their Girdles and Shooes, and fighting fiercely with one another for ſo courſe a diet. Driven in the end to that exigent, that they were faine to rake the ſincks and privies, and to feede on that which was loathſome to behold; neither could they keep what they found from the rapine of others.
                  Verſ. 44. The Babe re-enter her, &amp;c.]
                  Hunger had ſo overcome Nature, that a Woman of riches and honour, named Mary, being daily rob'd of her proviſion by the Seditious, ſlew her owne childe which ſuckt at her breſt, and having ſodden one halfe thereof, eat it. When at the ſent of fleſh, they broke in upon her; who preſented them with the reſt; the theeves then hardly refraining, though they trembled at ſo horrid a Spectacle.
                  Verſ. 45. While yet the eager Foe, &amp;c.]
                   The enemy aſſailed them without, and the Seditious

maſſacred one another within; divided into three parties: the Zealous, the Idumaean Robbers, and the reſt of the mutinous Citizens: but upon every aſſault of the Romanes, ſetting their private hatred aſide, united themſelves, as if of one Minde, and with admirable courage repulſed the Enemy: but upon the leaſt ceſſation renewed their bloudy diſcord; ſome beginning with their owne hands to ſet the Temple on fire.
                  Verſ. 47. Let th'Enemy, &amp;c.]
                  See the Notes upon the 35. Verſe.
                  Verſe. 50. The Reliques of their ſlaughter,]
                  In the dayes of Adrian, the Iewes raiſed a new Commotion: of whom his Lieutenant, Iulius Severus, ſlew five hundred and foure ſcore thouſand; tranſporting the reſt into Spaine by the command of the Emperour: ſo that Iewry was then without Iews, as it continues to this preſent.
                  Verſ. 52. Deſpiſ'd, and wretched, wander, &amp;c.]
                  Out of Spaine they were baniſhed in the yeer 1500. by Ferdinand and Emanuel. Now ſcattred throughout the whole World, and hated by thoſe among whom they live; yet ſuffered as a neceſſary miſchiefe: ſubject to all wrongs and contumelies; who can patiently ſubmit themſelves to the times, and to whatſoever may advance their profit.
                  
                  Verſ. 53. Aboliſh'd by their Law, &amp;c]
                   This they loſt in the deſtruction of their City. Yet daily expect that Meſſias who is already come: and, as they beleeve, ſhall reſtore them to their temporall Kingdome.
                  Verſ. 55. This infected ſoyle, &amp;c.]
                  The Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories report, how Ioſeph of Arimathea, after he had ſuffered impriſonment by the envy of the Iews, and was delivered by an Angel, left his Countrey, and ſailed to Marcellis in France: from thence paſſing over into this Iland, he preached the Goſpell to the Brittaines and Scots: who there exchanged this life for a better.
                  Verſ. 95. Who knows but ſoone a holier Age, &amp;c.]
                   
                     Helena the Mother of Conſtantine, throwing downe the Fane of Venus, which Adrian had erected on Calvary, covered both the Mount and Sepulchre with a magnificent Temple, which yet hath reſiſted the injuries of Inſolence and Time: and what was before without, in reverence to the place, is now in the heart of the City. To recover this from the Saracens, divers of the Weſterne Princes have unfortunately ventured their Perſons and People: though Godfry of Bullein, with an Army of three hundred thouſand, made of the City and Country an abſolute Conqueſt: Whoſe Succeſſours held it

for foureſcore and nine yeers, and then beaten out by Saladine the Aegyptian Sultan. Yet yeerly is the Sepulchre viſited, though now in the poſſeſſion of the Turke, from all parts of the World by thouſands of Chriſtians, who there pay their vowes, and exerciſe their Devotions.
                  Verſ. 109. Of his Royall Bloud, &amp;c]
                  Of Davids: See the Notes upon the 264. Verſe of the ſecond Act.
                  Verſ. 139. Not that fierce Prince, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Herod the Great, the murderer of the Infants: who put three of his ſonnes to death; with his wife Mariamme, whom he frantickly affected.
                  Verſ. 140. Nor his Succeſſour, &amp;c.]
                  
                     Herod Antipas, who cut off the Head of Iohn the Baptiſt.
                  
                  Verſ. 189. You neighbours to the Sunnes up-riſe]
                  The Perſian Magi.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               Imprimatur.
            
            
               Ioannes Hanſley.
               
                  September 27. 1639.
               
            
            
         
      
   

