
   
      
         
            A most pleasant ballad of patient Grissell To the tune of the brides good morrovv.
            Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.
         
         
            
               1600
            
         
         Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02251
            STC 12384
            ESTC S118558
            99853765
            99853765
            19160
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02251)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19160)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1205:10)
         
         
            
               
                  A most pleasant ballad of patient Grissell To the tune of the brides good morrovv.
                  Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.
                  Boccaccio, Giovanni, 1313-1375.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.)   
               
                  s.n.,
                  [London :
                  1600]
               
               
                  Attributed to Thomas Deloney.
                  Based on book 10, novel 10 of: Boccaccio, Giovanni. Decamerone.
                  Imprint from STC.
                  A ballad.
                  Verse - "A noble marques as he did ride on hunting hard by a forrest side:".
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Ballads, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-09
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-10
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2002-10
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            A most pleasant Ballad of patient Grissell.
            To the tune of the Brides good morrovv.
            
               A Noble Marques as he did ride on hunting
               hard by a Forrest side:
               A proper Mayden as she did fit a spinning
               his gentle eye espide.
               Most faire &amp; louely, and of curteous grace was she,
               although in simple attire:
               She sung full sweet with pleasant voyce melodiously,
               which set the Lords hart on fire.
               The more he looked the more he might,
               Beautie bred his hartes delight.
               and to this dainty Damsell then he went:
               God speede quoth he, thou famous flower,
               Faire mistres of this homely bower,
               where loue &amp; vertue liues with sweete content.
            
            
               With comely iesture &amp; curteous milde behauiour
               she bad him welcome then:
               She entertaind him in faithful friendly maner
               and all his Gentlemen.
               the noble marques in his hart felt such a flame
               which set his sences at strife:
               Quoth he, faire maiden shew me soone what is thy name?
               I meane to make thee my wife.
               
                  Grissell is my name quoth she,
               Farre vnfit for your degree,
               a silly Mayden and of parents poore.
               Nay Grissell thou art rich he sayd,
               A vertuous faire and comely Mayd,
               graunt me thy loue, and I wil aske no more.
            
            
               At length she consented, &amp; being both contented
               they married were with speed:
               Her contrey russet was changd to silk &amp; veluet
               as to her state agreed.
               And when she was trimly tyred in the same,
               her beauty shined most bright,
               Far staining euery other braue &amp; comly dame,
               that did appeare in her sight.
               Many enuied her therefore,
               Because she was of parents poore,
               and twixe her Lord &amp; the great strife did raise
               Some sayd this, and some sayd that,
               Some did call her beggers brat,
               and to her lord they would her soone dispraise
            
            
               O noble Marques (quoth they) why doe you wrong vs
               thus bacely for to wed?
               That might haue gotten an honorable Lady,
               into your Princely bed.
               Who will not now your noble issue still deride
               which shall hereafter be borne:
               That are of blood so base by their mothers side
               the which will bring them in scorne:
               Put her therefore quite away,
               Take to you a Lady gay,
               whereby your linage may renowned be:
               Thus euery day they seemde to prate,
               That malist Grisselles good estate,
               who tooke all this most milde and patiently.
            
            
               When that the marques did see that they were bent thus
               against his faithfull wife,
               Whom he most deerely, tenderly, and entirely,
               beloued as his life.
               Minding in secret for to proue her patient hart
               therby her foes to disgrace:
               Thinking to play a hard vncurteous part,
               that men might pittie her case.
               Great with childe this Lady was,
               And at length it came to passe,
               two goodly children at one birth she had:
               A sonne and daughter God had sent,
               Which did their father well content,
               and which did make their mothers hart full glad.
            
            
               Great royall feasting was at these Childrens christnings
               and princely triumph made:
               Sixe weeks together, al nobles that came thither
               were entertaind and staid:
               And whē that al those pleasant sportings quite were done
               the Marques a messenger sent:
               For his yōng daughter, &amp; his prety smiling son
               declaring his full intent:
               How that the babes must murdred be,
               For so the Marques did decree,
               come let me haue the children then he sayd:
               With that faire Grissell wept full sore,
               She wrung her hands and sayd no more,
               my gracious Lord must haue his wil obaid.
            
            
               She tooke the babies euen from their nursing Ladies
               betweene her tender armes:
               She often wishes with many sorrowful kisses
               that she might helpe their harmes.
               Farewel farewel a thousand times my childrē deere,
               neuer shall I see you againe,
               Tis long of me your sad &amp; woful mother heere.
               for whose sake both must be slaine.
               Had I been borne of royall race,
               You mighe haue liu'd in happy case,
               but you must die for my vnworthines:
               Come messenger of death said shee,
               Take my despised babes to thee,
               and to their father my complaints expres.
            
            
               He tooke the children, and to his noble maister
               he brings them both with speed:
               Who secret sent them vnto a noble Lady,
               to be nurst vp in deed:
               Thē to faire Grissel with a heauy hart he goes
               where she sate mildly alone:
               A pleasant iesture &amp; a louely looke she showes,
               as if this griefe she neuer had knowen.
               Quath he, my children now are slaine,
               What thinkes faire Grissell of the same,
               sweet Grissell now declare thy mind to mee;
               Sith you my Lord are pleasd in it,
               Poore Grissell thinkes the action sit,
               both I and mine at your command will be,
            
            
               My nobles murmur faire Grissell at thy honor
               and I no ioy can haue:
               Til thou be banisht both frō my court and presence
               as they vniustly craue:
               Thou must be stript out of thy costly garments all.
               and as thou camest to me:
               In homely gray in steed of bisse &amp; purest pall
               now all thy cloathing must be.
               My Lady thou shalt be no more,
               Nor I thy Lord, which grieues me sore,
               the poorest life must now content thy minde.
               A groat to thee I must not giue,
               To maintaine thee while I doe liue,
               against my Grissel such great foes I finde.
            
            
               When gentle Grissell did heare these wofull tidings,
               the teares stood in her eyes:
               She nothing answered, no words of discontent
               did from her lips arise.
               Her veluet gown most patienely she slipped off,
               her kirtles of silke with the same:
               her russet gown was broght again with many a scoffe
               to beare them all her selfe she did frame:
               When she was drest in this array,
               And ready was to part away,
               God send long life vnto my Lord quoth shee
               Let no offence be found in this,
               To giue my Lord a parting kisse,
               with watry eyes, farewel my deere quoth he.
            
            
               From stately Pallace vnto her fathers Cottage
               poore Grissell now is gone:
               Full sixteene winters she liued there contented
               no wrong she thought vpon:
               And at that time through all the land the speaches went:
               the Marques should married be:
               Unto a Lady of high and great discent:
               to the same all parties did agree.
               The Marques sent for Grissell faire,
               The Brides bed chamber to prepare,
               that nothing therein should be found awrye
               The Bride was with her brother come,
               Which was great ioy to all and some:
               and Grissell tooke all this most patiently.
            
            
               And in the morning when they should to the wedding,
               her patience now was tride:
               
                  Grissel was charged her self in princely maner
               for to attire the Bride.
               most willingly she gaue consent to do the same
               the Bride in her brauery was drest:
               and presently the noble Marques thither came
               with all his Lords as her request.
               O Grissel I would aske quoth he,
               If she would to this match agree.
               me thinkes her lookes are waxen wondrous coy,
               With that they all began to smile,
               And Grissell she replide the while,
               God send Lord Marques many yeres of ioy
            
            
               The Marques was moued to see his best beloued
               thus patient in distresse:
               He stept vnto her, and by the hand he tooke her
               these wordes he did expresse:
               Thou art my Bride, &amp; all the Brides I meane to haue:
               these two thine owne children be:
               The youthfull Lady on her knees did blessing craue
               her brother as willing as she,
               And you that enuied her estate,
               Whom I haue made my louing mate,
               now blush for shame, &amp; honor vertuous life:
               The Chronicles of lasting fame,
               Shall euer more extoll the name,
               of patient Grissell my most constant wife.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

