
   
      
         
            The most famous and tragicall historie of Pelops and Hippodamia Whereunto are adioyned sundrie pleasant deuises, epigrams, songes and sonnettes. Written by Mathewe Groue.
            Grove, Mathew.
         
         
            
               1587
            
         
         Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02273
            STC 12403
            ESTC S105883
            99841609
            99841609
            6205
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02273)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6205)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 546:9)
         
         
            
               
                  The most famous and tragicall historie of Pelops and Hippodamia Whereunto are adioyned sundrie pleasant deuises, epigrams, songes and sonnettes. Written by Mathewe Groue.
                  Grove, Mathew.
                  Smith, Richard, fl. 1587.
               
               [144] p.   
               
                  By Abel Ieffs dwelling in the Forestreete without Creeplegate, neere vnto Grubstreete,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1587.
               
               
                  Editor's dedication signed: R. Smith.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-I.
                  Running title reads: The historie of Pelops and Hippodamia.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-01
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-01
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE moſt famous and Tragicall HISTORIE of Pelops and Hippodamia.
Whereunto are adioyned ſundrie pleaſant deuiſes, Epigrams, Songes and Sonnettes.
            
            Written by Mathewe Groue.
            
               Imprinted at London by Abel Ieffs dwelling in the Foreſtreete without Creeplegate, neere vnto Grubſtreete, 1587.
         
         
            
            
            ¶ To the ryght Honorable, Sir Henrie Compton knight, Lord Compton of Compton hole, R. S. wiſheth long life with increaſe of honour.
            
               AS Moyſes once by law then made
               Was taught to ſwimme and not to wade
               Ariued (by God) at Princes place,
               Whom Pharaos daughter tooke to grace.
               And brought hym vp, and taught hym ſo,
               Who prooued at length as well ye know:
            
            
               So I by channce thys Pamphlet here
               Dyd ſaue ſometime from water cleere,
               And tooke it vp and brought to light,
               To be defended through your might.
               And ſo your Honours fauor finde,
               According to the Authors minde.
            
            
               Foure yeere and more I dyd hym nurſe.
               Although no whit it coſt my purſe,
               Yet driuen at length at coſt to be,
               Becauſe your Lordſhip ſhould it ſee,
               Yet no ſuch coſt as ſhall appeare,
               But mende my purſe within the yeare.
            
            
               
               Th'aucthor ſure I doe not know,
               N
                     •
                  whet
                     •
                  er he be high or low,
               Or now aliue, or els be dead:
               But this in few words may be ſead.
               Hoping your honor accept it will,
               According to the Authours skill.
            
            
               And for my part still ſhall I pray,
               That God your Lorſhip bliſſe alway.
            
            
               R. Smith.
            
         
         
            
            
               ❧ The Authors Epiſtle.
            
               WHen I had compiled (right honorable) this litle treatiſe, and barbarous Manuel, conteyning the Hiſtorie of Pelops and Hyppodamia, with ſundrie Songs and Sonets, (being none other in deede then ſuch as at leiſurable times hapned to my minde, and not of purpoſe inuented) I ſtoode in doubt whether I were better preſume to publiſh this my trauail, or in couert wiſe to keepe it cloſe. At length I aſſured my ſelfe although it would bring but litle pleaſure to the Readers if it were publiſhed, yet l
                  •
               ſſe would it be to any man if I kept it cloſe. To this ende, to this point and iſſue I reſolued my ſelfe for a ſeaſon, and minded in deede to bring it to light But the while (as it were by a viſion) another doubt and newe diſturbance hapned to my minde, that for ſo much as by often reading and peruſing of the ſame, I foūd my doings to be but rude, yea and as it were almoſt in vaine, I was in doubt I ſay, (right Honorable) weighing and conſidering theſe enormities, whether to ſet abroach this my newe wine, being but of ill colour, and worſe 
                  •
               aſt,

vpon mine owne head, or mine owne aduen ture: ſeeing ſo manie ſerpents tongues redie in the waie, and the teeth of ſo manie barking dogs readie to bite: on the one ſide com meth Zoylus or Theogninus, and bring with them a railing rout of Sycophanticall brablers: then thought I beſt on the other ſide to arme my ſelfe againſt theſe my miſchieuous enemies with the title of ſome honorable, that might defend me from all ſuch ſlaunde rous aſſaults. And ſeing that you by iuſt defcent and noble parentage, are ſuch a one as againſt whom I know for certainty by right ſuch men cannot be by enuie moued, I am ſo bolde as vnder your ſhielde to publiſhe this my worke. Therefore theſe two thinges I craue of your honor, which both I truſt of ſo gentle heart as heth within your breaſt ſhal not be denied. The one is this, that for ſo much as more boldlie then aduiſedlie I enterpriſe vnder your name to ſhewe the skyll of my tender quill (being ſo ſmall) I here deſire your Lordeſhip to pardon my raſh doings. And the other is this: for ſo much as this ſimple volume is geuen you of a meere good wil, I deſire you to accept it as a token and none otherwiſe then it is in deede. To be praiſed or extolled aboue the merites of

the ſame, I doe not deſire. My paines herein taken I would not eſteeme, ſo that I might obtaine the beneuolence of the readers: yet if it happen ſo that of the better ſort I ſtand wel liked of, let Momus moppe and mowe, til I bid him ſtaie. Thus truſting that this ſimple token you wil not deſpiſe, I ende, vnwilling anie further to moleſt you, yet the while beſeeching God to preſerue you in Galens health: and in time to endue your Lordſhippe with Neſtors yeares, and Xerxes wealth.
            (⸫)
Your Lordſhips to commaund to his povver, Mathew Groue.
            
         
         
            
            The argument of the Hiſtorie following.
            ONomaus was king of Archandia, vnto whom it was told by the Southſayers, that whonſosuer his onely daughter Hipodamia did marie, he ſhould dye, ſhe comming to her ripened yeeres, he proclaymed a prize of running with Charwis, that whoſoeuer did vanquiſh him therin, ſhould marry Hippodamia, and haue the Realme with her, but the vanquiſhed ſhould dye. Many of the Woers were ſlayne: at laſt Pelops promiſed priuily to Myrtilus that if hee ſhoulde winne the prize, Myrtilus ſhould lye with Hipodamia the firſt night to Whereupon he made the Axiltree of wax, by reaſon wherof in the courſe the Charet fell downe, which Onomaus thē per ceyuing, ſlew hymſelfe, and Pelops enioyed the Lady, and Myrtilus requyring that which was promiſed, Pelops threwe hym into the Sea, which euer after was called mare Myrtonum.
         
      
      
         
            
            The moſt famous and tragicall hiſtory of Pelops and Hippodamia.
            
               THere ſtretcheth long a Realme in Greece,
               
               of antique bruite and fame,
               Whoſe memory remayneth yet,
               
                  Archadia it we name.
               Which title Archas ſonne of Ioue,
               
               beſtowed on that land:
               Who ruled there with Regall crowne,
               and golden mace in hande.
               There is the fenne of Lernea,
               
               where Hidra monſter great
               With hundred hiſſing Serpents heads,
               retayned there her ſeate.
               Til Hercules inforced was
               with ſtrength the fiend to gripe,
               And Erymanthus riuer there,
               his ſurging courſe doth kéepe.
               Where once the ſcepter help in throne
               
                  Omaus with his might,
               
                  One of the ſonnes of dreadfull Mars,
               
               the furyous God of fight:
               
                  
Which wight of Parge ſiſters thrée,
               ſuch grace he gan obtayne,
               That they did all forbeare to cut
               or ſhred his threan in twaine.
               Wherby he drewe his vitall web,
               vntil the ſiluer heares
               Gan grow vpon hys aged ſkull,
               for cauſe of many yeares.
               He only Hippodame had,
               hys daughter damſel fayre.
               Which by deſcent and due deſert,
               ſhould ſtay his lawfull heire.
               Who guyded was in ſéemely life,
               by learned Sages ſtore.
               And as ſhe doeth encreaſe her dayes,
               ſo vertues hath ſhe more.
               She was her fathers only ioy,
               the fortreſſe of his life
               She left was only of his ſtock
               then ſole without a wife.
               In ſomuch that the greateſt care
               and ſtudie of the king,
               Was aye in vertues lore to trayne
               and this hys daughter bring.
               Which vertues ſhe conceiued ſo,
               and printed in her hart,
               
                  
As faſt as learned Patrons could
               inſtruct her them by arte.
               Which cauſed her in flaming yeres,
               to beare the worthy fame:
               And ne to haue among the reſt,
               her mate, a courely dame.
               But that ſhe dyd excell and ſhade
               the ſhape of euery wight
               As much as Luna with her hornes
               ſurpaſt a ſtarre by light.
               Theſe vertues and the like ſo rare
               enforſt the father olde
               With zealous care his daghter and
               her ſtate for to behold,
               And to prouide that damage ſmall
               hereafter ſhould annoy
               The tender corps by any meanes
               of thys his only ioy.
               For which intent he did retayne
               with him in Court alwayes
               A number ſéene in Magike arte
               and prone for ſuch aſſayes:
               Which by their learned ſkil forſhew
               vnto the king and his
               Thoſe things that long ſhal after fal
               of euil hap or bliſſe.
               
                  
Which men Omaus king gan will
               in preſence for to come,
               Which do approch, their dutie eke
               with bended knée ſoone downe,
               Do liſten then to heare their charge:
               to whom the king gan ſay.
               My tryed friends, ye learded péeres,
               in whom my truſt doth ſtay,
               As heretofore ye faithfull haue
               been vnto me and mine,
               In all aſpects and great affayres,
               ſo now your eares encline:
               You all do know our daughter dear,
               our Hippodame milde,
               Who ſéemeth now in youthly yéeres,
               a moſt vertuous childe,
               And ſhunneth yet each ſinfull lore,
               as farre as I can know,
               Whereby to me no little ioy,
               through her I ſay doth grow:
               Yet doubting now dame Fortunes wheele,
               which whirieth very ſtrange,
               I aſke your ayde, for to preuent
               and ſtop a ſodeyne change.
               For Fortune frayle not ſurely ſtayes
               her ſteppes ſtill in one place,
               
                  
But turneth as the winde, whereby
               I ſtay in doubtfull caſe.
               What if that ſhe ſhould be infect
               with Venus wanton ſport,
               Or other like: or if that ſhée
               ſhould any ill report,
               That may vnwiſhed come to paſſe?
               I ſilie wight in woe,
               Might wail the caſe of this my child,
               her ſelfe which noyeth ſo:
               For youth is fraile, and tendeth not
               ſometimes to ſage aduiſe,
               And ſhunneth that which they perceiue
               Thoſe men which do ſeem wiſe,
               For to embrace: for they whom that
               olde Senex ſtaffe hath ſmite,
               In ſadnes, not in youthly pranks
               doe ſtudie and delite.
               But youth doth tread the path to ſin
                     •…
                  
               
               and earſt t'obtaine that ſtill,
               Which they perceiue doth pleaſe the fleſh,
               hap either good or ill.
               And you doe know, there nothing is
               that fraile fleſh pleaſeth more,
               Than that which doth depend on vice,
               wereof there raigneth ſtore.
               
                  
And I remember Venus ſonne
               who with his ſhaft and bowe
               Doth often peérce the harts of thoſe
               who like pangues did ne know
               Alas if that ſhould light on her,
               as likely ſure it is,
               Vnwares to me then might I ſay
               adue my ioy and bliſſe.
               For that blind boy doth caſt his dart,
               not on the meaneſt fort,
               As ſoone as on thoſe ſtately Peéres,
               that places haue in Court.
               For why they driue their time in eaſe
               and idly ſpend the day
               They féede on dayntie diſhes race
               and reſt on downe for aye,
               There is no pleaſure but they taſte
               as may content the hart
               Which are the cauſes that he doeth
               ſo ſoone throwe them his dart.
               For if thou baniſh idlenes,
               thou breakeſt then the bands
               Which Cupid doth with flight deuiſe
               to tangle both thy hands
               If ſhe ſhould chaunce to fix hir mind
               in loue with one that is
               
                  
Inferior in degreé to her
               which match were farre amiſſe,
               I ſhould be loath, therfore my frends
               of this her deſtinie,
               I wil that ye enſearch foorthwith,
               and it reueale to me,
               To this intent I may prouide,
               for to preuent the ſame,
               If it ſhould happen for to be
               impayring to her fame.
               Yet willingly I would that ſhe
               ſhould ioyne with one in loue
               As meete is in degreé, which doeth
               from him all vice remoue,
               For this I know the time will be
               if that her yeres endure,
               Néeds ſhe muſt knit her ſelfe to one
               in wedlock ioy moſt pure.
               Wherfore repaire to th'uſed place
               and with our Gods aſſent
               As touching Hippodamia,
               
               to know their high intent.
               And take the faireſt goate that may
               within this towne be found
               Him offer vp in ſacrifice,
               to them, whoſe laude doeth ſound
               
                  
Aboue the ſtarres, who rule the globe
               who ſitte aboue the ſtarry ſkye,
               And know ſuch things as earſt were pa
                     〈…〉
                  ,
               and thoſe to come perdy.
               Then they all on their bowed knées,
               vnto the earth doe-fall
               And one of them doth anſwere then
               and thus in name of all,
               O king, if that we would not graunt
               now to thy heſt and thée,
               Vnworthy we were of our 
                     〈◊〉
                  ,
               true ſubiects ne were we.
               If that by Magike are we may
               ſatiſfie thée in this,
               We are right glad that by the ſame
               we thée asferre ſuch bliſſe.
               And now there doth remain no more
               but th'while to loue I pray,
               To further that our enterprize,
               which fortune doth aſſay.
               This Onomaus king was of
               and held the Payn
                     〈…〉
                   law,
               He kn
                     •
                  w not then the huing God
               ne kept himſelfe in awe:
               Wherefore he gan
                     〈…〉
                   a place
               as beſt he had in thought,
               
                  
Where hée and earſt his ſubiects moe,
               to fayned Gods they ſought.
               Herein were aulters many ſtore.
               where when in ſmart they fall,
               They offer vp their Sacrifice,
               and to their Gods they call.
               The cauſe is ſay they (for why)
               they offer vp ſuch gift
               And offerings brent for Sacrifice
               is for a proper ſhift,
               For this they thought, ſith that ſo farre
               of diſtance were the ſkies,
               Their voice might ſcarce be heard, or els
               ſo high as ſkies ariſe,
               Yet often they doe prayers houle
               vnto their gods aboue:
               To this intent when loud they crie,
               they might by chaunce haue loue:
               And eke on aulters them to moue
               with burned fleſh intend,
               The ſmoke whereof in litle while
               might vnto them aſcend.
               And thus although no voice might be
               ſo high as ſkies inclinde.
               Yet by the incenſe thereof, they
               might vnderſtand their minde:
               For ſmoake (they ſay) goes vpward ſtill,
               and riſeth with the winde.
               
                  
Theſe wiſemen to the temple goe,
               with haſt for to fulfill
               The heſt of Onomaus king,
               and ſearch for good and ill.
               They bring with them the kyd his death
               which reſteth to receiue,
               And one of them with p
                     〈…〉
                  recing knife
               doeth force him life to leaue.
               And wringing out the blood alſo,
               depriuing him his ſkyn,
               They prayers ſay, which they ſuppoſe
               doeth cauſe the Gods to blinne.
               Then kindle they the fire, and throw
               the Goate into the ſame.
               For to conſume to aſhes aye
               by violence of flame.
               They mark the diuers colours that
               in waſte doe flée therehence,
               The raynbow hue, to déeme thereby
               of Gods the high pretence.
               Some on Saturnus call, and ſome
               on Iupiter doe crye,
               Some on Mars, and ſome on Sol.
               
               yea ſome on Mercurie,
               
               Some on Venus, ſome to Luna
               
               make their vocation.
               No god there was but him they had,
               in appellation.
               
                  
As diuerſly their mindes were ſette,
               ſo diuerſly they cal
               Eche one vnto his god to proue
               which happyeſt would befall
               So they conſume the tyme vntyll
               the fleſhe is almoſte ſpente,
               Then déeme they what ſhall happen, as
               they thinke is Ioues entent,
               And other gods: then pray they one
               whiche oldeſt was of all,
               To ſhew them firſt what he did thinke
               ſhoulde afterwarde befall.
               But he with pauſe doth ſtay, as though
               ſome doubt he did perceyue,
               His rolling eyes caſte vp,
               and muſing he doth leaue
               And ſaid: my fréendes and fellowes deare
               ſhall I nowe tell in déede,
               This caſe, or as I thinke thereof?
               the more haſte the worſte ſpéede.
               I well perceyue by th'azure hue,
               that paynted aye the flambe,
               And by the ſtring that helde the heart
               of this our killed lambe,
               With other ſignes but euill newes,
               for vs aye to declare,
               It certayne is when Hippodame
               
               in mariage linke doth fare,
               
                  
Our king muſt l
                     •
                  ſe his life perforce
               whether he will or no,
               Such froward deſtinie for him
               the Gods haue graunt to ſhoe.
               And was not aye the verie like
               reueled to you all,
               Alas, this cruell ſodaine chaunce
               my minde doth much appall.
               How ſay my friends? but now ſuch feare
               hath ſtrike them to the heart,
               That they haue now ſcarſce power to ſpeake
               or him thereof impart.
               At length they cauſoe him vnderſtand
               that they did know full well
               The ſame, but that they gaue to him
               the preheminence to tell
               And firſt declare the ſame, for hée,
               was oldeſt them among,
               For reuerence ouht be giuen
               to th'old men, of the young:
               They all deuiſe the meane whereby
               they may this expreſſe
               Vnto Omaus, which doth expect
               an anſwere more or leſſe:
               And then that aged father doth
               his tale againe renew,
               Full bent to waile their owne ſtate,
               as after doth enſue.
               
                  
Alas what hay had we (quoth he)
               this arte for to aſſay,
               Why d
                     •
                  d not we beſtowe our minds
               or wits another way?
               I muſe wherfore each wight with tongue
               doth this our darke eſtate
               Moſt happy call, when vs they minde
               and when of vs they prate,
               And blabbe that we each thing doe knowe
               and ken each deſtiny,
               And eke the knots of fortunes laund
               can vndoe by and by.
               Alas if that we tel a man
               his preſent froward fate,
               Then are we ſure of hym to haue
               and purchaſe péeuiſh hate.
               And although hys deſire be
               to know the very ſame,
               Yet nay theleſſe if it be ſharpe
               he giueth vs the blame,
               Againe, or els if we conceale,
               and doe not tell the trueth
               Then are we ſure and certayn that
               the wrath of God enſueth.
               Thus on ech ſide the doubt is playne
               the perill is more great,
               We are in worſe caſe then they whom
               the deſtintes doe threat.
               
                  
As now when that we doe foretel
               this hap vnto the king,
               Who knowes what he in raging fits
               wil doe, or els what thing
               With miſchiefe ſhal be done by him,
               perhaps in that his ire,
               He wil pretend to ſlay vs than
               to quench his burning fire.
               As thogh that we were cauſe thereof
               our ſelues this doe we know
               Nor cannot aye vnleſſe we ſhould
               more ſacrifices ſhowe
               To déeme therby our frowarde fate
               but now the time doth haſte
               That we muſt wend vnto our king,
               and ſpend no winde in waſt.
               I would to Ioue that we might ſtay,
               vntil to morow day,
               And then to yéelde our anſwere vp
               the while we would aſſay
               By incence ſwéete the deſtinie
               that happen ſhould to vs.
               Then each doubt and each fearful poyat
               we would our ſelues diſcuſſe,
               But now there is no remedie,
               
                  Omaus king doeth ſtay
               Ere this time long in cloſet tilte
               to heare what we can ſay.
               
                  
He thinkes it long til that we come
               to tel to him this ſpight,
               Come let vs goe, the gods vs ſhield,
               and ſuccour with their might.
               Thus paſſe they on their way vntill
               vnto the hall they come,
               From thence they paſſe the chambers large,
               and goe through many a roome,
               Vntil the priuie chamber they,
               approach, wherein the king
               Remayned then, whom they ſalute
               as beſt with their liking.
               Then howe they down their knées to th'earth,
               then one of them gan ſay
               O ſoueraine king our liege and Lord
               thus much we doe thée pray,
               Sith thou doeſt wil that we reueale
               ſuch things we know to thée,
               To pardon vs, what euer that
               of vs ſhall ſpoken be.
               That being graunt, we boldly then
               our mindes may whole expreſſe
               And open thée each darkened poynt,
               as thou erſt wouldſt no leſſe,
               Which he gan graunt thus much, and ſayes
               ſome peruerſe newes I féele,
               Becauſe ye doubt mine ire, alas
               I dread dame Fortunes whéele.
               
                  
Perdy I thinke if that my chaunce
               were happy me to ſaue
               There were 
                     〈◊〉
                   ne
                     •
                  de that pardon thus,
               of me you yow ſhould 
                     〈◊〉
                  .
               Oh tell the ſame, then they agayne
               the Gods that rule the ſkye,
               And turne the rounded globe, whoſe power
               and whoſe authoritie
               Thou mayſt ne gaynſay once,
               to vs thus they declare,
               That whē thy daughter Hipodame
               
               in wedlock bands doth fare
               (Which now in ripened yeres doeth waxe)
               that thou ſhalt loſe thy liſe,
               The very day moſt ſure 
                     •
                  r which
               ſee giuen ſtares a wif
                     •
                  .
               Thus much we 
                     ••
                  a
                     •
                  ued haue, thus much
               the peruerſe deſt
                     •
                   y
               Of thee for her by offrings brent,
               we know aſſuredly
               Prouide therfore, it happen ſhall,
               as ſure as Ioue doth raigne
               As true as ſonne of Mars thou art
               in ſkies which did remayne
               
                  
                     ••
                  en he as foming bore that whets
               his tuſkes againſt the fight,
               oth rage with puſfed face, and erſt
               with ſwelling eyes for ſpight.
               
                  
His ire permits his tongue to tel
               the greefe he bides with payne.
               So vanquiſhe he with fury was,
               in dumpe doth ſo remaine,
               At length when memory he found
               his ſparkling eyes at laſt.
               Vpthrowen, this tale with warbling tongue
               among them be outcaſt,
               Oh Ioue what cruel hap is this,
               what deuiliſh deſteny,
               What horror doeth inuade my breſt?
               becauſe that I muſt dye.
               And muſt I die in déede for that
               as yet I neuer knew
               I neuer knew my face before
               what after ſhould enſue
               Oh fortune, fortune, which no treades
               her ſteps ſtill in one place,
               But wauering here and there moſt fraile,
               as doutfully doeth trace
               Why deales not ſhe as equally
               the golden gifts ſhe hath,
               But ſetteth ſome to top on high
               and ſome treades vnderneath.
               Oh Hippodame is this the gift
               and recompence I haue
               Becauſe that I thée traynes thus
               in Courtly place ſo braue▪
               
               
                  
Is this the fruits I reape of thée,
               who in thy childiſh yeres
               Didſt ſhew come thy ſire ſuch hope,
               and ſprang me ſiluer heares:
               Alas, alas, that thou ſhouldſt be
               the cauſer of my greefe,
               Which wa
                     •
                  t the only ioy to me
               and fortreſſe of my life.
               The ſtaffe wherby I teaned, when
               I fel in any ſmart,
               As often as I thought on thée,
               ful light was then my hart
               Oh A
                        •
                     ſculap reuiue my corps
               that paſſeth now to woe,
               Come Cl
                        •
                     o help my parched paines
               and haples hap to ſhowe.
               Ther was not ſince the world began
               a wight that felt ſuch gréefe
               As now I féele, or had ſuch cauſe
               to wayle his noyed life.
               Can there be any greater payne
               or torment can you tell,
               Bethought by furious fiery frendes,
               that lurke below in hell,
               I reade that Ixion is tuxned
               there, and toſt on hie,
               For promiſe broke, or whirling whéele.
               ſo for deſert perdy,
               
                  
                  Siſiphus doeth on ſhoulders beare
               the ſtone to top of hyl,
               Which rolling downe again, he doth
               renue his paynfull ill.
               Amyd the lake with thirſty iawes
               olde Tantalus therein
               Purſues the waues the water ſtream
               doth wet and waſh his chinne.
               And when to him now oft deceaued
               it doeth yet promiſe make
               Then flits the flood the fruite at mouth,
               his famine doth forſake.
               I reade alſo how Titius heart,
               to flying foule is praye,
               And Danaus daughters fill in vaine
               their watry veſſels aye.
               And all theſe féele ſuch pangues and paynes
               for ſome their iuſt deſert
               But I as giltles now abide,
               it for to péerce my heart.
               If for deſert I felt the ſame
               leſſe gréefe it were to me
               But once being come t'expulſe the ſame,
               I finde no remedy.
               Thus finiſhe he hys wayling ſtile
               commaunded earſt with ſpeede
               The Southſayers for to auoyde,
               which willingly for dreade
               
                  
Conſent, miſdoubting much that he
               in fury fond ſome fact
               To them would doe, whereby their gréeſe,
               they ſhould for nought exact.
               
                  Omaus then be takes hunſelfe,
               and goes in couert wiſe,
               To garden plot, where by him ſelfe,
               he wayles with watty eyes,
               There doubts he what were beſt to doe,
               what remedy to finde
               What wile for to coyne out that might
               deceiue fortune vnkind.
               At laſt he thinks to ſlea and dyd
               his daughter of her life,
               For ſo much as ſhe was the ſpring
               wherehence doeth flowe his gréefe
               And better it to be that ſhe
               in Charons boat ſhould w
                     ••
                  d
               Then he, who being dead
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               his deſtinie to end.
               For ſith that Ioue appoynted hath,
               this deſtinie to take,
               Effect when euer that ſhe did
               her ſole eſtate forſake.
               If ſhe were 
                     〈…〉
                  ne before that time
               by no meanes he can ſée,
               Through her deſert this hap to pas
               then no ſuch hap to be.
               
                  
And ſo himſelfe quyt for to leaue
               then ſtayeth be a while,
               At laſt he doeth reuoke thoſe words
               and them from mynd exile.
               And poureth out this playnt agayne,
               ah myſer, did I ſay
               That I with bayſterous hand ſhould pierce
               and Hippodame ſlay,
               I doe recant thoſe words againe,
               in no wiſe it may be,
               She is mine only child, which by
               my wife was left to me.
               Shal I embrue my hands with blood
               or that doe in my rage,
               Which I did neuer yet commit
               ſhall I thus ſtayne mine age?
               No, no, and more then that,
               ſhe is my only childe,
               Then ſhe once dead, Archadia
               
               hath fewe the crowne to wielde,
               If I were dead alſo, therefore
               Ile ſearch ſome witty wile.
               Wherby I may the churliſh ſnares
               of dame fortune beguile.
               And from theſe parched pinching paynes
               my ſelfe for to beguile,
               And therby for to faue her life
               for if that ſhe ſhould dye,
               
                  
I glad woulde be my ſelfe to wende
               with hir, then by and by:
               And what that I did ſpeake before
               I vtterly denye.
               In arbour he conſumes the tyme,
               at length he doth ariſe,
               As Muſa puts into his minde,
               a ſhyfte he can deuiſe,
               Which he thinkes beſt, this is the ſame:
               he myndeth to ordeyne
               A prize to runne with chariots ſwifte
               in fielde vppon the playne,
               And who ſo findes the chaunce
               the ſwyfteſt pace to trace,
               (And vanquiſhed the king) thereby
               for to departe the place
               Shall wedde this dame, and when the lyfe
               of this king is in hande,
               T' inioy Arcadie realme, and earſt
               the king therof to ſtand:
               But on the other ſide, if that
               
                  Omaus geues the foyle,
               The vanquiſhed to loſe their lyues
               for ventring in the broyle.
               Thus he decréed in minde, thereby
               if happie that hée be,
               To winne the prize, if contrarie,
               his owne death for toſée.
               
                  
And now when that he doth perceiue
               he found no better way,
               He hyes him into Pallace ſtraight,
               to publiſh this for aye.
               And then in déede he calleth in
               one which moſt mée
                     •
                  e he found,
               For ſuch aſſayes, whom he can will
               with trumpe in hand to ſound
               In euery place within the Realme,
               the Cities of the land,
               Proclayming to each wight theſe words
               or lyke, which next doe ſtande.
            
            
               Here foloweth the Proclamation.
               
                  IF there be any wyght that myndes to trye
                  By courſe of charets on the field ſhplayue,
                  And eke before the route of chyualry
                  VVorthy ſeeme to haue reward for payne,
                  It ſtayes the wyll of O
                           〈…〉
                        
                      grace,
                  That they approch within theſe thyrty dayes
                  Vnto the Court, where they ſhall finde in place
                  Hymſelfe ſole preſt to try in theſe aſſayes,
                  Gaynſt commers all, and who ſo vanquiſht is
                  On fyeld by him, ſhall ſoone t
                        •
                      enlo
                        •
                     e hys lyfe:
                  But who ſo ouer runnes the king with bliſſe
                  Shall eſpouſe Hipp
                           •
                        dami
                           •
                        
                      to hys wyfe:
                  And furthermore, the Realme for to enioy,
                  After the death of One mau
                           •
                        
                      king.
                  To hym without diſturbance or anoy
                  Of any man, and to hys chyldren after hym.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Tubicen goes and paſſeth fro,
                  he ſounds in euery place
                  The newes, and at the laſt returnes
                  and is one in ioyous caſe,
                  Becauſe that this his toyle,
                  and tournes is ſo paſt,
                  The commons muſe full faſt on this,
                  and are with feare agaſt,
                  Not knowing what the cauſe ſhoulde beé
                  of this ſo ſudden change,
                  But for the moſt part they impute
                  this hap to fortune ſtrange.
                  And as the vulgar people muſt,
                  the nobles ioy againe,
                  For ech of them doth thinke by fight
                  this Lady to obtaine.
                  Then might you ſée the knight concurre
                  on heapes, to haue a ſight
                  Of Hippodam vnto the court
                  t'encourage them to fight
                  And they who that vile daſtard hearts
                  before time did poſſeſſe,
                  In hope to winne this Ladie bright,
                  them now to runne doe preſſe.
                  So much the forme of women doth
                  enforce men for to doe,
                  Like as they neuer did before,
                  ne like againe would ſo,
                  
                     
Vnleſſe it were their enterpriſe
                  as authors olde dyd ſhewe
                  And they that learned are indeéde,
                  the very ſame doe know.
                  The luſty gallants of the Court,
                  that proper are and tall
                  Do mynd to venter now themſelues
                  and hazard life and all.
                  The chooſing is of courſers braue,
                  that trymly treads the way
                  And wel is he that hath the beſt
                  the cheefe to prooue that day.
                  There trim they vp the charets light
                  which put in redyneſſe
                  Ech thing that they ſhal neéd in field
                  themſelues they ſée to dreſſe.
                  The king alſo himſelfe, his horſe
                  prouided he doth ſée,
                  His charets al which lighteſt and
                  moſt meéte were thought to be.
                  In theſe affayres they doe conſume
                  and ſpend the thirty dayes
                  Ordeyning, and ech one hymſelfe,
                  to trye in theſe aſſayes,
                  Thus all things ſet in order due
                  as beſt were to deuiſe▪
                  
                  Among the troupe of chyuallers,
                  one Pelops doth ariſe,
                  
                     
And vewing aye the ſéemly port
                  of Hippodame bright
                  He mynds to try himſelfe to wynne
                  her if he may in fight.
                  There was that time one Myrtilus
                  
                  of fayned faith a wight,
                  Who ruled the charet of the king
                  and draue the horſes right.
                  To hym doth Pelops think to wend
                  there ſome meane to deuiſe
                  Wherby he may preuent the king,
                  and bleare the lookers eyes.
                  And thinks with gelt to ouercome
                  this myſers féeble minde
                  Or by ſome other way, he cares
                  not what, ſo he may finde
                  The meane to be Archadian king
                  wherby he ſhould enioy.
                  This dame, and evry thing he would
                  without let or anoy.
                  And ſearching aye the Pallace large
                  to finde this Myrtilus
                  
                  He commeth to his chamber, where
                  at length ſayes to him thus.
                  My frend, thou knoweſt that in field
                  the combat we ſhall ſee,
                  And veutrous wights to bear the fame,
                  amongſt the chyualry,
                  
                     
And as I one doe minde with force,
                  to ſhew my ſelfe in fight
                  To prooue if lucke will happen me
                  to winne that Lady bright.
                  Yet naytheleſſe by thy deuice
                  if I might winne the ſame
                  I ſhould reward thy veneuolence
                  aduauncing of thy fame.
                  But Myrtilus with fayned ſhew
                  of frendſhip to his Lord
                  Doth anſwere thus, in no wiſe I
                  may vnto theé accord.
                  Think not that I for this thy gloſe
                  of promiſe fine, will ſhewe
                  Me diſobedient to my liege
                  to whom I ſeruice owe.
                  Aduancement ne I craue of theé
                  my paynfull ſeruice may
                  Preferment get me of our king
                  wherfore thus much I ſay
                  Forſake this place, and now deſiſt
                  with talke to trouble me.
                  Then he which to obtaine his will
                  no meane or way did ſee,
                  Being almoſt in deſpaire of hope
                  doeth hope yet once againe.
                  To trye the wight which ſayd hym nay,
                  although it were his payne:
                  
                     
Oh Myrtilus if that I may
                  by any meanes aſpire,
                  To win the prize, and ſpecially,
                  if thou helpſt my deſire,
                  Thou ſhalt be ſure to match in bed
                  with Hippodamie deare,
                  If thou canſt finde the wile to bring,
                  to lucky end this geare.
                  We are as frends, what néede theſe words
                  and circumſtance of ſtile?
                  Eche thing ſhall common be with vs
                  what euer hap the while.
                  What though that thèu doeſt play this pranke
                  art thou the firſt that hath
                  Béen earſt vnfaithfull to his Lord,
                  for ſcant or els for ſcathe.
                  Let muſing go, though this ſéeme ſtrange
                  yet thinke if king I be
                  I will reward this thy deſert,
                  as thou in time ſhalt ſée.
                  Would it not moue a frozen heart
                  yea flinted for to bowe,
                  To haue in armes ſuch damſels as,
                  are rare I make a bowe?
                  Thinke therfore on the night that thou
                  in bed with her ſhalt haue,
                  Who ſtaynes each courtly dame that ſhines,
                  for beuties gift ſo braue.
                  
                     
Now Myrtilus euen as thou wilt
                  to me thine anſwere ſhow,
                  If thou wilt not, I muſt goe ſéeke
                  ſome other wight to know
                  That may me ayd, and think not but
                  if able that I be:
                  This thy vnkindnes Ile requite
                  what euer hap to me.
                  Then he that ſtood ſo ſtiffe gan turne
                  and vnto Pelops ſay
                  More for the brunt of Cupid blinde,
                  then any thing for aye,
                  If that thou liſt thy heſt to kéepe,
                  performde as thou doeſt vowe
                  Ile ſtand content to pleaſure thée,
                  as much as I may ſhowe.
                  If thou canſt be content, that I
                  as thou haſt ſayd before,
                  Shall lye with her, I will prouide
                  that thou néedeſt doubt no more
                  For I wil make the Axeltrée
                  the charet which doeth beare
                  Of waxe, which by force of a cracke
                  moſt ſuddenly ſhall teare
                  Wherby vnto the ground ye knoweſt
                  the charet néedes muſt fall:
                  In ſo much as the Axiltrée,
                  doth beare the charge of all.
                  
                     
Which beeing done, the courſe is loſt
                  then all the prize is thyne,
                  And therefore in the wedding night,
                  lette pleaſure fyrſt be mine.
                  Thou knowſt the king at eche courſe doth
                  with changed charet runne,
                  And thenrenewe his courſe agayne,
                  as firſt it was begunne:
                  Beware that thou doe not preſume
                  to run, till thou doeſt ſée
                  The firſt courſe and the ſecond too
                  expired for to bée:
                  Then valeantly foorth preace thy ſelfe
                  for I wil ready ſtand,
                  To offer him his wexed roome,
                  which next ſhall come to hand.
                  Then Pelops proud of this good hap
                  gramercy ſayes my frend
                  As now I haue no more to ſay,
                  for this thy councel kind,
                  But farewel once, for Phaeton
                  
                  deſcendes Olimpus downe,
                  And Phebus ſhunnes Proſerpina,
                  
                  his foe, that helliſh hound.
                  And I will earſt depart from thée
                  thoſe things for to prouide
                  Tomorow which within the liſtes,
                  
                     
in fight I ſhall haue néede
                  Adue agayne then trudgeth he
                  as faſt as he can fly,
                  Vnto his chamber, where that he
                  doth call to gods on hye
                  For help, but chiefe to Venus mylde
                  to whom young Paris gaue
                  Before the reſt for loue of Nimph
                  the golden apple braue.
                  And ſith that Luna with her black
                  and darkned horned hut,
                  Doth cauſe the ſparkling ſtarres in ſkyes
                  their places to renue.
                  He thinks it beſt to clyme hys bed
                  in ſléepe to ſpend the night,
                  That in the day betimes he might
                  be ready for to fight
                  The time thus doth conſume &amp; wear
                  the night doth vade away
                  And Phebus getting th'upper hand,
                  
                     Proſerpina doeth fray
                  He ſhewes himſelfe as chéeftain now
                  with chariot in the ſkye,
                  With twice two prauncing horſes yt
                  
                  ſhewes hys authoritie.
                  The ſmal birds by their chirping lay
                  doe ſhew the time to wake,
                  
                     
And ſluggiſh bed the drowſie place,
                  a tyme for to forſake
                  For as the day appoynted is
                  to haue with him for ſight,
                  Of things that appertayne to day
                  ſo likewiſe is the night
                  Appoynted hym things to be done
                  which appertayne to light.
                  Therfore each wight doth ſtyrre
                  hymſelfe for 
                        •
                     o prepare,
                  Into the field, and valiantly
                  hys armès for to declare
                  Among the reſt Omaus doeth
                  make ope hys drowſie eyes,
                  Vnwilling he to kéepe hys bed
                  doth ſuddenly ariſe.
                  In mind to make thaduenture ſhort
                  to loſe or els to wynne.
                  Wherfore he haſteth firſt hymſelfe
                  the array for to begyn.
                  Thoſe youthful ſéemly knights
                  who by their great deſire
                  Were pricked forth to try thēſelues
                  no leſſ: haſte dyd require.
                  They thinking long the time to bée
                  themſelues to field do haſt
                  And ſpend not iangling here &amp; there
                  the day which is farre paſt
                  
                     
When it was knowne by ſounde of trumpe,
                  the king at poynt to bée,
                  A number preſt in order braue
                  a man might then eſpie
                  For to attend vpon the king,
                  yea rather on the wight
                  For whoſe ſake now eche one doth knowe
                  to be this broyle and ſight
                  The king as chéefe and chalenger
                  firſt marcheth on the waye,
                  With all the crue of noble men
                  him after in araye,
                  Some wyth theire helmes beſette
                  with plumed fethers hye,
                  Some on theire horſſes heades for ſhewe
                  doe put the like perdie,
                  Which waueth with the winde:
                  the thirde but in degrée
                  Doth Pelops ryde in perfect hope,
                  but none ſo braue as he
                  The charrets make achéere full ſhewe,
                  the trumpets ſounde woulde moue
                  The heart of anie wight, yea ſure
                  the verie goddes aboue
                  So ſhrill a note with puffed chéekes,
                  thoſe men with breth doe ſounde,
                  That from the earth it flyes to ſkies,
                  from ſkyes agayne to grounde.
                  
                     
The horſes eares are filde with that
                  they ſnort, and ſtaring ſtand,
                  They prauncing iette, to ſhew themſelues
                  which beſt might tread the land.
                  But Hippodame whoſe face hath ſet
                  each heart on flamed fire,
                  Doth follow now with troupes of dames
                  in ſad and black attire.
                  Not as ſhe went the prize to ſée,
                  with ioy or to behold
                  But as though that ſhe went to mourn,
                  Oh wight of perfect mould.
                  Thoſe Ladyes that attend her trayne,
                  in lyke ſuite goe they all,
                  As though they wayled ſome their frend,
                  which lately tooke a fall.
                  Thus paſſe they foorth with meaſurde ſteps
                  til they come to the place
                  Where they appoynted are to ſtand
                  as Iudges of the caſe.
                  Within the lyſtes might no man come
                  vnleſſe they minde to trye
                  Themſelues, or footemen which attend
                  the king and Princeſſe nie,
                  Each one in order takes his roome
                  where he himſelfe would ſtand,
                  To run his courſe, and take his lot
                  which comes next to his hand.
                  
                     
What ſhould I ſay, the trumpets blowe
                  the blaſt of battle braue,
                  Each one doth hope by fortune good,
                  him ſelfe to quite and ſaue.
                  And now the time is come at poynte
                  when firſt the king doth ſay
                  He that doth mynd his charet firſt
                  with mine for to aſſay,
                  I wil that he come ſhew himſelfe,
                  then foorth one yodeth faſt
                  And ſayes I am the wight, ſir king,
                  to whom firſt lot is caſt.
                  Then there remains no more, but both
                  let run their charets light
                  As ſwift almoſt as Iphicus
                  
                  were there be ſéene in ſight.
                  But loe the king hath woon the prize,
                  as all men thought before
                  The trumpets ſound their warbling notes
                  for ioy of that therfore,
                  Then néedes the lawe muſt rigor take
                  which ſight did much appall
                  And dread the lookers on, ſo that
                  thers none amongſt them all
                  That venter durſt ſcarce for to runne
                  but muſing there they ſtand
                  At length the ſecond takes like charge,
                  and enterpriſe in hand.
                  
                     
Alas, he followes the other cleane,
                  and taketh ſelfeſame end.
                  For lozing aye the prize, he doeth
                  giue life it to amende.
                  Now Myrtilus oh caytiffe vile,
                  is ready for to bring
                  With trayterous face the charet waxt
                  with ſpeéd vnto the king.
                  Which taken gratefully,
                  the courſe doth then renewe,
                  By Pelops Prince of Phrygia,
                  
                  in order to enſue.
                  But loe, ere that demi the way
                  the courſe had ouerpaſt
                  That brittle axeltrée of waxe
                  euen with a thought was braſt.
                  And fell vnto the ground, wherfore
                  
                     Omaus ſeéing this:
                  Drawes out his goring knife or ſword
                  with force he ne doth miſſe
                  To ſtabbe hymſelfe nye to the hart,
                  ſuch frenzie tooke him then,
                  As ſcarce oppreſſed Hercules,
                  
                  when Iunos wrath began.
                  The only prize is giuen to
                  young Pelops, and the name
                  Of 
                        Ʋictor doth remayne to hym
                  and Fama ſhewes the ſame.
                  
                     
The perſed corps is taken vh,
                  and as the guyſe is there,
                  Vnto the temple of their Gods
                  to burning him they beare.
                  But Pelops takes the readie waye
                  to Hippodamia ſhéene:
                  Where as ſhe ſtood on plated ſtage,
                  to ſeé and to be ſeéne,
                  His bonet vailed, humblie he
                  gan ſay hir on this wiſe,
                  Due reuerence once being done
                  hys face toward the ſkyes,
                  Oh rare ſeéne ſparke of beuties flame,
                  oh Matron of the crue,
                  
                     Panthora thou, whoſe face doth ſtayne
                  bright Phebus golden hue.
                  Sith that the 
                        •
                     oas aboue haue ſhewed
                  to me ſuch dignity,
                  To beare the prize of winning theé,
                  by true authority.
                  To whom I render thanks for this
                  I come now for to clayme
                  And aſke my right, for ſith by Lawe,
                  I woon thée in thys playne,
                  I iudge theé mine, your Fathers heſt
                  doeth teſtifie the lyke.
                  Then ſhe whoſe roſeall hue was ſtaynde
                  and hyd on euery cheéke,
                  
                     
By ſpring of chriſtall teares, at laſt
                  this wiſe to him gan ſay,
                  Sir Pelops thou of Phrygia Prince
                  in whom vertue doeth ſtay,
                  Sith that by armes I am your own,
                  I thereto doe agreé,
                  As lawe requires: yet as thou art
                  a knight, this graunt to me
                  I may a while deplore the death
                  of my vnhappy ſire
                  Who cauſer is of his owne fall
                  by this his fond deſire.
                  For nature bynds the child to wayle
                  this day let me haue ſway
                  To morow I for to commaund,
                  am thine, and then alway
                  And that I may thoſe obſequies
                  and rytes which appertayne
                  To funerals fulfil, and then
                  thine owne I doe remaine,
                  Til Atropos my vitall twine
                  entends to cut in twayne,
                  If thou in heart agreé alſo,
                  and therefore I require
                  Theé for to reſt thy weary corps
                  and me haue my deſire.
                  Then he replete with ioy, doth wend
                  vnto the Pallace cleere,
                  
                     
And Hippodame tendes the corps
                  which layd is on the beére,
                  With woful hart and dreary playnt,
                  the Ladyes reſt doe wayle,
                  The king, but more bicauſe this wight
                  ſo much her mone doeth vayle.
                  The triumph thus imixt is with
                  huge ſadnes and ſome ioy,
                  As ſome lament, ſo ſome reioyce,
                  and thus they ſpend the day
                  Til Omaus dead inioys the flame
                  as worthy as may be,
                  After the vſe of Arabia
                  
                  as authors teſtifie.
                  But oh, prince Phaeton forſakes
                  with weary horſe the hil,
                  Deſcending down Olympus tops
                  below to ſtay, vntyll
                  By holes diſtinct, the time is ſet
                  t'aduance hymſelfe againe.
                  Then evry wight betakes him ſelfe,
                  to bed of releaſt payne,
                  And though that Pelops throwes himſelfe,
                  on bed for ſhewe of reſt
                  Yet ſleépes he not, ſo much with ioy,
                  his heart is ouerpreſt.
                  He hates this night, and hopes for day
                  He thinks it long to ſeé,
                  
                     
Til that dame Hippodame ſhe might
                  his ſpouſed mate once be.
                  Who now her tender corps in bed
                  hath hid in couert wiſe,
                  Of whom likewiſe Somnies with ſtright
                  
                     
                        •
                     a
                        •
                     ne approach their eyes.
                  Whom dalor rules, and woe reſtraynes
                  ſhe wayles the hapleſſe hap
                  Of her vnlucky Father, which
                  
                     Fortuna dyd entrap.
                  Yet thinketh ſhe her ſorrowes large,
                  now for to be the leſſe
                  Sith that for loſſe of father, ſhe
                  an huſband ſhal poſſeſſe.
                  Theſe thoughts conſume and driue the night
                  tyl Sol doeth ſhewe hys hue
                  And Terra glad thereof, doth now
                  forſake her watrye dewe.
                  Then might you ſée dame ſtoras arte
                  depaynted aye on gréene
                  How herbs ſtart vp their heds aboue
                  the ground for to be ſéene.
                  Ech feathered fowle diſdayns yt buſh
                  the trée is pearch for night,
                  And reſting boghs do ſéek their prais
                  in fields where they are pight.
                  And likewiſe as in ſiege each wight,
                  is ſtirring here and there,
                  
                     
Some doing this, ſome doing that,
                  all buſie euery where,
                  For this day comes in which they minde
                  with mirth and ioy to kéepe.
                  The mariage of two princes yong,
                  which now forſake the ſléepe.
                  The nobles of the Realm make haſt
                  and ſay, its time that they
                  Ordeine themſelues the temple to
                  therefore to come away.
                  Oh if that Clio would accept,
                  to ſhewe her worthy art
                  In bookes to wryte the order that
                  that day was kept with hart.
                  Then might you ſee a triumph, as
                  if Alexandrus were
                  With all his iolilyke royaltie,
                  in place among them there.
                  But to procéed, they ſeaſe the church
                  when trumpets ſound the blaſt
                  Where both they ioyn in one ere that
                  the day was demi paſt.
                  Euen as it did behoue ſuch Péeres
                  where both they crowned be
                  The king and Quéene of Archadie
                  
                  great ioy it was to ſée.
                  Mens minds wer not ſo fangled thē
                  
                  as now they doe appeare
                  
                     
Therefore eche ſolemne thing was done,
                  more rudely as I heare
                  But leaue we them to celebrate
                  thoſe things we haue in hand
                  And reuert to the Pallace, where
                  no wight doeth idle ſtand.
                  But there prepare of coſtly cates
                  a banket rare to ſée,
                  As thogh the muſes nine themſelues
                  inuyted gueſts ſhould be.
                  What ſhuld I ſay by al thing which
                  preſent dyd there abound,
                  It ſuffized then the very ground
                  and floore for to ſurround:
                  No heart could wiſh but there it was
                  as dyd thereto pertayne
                  No tonge can ſhew els what did lack
                  but there it was full playne
                  The diuyne rites performed then
                  they both retyre at laſt,
                  For Sol now in hys woonted roome,
                  Meridyan is plaſt.
                  Where they conſume the time at meate,
                  two houres large or more,
                  The noble men attending aye
                  and waytyng them before.
                  Both Dukes and Earles with ſuch lyke,
                  and Barons of hye priſe,
                  
                     
Eche one in office dyuerſly
                  as beſt was to deuiſe.
                  This dinner done, the armory
                  beginneth for to ſound,
                  Which to the land of Pelops, and
                  
                     Hippodame doth redound
                  There Orpheus ſcholers ſhewe,
                  their maſters ſkyll and arte
                  Then youthly knights betake themſelues
                  all things els ſ
                        •
                     c apart
                  T
                        •
                      daunce and rayſe the dames
                  or Nimphes almoſt in ſight.
                  And ſo in pleaſure they conſume
                  the tyme vntyll the night,
                  The king departs the hall hymſelfe,
                  as faſt as he can hye,
                  Which Myrtilus as prone therfore,
                  doeth ſuddenly eſpye.
                  And thus he ſayes, ſir Pelops now,
                  ſith that you doe obtayne
                  This dame and eke the Realme, by my
                  induſtry and my payne,
                  I reade you for to kéepe your heſt,
                  the time is preſent now
                  The night drawes on, therfore I pray
                  remember wel your vowe
                  But he theſe words doeth thunder out,
                  oh caytyffe borne to ill,
                  
                     
Oh myſer moſt, diſhonour ſuch
                  wouloſt thou me bring vntil:
                  Oh traytor vil
                        •
                     , diſſembler thou
                  thou ſhalt haue thy reward.
                  Becauſe mine honor, and thy faith
                  thou diddeſt not regard
                  For thy deſart and vſage aye,
                  example thou ſhalt be,
                  To other that commit ſuch crime,
                  what euer hap to me.
                  Now Pelops calles to other, which
                  he ſtudeth beſt to truſt,
                  And painteth out this hap to them
                  of Myrtilus vniuſt.
                  Who being bound they throw on horſe,
                  vnto the ſea they ride:
                  There plunge they in this Venus child
                  with this reproch that tide.
                  
                     Lye there thou Lecher, thou wouldſt fayne
                  
                  
                     aſſwage thy foule deſire,
                  
                  
                     On her who is thy Leege, on whom
                  
                  
                     thou oughtſt no ſhame require.
                  
                  And yet becauſe that by this help,
                  yaung Pelops gate the game,
                  In memorie of him he would
                  that ſea to be are his name.
                  This done, they all returne againe,
                  vnto the woonted place
                  
                     
But in the Citie they diſguiſe
                  themſelues with hidden face,
                  And maſke vnto the Court, where that
                  they ſpend much time in play,
                  Not knowen whothat they were, vntill
                  they threwe their maſke away,
                  Which done the Quéene departs the hall,
                  each wight departs to reſt,
                  King Pelops wiſhing nothing leſſe,
                  is thereto likewyſe preſt.
                  Where they content, both take their eaſe,
                  as both they dyd require,
                  And Pelops hath the onely wight,
                  whom moſt he did deſire.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            Epigrams and Sonets.
            
               Of the moſt famous, renowmed, and thrice happie Realme of England.
               
                  OH fertile ſoyle, thou l
                        •
                     ttle lande,
                  that Anglia hath to name,
                  Vnto whoſe bankes and lymits ſet
                  
                     Brutus of perfect fame
                  With forced ſhield gan turne his arme
                  vnto thée now I ſay,
                  Theſe worde to thée, in whom the waues
                  of hony ſwéete doe ſtay.
                  In whom the floods of milke doe runne,
                  and 
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                     e doth flowe,
                  Like l
                        •
                     n
                        •
                      our Lord to his elect,
                  did promyſe long agoe.
                  If euer thou hadſt cauſe to laugh,
                  or ioyfull to be ſéene,
                  They clay thy hands, and thanke the God
                  t
                        〈…〉
                     ue thee ſuch a Quéene.
                  W
                        〈…〉
                     ues doe aſcend and mount
                  vnto the very ſkyes,
                  And there doe moue the mighty Ioue,
                  
                  to turne to thée hys eyes.
                  With louely hand to poure on thée,
                  the ſeedes of this his grace
                  And plentie cauſeth of all things
                  to abound in euery place.
                  
                     
Within thy compaſſe cut thou canſt
                  not truely witnes this,
                  Before her dayes that like in thée
                  there was ſuch cauſe of bliſſe.
                  Nor aye there is none other cauſe
                  by wit which thou canſt finde
                  That mooued God to throw on thée
                  ſuch plenty thus aſſignde.
                  But her, before her dayes, in bookes
                  full playne its to be ſéene
                  What war, what ſtrife, and ſlaughter great
                  in thée at once hath béene.
                  What ſcarcitie with thée there was,
                  what penury each thing,
                  For want of grayne, the lack of foode
                  dyd to thy bowels bring.
                  The moued Gods by ſome thy fault,
                  what euer ſinne it were,
                  Did thée inforce the horror huge,
                  and wrack of warre to beare.
                  By reaſon when the people faynt,
                  and tyred could not toyle,
                  To tyll this land, wherby almoſt
                  it was vnfertile ſoyle.
                  But now ſith none there is in ſight,
                  oh thanke thy God therefore,
                  And wiſh her life that is the cauſe
                  of this thy perfect ſtore.
                  
                     
Who here in preſence prayeth plain,
                  vnto the Lord aboue,
                  At whoſe requeſt, and whoſe behalfe,
                  he poures on thée ſuch loue,
                  Yet thinke not (litle Realme) that it
                  is for thine owne aſſent,
                  Thy ſinne is ſore, it is for her,
                  or els thou mightſt be ſhen
                        •
                     .
                  Her vertues ſhine as bright as ſtars
                  as cléere as Phebus chéefe,
                  The port of hir doth ſtayne the moon
                  a Phenix by her life.
                  For chaſtity Lucretia
                  
                  ne could that Romiſh dame
                  Aſpire to her, though while ſhe liued
                  ſhe had the only ſame.
                  Let prudent Pallas pauſe a ſpace
                  and then for to eſchue
                  Let 
                        
                           •
                        lio muſe to paint the gifts,
                  which Ioue doth her endue:
                  Who worthy is to rule and raigne
                  beſides her kingdomes thrée
                  Ouer the globe which we account,
                  all Chaos for to be.
                  What ſhuld I ſay, what ſhal I write
                  but land the royall race
                  Of her who by her paſſing port
                  ſtaynes Iuno
                           •
                        s very face.
                  
                     
                     Elizabeth whoſe name compact,
                  doth ſtand of letters nine,
                  The effect thereof and meaning true
                  in fewe words to define.
                  She loues the Muſes nine, ſhe leues
                  their wiſdome paſſinglie:
                  She loues the ſugred ſkil, ſhe loues
                  their lawes aſſuredly.
                  Let ech true ſubiect on his knée
                  with thankful heart ſtil pray
                  For to preſerue this noble Quéene,
                  in vertues lore alway.
                  The queene of England, realme alſo
                  of France and Ireland
                  
                  Whom God protect from all annoy
                  by his moſt mighty hand.
                  And graunt her ſubiects her to ſerue
                  inheart with one accord:
                  While ſhe doth raigne here ouer vs,
                  as long as pleaſe the Lord.
                  And when that Atropos ſhal cut
                  and ſhred her webbe in twaine,
                  In ſkyes with him to ioy a place,
                  for euer to remayne.
               
            
            
               The Author being minded to write, but la
                     •
                   king an argument, made this following, thinking wherof he were beſt to write.
               
                  
                  VVHen Phebus in the azure Skye
                  Gan mount with horſes tracyng hye,
                  Then was my mynd bent to endite,
                  Some pretty toy with pen to write.
                  Of quyls I had in place good ſtore,
                  With inke and paper méete therfore
                  But arguments I wanted aye
                  That might conduct on the way
                  At length when zelous ſtudy had
                  Pretence to write of good or bad,
                  As aye my mind dyd geue me ſkill,
                  It ſelfe reprooued mine owne wil.
                  I wil of kings goe tel the raigne,
                  How they in throne doe hie remayne.
                  That doth ſur paſſe my baſe eſtate
                  Some other thing Ile imitate
                  Ile write of prieſtes, but with thoſe
                  It is mad medling in a gloſe.
                  Of good men I wil ſomewhat ſhewe,
                  But fewe ſuch on earth I know
                  Then wil I wryte of ſuch therfore,
                  As doe geue almes vnto the poore.
                  It is rare vſed in each place,
                  
                     Ergo I wil omyt that caſe.
                  Of faſting ſomething Ile declare
                  But let that goe it is ſo rare.
                  Ile write of rich mens huge deſtre,
                  The more they haue, more they require.
                  
                     
But ſhal I talke of a blaſt of wynde?
                  Then women Ile not leaue behinde.
                  Of naughtypacks Ile paynt the ſhowe,
                  That argument would ouerflowe.
                  Of whordome then ſhal I deuiſe
                  A volume large that would compriſe.
                  I wyll then flatter euery man,
                  But many men that ſcience can.
                  Then wyl I lye, Ile cog and face,
                  Nay that is vſed in euery place.
                  Shall I tel trueth, it is too rawe,
                  A blacke Swanue I neuer ſawe.
                  Oh Ioue what world is this to ſée?
                  Amendment no way found may be.
               
               
                  Omnium rerum viciſsitudo.
                  Warre bringeth pouertie,
                  Pouertie bringeth peace.
                  Peace bringeth riches,
                  Riches bringeth pride,
                  Pride bringeth warre.
                  Warre bringeth pouerty, &amp;c.
               
               
                  VVHereas by martiall power and might,
                  the Citie vanquiſht ſtayes,
                  And ouerrun by forraine foes
                  denyeth ſuch aſſayes.
                  Then pouertie purſues with payne,
                  and pyncheth euery wight.
                  
                     
With gréedie gripes to ſhewe his ſtrength,
                  and eke outragious ſpight,
                  By pouertie each man is forſt,
                  to aſſwage his hautie heart,
                  And hold himſelf content with peace
                  all horror ſet apart.
                  Then aye as authors witneſſe doe,
                  ſmall things for to encreaſe,
                  And grow ful great, as long as that
                  each wight enioyts the peace.
                  So that by peace it followes then
                  a man may ſoone obtayne
                  The ſand of golden Pactolun,
                  
                  and eke the ſiluer vayne
                  Then if a man enioyes the pelfe
                  of riches pleaſant molde,
                  He fals in pride, th'unhappy clog,
                  too high his head to holde.
                  Wherby he ſpurns againſt ſuch as
                  his betters farre are borne:
                  Then wat pu
                        •
                     ſues this peace again
                  in former place to torne
                  So doth this world flit alway,
                  ne conſtant doth abyde,
                  And fortune whirleth very ſtrange,
                  on rounded ſtoole to glide.
                  Wherfore I deem ech toyling wight
                  that traceth on the ball,
                  
                     
Farre better aye had béene vnborne
                  ne troubled there at all.
               
            
            
               The louer being demaunded wherefore he went alwaies in black attire, in cōmen datiō of the ſame, made anſwere to his Lady on this wiſe,
               
                  SIth that each man with brauery,
                  in colours doth him dight,
                  Such as may pleaſe his miſtreſſe eye,
                  and anſwere her delight,
                  Some chooſe the gréene, the white ſome weare,
                  ſome tawney light or ſad:
                  And ſome in yealow garniſht are,
                  in purple ſome be clad.
                  Some orient red, ſome watchet dye
                  ſome one, ſome diuers take,
                  And weare the ſame moſt curiouſlie
                  for their fayre miſtreſſe ſake.
                  And wheras I doe ſerue and ſue
                  and ſeéke to haue the grace
                  Of her that with her liuely hue
                  ſtaynes all that comes in place.
                  To know a reaſon you requeſt
                  what thing I ſhould deſire
                  That only I aboue the reſt
                  in blacke my ſelfe attire.
                  
                     
The black and browne doe ſeldome change,
                  they fixe their louely grace,
                  When other colours light and ſtrange,
                  doe vade within ſhort ſpace.
                  The yealow ſoone it waxeth pale,
                  the ruſſet keepes ſmall ſtay▪
                  
                  The tawny eke wil ſoone be ſtale,
                  the purple wil decay.
                  The white wil ſoyle, the gréene wil ſtayne
                  ſo wil the louing blew:
                  The red wil change with litle payne,
                  and take another hewe.
                  And ſo the grace is ſhortly gone,
                  their beuty ſoone decayes,
                  But black is black, and alwayes one,
                  and ſerues at all aſſayes.
                  And ſo the heart that you doth ſerue
                  what fortune ſo betide,
                  From trueth profeſt wil neuer ſwerue
                  but conſtant ſtill abyde,
                  Beſide all this theſe colours light,
                  doth nothing els declare,
                  But what their fancy and delight
                  doth will, the ſame they weare.
                  As virgin white and wel beſéene,
                  the hopeful ruſſet bewe,
                  The pleaſant yelow, youthfull gréene,
                  and eke the faithful blewe.
                  
                     
Thangry red, the men forſake
                  in tawney chuſe their weede.
                  And thus in colors they them ſhape
                  as folly doth them leade.
                  Of colors as is their attire,
                  ſo fléeting is their minde
                  They loue, they leaue, deſpiſe, deſire,
                  
                     
                        •
                     o ſtckle as the winde
                  But ſober black preſents a mind,
                  whom fully makes not fayne,
                  Dame prudēce there may fauor find
                  and lodge with all her trayne.
                  And as vnchanging is the hewe
                  and eke vnmedled die,
                  So conſtant is the heart and true
                  that vnder it doth lie.
                  And thus for this I weare the blacke
                  you may right wel bel
                        ••
                     ue
                  And not for that I mourn, or lack
                  but that which you may géeue.
                  Oh were the happy houre at hand,
                  come were that ioyfull day
                  When you my faith wil vnderſtand,
                  and trueth vprightly way.
                  And ſo releaſe my paynfull ſute,
                  to lie poſſeſt in place,
                  To reape the long deſired fruite,
                  and ioy the wiſhed grace
                  
                     
With colours then let them depart,
                  whoſe fancy flits alwayes
                  While I in black with ſtedfaſt heart
                  doe ſerue you all my dayes.
               
            
            
               The louer hauing daunced with his Lady, in the end thereof ſpeaketh theſe words.
               
                  MAdam, ſith that you doe vouchſafe
                  to daunce about with me
                  I render harty thanks, and though,
                  vnworthy now I be,
                  To kiſſe your tender palme with mouth
                  yet doe I naytheleſſe,
                  Remaine your ſeruant ſtil in heart,
                  and place of thrall poſſeſſe.
               
            
            
               The anſwere to the ſame.
               
                  GOod ſir, whereas you ſay that you
                  vnworthy are with me
                  To daunce, your pleaſure and
                  your tongue doe both agrée.
                  You may ſay what you liſt, but this
                  I knowe to be moſt true,
                  No dame there is within this place,
                  condigne to match with you.
                  Much leſſe am I that meaneſt am
                  inferior to them all,
                  
                     
A worthy dame t'aſpire to you
                  to daunce within this hal:
                  Stoupe not ſo lowe to kiſſe my hand
                  for if that you doe pleaſe,
                  I am your owne what ſo betide
                  your thraldome to releaſe.
                  And thinke that you haue gotten cut
                  and in this preſence found
                  A ſeruant true, as like that which
                  dame fame did once refound
                  Vnto Penelope the faire
                  which was Vliſſes wife.
                  What would you more, I am your owne,
                  in heart whileſt I haue life.
               
            
            
               Omne mundum poſitum est in malign tatem.
               
                  COmplayning I ne can refraine
                  with meaſure iuſt my tongue,
                  But he vnloſe with mingled tunes,
                  muſt make a dolefull ſong.
                  And ſay as 
                        
                           •
                        ullie ſaid, when he
                  the Romans did accuſe,
                  O maners, o time, becauſe that they
                  all goodnes did refuſe.
                  There was not ſith the world was
                  a worſer time than this
                  In which the Lady Virtus doeth
                  of preſeats alway miſſe.
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                     
The aſſembly huge of Reprobates
                  doth more and more encreaſe.
                  And treadeth downe the ſimple ſoules,
                  by their moſt heauy preaſe.
                  Which when my mind did know, foorthwith
                  by feare I dyd refrayne,
                  This tale not méete yet for ſuch as
                  doe virgins pure remayne.
               
            
            
               The reſtleſſe eſtate of a Louer, written to a frēd of his, whrein he craueth to haue ſome good councel to eaſe his greefe.
               
                  MY frend, the care that I ſuſtayne
                  and life I leade at all,
                  I ſend in paper here, as by
                  theſe lines perceiue you ſhall.
                  The ſluggiſh bed and drowſie place
                  I always doe deteſt
                  Sith I therin with weary limmes
                  enioy no quyet reſt.
                  Before that Phebus ſhewe his beams
                  in morning I ariſe
                  On field to fare then forth I paſſe,
                  as is my common guiſe.
                  Where of the luſty flowers gréene,
                  and ye alow freſh of hewe,
                  As by and ouer them I paſſe.
                  I take the perfect vewe.
                  
                     
Which colours two (though vading aye)
                  I like and euer ſhall,
                  For in the field while they remayne
                  they paſſen colours all.
                  Directly then vnto ſome hil,
                  or mountaine faſt me by,
                  In beaten path I take my courſe,
                  and way as it doth lie.
                  Where long I ſcale with féeble legs
                  my ſelfe vp for to get.
                  By reaſon though of troubled heart
                  I puffe and ſometime ſwet.
                  
                     
                        •
                     et ſtint I neuer till that I
                  on higheſt place may ſtand
                  
                     
                        •
                     nd top therof, me round about,
                  for to behold the land
                  The ſweling ſea with ſurging waues
                  alſo ſuch foules as flie
                  And euery thing that of the land,
                  or ayer comes me by.
                  The gréene forreſt which vnto me
                  doth ſéeme moſt fayre of all,
                  And euery fearefull beaſt thereof
                  to you which I name ſhal.
                  The mighty hart, his make the hind
                  the buck and eke the doe.
                  On ſide of hil there reſteth, and
                  the ſwift amazed Roe.
                  
                     
The nimble long ear'd hare that ſwift
                  before the hound gan run,
                  The litle crarknut ſquirel erſt
                  on tree, that pretie bun:
                  And further more I ſée by me,
                  the wilie ſubtile foxe.
                  The balſtone or the grey doth chaſe
                  and beate from clinie rocks.
                  Oh but at length I doe perceiue,
                  as wiſhed with the reſt,
                  A pallace pure of pleaſure, and
                  the place that likes me beſt.
                  And as in ioy (by ſight therof)
                  in dumpe there ſtil I ſtay
                  At length vnto my ſelfe theſe words,
                  with warbling tongue I ſay.
                  Within thy walles and chambers fayre
                  a perfect place of bliſſe,
                  My deareſt frend, the w
                        •
                     ght that hath
                  my heart, encloſed is.
                  Where oft I wiſh my wretched corps
                  in couert for to be,
                  So that no wight my ſodayne ſhape
                  or preſence knew but ſhe.
                  Tranſformed from my proper hew,
                  and changed in ſuch wiſe,
                  As for our ſureties both ſhe could
                  her ſelfe then beſt deuiſe.
                  
                     
A pretie little hound on her
                  with faithful heart to fowne,
                  I ſtand content ſo that my minde,
                  were preſent to her knowen.
                  A chirping mouſe in hole to créepe,
                  in caue or hollow wall:
                  When that in bed ſhe thinks to reſt,
                  my louing noyce were ſmall,
                  A linnet in a wretched cage,
                  before her for to ſing
                  With ſhrilliſh notes I would ne ſtay
                  nor ſtent of warbuling.
                  A Phillip Sparow on her fiſt
                  or elſwhere to be fed,
                  At her owne hands twice euery day
                  with choſen crums of bread.
                  A little Robin that doeth hop
                  about with reddiſh breſt:
                  Or els if Ioue would me conuert,
                  a blacke flea in her neſt.
                  In faith with force ne could I finde
                  or thinke once in my heart,
                  The prety naked ſoule from out
                  her ſléepe once for to ſtart.
                  But that mine eyes at leyſure might
                  her ſéemely corps behold:
                  Of God that rules the rounded ball,
                  none other thing I would.
                  
                     
Thus when my weary playnt
                  and wiſhes all haue ſayn:
                  Thie me home, becauſe the night,
                  approched to my paine.
                  Where I conſume the day, vntil
                  I ſée the mantled night:
                  Which come on bed, for ſhew of reſt,
                  I ſpend vntil the light,
                  And then my courſe to mountain hie
                  againe Idde renew
                  Of euery thing as yeſterday,
                  to take the perfect vewe
                  Lot here my frend I ſend to you
                  the patterne of my payne,
                  I craue nothing but of your hands
                  an anſwere ſage againe.
                  And as in pleaſure you haue béene
                  to me a faithfull frend,
                  So likewiſe in diſtreſſe and gréefe
                  to ſhew your ſelfe ſo kinde.
                  Some good aduice let me receiue
                  of that thy gratefull hand,
                  Wherby I may direct my path
                  as ſureſt for to ſtand.
                  The while I wil attempt with lines
                  and letters for to moue,
                  The frozen heart of that good ſaint
                  me to requite with loue.
                  
                     
If tok ens may ne boote, or that
                  none other thing preuaile,
                  Then wil I goe and yéelde my ſelfe
                  what ſo ere doth me aſſaile,
                  And preſent plead for grace, but now
                  for once let this ſuffice.
                  My Muſe and I with ſlender quill,
                  to endite wil now deuiſe.
               
            
            
               The Louer writeth to a Gentlewoman, by treatie to cauſe her to loue him, if he may poſſible.
               
                  MAdame, like as the drop that falles,
                  vpon the marble ſtone,
                  Doeth péerce the ſame thogh not with ſtrength
                  but with oft fall thereon.
                  So now thogh that the ſparke of fire
                  be ſmall within my breſt,
                  Yet euery day its like to be
                  ſtil more and more increaſt.
                  Unleſſe that ye vouchſafe to giue
                  to me the oyle of grace,
                  For to preuent the ſame, before
                  it take a roote and place.
                  Therefore theſe lines which I here ſend,
                  doe pray to haue releefe,
                  To flow from you, to him that is,
                  your ſeruant during life.
                  
                     
For ſith that Cupide with his dart
                  hath hit the marke that he
                  Did ſhoote at with his blunted bolt,
                  which ſtocke he made of me:
                  And ſith there is no creature that
                  can rid me fro my gréefe,
                  But onely you, Oh Ladie myne,
                  or cure my noyed life,
                  I ſend you here with faithful minde,
                  a preſent, though but ſmall,
                  Now take my hand, and eke my heart,
                  yea take my life and all,
                  To pleaſure you il that ye liſt
                  ne neuer to denie,
                  Let me enioy the name and place,
                  your ſiruant to ſupplie:
                  Let this ſuffice till that I knowe
                  the tenour of your minde,
                  Whether ye liſt to giue long life
                  or death vnto your fréend.
                  One of theſe two you may preuent,
                  for both reſt in your hande,
                  If that you liſt Panthora milde,
                  ſith I in hope do ſtand:
                  And as I doe perceiue the cauſe
                  of ioy or elſe of gréefe
                  Ile ſay it doth procéede from you
                  be it of death or life.
                  
                     
Go paſſe to hir ye printed lynes,
                  that doth poſſeſſe my heart,
                  If that you cauſe me to receiue
                  ſome comfort of my ſmart,
                  I ſhall reioyce, but if ye giue
                  to me a froward ſtile,
                  I ſhall be prone, and with good will
                  from life me to exile.
               
               
                  By him that hath bin here before
                  your owne, and ſo is nowe:
                  And for to be your owne he hath
                  yplight a faithfull vowe.
               
            
            
               Here the Ladie writeth an aunſwere to the letter of hir Louer, perſeuering in hir ſtubburneſſe: nothing ruing his faithfull heart.
               
                  YOur lines ſir, that you ſent
                  to me but of late dayes,
                  I haue peruſoe, as méete I thought
                  to be for ſuch aſſayes,
                  And ſi
                        •
                     h that you requeſt
                  to haue an anſwere ayne,
                  I ſtand content to do ſo much,
                  ſith you in hope remayne,
                  To put you out of hope,
                  thinke not I am ſo fayne,
                  
                     
To graunt ſo ſoone vnto your heſt
                  that were but folly plaine:
                  Goe chuſe and take your make
                  ſome elſwhere to be found.
                  I am not one that wil ſo ſoone
                  in any band be bound.
                  And you to be as free,
                  as erſt you were before,
                  Leaue of I pray you by my reade
                  and trouble me no more.
                  Yet ſay not naytheleſſe
                  that I the cauſer ſtay
                  And am the weauer of your woe,
                  that were no likely way.
                  Though that your pleaſure were
                  to forge ſuch fayned ſtile
                  And by the ſiluer hooke to catch
                  the fiſh that feares no gile.
                  The loue is very hot
                  for which a man would kill
                  Himſelfe, I know it very well
                  that is a painful ill.
                  Though Pyramus that wight
                  with ſword did péerce his heart,
                  For Thisbie, and ſhe likewiſe did
                  of like death take a part.
                  They two are dead in déede,
                  they two be layd in ſtone,
                  
                     
We neuer ſhal finde out by ſight,
                  their like now they are gone.
                  Now doubt I whether that
                  the like loue flowe from you
                  Therfore content your ſelfe yt while,
                  I muſt néedes ſay adue.
               
               
                  
                     By her that loues not aye,
                  
                  
                     To ſpend her words inwaſt
                  
                  
                     Wherfore ſhe ſends but few lines
                  
                  
                     To thee, farewell in hast.
                  
               
            
            
               The letter of a friend of a wounded Louer, wherein hee goeth about to diſſwade him from this louelie follie.
               
                  MY frend your parched letters are
                  late hapned to my hand
                  And them with eye I haue peruſde,
                  and euery ſentence ſcande.
                  Wherby I doe perceiue that you
                  doe languiſh ſtill in paine,
                  And now according to requeſt,
                  I write to you againe.
                  That I with dreary plaint accuſe
                  and wayle the haples hap
                  Wherin blind Cupid Venus ſonne
                  did lately you entrap.
                  
                     
But yet ſmall remedie I find,
                  if ſhe ſo froward be
                  As in your letters you report,
                  and ſhewe the ſame to me.
                  But that ye doe refraine from loue
                  me thinketh that the wight
                  That lerning hath might wel preuēt
                  and ſtop ſuch peeuiſh ſpight.
                  Loue is not of ſuch force &amp; ſtrength,
                  as farre as I can ſhowe,
                  But if it be by learning you
                  better then I doe know.
                  Then fixe your mind ſome elſwhere aye,
                  where you may reape the fruite
                  For which you haue ſo toyled long
                  by painfull ſuite.
                  But if you cannot ſoone withdraw,
                  from her your yelded hart
                  And thereby to exile your ſelfe,
                  from this your ſnared ſmart.
                  Then wander hence away into
                  ſome Countrey farther off,
                  If you can aye forbeare a while
                  this ſoyle to dwell aloofe,
                  And there with troupe of chiualrie
                  to exerciſe your ſelfe
                  In feates of armes, thereby to ſhun,
                  of loytring loue the elfe.
                  
                     
Such facts wil cleane exile, &amp; driue
                  from out your mazed minde
                  Theſe pranks, inſomuch yt they ſhal
                  no place hereafter finde.
                  The Adage old doth ſhew vs plaine,
                  and as I haue heard ſay,
                  Long out of ſight, clean out of mind,
                  and I beléeue it aye.
                  Then if that you attempt ſome way,
                  and worke ſome wittie wile,
                  By fauor of your frends to fare
                  a litle in exile,
                  And cut the calmed ſeas, the land
                  to treade at th'other ſide
                  You ſoon then wold leue of your loue
                  which now in hart you hide.
                  And if your heart doth not aſſent,
                  in forrain fields to trace,
                  Thē in ſome town within this realm
                  you muſt finde out ſome place,
                  For you that haue the ſtore of welth,
                  may leade your life as beſt
                  To court it out with other braue,
                  and royſt among the reſt.
                  In Court great knowledge is,
                  to which you may aſpire,
                  If that you liſt with zelous paine
                  to applie your whole deſire,
                  
                     
And in the Court alſo you ſhall
                  perceiue ſome condigne dame,
                  That may extinguiſh clean the print
                  and ſparke of the other flame.
                  In time to come perhaps alſo,
                  I ſay you ſhall reioyce,
                  And laugh to ſee this link, the which
                  you left haue by my voyce.
                  Perchāce yt gods haue you preſeru'd
                  vntil ſome better end,
                  Then may you ioy by right with me
                  that ſtandeth for your frend.
                  But if you mind not aye to paſſe,
                  into ſome other land:
                  Nether to ſerue in princely Court,
                  in Courtly roome to ſtand.
                  Then fixe your earneſt minde
                  to aſpire to knowledge hie
                  By ſtudie of the common lawes,
                  a Councelor to ſupplie.
                  And leaue ſuch fondly toyes
                  wherin you now doe frame
                  And trace your ſteps, yt more to tred
                  your preſent woe and paine.
                  And giue the common law the fame,
                  when each trade doth decay,
                  The prouerb old as you know wel
                  doth likewiſy to vs ſay;
                  
                     
No fiſhing to the ſea there is,
                  nor ſeruice to a king.
                  No ſuch game as the trade of lawe
                  doeth to our coffers bring,
                  The trade of Lawe doth fill to brinke
                  from bottome boyſterous bags
                  They royſt in ſilke, when other range
                  the ſtréete in rented rags.
                  Now iudge your ſelfe which of the twaine
                  doeth giue ſhewe beſt to be.
                  With one of them I would that you
                  in heart could aye agreé.
                  If that you like not aye the change
                  of dames within the court:
                  For Countrey prilles your youthfull life
                  with them to lead in ſport.
                  Or if you more eſteeme the ſight
                  of her that wayes not you:
                  More then the gilt that Law doth get
                  by learning to enſue.
                  I know not what thing I ſhall ſay,
                  but wayle the froward fate,
                  Which vnto you the Gods haue graunt,
                  to purchaſe peéuiſh hate.
                  Thus now adue my frend, marke well
                  theſe lines which I doe ſend,
                  And ſometime let me heare from you,
                  how that you doe entend,
               
            
            
               
               The Louer writeth once more to his friend, as doeth followe after.
               
                  THe paines that you haue taken ſir,
                  an anſwere to indite,
                  Vnto my letter that I ſent
                  with thankes I here requite.
                  Not able any other way by gifts
                  to recompence the ſame.
                  But with my pen a few lines
                  in paper here to frame.
                  Whereas you ſay I ſhould refraine,
                  and keépe my ſelfe from loue,
                  That were too hard, ſith loue it ſelfe
                  hath forſt the Gods aboue.
                  What moued Iupiter to turne
                  himſelfe to take the ſhape
                  And forme of Bull, but only loue,
                  for dame Europas rape?
                  And for becauſe (my frend) you ſay
                  loue is not of great ſtrength,
                  As farre as knowledge geueth you,
                  it ſhall appeare at length
                  Did not loues law enforce that Ioue
                  
                  to turne in Eagle ſtrange,
                  When that Aſterion he could
                  accept into his grange,
                  
                     
He tooke on him the forme of ſwanne,
                  as Leda when he had,
                  Vnder his feathred wings and breſt,
                  in ſafetie for to ſhade.
                  A Satyre ſtrange, he forſt him ſelfe,
                  that Iupiter by name
                  
                     Saturnus ſonne, to the intent
                  he might Necteis clame,
                  In forme of golden ſhowre when that
                  to Danae he could clyme
                  In towre ſtrong, for pleaſure then
                  with hir to ioy a time.
                  Thus loſe did he his former face,
                  as loue did oft compell,
                  Beſides him other gods alſo,
                  which all I can not tell.
                  But if that Poets tales ſeéme true,
                  then did Neptunus turne,
                  And had the face of other beaſts,
                  a Ramme ſometime to forme,
                  Sometime a luſtie horſe to be,
                  fometime a fiſh to play,
                  As of a Dolphin take the hue
                  as loue did beare the ſway.
                  And did not earſt Apollo take
                  the ſhape of Rauen blacke
                  Sometime a ſhepheard in the fielde
                  to bring his luſt to ſacke?
                  
                     
No god was frée, ſith all the ſhape
                  of chaunged formes gan take,
                  Of beaſtes or birdes, and oftentimes
                  of foule of fiſh of lake.
                  Then ſay not that loue hath no force,
                  the prouerbe thus doeth ſay,
                  
                     Amor vincit mundum, and then
                  nothing ſo ſtrong doth ſtay.
                  And where as you do giue aduice
                  me to withdrawe my minde,
                  And fixe my heart ſome elſewhere, that
                  I may ſome fauour finde.
                  Alas can I withdrawe my thought,
                  or els auert my heart
                  From hir whoſe picture ſtill I fynde
                  within my breſt impart:
                  No no, or elſe and ſhall I graunt
                  to wander in exile,
                  And drudge about as one vnknowne,
                  thus deſolate the while:
                  I can not aye endure that trade,
                  and where agayne you ſay,
                  I ſhould me trie in feats of armes,
                  and ſo driue loue away,
                  For once from ſight cleane out of mynde,
                  prouerbially you ſpeake.
                  That is moſt true of ſuch as would
                  there vowed promiſe breake,
                  
                     
My heart, aye giues me power inough
                  in foraine lands to wende,
                  And ouer ſurging ſeas to glyde
                  t'arriue at the other ende.
                  Yea if I had a thouſand liues,
                  I would them venter all
                  For hir, if that at my returne
                  reward for payne might fall.
                  Or where to ſerue in princely court
                  your heſt doth me aduiſe,
                  He that aduentures ſuch affaires
                  had néede be verie wiſe
                  In court though that great dignitie
                  be to be gotten aye,
                  I haue no minde to ſuch attempts
                  for things that I ſhall ſay.
                  In court at times to dice and carde,
                  a man muſt venture oft,
                  His winnings one time will be ſmall,
                  his loſings come aloft,
                  A man muſt not denie to play
                  an hundred pound or twaine,
                  If that he mynde to beare a name,
                  though nothing elſe he gaine:
                  And other exerciſes ſtore,
                  which when a man doth meéte
                  With ſuch as ſtand more than his match
                  his winning goes to fleéte.
                  
                     
The Court a ſit place is in deéde
                  for ſuch as know no ende
                  Of wealth, and ſuch as heape vp more
                  than they may yerely ſpende.
                  Such luſtie laddes n
                        ••
                     de take no dread
                  how that the
                        〈…〉
                     ſe or win,
                  Their tenants toytl, they know not how
                  their worldly wealth comes in.
                  And ſome by parents wiſe haue nowe
                  ſuch order in their land
                  And Bounds well ſet, that they ne 
                        〈…〉
                     de
                  about it fyle their hand.
                  And where you thinke in court there is
                  ſuch ſtore of damſels fayre,
                  Though they were like the Muſes 
                        •
                     ine,
                  that trece aboue the ayre:
                  Yet if that Enthinimias
                  
                  in court did aye remaine
                  More beautie ſhe ſhould ſhowe by ſight,
                  than any other twayne
                  Though that ſhe be a countrey prill,
                  no weight thereof doth ſtand,
                  Thinke you that ſome thoſe Courtly dames
                  are not of countrey land?
                  Yea though that they haue changed place,
                  and eke their wonted guiſe,
                  Yet countrey Ladie▪ they are ſtill,
                  as farre as I deuiſe.
                  
                     
If that you knowe the contrary,
                  ſuppoſe that if this dame,
                  (Though ſtubborne ſhe) were ſet in court,
                  ſhould ſhe not beare the name
                  To be a Courtier eke moſt fit:
                  ſmall is the difference
                  Nowe put 
                        •
                     ff you, if that ye 
                        〈…〉
                     ſt
                  to giue intelligence
                  And alſo of your other choyce,
                  I like much as the reſt.
                  The ſtudie of the common lawes
                  I ne account as beſt:
                  To bend my mynde vnto that ſide,
                  I thinke it follie playne,
                  The way is long and tedious,
                  ſo much more is his paine
                  That trieth it, and if ſuch ſtore
                  of gold be got thereby,
                  I wiſh ſome frend that hath no welth
                  his minde thereto apply:
                  But as for me, I thanke the Gods
                  that bleſſed me ſuch wiſe,
                  I greatly ne (as Prouerbes ſay)
                  do neéde to rub mine eyes.
                  And this I know for certaintie,
                  that he which linkes in ioue,
                  To earneſt ſtudie any t
                        •
                     me
                  his minde can neuer moue.
                  
                     
None of your choices thrée I like
                  but penſiue do remaine.
                  My ſorow groweth more and more
                  I feéle the worſer paine.
                  And where yon raiſe requeſt to kno
                  how that I do entend
                  The copy of my letter aye,
                  and hers before I ſend.
                  Therby you may perceiue and ſeé
                  how ſmall ſhe doth eſteéme,
                  The cankred care wherby I crie,
                  and ſtand at very brimme,
                  Of Stigian lake, yet do I mind,
                  ere many daies be paſt,
                  T'aſſay againe, for many men
                  ſay Loue comes not in haſt.
                  Yet will I pauſe a while,
                  and think on evrie poynt,
                  At length when I perceiue my time
                  Ile venter out a ioynt.
                  And then renue my painful ſute,
                  which now doth ſtand begun
                  It wil be long ere that I ende
                  the féeble fooles are wun,
                  With litle care as I haue learnd
                  thus fare you wel from T.
                  
                  Where oft to giue me councel good
                  I wiſh you for to be.
               
            
            
               
               The lamentation of a louer beeing refuſed, ſhewing no helliſh torments to be lyke his, wherwith he accuſeth his Ladies crueltie, &amp; yet at lēgth praieth to haue releefe.
               
                  COme on thou hart yt long haſt ſlept in wo
                        •
                     ,
                  Reuiue thy ſelfe thy haples hap to ſhew,
                  Yeé ſences all cloſde vp with couert care,
                  Vnloſe your ſelues my ſorowes to declare:
                  Thou tongue that tyed art by ſtring of paine
                  Be preſt to ſhew the woe where I remaine,
                  Thou hand yt long haſt ſtaid ſtretch out at laſt,
                  To ſhew the preſent greéfe and ſorowes paſt,
                  Of him that dying liues and wiſheth death,
                  Thogh dead in hart yet alway draweth breath
                  A thouſand times for woe who ſtil doeth crie,
                  And wiſheth death each day and cannot die.
                  Though Ixion nayled on the whirlmg wheéle,
                  Which helliſh ſtubs &amp; irkſom pains doth feele,
                  Though Tantalus amyd the lake therein
                  Parſues yt waues which wet &amp; waſh his chin,
                  And when to hun deceiude it promiſe makes
                  Thē fleets yt flood, his dryth and thirſt ne ſlakes
                  Thogh yt the treé with aureal fruit doth ſtand
                  By him, and when he reacheth out his hand
                  Thē flies yt ſtock on which the fruit doth grow
                  So bides he paine, and feeles exceſſiue woe.
                  
                     
Though Titus heart did lie a perfect pray
                  To flying foules, this payne he bides alway,
                  Though Danaus daughters fyll in vayne
                  The watry veſſels, and in toyle remayne,
                  Yet none of theſe for greéfe may ay compare
                  With me, for Clio may not yet declare
                  Ne paynt eche parched paine, wherby I pyne,
                  Though ſhe had all the helpe of Muſes nyne,
                  Or elſe expreſſe with ſlender quill in hand,
                  That eche wight might it fully vnderſtand.
                  Such dangrous dread doth double in my breſt
                  For hir, who reweth not this my vnreſt:
                  Ah froſen heart, ah wight of marble moulde,
                  Ah fem as fierce as Tygre to beholde,
                  Oh wolfe of viſage fell, who wouldeſt deuoure
                  Ech ſimple lamb, that ioyes but ſlender powre,
                  Theé to the noble Lyon to compare,
                  Were folly plaine ſith he this vertue rare
                  Enioyes, who neuer doth delight, with force
                  To teare the ſely beaſt yt yeldeth to his might,
                  But then 
                        •
                     s victor to returne away,
                  And ſomewhere elſe to ſeéke a condigne pray.
                  But thou whoſe mouth delighteth ſtil to feade,
                  Art not content my corps on ground to tread,
                  But ay to rent and teare my giltleſſe hart
                  In péeces ſmall by this my woe and ſmart.
                  If that thy pleaſure be to feéde on me,
                  So ſay, ile pull my heart to giue it theé,
                  
                     
Thereby for to aſſwage thy hot deſire,
                  Thereby of life to extinguiſh out the fire.
                  What wouldſt thou more to do thy bodie good?
                  I would on dagger fall to ſpill my blood,
                  Or elſe with lancing kniues to cut my fleſh,
                  To make thereof for theé a daintie diſh.
                  Then grant and yeéld to this my one requeſt,
                  I wiſh no more to breéd my quiet reſt.
                  When Cupid ſhot at me firſt with his dart,
                  And by the blow did péerce my tender hurt,
                  I knew no ſalue to cure my ſore againe,
                  But thereby did remaine penſiue for paine,
                  Till Amor now by ſleight the meane did find,
                  To rid the ſame if thou ne grow vnkind.
                  Rue then thou frozen har
                        •
                      and ſtomacke dire,
                  With friendlie woords grant now yt I require.
                  Let me inioy ſoone, eke the place poſſeſſe
                  Thy ſelfe, and thereby my wo redreſſe,
                  So me for to requite with loue againe,
                  Sith I in hart thine owne ſhal ſtill remaine,
                  Till ſiſters threé ſhall rid my vitall twine,
                  Thy loue let me haue aie, for thou haſt mine.
                  Grant this ye gods that glide on ſtarrie ſkie,
                  And guide that Chaos ball moſt equally,
                  What ioy were this to me that am a thrall,
                  If thou thy mate wouldſt me once frendly call,
                  Sith I ſo oft haue trauaile ſpent in waſt,
                  To reape the wiſhed frute now at the laſt.
               
            
            
               
               The Louer hauing written manye times, almoſt paſt hope, yet doeth renew his playnt againe.
               
                  ALthough that here before my déere
                  I written haue in waſt:
                  And ſent my lines to thée in vaine
                  expreſſing ſorowes paſt.
                  Yet hope doth hag me to encline
                  with pen once for to paynt
                  The ſtaggering ſtaffe wherby I ſtay
                  and ſhew to thée my playnt.
                  And thogh that yet thou alwais haue
                  béen ruler of my care
                  Yet now at length a gentle wight
                  doe thou thy ſelfe declare.
                  If any ſparke of mercy ſtay
                  now flaming in thy breſt
                  Then ſay the word that pr
                        〈…〉
                     t may,
                  and bring me wiſhed reſt.
                  Let not the guiltles ghoſt g
                        •
                     ue vp
                  the cynders to the ſoyle
                  But let your mercy be 
                        〈…〉
                     ayde
                  to helpe him geue the fayle.
                  To hatefull hap, let not my corps
                  to Charon bréery 
                        〈◊〉
                     ,
                  By paſſage ouer Stigian take,
                  a burthen aye to ſée.
                  
                     
Let not the wight that now enioyes
                  halfe yéeres to runne his race
                  So ſoone depart from terra gréen,
                  in Tartar to haue place.
                  Sith you may giue him light yt now
                  in darkenes doth remaine,
                  Sith you may giue him fréedome yt
                  
                  in thraldome ſtayes for payne.
                  Thinke on the faithful hart
                  of him that ſayd thée ſo:
                  Thinke on the meaning true of hym
                  that wandreth ſtil in woe.
                  Think earſt 
                        •
                     n him that doth not ay
                  eſtéeme his borowed life:
                  To pleaſure you if you vouchſafe
                  to remedy his gréefe.
                  And now ſith that you vnderſtand,
                  the ſecrets of my mind
                  Let this ſuffice I ſay, vntil
                  an anſwere be aſſignde.
                  And though that many ſundry times
                  I trauayled in waſ
                        ••
                     
                  
                  I waigh it not ſo that I may
                  haue mercy at the laſt.
                  
                     By him that ſtates in hart your owne,
                  
                  
                     as long as life doth last
                  
                  
                     And if that loue be after life,
                  
                  
                     your owne when life is paſt.
                  
               
            
            
               
               The louer being denied, yet ſingeth this ſong being conſtant, with hope to obteine hir at the laſt that may reward him for his paine.
               
                  THough ſurging ſeas do compaſſe me,
                  Of carking cares on euery ſide,
                  Yet truſt I once to range moſt frée,
                  And to the ioyfull valley glide,
                  And 
                        •
                     ke the wight for to obtaine,
                  That may releaſe me from my payne.
               
               
                  Though ſhe ſayes nay to my requeſt,
                  And doth deny my true deſire,
                  Diſdayning aye to bréed my reſt,
                  Whereby I fréeze amid the fire,
                  Yet truſt I once for to auart
                  Thus ſtubborne ſternneſſe from her hart,
               
               
                  My lady cals it follie plaine,
                  With toong ſuch hardned knot to knit,
                  As all the teeth with helpe of braine,
                  Shall ne be able to vnc
                        〈…〉
                     t,
                  She wrappeth wily wit ſo ſure,
                  It to obtayne its very dure.
               
               
                  She doubts leaſt that I meane awry,
                  She feareth leaſt my hart be fraile.
                  
                     
She thinks I loue not faithfully,
                  But outwardlie hir to aſſaile,
                  She thinketh aye my toong to flée
                  In words, with hart ne to agrée.
               
               
                  Oh that Caſſandras gift were plaine,
                  And woorthy ſkill for her to geſſe,
                  If that I liſt in hart to faine,
                  Contrary to that I profeſſe,
                  Then ſhould be ſeene the great good will,
                  I beare to her, and ſhall do ſtill.
               
               
                  Yet I ne blame that ſilly wight,
                  Though circumſpect alway ſhe be,
                  Vnfaithful loue hath brought much ſpight,
                  The proofe whereof we dayly ſee,
                  By ſuch as thinke contrary aye,
                  In hare to that which toong doth ſay.
               
               
                  Yet I am none of thoſe I vow,
                  I loue hir truly in my hart,
                  As is my thought the ſame I ſhow,
                  In outward words with wo and ſmart,
                  Wherefore theſe words I ſay certayne,
                  That iuſtly I ſhould her obtayne.
               
               
                  Though long it be ere I arriue
                  The ioyfull hauen to poſſeſſe,
                  
                     
Though long I wretch doe weare the giue
                  And carefull clog of heauineſſe,
                  Yet hope I once to ſeé that day
                  To haue my loue and none ſay nay.
               
            
            
               The Ladie by often intreatie being vanquiſhed with loue, doth write a comfortable letter to her Louet.
               
                  DEſiſt my Philo frend, to plunge
                  or welter ſtill in paine,
                  Where flowing aye the noyſome waues,
                  of woe alwayes remaine.
                  Leaue off to waile or mourne for that
                  which thou didſt déepe deſire.
                  Sith I am preſt with zelous care,
                  to extinguiſh out the fire,
                  And the vnwaſting coale that lyes,
                  now hid within thy breſt,
                  In couert wiſe, and by my meanes
                  to bring thée cauſe of reſt.
                  Deſiſt with pen to paint the paine,
                  which compaſt thee ech ſide,
                  Or dolefull tunes to ſhewe the gréefe,
                  in which thou didſt abide.
                  Leaue off that blacke attire, wherein
                  thou vſeſt for to goe,
                  A perfect hewe (as ſame report)
                  
                     
and ſtgne of wicked woe,
                  And fall to mirth, to ioy with her,
                  that comes to eaſe thy ſmart.
                  Thy earneſt ſuite hath found a place
                  to lighten on my hart.
                  Though once reſtraynd by force I fled
                  and thereto would not bowe,
                  For reaſons rough, this one among
                  the reſt I doe allowe
                  In bookes I readen haue ful oft,
                  and others many a time:
                  Of maydes deceiued by wyly wyghts
                  and led in loathed crime.
                  For Sathan meaneth moſt deceit,
                  when Angels ſhape he takes,
                  The fiſh is trapped ſooneſt with,
                  the ſiluer hooke in lakes.
                  I doubted aye the like, vntil,
                  that I enioyde the gift,
                  Which once Caſſandra held, that had
                  béene aye a preſent ſhift.
                  For to diſcerne and know thereby
                  the ſecrets of thy mind
                  If that I ſhould thée faithfull, or
                  a playne diſſembler find.
                  For this you know as wel as I
                  this is the greateſt care
                  Of maydes, how they beſtow themſelues,
                  
                     
in louely bands to fare.
                  And how they knit themſelues in league.
                  though loue be very ſtrong:
                  And not for pleaſure ſmall to ſing
                  alway a mournfull ſong.
                  But ſith that I by proofe perceiue
                  thy meaning true to be,
                  And without fraud I ſtand content
                  herein to pleaſure thée:
                  Then aye perſiſt in ſtedfaſt faith
                  for euer to endure.
                  And me in heart to be thine owne,
                  to finde thou ſhalt be ſure.
                  Now fare thou wel my only care,
                  my ſtedfaſt ſtaffe of ioy:
                  The only comfort of my life,
                  whom Ioue kéepe from annoy.
               
               
                  
                     By her that loues thee aye,
                  
                  
                     more better than her hart:
                  
                  
                     If theu conſent to yeeld thereto,
                  
                  
                     till death ſhall aye depart.
                  
               
            
            
               The ioyfull louer hauing by earneſt ſute obtained her whom he loued, made this ditue following.
               
                  COme on ye louers that long haue reſt in wo,
                  Leaue off your ſobs ſo tearing,
                  
                     
And helpe my ioyfull hap to ſhew
                  A face of laughter bearing:
                  Come on all ye I ſay agayne,
                  Your Ladyes fauour which obtayne,
                  And let vs all ſing.
                  For wée haue paſt the greateſt ieopat dy that might
                  Haue wrought vs any wo or gréefe
                  Nowe we arriue the hauen chéefe
                  And paſſe the ſea of ſpyght.
               
               
                  Though Cupides arow piercde my tēder hart
                  And brought to me ſuch payning,
                  Yet now exiled is my ſmart,
                  My deare I thus obtayning,
                  I ioy with hyr that ioyes with me,
                  I loue no wight ſo well as ſhe,
                  For like this ioy knew I neuer non before that day
                  In which theſe words were to me ſhowne
                  Come on my deare, thou art myne owne,
                  I will thée loue alway.
               
               
                  What words of cōfort were theſe now thinke you all
                  To bring ſuch libertie to me,
                  When I had liued long in thrall,
                  At laſt that day ſet to ſée,
                  I ne remember now my woe,
                  Which me compaſſed long agoe,
                  Therefore let vs ſing.
                  
                     
For I am recompenced wel for this my payne,
                  I haue the wight that I loue beſt,
                  Hir words do bryng to me ſuch reſt,
                  I wiſh none other gayne.
                  Ye Gods yt rule the rounded ball grant this to me
                  I aſke vnfaynedly,
                  If I loue byr with faythfull mynde,
                  As I loue hyr, let hyr loue me,
                  And not the contrary,
                  Let hyr ne growe in heart vnkynd,
                  And then may I ſing,
                  And purpoſe truely to loue hyr alwayes in my heart
                  What euer hap ſhall aye befall,
                  Yea though I loſe my life and all,
                  Till death vs two depart.
               
               
                  Tempus rerum edax.
                  
                     NOthyng there is but aye,
                     at length doth vaniſh cleane,
                     For tyme doth weare away,
                     ſuch things as earthly bene.
                     The Roſe for all his hue,
                     the ſkarlet Gillowfloure,
                     The Vyolet ſo blewe,
                     doe vaniſh in one houre.
                     The trée that groweth bigge,
                     and windeth euery way,
                     
                        
Doth once rot euery twigge,
                     when time ſayes nowe, decay.
                     The wight that hére is borne,
                     at laſt doth loſe his breath,
                     Though many wayes he turne,
                     and would not méete with death.
                     The marble ſtone moſt ſure,
                     that lyeth; vnder féete,
                     Can not alwayes endure,
                     but goeth once to fléete.
                     The king that ſits in throne,
                     with golden mace in hand,
                     At length ſhall be as none,
                     but earth on him to ſtand.
                     The houſe wherein we truſt.
                     though hard as flint it be,
                     At length ſhall weare to duſt,
                     a heape of ſtones to ſée,
                     The caſtel ſet on hic,
                     on hill that ſtandeth ſtout,
                     Its ſéene that time doth trye,
                     and beat the ſollage out.
                     The church that coured is
                     with laſting lead aboue,
                     At length time doth ne miſſe,
                     his beautie to remoue,
                     A doore of braſſe ſtrong made
                     of yron or ſuch like,
                     
                        
Time cauſeth once to glad,
                     and with decay it ſtrike.
                     The rock that ſtandeth ſtrong,
                     amyd the foaming flud,
                     Though that it laſteth long
                     time beateth it to mud.
                     The ſea bankes that are bie,
                     and ſeene from land to land,
                     Time waſteth vtterlie,
                     aye farther for to ſtand.
                     The Gun that by his ſtrength
                     can turrets ouerthrowe,
                     Time doeth conſume at length
                     his power and might to ſhewe.
                     The hil that ſtretcheth long,
                     and caſteth out his ſide,
                     As time doeth come more ſtrong,
                     then he in fall doeth glide.
                     The ſtarres that in the ſkie,
                     moſt thick ſet doe remaine,
                     Doe fade immediatlie,
                     when time doth come with main.
                     The ſunne that ſhines ſo bright,
                     ſhall loſe his comely grace,
                     And ſhewe no ſparke of light,
                     as time doeth take his place.
                     The moone that wandreth faſt,
                     and ſhineth on the land,
                     
                        
Muſt needes decay at laſt
                     when timely power is ſcande
                     The world of compaſſe round,
                     in faſhion of a ball,
                     At length ſhall not be found
                     when time conſumes it all.
                     Nothing there reſteth ſtil
                     but conſumes by and by,
                     When time doeth ſhew his will
                     then vades the earth and ſkie.
                  
               
            
            
               The Louer being willed of his Ladie to attire himſelfe in blacke and blewe, demaunded the reaſon, to whome ſhe made this anſwere folowing by a letter.
               
                  BEcauſe that you (my deare) requeſt
                  to know herein my will:
                  Wherefore that you in blacke and blewe,
                  ſhould aye attire you ſtil.
                  The black is ſaid by right report,
                  moſt conſtant to remaine:
                  And ne to change that colour ſad,
                  for any other graine.
                  The blewe preſents the wearers minde
                  and eke a louing hart:
                  Be tokening louely lyking ſtill,
                  not ſoone aye to depart.
                  
                     
Then ioyne theſe two in one, and if
                  thy rayment touch the blacke,
                  Imixt with blewe a lace or like
                  my loue ne fet it lacke.
                  For as the blacke preſents a face
                  of faythfull truſt to ſtay,
                  So doth the blewe aye repreſent,
                  a louing heart alway.
                  And for a token of true loue,
                  my ioy I ſend to thée
                  Encloſed here thoſe colours two,
                  weare thou the ſame for me,
                  Wherein is tyde a ſlight preſent,
                  in recompence of thyne,
                  A tablet wrought, I giue it thée,
                  it is no longer myne:
                  As often as you weare the ſame,
                  for my ſake and for me,
                  Then wiſh me well, for be thou ſure,
                  I wiſh the lyke to thée.
               
            
            
               The Louer writeth to his Ladie, wherein he condiſcendeth to weare the colours that ſhe willeth him for hir ſake.
               
                  IN colours two ſith you requeſt
                  I ſhould my ſelfe attyre,
                  
                     
As blacke and blew, I ſtand content
                  to anſwere your deſire,
                  For where as black preſents a mind
                  whom folly makes not fayne.
                  A colour fit it is for me,
                  changing for none other grayne.
                  If blewe a louing minde preſent,
                  and eke a faithfull hart,
                  It is for me that ne doth minde,
                  from conſtant loue to ſtart.
                  But by the gift that you me ſent,
                  I can not recompence
                  Inough, though daily I apply
                  thereto my full pr
                        ••
                     nce.
                  Yet though I haue no gift to giue,
                  that worthy is of thée.
                  In place of other yet let this
                  ſuffice now ſent from me:
                  And though it be a gift but light,
                  or recompence but ſmall,
                  I giue my hand, I plight my faith,
                  I ſend my hart and all.
                  That kéepe vntill I do repayre
                  to thée, though it belong,
                  My ſelfe to ioy in armes of loue,
                  and ſing a ioyfull ſong.
                  Farewell my ioy, farewell my life,
                  farewell my hart to thée,
                  
                     
Farewell thou wight to whom I wiſh
                  more good then erſt to me.
               
            
            
               To him that was diſappointed of his woman and louer.
               
                  TO freat thy ſelfe in frantike wiſe,
                  to beate thy ſenſleſſe brayne,
                  To clyme where nothyng hangs for thée,
                  to fiſh where ſlowes no gayne,
                  Me thinkes it booteth not at all:
                  deſiſt with ſpéede therefore
                  The enterpriſe thou haſt in hand:
                  this ſaw hath bin of yore,
                  That hard it is for to conuert
                  a womans vowed mynde,
                  Such ſterne and ſtubborne kynde of God
                  to them is ſo aſſignde.
                  Hir loue not bent is towards thée,
                  whom thou doſt fix in hart,
                  An other doth with ioy poſſeſſe
                  the wight that bréedes thy ſmart.
                  Yet for to eaſe thy mynde, here is
                  encloſde I ſende to thee
                  In token of beneuolence,
                  a wreath of willow trée.
               
            
            
               
               The louer writeth in the praiſe of his Ladie wherein he doth compare hir to a Laurel tree that is alwaies greene.
               
                  LIke as the Bay yt bears on branches ſwéet
                  The Laurel leaf that laſteth alway gréene
                  To change his hue for weather dry or wée
                        •
                     ,
                  Or elſe to loſe his leafe is ſeldome ſéene.
                  So doth my deare for aye continue ſtill,
                  As faythfull as the louing Turtle doue,
                  Rewarding me according to my will,
                  With faithfull hart for my moſt truſtie loue,
                  And ſith the time that we our loue began,
                  Moſt truſtie ſhe, yet hath endured aye,
                  And changeth not for any other man.
                  So conſtant ſhe of fayth in heart doth ſtay.
                  Wherefore vnto that trée I hir compare,
                  That neuer loſeth leafe, no more doth ſhe
                  Loſe tried trueth, how euer that ſhe fare,
                  But alwayes one by loue in hart to me.
                  Thē boſt I on this brāch of Bayes moſt pure,
                  Sith that ſo ſwéete I finde it at my hart,
                  And loue while that my life ſhall aye e
                        〈…〉
                     re,
                  And till that death our bodyes two ſhall part.
               
            
            
               The pretie birth of a childe.
               
                  IT fortund late a Frenchman for to dwell
                  In England, where himſelfe he quited well.
                  
                     
And tooke an Ihiſhwoman to his wife,
                  Hauing by her a childe of perfect life:
                  Now if this child beginning ſhall retaine
                  Of fathers ſide, a Frenchman he is plaine,
                  But contrary, if of the mother he
                  Shall take the ſpring, he Iriſh is to ſée.
                  But ſome ſay, that he ſhalbe of the land
                  Where he was borne, thē engliſh ſhal he ſtand.
               
            
            
               The wordes of a dame concerning her Louer, ſpoken to one Miſtreſſe Anne.
               
               
                  IN fayth goo miſtreſſe Anne I haue
                  found out a make in déede,
                  A proper man, and tall, and one
                  that ſéemes wil ſtand in ſtéede.
                  I loue hym wel, more then I fay,
                  I wiſh to him hys good,
                  I loue him like mine owne déere heart
                  or els my vytall blood.
                  For this you know that I ne loue
                  my blood once for to ſée,
                  No more I doe delight that he
                  within my ſight ſhould be,
               
            
            
               
               In praiſe of his Ladie.
               
                  
                     E ELiſa dame that Carthage Quéene,
                  
                     N Ne Polixena faire beſéene,
                  
                     T T'aſpire vnto my Ladies hewe,
                  
                     H Helena ne with all the crewe,
                  
                     I In paſſing ſort may not compare,
                  
                     N Nor vaunt them ſelues for beutie rare.
                  
                     I In circuit huge her like n
                        •
                      is,
                  
                     M Miron may muſe and talke of this.
                  
                     I In Gréece though Apelles did frame,
                  
                     A A picture cléere of Venus dame,
                  
                     S Sertaine ſhe doth the ſame excel
                  Of whome theſe lines the name doe tel.
               
            
            
               Of foure kindes of men that maie ſing at didner, and other meate meales.
               
                  THe Gentleman that hath the ſtore
                  of worldly wealth, may ſing
                  At meales of meate, for pleaſure great
                  that pleaſant ſongs may bring.
                  And next by order check, the foole
                  that ioyes none other graine,
                  May ſing and garre as doth the birde
                  againſt a ſhower of raine.
                  The Minſtrel then that fidleth 
                        ••
                     ne
                  at féeding times may play,
                  
                     
And ſing to heape into his purſſe
                  the coyne by night or day,
                  But chéefe, though laſt, the old cocke may
                  or cockold ne be dull
                  To crow and ſing fond fantaſies,
                  to hag from horned ſcull.
               
            
            
               Of couetouſnes and Lecherie together.
               
                  
                     A Purſſe full fraught with gold,
                  as worldly miſers frame,
                  Had one at codpice point, who tyed
                  with niggiſh kno: the ſame:
                  Thus were theſe two together k
                        •
                     it,
                  and ioynde in amitie,
                  A purſſe with pelfe of couetiſe,
                  at lace of lecherie.
               
            
            
               A perfect tricke to kill little blacke flees in ones chamber.
               
                  TAke halfe a quart of barly graine
                  a quart of ſtrongeſt béere.
                  And boyle withall in earthen pot,
                  a pint of water cléere,
                  Till all theſe thrée conſumed be
                  to ounces twelue or leſſe,
                  And then the place to which you will
                  theſe fleas in heaps to preſſe,
                  
                     
Anoynt with that: this water hath
                  in it this vertue raw
                  That all the fleas will thither come:
                  then take a ſlender ſtrawe,
                  And tickle them on the ſmall ribs,
                  and when you ſee one gape,
                  Thruſt thē the ſtraw into his mouth.
                  and death he ne ſhall ſcape.
               
            
            
               Each thing in his vocation.
               
                  THe préeſts enſearch for funerals,
                  and flatterers haunt the feaſt,
                  The ſurgions ſeeke the maimed, and
                  the Rauens carreyne creaſt.
               
            
            
               The fraileneſſe of women.
               
                  AN apple winnes hir mynde,
                  it loſt is with a nut:
                  Hir toung hangs filed with no edge,
                  yet it will quickly cut.
               
            
            
               To his friend of the fruileneſſe of dame Fortune.
               
                  VVHō fortune doth moſt ſmilingly aduance
                  Thoſe ſoneſt doth ſhe caſt vnto ye ground
                  Vnequall hap ſhe holdeth ſtill by chaunce,
                  For to extoll, or elſe defame by ſound.
                  
                     
I reade ſomewhat of Polycrates ill,
                  Who neuer felt the fel aduerſitie,
                  Yet dreading leſt ſhe once would work her wil,
                  Into the ſea did throw (to ſatiſfie
                  Her brittle minde) a ring of value great,
                  Yet fortune thoght to ſhew hir power &amp; might
                  And forſt a fiſh with gulching iawes to eate
                  The ſame: which geuen to the king, by ſight
                  The ring appéerde: with maruel he at laſt
                  Was captiue tane of great Orontes king,
                  And ſtrangling ſtring about his neck yeaſt,
                  Was forſt adieu vnto his life to ſing.
                  Learne thou by this I ſay my gentle frend,
                  That riches ranke, ne yet the precious ſtone
                  Can once deferre this fortune ſo vnkind,
                  For if it might this king had not béen gone,
                  And for becauſe that thou art ſet ſo bie,
                  And placed ſtayeſt in ſeate of this degrée
                  Vnwilling aye to loſe authoritie,
                  I cannot chuſe but now aduertiſe thée
                  To train thy ſelſe in ſuch wiſe thou maiſt haue
                  (If fortune fraile ſhould hap to ſlip from thée)
                  Ech mans good wil, wherby he might thée ſaue
                  Frō dangers dread, which yt might haply ſée,
                  For now a thing not rare it is in déede,
                  That where we wey our footeſteps beſt to be
                  With ſlippery place then ſooneſt doe we ſlide
                  Therefore marke wel that I haue ſaid to thée.
               
            
            
               
               The morning before the Louer went to his Ladie, made this petition to the Gods.
               
                  GOlde is a ſigne men ſay
                  of happy lucke and loue,
                  Then graunt ye Gods I pray
                  that rule the ſkie aboue,
                  This my requeſt to me,
                  that ſith that I this night
                  Did dreame ſuch gold to ſée
                  as anſwerd my delight,
                  That I may heare ſuch newes,
                  of her that hath my heart,
                  Like as ioy ſtil inſues
                  to rid me from my ſmart.
                  And Venus Goddes milde,
                  to whom the apple gaue
                  Young Paris Prince a child
                  a noble dame to haue
                  Graunt that I may by ſuite,
                  haue her I doe requeſt:
                  And I wil geue the fruite,
                  to thée before the reſt.
               
            
            
               The fooliſhnes of a painter.
               
                  REpairing to a Painters place
                  to view ſuch pictures rare
                  As he with penſil fine had framde
                  the fame away to beare.
                  
                     
Me thought I ſawe ſuch pictures there,
                  of beauties darlings braue,
                  As dyd ſurpaſſe, and condigne were
                  the onely brute to haue.
                  Whereby it ſéemde he far had ſought▪
                  
                  by ſea and eke by land,
                  Eche paſſing part of womanhood,
                  with eye had rightly ſkand.
                  At length his wife diſcending downe,
                  a paſſing péece in déede,
                  Me thought I neuer ſaw hir like,
                  attyrde in womans wéede.
                  Who there dyd draw myne eyes to hir,
                  from pictures cleane away,
                  By whom was playne dame beuty then
                  hir banner did diſplay.
                  And vewing there eche perfect poynt
                  which nature dyd apply,
                  That ſ
                        •
                     ly ſoule in co
                        •
                     ert wiſe,
                  I ſpeake thus by and by:
                  Thou paynter that with curious eyes
                  haſt ſéene ech courtly dame,
                  In mynde thereby by ſight of ſuch
                  a picture rare to frame,
                  What dydſt thou meane to ſéeke ſo farre,
                  and haſt at home a wife,
                  For beuty which knowes not hir peére
                  with woman which are chéefe,
                  
                     
Thou foole, if that thou liſt in déede,
                  with penſell to detrayne
                  A picture that all other ſhews
                  of pictures aye ſhould ſtayne,
                  Or if thou meanſt to frame a ſhew
                  of beauty catcht in net,
                  And ſuch one as the gaole thereby
                  thy ſelfe thou erſt might get,
                  Then forge the picture of thy wife,
                  and trauaile not for payne,
                  Sith ſhe the chéefe of beauties ſtocke,
                  among vs doth remayne.
               
            
            
               The grieuous complaint of him that had the hap to marie his miſtreſſe.
               
                  VVHen youthfull yeres did prick me forth
                  in ſtature for to growe
                  A tall yong man, and towardnes,
                  (to call) by ſight to ſhew,
                  I did requeſt in heart to be
                  a ſeruing man a ſpace,
                  Whereto my fréends dyd condiſcend,
                  and wiſhed me their grace.
                  A maſter méete my parents choſe,
                  as beſt they thought in minde,
                  That ſhould in ſeruice me retayne,
                  ſith I thereto was clynd,
                  
                     
A gentleman of antike ſtocke
                  by alltance very good,
                  By pedigrée and iuſt diſcent
                  he came of gentle blood:
                  And ſticken déep in yeres, this wight
                  a wife he had before,
                  A paſſing dame, a pleaſant wench,
                  of beutie which had ſtore.
                  They did continue many yeres,
                  in vertues wayes moſt pure
                  With faithful loue and amitie,
                  and frendſhips lore moſt ſure.
                  In ſo much that there was cauſe gin
                  to neighbors round them by,
                  To blaze this bruite in euery place,
                  by fame both farre and nic,
                  Happy to be that aged ſoule,
                  and luckie for to ſtand,
                  That had by Gods appointed him
                  a wife to lead in hand,
                  That aye dame beuties baner braue
                  diſplaied in ſuch wiſe
                  Withall, for vertue in no place
                  her like might once ariſe:
                  Wel, to enſue, dame Atropos
                  
                  can ſhread his web in twaine,
                  Leauing no iſſue him behind
                  as his heire to remaine.
                  
                     
Whereby the right of land and leaſe
                  of ſiluer and of golde,
                  Deſcended ſolely vnto her,
                  for euer it to holde.
                  Then was this widow often ſought,
                  in mariage league to wend,
                  But ſhe refuſing offers large,
                  to none would condiſcend,
                  Then I remembring many times
                  her vertues manifold,
                  The ſéemely port, the comely grace
                  which ſhe by ſight did hold
                  But chéefly aye the worldly wealth
                  and riches pleaſant ſtore,
                  That by her huſband was her left
                  ſurrounding aye the flore.
                  Was moued much by Cupid blinde
                  for to attempt with maine,
                  If that I might this paſſing wight
                  by any meanes obtaine.
                  And being daily conuerſant
                  I wrought the matter ſo,
                  That in ſhort time my hearts deſire
                  I obtainde
                        •
                     o my woe.
                  The mariage made, moſt ioyfull I
                  in heart did aye remaine
                  I neuer knewe what ſorrow meant
                  ne felt what thing was paine.
                  
                     
Ah pleaſantly we dyd conſume
                  two moneths and no more,
                  In pleaſant wyſe then dyd I thinke,
                  to ſue to get ſome ſtore,
                  Of gold if that I myght,
                  I knew ſhe had the ſame,
                  And fruitful bagges, but in no wiſe,
                  I could one crowne reclayme:
                  And as requeſt was made of me,
                  this anſwere by and by,
                  Was gin of hir in crooked wyſe,
                  and aye moſt frowardly,
                  Good ſir, I wedded not for that,
                  aduauncement ne you gaue
                  To the intent that any ſtore
                  of myne you ſhould thus craue,
                  And thinke to be your owne, but this
                  much I do to you ſay,
                  If that you ſtand to my reward,
                  your labor ile repay:
                  And what I giue you take,
                  myne offer 
                        •
                     e refuſe,
                  I was your miſtreſſe tyll I gaue,
                  you licence me to vſe.
                  Such as is yours is myne,
                  and myne is ſure myne owne:
                  Then none ye haue, ne none ye get,
                  vnleſſe frendſhip he ſhowne.
                  
                     
But I with rage and choler mooued,
                  ne could my ſelfe refrayne,
                  To me it was a preſent death,
                  and earſt a piercyng payne,
                  That I ſhoulde be a womans thrall,
                  that I ſhould be a ſlaue,
                  That I in place of huſband, ſhould
                  none of her ſubſtance haue.
                  It mooued me in déed, ſo that
                  though cleane agaynſt my vow̄,
                  I was conſtraynd by fury fell
                  ſome blowes for to beſtow,
                  But out alas, her fréends forthwith
                  gan giue her fréendly ayde,
                  Wherby I troden downe to ground
                  in mynd was aye diſmayde:
                  And ſhe puft vp by paſſyng pryde,
                  her head was growne ſo hye
                  Aboue my pate, that able ſhe
                  was it with nayles to clye,
                  With pot, with candleſticke, and eke
                  with bedſtaffe of huge weight,
                  Both ſtoole and forme flang at my face,
                  with care thus I was freyght.
                  On euery fide, oh miſer moſt:
                  oh caytyfe borne to payne,
                  Oh diuels drudge, oh frantike foole,
                  that marry wouldſt for gayne:
                  
                     
When I in ſtable ſerude the horſſe,
                  Then was I wearier aye,
                  On bench with clownes whole peny vp,
                  at treygobet to play
                  Than I am now beſide all this,
                  and which doth gréeue me more,
                  Of hornes by hir vile whoredome ſtrong,
                  accrueth to me ſtore.
                  No remedy I finde the while,
                  for ſtill before my face,
                  Royſters, ruffins, ſhe retaynes
                  in bed, my rightfull place.
                  Wherefore a thouſand tymes I wayle
                  my ſtate and myſery,
                  A thouſand tymes I call for death,
                  yet naytheleſſe can dye:
                  I ſhall liue longer than I would,
                  in thrall with mickle ſhame,
                  Oh God what hap had I, when firſt
                  I wedded home my dame.
               
            
            
               The Louer by pleaſant talke cauſed a Ladie to vnderſtand how a ſhrew or vnhappie woman came firſt into the world.
               
                  LEt no man muſe but this was firſt
                  the ofſpring of a ſhrowe,
                  As I in lynes here ſubſequent,
                  ſhall cauſe you for to know.
                  
                     
When as for ſinne the thunderer
                  
                     loue dyd the earth ſurround,
                  And ouerwhelmed aye with waues,
                  eche part of heauy ground:
                  
                     Deucalion onely ſaued was,
                  and Pirrha then his wife,
                  (As Poets ſay) of mortals, and
                  he longeſt ioyed life.
                  And whē perceiuerance did him take
                  that euery wyght was gone,
                  And that they two and no more
                  on earth were left alone,
                  Then penſiuely they tooke aduice
                  to Them
                           •
                        s for to wend,
                  To wete how mankind might again
                  his former life entend.
                  This Goddeſſe can reply them to,
                  wi
                        •
                     h anſwere on this wiſe,
                  If that Deucalion could find out
                  by ſight of gréedy eyes,
                  His mothers bones, and him behind
                  they throwen for to be,
                  Within ſhort tyme they ſhould ſtart vp
                  men lyuing for to be,
                  This maruell much diſmaide the mynds
                  of theſe two ſéely wights,
                  As though that they dyd fearefull ſtand,
                  by ſight of helliſh ſprights:
                  
                     
But this Deucalion beyng wyſe,
                  perceyued at the laſt,
                  The earth mother to be of all
                  things that are nowe and paſt:
                  And erſt to be the ſpring wherehence
                  all mortals firſt did flowe.
                  By reaſon then of earth he was
                  (by wit) he prompt dyd knowe,
                  And aye her bowels for to be
                  the ſandy cruſhing ſtones:
                  The marble and ſuch like alſo,
                  appoynted her for bones.
                  Wherefore he threwe behynde himſelfe
                  theſe ſtones of manifold,
                  Which to be men immediatly
                  (amaſde he gan behold.)
                  Of theſe came all the men that nowe
                  are liuyng vnder ſkye:
                  And Pirrha mylde to play her part
                  behynd her by and by,
                  Gan throw as many ſtones as this
                  
                     Deucalion threw before,
                  Which ſtreight became a troupe of dames:
                  of both kindes there were ſtore.
                  The reaſon now I gueſſe how that
                  ſuch ſhrewes in earth abound,
                  In euery place among the men,
                  a number to be found,
                  
                     
Is this, the ſea replet with ſalt,
                  dyd beate agaynſt the land,
                  And many ſtones within the ſame
                  of ſaltiſh taſt dyd ſtand,
                  Then to enſue, when all the earth
                  with ſea was ouerrune,
                  There was no land but water all
                  to be ſéene vnder Sunne.
                  Decreaſing yet it left ſuch ſtones,
                  remayning on the land
                  As ſaltiſh were, a number ſure:
                  perhaps to Pirrhas hand
                  Came one of thoſe, and made a fem:
                  the ſalt muſt freat alway,
                  Within that wight which firſt was made
                  of ſalted ſtone or clay,
                  Whereby to choler it prouokes
                  and her in rage to fall
                  In frantike wiſe: a ſhrewe to be
                  ſuch one we alway call.
                  For ſuch was Morrell ſlayne,
                  and layde in ſaltiſh bryne,
                  For ſaltiſh ſhrewes his ſkyn was flayne
                  ſuch ſhrewes in it to ſhryne.
               
            
            
               Offaithfull friendſhip.
               
                  VVHen worldly wealth doth vade &amp; decay,
                  And erthly riches to erth do turn againe
                  
                     
Yet fréendſhip moſt ſtedfaſt and ſure for aye,
                  Hap what hap may doth ſtyll remayne.
                  May any man find the lyke of Carion
                  
                  And Menalip companions aye,
                  Who to the death were friends? no not one,
                  Who kept this frendſhip moſt ſtedfeſt in ſtay,
                  There are fréends dead, and of ſorts twayne,
                  By prouing a man may finde it true,
                  The one in countnance all for gaine,
                  The others words dead to enſue.
                  Some men remember Pylades,
                  
                  A faithfull man, a truſty wyght,
                  Oh ſacred fréend vnto Oreſtes,
                  
                  Oh ſparkling ſtarre to giue vs light:
                  They all are gone and layd in graue,
                  Once we had Pilades, and once Oreſtes,
                  
                  But them againe or like, we none ſhall haue,
                  Ne haue not nowe, to trace their progreſſe:
                  
                     Menalip is gone, and Carion,
                  
                  The ſacred ſoules hath rapt them aye,
                  Their facts haue we as yet to looke vpon,
                  Such kept the flowre of fréendſhip in ſtay.
               
            
            
               What daunger inſueth if a man enterpriſe a higher place then his degree can aſpire vnto.
               
                  BY fortune came a countrey clowne
                  to London, for to ſée,
                  
                     
And roming vp and downe the ſtréetes
                  as beſt he thought to be,
                  Went to the court a place vnmeete
                  for ſuch a carter playne,
                  The ſame tyme where for princes ſport
                  great paſtime to ordayne
                  Men went about: the nyght drew on,
                  and Luna with hir hornes,
                  The azure ſkie and element
                  with ſparkling ſtarres adornes.
                  And he thus learned of the boyes
                  or lackeys of the courte,
                  Such paſſing pleaſure for to be,
                  and eke ſuch princely ſport,
                  Dyd mynde (if that he myght) to get
                  and wryng into the hall
                  To take the vewe, this beyiſh clowne
                  dyd nothing are appall,
                  Though with the ſight of nobles ſtore
                  his dolliſh eyes were fed,
                  But loppreth to the vpper end,
                  his cap vpon his head.
                  One of the wayters ſeeing this,
                  him by the arme can hold,
                  And ſayd ſirrha, to come ſo nygh
                  how dareſt thou be bolde?
                  Come on, if that thou liſt to viewe
                  and ſée ſome pleaſant ſight,
                  
                     
Goe get thée out into the ſtréete
                  and ſtare on the moone lyght.
                  But he with ſtrugglyng gan refuſe,
                  and very long reſiſt,
                  Till at the length his eare dyd fetch
                  ſomewhat at porters fiſt.
                  (I know not what it was) but he
                  with anger chafed much,
                  Dyd thinke if he were at the doore
                  to recompence this tuch,
                  So that in déede (that place attayne)
                  vnwares to any wight,
                  He gaue the porter another blow,
                  with all his power and might.
                  The fellowes ſéeing this, gan run
                  on heapes vnto the doore,
                  And for one blow they dyd him gyue
                  whole twenty, yea and more,
                  In ſo much that the fooliſh ſot
                  was forſt almoſt to cry,
                  When as he felt a weighty fiſt
                  to hit him on the eye.
                  They layd on load, but at the laſt
                  he eſcaped from the doore,
                  Thinking aye to go ſo far,
                  he venture would no more,
                  But to beware by this, ſith that
                  ſo fooliſhly he would.
                  
                     
Nowe venture in a place to high
                  for his decrée ſo cold.
                  This chaunce doth often hap to ſuch
                  as boldly do aſpire
                  To higheſt top as they are led
                  by fooliſh fond deſire:
                  Its often ſéene, that they which ſit
                  at meat at the vpper end,
                  Are often placed all belowe,
                  and loweſt thither ſend.
                  Let euery man him hold content,
                  and aye well pleaſed be,
                  In ech poynt, with ſuch haps as are
                  moſt méete for his degrée.
               
            
            
               Of parents deformed hauing a beutifull childe.
               
                  DOubling doubts &amp; muſings much I ſtande
                  To ſee dame natures fact, by ſkilfull hand,
                  I muſe how that the trée that beares by kynde,
                  The red hawe, ſhould to cheſtnuts be in clynde:
                  I muſe how that yt trée ſhould change that ſute
                  For grapes moſt pure his cat ſloes ſoure frute
                  This change ſéems ſomwhat ſtrange in déed to me
                  Such kindly gripes vnkindly for to be.
                  I muſe how that dame nature could with ſkill,
                  And learning large of high Pernaſſus hill,
                  
                     
Frame ſuch a peéce on earth here for to ſtray
                  Of parents as were made of clodded clay.
                  I muſe how that erſt ſuch a froward fyr
                  With drowſie wife whoſe loue is to the fire,
                  Should get a daughter damſell faire &amp; bright,
                  For to diſplay dame beauties banner bryght.
                  This fact departs by fame the onely deéd,
                  Of thundring loue, yt giues yt good their meéd
                  To reſt with him, and pai
                        •
                     s the ill their hire.
                  For to deſcead to hell and flaming fire.
               
            
            
               Of him that tooke a quart of wine when it was proffered by his freend, who minded to get a pottell.
               
                  ONe newly come to towne, of freénds
                  a number he gan meéte,
                  About the reſt, by freéndly talke
                  one cheefly thus him greéte,
                  Vnto your welcome ſir I haue,
                  ſome where a quart of wine,
                  Which willingly I would beſtow
                  on you this preſent tyme.
                  Mary (quoth the other) gladly
                  your gentle gift I take,
                  The quart of wine I meane not nowe
                  with nay thus to forſake.
                  Nay quoth the other ſtreight, you ought
                  for to haue offred me,
                  
                     
A pottell more for to requite
                  my gift offred to theé:
                  For curteſie doth will when that
                  one offreth theé a quart,
                  Thou ſhouldſt him giue the like or more,
                  to ſhew thy gentle heart.
                  Beſhrew me then (quoth the ſtranger)
                  for 
                        〈◊〉
                      thou drinkſt of mine,
                  I will be ſure before band aye,
                  to haue a taſte of thine.
                  For many men moſt mindfully,
                  do often offer make,
                  Such things as they ne willingly,
                  would any time forſake.
                  But for a ſkill to get the like
                  under colour and face
                  Of curteſie where crabbed clawes
                  deceitfully do trace,
                  So nowe this quart of wine
                  is offred aye of theé,
                  To the intent that thou mightſt get
                  a pottell more of me.
               
            
            
               To hir the Louer writeth, being familiarlie acquainted, refuſed in preſence to ſpeake to him.
               
                  SIth that thy fauour once I helde
                  and ioyed part thy grace,
                  
                     
What was the cauſe, that this diſdayne
                  ſhould brge himſelfe a place
                  In theé? at home I knowe,
                  and eke remember well:
                  Full louing tales and ſtories there
                  I often could theé tell,
                  And for reward I could receyue
                  of thée a kiſſe or twayne,
                  As iuſtly aye deſerude of me:
                  in recompenſe of payne.
                  I then was bold to go with theé,
                  in chambers low and hie,
                  And in mine armes on bed of downe
                  haue theé thereou to lye,
                  Though I reſtrayned by forced feare
                  would neuer enterpryſe
                  To taſte of Venus ſports, as things
                  ne to be ſéene with eyes.
                  Where as perhaps (as well appeard)
                  you willyng were thereto,
                  But that a doubt came in the wynde
                  that forſt a freénd a foe.
                  This token you remember well,
                  if that you liſt to yeéld.
                  She tooke a blow below the eare,
                  at Mooregate by the field.
                  To play at cardes and tables both,
                  to driue the tyme away,
                  
                     
And other games you coulde deuiſe,
                  as time ſerude day by day.
                  An hundred toyes were to be found,
                  that might vs merrie make,
                  Then had the Moone cleane loſt hyr forme,
                  and was ne like a cake,
                  I was thy darling then, alſo
                  I dyd poſſeſſe thy hart:
                  Eche word that ſtubbornly was caſt
                  dyd cauſe eche other ſmart.
                  Why now, what is the cauſe me tell,
                  that this ſo vile diſdayne,
                  Should theé. enforce ne to regarde
                  him that for theé bydes payne?
                  What was the cauſe that when you met
                  me with your fellowes mo,
                  And troupe of dames in open ſtréete,
                  you would ſo ſlyly go.
                  And looke awry as though not méete
                  I were to ſée your face?
                  (Such fréends as we are aye before)
                  this was a chaunged caſe.
                  But go thy way, to chooſe thy féere,
                  euen where it likes theé beſt,
                  Ile trouble theé from hence no more,
                  ne theé diſturbe of reſt.
                  But as long as by ſight I know,
                  a woman from a ſhéepe,
                  
                     
For thy ſake I will then bewart,
                  and looke before I leape.
               
            
            
               Of Vnthrifts.
               
                  THoſe men whoſe mindes are wolly bent
                  and ſet on pleaſure vayne,
                  Do take no care to get the thrift,
                  that brings inceſſant gayne.
               
            
            
               Of Whoredome.
               
                  AS aye amongſt th'vntamed beaſtes
                  that range amid the wood,
                  Thrre is no greater raue nor than
                  the Wolfe of cruell moode.
                  And as the Puttoke doth ſurpaſſe
                  eche winged foule perdy,
                  By egerneſſe to ſkirre hir pray,
                  once ſéene with greedy eye:
                  So aye excelles this monſtrous vice
                  of whoredome by hir kinde,
                  Eche other vice ſtupendious
                  by Sathan left behinde.
               
            
            
               Like will to like.
               
                  EVen as good men reioyce alway
                  With good men for to be,
                  In companie to ioy with them:
                  ſo like it is to ſée,
                  Ill men reioyce with like to haue
                  
                     
their companie alwaies:
                  The good with like, the ill with ill,
                  do ioyne in all aſſayes.
               
            
            
               Of vnwittie ſpending.
               
                  ME think ſuch wights, ſmall wit in head retaine,
                  Which do conſume &amp; ſpend that worldly gaine
                  Which they haue got with ſwet of browe and payne
                  no cauſe therefore:
                  Such treaſure thē as they for long haue ſoght
                  In litle tyme for to conſume to nought,
                  Such ſpendyng ay not taking any thought,
                  makes rich men poore.
               
            
            
               Perit quicquid feceris ingrato.
               
                  AMongſt ſuch déeds, as when that they are done
                  Inforce a man for to repent therefore,
                  This one thing chéefe remaines for ech to ſhun,
                  Though there aboūd by knowlege many more,
                  What euer thing thou doeſt with zelous mind,
                  T'a churliſh wight yt adage ſhewes ſuch ſenſe,
                  Its loſt: he will not leaue his doggiſh kinde,
                  Ne neuer meane the ſame to recompence.
               
            
            
               The propertie of Reprobates.
               
                  BY kinde they that are lewde in déede,
                  doe ioy in heart alway,
                  When as the good miſfortune find
                  and fall into decay.
               
            
            
               
               A good man.
               
                  PErforce a perfect wight in déede,
                  to be, he beares the fame,
                  Which no man harmes ne doth delight,
                  his neyghbour for to blame:
                  Then it inſewes, if he be good,
                  we ſhould him follow ſtill,
                  Sith we are taught to loue the good
                  and to abhorre the ill.
                  And if that vertue ought to be
                  imbraſt of euery wight.
                  Then ought we all embrace that man
                  that vertuous is and right.
               
            
            
               A perfect preſeruatiue for health.
               
                  FOr keeping of a man in health
                  there is no better way,
                  Than for to eate and drinke by meane,
                  one meane to kéepe alway,
                  And ne ſurpaſſe or change that meane
                  at one time more or leſſe,
                  For meaſure brings a treaſure tried
                  in pleaſure or diſtreſſe.
               
            
            
               A ſtupendious deſire.
               
                  SOme men there are that do imploy
                  and fix their gréedy mynde,
                  To gather riches to themſelues,
                  to priuate gayne inclynde:
                  
                     
And though they find no end of wealth,
                  yet more they do deſire,
                  And kindle vp vpon their heads,
                  a flaſhing flaine of fire.
               
            
            
               Olde men.
               
                  AL liuing wyghts whom that
                  old Senex ſtaffe hath ſmit,
                  Denieth youthfull ſlouthfulneſſe,
                  and otherwiſe delite.
               
            
            
               Diuerſitie of remembrance.
               
                  VVE all are wont (as well is knowne)
                  to prynt and beare in mynde,
                  A leſſon touching naughtineſſe,
                  to which vice is inclinde,
                  More ſooner than a godly phraſe:
                  ſo great diuerſicie
                  Of good and yll, we alwayes finde
                  fixt in our memory.
               
            
            
               The deceites of the Foxe.
               
                  FOr to haue learnde the Foxes wiles,
                  and rightly vnderſtand,
                  Were readieſt meane them to preuent
                  before they come to hand.
               
            
            
               Of a womans hatred.
               
                  THe anger of a ſhrew is aye,
                  more gréeuous to ſome wight,
                  
                     
Then is the ſting of ſerpent ſtrong,
                  that bringeth mickle ſpite.
               
            
            
               Of boaſting and bragging.
               
                  HE that doth litle thing performe,
                  yet bragges at euery houſe:
                  May be compared to an hill,
                  that once brought forth a Mouſe.
               
            
            
               A ſigne of anger.
               
                  IF that he bends the br
                        •
                     wes
                  in frowning wyſe to lowre,
                  We ſay that he then angry is,
                  or hath an angry ſhowre,
               
            
            
               The ſudden falling into danger:
               
                  NO wight there is that ſteppeth forth
                  or traceth on the ball,
                  That can from daunger him exempt,
                  ſo ſoone as in it fall.
               
            
            
               The pitie of Dormice.
               
                  OF pitie this is a ſigne.
                  And cond
                        〈…〉
                     e aye for to be knowne.
                  Howe that yong Oormice alway ſéede,
                  Their ſyers that in age are growne.
                  And when that they ne able are,
                  To trauayle for their pray,
                  The yong ones yet the ſame will get,
                  And bryng to reſt alway.
               
            
            
               
               Of imdietie of children.
               
                  VVHo can deny but vertue all
                  is vaniſht out of place,
                  When as the children ne obey
                  the fathers in no caſe.
               
            
            
               The ſinnes of Kings.
               
                  VVHen euer as the king doth ſinne,
                  and iuſtly loue therefore,
                  Doth vengeance giue, to the intent
                  that he ſhould ſinne no more:
                  We alwayes ſée the plague to light,
                  on commons many a one,
                  As well as on the wight that ſinde
                  and forceth them to grone.
               
            
            
               Of eating of egges:
               
                  AT meate there met both he and ſhe,
                  among thoſe diſhes rare
                  That there were ſet (not daintie though)
                  came egges t'augment the fare,
                  (Quoth ſhe) if that you eate this egge,
                  the prouerbe doth enſue,
                  Thrée ſhames therewith incontinent
                  ſhall happen vnto you.
                  But he applying this egge,
                  not printing that in minde:
                  There fell a drop, thers one (quoth ſhe)
                  the other be behinde.
                  
                     
With that he clapt the egge into
                  his mouth, the ſhelles and all,
                  Theres two (quothſhe) watcht for the third,
                  till that it doth befall.
               
            
            
               To him that was angrie becauſe the Cuckow did ſing before his doore.
               
                  FRend rage not with the Cuckow,
                  though he ſings before thy doore,
                  And Cuckow cry, ne chaunging aye,
                  the tune he ſang before.
                  He cryes not Cuckold, though much like,
                  thy wife do thou not blame,
                  For though thou thinkeſt he Cuckold cryes,
                  perhaps it is not thy name.
               
            
            
               Of Sugar and Salt.
               
                  SVgar and Salt begyn with like letter,
                  though ſugar be good, yet ſalt is better:
                  This ſugar is ſwéete in mouth to the taſte,
                  yet doth the Scripture ſhew vs at the laſt,
                  That ſalt doth ſeaſon all things that there be,
                  and no ſuch mention of ſuger we ſee.
               
            
            
               Of haſtie wiuing.
               
                  HE doth deſire a wife in déede,
                  and thinks it very ſwéete,
                  That willingly would marry aye,
                  eche harlot he doth méete.
               
            
            
               
               Of deſpiſing of the poore.
               
                  THough that he falne be in decay,
                  and wanteth to maintaine,
                  Yet it is not a godly point
                  to ſcorne the wight in paine.
               
            
            
               Of harlots.
               
                  AN harlot ſure in outward ſhew
                  profeſſeth feruent loue,
                  But from her heart ſhe doth expell
                  and faithful loue remoue.
                  But certaine ſhe is crauing ſtil,
                  and gréedy of thy golde,
                  And without that or ſuch like giftes,
                  no more touch they wil holde.
                  As long as thou doeſt fill her hand
                  with money, they remaine
                  Thine owne: but they are gone when that
                  they haue no hope of gaine.
               
            
            
               Of keeping companie with naughtipacks.
               
                  HE that doth cling to felowſhip
                  of naughtipacks alway.
                  Its maruel if he with their blots,
                  himſelfe ne ſpotteth aye.
               
            
            
               The Prouerbe.
               
                  IN age he hardlie ſhal enioy,
                  or riches ſtore obtaine
                  
                     
That could ne finde in heart in youth
                  to geue himſelfe to paine.
               
            
            
               Of anger without a cauſe.
               
                  HE that doth freat for each light cauſe,
                  or trifle in reſpect,
                  May wel be calde a foole by kinde,
                  his follie to reiect.
               
            
            
               Of husbandrie and Scholers.
               
                  SVch as doe toyle to till the land,
                  and huſbandrie maintaine:
                  Such as doe plowe and cart, abide
                  ten times more gréeuous paine,
                  Than ſuch as doe indeuour aye
                  and learning ſweéte deſire,
                  And geue themſelues by pleaſant trade
                  ſweéte letters to aſpire.
               
            
            
               Another Prouerbe.
               
                  HE ſéemes vnwiſe that doeth intend
                  the top of houſe to raiſe,
                  Before that he hath caſt the ſloore
                  to beare the heauie paiſe.
               
            
            
               The error of the wicked.
               
                  AS the Egles doe contemne
                  at béetles for to ſmite,
                  So rich men doe, to ſcorne the poore,
                  inheart ofttimes delite.
               
            
            
               
               Of pleading where a man's not heard.
               
                  IT better were that euery wight
                  ſhould hold his peace alway,
                  Than for to ſpeake and waſte his wind
                  not being heard for aye:
                  Yea where the people ne eſtéeme
                  his words, but count as vaine,
                  There were he better hold his peace,
                  and take no wilful paine.
               
            
            
               The frailneſſe of youth.
               
                  YOuthly age is bent ſo much
                  to fooliſh fond aſpect,
                  That if the maſters wil not once
                  with tongue their faults detect.
                  Another time, the worſer mad
                  you ſhal them ſurelie finde,
                  If that it happen ſo, that
                  correction be blinde.
               
            
            
               Nothing is hid from God.
               
                  VVHat ſinne ſoeuer thou commit
                  if it be great or ſmall,
                  If it be in moſt ſecrete place,
                  yet God beholds all.
               
            
            
               Of flatterie and lieng.
               
                  FLatterie beares a ſkill with it,
                  But lying comes by mother wit.
               
            
            
               
               A faithfull frend.
               
                  DOutleſſe a frend he is in déede,
                  and ought to be accounted ſure,
                  Which ſhewes himſelfe a frend vnto
                  his frend, as long as life endure.
               
            
            
               Of coſtlie apparel.
               
                  EXtreme follie it ſéemes to be
                  attyred in ſuch wiſe,
                  To which thy baſe ſtate and degrée
                  by much ne may ariſe.
               
            
            
               Of Neighbourlie aide.
               
                  LEt it ne gréeuous ſéeme to thée,
                  thy neighbour to reléeue,
                  Sith he, if thou ſhouldſt méete with néede
                  the like to thée may geeue.
               
            
            
               Of good counſell.
               
                  GOod councell ſée that thou obey
                  at firſt when thou begin,
                  Ne in ſuch hazard doe thou ſlide,
                  and ſodenly fall in:
                  From which thou maiſt not eaſily pul
                  or drawe thy foote againe,
                  And thus repent when its too late,
                  encreaſing ſtil thy paine.
               
            
            
               
               Of him that would ſight at home, and no where els.
               
                  VVIth me ne wouldſt thou ſtriue,
                  ne yet deuiſion make,
                  But at home on thine owne dunghill,
                  where all cocks proudly crake.
               
            
            
               Of a couetous mind.
               
                  SO ſparing he is ſtil, and harde
                  of that he doeth recleame,
                  That eaſier it is for to get
                  or drawe a water ſtreame
                  Out of a Flint, then for to wring
                  a penie from his bagge
                  Where thouſands lie, his beſt coat yet
                  is but a rotten ragge.
               
            
            
               The Prouerbe.
               
                  IN braue attyre who pampreth vp
                  his corps for ſéemely ſight,
                  In veluet, purple, and ſuch like,
                  his purſe then waies moſt light.
               
            
            
               Of wicked children.
               
                  THe childe that doeth account,
                  and thinketh ought for aye:
                  His Parents worthie ne to be
                  to whom he ſhould obaye,
                  
                     
Moſt méete is to be expelde,
                  out from the chriſt: n flock,
                  Leaſt graffes we ſhould haue more to growe
                  out of ſuch wicked ſtocke.
               
            
            
               Of vvailing for the dead.
               
                  VVHat profiteth to waile the dead,
                  and ſtrike my ſelfe with paine,
                  A man may wéepe til heart ſtrings breake,
                  yet haue not them againe.
               
            
            
               Of parents.
               
                  IT is not parents wit by right,
                  ſo much the childe to hate,
                  Rather to ſee him caſt away
                  than roughly him to rate.
               
            
            
               Of ſuch as had rather haue harlots than wiues
               
                  BY wit I ne allow the vſe
                  ne councel of that wight
                  Which rather would frequent the houſe
                  of harlots day and night.
                  Then chaſtly for to take a wife,
                  and Himeneus pleaſe:
                  And rather would ſuſtaine ſtil ſtrife,
                  than alwaies liue at eaſe.
               
            
            
               Of him that eſteemeth riches more than frendſhip.
               
                  VNworthy he of frendſhip is,
                  that more eſtéemeth gold
                  
                     
Than faithful frendſhip, which as long
                  as very li
                        •
                     e doeth hold.
               
            
            
               Of Deſtinie.
               
                  NO deſtinie a man may ſcape,
                  as reaſon doeth allowe
                        •
                     
                  
                  And hanging is a deſtinie,
                  as many men doe know:
                  Then i
                        •
                      a wight doth throwe himſelfe
                  amyd the 
                        •
                     urging 
                        •
                     ea,
                  In mind thereby to méete with death,
                  and drowning him to ſlea:
                  Yea though he ſight in ſkirmige dure,
                  and braul with ſuch as be
                  Surpaſſing him by manly force,
                  yet thus much doe we ſée:
                  Though many wayes for death he ſéek
                  himſelfe away to caſt.
                  If hanging be his deſtinie,
                  he hang ſhal at the laſt.
               
               
                  M. G.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
               LONDON, Imprinted by Abell Ieſſes, dwelling in the Foreſtréete without Créeplegate néere vnto Grubſtraete, 1587
         
      
   

