
   
      
         
            The Popes pittiful lamentation, for the death of his deere darling Don Ioan of Austria and deaths aunswer to the same. With an epitaphe vpon the death of the said Don Ioan. Translated after the French printed coppy. by H.C.
         
         
            
               1578
            
         
         Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02218
            STC 12355
            ESTC S105875
            99841601
            99841601
            6197
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02218)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6197)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 344:23)
         
         
            
               
                  The Popes pittiful lamentation, for the death of his deere darling Don Ioan of Austria and deaths aunswer to the same. With an epitaphe vpon the death of the said Don Ioan. Translated after the French printed coppy. by H.C.
                  Chettle, Henry, d. 1607?, attributed name.
                  Constable, Henry, 1562-1613, attributed name.
                  H. C.
                  Gregory XIII, Pope, 1502-1585, attributed name.
               
               [8] p.   
               
                  Printed by J. Charlewood,
                  [London :
                  1578?]
               
               
                  The attribution to Pope Gregory XIII is ironic. "The 'French coppy' is untraced, and may be fictitious"--Halkett &amp; Laing (3rd ed.).
                  In verse.
                  Translation sometimes attributed to Henry Chettle and to Henry Constable.
                  Caption title.
                  The work is dated 1 October 1578, the date of John of Austria's death.
                  Colophon reads "Imprinted by I.C."; printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               John, --  of Austria, 1547-1578 --  Poetry.
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-02
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-03
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2003-03
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ❧The Popes pittiful Lamentation, for the death of his deere darling Don Ioan of Austria: and Deaths aunswer to the same. With an Epitaphe vpon the death of the said Don Ioan. Translated after the French printed coppy. by H. C.
            ¶The Popes Lamentation.
            
               O Heauen, O Earth, O Elaments,
            and all therein containde,
            Lament with me, powre forth your plaints
            iust cause hath so cōstraind,
            Sith cursed Death, in cruel wise,
            hath reft me my delight:
            
               Don Ioan of Austria
               ▪ he that sought,
            by all the meanes he might,
            To saue my church &amp; me from harme▪
            
            to strengthen my estate,
            And with his power, to punish those
            that did my doings hate.
            
               Mine eyes sende forth, your brinish teares,
            more cause you neuer had:
            Since he is d
                  •
               ad, whose douty deedes
            erst made my hart ful glad.
            Now let my Halles be hangd about,
            with mestfull morning weed
                  •
               :
            For plea
                  •
               āt things, procure my paine,
            d
                  •
               lights my dole doe breede.
            Come, come, my carefull Cardnalles now,
            my Prelates and the rest:
            That wonted were to wish me well,
            I pray ye all be prest.
            To waile with woe, the want of him,
            that during tearme of life:
            Neglected nought that might bee wrought
            to make our glory rife.
            Alas how am I gript with grife,
            what cares do compasse me:
            For losse of him, whom I ordainde,
            my Champion cheefe to be,
            To 
                  •
               ight with those yt were my foes,
            whom I had handled so,
            That he beleeude I was a God,
            aswell as many moe,
            
               That with my charmes I did inchaūt
            to finde his like againe
            In all the world, who so should seeke,
            would labour loose in vaine.
            And for this cause I called him,
            to state of hye degree:
            Prouoking him to that which should
            for my preferment bee.
            Ful wel my couenaūts could he keepe
            my lawes and statutes large,
            My Buls, &amp; pardons, pleas'd him wel
            they weare his cheefest charge.
            And therfore Death, I curse thee now
            and eke thy cruel dart:
            Which did to that renowmed Prince,
            thy p
                  •
               ysoned power impart.
            These Huguenots thou mightest haue hitte,
            to pacifye thine yre,
            And let this worthy wight alone,
            to further my desyre.
            Thou hast not onely striken him,
            but diuerse more besyde:
            As by thy deadly Darte appeares,
            that in theyr blood was di'de.
            
               Thy furious force from me remooue,
            and straight thy strength extend
            Uppon a Prince whose name I hate,
            at him thy battry bende.
            So shall my sorrow somewhat cease,
            but gr
                  •
               ater griefes will growe,
            If thus thou seeke gainst me and mine
            thy rigorous rage to show.
            FINIS.
         
         
            ¶ Deathes aunswer.
            CUrse me as much, as care thou can,
            I waye it nought at all:
            Each earthly Wight I can constraine,
            to come when I doo call.
            T
                  •
               e s
                  •
               ruaunt o
                  •
                the liuing Lorde
            
               
                  〈◊〉
                am and must obaye
            His heauēly hests, whō he commaūds
            I must without delaye
            
               Depriue of life, my pearsinge Darte
            must execute his will
            On all that bide within my bounds,
            not one can scape by sk
                  •
               ll.
            Both Princes, Lords &amp; lo
                  •
               ty Peeres,
            I quickly can constraine
            To follow me, and quite forgoe
            their goodly gorgious traine.
            Thy selfe that saist thou art a God,
            to blinde and bl
                  •
               are mens eyes,
            Shalt passe the path that oth
                  •
               rs doe,
            no meanes thou maist deuise.
            To shonne the snare, but with the rest
            thou must my rigour
                  •
                taste:
            If I intende to touch thee once,
            thy waile
                  •
               ull wordes are wast.
            Though frant
                  •
               ck fooles thy court frequent
            from contryes far &amp; ne
                  •
               re:
            And honour thee as God on earth,
            to make thy pompe appear
                  •
               :
            Whereby they robbe the liuing Lord,
            of all his honor quight:
            I'le pul thee from thy princely throne,
            and maister thee by might.
            
               Thy treasures nor thy tripple crowne
            thy Iems and Iwels rare,
            Cannot corrupt me so, as I
            thy cursed corpes wil spare.
            When I shal call thee from thy pompe
            that pampreth thee in pride,
            Then shall I laugh to see thee lothe,
            my doleful doome to bide:
            For so my common custome is,
            when with my deadly darte
            I strike those wightes, that one the world
            haue wholy s
                  •
               t theyr hart.
            Alas sa
                  •
               th one, a stat
                  •
               ly howse,
            repl
                  •
               ate with ritches rare,
            A dainty dame, whose deere delights,
            can comfort all my care,
            And store of goodly ground I haue,
            well growen with grasse and graine
            Faire flocks of sheep, &amp; feeding beasts,
            with all that may maintaine
            A happy life: yet must I dye,
            and leaue them all behinde?
            O heauy happe, what greater greefe,
            might euer grype my minde.
            
               Another saith, I haue a wife,
            whose bewty doth surmount:
            Faire children fraught with natures gifts
            which makes my ioyes to mount▪
            
            Aboue the clowds: and there withall
            such gubbes of golde I haue,
            with plate &amp; precious stones such store
            as hart can wish or craue:
            Yet nothing may my raunsome paye▪
            
            nor me from death redeeme,
            He reaks not ritches, euery one
            he doth alike esteeme.
            Poore people are not found so fond,
            my furious force to flye
            No meanes they seeke, but when I strike,
            they gladly graunt to dye.
            And therefore had I rath
                  •
               r farre.
            the ritch
                  •
               r sort assaile:
            That I my selfe might merry make,
            to see them weepe and waile.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            ¶ Don Ioans Epitaph.
            
               DOn Ioan of Austria heere entomb'd doth lye,
               that was the worthy warriour willō
                   nam'd
               Who prowdly did of late, his power applye,
               the fatall foyle of Flaunders to haue fram'd.
            
            
               Of stomack stoute, and hawghty hart he was,
               and made his vaunt the Emperors sonne to bee▪
               
               But yet the thing, he thought to bringe to passe,
               the liuing Lord hath frustrate made wee see.
            
            
               
                  The fyrst of October. 1578.
               
            
            L'acquis abonde.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
               ❧Imprinted by I.C.
            
         
      
   

