
   
      
         
            The castell of laboure
            Gringore, Pierre, ca. 1475-1538?
         
         
            
               1506
            
         
         Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02248
            STC 12381
            ESTC S109550
            99845197
            99845197
            10084
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02248)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10084)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 49:14)
         
         
            
               
                  The castell of laboure
                  Gringore, Pierre, ca. 1475-1538?
                  Bruyant, Jean, 14th cent.
                  Barclay, Alexander, 1475?-1552, attributed name.
               
               [104] p. : ill.  
               
                  In fletestrete in the sygne of the sonne, by Wynkyn de worde,
                  [Enprynted at London :
                  Anno d[omi]ni. M.CCCCC.vi. [1506]]
               
               
                  A translation (attributed to Alexander Barclay) from the French original, which is based on Jean Bruyant's poem Le chemin de povreté et de richesse.
                  Imprint from colophon.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: a-h·⁴ i⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               French literature --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.
               Working class in literature --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-04
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-05
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  The castell of laboure.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
            
         
         
            
            Here begynneth the prologe
of this present treatyse
            
               YE mortall people that desyre to obtayne
               Eternall blysse by your labour dylygent
               With mortall ryches subdue you to payne
               To rede this treatyse to the ryght entent
               Whiche shall shewe you playne and euydent
               That ydelnes moder of all aduersyte
               Her subiectes bryngeth to extreme pouerte
            
            
               The ryche by ydelnes to pouerte are brought
               By it the oratour leseth his scyence
               The grete clerke by it is set at nought
               Thus is it ennemye vnto sapyence
               Wherfore let vs do our dylygence
               This leude capytayne fro vs to exyle
               Whiche nought entendeth but man to begyle
            
            
               Ydell people euer troubled are with thought
               With indygence mysauenture and necessyte
               And in the snare whan they are cought
               They are enuyroned with pouerte
               Than cometh dysconfort in theyr aduersyte
               And also dyspayre them doth manace
               And thought and trouble euer doth them chace
            
            
               Therfore ye people that be subiect to this vyce
               By your grete sleuthe and neglygence
               Breke your bondes / I aduyse you to aryse
               And to these wordes gyue your aduertence
               
                  
Whiche the wyse man sayth in brief sentence
               Who laboureth not to get his lyuynge
               Is no worthy here to haue abydynge
            
            
               ¶Thus whan this vyce a man dothe assayle
               Of sleuthsulnes and of ocyosyte
               By theyr meanes dothe ryches fayle
               What foloweth than but pouerte
               Thus tourneth his welthe vnto aduersyte
               So of his folye dothe he repent
               Than echone to hym doth iniurye
               Whiche oft to vs appereth euydent
            
            
               ¶Therfore to vs it is ryght profytable
               For to take reason for to be our gyde
               With vnderstoudynge / whiche are agreable
               Vs for to gouerne in euery tyde
               Wherby we may / yf sleuthe be set asyde
               Ouercome pouerte &amp; obteyne rychesse
               And dystroy thought mysfortune &amp; dystresse
            
            
               ¶But mannes mynde is full vnstedfast
               More prone to vyce than to goodlynesse
               And whan by vyce man thus is ouercast
               Than cometh dysceyte / vsurye and falsnesse
               Counseylynge man all to vnthreftynesse
               Thus yf that reason be not our frende and gyde
               Trouthe shall decay by falshode and pryde
            
            
               But who wolde lyue in meane moderate
               And by way of dylygence rychesse purchace
               Good wyll must he haue to be his aduocate
               
                  
With a good hert / for therin is solace
               Intencyon to good must we purchace
               And than may we lyue bytwene hye and lowe
               By suche meane that our frendes may vs knowe
            
            
               In this lyfe can none haue skarsnesse
               Whyle that reason is his protectour
               Yf he in labourynge take peyne and besynesse
               Auoydinge sleuth that blynde gouernour
               Whiche man assayleth euery day and hour
               Wherby are many brought to dystresse
               But dylygence bryngeth man to rychesse
            
            
               By whiche rychesse man cometh to noblenesse
               Whiche to vertue is as chyef nouryse
               Therfore leue we sleuth drawynge to besynesse
               Enclynynge to vertue and leuynge couetyse
               Thus is it good to eche that is wyse
               Remembrynge how sone he shall haue an ende
               In trouth and vertue his short tyme to spende
            
            
               Thus in conclusyon who redeth this treatyse
               To the rude langage gyue none aduertence
               It is but wryten the tyme to exercyse
               Without studye / peyne / or dylygence
               With style inornate / voyde of eloquence
               Expressynge the wayes of dylygence &amp; ydelnesse
               The one of pouerte the other of rychesse
            
         
         
            ¶Thus endeth the prologue and be
gynneth the castell of labour.
            
               
               
            
            
               IN musynge an euenȳge with me was none
               An olde prouerbe came in me subuenaūce
               A naturall foole in a house alone
               Wyl make for hymself shyft or cheuysaūce
               Than came in to my remembraunce
               A cyrcunspect of many dygnytees
               Fro whiche a man hauynge suffysaunce
               Withdraweth his herte as fro vanytees
            
            
               It is ay sene that youthes lustynesse
               For to subdue is harde and daungerous
               Some lyue in ioye / pleasure and gladnesse
               Fortune to some is ryght contraryous
               Some dethe tacheth in theyr estate prosperous
               Whome he ouerthroweth with his mortall blast
               Thus goeth the worlde / none is so eurous
               But other must he dye fyrst or last
            
            
               
               A yonge herte is vnstable and volage
               And knoweth not in what estate to byde
               Somtyme dysposed vnto maryage
               Somtyme to serue god the worlde set asyde
               Thus as my mynde varyenge dyd glyde
               I thought it most for myn auauntage
               Desyrynge god for to be my gyde
               Fermely I concluded vpon maryage
            
            
               Thus hauynge all my frendes at assent
               In short processe I puruayed me a wyfe
               Without wysedom / yet was I content
               To her to kepe the dayes of my lyfe
               I thought no thynge on wynnynge losse or stryfe
               She vnto me lyghtly dyd consent
               Than in an euenynge sad and pensyfe
               By her lyenge symple of myn entent
            
            
               
                  pouertye
                  necessyte
                  Dystresse
                  Nede.
               
            
            
               
               Sodanly I was in grete daunger
               For to me fyersly dyd appere
               An odyous man / an vnknowen straunger
               With thre women cruell of manere
               This company to me approched nere
               Whan that I them togyder sawe assemble
               So cruell was theyr countenaunce and chere
               That fere constrayned my body for to tremble
            
            
               The man was mysshapen / pale / and rusty
               Rude / foule / and ryght abhomynable
               The women also as I coude spye
               Of shape were foule aud detestable
               Theyr chere was yll and myserable
               With contenaunce replenysshed with ire
               Lene as ony wolf rauysable
               Theyr eyen brennynge as rede as fyre
            
            
               The man approched fyers as he woldefyght
               With starynge eyen / &amp; sayde his name was nede
               His wyfe sayde necessyte she hyght
               The seconde pouerte / and the thyrde in dede
               Her named dystresse so thought I by her wede
               Than I desyred to knowe theyr lynage
               Pouerte was theyr moder full of drede
               This tolde they me in bryef langage
            
            
               Touchynge theyr fader they coude not denye
               But that he dwelt in the depest pyt of hell
               Whan I that harde ryght sore aferde was I
               Than nede approched with coūtenaunce cruell
               Myn body streynynge so that it dyd swell
               Necessyte me so sore dyd handle
               So that sothly it semed ryght well
               
                  
Or that she went she wolde me strangle
            
            
               Than sodaynly came pouerte
               Whiche me tourmented with rudenesse
               Than with grete crudelyte
               Vpon my bely lept dystresse
               They all abounded in cruelnesse
               On me smytynge with all theyr myght
               Dysgorgynge fyre in theyr fyersnesse
               Vpon me as a torche lyght
            
            
               Some at me foyned / some smote downe ryght
               That the strokes loude dyd redounde
               For all my peyne / durynge that nyght
               My wyfe euer slept styll and sounde
               She in her pleasure dyd habounde
               And wolde not wake for my dysease
               For yf I were brought to the grounde
               I trowe she cared not a pease
            
            
               
                  thought
               
            
            
               
               
                  AS she thus slept and I in payne
               With these foure fures dyd endure
               To me approche I sawe certayne
               A foule and counterfayted creature
               Odyous / proude / &amp; fyers I you ensure
               And by the hande she toke me fast
               She thought her purpose to procure
               And drewe myn armes that they nere brast
            
            
               This fals witche me so dyd greue
               Whiche by her name was called thought
               That vneth coude I me remeue
               Thus vnto dethe she me nere brought
               Of wordes and tales she wanted nought
               Euer she talked I wote not what
               And behynde her a vylayne cought
               That was as blereyed as a cat
            
            
               
                  heuynes
               
            
            
               
               BEynge in this perturbacyon
               This chorle on me gaped full wyde
               I fered sore his entencyon
               Whan that I sawe hym by my syde
               He loked as he had ben fryde
               Of shape and colour was he full vyle
               Than he began with me to chyde
               In his langage whiche was subtyle
            
            
               Vpon my bely he set his knees
               And sayd his name was heuynesse
               With scarled bordred were his eyes
               Balde and full of vnlustynesse
               He semed fader of all vnthryftnesse
               Iagged and garded full vngay
               With a race fylled with falsnesse
               Berded lyke to a kytlynge of may
            
            
               Hym to beholde I was dysmayed
               Howe he of thynges past dyd clatter
               Many a newe tale to me he sayde
               He had well lerned for to patter
               Of thynges to come fast dyd he chatter
               Byddynge me call them to remembraunce
               He lyst no thynge with me to flatter
               But put me to extreme vttraunce
            
            
               He bad I sholde remember my dettys
               And brought me forthe my countynge boke
               He shewed me there of my receptes
               And me compelled theron to loke
               By fere constrayned me body quoke
               That power was past me for to speke
               
                  
That rybaude fered me with his loke
               That confort to me coude I none take
            
            
               Of his tourment what sholde I say
               I neuer was in suche encumbraunce
               He bode styll and went not away
               And dyd me moche more greuaunce
               Than all the other by theyr noysaunce
               And tourned me fro syde to syde
               To slepe he left me no suffraunce
               But fyresly styll at me dyd chyde
            
            
               This fals caytyf by his cruelnesse
               Troubled me that my wytte was gone
               He put me in so grete dystresse
               That my herte was colde as ony stone
               I knewe not to whome me for to mone
               So was I enuyroned rounde about
               They me tourmented so echone
               That of my lyfe I had grete dout
            
            
               ¶Than rounde about me dyd I loke
               Fyrst of all same I pouerte
               And fals nede by the berde me shoke
               There were dystresse and necessyte
               Thought was in theyr companye
               And heuynes dyd clater fast
               All these syr so layde at me
               That fro my bed they me nere cast
            
            
               Than as I dyd my hede remeue
               About me lokynge for confort
               I sawe one come / whiche dyd me greue
               More than all the other sorte
               
                  
He sayde his name was dysconfort
               Of colour was he pale and wan
               It nought auayled hym to exhort
               I sawe neuer suche an other man
            
            
               
                  Disconfort
               
            
            
               By the hande fast he me toke
               And with grete myght dyd m constrayne
               Full sore me by the berde he shoke
               This these renewed all my peyne
               His encumbraunce wasted my brayne
               That often I wysshed that I were dede
               He wolde hym selfe no thynge refrayne
               But kept me styll fast by the hede
            
            
               In frowarde imaginacyon
               Dysconforte kept me a longe space
               He bad me in conclusyon
               To sue to hym after his grace
               
                  
Saynge that the tyme and space
               Ones lost coude not recouered be
               With suche termes dyd he me manase
               Than in conclusyon thus sayd he
            
            
               A poore man how shalt thou pay
               All thy dettes that are behynde
               Brede and drynke must thou puruay
               And a house to kepe the fro the wynde
               Bothe men and maydens must thou fynde
               With euery thynge that longeth them to
               Doth not fortune strongly the bynde
               Now let se how thou canst do
            
            
               What I this harde I was nere mad
               And often fortune cursed I
               The specyall cause why I was sad
               Was for my purse was clene empty
               Than was it nede I dyd espye
               My gowne to pledge vnto one
               I sawe there was no remedy
               Though that I had but that alone
            
            
               O blessyd iesu what may this be
               Maryed was I in an euyll chaunce
               To lyue in suche pouerte
               As I this sayd thesame instaunce
               Came to me Despayre in cruell ordonaunce
               One of the worst of all the sort
               She was chyef capytayne of theyr daunce
               And doughter vnto Dysconfort
            
            
               
               
                  Despayre
                  dysconfort.
               
            
            
               This Despayre dyd me so assayle
               That lost was my dyscrecyon
               My face began to wax pale
               By fere of her cruell vexacyon
               So cruell was her perturbacyon
               Whiche on me she dyd extende
               That I thought in conclusyon
               Of my selfe to make an ende
            
            
               ¶I was redy to renne here and there
               To clymbe vp hye and than to fall
               By my lyfe set I not an here
               By meanes of this furye infernall
               I thought / who nedes to his deth shall
               It is but folye it to prolonge
               This is a worde sayde ouerall
               He that is drowned may no man hange
            
            
               
               And therfore thought I for to do
               The worst that eyther I coude or myght
               To sle my fader and moder also
               Yf I had founde them in my syght
               Than vnto my mynde came full ryght
               That I sholde dye no more but ones
               Wherfore dyspayre that wretched wyght
               Bad me go therto at ones
            
            
               I sawe well that without labour
               I neuer sholde sholde obteyne rychesse
               Fortune therof is gouernour
               To some she gyueth with largesse
               But I haue neyther more nor lesse
               So that I wery am of my lyfe
               Auoyde of ioyefull of dystresse
               Lo what it is to take a wyfe
            
            
               I se dysconfort doth me greue
               Despayre encreaseth my lang our
               That fote ne hande can I remeue
               Suche is my payne and my dolour
               Neyther thought I on worshyp ne honour
               On knyght squyer baron ne lorde
               My mynde was on no thynge that houre
               But to hange my selfe with a corde
            
            
               Or elles to lepe in to some ryuer
               And there with peyne my selfe to drowne
               I cared not in what maner
               I dyed so that my lyfe were done
               Despayre made me her champyon
               And had me so take in her snare
               
                  
That sodenly as I fell in suowne
               She me nere strangled or I was ware
            
            
               
                  treason
                  Despeyre
               
            
            
               
                  AS I was in this perturbacyon
               I sawe a lady pleasaunt and bryght
               For to beholde her meke fassyon
               Sothly it was a pleasaunt syght
               Her caperon with parle was pyght
               With precyous stones about enlumynynge
               Her beaute full face shone as bryght
               As phebus doth in a may mornynge
            
            
               This lady standynge me before
               In her behauour was meke and lyberall
               Good and gracyous to ryche and poore
               She semed to me the quene celestyall
               
                  
A quene excellent I may her call
               For she was doughter shortly to say
               Vnto that meke lorde and immortall
               The whiche was borne on Chrystmas day
            
            
               Sore I desyred to knowe her name
               By cause she was of suche excellence
               She sayde reason whome none doth blame
               Than was I ryght glad of her presence
               This noble lady by her dylygence
               Approched nere vnto my syde
               Despayre anone gate her thens
               And dysconfort with her dyd glyde
            
            
               All the hole company dyd auoyde
               What tyme reason sat by me thus
               It was some wynde wolde me haue noyed
               Sende vnto me by myght of Eolus
               I trowe that Pluto / or Neptunus
               Or mars chyef forger of batayle
               Or elles helporter Cerberus
               Engendred them me to assayle
            
            
               What sholde I say they fled that tyde
               Bothe despayre and the other rout
               Than was there none with me to chyde
               I rysynge vp loked rounde about
               Than of no thynge was I in doubt
               Whan reason began to speke softly
               Whan she had dryuen the other out
               That her to here grete Ioye had I
            
            
               Reason spake with delyberacyon
               Replete with wysedom excellently
               
                  
So that sothly in conclusyon
               She semed an oratoure wytty
               What she sayde was sayde playnly
               To the vnderstondynge of euery man
               And syttynge in a chayre me by
               Wys
                     •
                  ly to speke thus she began
            
            
               My frende this thought se thou eschewe
               Ferest thou that rychesse wyll fayle
               Subdue thy selfe to force and vertue
               And be reuled by my counsayle
               Whiche shall the guyde in eche batayle
               So thou consyder what thou hast to do
               Thou mayst gete gode by thy trauayle
               For to fynde the and all thyn to
            
            
               
                  ONe god alone must thou honoure
               And hym serue with all dylygence
               And as thy selfe loue thy neyghboure
               Agaynst hym do thou none offence
               In trouble se thou haue pacyence
               After the tyme and the season
               To eche man haue thou obedyence
               These be the termes of reason
            
            
               Thou sholdest not to largely
               Reioyse thy selfe of thy rychesse
               Nor yet be wrothe semblably
               Of pouerte / peyne / or dystresse
               Whan Atropos hymselfe doth dresse
               Eche to smyte with his mortall lance
               He smyteth the ryche with cruelnesse
               And to the poore hath oft suffraunce
            
            
               
               Why shold thyn herte for sere thus fayle
               Is it not rychesse ynough to the
               To haue thy handes redy to trauayle
               Without wem or mayme of thy body
               Yf that thou 
                     ••
                  bour certaynly
               Thou shall 
                     •
                  ot fayle to haue rychesse
               So that thou from all synne do fle
               Peasably lyuynge in mekenesse
            
            
               Fyrste auoyde eche synne mortall
               Replenysshe the with the grace dyuyne
               Behaue the so in this lyfe mortall
               That thou to hell do not declyne
               Submyt thy selfe vnto the discyplyne
               Of hym that made eche creature
               Praye hym thyn herte so to enlumyne
               That thou aduersyte may endure
            
            
               Whan nede cometh to thy presence
               To besye labour infyx thy courage
               So shalt thou make hym to go thens
               Constreynynge hym maugre his vysage
               And yf dystresse do vnto the outrage
               Thorough besynesse awaye hym chase
               Yf thought wolde do to the domage
               In some good dede put thy solace
            
            
               And yf pouertye do the assayle
               Or fals and feble necessyte
               Enforce thy body vnto trauayle
               By suche meane shalt thou cause them fle
               Yf dysconfort do trouble the
               Tende not vnto his tempta cyon
               
                  
Yf despayre 
                     〈…〉
                   olde thy lady be
               Leue her and come vnto me reason
            
            
               
                  humilitie casteth Pryde
               
            
            
               YF pryde on the do auenture
               Despyte dysdayne or presumpcyon
               Beware of them they are not sure
               Of them cometh grete abusyon
               Cast fro the collaudacyon
               Vayne glorye with mysgouernaunce
               Fle fro fals ymagynacyon
               Fle bostynge and oultrecuydaunce
            
            
               Yf suche vyces on the do warre
               Them and theyr werkes se thou despyse
               Constrayne them by myght to stande a farre
               Pray humylyte the to promyse
               Her helpe and socoure in ony wyse
               With contemplacyon and deuocyon
               But aboue all I the aduyse
               Be meke of thyn entencyon
            
            
               
               Humylyte must be the chyef
               Agaynst pryde grounde of all vyce
               And for to kepe the fro myschyef
               Do so that thou mayst haue iustyce
               Gete good prouysyon yf thou be wyse
               Lete hym euer kepe the vantgarde
               Than shall pryde full of malyce
               Renounsynge the auoyde rerewarde
            
            
               
                  charite casteth Enuye
               
            
            
               
                  AFter that pryde is fro the chased
               By the myght of humylyte
               With a nother thou shalt be menased
               Whiche is daungerous called enuye
               Accompanyed with myserye
               With falshode / murder / and treason
               Suche shall be in his companye
               With sclaunder and fals detraccyon
            
            
               
               As a daungerous capytayne
               Enuye wyll the assayle and touche
               He shall do the full mouche payne
               Yf thou as subiect vnto hym crouche
               Ill reporte hath he in his pouche
               With many vyces and dyuers
               Whiche vnto vertue are reproche
               Hym alway tendynge to reuers
            
            
               Whan that thou seest her the aboute
               In me put thou thy trust and Ioye
               Be not afrayde nor do not doute
               Trust well I shall them all destroye
               Fayth and charyte shall them noye
               Se thou alwaye do her honoure
               So shall she wyt on the employe
               To knowe how she men doth socour
            
            
               Charyte hath waytynge on her dygnyte
               Very true loue and miserycorde
               Beneuolence with grace and veryte
               Amonge them founde is no dyscorde
               But peas mekenesse and concorde
               These shall the helpe in thy necessyte
               And thus as I vnto the recorde
               They shall enuye auoyde fro the
            
            
               
               
                  pacience ca
                        ••••
                      yre
               
            
            
               
                  ANd than whan done is this assaute
               On the shall come a tyraūt daūgerous
               Whose name is Ire withouten faute
               To all vyce fyers and desyrous
               And vnto vertue alwaye contraryous
               The whiche in seruauntes doth abounde
               He may well say that he is eurous
               Whome this vyce doth not confounde
            
            
               Cruelte bereth his banyer
               Felonye is his chyef champyon
               Peruersyte is his portere
               Madnes reygneth in his dongeon
               Cursed murder that fals felon
               Of his hous is as chyef captayne
               Here is a cursed relygyon
               To hym that foloweth theyr trayne
            
            
               Therfore yf Ire do the dystresse
               Shewe thy force and thy puysaūce
               Call vnto the debonayrnesse
               
                  
Agaynst yre a full myghty launce
               With her shall come fayre suffraunce
               Pacyence is chyef / with dyscrecyon
               Stedfastnesse with attemperaunce
               Subduynge the vnto correccyen
            
            
               Ire hath neyther mercy nor pety
               On man nor woman here lyuynge
               But echone assayleth full cruelly
               Ennemye to peas and to warre accordynge
               Susteyner of eche vyce semynge
               Whose furour melteth mannes hert
               Whiche to his counsell are lenynge
               Wherfore thy syght therfro dyuert
            
            
               It is impossyble that a man Irous
               May vnto god do good seruyce
               For Ire is a synne ryght daungerous
               Whiche is gouerned without Iustyce
               It is a fyers and mortall vyce
               Whiche often dothe ryght grete domage
               Syth thou art warned be thou wyse
               Lyst that he do to the outrage
            
            
               Shewe thy force and puyssaunce
               Call vnto the force with noblenesse
               Pray pacyence to be thy launce
               Whiche shall this vyce lyghtly oppresse
               Whan yre is gone sleuthe shall her dresse
               On euery syde with the to fyght
               Whiche of all vyce is chyef maystresse
               A stronge tyraunt despysynge ryght
            
            
               
               
                  Dylygēce casteth Sleuthe
               
            
            
               
                  AS chyef capytayne of all the rout
               Sleuth shall haue pleasure ye to assayle
               And sonne I put the out of dout
               That in thy bed she shall not fayle
               On the to lye bothe wanne and pale
               On her shall wayte vnlustynesse
               With neglygence voyde of trauayle
               Chyef guyder of all vnthryftenesse
            
            
               Defende the fyersly as a man
               For with sleuthe shall come rychelesse
               For to subdue the yf he can
               Puttynge the to vnlustynesse
               Accompanyed with fals fayntnesse
               The whiche by theyr iniquyte
               Many one bryngeth fro tychesse
               Vnto grete payne and pouerte
            
            
               Cowardyse wyll the folowe fast
               Yf thou do not thy selfe defende
               
                  
Vnto the grounde he wyll the cast
               But yf that thou thy myght extende
               And her withstandynge yf thou entende
               With her to fyght by force souerayne
               Vnto the grounde shall she descende
               Lyke the wynde peased by rayne
            
            
               Sleuth to the wyll make good chere
               By faynt and feble dyssymulacyon
               But at the ende is his manere
               For to stange lyke the scorpyon
               Beware of his abusyon
               Lyst that thou in his bondes rest
               But for helpe in conclusyon
               To god must thou make thy request
            
            
               Agaynst sleuth for thy defence
               Entencyon to good must thou requyre
               Prouyde chyefly for dylygence
               Besynesse with charge se thou desyre
               And for good hert se thou enquyre
               Pray good wyll to be thy gyde
               So shalt thou sleuth cast in the myre
               Hym and his asse as he doth ryde
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
               
               
                  Largesse casteth Covetyse.
               
            
            
               
                  After this assaut perylous
               On the shall come voyde of Iustyce
               One ougly fyers and daungerous
               Whose name is called auaryce
               Beware his cursed couetyse
               For by his wordes fals and subtyle
               Many one to hym dothe he atyse
               Whome at the ende he dothe begyle
            
            
               Auaryce is so yll and vnsacyable
               Neuer fulfylled with rychesse
               And of his mynde ay founde vnstable
               By thought euer fulfylled with heuynesse
               This auaryce doth all them oppresse
               Whiche lyghtly fyndeth not socoure
               He and his seruauntes wyll them dresse
               The to assayle at euery houre
            
            
               Whan auaryce dothe the assayle
               With hym wyll come full lyghtly
               Vsurye and rapyne withouten fayle
               
                  
Fals swerynge and okerye
               Murder / theft / and trecherye
               Fraude / falshode / and decepcyon
               Accompanyed with roberye
               Malyce and cauyllacyon
            
            
               Whan that thou seest this companye
               With auaryce the to dystresse
               Withdrawe thy selfe to charyte
               To suffysaunce and to largesse
               But in largesse auoyde excesse
               And by almes I the ensure
               Auaryce thou shalt oppresse
               That he no lenger shall endure
            
            
               And yf that ony maner creature
               Wolde say that these vyces all
               Be gyuen vnto them by nature
               Or yet by destenye infernall
               Mesemeth nay / theyr wyll is lyberall
               God hath vs gyuen reason and wyt
               Vs for to guyde vnto ioy eternall
               Whiche we shall haue ye we deserue it
            
            
               Th
                     ••
                  fore my sone se that thou entende
               Vnto thy selfe with perfyte dylygence
               Wherby thou mayst the fro this vyce defende
               For euer thou seest by playne euydence
               That auaryce full of malyuolence
               Hym moost hurteth that loueth it best
               With largesse make for hym defence
               Yf thou woldest haue thy mynde in rest
            
            
               
               
                  sob
                        ••
                     te casteth glotony
               
            
            
               
                  SO whan thou ouercome hast auaryce
               With the braunches of his lynage
               To the wyll come a cruell vyce
               Named glotonye full of outrage
               Whiche wyll to the do grete domage
               Yf thou thy selfe to hym subdue
               As wel in youthe as in thy age
               This vyce on many doth renewe
            
            
               To drynke whan thou hast no thurst
               Without mesure or ony reason
               And to ete whan thou hast no lust
               Therin is no dyscrecyon
               He may be called a foule gloton
               That of his wombe his god doth make
               Beware of this abusyon
               Lyft in his bondes this vyce the take
            
            
               Dysordered appetyte is with glotonye
               And serueth hym chyef on the nyght
               And gurmandyse is of his meyny
               
                  
And sleuth with hym encreaseth myght
               All these fyersly on the wyll lyght
               On eche syde the temptynge myghtely
               But lyft vp thyn eyen to heuen bryght
               Besechynge god of helpe mekely
            
            
               Sothely whan that thy stomake
               Is furnysshed with mete beyonde nature
               Thou mayst be lykened vnto a sacke
               Replete with fylthe dunge and ordure
               It dyspleaseth god sore / I the ensure
               And to thy selfe doest thou outrage
               Than bableth thy tunge without mesure
               To others hurt / sclander and domage
            
            
               Yest mayst thou make ryght good resystence
               Agaynst them maugre theyr vysage
               So that thou wylt take abstynence
               The whiche shall be for thyn auauntage
               Sobryete is chyef of this passage
               Whiche shall glotonye fro the auoyde
               Who in grete drynkynge hath vsage
               By deth lyghtly is destroyed
            
            
               Drunkenesse dothe the longes brenne
               And maketh the membres for to quake
               Dr
                     •
                  nken men often laugh and greene
               Than me 
                     ••
                  ooth them for fooles take
               Drunkenesse the wyt doth brake
               It maketh a man to fyght and chyde
               Sothly this vyce often doth make
               A man of his frendes homycyde
            
            
               
               
                  chastite casteth lechery
               
            
            
               WHan thou escaped hast glotonye
               And passed his cruell morsure
               The sore assayle wyll lechyerye
               A cruell vyce I the ensure
               The whiche is of suche nature
               At her begynnynge her face to paynt
               But yf that she a whyle endure
               Thy body wyll she make full faynt
            
            
               This foule synne ougly to name
               With her braunches ryght many folde
               Hym that it loueth bryngeth to shame
               Example of Hercules the bolde
               I coude mo counte yf that I wolde
               Whome lechery hath made to smerte
               Bryefly yf thou wylt haue tolde
               It destroyeth many a noble herte
            
            
               It wyll the gyue foolysshe pleasaunce
               With a desyre ryght dysordynate
               Superfluyte with his launce
               Yf he with the do make debate
               
                  
He wyll the lay on the grounde prostrate
               And brynge the vnto captyuyte
               Makynge the fall fro thyn estate
               And to knowe thy fragylyte
            
            
               Cupydo shall thyn eyen bynde
               Hauynge venus hym to socoure
               Thus whan these two haue made the blynde
               They shall the brynge in grete erroure
               Than shall thou fall in to langoure
               For whan thou art in theyr bondes cought
               Yf thou leue not by theyr rygoure
               Shortly they shall the brynge to nought
            
            
               For to auoyde the crudelyte
               Of this fals archer amerous
               Take thou the shelde of chastyte
               Therin is fortune prosperous
               Chastyte is so vyctoryous
               That he wyll take vyndycacyon
               Of this fals vyce full vycyous
               And vaynquysshe his operacyon
            
            
               Many be that wyll them excuse
               Of theyr loke and beholdynge
               Saynge that none can theym accuse
               For beholdynge of ony thynge
               This reason is vnto them semynge
               Be not our eyen made for to se
               Suche excusacyons wyll they brynge
               For to defende theyr infelycyte
            
            
               Thus say they for theyr excusaunce
               Why may we not loke here and there
               
                  
That is trouth without doutaunce
               Of thy loke nedest thou not to fere
               But yet my sone this mayst thou lere
               Thyn eyen vnto the god hath sent
               With them to loke euery where
               So that thou haue a good entent
            
            
               The fayre regarde of maryage
               Is vnto god ryght grete delyte
               In good hope for to haue lynage
               Or ellys it is of no profyte
               Therfore yf thou wylt be perfyte
               Dryue awaye this foolysshe pleasaunce
               Geuynge vnto hym no respyte
               For to take the in to his daunce
            
            
               Remember the grete and fore vengeaunce
               Taken of god for this outrage
               Often tymes without doutaunce
               Of the mayster it maketh the page
               But as I sayde in maryage
               Behaue the as thou ought to do
               With good hope for to haue lynage
               Or elles sothly thou synnest to
            
            
               Therfore in bryef conclusyon
               To auoyde the peyne infernall
               Fle from all yll operacyon
               Procedynge of these synnes mortall
               And of pryde in especyall
               For whiche Lucyfer fell downe to hell
               Take this for a doctryne generall
               Whiche ensuynge I shall the tell
            
            
               
               ¶Agaynst pryde take thou mekenesse
               For enuye take thou charyte
               Pacyence putteth Ire in dystresse
               By dylygence sluethe is in captyuyte
               For couetyse take thou lyberalyte
               Glotonye by sobrenesse is made thrall
               Chastyte subdueth lechery
               But good and ferme fayth ruleth all
            
            
               It is trouth that mannes nature
               To all yll vyce is prone and redy
               Wherfore the better may he endure
               The whiche vseth somwhat percyte
               Whiche is a grete frende vnto chastyte
               Agaynst synne take suche resystence
               Yf thou wylt auoyde aduersyte
               And purchace a place in goddes presence
            
            
               Therfore yf thou wylt heuen obteyne
               As thy selfe loue thy neyghboure
               Fro mortall synne thy selfe refrayne
               Fere god and do hym honoure
               Do his hyddynge whiche is thy creatoure
               Speke lytell here what wyse men say
               So mayst thou escape terrene lan goure
               And haue wheron to lyue alway
            
            
               Where as many wordes are spoken
               For to speke in breef langage
               Often wysedom and trouth is broken
               Of moche speche cometh grete domage
               Who in grete langage hath vsage
               Some worde may he say in good entent
               
                  
The whiche soundeth to grete outrage
               And causeth hym after to repent
            
            
               Behaue thy selfe curtes and amyable
               Cause no debate / stryfe / nor dyscorde
               Be prudent / symple / and seruyable
               Speke thou of no man yll report
               Take good hope and good confort
               Lo here the playne waye of hardnesse
               Whiche shall the brynge vnto the fort
               That thou desyrest
               that is rychesse
            
            
               Rychesse goten by fore labour
               By watchynge trauayle and by peyne
               Is vnto god moche more pleasour
               Than it is whan it is sodayne
               One may in this lyfe mundayne
               Obteyne rychesse with grete vertue
               But whan it is yll goten certayne
               The getters vnto the deuyll subdue
            
            
               Folowe therfore the vertuous waye
               On the ryght hande that none doth begyle
               Leue the left / the whiche alwaye
               Destroyeth man / be he neuer so subtyle
               This waye that none doth defyle
               On the ryght hande is called dylygence
               For though the left on the do smyle
               The latter ende is voyde of all defence
            
            
               In this cursed waye on the left syde
               Many a man doth walke gladly
               So at the ende are they destroyed
               For that theyr good is goten falsly
               
                  
Some be drowned and some hanged on hye
               Be they neuer so hardy / subtyle / or wyse
               Suche is the ende / but the other sothly
               Bryngeth a man vnto paradyse
            
            
               A man that foloweth the left way
               Can vnneth hym selfe refrayne
               He that hym selfe refrayne not may
               Shall fynde it harde to come agayne
               Therfore begynne in the waye of peyne
               Whiche shall the brynge to the sterred regyon
               And for thy ledars haue no dysdayne
               To take vnderstandynge wyt and reason
            
            
               Some fooles yll and obstynate
               Whan they are repreued by Iustyce
               Say that they there to are destynate
               Wenynge for the excuse theyr malyce
               They say that fortune must accomplyse
               That / that is theyr destyne
               Thus dothe the deuyll these wretches atyse
               To kepe them in theyr incredulyte
            
            
               Good wyll must thou haue therfore
               Auoyde yll thought fro thyn entent
               And yf that thou be tempted sore
               Beware do not therto consent
               Lyft vp thyn eyen to the fyrmament
               Prayenge for helpe and than I reason
               Shall be ryght glad / fayne and dylygent
               The to delyuet in euery season
            
            
               Yf destryne shold haue domynacyon
               Than our good dedes sholde not auayle
               
                  
Echone wolde make transgressyon
               Yf thou so thynke thy mynde doth fayle
               Yf thou do well for thy trauayle
               Thou shalt haue Ioye / and for yll punycyon
               Gete heuen / and withouten fayle
               Thou escapest all tribulacyon
            
            
               Though that thy destenye be nought
               Be thou not redy to do the werst
               He that is of a cursed thought
               Euermore leueth the best
               Yf thou do yll beware the last
               Iustyce to eche geueth his guerdon
               Whan thy soule tro this lyfe is past
               Thou shalt haue euen as thou hast done
            
            
               In this noble way of dylygence
               Yf that thou thy selfe redresse
               Thou shalt by playne experyence
               By meane there of obteyne rychesse
               As for the waye of sleuthfulnesse
               Now euer it appere the ende is nought
               There is but wo / peyne and dystresse
               Dysconfort / trouble / care / and thought
            
            
               The waye of sleuth a man doth brynge
               Vnto a place of captyuyte
               Where nought is but hunger and mournynge
               Called the maner of wo and pouette
               There is no thynge but necessyte
               Brede nor drynke / worke nor trauayle
               There lyueth man in suche penurye
               That hunger constrayneth his hert to fayle
            
            
               
               Whan one is fall in suche myschaunce
               And subdued in suche pouertye
               He must to haue his sustenaunce
               His clothes sell releued for to be
               Whan they are gone than what doth he
               Than must he be a begger or a thefe
               So in conclusyon here may ye se
               Of sleuthe what is the ende and prese
            
            
               Of suche folke that ben ocyous
               By ryght no man sholde haue mercy
               They are to theym selfe contraryous
               Sleuth dysceyueth them so falsly
               Some be pale blacke and rusty
               Agaynst the sonne syttynge for solace
               Some dye for hunger some colde and thursty
               Sorowe mot he haue that it doth purchace
            
            
               Yf thou hast passed a place perylous
               And thens escaped without domage
               Take good hede se thou be cautelous
               Retourne not theder for thyn auauntage
               But the behaue as prudent wyse and sage
               Auoydynge all sleuthe and neglygence
               Go about by another passage
               Whiche is the waye of dylygence
            
            
               Yf thou se some goynge amysse
               Lyghtly auoyde theyr company
               Suche as in thy presence thy mouth wyl kysse
               And wolde the sle yf they myght preuely
               Be not aquaynted with suche comonly
               Kepe well thy counsell shewe not it
               
                  
Whan one blynde ledeth another lyghtly
               Often they bothe fall in the pytte
            
            
               Take therfore the ryght passage
               Of good hope and good esperaunce
               Be dylygent for thyn owne auauntage
               For therin is rychesse and pleasaunce
               Bothe in plentye and in suffysaunce
               But set not thyn hert theron to sore
               Gete not wrongfully suche abundaunce
               That thy soule suffre peyne therfore
            
            
               Who that tychesse to moche dothe pryse
               For it takynge labour and greuaunce
               Is so brought by vnhappy couetyse
               That he is neuer at his pleasaunce
               Though he haue rychesse in abundaunce
               For all is he not there with content
               But a man that hath suffysaunce
               To all good gladly dothe consent
            
            
               Suffysaunce doth god gretely please
               As thou full well mayst vnderstonde
               And couetyse dothe hym dysplease
               Therfore auoyde his cruell honde
               Let hym not take the in his bonde
               Lyst his excesse do the begyle
               Yf thou remember thou art but fonde
               With it thou endurest but a whyle
            
            
               Remember it is no thynge permanent
               In abundaunce to haue rychesse
               As water rennynge sone is it spent
               Whan deth cometh all thyn excesse
               
                  
Of welth and rychesse tourneth to heuynesse
               Thou must it all leue the behynde
               Than one of thy kynne with largesse
               Bloweth thy pens out with the wynde
            
            
               Therfore with lytell be thou content
               Thankynge euer god of pouerte
               Thanke hym of that he hath the sent
               Auoydynge synne and iniquyte
               If thou with synne subdued be
               Thou canst do no dede merytorye
               Do well and than I ensure the
               Thou shalte obteyne the heuenly glorye
            
            
               Some folke in all theyr lyfe
               To gete good are full dylygent
               Lettynge neyther for hatred ne stryfe
               And yet are they neuer content
               Vnto all falshode they do consent
               They tende not but to gete and saue
               With couetyse is theyr herte so brente
               That they thynke neuer ynough to haue
            
            
               Whan they are moost in fortunes grace
               Lyfted vp hye vnto the mone
               She shewynge them her frowarde face
               Causeth them lyghtly to come downe
               Though they before sate in theyr trone
               Fortune on them hath made a mowe
               Wherby theyr rychesse fro them is gone
               Than on the grounde lye they full lowe
            
            
               Therfore se thou fortune defye
               Syth her rychesse is so vnstable
               
                  
And in god onely thy selfe affye
               In whome is rychesse perdurable
               His suffysaunce is full profytable
               Therfore in hym thy selfe assure
               And in this purpose be thou stable
               God hym loueth that doth endure
            
            
               A man ryche full of ygnoraunce
               Whiche in tyme passed hath had honour
               In fortunes rychesse hauynge pleasaunce
               Is now downe dryuen by a sodayne shoure
               He neuer afore was vsed to laboure
               Thus after he hath lepte from hype to lowe
               By ydelnes fortune doth on hym loure
               He lyeth on the grounde &amp; none wyll hym knowe
            
            
               Of clothynge desyre thou no newe guyse
               But clothe thy selfe alway honestly
               Suffre not pryde vpon the to ryse
               But go ay meke and symplye
               And se thou be content onely
               So thou haue good whereon to Iyue
               Without gatherynge ouer largely
               Thou knowest not whan deth wyll arryue
            
            
               If it fortune that by necessyte
               Thou put thy selfe in the seruyce
               Of ony man of grete auctoryte
               Other lorde / marchaunt / or Iustyce
               Be not folysshe / flaterynge / nor nyse
               Nor yet slouthfull in ony wyse
               Se that thou flee fro echo vyce
               Leest he the vtterly despyse
            
            
               
               What euer he saye suffre mekely
               Fere hym with loue entyer and cordyall
               Serue hym bothe daye and nyght truly
               Saye of hym good ouer all
               Remembre loue is so specyall
               That without it no good is done
               Of his goodes be not lyberall
               And god shall paye the thy guerdon
            
            
               Thou ought of ryght to set thy herte
               With all thy myght and thy puyssaunce
               Thy maysters wyll for to aduerte
               And it to fulfyll without doutaunce
               So call thou vnto thy subuenaunce
               This prouerbe that I the lere
               Kepe it in thy remembraunce
               Loue goth neuer without fere
            
            
               Fere without loue may ryght well be
               We fere without loue them that vs menase
               But where as true loue is in certaynte
               It maketh men lyue euen by compas
               Therfore this loue se thou purchace
               And than thou shalte fall in his fauour soone
               Than thy rewarde to thy solace
               Shall be euen after as thou hast done
            
            
               If thou truly thy mayster serue
               He shall perceyue it within a whyle
               Than shalte thou haue that thou dost deserue
               With a a good name whiche none doth fyle
               But yf that thou do hym begyle
               He shall perceyue it at the last
               
                  
Than shall thy dedes thy name defyle
               So out of his hous he shall the cast
            
            
               Whan that thou arte thus departed
               Without his loue full folysshely
               As a seruaunt full yll aduerted
               Another mayster must thou seke truly
               Than shall other come pryuely
               And enquyre whether thou were yll or good
               If he saye yll that they may spye
               No man wyll haue the by the rode
            
            
               But yf that ony be in necessyte
               And can none other seruaunt fynde
               Than parauenture he wyll haue the
               And alway be to the vnkynde
               But yf he be a fole or blynde
               Elles wyll he none of thy seruyse
               Than shalte thou wander out with the wynde
               No mayster shall loue thy guyse
            
            
               If that thou wylte thy mayster please
               Thou must haue these thre propretees
               Fyrst must thou haue an asses eares
               With an hertes fete in all degrees
               An hogges snoute / and after these
               By suche meanes shall I declare
               That in tyme of aduersytees
               By them the better thou mayst fare
            
            
               By an asses eares this is ment
               That thou must harken hym aboute
               If thou se he be not content
               Saye nought but se thou hym doute
               
                  
Where as he is se thou not route
               What he cōmaundeth do gladly
               Than shall he not put the out
               If thou behaue the thus wysely
            
            
               By this hogges snoute mene I this
               What mete so euer to the is brought
               Though it be somwhat a mysse
               Take pacyence and saye thou nought
               Ete thou it not but it be ought
               Rather suffre thou a lytell penurye
               Another tyme better shall be bought
               For to amende that Iniurye
            
            
               Let thy snoute smell in eche place
               And specyally for to seke labour
               If thou so do in lytell space
               Thou shalte not fayle of his fauour
               Let thy pacyence ouercome his rygour
               And take good hede to his condycyon
               Se that thou alway hym honour
               Submyttynge the to his correccyon
            
            
               This sygnyfyeth the fete of an herte
               Thou must do thy mayster socour
               Bothe daye and nyght though thou sholde smerte
               To renne and go at euery houre
               Daye nor nyght spare no laboure
               Rather than he sholde haue domage
               Helpe hym in welth and in doloure
               If ony man do to hym outrage
            
            
               Thus reason lefte of her parlyament
               Than after tourned I me to rest
               
                  
And than came wysedome full dylygent
               A man prudent / dyscrete and honest
               Stondynge nere afore my brest
               I lyfted my heed vnto hym nere
               He made suche glose vpon the texte
               That I had meruayle hym to here
            
            
               
                  wysedome.
               
            
            
               
                  HE that hym ruleth by reason
               Geteth bothe ryches and honour
               Takynge vpon hym labour
               Euer hath he a ryche mansyon
               That is ruled by reason
            
            
               He puruayeth eche thynge in season
               As best is whan the tyme is grene
               After a storme the sonne doth shene
               That man is quyte of all dyscencyon
               Whiche is ruled by reason
            
            
               
               ¶Sothly my frende it is abusyon
               This caduke rychesse gretly to prayse
               To many a man it doth dysease
               He auoydeth sclaunder and detraccyon
               Whiche is ruled by reason
            
            
               ¶Ye knowe that within a lytell season
               Fortunes fauour many one procure
               But of her grace no man is sure
               Therfore he wyse is in conclusyon
               Whiche is ruled by reason
            
            
               I make townes &amp; castelles stronge of walles
               I make Iestes / storyes / and comedyes
               I made the seuen artes lyberalles
               With poemes and many tragydees
               I haue made many omelyes
               Whiche vnto man are full profytable
               Wherby he may auoyde all folyes
               And of his mynde be ferme and stable
            
            
               Whan reason on man hath dominacyon
               I promote hym vnto grete dygnyte
               I hate dyscorde / and adulacyon
               And loue peas / concorde / and equyte
               He that wyll lyue well in prospetyte
               Must haue reason to be his gouernour
               And than wyll I of myn owne lyberte
               Of very ryght be his protectour
            
            
               I am wysedome whiche haue knowlegynge
               Of good and yll without doutaunce
               But without reason I do no thynge
               For in her is so maner ygnoraunce
               
                  
Who me procureth I hym auaunce
               Wherfore sone yf thou wylte procede
               Be euer concent with suffysaunce
               Than shall I helpe the at thy nede
            
            
               Obey to reason what euer she saye
               With all thyn herte in lowlynesse
               Than by her grace shalte thou puruay
               Bothe worshyp honour and rychesse
               She helpeth men out of dystresse
               By her wytte and dyscrecyon
               If thou wylte come to parfytnesse
               Put the in her subgeccyon
            
            
               The auctour
               
                  ¶Thus wysedome vnto me spake
                  At reasons wyll and cōmaundement
                  Wherby grete comforte dyde I take
                  His reasons were so wyse and prudent
                  On whose saynge I fyxed myn entent
                  Concludynge vpon the way of payne
                  But for the tyme passed I was dolent
                  Whiche lost / coude not be called agayne
               
               
                  Than halfe faynt for watchynge excessyfe
                  I lyfted my hede vp lokynge me aboute
                  Lefte alone sore / sad / and pensyfe
                  Than was I agayne in doute
                  I fered them that afore wente out
                  Than sawe I one full of grauyte
                  Go compassynge my bedde aboute
                  With two seruauntes in his company
               
               
                  Whan he vnto me dyde appere
                  I thought he had ben some aduocate
                  
                     
His hode was furred with menyuere
                  His gowne of the same lyke his estate
                  He me behelde without ony debate
                  And sayd his name was dysceyte full slye
                  Of whome cometh many a mortall fate
                  His lytell varlet was named vsurye
               
               
                  Falshode was his seruauntes name
                  So knewe I by his fals vysage
                  The mayster cared no thynge for shame
                  Yet was he a comely personage
                  He me so flaterynge by his langage
                  Set hym downe there by my cheke
                  I meruaylled what was his vsage
                  Than thus vnto me he began to speke
               
               
                  
                     vsurye
                     falshode
                     deeeyte
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
               
               
                  
                  
                     SAy my frende wheron dost thou 
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  Thou doost thy selfe destroy wt thought
                  All thy wytte thou doost abuse
                  Thou studyest sore and all for nought
                  Reason hath the in her bondes cought
                  But let her go by my counsayle
                  Than of rychesse that thou hast sought
                  By my helpe thou shalte not fayle
               
               
                  Wysedome hath the aduertysed
                  To put the in reasones subgeccyon
                  A strawe man let her be dyspysed
                  And yelde the vnder my proteccyon
                  Who loueth reason lacketh dyscrecyon
                  Thou alway seest a man resonable
                  That fereth god Iustyce and punycyon
                  Hath neuer ought this is verytable
               
               
                  Reason that fole doth the counsayle
                  To lyue alway vertuously
                  Thou shalte haue hunger for thy trauayle
                  She byddeth the alway labour besely
                  But by my crafte I all sodaynly
                  Make hym this daye poore ryche to morowe
                  Therfore reason se thou defye
                  Let her and all hers go with sorowe
               
               
                  Reason with lytell is well content
                  She setteth no thynge by excesse
                  For to labour she is euer dylygent
                  Without gatherynge of grete rychesse
                  But I exalte men vnto noblesse
                  Sodaynlye by my arte subtyle
                  
                     
If ony wolde do me falsnesse
                  I take hym lyghtly in his owne wyle
               
               
                  But whyle that thou ensuest reason
                  Thou shalte neuer come to dygnyte
                  But poore and symple in euery season
                  As a bonde man had in captyuyte
                  Out of all maner hope lyberte
                  Oppressed shalte thou be ouer all
                  Euery daye well mayst thou se
                  That the grete dothe the small
               
               
                  Leue therfore reason by my counsayle
                  If thou wylte haue rychesse lyghtly
                  And yf that ony do the assayle
                  By my crafte I shall blere theyr eye
                  If that thou do entende to me
                  Thou shalte fynde that thou hast sought
                  I shall be at thy wyll redy
                  And whyle I lyue thou shalte lacke nought
               
               
                  If that thou wylte come to thyn ease
                  And haue golde at thy pleasour
                  Thy neyghbour se that thou dysease
                  With iniwaye / domage / force / and rygour
                  Let me dysceyte be as thy gouernour
                  Or elles my seruaunt vsurye
                  From one to other go euery houre
                  With a glosynge langage of flaterye
               
               
                  Let thy tunge be as a knyfe
                  With euery man therwith to rage
                  And where thou woldest haue no stryfe
                  Shewe thy selfe dyscrete and sage
                  
                     
Specyally where as is 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  Speke fayre tyll thou haue thy pray
                  But yet let not to do domage
                  To euery man whyle that thou may
               
               
                  Gouerne the euer with dyscepcyon
                  Care not for them that are in payne
                  At poore folke haue thou deryson
                  To gete good do the not refrayne
                  For to deceyue men set thy brayne
                  In theyr presence shewe them good chere
                  But of theyr hurte se thou be fayne
                  In theyr absence in eche manere
               
               
                  Speke fayre with falshode amonge
                  Shewe thy selfe meke and treatable
                  Take mony by ryght and wronge
                  Make the ryche man myserable
                  Gather togyder tychesse arrable
                  Fere neyther god ne the deuyll of hell
                  Of thy wordes be thou not stable
                  To ryche enuyous
                  to poore cruell
               
               
                  Paye nought in plede / nor in processe
                  Lene no thynge but vnto vsure
                  Se that thou the poore oppresse
                  Take theyr herytage and nouryture
                  Spare no thynge the to periure
                  And yf that ony do the repreue
                  By swerynge fast thy selfe assure
                  From his good hym to remeue
               
               
                  Thou shalte haue rychesse at the last
                  To lyue in grete prosperyte
                  
                     
If thou speke fayre and borowe fast
                  Faynynge thy selfe in charyte
                  For now a dayes in trouth and veryte
                  No man of the wyll haue count
                  Without clothynge of auctoryte
                  Lyke a knyght or a vycount
               
               
                  Kepe thy termes lyke thyn estate
                  With ermyne or sables furre thy gowne
                  If ony man haue enuye therate
                  By thy crafte tourne hym vp set downe
                  Thus mayst thou encrease thy renowne
                  And yf ony come with the to speke
                  Let thy man saye thou arte not in the towne
                  That he may come often the to seke
               
               
                  Let hym retourne the to enquyre
                  Be not asshamed for to lye
                  And what thynge that thou doost desyre
                  Be it good or badde do it lyghtly
                  Take no hede to well nor truly
                  So it be done take thou no thought
                  And I shall helpe the euer besely
                  So that at nede thou shalte lacke nought
               
               
                  To hym that is curteys and lowly
                  Euery man dare agaynsaye
                  But to one ryche gaye and hastye
                  Scant is one that dare saye nay
                  They wyll hym fere lyst that he fraye
                  Therfore eche man wyll hym forbere
                  Fayne felonye on them to laye
                  And than shall euery man the fere
               
               
                  
                  What euer thou doost worke by whle
                  Fyll thy stomacke full of falsenesse
                  Fro the reason do thou exyle
                  Of her nought cometh but dystresse
                  Refuse fayth take thou falsnesse
                  For suche is the worlde in this season
                  As thou mayst se by euydence expresse
                  They are all poore that folowe reason
               
               
                  Se thou be redy aye to take
                  Without gyuynge ought agayne
                  Thy promesse swerynge se thou forsake
                  Thus mayst thou haue rychesse sodayne
                  Let thy tunge folowe the comyn trayne
                  Of adulacyon couered with eloquence
                  Thus shall euery man be fayne
                  Vnto the for to do reuerence
               
               
                  If there come to the ony myschaunce
                  Care not it shall do the no grefe
                  Thou shalte haue for thy sustenaunce
                  Me and my men the to relefe
                  We shall defende the fro myschefe
                  And vnder the vmbre of veryte
                  Though he be neuer so fals a thefe
                  We shall ouercome hym by our subtylte
                  Loke what it is for to haue polyce
                  With crafte subtylte and practyke
                  By whiche meanes he that worketh slye
                  Casteth his encmye lyghtly in the dyke
               
               
                  Trewe wysedome se thou exyle
                  Whiche causeth thought and heuynes
                  
                     
Muse alway men to begyle
                  Let not to make fayre promesses
                  Euery daye here twenty masses
                  But haue at none of them deuocyon
                  And space thou not to take excesses
                  Of thefte / falshhode / and extorcyon
               
               
                  Byleue me for thyn auauntage
                  And refuse thou reason vtterly
                  Falshode my frende shall be thy page
                  Exaltynge the to rychesse myghtely
                  Whan thou arte in suche case truly
                  Euery man shall do the honour
                  And yf that ony do to the vylany
                  Se thou hym tame by thy rygour
               
               
                  Whyle that reason on the doth reyne
                  Thou shalte neuer come to worthynesse
                  But euer of pouerte complayne
                  Auoyde of myrth full of sadnesse
                  Thou shalte not nede to count expresse
                  Crownes / nobles / nor royalles
                  Thou shalte be voyde of all rychesse
                  And of degrees temporalles
               
               
                  Thou hast herde what I haue the tolde
                  This is my mynde and my counsayle
                  Wherfore on me se thou be bolde
                  And do here after for thyn auayle
                  Thus mayst thou come without trauayle
                  To rychesse so thou autoyde reason
                  If thou thus do without fayle
                  No more wyll I saye at this season
               
            
            
               
               The auctour.
               
                  ¶Whan this fals catyf had thus sayd
                  I was abstracte nere fro my mynde
                  His wordes made me sore afrayde
                  That I vnstable was as the wynde
                  Aboute me socour coude I none fynde
                  For fere I quaked / colde were my fete
                  I had in me as good a mynde
                  As hath a gose vpon a spete
               
               
                  That whiche reason dyde me counsayle
                  Was good holsome and reasonable
                  Dysceyte contrarye dyde me assayle
                  Shewynge me craftes dysceyuable
                  Thus was my mynde as varyable
                  As a fane strondynge in the wynde
                  In no purpose ferme nor stable
                  As now a dayes we may fynde
               
               
                  As I thus laye troubled full sore
                  Wysedome retourned to me agayne
                  More prudent than he was before
                  Whiche with his langage dyscrete &amp; playne
                  Exorted me for to refrayne
                  Me fro that thefe decepcyon
                  And than reason sholde me mayntayne
                  And thus sayd he in conclusyon
               
            
            
               ¶Wysedome.
               
                  
                  
                     wysedome.
                  
               
               
                  
                     DOst thou trust falshode or dysceyte
                  A poore man they wyll the dyffame
                  They loue but dyscorde and debate
                  They prayse the yll &amp; good doth blame
                  And they pryncypally are the same
                  Whiche bryngeth man to the pytte of hell
                  Trust in reason moost noble of fame
                  Whiche no thynge doth but that is well
               
               
                  That man is madde that leueth reason
                  Vnto dysceyte for to be lenynge
                  He that so doth after in brefe season
                  Ayenst hym selfe is murmurynge
                  Therfore be thou the withdrawynge
                  For of hym venym doth dyscende
                  
                     
Lyue after reason aboue all thnge
                  For who well lyueth well doth ende
               
               
                  How many dayly doost thou se
                  That leuynge reason them selfe assure
                  In falshode hauynge grete dygnyte
                  Fro poore men takynge theyr pasture
                  In this extorcyon they longe endure
                  By falshode getynge good mundayne
                  But whan that knowen is theyr nature
                  They he made poore by chaunce sodayne
               
               
                  We haue ofte sene grete wyndes blowe
                  And with a lytell rayne ouercome
                  So many men be brought full lowe
                  Before exalted by fals custome
                  Some rayed in scarlet / and other some
                  Arayed in golde / tyssue / and veluet
                  The one after vnto the swerde become
                  The other trayned vnto the gybet
               
               
                  If that they had trusted in reason
                  Leuynge falshode that dysceyuour
                  They sholde not haue had suche confusyon
                  But styll haue lyued in theyr honour
                  Reason that lady of grete valour
                  Doth nought that is to repreue
                  But dysceyte that fals traytour
                  His chefe subgertes doth myschefe
               
               
                  Syth that rychesse is so varyable
                  Wherfore take we therfore suche payne
                  Consyderynge our lyfe so vnstable
                  From deth we can vs not refrayne
                  
                     
The daye and houre is vncertayne
                  Therfore let vs lyue scarsely
                  For this is a thynge moost certayne
                  That fyrst or last we must nedes dye
               
               
                  Dysceyte in his fyrst begynnynge
                  To eche man well ynough doth sounde
                  But an euyll deth is his endynge
                  His scolers thus doth he confounde
                  But hym that in rychesse doth abounde
                  By reason goten eche man doth prayse
                  In dysceyte suche ende is founde
                  That euery man doth it dysprayse
               
               
                  By reason well mayst thou obtayne
                  Rychesse mundayne suffycyently
                  Who that hath none bydeth in payne
                  And ofte is entreted vncurteysly
                  Who hath not money and that largely
                  Were he as holy as was saynt poule
                  Where euer he goth contynually
                  He shall be taken but for a fole
               
               
                  Who that by reason doth good purchace
                  He lyueth therwith ryght merely
                  To his pleasour with grete solace
                  But yf that ony thrugh enuye
                  Wolde do hym wronge or iniurye
                  He must to god call for socoure
                  And than shall he full hastely
                  Hym ayde and helpe at euery houre
               
               
                  
                  Thus in my bedde sore troubled layde
                  Halfe releued was my courage
                  I toke good hede to that he sayd
                  For he was wyse dyscrete and sage
                  And thynkynge it for myn auauntage
                  Submytted me to the grace dyuyne
                  I knowe dysceyte by his outrage
                  Wolde me haue brought vnto ruyne
               
               
                  So purposed I fully to take
                  The counsayle of my lady reason
                  And dysceyte vtterly forsake
                  With his falshode and abusyon
                  Than beynge of this opynyon
                  Reason dyde vnto me appere
                  With her face bryght as the sonne
                  Arayed in a ryche manere
               
               
                  This lady was ryght gracyous
                  Pleasaunt curteys and amyable
                  On me lokynge with chere Ioyous
                  With a salutacyon ryght honourable
                  For this fals caytyfe myserable
                  Dysceyte with his seruauntes two
                  For all theyr chere abhomynable
                  At her comynge dyde fro me go
               
            
            
               Reason.
               
                  
                  
                     Reason
                  
               
               
                  
                     I Am gladde of the perfyte vyctorye
                  Whiche thou hast obteyned this nyght
                  It shall be to the ryght merytorye
                  In the hygh trone that is so lyght
                  Wysedome with his noble myght
                  Hath ben for the a good solycytour
                  But syth thou hast agreed to the ryght
                  Now shalte thou be my seruytour
               
               
                  I gyue the in cōmaundement
                  For to serue me ferme and faythfully
                  Haunt company wyse and prudent
                  So shalte thou haue ryches largely
                  I knowe that mannes mynde truly
                  By temptacyon full ofte doth vary
                  What I cōmaunde do thou gladly
                  And to me reason be not contrary
               
               
                  
                  What man that I do sustayne
                  I make clene from all maner vyce
                  But he that falshode doth mayntayne
                  Hateth concorde / peas / and Iustyce
                  God wyll that thou leue malyce
                  And vsurye in pryncypall
                  Whiche thou must do yf thou be wyse
                  With perfyte wyll and cordyall
               
               
                  I kepe men in theyr fraunchyse
                  I make the feble stronge and able
                  Dysceyte to yll men doth atyse
                  And doth nought that is profytable
                  Be therfore constaunt / ferme / and stable
                  Endue thy herte with forte and vertue
                  So shalte thou dysceyte full myserable
                  By godly wysedome strongly subdue
               
               
                  Good name is better than rychesse
                  The grace of god is full excellent
                  Trust not in the fayre promesse
                  Of dysceyte / ne his termes eloquent
                  Behaue thy selfe wyse and prudent
                  Be ruled by grace and pacyence
                  Bothe daye and nyght be dylygent
                  To gete the treasour of sapyence
               
               
                  And yf that god gyue the wysedome
                  Be not therof proude nor gloryous
                  But more symple se thou become
                  Thankynge hym with chere pyteous
                  Let thy mynde be euer vertuous
                  Submyttynge the to thy creatour
                  
                     
Whiche is so meke and gracyous
                  That he wyll be thy gouernour
               
               
                  With eche man be in charyte
                  Begynnynge at thy selfe fyrst of all
                  Let all thy dedes sounde vnto equyte
                  To poore men be thou lyberall
                  Men wyse and vertuous to the call
                  Whiche shall the kepe from all domage
                  Auoyde flaterers from thy hall
                  The to dysceyue is theyr vsage
               
               
                  With me abydeth none malycyous
                  Tyraunt traytour nor cowarde
                  But noble people wyse and vertuous
                  And peas as chefe bereth the standarde
                  Who casteth on me his regarde
                  Shall suerly scape bothe hole and sounde
                  Who in dysceyte hath his forwarde
                  Whan he moost trusteth is brought to grounde
               
               
                  If that by fortune thou haue aduersyte
                  Without noyse pacyently endure
                  God knoweth thy fragylyte
                  Fro poynt to poynt I the ensure
                  And yf dysceyte on the procure
                  Auoyde the cause the tyme and place
                  For without doute I the ensure
                  Dysceyte stynketh in goddes face
               
               
                  Where as is pryde myschefe is bye
                  Therfore of humylyte take comforte
                  Fals flaterye se thou defye
                  And tende no thynge to dyscomforte
                  
                     
Beware falshode and yll reporte
                  Auoyde robberye and all maner wronge
                  If thou do as I the exorte
                  In vertue shalte thou lyue full longe
               
               
                  Thou mayst gete yf thou folowe me
                  Rychesse mundayne in suffysaunce
                  Without falshode or iniquyte
                  Or doynge thy neyghbour ony greuaunce
                  Thy good and yll in a balaunce
                  Shall be weyed at the daye extreme
                  And than after thyn ordynaunce
                  The myghty Iuge shall the deme
               
               
                  Therfore sone by me thou may
                  Obteyne goodes mundayne &amp; eternall
                  Lyue without thought in lowe aray
                  Without ony payne corporall
                  Of this rychesse that is temporall
                  Thou mayst with Ioye haue here thy parte
                  And the hyghe glorye celestyall
                  Whan thy soule shall hens departe
               
               
                  Beholde what two grete benefyces
                  I ordayne for my seruytour
                  Where other fylled with malyces
                  By falshode lese all suche honours
                  Periurers theues and seductours
                  Saturate with synne and ordure
                  Lyue here in castelles and in toures
                  But theyr estate can not endure
               
               
                  Robbery / pykynge / and cauyllacyon
                  Thefte with falshode doth gouerne
                  
                     
That fals tyraunt decepcyon
                  And ledeth hym vnto the tauerne
                  Fals vsurye doth dyscerne
                  Theyr armes with his termes blasynge
                  With pryde of all vyce lanterne
                  Vnto theyr counseyll is lenynge
               
               
                  Suche as they haue but small conscyence
                  Wherfore se that thou them dyspyse
                  They refuse vertue / cunnynge / and scyence
                  Lenynge to ryotte suche is theyr guyse
                  Wherfore dere sone I the aduyse
                  Let not theyr power on the extende
                  For yf it do I the promyse
                  At tyborne wyll they make the ende
               
               
                  If falshode thrugh his wylynes
                  Exalte a man vnto honour
                  And after yf that his ryches
                  Be lost by some sodayne shoure
                  They to whome ye dyde rygour
                  Before wyll Ioye of his domage
                  They wyll be redy at euery houre
                  To hym to render his outrage
               
               
                  One vnto another wyll saye
                  Loke where he lyeth that was so ryche
                  His good yll goten is now awaye
                  And lo where he lyeth in the dyche
                  We thought that his ende wolde be suche
                  He hath lyued in welth to longe
                  His scabbed skyn lo now doth ytche
                  That he dare not come vs amonge
               
               
                  
                  Thus mayst thou se it is profytable
                  To lyue truly in this mortall lyfe
                  Getynge rychesse by meanes verytable
                  Syth it yll goten encreaseth stryfe
                  Who laboureth for rychesse excessyfe
                  Weneth to come vnto hye estate
                  But at the last he abydeth pensyfe
                  And euery good man doth hym hate
               
               
                  Leue therfore vyce and loue vertue
                  If thou wylte lyue in lybertye
                  And than men knowynge the good &amp; true
                  Wyll be gladde of thy company
                  But yet must thou haue humylyte
                  With pacyence &amp; concorde thy way to dresse
                  With fayth / trouth / and equyte
                  If thou wylte gete heuenly rychesse
               
               
                  Be thou symple of countenaunce
                  Speke fayre with chere amyable
                  Beware dysceyte and fere his launce
                  Be not of purpose varyable
                  It is a thynge abhomynable
                  Vnde an abyde of faythfulnesse
                  To haue a fals herte &amp; reprouable
                  Full of wrathe / yre / and falsnesse
               
               
                  Vnder the vmbre of veryte
                  Many one vseth fals dyscepcyon
                  Vsynge to speke ryght faythfully
                  But falshode is in theyr entencyon
                  Then thynke other to dysceyue by treason
                  But theyr selfe dysceyued do they fynde
                  
                     
But lerne this sone of me reason
                  God knoweth euery mannes mynde
               
               
                  God knoweth playne and clerely
                  Mannes mynde thought and courage
                  For he by his grace ineffably
                  Made hym lyke to his owne ymage
                  Sholdest thou not than do hym homage
                  Whiche hath the gyuen so grete a benefyce
                  Passynge all other in auauntage
                  That is the realme of paradyse
               
               
                  And after whan by dysobedyence
                  Man was dampned to be in payne
                  That hyghe lorde a lambe of innocence
                  With his owne blode brought hym agayne
                  This blessed lorde had no dysdayne
                  For to become a man mortall
                  And suffre deth with many a payne
                  To make vs fre that erst were thrall
               
               
                  This lorde chefe mayster of Iustyce
                  Shall kepe his Iugement fynall
                  Than some that there be moost of pryce
                  Shall than be myserablest of all
                  The poore and ryche shall be egall
                  Eche man shall haue lyke audyence
                  All mankynde there in generall
                  Shall there abyde this Iuges sentence
               
               
                  The aungelles shall theyr trumpettes blowe
                  Callynge men to the Iugement
                  Than euery man full well shall knowe
                  How that he here his lyfe hath spent
                  
                     
With an hygh voyce that lorde omnipotent
                  Shall call my seruauntes with hym to dwell
                  The badde all pensyf / woo / and dolent
                  Perpetually shall be dampned to hell
               
               
                  Now arte thou so that thou mayst chuse
                  The harde waye of saluacyon
                  Or elles yf thou wylte that abuse
                  Thou fyndest the waye of perdycyon
                  Do after me sone that am reason
                  To auoyde the fendes cruell bonde
                  And than that Iuge prynce of dyscressyon
                  Shall the set on his ryght honde
               
               
                  On the rayne bowe meke and propyce
                  On hye shall syt that myghty lorde
                  Hauynge on his one hande Iustyce
                  And on the other myserycorde
                  With them shall be peas and concorde
                  And veryte shall be there playne
                  This Iuge with these at one accorde
                  Shall Iuge the lygnage humayne
               
               
                  God shall my seruauntes vnto hym call
                  With meke chere and countenaunce
                  Vnto his hyghe sete emperyall
                  But after another maner of chaunce
                  He shall saye wordes of grete penaunce
                  To falshode seruauntes whiche shall be dum
                  Puttynge them to extreme vttraunce
                  Ite maledicti in ignem eternum
               
               
                  What shall theyr rychesse than auayle
                  Whan they shall haue but ryghtwysnesse
                  
                     
Eche man shall haue after his trauayle
                  The good lyght and the yll derkenesse
                  Some shall thynke it a daye of swetnesse
                  But other some with crye and yell
                  Shall thynke that daye of bytternesse
                  Dyscendynge downe to the pytte of hell
               
               
                  Therfore frende to thy selfe take hede
                  Renounce falshode with all iniquyte
                  This daye shall make the to haue drede
                  If thou it call to mynde truly
                  Who geteth rychesse here falsly
                  Of hell paynes shall haue his parte
                  And therfore hyther come am I
                  Fro this payne the to dyuerte
               
               
                  Therfore aryse and do me homage
                  With meke herte and entencyon
                  Refusynge falshode with his outrage
                  Makynge sucke prouysyon
                  That thou mayst lyue by dyscressyon
                  Than shall I make the to possede
                  A place in the heuenly regyon
                  Lo all my seruauntes hath suche mede
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  
                  
                     Reason
                  
               
               
                  
                     AFter that I herde my lady reason
                  So wysely speke full of prudence
                  I forsoke dysceyte / falshode &amp; treason
                  Yeldynge me vnto her magnyfycence
                  I kneled downe in her presence
                  Knowynge it for myn auauntage
                  With meke Ioue and obedyence
                  Vnto reason I made homage
               
               
                  Holdynge my handes vp to her grace
                  With lowe chere dyde I me present
                  There shewed I her all the case
                  How that I my lyfe had spent
                  
                     
This noble lady wyfe and prudent
                  Surely vnto me dyde promesse
                  So I wolde make amendement
                  To be my lady and maystresse
               
               
                  Than this lady approched nete
                  Of all other moost good and gracyous
                  With lowly countenaunce and chere
                  Of my helth gretly desyrous
                  And to her seruauntes neuer contraryous
                  Seynge her nere thus vnto her sayd I
                  Moost excellent lady moost good &amp; gloryous
                  To you wyll I me submytte gladly
               
               
                  Do ye with me what is your pleasour
                  I am euer redy gladde and dylygent
                  To do all thynge that may you honour
                  Neuer wyllynge more to be neglygent
                  To suche vertues / or counseyle prudent
                  I defye falshode with his subtyltees
                  To you obeyenge with hole entent
                  Bothe in welth and aduersytees
               
               
                  Reason was gladde in eche degre
                  Whan she herde me saye in this wyse
                  Than as syster vnto humylyte
                  Out of her chayre sone dyde she ryse
                  And kyssynge me she dyde promyse
                  Euer at my nede for to be kynde
                  Than sodaynly in a secrete wyse
                  This lady entred in to my mynde
               
               
                  Thus whyle that reason was my guyde
                  I gouerned me well and wysely
                  
                     
Dysceyte and falshode settynge asyde
                  With wretchednesse and vsurye
                  To byde with reason purposed I
                  As longe as god lent me my lyfe
                  Beynge in this purpose dyde I espye
                  Approche an olde man and his wyfe
               
               
                  Whan I them sawe I was content
                  They were so meke and gracyous
                  The mannes name was euydent
                  Good wyll / to none was contraryous
                  The womannes good herte to none enuyous
                  The whiche two had with them brought
                  A yonge chylde / pleasaunt / good and vertuous
                  In excellence passynge my thought
               
               
                  This chylde euer by good wyll stode
                  Vpon her hande to her lenynge
                  This was his name / lust to do good
                  As me thought vnto my semynge
                  These thre togyder on me smylynge
                  Approched nere and fyrst of all
                  Good herte began with this saynge
                  With meke countenaunce and lyberall
               
            
            
               ¶Good herte.
               
                  
                  
                     good herte
                     good wyll
                     lust to do good
                  
               
               
                  
                     SIth that reason resteth in the
                  Sone I shall not from the departe
                  The tyme &amp; season now mayst thou se
                  Whiche to the bryngeth the ease of hert
                  We shall fro the all yil dyuerte
                  Puttynge in to thy subgeccyon
                  Thy wyfe &amp; chyldren hole &amp; quarte
                  Whan age cometh the vpon
               
               
                  We thre togyder shall the conuay
                  Vnto a place full of all pleasaunce
                  There shall we shyfte for to puruay
                  To helpe the out of all greuaunce
                  This place is of grete cheuysaunce
                  Goten onely by waye of dylygence
                  The whiche place shall the auaunce
                  To the hye degre of excellence
               
               
                  
                  Folowe vs and we shall the brynge
                  In to the hye way whiche is ryght spacyous
                  The whiche way hath at his endynge
                  A fayre castell pleasaunt and sumptuous
                  In whiche remayneth a treasour precyous
                  That is worldly goodes full of noblesse
                  This place is called that is so beauteous
                  Labour / wherin remayneth rychesse
               
               
                  Reason ryght often hath the tolde
                  Of this castell whiche is so honourable
                  Passynge all castelles a thousande folde
                  And vnto mankynde moost profytable
                  But the waye is so varyable
                  That none can come thyder without vs thre
                  But he must haue some fortune myserable
                  And be compelled agayne to fle
               
               
                  Therfore who thyder doth hym dresse
                  Not hauynge vs in his companye
                  Shall neuer truly haue rychesse
                  His fortune is in grete dyffycultye
                  Many one cometh vnto dygnyte
                  By falshode / vsurye / and rapyne
                  But at the rnde symple pouertye
                  Kepeth them fallen in to ruyne
               
               
                  Syth thou applyest to reasons doctryne
                  I shall helpe the euer at thy nede
                  My wyfe shall vnto the enclyne
                  My sone shall helpe the for to spede
                  Do after vs and haue no drede
                  For we thre shall to the be kynde
                  
                     
Whan thou hast laboured / for thy mede
                  If thou well do thou shalte well fynde
               
               
                  Lust to do good is now redy
                  Vnto this place the to conuay
                  Therfore aryse and come lyghtly
                  And we shall well for the puruay
                  Reason her seruauntes helpeth alway
                  Whiche hath vs hyther vnto the brought
                  Ryse vp let vs go without delay
                  For after grete rest ofte cometh thought
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  ¶I accorded vnto them lyghtly
                  Auoyde of slouth and neglygence
                  With them thyder to go gladly
                  Vnto this place chefe of dylygence
                  Whiche of all honour hath preemynence
                  Eche man for to helpe at his nede
                  Than thought I for to recompence
                  The tyme loste / and thyder to spede
               
               
                  But I tolde them I knewe no thynge
                  Of dylygence / nor yet of besynesse
                  Good herte sayd / by our techynge
                  Thou shalte knowe the way expresse
                  Thou mayst bothe saye &amp; thynke doutlesse
                  Whyle we thre are thy conductours
                  That thou arte voyde of heuynesse
                  And sure of all worldly honours
               
               
                  Awake and put the in apparayle
                  To moche slepe hurteth man certayne
                  In this waye must thou fore trauayle
                  For reason so doth it ordayne
                  
                     
For what man that taketh payne
                  On hym with trauayle and abstynence
                  To rychesse nedes must attayne
                  Therfore aryse and go we hens
               
               
                  Go sone thou must bestowe thy tyme
                  In other wyse than thou hast done
                  Let not to labour for no cryme
                  Lettynge thy dedes ay sounde to reason
                  And as for me I me abandon
                  With my husbande on the to wayte
                  Vnto this castell and noble mansyon
                  Wherin is rychesse without dysceyte
               
               
                  Who other begyleth hym selfe dysceyueth
                  Rychesse yll goten cometh to yll ende
                  Who in this castell falshode conceyueth
                  Shall not his power ferre extende
                  But after deth yf thou wylte ascende
                  Take me and trauayle to be thy guyde
                  Whiche in this castell shall the defende
                  By our meanes in euery tyde.
               
            
            
               ¶Lust to do good.
               
                  ¶Do my faders cōmaundement
                  If thou truly wolde haue rychesse
                  And to my moder be dylygent
                  In that thou mayst with lowlynesse
                  And I shall do my wyll and besynesse
                  Vnto my power the to sustayne
                  Wherfore auoyde thou slouthfulnesse
                  And vs to folowe take on the payne
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  
                  
                     good herte
                     good wyll
                     Lust to do good
                  
               
               
                  
                     THus I hauynge grete delyte
                  To here them speke so wysely
                  Lepte fro my bed without respyte
                  And made me redy hastely
                  Good wyll wente full redely
                  To lyght a candell at myn instaunce
                  Whiche as she wente songe so merely
                  That her to here I had pleasaunce
               
               
                  I toke my clothes vnto me necessarye
                  And made me redy at theyr instaunce
                  Lust to do good full gladly
                  To bere the candell had grete pleasaunce.
                  Than wente they forth all in ordynaunce
                  As folke replenysshed with mekenesse
                  That to beholde theyr countenaunce
                  My herte was fylled with gladnesse
               
               
                  
                  Lust to do good wente alwaye
                  Before berynge the candel
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     yght
                  Good 
                        •
                     yll wente nexte in tayre araye
                  And than good herte I folowed ryght
                  Sothly it was a pleasaunt syght
                  To se togyder so meke a company
                  I had not suche sorowe all the nyght
                  As I had than myrth and melodye
               
               
                  
                     good herte
                     good wyll
                     besinesse.
                  
               
               
                  
                     THan entred we in to the waye
                  Of grete payne called dylygence
                  Without restynge I wente alwaye
                  There founde I no resystence
                  These thre were euer in my presence
                  For the waye was vnknowen to me
                  I hasted me vnder theyr defence
                  That I myght there the sooner be
               
               
                  
                  Thus wente we forth a lytell whyle
                  Of the waye was I ygnoraunt
                  My thre felawes dyde on me smyle
                  On me beholdynge with glad semblaunt
                  Than sawe I this castell fayre &amp; pleasaunt
                  Moost ryche / stronge and sumptuous
                  Whan I it sawe so resplendaunt
                  Sothly of herte I was full Ioyous
               
               
                  Vnto the gate whan I was nye
                  I wolde haue entred without sauegarde
                  But the porter resysted me
                  Beholdynge me with chere frowarde
                  Of that castell he kepte the garde
                  His wyfe was euer in his presence
                  Thynkest thou to entre he sayd cowarde
                  Not hauynge our loue nor our lycence
               
            
            
               ¶Besynesse.
               
                  ¶Thynkest thou to entre without our leue
                  In to this castell chefe grounde to rychesse
                  Nay nay thou must hens remeue
                  None entreth here but by mekenesse
                  My wyfe Cure and I besynesse
                  Haue suche offyce in this castell
                  To vs obeyeth bothe more and lesse
                  That hath intencyon therin to dwell
               
               
                  By the fayre path of dylygence
                  Thou arte come hyder as I byleue
                  Yet mayst thou not here haue resydence
                  Without our loue fauour and leue
                  
                     
Thou mayst not entre therfore remeue
                  For with the am I not content
                  Auoyde or elles I shall the greue
                  His wyfe than sayd incontynent
               
            
            
               ¶Cure.
               
                  ¶Gentyll husbonde holde hym excused
                  He wyll obey vnto your cōmaundement
                  Let not his mekenesse be refused
                  He wyll nought without your assent
                  I knowe hym wyse / dyscrete / &amp; prudent
                  He wyll gladly do you homage
                  So it wyll please you be content
                  Of fauour to graunt hym passage
               
               
                  Cōmaunde hym what so euer ye please
                  And he shall do it without fallace
                  He purposeth not you to dysplease
                  But hym submytteth vnto your grace
                  Prayenge that he may haue place
                  In to this castell for to go
                  He hath our fauour to purchace
                  Good herte and good wyll also
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  ¶ Than besynesse as a man full kynde
                  Sayd / syth thou hast suche socour
                  My fauour redy shalte thou fynde
                  The for to helpe at euery houre
                  To here hym speke I had pleasoure
                  Than sayd he / syth thou hast reason
                  Thou shalte not fayle of grete honoure
                  With welth and rychesse in brefe season
               
            
            
               ¶Besynesse.
               
                  
                  
                     The castell of laboure.
                     cure
                     besines
                  
               
               
                  
                     I That called am besynesse
                  Vnto man rychesse do procure
                  My wyfe also in all dystresse
                  Doth man of her helpe assure
                  This place is called by droyture
                  The excellent castell of labour
                  If thou here be I the ensure
                  Thou must be besye in euery houre
               
               
                  Syth thou arte in our subgeccyon
                  Trust well thou shalte come to rychesse
                  For whyle in thy mynde abydeth reason
                  By no meane cannest thou haue skarsnesse
                  I shall helpe the in all besynesse
                  In this castell to ensue the trayne
                  
                     
The capytayne therof and the maystresse
                  Are called by name trauayle and payne
               
               
                  Thou shalte in this place haue moche ad.
                  Mannes good wyll for to deserue
                  Thou shalte skant fynde the meane therto
                  The capytayne is so yll to serue
                  Vnneth his byddynge canst thou obserue
                  Without it be well done and a pace
                  But in goodnesse thou the styll preserue
                  Thou shalte be soone out of theyr grace
               
               
                  Thus do I the afore aduerte
                  Of the grete payne that thou shalte fynde
                  Lest that after it sholde greue thy herte
                  Therfore on wysedome set thy mynde
                  The capytayne is somwhat vnkynde
                  Whiche shall do to the grete rygour
                  Eche thynge tourneth as the wynde
                  Within this castell of labour
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  ¶All that shall do me none yll
                  I shall assaye them for to please
                  I haue founde good herte and good wyll
                  With lust to do good whiche shall me case
                  I trust no man for to dysplease
                  Whyle I of them do take counsayle
                  I wyll not let for no dysease
                  To go in to this castell of trauayle
               
               
                  
                  
                     cure.
                     besinesse
                  
               
               
                  
                     THan besynesse &amp; cure brought me in to
                  This castell / ample / and spacyous
                  Shewynge me men and women also
                  Sore workynge and none ocyous
                  Thē to beholde was a thȳge meruaylous
                  Bothe yonge and olde of euery facultye
                  To labour was there none contraryous
                  Eche one wolde afore his felawe be
               
               
                  They smote with hambers that were stronge
                  That to beholde I had grete wonder
                  Suche a noyse was them amonge
                  That it sounded lyke the thunder
                  Some were aboue and some were vnder
                  In theyr shertes labourynge for hete
                  Some dyde peces breke in sunder
                  Some agayne them togyder bete
               
               
                  
                  To beholde them I had delyte
                  Seynge them worke so lustely
                  That to labour I had appetyte
                  Cure and besynesse that dydespye
                  Whiche sayd vnto me shortly
                  That yf I coude labour well
                  They wolde gete me lycence gladly
                  In that castell for to dwell
               
               
                  Than to them answered I certayne
                  That to labour I was content
                  Than spake they to the capytayne
                  Requyrynge hym for to assent
                  He graunted me a place present
                  Conuenyent for my degre
                  There promysed I for to be dylygent
                  So that in theyr fauour I myght be
               
               
                  I set me downe vnto labour
                  With besynesse and parfyte dylygence
                  Trustynge therby to haue honour
                  Cure and besynesse were not thens
                  I was ryght glad of theyr presence
                  For they taught me how I sholde do
                  Vnto them I gaue audyence
                  And what they sayd I agreed therto
               
               
                  Than came the wyfe of the capytayne
                  Goynge here and there trottynge
                  They tolde me that her name was payne
                  Eche mannes labour vysytynge
                  Her handes and her forehede swetynge
                  She taryed nomore in ony place
                  
                     
Than doth a pursuyuaunt rydynge
                  Whan he wolde purchace some grace
               
               
                  Somtyme in her smocke rennynge fast
                  No thynge tendynge to rest nor ease
                  She ran styll whyle her breth wolde last
                  Not sparynge for no dysease
                  She was dylygent eche man to please
                  And me behelde approchynge nere
                  She sayd syr porter ye me dysplease
                  For bryngynge of this straunger here
               
            
            
               ¶Payne.
               
                  Syr besynesse that are porter
                  Of this castell shewe me playne
                  Who hath brought hyther this straunger
                  I sawe hym neuer afore certayne
                  Cometh he fro fraunce or fro brytayne
                  I must knowe his cause and his entent
                  He must submytte hym vnto my payne
                  Or elles in vayne his tyme is spent
               
            
            
               ¶Besynesse.
               
                  ¶My lady payne haue ye no doute
                  For hyther is he come truly
                  With good herte and good wyll hym aboute
                  Whiche hyther hath hym brough besely
                  Lust to do good is to hym nye
                  Whiche is a chylde ryght honourable
                  Ye shall fynde hym to you redy
                  Humble of herte and seruysable
               
            
            
               ¶Cure.
               
                  ¶My husbonde and I loue hym ryght well
                  We shall helpe hym at euery nede
                  
                     
Ye shall not nede hym 
                        ••
                     ght to tell
                  Therfore my lady haue ye no drede
                  Euen as he doth gyue hym his mede
                  And my husbonde shall be his borowe
                  That in his labour he shall spede
                  And neyther spare for payne nor sorowe
               
            
            
               ¶Payne:
               
                  
                     payne
                     Cure
                  
               
               
                  YE saye bothe well and wysely
                  I knowe not yet how he wyll preue
                  For many one be soone wery
                  Of labour whan it doth them greue
                  But suche sothly be to repreue
                  But we shall soone se what labour
                  He can do / or that he remeue
                  To come to rychesse and honour
               
            
            
               
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  ¶Than payne to me approched nere
                  Byddynge me labour dylygently
                  And that I sholde in eche manere
                  Do my besynesse well and wysely
                  Not sparynge my body nor my bones
                  And he that dyde not so truly
                  Sholde auoyde that place at ones
               
               
                  I tolde her that I had desyre
                  To worke fast without fayne
                  And for to folowe her pleasyre
                  So that she sholde not complayne
                  Saynge I trusted to obtayne
                  By my labour welth and rychesse
                  And that I sholde my setfe constrayne
                  To be nere Cure / and Besynesse
               
            
            
               ¶Payne.
               
                  ¶That is answered by good moyen
                  Whan trauayle my husbonde shall you se
                  The whiche is feble and auncyen
                  Your worke and labour shall he ouerse
                  Of hym rewarded shall ye be
                  After your worke and your labour
                  And in the meane tyme ye shall haue me
                  Alway redy at your socour
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  ¶Than began I to labour fast
                  Employenge theron pleasure &amp; myght
                  Contynuenge whyle the nyght dyde last
                  Than in the mornynge appered lyght
                  
                     
In at a wyndowe that was bryght
                  Than blewe I my candellout
                  Labourynge styll with all my myght
                  As other that were me aboute
               
               
                  Styll to labour I dyde me cast
                  By suffraunce of the grace dyuyne
                  Vnto the tyme of the brekefast
                  Where we had neyther ale ne wyne
                  They myght not tary for to dyne
                  So sure on labour was theyr purpose
                  Tyll labour caused them to declyne
                  By payne constrayned so vp they rose
               
               
                  They were all homely as companyons
                  Theyr labour gaue them an appetyt reall
                  Some ete garlyke / some ete onyons
                  Suche seruyce was amonge them all
                  Browne brede to them was cordyall
                  Wetynge it in the water clere
                  Drynkynge of the fountayne clere as crystall
                  They had no scorne of this manere
               
               
                  There was neyther befe ne moton
                  To ete whan hunger dyde them assayle
                  Suche is the maner in this season
                  Some be rewarded yll theyr trauayle
                  They wrought in peas and in batayle
                  Some etynge and labourynge bothe at ones
                  Not sparynge theyr body without fayle
                  As chefe labourers for the nones
               
               
                  
                  
               
               
                  
                     WHan that I sawe theyr condycyon
                  So prone to labour and besynesse
                  I set myn hole and ferme entencyon
                  By suche labour to gete rychesse
                  Than vpon me came fayntnesse
                  That I had lust to refresshe nature
                  Whan they me sawe in suche dystresse
                  I lacked no brede I you ensure
               
               
                  I wolde be of theyr company
                  And takynge this brede with good wyll
                  I therof bote ryght merely
                  Styll workynge not thynkynge yll
                  I had no scorne me for to fyll
                  With this brede but theron bote
                  
                     
And after with chere meke and styll
                  With fayre water I wasshed my throte
               
               
                  I fylled my bely fayre and well
                  With this fayre brede made of rye
                  Drynkynge alway at the well
                  And yet styll wrought I merely
                  I was as well at ease truly
                  As though I had had all deyntees
                  In the worlde / for certaynly
                  To moche is nought in all degrees
               
               
                  Shortly to saye I was as full
                  As was conuenyent to nature
                  For excesse maketh the mynde dull
                  I reporte me to besynesse and cure
                  For often tymes man doth murmure
                  Whan he is full of mete and wyne
                  To all vyce prone I the ensure
                  Excludynge hym from the grace dyuyne
               
               
                  Whan I was thus refresshed well
                  I drewe me to my werke agayne
                  Good herte and good wyll dyde me tell
                  How I sholde do also certayne
                  Lust to do good dyde me mayntayne
                  Thus drewe I me vnto besynesse
                  I spared neyther trauayle nor payne
                  Without falshode to gete rychesse
               
               
                  
                  
                     Cure
                     Besynes
                     good hert
                     good wyll
                     lust to do good
                  
               
               
                  
                     CVre and charge dyde me beholde
                  Cōmaundynge me to labour fast
                  And tolde me suerly that they wolde
                  Rewarde me truly at the last
                  So laboured I tyll the daye was past
                  And as I laboured songe I merely
                  Tyll hesperus cloudes the daye ouercast
                  And that the nyght approched nye
               
               
                  Than cure vnbyden wente a p
                        •
                     ce
                  And lyghtly lyghted a candell
                  She set it by my workynge place
                  And many newe poyntes to me dyde tell
                  She sayd who bydeth in this castell
                  After the cōmaundement of reason
                  Must worke vnto the curfue knell
                  Consyderynge the tyme and season
               
               
                  
                  At her byddynge I wrought styll fast
                  Hauynge therin delyte and pleasoure
                  Tyll that the bell range at the last
                  Whiche was a conuenyent houre
                  Than hunger came with his rygour
                  Whiche cruelty dyde me assayle
                  With that sawe I come from a toure
                  The capytayne called trauayle
               
               
                  
                     trauayle
                  
               
               
                  
                     FRende yu arte welcome vnto this place
                  For thy labour true and dylygent
                  Whiche hath brought the in to my grace
                  Therfore shal I gyue ye ryches ꝑmanent
                  So after that thy youthe is spent
                  I shall the promyse and behest
                  
                     
After thy labour incontynent
                  Thou shalte come to the hous of rest
               
               
                  Thou shalte haue rest at thy desyre
                  After thy payne and trybulacyon
                  Thou shalte syt merely by the fyre
                  After that thy worke is done
                  There shalte thou fynde consolacyon
                  After thy payne and thy trauayle
                  Thus shalte thou fynde in conclusyon
                  After pouerte ryche apparayle
               
               
                  And therfore at one worde shortly
                  Now do as thou thynkest best
                  For with good wyll the leue gyne I
                  For to go home vnto thy rest
                  And thy prayer and thy request
                  I trauayle shall vnto the promesse
                  Go now thou shalte haue my behest
                  After labour / that is rychesse
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  ¶Than toke I leue of trauayle
                  Goynge to rest full of gladnesse
                  Than with hye voyce withouten fayle
                  I called the porter named besynesse
                  Than to the gates I dyde me dresse
                  The whiche were shytte than had I doute
                  Yet shewed I the porter suche mekenesse
                  Than he agreed to let me out
               
               
                  
                  
                     Besynes
                     Cure.
                  
               
               
                  
                     BEsynesse and cure his wyfe
                  Let me out at the gate mekely
                  Alway me warnynge for brede of stryfe
                  On the mo
                        •
                     nynge to ryse erly
                  My labour for to fynysshe parfytly
                  Saynge all that I had done was nought
                  Without it were ended lyghtly
                  Wherfore theron set thy thought
               
               
                  He sayd in the castell of rychesse
                  No man can haue ony audyence
                  Whyle he soiourneth with ydelnesse
                  The capytayne hath gyuen that sentence
                  But by the waye of dylygence
                  One may ryght well obteyne this place
                  
                     
Here mayst thou se in thy presence
                  By what hardnesse thou fell in grace
               
               
                  In labour must thou haue perseueraunce
                  Auoydynge grete test that is so daungerous
                  Whiche bryngeth wyse men in to ygnoraunce
                  And to rychesse is ryght contraryous
                  Auoyde slouth whiche is so odyous
                  That of hym cometh nought but pouerte
                  Aboue all to falshode be contraryous
                  Despysynge his goodes full of iniquyte
               
               
                  If thou hym loue sone I ensure the
                  Of my worde mayst thou be certayne
                  That thou offendest the deite
                  Of our lorde and deseruest payne
                  Eternall / therfore the refrayne
                  Fro this falshode in eche degre
                  And yf that slouth vpon the fayne
                  As poore as Iob was shalte thou be
               
               
                  Without rest no man may lyue
                  For it is accordynge to trauayle
                  But yf in rychesse yf thou wystē preue
                  Rest not to moche by my counsayle
                  Remembre this lesson se thou not fayle
                  And to the entent thou forsake not this lawe
                  Not it forgettynge / for thyn auayle
                  By thyn eare I shall the drawe
               
            
            
               ¶Cure.
               
                  My frende one can not aye endure
                  For to labour to his auauntage
                  
                     
Therfore se thou thy selfe assure
                  To labour fast in thy yonge age
                  Infyre thy mynde and thy courage
                  On reason and thou shalte haue rychesse
                  By ydelnesse thou doost outrage
                  Bothe to the and all thy doutlesse
               
            
            
               ¶The auctour.
               
                  ¶Than drewe she myn ere agayne
                  As cure had done before doutlesse
                  And than vanysshed away certayne
                  Leuynge me there full of fayntnesse
                  Procedynge of my labour and besynesse
                  Thus seynge them gone I thought it best
                  To refresshe nature without excesse
                  And so drewe me to the hous of rest
               
               
                  I sawe rest whiche dyde me abyde
                  Within his hous withouten blame
                  And my wyfe on the other syde
                  Dressed my souper without dyffame
                  There rested I in goddes name
                  Famylyarly not as a straunger
                  Thankynge god of immortall fame
                  That I escaped was that daunger
               
               
                  
                  
                     The house of rest
                  
               
               
                  
                     VNto the table I wente that tyde
                  Entendynge to soupe without outrage
                  My wyfe sate on the other syde
                  After my custome and olde vsage
                  There had we brede wyne &amp; potage
                  And of flesshe a small ꝓytaunce
                  Without to ony hurte or domage
                  We souped togyder at our pleasaunce
               
               
                  My wyfe voyded the table clene
                  And vnto me approched nere
                  Than on my shulder dyde she lene
                  After her custome and manere
                  There tolde I her of the daungere
                  Whiche I was in the nyght before
                  How that she slepte with mery chere
                  The whyle that I was troubled sore
               
               
                  
                  I tolde her that in all my lyfe
                  I had not so grete peruersyte
                  Now in pleasure and now in stryfe
                  Tourmented fyersly felte I me
                  For fals Nede / and Necessyte
                  With Pouerte / &amp; her felawe Dystresse
                  Thought and heuynes with cruelte
                  Laye on my bedde me to opresse
               
               
                  Dyscomforte and Dysesperaunce
                  Laye vpon me with theyr treason
                  Redy to brynge me to myschaunce
                  Or in the waye of perdycyon
                  That had not ben my lady reason
                  Whiche me enfourmed to myn auauntage
                  They had brought me vnto confusyon
                  Or done to me some grete outrage
               
               
                  Wysedome dyde gretly me profyte
                  For I haunted his companye
                  Whiche by his meanes made me quyte
                  Of falshode / dysceyte / and vsurye
                  Whiche thre by theyr polecye
                  Had me nere brought to confusyon
                  But after agayne comforte had I
                  Of that wyse lady called reason
               
               
                  To whome I haue made homage
                  For the of her owne beneuolence
                  Hath gyuen me at brefe langage
                  Good herte and good wyll for my defence
                  Whiche haue a chylde ay in my presence
                  Lust to do good named is he.
                  
                     
Redy to helpe me in all indygence
                  Out of payne and peruersyte
               
               
                  We wente vnto the castell of labour
                  Where was many an artyfycer
                  Cure stode at the gate that houre
                  Besynesse her husbonde was porter
                  They receyued me with good chere
                  Trauayle was theyr capytayne
                  His wyfes name was called payne
               
               
                  There wrought I all daye &amp; nyght certayne
                  With fre wyll and glad pleasaunce
                  To morowe must I retourne agayne
                  To this castell of fayre ordynaunce
                  There founde I but small pytaunce
                  But euery man after his degre
                  After his labour had his fe
               
               
                  And therfore my welbeloued wyfe
                  Consyder the payne and the trauayle
                  Whiche whyle ye slepte without stryfe
                  Ryght cruelly dyde me assayle
                  But now am I well without fayle
                  Syth I haue escaped this daungere
                  And in your presence may appere
               
               
                  My wyfe therof cared no thynge
                  But leughe me to derysyon
                  She scorned me and my talkynge
                  For were it wynnynge or perdycyon
                  It was to her all one conclusyon
                  For so she were serued at her desyre
                  She cared not yf I laye in the myre
               
               
                  
                  She called me fole and cared nought
                  And was nere redy with me to fyght
                  She swore by god that her dere bought
                  She wolde make me remembre that nyght
                  Therfore I wente to bedde euen ryght
                  For the thyre foted stole fore fered I
                  To that with a woman it is but foly
               
               
                  A man sholde take no hede at all
                  To what someuer a woman saye
                  Of her tunge she is lyberall
                  It is no wysedome her to denay
                  In peas may he be by no way
                  That wolde styll a woman / it is contrary
                  She is a publyke and comyn secretary
               
               
                  Who euer he be that hath a wyfe
                  Had nede for to haue paryence
                  Or elles must he lyue alway in stryse
                  Though she be bounde to obedyence
                  Yet doth she after her owne sentence
                  I dare no more saye for drede of blame
                  That man is happy that one can tame
               
               
                  On this poynt I made we redy
                  And so wente to my bedde full ryght
                  Where I slepte styll and merely
                  Cyll foure of the clocke after mydnyght
                  Than vp I rose by the candell lyght
                  Thynkynge on cure and besynesse
                  And to my worke soone byde I me dresse
               
               
                  Ay prayenge god by his ordynaunce
                  That yf I may not obtayne rychesse
                  
                     
That I may purchace suffysaunce
                  Whiche is my lady and my maysteresse
                  To enfourme me to lyue in symplenesse
                  So that after this lyse mortall
                  I may reioyse the realme eternall
               
            
            
               ¶Actoris excusatio.
               
                  GO forth small treatyse &amp; humbly the present
                  Vnto the reders as indygne of audyence
                  Exortynge them with meke and lowe entent
                  To this rude langage to gyue none aduertence
                  For many one hath parfyte dylygence
                  Whiche by no meane his mynde can expresse
                  The cause therof is lacke of eloquence
                  Whiche now is caduke by meane of slouthfulnesse
               
               
                  The yonge chylde is not all parfyte
                  To renue whan he can neyther crepe nor go
                  But whan he begynneth he hath grete delyte
                  In his newe scyence / wherfore he hath grete wo
                  Endurynge falles with many paynes mo
                  Thus suche payne so longe doth he endure
                  And to hym selfe he entendeth so
                  That of his fete he is parfyte and sure
               
               
                  So certaynly in suche case am I
                  Somwhat assayenge yf I can ensue
                  The steppes of them the whiche craftely
                  All vyce of wrytynge vtterly eschue
                  But ygnoraunce ryght ofte doth me subdue
                  And often I fall for lacke of exercyse
                  
                     
This rude langage so on me both renewe
                  That I agayne vnnethes may aryse
               
               
                  The cause why I folowe not these oratours
                  Is for lacke of intellygence
                  And that I haue not smelled of the floures
                  Spryngynge in the gardyn of parfyte eloquence
                  Wherfore with humble and meke obedyence
                  I submytte me to the correccyon
                  Of them whome minerua with her scyence
                  Hath endued this is my conclusyon
               
            
         
      
      
         
            ¶Thus endeth the castell of labour
wherin is rychesse / vertue / &amp; honour.
Enprynted at London in Fletestrete
in the sygne of the sonne. by Wynkyn
de worde. Anno dnī. M.CCCCC.vi.
            
         
      
   

