
   
      
         
            The honour of Christian churches and the necessitie of frequenting of divine service and publike prayers in them. Delivered in a sermon at VVite-Hall before the Kings most excellent Majestie on the eight day of December last being Sunday, by Walter Bancanquall ...
            Balcanquhall, Walter, 1586?-1645.
         
         
            
               1633
            
         
         Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02233
            STC 1237
            ESTC S100539
            99836376
            99836376
            644
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02233)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 644)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 693:04)
         
         
            
               
                  The honour of Christian churches and the necessitie of frequenting of divine service and publike prayers in them. Delivered in a sermon at VVite-Hall before the Kings most excellent Majestie on the eight day of December last being Sunday, by Walter Bancanquall ...
                  Balcanquhall, Walter, 1586?-1645.
               
               [2], 29, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by George Miller for Robert Allot at the blacke Beare in Pauls Church-yard,
                  London :
                  1633.
               
               
                  On Matthew XXI, 13.
                  Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-09
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-10
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2004-10
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
HONOUR
OF CHRISTIAN
CHVRCHES;
AND
THE NECESSITIE OF
frequenting of Divine Service and
Publike Prayers in them. Delivered in a Sermon at White-Hall
before the Kings most excellent Majestie on the
eight day of December last being Sunday, BY WALTER BALCANQVALL Doctor of
Divinity and Deane of Rochester being then in
his ordinarie attendance. And now published by his Majesties
speciall commandement.
            
               LONDON,
Printed by George Miller for Robert Allot at the blacke
Beare in Pauls Church-yard. 1633.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               MATH. 21. Ver. 13.
               It is written, my house shalbe called the
house of prayer, but you have made it a
den of theeves.
            
            
               THe occasion of which words
was briefly this; Kings at the
first entry unto their Raignes
do use to begin with the reformation
of abuses crept into
the Church and Service of
God: so did David, Iosias, Ezekiah
before Christ, so did the
Christian Emperours and Princes
after Christ, as appeareth in their first rescripts: so
do yet all Christian Kings, their first Acts of State or
Parliament take rise at the threshold of the Sanctuarie,
and begin with confirmation, or (if need be) reformation
of the Church: Now the Sonne of God in this
Chapter making his solemne entrie like a King into
Hierusalem, and so received by the people, he first getteth
him to the Temple, and finding it most lewdly
profaned both by secular and spirituall or Simoniacall

negotiation he falleth upon them with both hands: as a
King with his secular arme he whippeth out the profaners;
as a Priest he useth the spirituall arme, It is written:
and these words, It is written, be all the words of
this text, which may properly be said to be Christs
own words, the rest are but cited by him from others;
the first sentence my house shall be called the house of prayer,
from Isaiah 56. 7. the other, but you have made it a den of
theeves, from Iere. 7. 11. But both of them so rehearsed
and withall applied by him, that they are now become
his own, for as well quem benè, as quem malè dum recitas,
incipit esse tuus.
            
            And as these two sentences when they were first
spoken of by these two Prophets, were a Prophesie of
Christ his times, and the iniquitie of the Iewes in his
time fulfilled them, so as they are now rehearsed by
Christ, they seeme to have beene a Prophesie of our
times, which have fulfilled them by repeating the same
profanations: In which regard I should not perhaps
divide these words much amisse, if I should divide
them into an Appropriation, and an Impropriation: an
Appropriation, or the proper use for which God appointed
his Temple, my house shalbe called the house of
prayer; an Impropriation, or the abuse of the Temple,
whereby men disappoint God of his appointment, but
you have made it a den of theeves: And this division is
much about one with our Proverbe, wheresoever God
hath a Church the Divell hath a Chappell; my house
shall be called the house of prayer, there is Gods Church;
but you have made it a den of theeves, there the Divell goeth
about presently to turne it into his Chappell.
            Or these words being spoken of the Materiall Temple
of Hierusalem may be divided as in some sort that

Temple might have beene divided: amongst diverse
gates in the Temple there were these two, afore-gate
and a backe-gate, the fore-gate at which the people entred
called the Beautifull gate, where the diseased lay
and begged almes, Acts 3. 2. The backe-gate called
Shallecheth or the dung-gate, out of which was carried
all the filth or sulledge of the Temple: now betweene
these two gates stood the Temple it selfe; so here, first
you have the preface or fore-gate to the text, it is written;
and we may call it the beautifull gate, for it pointeth
to the very beauty of holinesse, that is, the Scripture:
next the Temple it selfe, which is the maine structure
and building of the text, my house shalbe called the
house of prayer: and lastly, the backe or dung-gate at
which Christ throweth out the profaners of the Temple,
who had made it a dunghill, or a den of theeves, but
you have made it a den of theeves.
            
            But there is one word in the text from whence I
meane to fetch that division of the words which at this
time I purpose to pursue, and that is the word appellabitur,
shalbe called; since the text is of the right naming,
calling, or as it were christening of the Temple, I shall
pray you to take notice of these foure particulars▪
First of the Churches name, my house, and we may call
it the proper name of the Church, for it giveth God a
propriety in it: Secondly, the Churches surname or appellative
name by which it shalbe called, the house of
prayer, my house shalbe called the house of prayer: Thirdly,
the Churches nicke-name, by which in regard of the
great abuse offered unto it, Christ miscalleth it, a den of
theeves, but you have made it a den of theeves: Fourthly,
the Church-booke or register in which all these names
are recorded, the name and surname in Isaiah, the nick-name

in Ieremiah, it is written: Neither need we doubt
but that all these names are very significant, for if Adam
by that originall wisdome wherewith God indued him
was able to give names to all the creatures according
to their natures, much more is God himselfe able to do
so when he will name any thing.
            Now in each of these foure there be two particulars;
in the first, that is, the name, my house, these two: First,
It is fit God should have houses built to him on earth as
well as men, my house. Secondly, These houses built
unto God become God his houses by propriety, so his,
that they may never be taken from him; my house. In
the second, that is, the surname of the Church, shalbe
called the house of prayer, these two: First, Houses built
unto God are to be solemnly called, or (as it were)
christened, that is, consecrated and dedicated to the
service of God, shalbe called. Secondly, As they are to
be dedicated to all the parts of God his service, so especially
they are to be consecrated to prayer, shalbe called
the house of prayer. In the third, that is, the Churches
nicke-name, but you have made it a den of theeves, these
two: First, God his Church may become the Divels
Chappell, Bethel may become Bethaven; the house of
prayer, a den of theeves. Secondly, The theeves and
robbers who make it so, are principally the Priests, but
in their owne place the people too; for both are here
meant by you; the Priests for letting out the shop-keepers
standings, and the Lay-people for selling in those
shops, being upon holy ground. In the fourth, that is,
the Church-booke or Register, It is written, these two:
First, The authority by which the proper use for the
Temple for prayer is to be proved, by Scripture: next,
the authority by which the abuse of the Temple is to

be reproved, by Scripture too: Christ indeed (who
was a King as well as a Priest) besides the text, useth
the whip too: but Church-mens best whip is Scriptum
est, It is written; in the old Testament, in the new Testament,
and in their owne place, in the Canons of the
Church; a threefold cord is not easily broken, this
three-stringed whip will hold upon the consciences of
men, or nothing will: if not, the Prince then must use
the secular whip indeed: As Christ used the Divell,
sometimes throwing him by maine force out of them
that were possessed, sometimes throwing him upon his
back by force of Scripture, It is written, as in his temptations,
so here he useth these divellish men; as a King▪
he drives them out of the Temple with a whip; as a
Priest, with the text; It is written, my house shalbe called
the house of prayer, but you have made it a den of theeves.
And of so many of these parts in this order which
I have now propounded, as the time and your royall
patience shall give me leave.
            And first of the Church its name, my house, and in it
of the first particular, which is this, It is fit God should
have houses built unto him upon earth as well as men,
for though the heaven of heavens cannot containe
him, much lesse this house which is made with
hands, as Salomon speaketh at the Dedication of his
Temple; and the Almighty dwelleth not in houses
made with hands, as Peter speaketh in the Acts; yet
since God hath given to man the whole surface of the
earth to build upon for himselfe, he expecteth that man
by way of gratitude should find out some corner wherupon
to build to his God; as when God requireth of us
to give some of our goods to the poore, it is not that he
could not provide for the poore without us, If I were

hungry (saith the Lord) I would not tell thee, for all the beasts
of the field are mine, and the flockes upon a thousand mountaines:
but since he hath given unto us all that we have,
he expecteth that by way of thankfulnesse wee should
give backe unto him (for what we give to the poore he
accounteth given to himselfe) a little of that all: Even
so having given man the whole earth to build upon for
himselfe, he looketh that man should set out some part
of that whole whereupon to build, and be at some cost
with his God: that was a noble strife betweene a King
and his subject, David and Araunah the Iebusite, Sam. 2.
24. concerning the threshing floore upon which David
was commanded to build an Altar to God, Araunah
would have given it freely because it was for God, but
David scorned to build unto his God upon that ground
which should cost him nothing.
            Now these houses built by men unto God were of
old called Temples, now Churches, and though they
were of mens building, yet were they not of mens devising,
but of God his owne institution: Moses is the
auncientest writer we have extant, and in him we have
the first mention of a Temple, for God delivered unto
him in the patterne of the Tabernacle the modell of the
Temple: It is true indeed that the Gentiles by instigation
of the Divell who is God his ape, in imitation
hereof did erect Temples to false gods; but first wee
have mention of God his Temple, as truth is more ancient
than a lie: And even before either that Tabernacle
or Temple, we find that there were Analogicall
Temples, that is, places set apart and consecrated to the
service of God. Abel though he sacrificed abroad
and in an open place, yet was it a place prepared; Noah
offered sacrifice upon an Altar, Iacob upon a stone turned

to the forme of a Pillar and annointed with oyle, which
he called by the very name in the text, my house, Bethel
the house of God, Genes. 28. The same custome was (no
question) observed by the Patriarkes downe to Moses,
unto whom God himselfe delivered the patterne of the
Tabernacle, which should be a patterne of the Temple;
and then came the Temple of Hierusalem it selfe, the
most glorious structure the Sun did ever behold: To
this Temple, under the Gospell succeeded the
Churches of Christians, at first indeed but meane, the
Church being under persecution: but when the Emperours
and Princes became Christians, most glorious;
so magnificent for structure, so rich for indowments,
that as Moses was glad by sound of trumpet to make
proclamation throughout the Campe that the people
should bring no more materials for the furnishing of
the Tabernacle; so Christian Princes were over-ruled
by their subjects, to make Edicts of restraint for giving
any more to the Church. From whence appeareth
the vanity and ignorance of those humorists, who ask,
what needeth all this cost of oyntment upon Christ
his head? all this cost upon the building and ornaments
of Churches? since the first and best Christians
were not acquainted with them? They may as well
aske what silly men were David to provide such a
masse of mony and materials, and Salomon to spend
them all and many millions more upon the Temple of
Hierusalem, since God before was well enough worshipped
and sacrificed unto by Abel and Noah perhaps
upon a turfe, by Iacob upon a stone. But when God
had given to his people the blessing of a magnificent
Monarchie, he would not have them dwell in houses
of Cedar, and his house remaine within curtaines, but

would haue the house where his honour was to dwell,
for state and magnificence to be the beauty of the
whole earth; so while Christians at the first had much
ado to live and breathe under their persecutions, God
was contented to be worshipped by them in such mean
places as they could provide for him: but when Emperours
and Princes became Christian, and Christians
under them enjoyed peace and plenty, he expected
from them glorious and sumptuous Churches, neither
was his expectation deceived: for though they were
not able to reach the beauty of the Temple of Hierusalem,
the Iewes themselves not being able to match the
first Temple; yet we find that Christians in building
their first Churches had an eye to that Temple: for
though our novelists if they chance to build a Church,
(as they do sometime beyond the seas) will take any
modell perhaps of a great hall or barne, rather than of
the ancient Christian Churches; yet the first builders
of Christian Churches even for the forme of fabricke
did in some sort imitate that Temple of Hierusalem.
For, as in that Temple there were foure distinctions,
the Porch which was called Salomons; Atrium or the
Court, whither the people came; Sanctum the holy
place, whither the Priests came; and the Sanctum Sanctorum
the holy of holiests, into which onely the high
Priests were to enter: So in the old Christian
Churches (though not for the same uses) were foure
distinctions; the outmost place of all answerable to
the Porch, unto which infidels or such as were excommunicate
and cast out of the Church might come, but
no further; into the next place as it were in Atrio,
came the penitents, such as did penance, but no further;
the third place was the body of the Church, which we

may call Sanctum, and whither the people came to bee
partakers of Gods worship; and the fourth was as it
were the Sanctum Sanctorum, the inclosed place where
the Altar or Communion-Table stood, into which
none did enter but such as were in holy Orders, and
had power to consecrate the blessed Elements; so great
followers were the Primitive Christians of antiquity,
rather than incliners unto novelty.
            Now to move our times (in which some pull down
as fast as our Fathers built, and deface as much as they
did decke) a little to looke to Gods houses and buildings,
I shall briefly offer two things to your consideration.
First, the great estimation which God hath of
these houses; next, the high esteeme in which men
have had them: so that if we either feare God, or reverence
men, there can no argument be wanting God
his estimation of Temples appeareth by his delivering
unto Moses the patterne of the Tabernacle even to the
least pin, which was to be but a patterne of the Temple;
by not giving way to David his building of the
Temple, although a man according to Gods owne
heart, onely for that exception of bloud which God
had against him, and not of bloud unlawfully shed, but
in lawfull warres, and undertaken by God his owne
commandement; for this exception was laid against
David, before the matter of Vriah; by his accepting
the Temple at Salomons hands in the very time of the
dedication of it, filling it so with his presence in the
cloud, that the Priests were interrupted in performing
the rites of consecration; by promising to put his name
there for ever, and to fix his eyes and heart there perpetually,
by performing this his promise of presence▪ for
many times he appeared betweene the Cherubins, and

in that Temple did inspire diverse with the spirit of
prophesie; by ordering that the most precious and holy
things should be kept in it; the Arke of the Testament,
the Tables of the Law, Aarons rod, the heavenly
fire, Vrim and Thummim, &amp;c. By threatning the
destruction of that Temple, as the greatest judgement
that should ever befall them, (as indeed it was) for after
the destruction of that Temple they ceased to be
any more a people. And as by God, so by men this
Temple of all buildings had in the highest esteeme,
Hierusalem in regard of it counted the joy of the whole
earth; to this Temple came all the people once in the
yeare, and when they did not come, they powred forth
their supplications with their faces towards it: you
know David his one wish, although it was not granted
him, that All his life long he might dwell in the house of
the Lord, and visit the beauty of his holy Temple; he accounted
the Sparrowes happy which might but hop
and sing and lay their young about the Altars of it; he
accounted the meanest officer, even a doore-keeper in
it happier than they that lived in the Pallaces of Princes:
In a word, consider the revenge which Christ
(who was God) taketh here upon the profaners of the
Temple, and the vast expence laid out upon it by David
and Salomon who were men, and we must needs see
that high esteeme in which that Temple was had both
by God and men.
            But what is all this (will you say) to our Christian
Churches? Very much; for they are come in place of
that Temple, as the Christian Religion is come in place
of the Iewish: that Temple was but a type of our
Churches, as all that service was a type of our Christ:
We have an Altar, saith the Apostle, and therefore a

Priesthood as that Temple had: there was the Arke of
the Testament, our Churches are the Arkes of two
Testaments: of theirs, which was the old Testament;
and of another better than theirs, the new Testament:
in our Churches are the daily sacrifices of praise and
prayer, the two Tables of the Law, and they expounded
and vindicated from false gloses and interpretations
by our Saviour in the 5 of Math. which that Temple
had not; in our Churches is Aarons rod▪ that is,
Ecclesiasticall discipline; Vrim and Thummim in our
Priests: and above all, in our Churches is celebrated
the commemorative sacrifice of the most precious body
and bloud of the Sonne of God: no doubt then to
be made of Gods high esteeme of Christian Churches
built unto him. Now how they have beene honoured
by men, witnesse the infinite cost bestowed by our
fore-fathers in fabricke and maintenance of them, the
infinite priviledges granted by Christian Princes unto
them; although the beginning of our age did scatter as
fast as the former age did gather; and the later lawes
of taking no more from the Church, were farre more
necessary than those former lawes, for giving no
more to it.
            Whose charity then can bee straitned when a
house of God is to be inlarged; when either it is to be
built, or being built is to be kept from ruine? Can
men have summer and winter houses, and the Temple
of God lie so, as it keepeth out neither summer Sun nor
winter weather? the Temple of God I say, a name so
glorious, that even the most glorious; all the persons
of the Trinity delight to be called by it: God the Father,
Revel. 21. 22. Iohn saw no Temple in the holy City,
For the Lord God Almighty and the Lambe are the

Temple of it. God the Sonne, his person the Lambe in
that place is called a Temple by Saint Iohn, his body
by himselfe, Destroy this Temple, and I will build it up againe
in three dayes. The Holy Ghost, although he be
not called a Temple, yet Temples he hath, and delighteth
to dwell in them, even our bodies, Know ye not that
your bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghost? The summe
of all is, houses are to be built unto God, and being built,
are highly to be honoured, because they are his houses
by propriety: which I told you was the second particular
in the Church its name, and is now the next point to
be spoken of, My house.
            
            
               My house, that is, mine by propriety, and if so, then
we must looke to three things. First, if the Church
be Gods house, then Take heed to thy foot when thou enterest
into it, Eccles. 4. 17. do not rush rudely nor rashly
into it, but be sure you keep your distance, els you may
be turned back with shame enough, and sent home unjustified
as the Pharisi
                  •
                was, because he kept not the
Publican his distance, who stood afarre off and would
not so much as lift up his eyes towards heaven: How
fearefull (saith Iacob) is this place, the Lord was in it and I
knew it not, it is nothing els but the house of God, and the very
gate of heaven. The truth then is, if the Church be
my house, that is, Gods, we must observe a reverend distance
in all our approaches which we make to God in
it, els we run upon certaine danger; are you in this
house to speake unto God by prayer? be sure you
make a curtsie low enough with David, I am a worme
and no man: or if you will, a little lower with Abraham,
Since dust and ashes have begun to speake unto thee:
els you may justly feare that your prayers shalbe turned
into sinne. Are you in this house to heare God

speake unto you by his Word read or preached? Be
sure you keepe your distance, as the people were commanded
at the hearing of the Law, els you know your
danger, For if so much as a beast shall touch the smoaking
mountaine, it shalbe stoned to death, or thrust through with a
dart. Are you in this house to converse with God in the
blessed Sacrament? Use first a reverent preparation,
Let a man examine himselfe, and so let him eat of that bread
and drinke of that cup; els you know the danger, You shall
be guilty of the body and bloud of the Lord. For observing
this distance in Gods house, I will but name unto you
two reasons. First, we do not find in Scripture▪ that
God hath used to be familiar with any, to entertaine
them, or be entertained by them, unlesse they have observed
this distance, and first prepared themselves for
that interviewe or parlie. Before God would speake
one word to Moses on the backe of Mount Horeb, he
first biddeth him put off his shoes, because the place on
which he stood was holy ground: when God delivered
his Law to his people from the top of Mount Sinai,
he first commanded them to sanctifie themselves three
dayes before, that all that while they might be the
more reverently prepared to harken unto that which
God was to say unto them; so must we when we come
into the house of God (if we be to speake to him by
prayer, or to heare him speake to us by his Word) put
off our shoes, that is, all worldly thoughts and affections;
and sanctifie our selves, that is, put on all new and
holy thoughts and affections. The second reason is
this: We do not find that God hath ever yet suffered
the unreverent handlers, or lookers upon the places of
his presence, to go away unpunished; Vzza did but irreverently
touch the Arke of the Lord, and the Lord

presently killed him; the men of Bethshemesh did but
irreverently looke into the Arke of the Lord, and the
Lord presently slew fifty thousand of them: How
few be they in our times, who by observing this distance
do declare that they believe the Church to be
Gods house, how many that come in without preparing
themselves at first by devotion and prayer? How
many who clap on their hats when God is speaking to
them by his Word, I meane in the time when the very
text is reading? Nay the servant who wilbe uncovered
before this master in his owne house, will many times
be covered before him in Gods house; all which bewrayeth
that many men do either take the Church not
to be my house, that is, Gods; or (which is worse) Gods
house not to be so good as their owne.
            Next, if the Church be my house, that is, Gods, then
the zeale of the Church must eat us up: to this we are
warranted both by David and by Christ the Sonne of
David, The Zeale of thine house hath eaten me up, saith David;
and in this Christ shewed himselfe truly to be the
Sonne of David, for we do not find that Christ in his
life did ever use severity with his hands, but once;
twice he did it, but it was one and the same case, the
profanation of the Temple: When he was apprehended,
bound, buffered, smitten, mocked, reviled, scourged,
spit upon, tortured, crucified, he bare all patiently,
and As a sheepe before the slaughterer is dumbe, so he opened
not his mouth: but if he see the least indignity offered to
his Fathers house, his zeale bursteth out into a flame, he
setteth his hand to the whip, and his tongue to the t
                  •
               xt:
When his Disciples did see that fiercenesse of his in the
2. of Iohn, they were astonished at it; especially comparing
it with his usuall meeknesse at other times, when

they thought there was greater occasion offered; but
at the 17 Verse of that Chapter they were easily satisfied,
when They remembred how it was written, The Zeale of
thine house hath eaten me up. Now the best way to try
whether we have this zeale towards Gods house, is the
comparative rule: if we expresse more reverence in
this house than in the house of any other man whosoever;
if we be more forward (according to our places)
to punish an offence or irreverence in this house, than
those that are committed any where els; if we can be
contented to be at more cost for repairing and adorning
this house, than if it were our owne: if not, then
certainly either we do not believe the Church to be my
house, that is, Gods; or (which is worse) Gods house
not to be so good as our owne.
            Thirdly, if the Church be my house, that is, Gods,
then no humane power may take it from him; his title is
like the Character of his Priesthood, indelebilis; no
time, no prescription can prejudice it: for if nullum tempus
occurrit Regi, if no time can prescribe against our
King his title to the Patronage of a Church, much lesse
can it prescribe against his title who is the King of
Kings: Before thou buildedst a house to God, the
ground and the cost were thine own, and thou mightest
have done with them what thou wouldest, as Peter told
Ananias; but when thou hast once given them to
God, it is no more thine, but my house: for as Gods
gifts towards us are without repentance, so ought our
gifts towards God to be: He who among us shall kill
himselfe, and become fello de se, maketh all his goods
Deodands; and it is as true inverted, he who hath made
any of his goods Deodands, and shall afterward do any
act of resumption, is fello de se, a murtherer of himselfe,

and a destroyer of his owne soule. Stories are full of
their tragedies who any wayes went about to alter either
the propertie or use of the Temple of Hierusalem;
we know what became of Antiochus after he set up the
statue of Iupiter Olympius in it; upon the Caldeans destruction
of that Temple followed the losse of their
Empire; the Macedonians after their violation of it lost
their Dominions; Pompey after his comming up to the
Sanctum or holy place, which was not lawfull for him
to do, had never luckie day after; no more had Cassius
after his profanation of it. They who have medled
with the Christian Churches have not fared much better:
for they who have pulled downe these houses of
God, have found that withall they have pulled downe
their owne houses; and they who have built their own
houses where Gods house stood, have found that they
have built upon sandy and sinking ground, and that the
Church-stones have crumbled their houses to nothing,
and sunke their estates irrecoverably. Now they who
pervert Gods house and turne it to any secular use, do
deny it to be my house, that is, Gods, as much as they
who evert it and pull it downe. It is a notable cunning
of the Divell, as to make us believe that God is a good-fellow,
and that we may retaine him in our hearts with
our sinnes; so to make us believe that his house is a
house of good-fellowship, and that it may serve for other
uses besides the service of God; to lay lumber in,
or things out of the way, in a Progresse time to serve
for a Wardrobe, in the countrey for Iuries of Leets to
sit in and consult about their verdicts, and most commonly
at the Communion-Table to make their Sesses,
not onely for the poore (which is a Church-duty) but
also for all other compositions, where they seldome

meet without wrangling, and I am afraid many times
not without swearing: But if it be Gods house, he must
and will have it alone, or not at all: That passage of the
Philistims setting the Arke of God in the Temple of
Dagon, is very remarkable; one would wonder why
God should plague the Philistims for it; for I am perswaded
the Philistims made account they had done the
Arke the greatest honour that they could imagine, by
setting it in the Temple of their owne god: yet God
tumbled downe Dagon, smote the Philistims, and would
have consumed them if they had not dismissed his Arke:
What meant this? Onely to tell the world that with
God it is all one to be turned out of doores, and to be
lodged by an Idoll: Let God have his house alone,
there he will dwell: make it thine as well as mine;
that is, make it serve for thine use and the service of
God too, thou diseasest God and turnest him out of
doores▪ The reason is, because houses built to God are
only to be consecrated to him and his service, which
is now the next point to be spoken of, I called it the
Churches surname, shalbe called the house of prayer.
            
            In it I told you of two particulars. First, Gods
house is to be called, or as it were christened, that is,
consecrated and dedicated to God and his service, my
house shalbe called. Secondly, among all the parts of
Gods service, it is especially to be consecrated to prayer,
shalbe called the house of prayer. For the first, that the
consecra
                  •
               ion and solemne dedication of Temples and
Churches is very ancient, it is argument enough, that in
all the three languages we have a proper word for it, in
the Hebrew (Chanucah) from Chanac, which signifieth
to dedicate a thing when it is finished, in Greeke 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               encoenia from 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                which signifieth an initiation

or making of a thing new, the word used by Iohn
10. 22. for that feast of dedication at which Christ was
present, and then the Latine words dedicatio and consecratio:
Consecration or setting apart persons or things to
God both by God himselfe and men, is very ancient.
God consecrated to himselfe our first parents, and
made their mariage a kind of Sacrament of the union
and spirituall mariage betweene Christ and his
Church, as the Apostle testifieth, Ephes. 5. so he consecrated
to himselfe the posterity of Seth, of Iacob, every
male which first opened the wombe, at last the Iewes
had delivered unto them among other parts of the Ceremoniall
Law, the rites of dedication of certaine persons,
vessels, vestures: Now for the solemne dedication
of the houses of God, we have first the dedication
of the Tabernacle which was but the patterne of the
Temple, Exod. 40. then of the Temple it selfe we have
three solemne dedications recorded in Scripture: the
first by Salomon, Kings 1. 8. the second by Zorobabel and
others, Ezra 6. and related by Iosephus antiq. lib. 11. cap.
4. the last by Iudas Macchabeus after the defeat of Antiochus,
which was indeed especially of the Altar, of
which we read Mach. 1. 4. and Ioseph. antiq. lib. 12. cap.
10. and this last was the feast of dedication which
Christ honoured with his presence, Iohn 10. for it is
plaine by the text both that it was in winter, and anniversarie,
neither of which is true of the two former
dedications: Among Christians their Churches used
ever to be consecrated. Euseb. lib. 9. cap. 10. of his Historie,
and in the life of Constantine describeth unto us the
dedication of that Church which Constantine first built
at Hierusalem. When Churches at the first were rare,
the authority of consecration came from the Prince and

Magistrate, but the rites of consecration in the Iewish
Church were ever performed by the Priests; in the
Christian by the Bishops: the first dedication of the
Temple of Hierusalem done by the authority of Salomon,
the second of Zorobabel, the third of Iudas Macchabeus;
but all of them performed by the Priests: so among
Christians, the first Christian Church at Hierusalem
consecrated by the authority of Constantine, but
by the ministery of Eusebius: that of Alexandria by
the same authority, but by the ministerie of Athanasius:
The rites of consecration are left to the Church
and her Bishops; onely there be some of them of the
Quorum, without which there cannot well be any consecration:
as first, Churches ought to be consecrated
by prayer; for Salomon his dedication is conceived in
the very forme of a prayer: next, Churches are to be
consecrated by reading of the Word; for at the dedication
of the Temple the law was ever read: Thirdly,
Churches are to be dedicated with the celebration of
the Sacrament of our Saviour his most precious body
and bloud, as in all the three dedications of the Temple
ever sacrifice was offered: But above all, Churches
must onely be consecrated and dedicated to God, not
to Saints, Angels, or any created Patrons: But may
not the Churches of Christians be called by the names
of Saints and Martyrs, as S. Maries, S. Peters, &amp;c? Yes,
they may be patrini, but not patres, godfathers, but not
fathers of our Churches; as men are contented their
children should be called by the names of their friends
whom they chuse for godfathers, but will have themselves
still onely acknowledged for fathers: so God alloweth
that his Saints and Martyrs should be susceptores,
godfathers of Christian Churches, especially if it shall

not be done as now it is in the Church of Rome, to derogate
from God his Patronage: and no particular office
or service shall be allowed to be said in the Church
to that Saint after which it is named. The truth is, in the
Primitive Church, Christian Churches were called by
the names of Saints and Martyrs for two reasons, the equity
of both which holdeth still. First, to testifie
their thankfulnesse to God for the benefits which the
Church had received by the ministerie of these Saints.
Secondly and principally, God in the infancy of the
Church did shew many miracles at the Tombes and
Sepulchers of the Martyrs; and therefore the Christians
did there erect Churches, and call them by the
names of those Martyrs, out of a desire to honour those
whom God had so much honoured, and the world so
much despised. The summe then of all is, Christian
Churches may be called by the names of Saints and
Martyrs, but must be dedicated onely to God and his
service; and as to all parts of his service, so especially to
prayer: which I told you was the second particular in
the Churches surname, and is now the next point to be
spoken of, shalbe called the house of prayer.
            
            Why not the house of Sacrifice, Sacraments, Prophecying,
Preaching? Because all these are worth nothing
unlesse they be seasoned with prayer: It is not to
be passed over with sleight observation, that although
all these, except their Sacraments, were performed in
the Iewish Temple, and all of them are performed in
Christian Churches; yet the duties of the Temple
most commonly have their denomination in Scripture
from that of prayer: Salomon in the dedication of his
Temple (as he conceived it in the forme of a prayer) especially
beggeth of God his attention to the prayers

that should be made in that place, and the whole tenour
of his dedication runneth upon it, and God his answer
to Salomon is accordingly for prayer: Anna in the 2. of
Luke is said not to have gone out of the Temple, but to
have continued in it fasting and praying; In Luke 2. 37.
the Pharisie and the Publican went up to the Temple to
pray: Acts 3. 1. Peter and Iohn went up to the Temple
about the houre of prayer, being the ninth houre; which to
the Iewes was the third houre before the setting of the
Sun, the very houre of the evening Sacrifice; here the
Temple is called the house of prayer, and the Christian
Churches accordingly were called Oratories; why all
this? To teach us two things. First, the excellency of
prayer among all other religious duties. Secondly, the
excellency of publike prayer above all other private
prayers made any where els. For the first, I will not in
a Sermon enter upon the common place of prayer, onely
this: you shall not find in Scripture any man registred
for one of God his speciall friends and favourites, who
was not likewise a man of prayers and supplications,
Moyses, Abraham, Iob, David; but above all looke
upon Christ, so given to prayer, that as he was called
by the Prophet vir dolorum, a man of sorrowes, so he
might have been called vir clamorum, a man of cryings
and supplications; for he used them at home and abroad,
upon the Mount, in the Garden, upon the Crosse
dying, nay after his death; which maketh highly for
the commendation of prayer; Christ was a Priest, now
the office of the Priest consisted in these two things, in
offering up sacrifice for the sinnes of the people, and in
offering up prayers for the sinnes of the people: that
part of Christ his Priesthood which concerned sacrifice
expired with his life, for he offered up the perfect

sacrifice of his body once for all, but so did not that
part of his Priesthood which concerneth prayer; for
as he died praying, so he still continueth a Priest in regard
of prayer, two wayes. First, because he himselfe
at the right hand of God still maketh intercession for us,
Heb. 7. 25. Wherefore he is utterly able to save all them that
come to him, since he ever liveth to make intercession for us.
Secondly, because as our Advocate he offereth up into
the bosome of his Father all the Prayers which we
make to God in his name, Rev. 8. 3. It is said of Christ
the Angell of the covenant, that he offereth up many
sweet odours, which are the prayers of the Saints.
            
            Secondly, the Temple is called the house of prayer, as
to shew us the excellency of prayer in generall, so in
particular to expresse unto us the excellency of publike
prayer in the Temple. And here I am sorie that the iniquity
of the times should put me upon two comparisons
which to some will seeme odious: the one is betweene
prayer in the Temple, and preaching in the
Temple: the other betweene prayer in the Temple, and
prayer any where els. For preaching, far be it from any
Christian to under-value the holy and blessed Ordinance
of God: onely I would have men, as upon
preaching, so likewise to set a true value upon prayer in
the Temple. There is a generation of fooles risen up
in the world, who think that all religion consisteth in
preaching and hearing of Sermons, and will run some
miles to heare them: But for the publike prayers of
the Church, they will hardly crosse the street; but cast
themselves to come into the Church about the ending
of Divine Service, and beginning of Sermon: now
S. Pauls question poseth them all, If all were hearing,
where were seeing, and the rest of the senses? so doth this

name which Christ here giveth to the Temple, the
house of prayer. But they will say, can there be too much
preaching or hearing? Yes, there may be too much of
any thing: Take this for a rule, no truth can be repugnant
to another truth in any science whatsoever: much
lesse can Theologicall truths be repugnant one to another,
and therefore all Theologicall truths must be expounded
as they may stand in grosse one by another: He
that hath said, Be swift to heare, hath likewise said, Pray
continually, and he that provideth not for his family is worse
than an Infidell: Men then must so heare, as they neglect
not prayer, as that in weeke dayes, if their families
be sustained by their trade and calling, they neglect not
that, to run after Sermons; for there is no religious
worke which may not be over-done: we are commanded
to give almes, but if one shall give all he hath,
knowing that he must become chargeable to others, it
is sin, and that voluntary poverty which we condemne
in many of the Mendicant Friers: Fasting is a religious
duty, but if one shall abstaine so much, as he knoweth
he shalbe accessary to his owne death, it is a sinne, as
Gregory Nazianzen complained of his sister Gorgonia:
Even prayer it selfe, which I am now commending,
when it is over-done, it is called by our Saviour, vaine
babling and idle repetitions: So for hearing, we ought
to heare on that day which God hath set apart for his
service, all excuses laid aside; and on the weeke dayes
too, omit no good occasion of hearing, so farre as our
callings and places will permit; but so as we never omit
the frequenting of the Divine Service and Publike
Prayers of the Church.
            Next from this, that the Temple is called the house of
prayer, we may see the excellency of publike prayer in

the Temple, above private prayer any where els: which
I pray you may not be taken as spoken any way in derogation
from private prayer, to which I find our Saviour
was so much addicted, as appeareth by his prayer in
the Garden, which he powred forth in a private place,
a garden; at a private time, in the night, privately and
alone by himselfe; for he was separated not onely
from the rest of his Disciples, but even from the three
Disciples that entred with him, by the space of a stones
cast: Sure none can speake against private prayer, but
they who never felt that sweetnesse which the soule of a
Christian findeth in her private retirement, familiarity
and conversation with God: You who do use it, use it
still; for besides many other, you shall find these three
great conveniences in it. First, an easie ravishing of the
mind of a Christian: for if that definition of prayer which
the Fathers give us be true, that prayer is nothing els
but the lifting up or ravishing of a mans mind from all
worldly things towards God; how can the mind of
man be more easily lifted up from worldly things, than
when being alone with his God, he is remooved from
the sight and sense of them? Secondly, in private
prayer we find greater security from vaine-glory,
which though perhaps in publike prayer we do not affect,
yet we do not know how the Divell may spice our
prayers with pride, when we thinke that every one is
looking upon us. Thirdly, in private prayer we may
use greater freedome and liberty with God in expressing
of our wants; as broken words, crying, ejaculatorie
voices, confused sighs, &amp;c. which though they be
acceptable to God, yet are not seemly nor decent before
men; and therefore may be used with greater
freedome in private, than they can be in publike

prayer: For these and many more such reasons, follow
Christ his counsell, Enter into thy chamber and shut
the doore behind thee, that is, give your selves to private
prayer.
            But much more, be sure never to neglect publike
prayer, to which we find likewise that our Saviour was
so much addicted; take for instance those prayers
which he powred forth publikely at his death, for they
were made at a publike time, the time of the Passeover,
when untill that time twelvemoneth there was not so
great a confluxe of people to be at Hierusalem to heare;
in a publike place, the place of execution, large and able
to receive great multitudes: and that they might yet be
heard the better, made upon the top of a hill, Mount
Calvarie: nay yet, upon the top of a beacon which
stood upon the top of that hill; nay yet, that they
might be the better heard, as it is said in the Gospell,
that he spake his last word consummatum est, with a loud
voice, so saith the Apostle Heb. 5. 7. that he offered up
his prayers there clamore valid
                     •
                  , Who offered up prayers
and supplications with strong cryings and tears, which place
the Fathers expound of his prayers upon the Crosse among
the rest; and here I think publike prayer is sufficiently
warranted. And if you shall say, what is all this
to publike prayer in the Temple? I answer, very much;
for that place in which our Lord dying prayed, was a
Temple: the reason is this, sacrifice was onely to be offered
up in the Temple; Christ therefore in this place
offering up the sacrifice of his owne body, made it truly
to be a Temple: truly I say, because the Temple of
Hierusalem in which the daily sacrifice was offered up,
was nothing els but a type of this very place in which
was to be offered this perfect sacrifice once for all; as

therefore Christ called his body a Temple, Destroy this
Temple, and I will build it up in three dayes, so offering up
the sacrifice of his body in this place, he might challenge
God to heare the prayers which he should make
in this place, by vertue of that promise which he had
made, to heare the prayers which should be made in the
Temple: And Christ praying in this place, was quit
with the Iewes in my text; for this place was Golgotha,
the place of dead mens sculs; that is, the place where
lay the bodies of executed malefactors and theeves: so
that looke how much the Iewes had dishonoured the
Temple in my text, so much did Christ honour Mount
Calvarie. As they had made the house of God, which
was the house of prayer, to be a den of theeves, so
Christ made Golgotha which was a den for the dead bodies
of theeves, to become the house of prayer.
            The excellency of publike prayer is well set forth
by our Saviour, Math. 18. in that excellent rule which
he giveth for publike prayer, for that rule includeth
three reasons why we should give our selves to it. The
first is, the consent and agreement of Christian minds
in prayer, a thing most acceptable to God, Vers. 18. If
two of you shall agree upon any thing in earth, it shalbe given
unto you. Secondly, because of the assembling of the
Saints together in one place, which meeting even of
their bodies is a thing most delightfull unto God, in the
next verse, For where two or three are gathered together,
there will I be in the middest of them. Thirdly, because of
the unity of faith which is most pleasant unto God, the
people assembling themselves in the name of Christ, in
the same verse, where two or three are gathered together
in my name, there will I be in the middest of them:
to these reasons we may add this, that the publike

prayers of the Church are far more excellently conceived
and penned than any private extemporary prayers
can be: for there is more pith in one of the well conceived
Collects of the Church, than in many of those
pitifull fellowes more pitifull bablings and idle repetitions,
in which (as our Saviour speaketh) they think to be
heard for their length, whereas prayer consisteth not in
length, but strength, which is to be had in the well
compacted Collects of the Church. Have you not
heard some of these men in their extemporary exclamations,
or declamations rather, (for sometimes their
prayers are libels) talke to God, not onely with that familiarity,
but homelinesse, that you would not have indured
them to talke to you? And perhaps they who
stand now so much onely for extemporary prayer and
preaching too in the Church, ere it be long (for I see no
reason why it may not hold in this, as well as in the other
two) will venture and put in for extemporary singing
in the Church, and then they will make themselves
ridiculous indeed. The summe of all is, although thou
givest thy selfe never so much to private prayer, which
is well done, yet do not neglect the publike prayers of
the Church, in the Church, which is here called the
house not of knowledge, righteousnesse, mercy,
preaching, hearing, &amp;c. although it be all these, but
the house of prayer. So that those men who do wilfully
excommunicate themselves by not comming to the
prayers of the Church, but onely to the Sermon, or usually
go out of it before the blessing or last prayer be
pronounced, since the Church is called the house of
prayer, they are like them who come unto a schoole, but
will not learne, to a battell, but will not fight, to a bed,
but will not sleep, to a feast, but will not feed: all which

tendeth nothing to any derogation from private prayer:
For as God dispersed the places of refuge throughout
the land to his people, so thicke and at such distances,
as the offenders might reach some of them by
night, lest they should be over-taken by the avengers
of their bloud, but yet appointed the Temple for the
only place whither afterwards the offenders were to resort,
and to expiate their offence by sacrifice: so for
our sinnes which we daily and hourely commit, God
alloweth and requireth us daily to have refuge to him
by private prayer, but so, that we neglect not to reconcile
our selves to him for these sinnes by our publike
prayers in the Temple, which is the house of prayer; for
whosoever robbeth God and his Temple of this honor
which is due unto him in it, doth what in him lieth in
some sense to make the house of prayer a den of theeves;
which is now the next point to be spoken of, I called it
the Churches nicke-name, but you have made it a den of
theeves.
            
            In unfolding of which part (if time had suffered me)
many would have been found theeves and robbers who
passe for vertuous and honest men: Hardly would any
pretence have served their turne: For the money-changers
and dove-sellers, and the Priests suffering
them to sell in the Court, (for it was in the Atrium or
Court only that they sold, not in the Temple it selfe, although
it be here called so, because it was consecrated
and holy ground as the Temple was) had as specious a
pretence for this their merchandizing as might be, even
the pretence of that Law, Deut. 14. 24. whereby it was
permitted to the people for the more easie cariage, to
change their tythes and offerings into money, and with
that money at Hierusalem to buy the like: Now for

this purpose, to fit such people with sacrifices and
offerings, did the Priests pretend that they suffered the
money-changers and dove-sellers to set up their shops
there, although indeed they did it to get money for
their standing, and the shop-keepers to make gaine of
the people; and therefore our Saviour here cals their
getting plaine thee very and robbery: But the time will
not give me leave to arraigne these theeves now. To
God the Father, God the Sonne, God the Holy
Ghost bee ascribed all honour and
praise, now and ever.
Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

