
   
      
         
            Three rare monuments of antiquitie, or Bertram, priest, a French-man, of the body and blood of Christ, (written 800 yeares agoe) with the late Romish purging thereof: Ælfricus, Arch-bishop of Canterburie, an English-man, his sermon of the sacrament, (preached 627 yeares agoe:) and Maurus, abbot, a Scots-man, his discourse of the same (820 yeares agoe:) all stronglie convincing that grosse errour of transubstantiation. Translated and compacted by M. VVilliam Guild, minister at King-Edward
            De corpore et sanguine Domini. English. Abridgments
            Ratramnus, monk of Corbie, d. ca. 868.
         
         
            
               1624
            
         
         Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02359
            STC 12492
            ESTC S103528
            99839280
            99839280
            3686
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02359)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3686)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1174:13)
         
         
            
               
                  Three rare monuments of antiquitie, or Bertram, priest, a French-man, of the body and blood of Christ, (written 800 yeares agoe) with the late Romish purging thereof: Ælfricus, Arch-bishop of Canterburie, an English-man, his sermon of the sacrament, (preached 627 yeares agoe:) and Maurus, abbot, a Scots-man, his discourse of the same (820 yeares agoe:) all stronglie convincing that grosse errour of transubstantiation. Translated and compacted by M. VVilliam Guild, minister at King-Edward
                  De corpore et sanguine Domini. English. Abridgments
                  Ratramnus, monk of Corbie, d. ca. 868.
                  Guild, William, 1586-1657.
                  Aelfric, Abbot of Eynsham. Sermo de sacrificio in die Pascae. aut
                  Rabanus Maurus, Archbishop of Mainz, 784?-856. De sacramento Eucharistiae. aut
               
               [3], 6-150, [2] p.   
               
                  By Edward Raban, for David Melvill,
                  Printed at Aberdene :
                  1624.
               
               
                  Translations and abridgments of "De corpore et sanguine Domini" by Ratramnus, monk of Corbie; "Sermo de sacrificio in die Pascae" by Aelfric, Abbot of Eynsham; and "De sacramento Eucharistiae" by Rabanus Maurus.
                  The sermon by Aelfric is based on the version in "A testimonie of antiquitie", edited by Matthew Parker and John Joscelyn.
                  The last leaf contains an armorial woodcut.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Lord's Supper --  Real presence --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-04
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-05
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THREE
Rare Monuments of Antiquitie,
OR
BERTRAM, PRIEST, A FRENCH-MAN,
Of the Bodie and Blood of CHRIST, (written 800 yeares agoe)
with the late Romish purging thereof:
            
            AELFRICVS, Arch-bishop of Canterburie,
an ENGLISH-MAN,
His Sermon of the Sacrament, (preached 627 years agoe:)
AND
MAVRVS, Abbot, A SCOTS-MAN,
His discourse of the same (820 years agoe:) All stronglie convincing
that grosse Errour of TRANSVBSTANTIATION.
            
               Translated and compacted
By M. VVilliam Guild, Master at King-Edward.
            
               Printed at ABERDENE, by Edward Raban,
For David Melvill, 1624.
         
         
            
            
            To the truelie Noble,
and right honourable,
VVILLIAM,
EARLE,
Marshall of Scotland,
Lord Keyth and Altrie, &amp;c.
My singular good Lord,
and Patron:
AND TO
The Right Honourable, His most
Worthie &amp; Religious Ladie; the
Gracious Daughter of a most
Godlie Mother.
            
               I Doubt not but your
Honoures knowe,
that when the most
ancient treuth of the
ancient of dayes, registrate
in his holie
word, and left vnto
vs to be the onlie rule of our fayth,
doeth fayle our Adversaries of the

               Romish Church, that then their next
refuge is, after that they haue loaded
sacred Scripture with odious
imputations of obscuritie, imperfection,
and sweying everie way, in
their severall conflictes, to fill the
eares of each one with their clamorous
vp-brayding of Antiquitie,
and humane authoritie, when divine
hath forsaken them; like Saul,
who when God would not aunswere
him, had his recourse to Samuel.
Which notwithstanding how
little it maketh for them, &amp; how as
smallie it avayleth them, as Balaam
did Balak, when hee sent for him to
curse, where in the contrarie hee
blessed: or as Baal ayded his owne
priests, when hee was so earnestlie
in-called vpon by them to answere,
while in the meane time there was
no voyce heard; any one, who with
a single eye ever perused the same,
may easilie perceiue, and manifolde
experience hath oftentimes proven.
            And yet we see that this is their
great Diana of Ephesus, wherein they

glorie more than the Iewes, when
they cryed, The Temple of the Lord, the
Temple of the Lord: and as Rahel hid
her fathers Idoles, with the Camels
furniture, and sate on the same, and
would not aryse; So with the furniture
of venerable, but wrested and
wronged Antiquitie, they would
hyde their Errours, and cover the
Idolatrie of their whorish mother,
from whom they can not bee mooved
to depart, nor goe out of Babel,
or put away their strange gods, and
bee purged with Iaakobs godlie familie.
            So that their doing is like the
craftie dealing of the Gibeonite Ambassadoures,Ioshua, 9.
who to make a League
with the Lordes People, pretended
that they had journeyed from a verie
farre countrey, and were come
for the Name of the Lord: and this
their impudent lie (which yet they
would haue to bee believed as an
vndoubted trueth) they soothe vp
(forsooth) by demonstration of
Antiquitie; that therefore all which

they had was olde: and this was
their onlie proofe, whereby Ioshua,
and both Princes and People were
deceived: the reason whereof is given
in Scripture, Because they asked
not counsell at the mouth of
the Lord.
            Even so, that which our Adversaries
bring, when they haue quitted
Scripture, to make their blasphemous
lies to bee believed, as
sure &amp; sacred trueth, is that which
(as they pretende) is from a verie
farre, even the Apostles tymes, and
ancient holie Fathers of the primitiue
Church, glorious in sufferings,
and from their immediate successours:
And all this they doe (forsooth)
but for the Name of the
Lord, having a religious pretence
(as Simeon and Levi did) of clearing
trueth, &amp; convincing errour thereby,
and so to make vnitie of fayth
in the Church of God.
            And to performe all this, all
which they would seeme to showe
or say, is all olde, drawne from Antiquitie:

But beeing aware (by Ioshua's
example) will wee trye the
men, and their speaches, their furniture,
and pretences, and all this by
the right rule, with the men of Berea,
and as Israel should haue done
the Gibeonites, asking counsell at the
mouth of the Lord, which hee hath
opened in holie Scripture, and
which wee are bidden search, not
believing rashlie everie doctrine, to
bee carried about there-with, but
trying the spirits, whether they bee
of God, or no: and then wee shall
easilie discerne and discover their
guyle, and knowe the Beast by his
Dragon mouth, to bee but a craftie
counterfet of the Lambe.
            And tho for a seducing ende
(as was that of the olde Prophets
of Bethel,
               1. King. 13. pretending the word of
the Lord) that these ancient Fathers
are adduced by them to proue,
yet they are found rather to improue
their erroures: and beeing
violentlie drawne contrarie to their
minde, to pleade for lies, they either

stand (as Christ before Pilate) not
vttering a word, or (as Daniel for
Susanna) opening their mouthes to
withstand conspyring falshood, and
defende injured innocencie, whereby
bragging Goliah so, hath oftentimes
his head cut off with his own
sword; and what they most repose
in, is found truelie to depose against
them.
            And moreover,How the Papist
                     •
                  s 
                     •
                  buse Antiquitie. howe they vse
Antiquitie, let the single eye judiciouslie
heere-by remarke:
            First,1. By making them 
                     •
                  lu
                     ••
                   Iudg
                     •
                  s over the Ancients. by making themselues
Iudges of the Fathers, whome yet
they pretende to admit as Iudges
over them, by admitting the Interpretations
of such as they list, and
seeme to make for them, and roundlie
rejecting the Expositions of
others; as Bellarmine doeth clearlie,
lib. 1, de Pu
                     •
                  g. cap. 5, of such as make
against them. And as for the Pope,
by giving him vncontrollable power
to over-top them,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   Q
                     ••
                  to. de 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Epist. in 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                assigning to
their wordes his fittest meaning,
yea, and to make to bee the mea
               
                  ••
               ng

which is not, by his celestiall
judgement.
            Next,2 By wresting then meaning. (as is set downe in the

                  •
               xpurgatorie Index of this same

                  •
               ERTRAM) they avowedlie professe,
That in the ancient Catholick
Writers they tolerate manie Er
               
                  •
               ours,
and must extenuate and ex
               
                  •
               use
them, and oftentimes must de
               
                  •
               ye
them, by devysing a fit shi
                  •
               t,

                  •
               nd some handsome meaning vnto
them, when in Disputations they
are opposed against them.
            Besides,3. By razing out of their W
                     ••
                  s what makes against them. howe shameleslie they
raze out of Auncientes whatsoever
maketh against them, their avowed
practise of the same, in the last Edition
of Sainct Augustine, printed at
Paris, by Nivel, in Sainct Iacques
Streete, at the Storks, 1571, in these
wordes doeth testifie, Ex sanctiss.
Tridentini Concilii decreto veterum patrum
codices sunt expurgandi. To
whome I must say as Amb
                     •
                  ose sayde
of olde to the Arrians,
               Orat. 
                     •
                  . contra Arriā. That they
may well blot out the letters, but
the fayth they shall never abolish.
            
               Moreover,4. By rejecting them g
                     •
                  oss
                     •
                  ly. how disdainfullie
                  •
               
times they reject all the Father
                  •
               
and bring in some handsome expo
                  •
               sition
of their owne, to fit their pur
                  •
               pose,
let that practise of Bellarmine
                     •
                  
lib. 1. de purg. cap. 6, giue proof
                  •
               
and in particular of some, (as o
                  •
               
               Tertullian) saying,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                That little cred
                  •
               
is to bee given him: and of others
(as Origen) That hee was accursed
on earth,
                  
                     〈…〉
                   lib. 2. cap. 8. and was seene in Hell a
                  •
               
               ter
death, with Arrius and Nestorius.
            
            Yea, of them all in common h
                  ••
               
spareth not to say, when they mak
                  •
               
against him, Scripta Patrum non sun
                     •
                  
regulae,
               De Co
                     •
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                   2, cap. 12. 
               nec habent authoritatem obligandi.
And againe, Argumenta à veterum
testimonio petita,De Co
                        •
                     cil. I. 1, cap. 
                        •
                     3. posse merito c
                     •
                  ntemni
dum 
                     •
                  a opponuntur.
            
            In like manner, such as they
grant of the Auncientes to bee but
counterfets,5. By calling them Count
                     •
                  rf
                     •
                  ts, wh
                     ••
                   they make against them: but obtruding them as true, when they seeme to make for them. (especiallie affirming
so, when they are adduced against
them) in peremptor manner they
obtrude them as true, when they
seeme to make for them, as the

cleare collation of the ensuing places
will evidentlie giue notice: Bella
                     •
                  m.
lib. 1, de Christo, cap. 10, compared
with lib. 2, de Pont. cap. 16.
Also lib. 2, de Missa, cap. 12, compa
               
                  •
               ed
with lib. 1, de Verbo, cap. 14.
            In the same forme they vse
their owne moste famous Writers,6. By calling them manif
                     •
                  st L
                     •
                  ars. 
               
                  •
               nd Histriographers, calling them

                  •
               eart Liars, when they make
against them, as Bellarmine doeth

                  
                     •
                  ozomen and Socrates, lib. 1, de Cleri
                  
                     •
                  is,
cap. 20: and yet as moste faythfull
Writers hee vseth them to
prooue this point, lib. 4, de Pont.
cap. 9.
            Neither may I omit the shamelesse
corrupting of the Fathers,7. By putting in fal
                     •
                  e words of their owne in the Writs of the Auncients. by
putting in false wordes, as well as

                  •
               hey raze out the true: Examples
whereof in place of manie wee may
see in Bellarmine, lib. 2, de verbo, cap.
               
                  •
               2: where hee citeth Chrysostome to
haue 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , where hee hath truelie

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : and lib. 2. de reliq. Sanctor.
cap. 3, hee maketh Chrysostome to say
in his Sermon of luventius and Maximus,

Tumules Martyrum adoremu
                     •
                  .
where there is no such word in t
                  ••
               
Greeke.
            And as wee haue showne,8 By call
                     ••
                  g the most ancient Councels false. and fraud
                     •
                  ull. how
they vse the ancient Fathers at the
pleasure, so how they vse ancie
                  ••
               
Councels, when they make not f
                  ••
               
them, let Bellarmine declare in h
                  ••
               
Preface, De summo Pontifice, and e
                  •
               
where; accusing the second gen
                  •
               
               rall
Councell of Heresie, for oppug
                  ••
               ning
the Papall Supremacie,B
                     •
                  ll l. 1, de L
                     •
                   i
                  
                     ••
                  , cap. 20. 
               An
                     •
                  
381: and the Councell of Chalcedo
                     •
                  
               
holden Anno 451,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   1, de P
                     ••••
                  , cap. 9 of falshood an
                  •
               
fraude, while as yet they will haue
the Pope onelie with his privat
                  •
               
Consistorie, whether hee erre, 
                  〈◊〉
               
not, to be obedientlie believed.
            But moste clearelie (to con
                  •
               clude)
how despisinglie they reject
not onelie humane Antiquitie,9. But most of all, in pudentlie rejecting
                     •
                   and tran
                     •
                  gre
                     •
                  
                  sing (by their owne Con
                     ••
                  ss
                     •
                  on, the most sacre
                     •
                   Antiquitie of 
                     •
                  ll, which is that of scripturall Precept, and Christ
                     •
                  s practise. b
                  ••
               
divine there-withall, how ever the
                  •
               
brag of nothing more, let their ow
                  ••
               
plaine Confession in that Councel
                  •
               
of Constance, Sess. 13, beare witnesse
                  •
               
where concerning the taking away
the Cup from the people, they say
                  •
               
               
Albeit Christ instituted the Supper
vnder both kyndes of Bread and
Wine; and such-lyke, albeit in the
primitiue Church this Sacrament
was received vnder both kindes,
yet for avoyding some dangers, let
it be taken heere-after by Laiks onlie
vnder one kynd,Concil. Trid. S
                     •
                  ss. 5, cap. 3, can. 1. and that vnder
the paine of a Curse, as the Councell
of Trent hath decreed.
            So that as the chiefe Priests, and
Elders, and all the Councell, sought
false witnesses against Christ, and
tho manie came; yet found they
none, till at last two came: Even so,
altho the Pope, and all his Councell,
seeke busilie false witnesses
against Christes blessed Trueth registrate
in Scripture, yet amongst
these reverend Fathers, and ancient
Doctors of the primitiue Church,
they shall finde none conspyring so
together in everie age, as they alleadge
for them: &amp; tho they would
make a show of manie who seeme
to say for them, yet in effect the judicious
and vnpartiall Reader and

remarker shall finde it so no wise,
till some came in in later tymes for
the behoose of that Romish high
Priest, and few Pople in great store
in the Lords field, and thorow faire
pretences, and secret subdolous
meanes which they vsed, and the
not so warie vigilancie of the Lords
owne Servants, altho they were not
so clearelie perceived, nor heedfullie
resisted in the beginnings, yet
when that wicked seede beganne to
kythe more plainlie by anie growth
and discoverie of it selfe, it was
remarked by sundrie vvho vvere
awake, and from tyme to tyme opposed
by some, tho few, who were
as Elias in Achabs time, or the two
afflicted witnesses spoken of in the
Revelation, who were still suppressed
as they rose and spake, or els killed
by that bloodie Beaft.
            A particular prooffe of the
trueth heereof your Honours may
see in these worthie Monuments of
Antiquitie, concerning that maine
pillar whereon Poperie standeth,TRANSVESTANTIATION.
               
the verie Soule of their Soule-Masses;
which beeing taken away, lyke
Dagons house, it falleth to the
ground, and the palmes of the
handes of that proude Idole are cut
off, where-by for their spirituall
merchandize they so largelie receiue.
            COnsidering then the worthie
paines that the Pennes of the
godlie of our Neighbour-Nation
from time to time haue taken, for
the common benefite of all, in
translating sundrie worthie Authors,
for comforting and confirming
the truelie religious amongst
them; as also finding how that glorious
reformed and refined Church
of France had not suffered the same
to bee hid from the eyes of their
people, and had therefore translated
the same into their natiue Idiom;
the sight whereof in that worthie
Gentle-mans Librarie, George Ogilvie
of Carnusie, (a Lover of Letters, and
the Learned) did much encourage

me to put Pen to Paper. And therewith
considering with what serious
intreatie that great &amp; glorious Martyr,
                  
                     •
                  ooke of. Martyrs, Fol. 1660.
Bishop Hooper, at his going to
the fyre, made to Doctor Brookes,
then Bishop of Glocester, for his right
information in the matter of the
Sacrament; desiring him to reade
this worthie BERTRAM, whom in
a singular and earnest manner hee
recommended vnto him.
            Weighing these together, (I
say) and viewing with what rare
light, as a cleare Torch-bearer, this
man so long since hath gone before,
howsoever others worthilie of late
haue followed after, I was moved
to bestow some paines in exposing
it (especiallie in these dangerous
dayes) to the common view of all:
whereby if our spirituall Nasci &amp;
Pasci, the new birth, and new repaste,
be compared, and the trueth,
or realitie of both, according to the
effectuall force and vertue which a
thing hath, be rightlie considered,

(which maketh the verie renewed
Gentile to be a true Iew indeed) so far
as ignorant Nicodemus swarved by
his literall and carnall meaning,Rom. 2, 29. from the true vnderstanding of
Christs words, when Hee spake of
the one; as farre with the carnall
Capernaite shall our Adversaries bee
groslie found to erre, by their like
literall and carnall meaning, from
the true vnderstanding of Christs
words, when he spake of the other.
And that to them as clearelie Hee
showeth the way to vnderstand
aright the true manducation of His
Bodie, while as Hee sayeth, The
wordes that I speake, are spirite and
lyfe,
               Iohn, 6, 63. as Hee pointeth at the true
meaning of His wordes, that a man
must be borne of new againe, while
as Hee sayeth, Except a man be borne
of water,
               Iohn, 3, 5. 
               and the spirite, he cannot enter
into the Kingdome of GOD.
            
            These paines then that I haue
taken heerein, with a most duetifull
hand, &amp; devoted heart, to your Honours

gracious acceptation, humblie
doe I offer the same, without
assentation, (which least of anie
becommeth not my calling) ceasing
to blaze mans praise; and as
best befits mee, I pray to God, that
the deepe Impression of His Image,
who is the viue Character of the
Father, may by the powerfull hand
of his Spirit bee so seated and setled
in your heartes, that by that heavenlie
Stampe it thay bee both inwardlie
witnessed to your owne
Consciences, and outwardlie testified
in your liues to the world, that
Your Honoures are the adopted
Children of that heavenlie Father,
whome as You set Your selues to
glorifie on earth, hee shall not (after
the heaping of much Honour
and Happinesse vpon You and
Yours) fayle to glorifie You in the
highest Heavens, which is the full
Felicitie and blessed Rest of His
owne Sainctes, and which, as the
highest of all Wishes, I shall not

ceasse to beseech GOD to effectuate
towardes YOVR HONOVRS,
and YOVR Hopefull
and Happie Off-spring.
            Your Honoures,
in all humble
duetie,
WILLIAM GVILD.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE READER.
            THis Popish Plasma, bred of Hydra's Braine,
            Come from the Snakie Cerberus his Lake;
            Which Pitchie-Charon-Popes for trueth maintaine,
            And it a Fulcre of their Fayth doth make.
            Loe! GVILD but guyle doth here expand their Packe
            Of wicked Wares, vnto judicious view:
            That who so reades this Booke, may notise take,
            And clearlie see this Paradox vntrue.
            By written Word, and Antiquaries olde,
            He doth this Dogma dash, and Trueth vnfolde.
            WALTER FORBES.
         
         
            
            The Life of
BERTRAM,
PRIEST,
BY IOHN TRITHEMIVS,
a Popish Histriographer.
            
               
                  BERTRAM,
PRIEST, and
MONKE, was
one that was singularlie
Skilfull in holie
Scripture, and notablie
learned in like manner in humane Sciences,
of a most pregnant and quicke wit,

of an excellent and eloquent vtterance:
Neyther was hee lesse Notable and renowned
for his holie lyfe, than his
great learning.
            Hee wrote manie excellent Workes,
and Treatises, where-of not-with-standing
few haue beene suffered to come to
our knowledge: but in especiall, hee
wrote a most laudable and prayse-worthie
Worke of Predestination, vnto
King Charls, Brother to Lotharius
the Emperour: and like-wyse a Booke
of the Bodie and Blood of the LORD.
Hee lived in the tyme of Lotharius
the Emperour aforesaid,
in the YEARE of
GOD
840.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            BERTRAM
His Treatise
Of the Bodie and Blood
OF CHRIST:
TO CHARLES, King of FRANCE,
Nephew to CHARLES, the
Great Emperour.
            
               THE PREFACE.
               
                  YOu command
(Renowned Prince)
that what I thinke
concerning the mysterie
of the Bodie &amp;
Blood of CHRIST,
I should signifie to your Highnesse:
A Commandement (indeede) in

howe much worthie of your high
Soveraignitie to enjoyne, in so
much moste harde to my small
strength to performe: For what
is more worthie of Royall providence,
than catholicklie to vnderstand
His holy Mysteries who hath
deigned to bestowe vpon you that
princelie Throne, and not to suffer
your Subjectes divers
                     •
                  ie to bee distracted
in Opinions concerning
the Bodie and Blood of CHRIST,
wherein doeth consist the summe
of Christian Redemption?
               For while some of the Faithfull
affirme,The state of the Cont
                        •
                     oversie. that the mysterie of the Bodie
and Blood of Christ, which is
daylie celebrated in the Church, is
to bee considered without anie figure
or vaile, (of vsuall, to wit,
and sacramentall speach) and to be
taken onelie according to the naked
simplicitie of the verie literall
words: and others againe, that these
things are set downe, and comprehended
vnder a figure, and mysticallie;
so that it is one thing which

is seene by the bodilie sight, and
another thing altogether diverse
which the eye of fayth onelie beholdeth.
Heereby it commeth to
passe, that no little strife is found to
bee amongst them.
               And seeing the Apostle writeth
to the faythfull,1. Corinth. 1. that they thinke
and speake all one thing, and that
no division be seene to be amongst
them; they are not then a litle divyded,
who speake so diverslie of the
Bodie and Blood of Christ, not
beeing alike minded.
               Wherefore your Royall Majestie,
stirred vp by the zeale of Fayth,
weighing these things aright, and
desiring according to the Apostles
direction, that all thinke and speake
one thing, doeth diligentlie search
the hid trueth of this point, that
you may call backe the wanderers
vnto it: whence it is that you disdaine
not to inquire the veritie therof,
even from them of the meanest
ranke, knowing that the mysterie
of such an hid secret cannot bee vnderstood

but by God his revealing
of the same, who without exception
of persons showeth foorth the
light of his trueth by whomsoever
he chooseh.
               But in how much it is pleasing
to my meannes to obey your command,
it is as hard to dispute concerning
a matter most distant from
humane senses, and not to be passed
thorow without the instruction of
the Spirit of God.
               Beeing subject then to the direction
of your Highnesse, and confyding
in his favour and aide concerning
whom we speake, in as few
words as I can, not trusting to mine
owne wit, but following the footesteps
of the holie Fathers, I shall
open vp what I thinke in this matter.
            
            
               
               
                  YOVR High
Excellence desires
then to vnderstād,The two Questions which this Trea
                        •
                     ise proponeth.
If that Bodie and
Blood of CHRIST
which is taken by
the mouth of the Faythfull in the
Church, bee taken so in a mysterie,
or according to a literall veritie?
that is, Whether it containe some
secret thing, which is onlie manifest
to the eyes of Fayth? or without
the covering of anie such mysterie,
if the eyes of the bodie beholde
that outwardlie, which the soule
and mynde doeth beholde inwardlie?
               That the whole matter which
is in hand then, may appeare manifest,
and if it bee that same Bodie
which was borne of the Virgine
Marie, which suffered, died, and
was buried, and rising againe, ascended

to heaven, and sitteth now
at the right hand of the Father; let
vs looke throughlie first to the former
of these questions.
               And lest we be intangled within
the obscure circuit of ambiguous
and doubtfull words,The fi
                        •
                     st Question is, Whether the literal sense, or a figu
                        •
                      at 
                        •
                     e, is to be 
                        •
                     etained in the word
                        •
                     s of the LORDES Supper? we must first
define what a figure is, and what
we call literall veritie, that so eyeing
some certaine thing, we may know
assuredlie whither to direct the
course of this our present discourse.
               A figure then,He call
                        •
                     th at a figure, which we cal a Tro
                           ••
                        , and C
                           ••
                        ero. the ligh
                        •
                     es of speach. is a certaine overshadowing
of a thing with some
vailes (or ornaments of speach)
manifesting so what it intendes, as
for example,So Sacramentes are visible wordes, and externall 
                        •
                     ig
                        ••
                     es, wherby (as Loinbard sayeth, lib. 4, dist. 1.) we are taught in heavenly matters. when wee speake of
the worde, wee call it Bread, as in
the Lords Prayer, when wee desire
to bee given vs our daylie Bread, or
when Christ (who is the incarnate
worde) speaking in the Gospell,
sayeth of himselfe, I am the living
Bread, which came downe from Heaven:
                  Iohn, 6, &amp; 15.
Or when hee calleth him
                     •
                  elfe
a Vine, and his Disciples Branches;

all these speaches say one thing, and
signifie another.
               But [literall] veritie is the demonstration
of a manifest thing not
covered with anie resemblances of
shadowing,He c
                        •
                     lleth that V
                        •
                     ritie, which is a proper speach: and which there
                     
                        •
                     fter hee calleth a proprietie. Therefore Augustine sayeth, lib. 3, contra Maxim, Sacramentes are one thing, but signifie another. Therfore wee must beware, that wee take not a figuratiue spe
                        •
                     ch according to the let
                        ••
                     r, lib. 3, de do
                           ••
                        . Christ. cap. 10. but insinuated in its
owne pure and proper (and that
wee may speake more plainlie) in
its owne naturall and manifest signification,
as when Christ is said to
be borne of the Virgine Marie, suffered,
was crucified, died, and buried;
there is nothing heere over shadowed
with covering figures; but the
veritie of the thing is showne by
the proper signification of the naturall
words themselues; neither may
wee vnderstand anie other thing
heere than is spoken. But in the
former examples it was not so: for
Christ substantiallie is not Bread,
nor a Vine, neither were the Apostles
Branches; wherefore heere is
pointed foorth a figure: but in the
preceeding speaches the literall veritie,
that is, the plaine and open

meaning in a cleare discourse is manifestlie
showne.
               But let VS returne to that for
whose cause these thinges are formerlie
spoken, to wit, to the consideration
of the Bodie, and Blood
of Christ:
               For if the mysterie thereof bee
celebrated without anie figure,1. Argument, taken from the nature of a mysterie. it is
not convenientlie called a mysterie;
seeing that cannot bee called a mysterie,
wherein there is no secret
thing, nothing removed from our
corporall senses, nothing hid with
some coverture or other: But that
bread which by the administration
of the Priest is made the Bodie of
Christ, showeth one thing to the
outward senses of men, and cryeth
another thing inwardlie to the
soules of the Faythfull: Outwardlie
the Bread is that selfe-same which it
was before; for wee see that same
shape, and colour, and that same savour
thereof is also perceived; but
inwardly a farre more different, precious,
and excellent thing is intimated

and exhibite, because it is heavenlie
and divine; that is, the Bodie
of Christ is showne vnto vs, which
is not seene with these fleshlie eyes,
but is seene, and taken, and eaten,
by the looking on of a faythfull
soule.
               The Wine also which by the
Priestlie consecration is made the
Sacrament of Christs Blood,2. Argument, from the judgement of our senses
                        •
                      and from experience
                        •
                      v
                        •
                     to which judgement Christ him selfe eppealeth, Luke, 24. representeth
one thing outwardlie, and
containeth another thing inwardlie;
for what see wee outwardly, but
the substance of Wine? taste it, and
it is Wine; smell it, and it savours
Wine; looke to it, and you shall beholde
the colour of Wine: But if
it bee considered inwardlie in the
mynde, it tasteth not as Wine, but
as the Blood of Christ, vnto the Believers
soules, and is acknowledged
so while it is seene, and is approven
while it is so smelled.
               These things to bee so, it is manifest,
seeing no man can denye the
same; because that Bread and that
Wine figuratiuelie onelie is the Bodie

and Blood of Christ: for in that
Bread, as is clearelie seene, there is
no flesh knowne to bee in it; or in
that Wine anie drop of blood to
bee pointed foorth, while as after
this mysticall consecration they are
not-with-standing neyther called
Bread nor Wine, but the Bodie and
blood of Christ.
               For if according to some there
bee nothing taken figuratiuely in
this Sacrament,3. Argument, from the nature of fayth, whose propertie is 
                        •
                     o be
                        •
                      conver
                        ••••
                      about spiritual subjectes. Heb
                        •
                     . 11, 1. but all bee considered
according to the 
                     •
                  oresaide verball
veritie, (or literall meaning)
then faith worketh nothing heere,
because there is nothing heere considered
spirituallie, but all whatsoever,
is taken corporallie. And seeing
fayth, according to the Apostle,
Heb. 11. 1, is an evidence of things
which appeare not, that is, not of
those substances which are seene,
we shall get nothing heere by fayth,
because whatsoever is heere, falleth
vnder, and wee judge it with our
corporall senses.
               There is nothing more absurd4. Argument, diffe
                        ••
                     t things cannot be pred
                        ••
                     ble one of another
                        •
                      but the br
                        ••
                     d and the bodi
                        •
                      of Christ are different, &amp;c. L
                           •
                        go.
                  
                  
also than to take that bread to bee
flesh carnallie, or to say that that
Wine is Blood reallie; for so it will
not bee a mysterie, seeing there is
no secret nor hid thing in this sort
of speach anie way contained.
               How likewise are these sayde to
be the Bodie and Blood of Christ?
seeing there is no change vnderstood
to bee made of them;5. Argument, from the 
                        ••
                     du
                     
                        •
                     uon of diverse forces of substanti
                        •
                     ll changes, whereof Tr
                        •
                     nsubs
                        •
                     ntiation 
                        〈◊〉
                      e
                        •
                      1. o
                        ••
                     . for all 
                     〈◊〉
                  
change is either from that which is
not, into that which is, or from that
which is, into that which is not, or
from that which alreadie is, into
another which in like manner is.
But in this Sacrament, if the trueth
in simplicitie be onelie considered,
and none other thing bee believed
by the senses than that which they
see, there shall none alteration heere
bee seene to bee made.
               For neither is there a change
out of that which was not, into that
which is, which manner of change
is seene in things growing, seeing
they were not before, but that they
may haue a being, they are changed

from not being, into that which
hath a being: But this Bread and
Wine were, before they were turned
into the bodie and blood of
Christ. Neither is there such a
mutation as of that which hath a
being, changing into that which
hath no being; which sort of alteration
is in thinges perishing by decaying;
for whatsoever decayeth,
first of necessitie had some being;
neither can that suffer such an alteration,
which never had a being.
Now that this sort of alteration, is
not in the Sacrament, is cleare lykewyse;
because according to the
trueth, the forme of the creature
which it had before, is knowne as
yet constantlie to remaine.
               Also, there is an alteration
which is of that which hath a being,
into that which lyke-wyse hath a
being; which sort is seene in things
suffering a change in their qualities
onelie, (the substance remaining)
as when that which was white, is
changed into that which is blacke:

but neither is this alteration known
to be made in this Sacrament; for
there is nothing found heere to bee
changed, neither in touching, nor
colour, nor favour. If therefore
there bee nothing heere changed,
the elements are none other, than
that they were before.
               But heere the Bread and Wine
are other things,6. Argument, from a S
                        •
                     cr
                        •
                     
                     mentall sort of 
                        〈◊〉
                     , which must be granted in 
                        〈…〉
                     
                   because the bread
is made to bee the bodie, and the
wine the blood of Christ; for so saith
he himselfe, Take, eate, this is my
bodie: and so of the Cup, Take drinke,
this is the blood of the new Testament,
&amp;c. Wee must then demande of
them, who will vnderstand nothing
heere figuratiuelie, but all things to
consist in verball simplicitie, wherein
this alteration is made? seeing
they are not nowe these thinges
which they were before, to wit,
bread and wine, but are the bodie
and blood of Christ; for according
to the forme and shape of visible
thinges, both these haue in themselues
(substantiallie) none alteration:

and if they haue suffered no
alteration, they are nothing else but
that which they were before.
               Wherefore (Renowned Prince)
your Highnesse seeth to what point
these of the contrarie opinion are
driven; for they denye that which
they are thought to affirme, and
that which they belieue, they are
found to destroy.
               For they confesse truelie, that
it is the bodie and blood of Christ:
and when they say this, without
doubt they graunt, that the bread
and wine is not that nowe which
they were before: and if they bee
other than they were, then they are
changed, seeing that cannot bee
denyed. Let them therefore tell
wherein they are changed? for we
see nothing corporallie to be changed
in them: of necessitie then they
must confesse either that they are
changed in some other respect, (to
wit, in vse) and consequentlie not
to bee that which they otherwise
are seene to bee in veritie, but another

thing which they are not seene
to be according to their owne proper
and substantiall existence. Or
if they will not confesse this, they
shall bee constrayned to denye, that
they are the bodie and bloode of
Christ at all: which not onelie is
abhominable to say, but to thinke
onelie.
               But because they will confesse,
that they are the bodie and blood
of Christ, neither could they haue
beene so, except the change had
beene to the better; neither is that
change corporallie, but spirituallie
made, of necessitie the speach thereof
is figuratiue; because vnder the
vaile or curtaine (as it were) of
corporall bread and wine, is convoyed
vnto the soule the spirituall
bodie and bloode of Christ: Not
that these are the existences of two
diverse things, to wit, as of a bodie
and a spirit, but one and that same
selfe thing, according to one consideration
is a sort of bread and wine,
and according to another is the bodie

and blood of Christ: according
to that, as they are touched corporallie,
they are kyndes of corporall
creatures; but according to that
power whereby they are made so
spirituallie, they are the mysteries
of the bodie and blood of Christ.
               Let vs consider also the Laver
of holie Baptisme,7. Argument, from B
                        •
                      p
                        ••••
                     , wher
                        ••
                     n the water change
                        •
                     h not its 
                        〈◊〉
                      nature; therefore neyther the bread and w
                        •
                     ne in the Lords Supp
                        ••
                     . which worthilie
is called the fountaine of life, because
it reformeth the commers vnto
it, by the newnesse of a better
life, and gif
                     •
                  eth them that are dead
in sinne, with liuelie grace and righteousnesse:
according to that it is
the element of water, hath it that
power? and yet except it had the
vertue of Sanctification, it could
not wash away the blot of sinne: and
except it contained the strength of
life, it could no wise giue life to the
dead: not in the flesh, (I meane)
but in the soule. And yet if wee
consider, in that fountaine onelie
that which our bodilie eye perceiveth,
it is seene to bee a moyst element,
subject to corruption, having

no power, but to wash onelie the
bodie: but the accessorie vertue of
the holie Spirit, by priestlie consecration,
maketh it pithie, not onelie
to wash away the filth of the bodie,
but also to purge, by a spirituall
grace, the foulenesse of the soule.
               Beholde then, in one, and that
same element, wee see two contrarieties
to remaine; that is, that which
is subject to corruption, to giue incorruption;
and that which hath no
lyfe, to giue lyfe. It is manifest
then, into that fountaine to be both
that which the corporall senses seeketh,
and therefore to bee changeable,
and corruptible: and againe
that also to bee in it, which onelie
sayth beholdeth, and therefore cannot
bee corrupted, nor suffer the
losse of lyfe. If thou consider it,
as it washeth outwardlie, it is an element;
but if thou weigh it, as it
cleanseth inwardlie, it is the power
of lyfe, of sanctification, and immortalitie.
Therefore in the proper
nature thereof it is corruptible

water, but in the mysterie thereof,
and holie vse, it is curing grace:
even so that which is called the bodie
and blood of Christ, in the outward
show considered, it is a creature,
subject to mutabilitie, and corruption,
but if wee consider the vertue
of the mysterie thereof, it is life,
giving immortalitie to the partakers
thereof.
               These thinges then are not all
one,8. Argument, from 
                        〈◊〉
                      for that which 
                        〈…〉
                      the body 
                        〈…〉
                      he 
                        〈◊〉
                      or 
                        〈◊〉
                      which i
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      of the bodie. as they are seene, and as they
are believed: for according to that
as they are seene, they beeing corruptible,
they feed the bodie which
is corruptible; but as they are believed,
beeing immortall, they feede
our soules to immortal
                     ••
                  ie.
               
                  The Apostle also writing to the
Corinths,1. Cor 10. 9 Arg
                        •
                     ment, from 
                        〈◊〉
                      Apostl
                        •
                     . his 
                        〈◊〉
                      Our F
                        •
                     thers in the Ser, 
                        〈…〉
                      and in the water that pushed out of the Rocke, were p
                        ••
                     t
                        •
                     
                     kers of Christ his bodie and blood; otherwise they shoulde no
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      vnto the faythfu
                        •
                     l in the Old. Testam
                        •
                     t that which th
                        •
                     y 
                        〈◊〉
                      but all the form
                        •
                     , non 
                        〈◊〉
                      of them required not the 
                        •
                     o porall prefence of that which they signi
                        ••
                     ied. ther
                     
                        •
                     oe according to the invisible 
                        •
                     fficacie of the holie Ghost onelie they had their 
                        〈◊〉
                      men
                        ••
                     ll force
                        •
                      as doeth the LORDES Supp. 
                        •
                     . sayeth, I would not, Brethen,
that you should bee
                     •
                   ignorant, that all
our Fathers were vnder the Cloude, and
all passed though the Sea, and were all
baptized vnto Moses in the Cloude, and
in the Sea, and did cate the same spirituall
meate, and drinke the same spirituall
drinke: For they dranke of that spirituall

Rocke that followed them, and that
Rocke was CHRIST.
               
               Wee perceiue then, that the
Sea, and the Cloude, did carrie a figure
of Baptisme, and that our Fathers
in the olde Testament haue
beene baptized in them. Now,
could the Sea, in that it was an element,
haue in it the vertue of Baptisme?
or could the Cloude, in that
respect it did kythe the thickest part
of the aire, sanctifie the people?
Neither can we say, that the Apostle
(speaking in Christ) hath sayde
vntruelie, that our Fathers were
baptized in the water, and in the
cloude. And albeit that Baptisme
did not represent the same forme of
Baptisme of Christ which is nowe
vsed in the Church daylie, yet notwithstanding
no man, in his wits
can denye, but it was a sort of Baptisme,
and in it our Fathers to haue
beene baptized; except, madlie, he
presume to gaine-say the Apostles
wordes.
               Therefore the sea and the cloud,

in that they are naturall bodies, giue
not the cleannesse of sanctification,
but according to that they contained
in them invisiblie the sanctification
of the holie Spirit; for there
was in them a visible forme, which
might appeare to the corporall senses
of all, not in similitude, but in
the veritie it selfe; and inwardlie a
spirituall power shyned, which appeared,
not to carnall eyes, but to
the eyes onelie of the soules of the
godlie.
               Like-wyse the heavenlie Foode
which rayned from Heaven, and
the water that gushed from the
rocke, was corporall, and fedde and
watered the people corporallie: yet
not-with-standing the Apostle calleth
that M
                        •
                     nna, and the water Spirituall
Food. Wherefore serveth this?
Because there was a spirituall power
of the word of GOD in these
substances, which did feede and water
rather the soules of the believers,
than their bodies.
               
                  And altho that meate and drinke
fore-shewed the mysterie of the bodie
and blood of Christ,10, Argument, from the intern
                        •
                     ll matter of the Sacrament
                        •
                     s: Our F
                        •
                     th
                        •
                     rs were m
                        •
                     d
                        •
                      pa
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     
                     k
                        •
                     ts of Christ, but wee are m
                        •
                     de 
                        〈◊〉
                      of Christ: 
                        〈◊〉
                     , both wee and they of one thing. then onelie
to come, which the Church nowe
celebrateth as come; not-with-standing
the holie Apostle affirmeth
constantlie, That our Fathers did
eate that same spirituall foode, and
did drinke that same spirituall
drinke.
               Perhaps then thou wilt aske,
what hee meaneth by that same spirituall
meate and drinke? To wit,
Even that same which the Children
of the faythfull eate and drinke
now-a
                     •
                   dayes in the Church: for
wee must not conceiue diverselie
heere, because one, and that selfesame
CHRIST, who fed the people
in the Desart, being baptized in
the water, and the clowde, hee watered
them then with his bloode,
which hee gaue them to drinke, and
fed them then with his flesh: and
nowe in the Church of the Faythfull
hee feedeth his people with the
same bread of his bodie, and giveth

them the same water of his bloode,
both for drinke and nowrishment.
Which thing the Apostle did goe
about to signifie, when hee sayde,
That our Fathers did eate that same
spiritual food, and dranke that same
spirituall drinke: and therefore hee
did consequentlie adde, That they
dranke of that Spirituall Rocke
which followed them, and the
Rocke was CHRIST: that wee
might there-by vnderstand, that
Christ in the Desart did consist in
that spirituall Rocke, and gaue to
the people the water of his bloode.
Who there-after having taken flesh
of the Virgine, hath given him selfe
in our tyme vnto the death of the
Crosse, for the saving of the faythfull:
and since that tyme hath shed
the water of his blood, where-by
not onelie wee might bee redeemed,
but also where-of wee might
plentifullie drinke.
               A wonderfull mysterie indeed,
because incomprehensible, and inestimable!
Hee had not as yet taken

on the shape of Man, Hee had
not as yet tasted of Death, for the
safetie of the Worlde, Hee had not
as yet redeemed vs, with his precious
blood, when alreadie our Fathers
in the Desart, by Spirituall
Food, and invisible Drinke, did eate
his bodie, and drinke his blood, as
the Apostle t
                     •
                  stifyeth, when hee affirmeth
our Fathers to haue eaten
that same Spirituall Food, &amp; drunken
that same Spirituall Drinke:
Not that how the same was done is
to bee inquired; but Fayth that it
was so done, is to bee acquired: For
that selfe-same GOD, who in his
Church, by his Almightie power,
changeth the Bread and Wine, into
his Flesh and Blood, after a Spirituall
manner; that selfe-same GOD
(I saye) turned in the verie like
sorte the Manna which rayned from
Heaven, into his owne bodie vnto
them invisiblie; and turned the water,
gushing out of the rocke, into
his owne blood.
               
                  Which thing David vnderstanding,11. Argument, from o
                        ••
                      feleo
                        •
                      pur
                        ••••
                     rs o
                        •
                      that 
                        •
                     pirituall and 
                        •••
                     
                     
                     
                        •••
                     lie foode. The Angels did not
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      of that corpo
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     ll Manna, 
                        〈◊〉
                      of that spirituall; therefore even so the 
                        •
                     aythfull, not in a corpor
                        •
                     ll, but in a spirituall manner, by fayth doe 
                        •
                     ate the 
                        •
                     od
                        •
                     e of CHRIST. hee declared the same manifestlie,
beeing instructed by the holie
Ghost, saying, that Man did eate
the bread of Angels. For it is a
thing to bee laughed at, to suppose
that that corporall Manna given to
the Fathers, doeth feede that heavenlie
hoaste, or that they doe eate
anie such meate, who are filled with
the Banquets of that Heavenlie
worde. The Psalmist surelie showeth,
or rather the Spirite of God
speaking by the Psalmist, either what
our Fathers by that heavenlie Manna
did receiue, or what the faythfull
nowe in the mysterie of the bodie
and blood of Christ ought to conceiue,
and belieue. In both these
(surelie) Christ him selfe is meant,
who feedeth the soules of the earthlie
believers, and is the meat of the
heavenlie Angels: and both this is
done, not with a corporall tasting,
nor by a bodily foode, but by the
vertue of the spirituall word.
               
                  And vvee vnderstand by the
Evangelistes rehearsing,12. Argument, from the c
                        •
                     rcumstance of the tyme of the 
                        〈◊〉
                      rat
                        •
                     on and institution of the Lords Supp
                        ••
                     s Matthew, 20. that our
Lord Iesus Christ, before that hee
suffered, taking bread, gaue thanks,
and gaue to his disciples, saying,
This is my Bodie which is given for
you; doe this in remembrance of Mee.
Likewyse He tooke the Cup, after
Supper, saying, This Cup is the New
Testament in my Blood, which is shed
for you: Where wee see that Christ
as yet had not suffered, and yet the
mysterie of his bodie and his blood
was alreadie celebrated: for wee
thinke not, that anie of the faythfull
will doubt, that that bread was
made the bodie of Christ, which
giving to his disciples, hee sayeth
thereof, This is my Bodie, which is
given for you: Neither that they will
doubt, that that Cup doeth containe
the blood of Christ (sacramentallie,
to wit) concerning the which hee sayeth also, This Cup is
the new Testament in my blood, which
shalbe shed for you: So that a little
before hee suffered, hee could thus

haue changed that substance of
bread, and creature of wine, into his
owne bodie which was to suffer,
and into his blood, which was to be
shed: and so also he was able to convert
that heavenlie foode after the
same manner that rained in the wildernesse,
and that water which gushed
out of the Rocke, into his bodie
and blood, albeit that long after
hee was incarnate, and his flesh was
to hang vpon the Crosse for vs, and
his blood was to bee shed for our
ablution.
               Heere also wee ought to consider
how the words are to bee taken
which himselfe sayeth,Iohn, 6. 
                        •
                     3 Argument, from the absued and wicked v
                        ••
                     l 
                        〈◊〉
                     , which necessar
                        ••••
                      followeth that gross
                        •
                      &amp; 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        ••
                     t
                        •
                     ng of Chi
                        •
                     stes 
                        •
                     od
                        ••
                     . 
                  Except yee
eate the flesh of the Sonne of man, and
drinke his blood, yee haue no lyfe in you.
Hee sayeth not, that his flesh which
did hang vpon the crosse should be
cutted in pieces, and eaten by his
Disciples; or that his blood, which
was to bee shed for the redemption
of the worlde, was to bee given to
his Disciples to drinke, for that were
a facinorous and an abhominable

thing, if either his blood were so
drunken, or his flesh eaten; according,
as that grosse and incredulous
people thought. Wherefore in the
words following,14. Argument, from Christes visible as
                        •••
                     
                     sion, and the estat
                        •
                      of his glorious bodie in heaven: not to be broken any more, or catnallie to be eaten by p
                        •••••
                     ale on earth. hee sayeth to his
Disciples, who indeede believed his
words, but not as yet had throughlie
pearced vnto their right meaning,
Doeth this (sayeth hee) offend
you? what therefore if yee shall see the
Sonne of man going vp, where hee was
before? As if he would haue sayde,
Yee shall not thinke that my bodie
is to bee divyded in partes amongst
you, to bee eaten corporallie, or my
blood to be so drunken; when after
my resurrection yee shall see mee
going vp to the heavens, with the
whole fulnesse of my bodie and
blood, then ye shall vnderstand that
my flesh is to be eaten by the faythfull:
not as these grosse and incredulous
people doe thinke, but truelie,
and in a mysticall manner, bread
and wine being converted (sacramentallie,
to wit) into the substance

of my bodie and blood, to
bee taken by the faythfull.
               And thereafter hee lyke-wyse
sayeth,
                     15. Argument, from the Author of that 
                           〈◊〉
                        , whereof the 
                           〈…〉
                         by the 
                           〈◊〉
                         to wit, the 
                           〈◊〉
                        , which qu
                           ••
                        
                        keneth.
                     Where wee haue to no
                           •
                        , 
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                   
                  It is the Spirit that quickeneth,
the flesh profiteth nothing. Hee sayeth,
the flesh profiteth nothing that way
as the incredulous Capernaites vnderstood:
for other-wise it giveth
lyfe, as it is taken in a mysterie by
the faythfull. And hee showeth
manifestlie himselfe wherefore this
is, when hee sayeth, It is the Spirit
that quickneth. Therefore in this
mysterie of the bodie and blood of
Christ, there is a spirituall operation
which giveth lyfe; without the
which operation these mysteries
profite nothing, because they may
feede the bodie indeede, but they
cannot nowrish the soule.
               But heere aryseth a question,
which sundrie doe propone; affirming,
That these thinges are not figuratiuelie
to bee vnderstood, but
according to the verie literall veritie:
which while they say, they withall
gaine-say the writings of the holie

Fathers. Sainct Augustine, one of
the chiefe Doctors of the Church,
in his third Booke concerning the
doctrine of Christ, writeth so; Except
yee eate (sayeth our Saviour) the
flesh of the Sonne of man, and drinke
his blood, yee shall not haue lyfe in you.
Hee seemeth to command a wicked
and facinorous fact; but hee doeth
not so: for he speaketh figuratiuelie,
commanding vs to communicate
of the Passion of the Lord; and that
wee should profitablie and comfortablie
lay it vp in our mynde, That
his bodie was crucified, and wounded
for vs.
               Wee see then, that Augustine
sayeth,16. Argument. from the 
                        〈◊〉
                      of 
                        〈◊〉
                      who sayeth, 
                        〈…〉
                      wordes 
                        〈…〉
                     . that the mysterie of the bodie
and blood of Christ, is to be celebrated
by the faythfull, vnder a
figure, or in resemblance: for to eate
his flesh, and drinke his blood carnallie,
it is not a point of Religion,
but of wicked villanie: amongst
whom were these, who in the Gospell
vnderstanding the wordes of
our Saviour carnallie, departed

from him, and went no longer with
him.
               Lyke-wyse Augustine,
                  17. Argument, from the 
                        ••
                     u
                        •
                     l soune of speach in such things, which is 
                        •
                     igura
                        ••••
                     e, and yet easilie vnderstood. in that
Epistle which he wryteth to Bishop
Boniface, amongst other things saith
this, to wit, When Easter approacheth,
wee vsuallie say, that the
morrow is the day of the Lords Passion,
when not-with-standing hee
hath suffered manie yeares agoe; neither
was that Passion of his but
once, and vpon the Sabbath thereafter
wee say, This is the day of the
Lords Resurrection, when notwithstanding
manie yeares are by-past
since hee arose. Wherefore no man
will bee so foolish, as to accuse vs,
because wee call these dayes so, but
according to the similitude and memoriall
of those on which these
things were done. So that that is
called the day, which is not the day
it selfe, but alyke vnto it by revolution
of tyme, and that is sayde to be
done on that daye, in respect of the
celebration of the Sacrament, and
memoriall thereof, which notwithstanding

is not on that day indeede,
but long agoe is done.
               Was not Christ lyke-wyse but
once onelie crucified in his owne
person?18. Argument, from the sacramentall proportion &amp; similitude betweene the sigue, and th
                        •
                     ng signified; which who taketh away, overthroweth the nature of a Sacrament. and yet not-with-standing
not onelie in the Sacrament at all
these solemnities at Easter, but everie
day also hee is crucified before
the whole people.
               Neither speaketh hee vntruelie,19. Argument, likewise who knoweth not, that for this resemblance the name of the thing signified is imposed on the signe, is ignorant of the nature of Sam
                        •
                     ntes. who beeing asked at the tyme of
the Sacrament, and in the meane
while answereth, that Christ is in
crucifying: for if Sacramentes had
not a similitude of the things themselues
whereof they are Sacraments,
they were not at all to be called Sacraments.
               From this similitude then,20. Argument, that which after a sa
                        ••
                     ament
                        •
                     ll manner is Christes bod
                        •
                     e, is not the same properlie. and
resemblance, the Sacramentes, for
the moste parte, take the names of
the thinges them selues.
               As then, according to a certaine
manner, the Sacrament of Christes
bodie, is the bodie of Christ; and
the Sacrament of Christes bloode,

is the bloode of Christ; so the Sacrament
of Fayth, is Fayth.
               Wee see then,21. Argument, Who con
                     
                        •
                     oundeth the signe, with the thing signified, making the one to be the other, destroyeth the n
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     re of a S
                        ••••
                     ment. that holie Augustine
sayeth, that the Sacrament, in
effect, is one thing, and the thing
signifyed, another: for the bodie of
Christ which suffered, &amp; that blood
which gushed foorth out of his
syde, are the reall thinges them
selues; but the mysteries of these
thinges, are that which hee calleth
the Sacrament of the bodie and
blood of Christ, which is celebrated
in rememberance of the Lords
Passion: not onelie at the solemnitie
of Easter yearlie, but also everie
day through-out the whole yeare.
               And not-with-standing that
there is but one bodie of the Lord,22. Argument, from the nature of Christ
                        ••••
                      Bo
                        ••
                     e, which is but one, &amp; therefore can bee but in one place at once. And seeing he suffered therein on
                        ••
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , it cannot bee anie more corporallie broken, nor his blood shedde againe. where-in hee suffered once onelie;
and one blood, once onelie shedde
for the redumption of the worlde:
yet the Sacramentes haue taken the
names of those same thinges them
selues: so that they are called the
Bodie and Blood of Christ, while
as they are so onelie called but for

the similitude of those things which
they signifie: as the Passion daye,
and the daye of the Resurrection,
are so called, which are yearlie celebrated,
while as not-with-standing
in his bodie hee suffered but once,
(as is sayde) and rose but once:
Neyther can these dayes bee called
backe againe, because they are alreadie
by-gone: Yet not-with-standing,
by that forme of speach, they
are called such dayes, where in the
rememberance of the Lordes death
and Resurrection is commemorated,
because they haue the similitude
and resemblance of those
dayes, where-on our Saviour suffered,
and rose againe: Whence wee
say, the daye, or tomorrowe, or the
day after, to bee the daye of the
Lordes Passion, or his Resurrection:
when as not-with-standing those
dayes where-on these thinges were
reallie done, are by-past manie
yeares agoe.
               So also wee may saye, That the
Lord is sacrificed, or offered vp,

when the Sacrament of his Oblation
is celebrated,23. Argument, from the manner how he is sayd daylie to bee sac
                        •••
                     ced, or suffer; which is sacramentallie onelie, or by resemblance, and commemoration. while as not-with-standing
hee was but once
onelie sacrificed, for the salvation
of the worlde, in his owne person,
as the Apostle sayeth, CHRIST
once suffered for vs, leaving an example
vnto vs, that wee might followe
His Foote-steppes:
                  1. Pet. 2. For hee sayeth
not, that hee suffereth daylie in his
owne person, which hee did but
once: but hee left vs that example,
which vnto vs that are the faythfull,
is daylie represented in the
mysterie of his bodie and bloode:
that who-so-ever commeth vnto it,
may know, that hee must bee partaker
of the Lordes sufferinges: the
patterne and resemblance where-of,
hee giveth in his holie mysteries, according
to that of Salomon,
                  Prov. 23. 
                  When
thou commest to eate at the Table of
a mightie man, consider diligentlie
what is set before thee, knowing
that thou must prepare such things
againe.
               
                  To come then to the Table of
this mightie man,24. Argument, the thing signified in the Sacrament. cannot be received and eaten with the mouth. is to bee partaker
of the heavenlie Food: and the taking
heede to those thinges which
are set before thee, is the vnderstanding,
and discerning aright, of the
bodie and blood of Christ: Whereof
who-so-ever hee bee that is partaker,
let him take heede, that hee
must prepare such thinges also; to
wit, that hee must bee Christes follower,
by dying with him: the memorie
of whose death, hee must
not onelie by believing, but by tasting
also confesse.
               Also the blessed Apostle Sainct
Paul, wryting to the Hebrewes, sayth,
Such an high Priest it became vs to
haue,
                  Hebr. 7. 
                  who is holie, harmelesse, vndefyled,
separate from sinners, and made
higher than the Heavens: Who needeth
not daylie, as those high Priestes
vnder the Lawe, to offer vp Sacrifice,
first for his owne sinnes, and then for
the peoples: for this the Lord IESVS
CHRIST did once, when hee offered
vp him selfe. And now that which

hee did once, is daylie re-iterated:
for hee offered himselfe once for
the sinnes of the people, and yet
not-with-standing this Oblation is
daylie celebrated by the faythfull,
but in a mysterie, that that which
our Lord IESVS fulfilled, by
offering vp him selfe once in person,
might, in rememberance of his
Passion, bee daylie performed, and
that by celebrating the holie mysteries
there-of.
               Neither is it vntruelie sayd, that
in these mysteries the Lord is crucified,
or suffereth, because they carrie
the similitude of that death and
suffering, whereof they are resemblances:
Whence it is also, that
they are called the Lords bodie, and
his blood, because they take the
name of that, whereof they are the
Sacrament.
               Hence it is,25. Argument, from the matter of the Sacrament, which is the fruites of the earth; and therefore not Christes bodie and bloode properlie, seeing it was of the seede of the Virgine. that blessed Isiodor,
in his Booke of Etimologies sayeth,
that this word SACRIFICE, is
so called as it were a Sacred fact, because
this action, or Sacrament, is

consecrated with a mysticall sort of
Prayer, vnto the remembrance of
the Lords Passion. From whence
it is, that at his command wee call
that the bodie and blood of Christ;
the which while it is made of the
fruites of the earth, it is sanctified,
and so becommeth a Sacrament, by
the Spirite of God, working invisiblie.
The Sacrament of which Bread
also, and of which Cup, is in the
Greeke called Eucharict, which in
Latine being interpreted, signifieth
THANKS-GIVING.
               And what is better (I pray
you) than the bodie and blood of
Christ?26. Argument, That which is compared vnto the bodie and bloode of Christ, is not the verie same. and therefore that bread
and that wine are compared to the
bodie and blood of Christ, because
as the substance of this visible bread
and wine nowrisheth,27. Argument, That which is the foode of the soule onelie, is not food for the bodie also. and refresheth
the outward man, so that word of
God, which is the living bread, by
the participation of it refresheth the
mynds of the faythfull.
               And that holie fore-named Father
doeth ever teach, that the mysterie

of the Lords Passion,28. Argument, Th
                        •
                     t which is celebrated in remembrance only of Christ his suffering, is not that bodie which properly suffered. is to be
celebrated in remembrance onlie of
the Lords suffering for vs. And so
by saying this, hee showeth, that
the Lords proper suffering was but
once, but that the daylie rememberance
thereof in our holie Solemnities
is often to bee represented.
Whence it is, that the bread which
is offered, al-be-it it be taken of the
fruits of the earth, while it is sanctified,
it is turned in the bodie of
Christ; and that wine which did
proceede from the Vine-grape, by
the sanctification of the holie mysterie,
is made the blood of Christ:
not visiblie, (as is vsuall, is substantiall
conversions) but (as the same
Father sayeth) by the invisible operation
of the holie Ghost.
               And because they are a farre
more different thing,29. Argument, whatsoever outwardlie is taken by the mouth, serveth for the refreshment of the bodie: but Christes bodie and blood serveth for the invisible and spirituall feeding of the soules, and therefore it is so taken. by the invisible
power, than they appeare outwardlie,
and are seene to bee, hee
distinguisheth them, while he saith,
that the bread and wine are therefore
compared to the bodie and

blood of Christ; because as the substance
of the visible bread and wine
nowrisheth and cheareth the outward
man, so the worde of God,
which is the liuelie bread, by the
participation thereof, refresheth in
like manner the soules of the faythfull.
               By saying of which things, hee
confesseth plainlie, that whatsoever
is taken outwardlie in the Sacrament
of the Bodie and Blood of our
Lord, it is meete for the refreshment
of the bodie onelie; but the
word of God, which is the invisible
bread, beeing invisiblie present in
that Sacrament, doeth feede the
soules of the faythfull invisiblie,
quickning them by the participation
of himselfe.
               Hence it is, that the same divine
Doctor sayeth, that it is a Sacrament,
in anie celebration, when the
action is so performed, that some
thing is vnderstood to be signified,
which is to bee holielie taken. By
saying which, hee showeth, that all

Sacramentes in holie matters, doe
containe some mysticall thing, and
that it is one thing which is seene
by our outward eyes, and another
thing which is inwardlie to bee vnderstood
by our mynds. And after
this hee showeth what Sacraments
are to bee celebrated by the faythfull,
to wit, Baptisme, and that of
the Bodie and Blood of Christ.
               Which are called Sacramentes,30. Argument, Those thing
                        •
                     s which vnder the over of corporall thing
                        •
                     s haue an b
                        •••
                      and divine operation, ends not to h
                        ••
                     ge their essence: but the sacraments are so: Ergo, &amp;c. because vnder the covering of the
corporall thinges in these Sacramentes,
the divine vertue more secretlie
worketh salvation: Whence
it is, that from their secret and sacred
vertue, they are called Sacraments.
And thereafter hee sayeth,
that in the Greeke they are called
MYSTERIES, because they
haue a secret and hid nature and disposition
with them.
               What then are we taught here?31. Argument, Those thinges that are not perceived, nor taken, but by diverse instrumentes, they are not the same, but the Bread and Wine, and the Bodie and Bloode of Christ, are not perceived, nor taken, by the same instruments, but by diverse: and therefore are not the same.
but that these things which are sayd
to bee the bodie and blood of our
Lord, are therefore called mysteries,
because they haue a secret and hid

disposition and qualitie; that is, that
one thing they show outwardlie,
and another thing invisiblie they
worke inwardlie. From this they
are also called Sacramentes, because
by the covering of corporall things,
the heavenlie power more secretlie
dispenseth the salvation of the faithfull
partakers.
               Out of all then which hath bene
formerlie spoken, wee haue showne
vnto you, that the bodie and blood
of Christ, which is taken in the
Church, by the mouth of the faythfull,
are signes and figures, according
to their visible shape; but according
to their invisible substance,Conclusion.
that is, according to the power of
the heavenlie word, they are the bodie
and blood of CHRIST truelie:
whence it is, that according as they
are seen as the visible creatures, they
nowrish the bodie; but according
to the vertue of the more powerfull
substance, they both nowrish and
sanctifie the soules of the faythfull.
            
            
               
               
                  WE must looke now
to the drift of the
second Question,The second Question, Whether the matter of the Sacrament bee the naturall Bodie of CHRIST, or no? &amp; consider if that
same bodie which
was borne of the
Virgine, and suffered, died, and was
buried, and sitteth now at the right
Hand of the Father, bee that which
is taken by the mouth of the faythfull,
daylie in the mysterie of the
Sacrament?
               Then let vs aske at Sainct Ambrose,
                  1. Argument, from 
                        〈…〉
                      showi
                        •
                     g, that the matter of the Sacrament is taken corporallie, and nowrisheth of itselfe but the naturall lyfe: But the Bodie of Christ is not so, for it nowrisheth onelie the spirituall lyfe.
what hee doeth thinke concerning
this matter? for hee sayeth, in
his first Booke of the Sacramentes,
Surelie it is a wonderfull thing, that
God rained downe heavenlie Food
vnto our Fathers, and that they
were daylie nowrished vpon celestiall
meat; whence it is sayde, that
Man did eate the bread of Angels:

and yet they who did eate that
bread, died all in the Desart. But
that meate which thou takest, and
that bread of life which came down
from heaven, furnisheth the nowrishment
of everlasting lyfe: and
who-so-ever eateth this bread, hee
shall never die: and this bread is the
bodie of Christ.
               Looke then in what respect it
is, that this holie Doctor sayeth, that
Christes bodie is foode, which the
faythfull receiue in the Church; for
hee sayeth, that bread of lyfe which
came downe from heaven, furnisheth
the nowrishment of everlasting lyfe.
                     These words directlie contradict Pope Nicolas, De Consceratione, Dist. 2. cap. Evo Berengarius. Now (I aske) if it
furnisheth that nowrishment, as it
is seene? or as it is taken corporallie?
as it is chewed with the teeth?
swallowed with the mouth? and
received in the stomacke? Not.
For that way it should feed the flesh
onelie, which is mortall; neyther
giveth it anie immortalitie that way,
nor can it bee sayde, that who-so-ever
eateth this bread so, shall not

die for ever: for that which the bodie
receiveth, is corruptible: neither
can it availe vnto eternall lyfe, because
that which is subject to corruption,
cannot giue eternitie. Therfore
in that bread there is a lyfe,
which is not seene with these corporall
eyes, but which wee beholde
with sight of fayth, and that is that
heavenlie bread which came downe
from heaven; and concerning the
which it is sayd, who-so-ever eateth
this bread, shall liue for ever, which
is the bodie of our Lord.
               Also in the wordes following,
when hee was speaking of the almightie
power of Christ, he sayeth
so, The word of God that might of
nothing make that which was not,
can Hee not change these thinges
which are, into that vvhich they
were not? For it is not a greater
matter to create new things, than to
change natures.
               Sainct Ambrose then sayeth, that
there is in the Sacrament of the bodie
and blood of our Lord, a mutation

made marveilouslie, because
divinelie and ineffablie, in respect
it is an incomprehensible mysterie.
               Let them tell then (sayeth he)
who will haue nothing vnderstood
according to an internall secret vertue,2. Argument, What change is in the Sacrament? Not of substances: and therefore no T
                        ••
                     usubstan
                        ••
                     ation, but a mysticall change, and in vse.
but all to bee esteemed after an
outward and visible manner onelie,
wherein this mutation is made? for
according to the substance of the
creatures, they are that same thereafter,
which they were before the
consecration: they were first bread
and wine, vnder the which shape
they beeing consecrated, are seene
still so as yet to remaine. It must be
inwardlie then, that they are changed,
by the mightie power of the
holie Spirit; and that which fayth
beholdeth, feedeth the soule onlie,
and furnisheth the nowrishment of
eternall lyfe.
               Also in the words following he
sayeth, Wherefore seekest thou the
order of nature in the bodie of
Christ? aboue the order of nature
our Lord was borne of the Virgine

                  Marie. But heere then aryseth the
hearer, and sayeth, that that is the
verie bodie of Christ which is seene,
and that is his blood which is drunken;
neither that we must aske, how
it is so; but that wee must belieue,
that it is so.
               Thou seemest (for-soothe) to
thinke well, but if thou weigh diligentlie
the force of the wordes,
thou believest indeede faythfullie,
that it is the bodie and blood of
Christ: but yet if thou wouldest vnderstand
aright, thou shalt finde
that that which thou believest,
thou seest not as yet: for if thou diddest
see it, thou wouldest not say,
I belieue that this is the bodie
and blood of Christ, but I see the
same.
               Now then, because fayth onelie
beholdeth all that,3. Argument. The Br
                        •
                     ad &amp; Wine are Christ
                        •
                     s Body and Bloode in ver
                        •••
                      onelie, and efficacie, vnto the faythfull applyer alone: &amp; not so of themselues substantiallie. what-so-ever the
same be, and the carnall eye apprehendeth
nothing there-of, a man
may easilie vnderstand, that these
things in outward forme which are
seene, are not the bodie and blood

of Christ, but that they are so in
vertue onelie and efficacie.
               Whence he sayeth, The order
of nature is not to bee looked to
heere, but the mightie power of
Christ to bee adored, who what-so-ever
hee will, how-so-ever he will,
and in what-so-ever hee will, createth
that which was not, and beeing
created, changeth it into that which
it was not before.
               The same Doctor subjoyneth,4. Argument, From the distinction betweene Christ his Flesh, where-in hee was but once crucifyed in veritie, and the Sacrament of his Flesh. where-in hee is daylie crucifyed in resemblance and mysterie.
The true flesh of Christ (saith he)
which was crucified, and buried, is
then truelie the Sacrament of his
flesh: for the Lord Iesus Himselfe
cryeth, saying, This is My Bodie.
How carefullie and wyselie, therefore,
is this distinction made? for
hee speaketh concerning the flesh
of Christ, which was crucified,
which was buried, that is, according
to which Christ was both crucified
and buried; that is indeede
the true flesh of Christ: but concerning
that which is taken in the Sacrament,
hee sayeth, This is truelie

the Sacrament of his flesh: distinguishing
so the Sacrament of his
flesh, from the veritie of his flesh,
in that respect that he sayeth, According
to the veritie of his flesh,
which hee tooke of the Virgine,
that hee was crucified, and buried:
but that mysterie which is now celebrated
in the Church, hee would
call that the Sacrament of that true
flesh wherein he was crucified: Teaching
the faythfull evidentlie, that
this flesh where-in Christ was crucified,
and buried, is not a mysterie,
but the plaine veritie of nature: but
this flesh which beareth the similitude
of it in the mysterie, is not flesh
indeede, but by a sacramentall manner,
seeing according to the outward
shape it is bread, but in the
Sacrament it is the bodie of Christ,
seeing he sayeth himselfe, This is My
Eodie.
               
               Also in the wordes following:5. Argument, from the spirituall sense of 
                        •
                     us
                        ••
                     g spiritual
                        ••
                      howe sweete the Lord is: and not by a corpovall taste, which is but of Bread and Wine onelie.
what wee should eate, and what we
doe drinke, the holie Spirit (sayth
hee) expresseth vnto vs, by the

holie Prophet else-where, saying,
Taste, and see how sweet the LORD
is; happie is the man that trusteth in
Him. Showeth the corporall taste
of that bread or wine how sweete
the Lord is? Not: For what-so-ever
is sweete that way, is corporall
onelie, and delighteth the mouth.
               To taste then howe sweete the
Lord is, is it to taste by the outward
sense anie corporall thing? Not: It
is the Spirituall taste then which inviteth
vs to prooue this sweetnesse
spirituallie; and in that bread and
wine to consider nothing corporallie,
but to vnderstand all to bee spirituallie
meaned,6. Argument. Christ is in that Sacramēt, (as the thing signifyed with the signe,) compleating the same
                        •
                      but the Bread and Wine is to: Christ. For by that substantiall ch
                        ••
                     nge, the signe, with the thing signified, should bee so confounded. because the Lord
is a Spirite, and blessed is the man
that putteth his trust in Him.
               Also there-after he saith, Christ
is in that Sacrament, because that
Sacrament is the bodie of Christ:
therefore it is not a corporall food,
but a spirituall nowrishment. What
is more cleare, more manifest, and
more divinelie spoken? For hee
sayeth, In that Sacrament CHRIST

is. Hee sayeth not, that that bread
and that wine is Christ. Which if
hee had sayde, hee would haue affirmed,
that Christ was subject to
corruptabilitie, and mortalitie:
for what-so-ever is seene, or tasted
in that foode corporallie, it is manifest,
that it is subject vnto corruption.
               Heere-to hee addeth; Because
it is the bodie of Christ (sayeth he)
thou wilt object, and say, Beholde,
manifestlie hee confesseth, that this
bread, and this wine, is the bodie
and bloode of Christ. But take
heede what is subjoyned: This is
not corporall foode, but spirituall.
Looke that thou conceiue not a
a carnall meaning heere-fore; for
there is no such thing heere. True
it is, that it is the bodie of Christ;
not corporall, but spirituall: the
blood of Christ; not corporall, but
spirituall. Therefore there is nothing
to bee vnderstood heere corporallie,
but spirituallie. It is the

bodie and blood of Christ, but not
corporallie.
               Also in the wordes following,
hee sayeth, The Apostle speaketh
concerning the Type of Him, Our
Fathers did eate the Spirituall Foode,
and dranke the Spirituall Drinke: For
the bodie of God, is a spirituall bodie:
the bodie of Christ, is the bodie
of a divine Spirite, because that
Spirit is the Spirit of Christ, (who
is God, and therefore it is divine)
as wee reade in the Lamentations,
                  Lament. 4. He
is a Spirite before our face, even
CHRIST the LORD.
               The Apostle hath taught vs
then sufficientlie, howe wee ought
to vnderstand the mysterie of the
bodie and bloode of Christ: For
when hee had sayde, that Our Fathers
did eate that Spirituall Foode, and
dranke that Spirituall Drinke; which
Manna not-with-standing that they
did eate, and which Water whereof
they did drinke, were corporall bodies,
as no man doubteth, hee addeth
there-to, concerning the mysterie

which is vsed in the Church
daylie,7. Argument. No spirituall thing is visible, nor p
                        •
                     lpable. but th
                        ••
                      which we receiue in tha
                        •
                      divine mysterie, is spiritual: The Blood and Wine of the contra
                        ••
                     , beeing palpable, and visible, therefore they are no that spirituall thing
                        •
                      seeing we both feele and see them. showing in what respect it
is the bodie of Christ, while hee
sayeth, that the bodie of God, is a
spirituall bodie: For Christ is God,
and that bodie which hee tooke of
the Virgine, which suffered, which
was buried, and rose againe, was a
true bodie, to wit, that same which
remained visible, and palpable. But
that bodie, which is called The divine
Mysterie, is not corporall, but
spirituall. And if it bee spirituall, it
is not visible, nor palpable.
               Hence Sainct Ambrose subjoyneth
this, saying, The bodie of
Christ, is the bodie of a divine Spirit:
but a divine Spirit hath in it no
corporal nor corruptible thing, neither
is it palpable in the existence
there-of. But this bodie, which is
celebrated in the Church, according
to the visible forme there-of,
it is both corruptible, and palpable.
How is it sayde then to bee the bodie
of a divine Spirit? To wit, according
to that it is spirituall; that

is, as it is invisible, impalpable, and
consequentlie incorruptible.
               Hence in the words following,Note That the 
                        〈◊〉
                      of Christ indeed giveth lyfe, 
                        〈◊〉
                      not absoluteli
                        •
                     , but as it is the flesh or the divine Worde. From whome, as the Po
                        ••
                     
                     
                     
                        •
                     taine, by the fleshe, as the Channell, lyfe is conveyed vnto vs.
                  Because CHRIST is a Spirit, as wee
reade Lament. 4, Hee is a Spirite before
our face, even CHRIST the
LORD, hee showeth clearlie, in
what respect it is esteemed the bodie
of Christ; to wit, because the
Spirit of Christ is in it; that is, the
power of the Word of God, which
not onelie feedeth the Soule, but also
cleanseth it.
               Wherefore the Author him selfe
sayeth in the wordes following,8. Argument, From the nature of the soule, which is spirituall: and therefore requireth spirituall Food. To
what effect, as the Prophet rehearseth,
doeth that food confirme, and
that drinke gladden the heart of
man? for confirmeth corporall food
the heart of man? or doeth earthlie
drinke gladden the soule? No.
That hee might showe then what
foode, and what drinke hee meant,
hee added emphaticallie, and in a
speciall manner, That drinke (saith
hee) and that meate. What meaneth
hee by that meate, and that

drinke? to wit, the bodie of Christ,
the bodie of that divine Spirit. And
that it may bee more clearelie named,
It is spirituall Christ, concerning
whome it is sayde, Christ the
Lord is a spirit before our face.
               By which thinges it is showne
evidentlie vnto vs, that nothing is
vnderstood in that meat and drinke
corporallie, but all is to bee taken
spirituallie: for the soule of man,
which is signified by his heart, is
not fed with corporall foode, but is
nowrished and quickened by that
word of God. Which the same
Doctor showeth more manifestlie,
in his fift Booke of the Sacraments,
saying, It is not that bread wich entereth
into the bodie, but that bread
of lyfe, which giveth quickning to
our soules.
               And that Sainct Ambrose spake
not this of the common bread, but
of the bread of the bodie of Christ,
the next words manifestlie declare,
for hee speaketh of the daylie bread,
which the faythfull desire to bee

given them, and therefore hee subjoyneth
these wordes, If it bee our
daylie bread, why take yee it onelie
at the ende of a whole yeare? as the
Grecians in the East vsed to doe. Take
then that daylie, which will bee
profitable to thee daylie; and liue
so, that thou mayest bee worthie
daylie to receiue it.
               It is manifest then concerning
what bread hee speaketh, to wit,
concerning the bodie and blood of
Christ, which nowrisheth not, in
that it goeth downe into the bodie,
but because it is the bread of everlasting
lyfe.
               By the authoritie then of this
most learned man wee are admonished,A cleare Conclusion of Ambrose mynde. that there is a great difference
betweene the bodie of Christ which
suffered, and his blood which gushed
foorth out of his syde on the
Crosse, and betweene this bodie
which is celebrated daylie by the
faythfull, in the mysterie of the
Lords Passion, and that blood which
is taken by the mouth of the faythfull;

seeing it is the mysterie onelie
of that blood, wher-with the whole
world was redeemed.
               That bread and that drinke,
therefore, according to that they
are seene; are not the bodie and
blood of Christ, but according to
that they furnish the nowrishment
of lyfe spirituallie. But that bodie
of Christ, wherein he was crucified,
carried none other shape, or appearance,
than wherein it did consist
truelie: for it was truelie that bodie
which was seene, which was touched,
which was crucified, which
was buried; lyke-wyse that blood
which gushed foorth out of his side,
seemed not one thing outwardlie,
and mysticallie covered another
thing inwardlie; therefore it was
true blood which sprang from that
true bodie. But that blood of Christ,
which now the faythful drinke, and
the bodie which they eate, is one
thing according to their shape, and
another thing according to their
signification: for it is one way wherby

they feede the bodie with corporall
foode, and another where
                     •
                  y
they fill our soules with the substantiall
nowrishment of eternall
lyfe.
               Concerning which thing Sainct
Ierome,
                  9 Argument, From Sainct Ierome his testimonie. in his Commentarie vpon
Sainct Paules Epistle to the Ephesians,
writeth so, The bodie and
blood of Christ (sayeth hee) may
be vnderstood two māner of ways;
either spirituallie, concerning the
which hee sayeth, My Flesh is Meat
indeed, and My Blood is Drinke indeede:
or corporallie, according to that
flesh which was crucified, and that
blood which was shed by the Souldiours
Lance. It is not then by a
small difference that hee maketh
such a distinction of the bodie and
blood of Christ: for while he saith,
That this flesh or blood which is
taken by the faythfull, is spirituall,
but that flesh which was crucified,
and that blood which was shed by
the Souldiours Lance, is not spirituall,
hee insinuateth thus much,

that there is great difference betweene
these, as there is betweene
corporall things and spirituall, visible
and invisible, naturall and supernaturall:
and in respect that they
differ so, it followeth, that they are
not one.
               Therefore that spirituall flesh
which is taken by the faythfull onlie,
and that spirituall drinke, which
is exhibited vnto the believers daylie
to bee drunken, differeth from
the flesh which was crucified, and
the blood which was shedde by the
Souldiours Launce, as the authoritie
of this holie Man testifieth: and
therefore (I say) they are not all one
thing.
               For that flesh which was crucified,10 Argument, From the diversitie of that which is Christs naturall bod
                        •
                     e, 
                        ••
                     d that which is his sacramentall bodie. was made of the Virgines
flesh, joyned with Bones and Sinewes,
distinguished by the Lineamentes
of humane Members, quickened
with the spirite of a reasonable
soule, to the vse of a proper life,
and agreeable motions. But that
spirituall flesh, which feedeth the

believers spirituallie, according to
the outward shape, it consisteth of
the graines of Corne, made by the
hand of the Baker, joyned with no
sinewes nor bones, distinguished
with no varietie of members, quickned
vvith no reasonable soule, and
which can exercise no proper motions:
for what-so-ever in it giveth
lyfe, is of a spirituall power, of an
invisible efficacie, and of an heavenlie
vertue: for it is a farre more different
thing, as it is believed in a mysterie,
than as it is seene outwardlie.
               More-over,11. Argument. As the Bread made of many Graines, is the Bodie of the Church, so is it the Bodie of Christ: But it is the one by representation, 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     ot by anie corporall cha
                        •
                     ge: Therefore so is it the other. the flesh of Christ
which was crucified, shewed no
more outwardlie, than it was in it
selfe, because it was the flesh of a
true man onelie, to wit, a true bodie,
vnder the shape of a true bodie. But
we must not onelie consider in that
bread, this bodie of Christ, but also
the bodie of the whole believers in
him must be represented, for which
cause it is made vp of manie graines
of Wheate, because so the bodie of
the Church is made vp of manie believers,

by the word of Christ: for
which cause as in the mysticall
bread, the bodie of Christ is vnderstood;
so also in the same mysterie
the members of the Church are represented,
to bee one in Christ: and
as not corporallie, but spirituallie,
that bread is called the bodie of the
Church, or believing people. So
also of necessitie it must bee vnderstood
to be the bodie of Christ, not
corporallie, but spirituallie.
               So also in the wine,12. Argument From 
                        〈…〉
                      Christs blood
                        ••
                      is converted in his blood. which is
called the blood of Christ, it is commanded
to bee mixed with water:
neither is it suffered, that one of
them bee offered without the other,
because the people can-not be without
Christ, nor Christ without his
people; even as the head cannot be
with-out the members, nor the
members with-out the head: for
the water in that Sacrament signifieth
the people. Then if that wine,
which is sanctified by the office of
the Ministers thereof, bee turned
corporallie into the blood of Christ,

the water also which is mixed with
it, of necessitie must bee converted
corporallie into the blood of the believers:
For where there is one sanctification,
there is one operation;
and where there is a-lyke reason,
there is a-lyke mysterie: But wee
see in the water nothing to be changed
corporallie, and therefore consequentlie
neither in the wine: So
that what-so-ever in the water is
signified concerning the people, it
is taken spirituallie: Then of necessitie
what-so-ever in the wine is
meaned concerning the blood of
Christ, must be taken spirituallie.
               Also these thinges which differ
amongst them selues,13. Argument, From the opposite difference of Christ his naturall bodie, and the sacramental
                        ••
                     . are not one:
the bodie of Christ then, which hath
died, and is risen, and is made immortall,
dieth not now; for Death
hath no more dominion over it, for
it is eternall, neither is it now passible
at all: but this which is celebrated
in the Church, is temporall, and
not eternall; corruptible, as that
which is yet in the way, and not alreadie

in the natiue Countrey: wherfore
they differ from them selues,
and therefore are not one.
               But if they bee not one, howe
then are they called the true bodie
and blood of Christ? For if it bee
the bodie of Christ, and that bee
sayde truelie, because it is so, then
in veritie it is his bodie: and if it be
in veritie his bodie, it is incorruptible,
and doeth not nowe suffer,
and consequentlie is eternall. Then
of necessitie this bodie which is celebrated
in the Church, must bee
incorruptible, and eternall. But it
can-not bee denyed, but that is subject
to corruption, which is divyded
in partes, to bee taken; and
beeing brayed with the teeth, is sent
downe into the Bellie. Therefore
it is one thing that is seene outwardlie,
and another thing which is believed
by fayth inwardlie. For as
it falleth vnder the sense of the bodie,
it is corruptible; but as fayth
believeth, it is incorruptible. That
which is seene then outwardlie, is

is not the thing it selfe, but the resemblance
of it; but that which is
felt inwardlie, and vnderstood by
the mynd, is the veritie of the thing
it selfe.
               Hence it is, that Sainct Augustine, in the Exposition of the Evangelist
Sainct Iohn, sayeth, while hee
was speaking of the bodie &amp; blood
of Christ;14. Argument, From the testimonie of Augustine.
                   
                  Moses did eate (saith he)
that Manna, and Aaron, and Phineas,
and manie moe die eate the same
there, who pleased GOD, and
they died not. Wherefore? because
they tooke that visible meate spirituallie,
they tasted spirituallie, that
they might bee filled spirituallie: for
wee now-a-dayes in lyke-manner
take visible bread. But a Sacrament
is one thing, and the vertue
of a Sacrament another.
               Also in the wordes following:
this is the bread which came down
from heaven: that heavenlie Manna
did fore-show this bread: the Altar
of God also did fore-shadow this
bread. All these were Sacraments,

which are diverse, according to
their signes, but a-like in that which
they signified.
               Let vs heare the Apostle Sainct
Paul also:1. Corinth. 10 
                  Brethren,
                  15. Argument, From Sainct P
                        ••••
                      his wordes. 
                  (sayeth hee) I
will not haue you ignorant, that our
Fathers were all vnder the Cloude, and
did all passe through the Sea, and that
they were all bap
                        •
                     ized vnto Moses in
the Cloude, and in the Sea, and did
all eate that same Spirituall Meat, and
did all drinke that same Spirituall Drinke.
I say, that same spirituall meat, and
that same drinke, because they did
eate other corporall meat, &amp; dranke
other corporall drinke, in respect
they did eate Manna; But wee doe
eate another thing, and yet they did
eate the same spirituall meat which
wee doe: and they all dranke that
same spirituall drinke. But according
to the visible shape, these
thinges were different, which notwith-standing
did signifie but one
thing spirituallie. Howe then did
they drinke of that same drinke?
Hee answereth, They did drinke of

that spirituall Rocke that followed
them, and that Rocke was Christ.
From thence came the Bread also,
from whence the Drinke came: and
the Rocke Christ was given them
for a signe: but true Christ was exhibited
in the worde, and in the
flesh.
               Also, this is the Bread which
came downe from Heaven; whereof
if anie man eate, hee shall not
die. But hee meaneth heere that
which appertayneth vnto the vertue
of the Sacrament, and not that
which appertayneth to the visible
Sacrament. Who so eateth within,
and not without, participateth
heere-of, who so eateth with his
heart, and not with his mouth.
               Also in the wordes following, bringing in the wordes of our Saviour,Iohn, 6.
hee sayeth,16. Argument, From Christ his wordes. Doeth this offende
you, because I sayde, I giue
you my Flesh to eate, and my Blood
to drinke? What then if yee shall
see the Sonne of man going vp

where hee was before? What
meaneth hee by this? Heere hee
taketh away that doubt which troubled
them: heere hee cleareth that
which offended them: For they
thought, that hee was carnallie to
bestowe his bodie vpon them by
morsels. But hee shewed, that hee
was to goe vp to Heaven, with his
whole bodie. When yee shall see
the Sonne of Man then going vp
where hee was before, surelie then
it shall be manifest, that the LORD
bestoweth not his bodie according
as yee suppose: surelie then yee shall
vnderstand, that his grace is not
consumed by mo
                     •
                  sels.
               Also hee sayeth, It is the Spirite
that quickeneth,17. Argument. the flesh profiteth
nothing. And a good while after
hee addeth this, Who-so-euer hath
not the Spirite of Christ,Rom. 4. (sayeth
the Apostle) the same is not his.
Then it is the Spirite that quickeneth,
the flesh profiteth nothing.
The wordes that I speake vnto you

are Spirit and Lyfe: That is (sayeth
hee) they are to bee vnderstoode
spirituallie. Vnderstandest thou
them spirituallie? Then they are
Spirit and Lyfe vnto thee, Vnderstandest
thou them carnallie? Even
yet they are Spirite and Lyfe, but
not vnto thee.
               By the authoritie then of this
learned Doctor,A cleare Conclusion out of Augustines wordes. wee are taught manifestlie,
that the wordes of our Saviour,
concerning the Sacrament
of his bodie and blood, are to bee
vnderstood spirituallie, and not carnallie:
as hee sayeth him selfe, The
wordes that I speake vnto you, are
Spirit and Lyfe: To wit, the wordes
concerning the eating of his fleshe,
and drinking of his bloode: For it
was concerning this that hee was
speaking when his Disciples were
offended. Therefore, that they
might not bee offended, our heavenlie
Master calleth them backe,
from the flesh, vnto the Spirit; from
corporall sense, to spirituall vnderstanding.
               
                  Wee see then, in the eating of
the Lord
                     •
                   bodie, and drinking of
his blood, in what respect the same
is his bodie, and his blood, truelie;
to wit, according to that that the
same is Spirit and Lyfe.
               Also these things that are a-like,
are comprehended vnder one definition.
Nowe concerning the true
bodie of Christ, it is sayde, That
hee is true God, and true man, who
in the latter tymes of the world was
borne of the Virgine Marie. But
these things cannot be sayde of the
bodie of Christ, which is celebrated
by a mysterie in the Church. According
then to a certaine manner
onelie, it is acknowledged to be the
bodie of Christ; and that manner is
by a figure, and in resemblance,
that so the veritie and thing it selfe
may bee the more sensiblie vnderstood.
               In the Prayers also which are
sayde after the mysterie of the body
and blood of Christ,18. Argument, From the olde custome of praying at the Sacrament. and wherein

the people answere AMEN,Here wee see, that of olde, when these Prayers were made, there were no private Masses, where
                        ••
                      the Priest 
                        〈◊〉
                      communicated: but both People and Pa
                        ••
                     or did communicate. And the Sacrament then was for 
                        〈◊〉
                     , and thankesgiving; and not a propi
                     
                        •••
                      sacrifice for the quicke and the dead. the
Priest vttereth these wordes, Wee
request Thee humblie, O LORD, who
are now partakers of the Pledges of
eternall Lyfe, that which we touch
in the resemblance of this Sacrament,
wee may receiue in the manifest participation
of the thing it selfe.
               
               Now we know that a pledge or
resemblance, is of another thing,
where-of they are the pledges or resemblances;
that is, they are not to
bee considered as they are in them
selues, but as they haue a reference
to another thing: for a pledge is of
that for the which it is given; and
so is an Image the resemblance of
that whose similitude it representeth:
they signifie then the thing
whose Images they are, and doeth
not showe the same in it selfe manifestlie.
               Which while they are so, it is
evident, that this bodie and blood
are the pledges and resemblances of
that to come, that that which is

shown vnto vs by a similitude now,
shalbee clearlie revealed vnto vs in
tyme to come. It is one thing then
which is done nowe, and another
which shall bee manifested heereafter.
               Wherefore it is the bodie and
blood of Christ which the Church
celebrateth,
                     
                        〈…〉
                      Prayer. but as a Pledge and resemblance:
the veritie it selfe shall
bee when neyther Pledge, nor representation,
but He him selfe shall
clearlie appeare.
               And in another place he sayth,19 A
                        •
                     gument, F
                        •
                     o 
                        •
                     he distin
                        ••
                     on of the resemblance, and the thing it selfe.
O LORD, accomplishe in vs that
which THY Sacramentes contayne;
that that which wee nowe celebrate in
resemblance, wee may bee partakers
also of the veritie of the thinges them
selues. Hee sayeth then, that these
thinges are celebrated in resemblance;
that is, by similitude, and
not by the manifestation of the
thing it selfe: So that the resemblance,
and the veritie of the thing
it selfe, are there distinguished.
               
                  Wherefore the body and blood
of Christ, which is nowe celebrated
in the Church, differeth from that
bodie and blood which is knowne
to bee glorified in Christ his bodie
by his resurrection. And this bodie
which is celebrated in the Church,
is but a Pledge and resemblance of
that; but that is the veritie it selfe.
This is done, while wee come to
that; but when wee come to that,
this shall bee remooved.
               It is manifest then, that there is
great difference betweene them, as
much as there is betweene a Pledge,
and that wherefore it is given; and
as much as there is betweene an
Image, and that which it representeth;
and as much as there is betweene
the resemblance of a thing,
and the veritie it selfe.
               Wee see then that there is great
difference betweene the mysterie of
the bodie and bloode of Christ,
which is taken in the Church by
the Faythfull, and that which was

borne of the Virgine, which suffered,
which was buried, which rose
againe, and went to heaven, and
now sitteth at the right hand of the
Father: For this which is celebrated
in this mortall Iourney, is taken
spirituallie, because fayth believeth
that which it seeth not, and spirituallie
feedeth the soule, and gladdeneth
the heart, and giveth eternall
lyfe, and immortalitie, while that
is not taken heede vnto which feedeth
the bodie,20. Argument From the properties and 
                        〈…〉
                      of the 
                        〈◊〉
                      of Christ his naturall bodie, eve
                        •
                      after his resurrection, which that which is 
                        •
                     orged by Transsubstantiation hath not. and is torne with
the teeth, and broken in pieces; but
that which is spirituallie taken, and
by fayth apprehended.
               But that bodie wherin he suffered,
which rose againe, and is his
proper bodie, which hee tooke of
the Virgine, was palpable and visible,
after his resurrection, as hee
him selfe sayeth vnto his Disciples;Luke, 24.
Wherefore are yee troubled? and
wherefore doe cogitations enter into
your heartes? Looke to mine
Handes and Feete, if I bee not the

same Man: handle, and see, because
a spirit hath not flesh and bones,
yee see mee haue.
               Let vs also heare what holie
Fulgentius sayeth,21. Argument, From the Testimonie of E
                           •
                        lg
                           ••
                        ius.
                   in his Booke concerning
Fayth; Gripe stedfastlie,
(sayeth hee) and doubt no-wyse,
that the onelie begotten Sonne of
God was made flesh, that he offered
him selfe vp in a Sacrifice acceptable
to God, to whome, with
the Father, and the holie Spirit,
the Patriarches, Prophets, and
Priestes in tyme of the Olde Testament
sacrificed Beastes; and to
whom now in the tyme of the new
Testament, with the Father and
the holie Spirite, who maketh but
one God-head, the Sacrifice of
bread and wine is through faith and
charitie offered by the Catholicke
Church throughout the world. In
these carnall Sacrifices, there was a
representation of the flesh of Christ,
which he was to offer for our sinnes,
being without sinne him selfe; and

of his blood, which he was to offer

                     〈◊〉
                   the remission of our sinnes. But
in this Sacrifice is a Thanks-giving,
and commemoration of the bodie
of Christ, which hee offered for vs;
and of his blood, which hee shed
for vs: concerning which the blessed
Apostle Paul sayeth, in the Acts
of the Apostles;Acts, 20. Take heede therefore
vnto your selues, and to all the
flocke, over which the holie Ghost
hath made you over-seers, to feede
the Church of God, which hee hath
conquest with his owne blood. In
those Sacrifices then it was showne
figuratiuely, what was to haue bene
given vnto vs: but in this Sacrifice
is clearelie showne, what is alreadie
given vnto vs. Saying then
that it was signified in those Sacrifices,
what was to bee given vnto
vs, but in this Sacrament that wee
should commemorate that which is
alreadie given, hee showeth evidentlie,
that as that had a figure of
the things to come, so this should

haue a resemblance of thinges alreadie
by-gone.
               By which wordes also he declareth
manifestlie, what great difference
is betweene the bodie of
Christ which suffered, and that bodie
which serveth for the commemoration
of his death and suffering:
for the one was his true and proper
bodie, having no mysticall signification,
nor resemblance of any other
thing in it; but this other is mysticall,
showing one thing outwardlie
by figure, and inwardlie representing
another thing vnto vs, by the
vnderstanding of faith.
               Let vs bring one testimonie yet
of Sainct Augustine,
                  22. Argument From a Testimonie of saint Augustine.
                   which will
confirme the thing we haue said, &amp;
put an ende also to our present Discourse:
In that Sermon which he
made vnto the people concerning
this Sacramēt of the Altar, he saith;
That which yee see on the Altar of
God, yee saw it this night by-gone,
but yee heard not yet what it was,

or what it meaned, and of howe
great a thing it was a Sacrament.
That which yee see then, it i
                     •
                   bread
and wine, which your eyes point
foorth vnto you: but that which
your fayth is to bee instructed in, is
this, That that Bread is the Bodie
of Christ, and that Cup the Blood
of Christ. This is shortlie sayde,
which perhaps would suff
                     •
                  ce your
fayth: but your fayth requireth instruction;
for the Prophet sayeth,
Except ye
                     •
                   belieue,I
                        ••
                     , 6. ye shall not vnderstand.
Yee may then say vnto
mee, Thou hast commanded vs to
belieue; declare vnto vs, that wee
may vnderstand; for this cogitation
may enter into the mynde of anie
man; wee know whence our Lord
Iesus tooke flesh, to wit, of the Virgine
Marie, being an Infant, he sucked,
hee was nowrished, hee came
vnto youth-head, hee suffered persecution
of the Iewes, hee hung vpon
a Tree, hee was killed, taken
downe from the Crosse, hee was

buried, and rose againe the third
day, at his appointed time, he went
to the Heavens, and lifted vp his
bodie thither, from whence hee is
to come, to judge the quicke and
the dead, &amp; there he is presentlie, at
the right hand of his Father sitting;
howe then can this bee his bodie?
or this Cup, or that which it containeth,
his blood? Brethren, these
thinges are called Sacramentes, because
in them there is one thing
seene, and another thing is vnderstood:
that which is seene, hath a
corporall shape; but that which is
vnderstood, hath a spirituall fruit.
               This Venerable Doctor then,
by saying this, teacheth vs, what
wee ought to thinke, concerning
the proper bodie of Christ, which
was borne of the Virgine, and sitteth
nowe at the right Hand of the
Father, in which hee is to come
to judge the quicke and the dead:
and what wee ought to thinke of
that which is offered vpon the Altar,

where-of the People are made
partakers. That bodie is whole;
neither is it divided by any cutting,
nor covered with anie figures: But
this which is set vpon the Table of
the Lord, is a resemblance of that,
because it is a Sacrament: And that
which is seene outwardlie, hath a
corporall shape, and feedeth the bodie:
but that which is vnderstoode
inwardlie, it hath a spirituall fruite,
which quickeneth the Soule.
               And when he would haue spoken
more manifestlie, concerning
this mysticall bodie, hee sayeth thus
in the wordes following; If ye will
vnderstand concerning the bodie
of Christ,1. Cor
                        •
                     nth. 10. heare the Apostle, saying,
Yee are the Bodie and Members of
Christ. If then yee bee the bodie
and members of Christ your mysticall
resemblance is set on the Lords
Table, and yee receiue the mysterie
of the Lord, and vnto that which
you are, yee say AMEN,Here you see, that the olde custome was, that the whole people, &amp; not th
                        •
                      C
                        •••
                     ke onlie, said AMEN. and by aunswering
so,Iust. Apolog. 2. yee subscrybe there-vnto.
Thou hearest then of the bodie

of Christ, and thou aunswerest
AMEN. Bee a member then of
the bodie of CHRIST, that that
may bee a true AMEN.
               Wherefore then is this mysterie
in the bread? Wee shall bring
nothing heere of our owne wit, but
let vs heare the Apostle, when hee
was speaking of that Sacrament,
saying, For wee being manie, are
one bread, and one bodie.
               And holie Augustine, instructing
vs sufficientlie of the rest, sayeth,
That as in that bread which was
offered on the Altar, the bodie of
Christ was resembled, so also the
bodie of the people that did receiue,
it was lyke-wyse represented;
that so hee might showe manifestlie,
that that is the proper bodie
of Christ onlie, which was borne
of the Virgin, sucked, suffered, died,
was buried, rose againe, ascended
to the Heavens, and which presentlie
sitteth at the right Hand of his
Father, and is to come to Iudgement:
But this which is set vpon

the Lordes Table, containeth the
mysterie of the bodie of the faythfull,
as the Apostle witnesseth, saying,
For wee beeing many, are one
bread, and one bodie in Christ.
               Wherefore (most Noble Prince)
let your wisedome consider, that
it is most clearlie showne, by Testimonies
of holie Scripture, and Sayings
 of the holie Fathers, That that
Bread which is called the Bodie of
Christ, &amp; that Cup which is called
the Blood of Christ, is a figure, because
it is a mysterie.
               
                   And that there is a great difference
betweene the mysterie of his
bodie, and his bodie it selfe, which
suffered, was buried, and rose againe;
because this is the proper
bodie of our Saviour; neither is
there in it any figure, or signification,
but the manifestation of the
thing it selfe is knowne; and the believers
desire the sight of him, because
hee is our head: and by the
sight of him, our desire shal be satisfied,
because He and the Father is

one, not according to that that our
SAVIOVR hath a bodie, but
according to the fulnesse of the
DEITIE which dwelleth in the
Man CHRIST. But in that which
is celebrated in a mysterie, is a resemblance,
not onlie of the proper
bodie of Christ, but also of all believers
in him: for it beareth the figure
of both the bodies; that is, both
of Christ which suffered, and rose
againe, and of the people which are
renewed in Christ by Baptisme, and
quickned from the dead.
               Let vs also adde this, That that 
Bread and Cup which is called the
Bodie and Blood of Christ, representeth
the remembrie of the Lords
Passion, or Death,Matthew, 26. as him selfe sayde
in the Gospell, Doe this in rememberance
of Mee. Which the Apostle
Sainct Paul expoundeth,1. Corinth. 11. saying,
How often so-ever yee eate this Bread,
and drinke this Cuppe, yee shall remember
the LORDES death, till
His comming againe. We are taught
then by our Saviour, and also by the

holie Apostle Sainct Paul, That
that Bread, and that Bloode, which
is set vpon the Altar, is set downe
in rememberance and resemblance
of the Lordes death and Passion,
that it may call to recent memorie
that which was done long a-goe:
where-by wee beeing remembered
of his death and suffering, may bee
made partakers there-by of that
heavenlie Gift, where-by wee are
redeemed from Death ever-lasting.
               
                   Knowe wee lyke-wyse, that
when wee come to the sight of
Christ him selfe, wee shall not haue
neede of such meanes, where-by
wee may bee admonished, what his
great bountifulnesse sustayned for
vs: because beholding him selfe,
face to face, wee shall not bee put in
mynde, by the outward admonition
of temporall thinges; but wee shall
beholde him by the contemplation
of the veritie it selfe, even as wee
ought, to giue thankes for ever vnto
the Author of our Salvation.
               
                  Neyther, there-fore, let it bee 
thought, al-be-it wee say this, that
there-fore the Bodie and Bloode of
Christ is not truelie apprehended
by the Faythfull, in the mysterie of
this Sacrament; seeing Fayth apprehendeth,
not that which the Eye
seeth, but that which it selfe believeth;
because it is spirituall foode,
and spirituall drinke, feeding the
Soule spirituallie, &amp; giving lyfe full
of eternitie, as the Lord, our Saviour,
commending this mysterie,
fayeth,Iohn, 6. 
                  It is the Spirite that quickeneth,
for the Flesh profiteth nothing.
               
               Desiring, then, to obey Your
Highnesse Commaund heere-in, I
beeing but of small abilitie, haue
vnder-taken to reason concerning
thinges of no small importance and
controversie: not following the
presumptiō of mine own thoughts
and estimation, but looking to the
authoritie of Fathers, and those
that haue gone before mee. Which
if You allowe to bee spoken catholicklie,

attribute the same vnto the
worthinesse of Your Fayth; who
laying a-syde the Glorie of Your
Royall Majestic, was not ashamed
to haue an Aunswere of the Veritie
from Your humble Servaunt. But
if it please You not, let it bee imputed
vnto mine insufficiencie, vvho
was not able to declare these things
so effectuallie, as other-wyse I desyred.
               AMEN.
            
         
         
            
            The Purging of
BERTRAM,
            
               Out of the Expurgatorie
Spanish Index, of Don Gasp
                     •
                  r,
Quiroga, Cardinall, and Arch-bishop
of Toledo, Generall Inquisitor of
Spayne; and set foorth by his Commaund,
and of the Councell of the
sayde Generall Inquisition; according
to the Decreet of the Councell of
Trent: and by the speciall Mandate &amp;
Authoritie of Philip the second, King
of Spayne; And by the care and direction
of the Duke of Alue, in the
Low-Countreys. Framed, and made
vp, Anno 1571.
            
               According to that Copie, printed
at Madrill there-after, by Alphonsus
Gomesius, His Majesties Printer
there, Anno 1594.
            
            That the Booke of BERTRAM,
Priest, Of the Bodie
and Blood of CHRIST, beeing
amended, may bee hence-foorth tolerated.
            The Iudgement, and Decree, of
the Vniversitie of Duay, approoved
by the Censures, as fol
                  •
               oweth:
            ALtho wee greatlie account
not of this Booke, and
therefore we are not much
carefull altho it were not at
all, or had perished: yet not-withstanding
seeing it hath beene often
printed here-to-fore, &amp; read by sundrie,
&amp; that by the forbidden name
there-of it hath bene made knowne
to all, and that the Heretickes doe
vnderstand of this mans prohibition
by diverse Catalogues, and
that he was a Catholicke Priest, and
a Monke of the Monasterie of Corbei,
and greatlie beloved and reverenced,
not so much by Charles the Great,

as Charles the bolde, as we may consider
in the Historie of his age: yet
in him, as in other Catholicke Writers,
wee must beare with many Erroures
of theirs, and we must extenuate
and excuse them, and oftentymes
by devising a fit exposition
to their words: Let vs even oftentymes
denye them, &amp; frame a commodious
meaning vnto them, while
as in Disputes, or conflicts with the
Adversaries, they are opponed against
vs: And therefore wee see
not why this BERTRAM requireth
not the same equitie, and diligent
examination: lest doing other-wyse,
by full suppressing of him, the Heretickes
accuse vs, That wee burne
and prohibite all Antiquitie making
for them: And therefore, that
it is no marvell that fewe seeme to
make for them, when wee that are
Catholickes, so vnreverentlie and
disdainfullie thrust foorth, and destroy
all Antiquitie amongst vs,
that but in verie show doe disagree
from vs.
            
               As also wee feare that not onlie
that Booke bee read by Heretickes,
but also that by disobedient Catholickes
the same bee more greedylie
perused, in respect of the interdiction
there-of, and that the same be
more dangerouslie alleadged; and
that beeing al-to-gether prohibited,
that it shall hurt more than beeing
permitted: for there is nothing in
it worthie of rebuke, except the obscurenesse
of the mans speach, and
an vnfit, either vsurpation, or exposition,
of some wordes, and sentences,
which by a marginall explanation,
either prefixed, or affixed,
if they were interpreted, and the
Authores meaning and scope were
there-by declared; and finallie, if
that some thinges which seeme not
obscurelie to be by some Hereticke
inserted, or added, about the ende
of the Treatise, were remarked, and
eschewed, there would bee nothing
then resting which might be feared
by the Reader in this Worke.
            
               There-fore, neyther evill, nor
vnadvisedlie, let all these thinges
bee omitted.
            About the ende of the thirde
Page, these wordes, It is lyke-wyse
to bee considered, that in that Bread,
&amp;c. Even to this a good deale after,
But it is another thing which is
outwardlie done, &amp;c. And againe,
even in the same Page, and in the
next there-vnto, all these speaches
which followe.
            
               As also these things that are one, are
comprehended vnder one Definition, &amp;c.
Even vnto that. For that which is
done in the lyfe spirituallie, &amp;c. So
these thinges beeing omitted, neyther
shall they obscure the preceeding
meaning, nor cause anie thing
to bee maymed, or superfluous.
            There resteth onlie one scruple,
but verie little to them that are Catholicklie
taught, (as BERTRAM

not once sayeth) That that which
appeareth in the 
                  •
               VCHARIST
doeth seede the bodie, is corruptible,
and not eternall, &amp;c. For that
the Catholicke Fayth attributeth
all these thinges vnto the Species
and Accidents of the Substances which
were before Trans-substantiation, is
more clearlie knowne, than can bee
declared other-wyse. For so wee
aunswere vnto the Experiences and
Assertions of the Berengarians, which
are rehearsed in Gvitmundus, who
sayde, That they founde by experience,
some to haue lived long, and
growne, by the Encharist alone: to
wit, these Accidents did as much as
other Substances.
            
            Neyther doe wee thinke, with
Guitmundus, that another substance
was substitute for their incredulitie,
or that Consecration or Trans-substātiation
did not solow, when their
intention who did celebrate the
same was wrong: For the naming

of the Substances of Bread and
Wine, (as hath beene sayde) are
taken for the formes, or accidentes,
of Bread and Wine. Altho I denye
not, but BERTRAM at that time
did not exactlie vnder-stand, that
these Accidentes did subsist without
a substance; and other thinges
also, which in the latter Age moste
subtillie, and truelie, by holie men
were added.
            Next, followeth those thinges
vvhich out of BERTRAM are al-together
not to bee deleted.
            Fol. 1137, reade Invisiblie for
Visiblie. And there-after, According
to the substance of the creatures, which
they were before Consecration, that same
they remayne after. It is to bee interpreted,
According to the externall
Accidents of the Sacrament.
            Fol. 1140. But this which is celebrated
in the Church, is temporall,

not eternall. It is to bee interpreted,
According to the corruptible accidents,
or of the thing it selfe, or
vse of the Sacrament, vvhich onlie
is in this Lyfe.
         
         
            
            An ancient Sermon,
of AELFRICVS,
Arch-bishop of Canterburie,
an English-man,
OF THE SACRAMENT:
Convincing the late Errour now-a-dayes
of Trans-substantiation.
Preached in the time of Etheldred,
King, And in the Yeare of our
LORD 996. Vttered in the
SAXON Tongue: And
thereafter in an old
English translated.
            MEN, BELOVED,
It hath beene often sayde
vnto you, about our SAVIOVRS
Resurrection; Howe hee
on this present day, after his suffering,

mightilie rose againe from
Death. Now will wee open vnto
you, by GODS Grace, of the holie
HOVSELLor Sacrament,, vvhich ye should now
goe vnto; and instruct your vnderstanding
about this Mysterie, both
after the Olde Covenan
                  •
               , and after
the New, that no doubting trouble
you concerning this lyuelie Food.
            The Almightie God bade Moses,
his Captaine, in the Land of Aegypt,
to command the people of Israel to
take to everie Familie a Lambe of a
yeare olde, the night that they departed
out of the Countrey, towards
the Land of Promise; and to offer
that Lambe to God; and after to cut
it, and make the signe of the Crosse
with the Lambes blood vpon the
side-poastes, and vpper poast of the
doore: and afterwards to eate the
Lambes fl
                  •
               sh roasted, and vnleavened
Bread, with wylde Lettuice.
God saith vnto Moses, Eate of the
Lambe, not raw, nor sodden in water,
but roasted at the fire; eate the

head, and the seete, and the inwards;
and let nothing of it bee left till the
morning: and if any thing remaine,
that shall yee burne with the fire.
Eate it this wise, Gird your Loynes,
and doe your Shooes on your seete,
haue you Stau
                  •
               s in your hands, and
eate it in haste. This is the Lords
Passeover. And there was r
                  •
               a
                  ••
               e on
that night, in everie house throughout
Pharaohs Reigne, the f
                  ••
               st-borne
chylde: and Gods people of Israel
were deliuered from that sudden
death, thorow the Lambes offering,
and his bloods marking.
            Then said God to Moses, Keepe
this day in your remembrance, and
holde it a great Feast in your Kinreds,
with a perpetuall observation;
and eate vnleavened bread alwayes
seaven dayes at this Feast.
            After this deede, God led the
people of Israel thorow the red Sea,
with drye foote, and drowned therin
Pharaoh, and all his Armie, together
with their Possessions; and

fed afterwards the Israelites fourtie
yeares, with heavenlie foode, and
gaue them water out of the hard
Rocke, vntill they came to the promised
Land.
            Part of this Storie we haue treated
of in another place, and part we
shal now declare; to wit, that which
belongeth to the holie Housell.
            Christen men may not now
keepe that olde Law bodilie; but it
behoveth them to know what it
ghostlie signifi
                  •
               th. That Innocent
Lambe, which the olde Israelites did
then kill, had signification after
ghostlie vnderstanding of Christs
suffering, who vnguiltie shed his
holie blood for our redemption.
Heere-of sing Gods servantes at
everie Masse, Agnus Dei, qui tollis peccata
mundi, miserere nobis: that is in
our speach, Thou Lambe of God,
that takest away the sinnes of the
world, haue mercie on vs.
            Those Israelites vvere delivered
from sudden death, and Pharaohs
               
bondage, by the Lambes offering,
which signifyed Christes suffering;
thorowe which wee are delivered
from ever-lasting Death, and from
the Devils cruell reigne, if wee
rightlie belieue in the true Redeemer
of the whole Worlde, even
Christ, the Saviour.
            That Lambe was offered in the
Evening, and our Saviour suffered
in the last Age of the Worlde. This
Age of the corruptible Worlde, is
reckoned to the Evening.
            They marked with the Lambes
blood vpon the Doores, and vpper
postes, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , THAV, that is the signe
of the Crosse, and were so defended
from the Angell that killed the
Aegyptian first-borne. And we ought
to marke our Fore-heads, and our
Heartes, with the Bloode of our
Lordes Suffering.
            Those Israelites did eate the
Lambes flesh yearlie, at Easter time,
when they were delivered: And
wee receiue Christes bodie ghostly,

and drinke his bloode, when wee
receiue, with true beliefe, that holie
Housell.
            That tyme they kept yearelie at
Easter, seaven dayes, with great
worship, when they were delivered
from Pharaoh, and departed from
that I and. So also Christen men
keepe Christes Resurrection, at the
tyme of Easter, seaven dayes, because
thorow his Suffering, and rysing,
wee are delivered, and are
made cleane, by going to this holie
Housell, as Christ sayeth in his Gospell,
Verilie, verilie, I saye vnto
you, Yee haue no lyfe in you, except
yee eate My Eleshe, and drinke My
Blood. Hee that eateth My Fleshe,
and drinketh My Bloode, abydeth in
Mee, and I in him, and hee hath
that Ever-lasting Lyfe, and I will
rayse him vp at the last Daye. I am
that lyuelie Bread which came downe
from Heaven: not so as your Fathers
did eate Manna in the Wildernesse, and
died. Hee that eateth this Bread, liveth
for ever.
            
            
               Hee blessed then Bread before
his suffering, and divided it vnto his
Disciples, thus saying, Eate of this
Bread, It is My Bodie: and doe this
in My rememberance. Also he blessed
Wine in one Cuppe, and sayde,
Drinke yee all of this: This is My
Blood, which is shedde for manie, in
forgiuenesse of sinnes. The Apostles
did also as Christ commanded: that
is, They blessed Bread and Wine, to
housell againe afterwardes in his rememberance.
Even so also their
Successoures, and all Priestes, by
Christes Commaundement, doe
blesse Bread and Wine, to housell
in his Name, with the Apostolicke
Blessing.
            Nowe men haue often searched,
and doe yet often search, howe
Bread, which is gathered of Corne,
and thorowe Fyres heate baked,
may bee turned to Christes bodie?
Or howe Wine, which is pressed
out of manie Grapes, is turned, thorowe

a blessing, to the Lordes
bloode?
            Nowe saye wee vnto such men,
That some thinges bee spoken of
Christ by signification, and some be
thinges certayne. True this is,
and certayne, That Christ was
borne of a Mayde, and suffered
death of his owne accorde, and
was buried, and on this Daye rose
agayne from Death. Hee is sayde
to bee Bread then by signification,
and a Lambe, and a Lyon, and a
Mountayne. Hee is called Bread,
because hee is our Lyfe, and Angels
lyfe. Hee is sayde to bee a Lambe,
for his innocencie. A Lyon, for
strength, where-with hee overcame
the strong Devill. But Christ
is not so, not-with-standing, after
true nature, neyther Bread, nor a
Lambe, nor a Lyon.
            Why is then that holie Housell
called Christs bodie? or his blood,
if it bee not truelie that which it is
called? Truelie the bread and the

wine, which in the Supper by the
Priest is hallowed, showe one thing
with-out, vnto humane vnderstanding;
and another thing with-in,
vnto believing mindes. With-out,
they are seene bread and wine, both
in figure, and taste: and they bee so
truelie after their hallowing: But
Christes bodie and blood, by ghostlie
mysterie.
            An Heathen Chylde is christened,
yet hee altereth not his shape
with-out, though hee bee chaunged
with-in. Hee is brought vnto the
Font-stone sinfull, thorowe Adams
disobedience: And how-be-it hee
is washed from all sinne with-in,
yet hee hath not changed his shape
with-out.
            Even so the holie Font water,
which is called the Well-spring of
Lyfe, is lyke in shape vnto other
water, and is subject to corruption:
but the holie Ghostes might commeth
to the corruptible water, thorowe
the Priestes blessing: and it

may after wash the bodie and soule
from all sinne, thorowe Ghostlie
might.
            Beholde, nowe wee see two
thinges in one creature, after true
nature, that water is corruptible
moysture, and after ghostlie mysterie,
hath whole-some vertue. So
also, if wee beholde that holie Housell
after bodilie vnderstanding,
then wee see that it is a creature,
corruptible, and mutable: but if
we acknowledge there-in ghostlie
might, then vnderstand wee that
life is there-in, and that it giveth
Immortalitie to them that eate it
with beliefe. Much is between the
invisible might of this holy Housel,
and the visible shape of its proper
nature. It is naturallie corruptible
bread and wine: and is by might
of Gods word, truelie Christes
bodie, and his blood: not so, not-with-standing,
bodylie, but ghostlie.
            Much is betweene the bodie

of Christ, which hee suffered in,
and the bodie which is hallowed to
housell. The bodie, truelie, that
Christ suffered in, was borne of the
flesh of Ma
                     •
                  ie, with blood and bone,
with skin and sinewes, in humane
limmes, with a reasonable soule,
living: But his ghostlie bodie,
which wee call the Housell, is gathered
of many Cornes, with-out
blood and bone, with-out limme,
with-out soule; and there-fore nothing
is to be vnderstood there-in
bodilie, but all ghostlie. What-so-ever
was in that Housell, which
giveth substance of life, that is of
the ghostlie might, and invisible
doing.
            Therefore is that holie Housell
called a mysterie, because there is
one thing in it seene, and another
thing vnderstoode. That which is
there seene, hath bodilie shape; and
that which wee doe there vnderstand,
hath Ghostlie might.
            Certainlie, Christs bodie which

suffered death, and rose againe from
death, never dieth hence-foorth,
but is eternall, and impassible. That
Housell is temporall, not eternall;
corruptible, and dealed in-to sundrie
partes; chewed betweene the
Teeth, and sent downe in-to the
bellie: how-be-it never-the-lesse
after Ghostlie might, it is all in everie
part: Manie receiue that holie
bodie, and yet not-with-standing it
is so all in everie part, after Ghostlie
mysterie. Though some chewe
the lesse, yet there is no more might
not-with-standing, in the more
parte, than the lesse, because it is
whole in all men, after the invisible
might.
            This mysterie is a Pledge, and
a Figure. Christes bodie is Trueth
it selfe. This Pledge wee doe
keepe mysticallie, vntill that wee
bee come vnto the Trueth it selfe,
and then is this Pledge ended.
Truelie it is so as wee before haue
saide, Christes bodie, and his blood,

not bodilie, but ghostlie.
            But now heare the Apostles
wordes about this mysterie. Paul
the Apostle speaketh of the olde Israelites
thus, writing in his Epistle
to faythfull men; All our Fore-fathers
were baptized in the Cloude, and in the
Sea; and all they did eate the same
ghostlie Meate, and dranke the same
ghostlie Drinke: They dranke truelie of
the Stone that followed them, and that
Stone was Christ. Neither was that
Stone then from which the Water
ranne, bodilie Christ; but it signified
Christ, who calleth thus to all
believing and faythfull men; Who-so-ever
thirsteth, let him come to Me, and
drinke, &amp; from his bowels shall flow liuely
water. This hee saide of the holie
Ghost, which they received, who
believed in him.
            The Apostle Paul saith, that the
Israelites did eate the same ghostlie
Meate, and dranke the same ghostlie
Drinke, because that heavenlie
Meate that fed them fourtie yeares,

and that water which from the
Stone did flow, had signification
of Christs bodie and his blood,
which now are offered daylie in
Gods Church. It was the same
which wee now offer, not bodilie,
but ghostlie.
            Wee saide vnto you ere-while,
that Christ hallowed bread and
Wine, to housell before his suffering,
and said, This is My Bodie,
and My Blood: yet he had not then
suffered, but so, not-with-standing
he turned, thorow invisible might,
that bread to his owne bodie, and
that wine to his owne blood, as hee
before did in the Wildernesse, before
that he was borne to be a Man,
when hee turned that heavenlie
meat to his flesh, and the flowing
water from that Stone to his owne
blood.
            Verie manie did eate of that
heavenlie Meat in the Wildernesse,
and dranke that ghostlie Drinke,
and were never-the-lesse dead, as

Christ saide: and Christ meant not
that death which none can escape;
but that ever-lasting death, which
some of that folke deserved for their
vnbeliefe. Moses and Aaron, and
many others of that people which
pleased God, did eate that heavenlie
Bread, and they died not that everlasting
death, tho they died the
common death. They saw that
that heavenlie Meate was visible
and corruptible, but they ghostlie
vnderstood, by that visible thing
another Meate, and ghostlie received
it.
            Our Saviour, saith, Hee that
eateth My Flesh, and drinketh My
Blood, hath ever-lasting Life. Now
hee bade them not eate that bodie
where-with hee was inclosed, nor
drinke that blood which he shed
for vs: but hee meant by these
words, that holie Housel, which
ghostlie is his bodie and his blood;
and hee that tasteth it with a believing
heart, hath that eternall life.
            
               In the olde Law faythfull men
offered to God diverse Sacrifices;
which had fore-signification of
Christs bodie, which for our sinnes
hee him selfe hath since offered to
his heavenlie Father for sacrifice.
Certainlie this Housell, which wee
hallow now at Gods Altar, is a Remembrance
of Christs bodie, which
hee offered for vs: and so him selfe
commanded, Doe this in My remembrance.
Once suffered Christ by him
selfe; but yet never-the-lesse his
suffering is daylie renewed at this
Supper, thorow the mysterie of the
holie Housel.
            Therefore wee ought to consider
diligentlie, how that this holie
Housel is both Christs bodie, and
the bodie of all faithfull men, after
ghostlie mysterie, as wyse Augustine
saith of it, If yee will vnderstand of
Christes bodie, heare the Apostle
Paul, thus speaking, Yee, truelie, be
Christs bodie, and his members.
Now is your mysterie set on Gods

Table, and yee receiue your mysterie,
which mysterie yee your
selues bee. Bee that which you see
on the Altar, and receiue that which
yee your selues bee.
            Againe, the Apostle Paul sayeth,
Wee beeing manie, are one Bread,
and one Bodie. Vnder-stand now,
and rejoyce: Manie bee one Bread,
and one bodie in Christ: Hee is our
head, and wee are his limmes. And
as the Bread is not of one Corne,
but of manie; nor the Wyne of one
Grape, but of manie: So also wee all
should haue one vnitie in the Lord;
as it is written of the faythfull Armie,
howe that they were in so
great an vnitie, as tho all of them
were one soule, and one heart. So
Christ hallowed on his Table, the
mysterie of our peace, and of our
vnitie. Hee which receiveth that
mysterie of vnitie, and keepeth not
the band of true peace, receiveth no
mystery for him selfe, but a witnesse
against him selfe.
            
               It is verie good for Christen
men, that they goe often to housell,
if they bring with them vnto the
Altar Vnguiltinesse, and innocencie
of heart: if they bee not oppressed
with sinne. To an evill man it
turneth to no good, but to destruction,
if hee receiue vnworthilie
that holie Housell.
            Holie Bookes commaund, that
water bee mingled with that wine
which shall bee for housell; because
the water signifyeth the people,
and the wine Christes blood: And
there-fore the one, with-out the
other, shall not bee offered at the
holie Housell: that Christ may bee
with vs, and wee with Christ; the
head, with the limmes; and the
limmes with the head.
            Wee would before haue intreated
of the Lambe which the olde
Israelites offered at their Easter time,
but that we desired first to declare
vnto you of this mysterie, and after,
how wee should receiue it.
            
               I. That signifying-Lambe was
offered at the Easter: and the Apostle
Sainct Paul sayeth, in the Epistle
of this present day, that Christ
is our Easter, or Passe-over; who
was offered for vs, and this daye
rose agayne from death.
            II. The Israelites did eate the
Lambes flesh, even as GOD had
commaunded them, with vnleavened
bread, and wilde Lettuice: So
should wee receiue that holie Housell
of Christes bodie and bloode,
with-out the leaven of Sinne and
Iniquitie: For as Leaven turneth
the creatures from their nature, so
doeth Sinne also change the nature
of Man, from Innocencie, to Vncleannesse.
And the Apostle hath
taught, howe wee should feast, not
in the Leaven of Evilnesse, but in
the sweete Dough of Puritie and
Trueth.
            III. The Hearbe which they
shoulde eate with the vnleavened
bread, is called Lettuice, and is bitter

in taste: So wee shoulde with
bitternesse of vnfeigned repentance
purifie our myndes, if wee will
eate Christes bodie.
            IIII. Those Israelites were not
wont to eate rawe flesh, and therefore
God bade them to eate it neyther
rawe, nor sodden in water, but
roasted with fyre. Hee shall receiue
the bodie of God rawe, that
shall thinke, with-out reason, that
Christ was onelie Man, lyke vnto
vs, and was not God. And hee
that will, after mans wisedome,
search of the mysterie of Christes
Incarnation, doeth lyke to him that
seetheth Lambes flesh in water; because
that water in this same place
signifyeth mans vnder-standing.
But wee should vnder-stand, that
all the mysterie of Christes humanitie
was ordered by the power of
the holie Ghost. And then eate
wee his bodie roasted with fyre,
because the holie Ghoste came in

fyerie lykenesse vnto the Apostles,
in diverse Tongues.
            V. The Israelites should eate the
Lambes head, and the feete, and the
purtenances; and no-thing must
there-of bee left over-night. If
anie thing there-of was left, they
did burne that in the fyre: And
they brake not the bones. After
ghostlie vnder-standing wee doe
then eate the Lambes head, when
wee take holde of Christes Divinitie
in our Beliefe. Againe, when
wee take holde of his Humanitie
with loue, then eate we the Lambes
feete; because that Christ is the Beginning,
and the Ende, GOD before
all Worlde, and Man in the
ende of this Worlde. What bee
the Lambes purtenances, but even
Christes secret Preceptes? And
these wee eate, when wee receiue
with griedinesse the Worde of
Lyfe. There must no-thing of the
Lambe bee left till the morning; because
all Gods Sayinges are to bee

searched with carefulnesse, and
great diligence: so that all his Preceptes
must bee knowne in vnderstanding
and deede, in the night of
this present lyfe, before the last day
of the vniversall Resurrection doe
appeare. And if wee can not
search out throughlie all the mysterie
of Christes Incarnation, then
ought wee to betake the rest vnto
the might of the holie Ghost, with
true humilitie: and not to search
rashlie of that deepe secretnesse,
aboue the measure of our vnderstanding.
            VI. They did eate the Lambes
flesh with their Loynes girded. In
the Loynes, is the lust of the bodie.
And hee that will receiue that holie
housell, shall cover and wrap in
that Concupiscence, and take with
Chastitie that holie Receit.
            VII. They were also shod. And
what bee Shooes, but of the hydes
of dead beastes? Wee bee truelie

shod then, if wee match in our steps
and deedes, the liues of men departed
this lyfe, which pleased God
with keeping of his Commandementes.
            VIII. They had Staues in their
handes, when they did eate. This
staffe signifieth a care-fulnesse, and
a diligent over-seeing: and all they
that best knowe, and can, should
take care of other men, and stay
them vp with their helpe.
            IX. It was enjoyned to the
eaters, that they should eate the
Lambe in haste; for God abhorreth
sloath-fulnesse in his Servants: and
those hee loveth, which seeke the
joye of Ever-lasting Lyfe, with
quicknesse, and hastinesse of mynd.
Prolong not to turne vnto GOD,
left the tyme passe away, thorowe
thy slow tarrying.
            X. The eaters might not breake
the Lambes bones: No more might
the Souldioures, which did hang

CHRIST, breake His Holie
Legges, as they did of the two
Thieues which hanged on eyther
syde of Him: And the LORD
arose from death sound and whole,
with-out all corruption: And at the
last Iudgement, they shall see Him,
Whome they did moste cruellie
wound on the Crosse.
            XI. This Tyme is called in the
Hebrew Tongue PASCHA, and in
Latine TRANSITVS, and in English a
PASSE-OVER; Because that
vpon this daye the people of Israell
passed from the Lande of Aegypt,
thorowe the redde Sea, from
the bondage of Pharaoh, towardes
the Land of Promise. So also did
our LORD, at this Tyme, departe
(as sayeth Sainct IOHN the
EVANGELIST) from this Worlde,
to His heavenly Father. And even
so wee ought to follow our HEAD,
and to goe from the Devill, vnto
CHRIST: from this vnstable

Worlde, vnto His stable KINGDOME:
How-bee-it wee shoulde
first, in this present lyfe, departe
from Vyce, vnto holie VERTVE:
from evill manners, vnto good: if
vvee vvill, after this our lent lyfe,
goe to that Eternall Lyfe, and after
our resurrection, to CHRIST:
Hee bring vs vnto His Ever-lasting
Father, Who gaue Him vnto
Death for our Sinnes: To Him
bee Honour, and Prayse of
Well-doing, Wordle
with-out ende.
            AMEN.
         
         
            
            
               
            
         
         
            
            A Notable Short
DISCOVRSE,
VVritten by a Scots-man,
(AS BALE vvitnesseth)
OF THE SACRAMENT:
Who lived in that same Age with
BERTRAM, 800 yeares agoe: named
RABANVS, or Magnentius
Maurus: learned in all Sciences,
A Professor long in the
Vniversitie of Paris,
and at last made
An Abbot, vnder Lodovicus Pius.
            OF the other two thinges,Lib. 5. c. 11 De Seim. propriet.
left vnto vs in Legacie,
that is, Of the Bodie and
Blood of the LORD, it may be asked,
Why amongst all the Fruites

of the Earth, chiefelie he did choose
Bread and Wine, to designe the
same, as if these did excell all other
Fruites of the Earth in woorth, and
were of greatest value? Which
Question wee thinke may bee thus
solved: Our LORD did choose,
that the Sacrament of his bodie
and blood should bee so received
by the mouth of the Faythfull, and
that the same should bee converted
to their nowrishment; that by the
visible worke, the invisible effect,
and working of the other, might
be showne, and made manifest.
            For as the materiall Foode outwardlie
nowrisheth and feedeth the
bodie, so the Word of God inwardlie
nowrisheth the Soule, &amp; strengtheneth
the same: For it is not by
Bread onelie that Man liveth, but
by everie Word that procedeth out
of the Mouth of God: And the
Word is become Flesh, and hath

dwelt amongst vs (sayeth Trueth
it selfe.)
            And (as sayeth Christ himselfe)
My Flesh is Meat indeede, and My
Blood is Drinke indeede. Now the flesh
of Christ is Meate indeede, because
it feedeth truelie, and nowrisheth
man vnto eternall Life; (which is
onelie true Life) and his blood is
Drinke indeede, because truelie and
solidlie it satiateth and slockeneth
for ever the hungering and thirsting
soule after Righteousnesse. For as
for temporall life, men indeede may
haue the same with-out this meate
and drinke; but that Eternall they
cannot attaine vnto; because that
this Meate and Drinke signifieth
that eternall societie and fellowship
of the members vvith their
head, and their strait conjunction:
For (sayeth hee,) Hee that eateth
My Flesh, and drinketh My Blood,
abydeth in Mee, and I in him. Wherfore
it is needfull, that wee receiue

his bodie and blood, that wee may
abyde in Him, and become members
of His Bodie.
            And the Sacrament heere-of,
to wit, of our Becomming one
with CHRISTES bodie and
blood, it is taken off from the Table,
to some men, vnto destruction; but
the thing it selfe which is signified,
is taken by all men vnto lyfe, and
by none vnto destruction. For who-so-ever
is partaker of that, the same
man shall bee associate as a member
to CHRIST his head, into that
Heavenlie Kingdome.
            For it is another thing the Sacrament
it selfe, and the vertue of
the Sacrament. The Sacrament it
selfe, is onelie taken by the mouth;
but by the vertue of the Sacrament,
the inward man is refreshed. The
Sacrament also is turned into the
food of the bodie; but by the vertue

of the Sacrament, the dignitie
of eternall Lyfe is obtained. In the
Sacrament againe, all the faythfull
Communicantes make a paction of
mutuall fellow-ship, and brotherlie
peace amongst them selues heere;
but by the vertue of the Sacrament,
all the members, joyned and straitlie
coupled with their head in eternall
Glorie, shall rejoyce for ever.
            Therefore, as the Sacrament it
selfe is turned in our substance,
when wee haue eaten and drunken
the same; so lyke-wyse shall wee be
turned into the bodie of Christ, if
wee obedientlie and holilie liue in
him.
            Wherefore, because Bread
strengtheneth the bodie, therefore
for the lyke operation towardes the
soule, it is called Christs bodie: and
because Wine furnisheth nutritiue
blood, and cheareth the bodie,
therefore is for that relation to

Christes bloode, why it is compared
there-vnto. And these visible
signes, when they are sanctified,
then by the holie Spirit they are
converted into the Sacrament of
the bodie of Christ.
            But it is onelie in the way of
this lyfe,Cap. 10. de Eucharistia. that wee are so sed, and
refreshed with the Sacrament of
the bodie and blood of Christ; that
so nowrished there-by, wee may
become one bodie: and by the tasting
of this heere, wee may bee
prepared for immortall and eternall
thinges heere-after.
            And in so farre as spirituallie
wee are quickened in him, being
sealed vp by Angels Foode vnto
that lyfe, that holie Spirite of his
worketh powerfullie in vs, by these
his holie Sacraments.
            And because according to the

flesh it behoved him to pearce the
Heavens,Cap. 41. that these who by fayth
are renewed, and borne over againe
in him, might more confidentlie
and earnestlie long after him, hee
hath left vnto vs this Sacrament,
as a visible Figure, and Resemblance;
a Signe, and a Seale of his
bodie and blood: that by these
thinges, our myndes, and our bodies,
by fayth, more plenteouslie
may bee nowrished, to partake of
invisible and spirituall thinges.
            Now it is the Signe and Seale
which outwardlie we see and feele:
but that which is inwardlie participated,
is all Substance and Trueth,
and no shadowing or resemblance:
and therefore there is nothing but
Trueth, and the Sacrament of the
verie flesh of CHRIST, which
is manifested vnto vs. For the
verie flesh of CHRIST which
was crucified, and buried, even the

SACRAMENT of that true flesh
it is, which by the Priest vpon
the Altar, through the word
of CHRIST, and power
of the holie Spirit,
from Aboue is
consecrated,
&amp; made
holie.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            
               
               
                  
               
            
            
         
      
   

