
   
      
         
            The demonstration of Antichrist. By Edmund Gurnay, Bach. Theol. p. of Harpley Norfolke
            Gurnay, Edmund, d. 1648.
         
         
            
               1631
            
         
         Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02398
            STC 12529
            ESTC S120940
            99856131
            99856131
            21654
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02398)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21654)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1069:9)
         
         
            
               
                  The demonstration of Antichrist. By Edmund Gurnay, Bach. Theol. p. of Harpley Norfolke
                  Gurnay, Edmund, d. 1648.
               
               [6], 28, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by I[ohn] B[eale] for Iames Boler, and are to be sold at the signe of the Marigold in Pauls Churchyard,
                  London :
                  1631.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A¹²  B⁶.
                  Running title reads: Ecce Antichristum.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  Tightly bound.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.
               Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.
               Popes --  Primacy --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-02
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-02
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE Demonſtration OF ANTICHRIST.
            
            BY EDMVND GVRNAY, Bach. Theol. P. of Harpley Norfolke.
            
            LONDON, Printed by I.B. for Iames Boler, and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Marigold in Pauls Churchyard. 1631.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE ALL-HOPEFVLL Charles, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, PRINCE of Wales, &amp;c.
            
               IT is the glorie of all temporall power to maintaine the glory of Chriſt,

and ſo conſequently to confound Antichriſt, When, therefore, the prouidence of God ſends temporall Princes into the world, ſuch as can giue any intelligēce toward the diſcouering this Antichriſt, cannot be thought ouerhastie in preſenting the ſame vnto them. Indeed, the intelligence which this little Booke can do in ſuch kind of buſineſſe muſt needs be thought

little; notwithſtanding, it was a little pibble-ſtone that bored the Front of Goliah, when the valiant men of Iſrael were afraid to encounter him. Alſo the littleneſſe of it may be a meanes to induce Gods little ones, the ſooner to begin to turne the leaues thereof as they ſhall begin to awake vnto the day-light of vnderſtanding. Which happy time of our Princes awaking,

It reſoluing to wait; the Author ſhall in the meane time beſeech the Almighty to viſit him daily with the light of His countenance, and as his Abilities ſhall grow, to allure them into the moſt pleaſant paths of His moſt Royal
                  •
                ſeruice.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               ECCE ANTICHRISTƲM.
            
               HEE that profeſſeth himſelfe the ſupreme head of the Church of Chriſt, and yet forceth men, vpon paine of death, to blaſpheme Chriſt, Hee is Antichriſt.
            Becauſe it cannot be imagined how any power vpon earth can more cunningly, and out of a deeper myſterie doe Chriſt ſuch vniuerſall miſchiefe.
            But the Pope of Rome does

profeſſe himſelfe the Supreme head of the Church of Chriſt, (and that is granted) and yet forceth men vpon paine of death, (both temporall and eternall) to blaſpheme Chriſt.
            And this we thus proue:
            Hee that forceth men vpon paine of death to grant, that there is no other Chriſt but He whoſe perfit Body, Soule, and Deity hath, for theſe 1600. yeers laſt paſt, beene ordinarily preſent amongſt men vnder that particular forme which immediately before the ſpeaking of a few words was the forme of a ſenſeleſſe creature, and in that forme does enter into the mouthes of liuing creatures▪ he forceth men to blaſpheme Chriſt.
            Becauſe this poſition does blaſpheme,

                  
                  The Manhood of Chriſt.
                  The God-head of Chriſt.
                  The Maieſty of Chriſt.
                  The Holineſſe of Chriſt.
                  The Iuſtice of Chriſt.
                  The Mercy of Chriſt.
                  The Wiſdome of Chriſt.
                  The Power and Word of Chriſt.
               
            
            Firſt, it blaſphemes the manhood 
of Chriſt; becauſe it giues Him ſuch a Body as in the outward eyes of thoſe that are preſent with Him hath no more ſimilitude with the body of a man than a chip or a ſtone.
            Secondly, it blaſphemeth His 
God-head; becauſe it ſuppoſeth the Creator to be ordinarily vnited vnto the forme of a creature.
            Thirdly, it blaſphemeth his 
Maieſty; becauſe it giues Him

ſuch an outward preſence as the vileſt and pooreſt man liuing would be aſhamed of, and euen vtterly abhorre.
            
                Fourthly, it blaſphemeth His Holineſſe; becauſe it ſuppoſeth Him to goe through more vncleane paſſages, than euer liuing man did, and ſuch as of neceſſity do either reiect or corrupt whatſoeuer they receiue.
            
                Fifthly, it blaſphemeth His Iuſtice; becauſe it affirmeth Him to be ordinarily preſent amongſt men, in a forme nothing like a man; and yet wee muſt vpon paine of damnation beleeue that He is a perfit man.
            
                Sixthly, it blaſphemeth His Mercy; becauſe it layes this intolerable burthen vpon the Faith of little ones, either to looke for no ſaluation, or to beleeue that

thing to be their Sauiour which in all outward appearance is but a morſell of bread.
            Seuenthly, it blaſphemeth His 
Wiſedome; becauſe it ſuppoſeth Him to worke daily multitudes of moſt incredible and moſt ſtupendious miracles, for no other purpoſes but ſuch as are daily effected without any miracles at all: there being no kinde of benefit redounding vnto mankind by this His ſuppoſed bodily preſence, but ſuch as daily does redound vnto vs in His bodily abſence: For daily does Hee giue vs the gift of Faith in His bodily abſence; daily does He conuerſe with men, ſup with men, and dwell with men in His bodily abſence; daily does Hee giue all kind of gifts vnto men in his bodily abſence; daily does

He ſend the cōforter in his bodily abſence; For the cōforter wil not come vnles He goes away; Ioh. 16.7. Yea (finally) daily does e giue vs his fleſh to eat in His bodily abſence; For except we eat his fleſh, we haue no life in vs, (Ioh. 6.53.) But hee that beleeueth hath euerlaſting life (Ioh. 6.
                  •
               7.) and therefore he that beleeueth, does alwayes (in His moſt bodily abſence) eat His Fleſh. To conclude, What benefit, what Grace, what comfort was euer heard of, or can be imagined, but may bee imparted vnto men as well (not to ſay incomparably more eaſily, more ſweetly, more credibly) In His bodily abſence, as in this ſuppoſed bodily preſence, wherunto ſuch ſtupendious miracles muſt concurre: namely (for a taſte of them) theſe amongſt others:

1. That the perfit Body of a man muſt bee couched and contriued into the forme of a bit of bread. 2. That the liuing body of one man muſt wholly enter into the mouth of another. 3 That the ſame man ſhall be in infinite places at once. 4. That the perfit Body of man ſhall ordinarily come downe from heauen, and yet the outward eyes of thoſe which entertain Him ſhall not ſee it. 5. That theſe ſo vncouth wonders ſhall be wrought at the call of mortall men (euery Prieſt) vnto the end of the world, &amp;c. And is not this a blaſpheming of the wiſedome of the Almighty to make him the de
               
                  •
               iſor of theſe ſo inglorious, and (to ſay nothing of the quality of them) inſuperfluous miracles.
            Alſo wee further adde, that it 
               
blaſphemeth his Power; becauſe it makes it the inſtrument of ſuch operations as are diſhonourable and repugnant vnto His Wiſdome, His Maieſty, His Iuſtice, and euen all His conditions and attributes; whereas the power of God on the contrary does ſo infinitely apply it ſelfe to the honour and glory of God, as that it doth continually reſiſt, confound and deſtroy whatſoeuer does offer the leaſt diminution vnto it.
            
                Laſt of all, it blaſphemeth his Word; and that both His created Word, and alſo His reuealed Word.
            For what is his created Word, but the faculties of Senſe &amp; Reaſon? What word, or what light had man in his innocency, to ſhew him which was the middle

tree in the garden (which vpon paine of death he was forbidden to taſte of) but his common Senſe? And what other word or light haue men now in the ſtate of recouery, to tell them which is a man, and which is a beaſt; which is a fiſh, and which is a ſerpent; and to lay them out their particular taskes, portion▪ and callings, but their common Senſe? This therefore ſo immediately created and ſacred light, if it bee made a notorious lyar, (for what is it elſe if it conſtantly affirmes that to bee a morſell of bread which indeed is the perfit Body of a man?) Is not therein the Word of God blaſphemed?
            And as for his Reuealed Word, both His Originall Word (the Scriptures) and alſo His deriued Word (the Fathers) are not they

alſo contradicted and blaſphemed by this poſition.
            For firſt, concerning the Scripture, does not that euery where tell vs, That our Sauiour was in euery point like a man? That He had the face, limbs, and properties of a man? That Hee did eat, drinke, and ſpeake like a man? Alſo doe not the Scriptures expreſly ſay, That the Heauens muſt containe him till all things bee reſtored? Acts 3.20. And that He ſhall ſo deſcend from heauen; as Hee firſt aſcended vp into heauen? Whereas by this poſition Hee hath for theſe 1600. yeeres continually deſcended bodily from heauen, not once in ſuch a manner deſcend, as Hee firſt aſcended: Yea, the Scripture euery where tells vs that now Hee is in the ſtate of Glory; whereas this

poſition contriues Him into a more vile forme than euer man had, and tyes Him to a more baſe condition than euer any man (or indeed any liuing creature) did vndergoe. For though they ſeeme to doe Him great honour while they carry Him about (in thoſe breaden formes) in their pompous proceſſions; yer when withall they profeſſe that in the end he is to be eaten vnder thoſe breaden formes, all the honour they beſtow on him is no better honour vnto him, then the guilding the Buls hornes when hee is led to be baited, is an honour vnto the Bull. Finally, the Bread which our Sauiour termed His Body, does not the Scripture every where call it ſtill bread notwithſtanding, He tooke, brake, bleſſed, and gaue Bread, ſay all

the Euangeliſts; ſometime alſo ſaying as much of the cup as of the wine: Paul alſo calling it bread, both in the bleſſing, and in the eating, and alſo after the eating: and the Acts of the Apoſtles terming theſe Communions (Chap. 2.42.) a continuance in breaking bread: and (Chap. 20.7.) a comming together to break bread: And all the Fathers for many hundred yeeres together immediately following the firſt Inſtitution, when at any time they made mention of it, as ſecurely calling it bread, as if they neuer imagined that any would euer make queſtion thereof. And for proofe hereof, wee haue thought good to cloſe vp this point with a border of citation
                  •
                out of them; leauing the force of their ſayings to the applicati
                  •••
               
               
of the Reader for breuity ſake.Circa An. c. p 2.
               
            
            
               Clemens Romanus (to cite them according to the times wherein they liued) ſaith thus of it; We offer vnto thee our King and our God, this bread and this wine, giuing thee thankes: Concil. Tom. 2.
            
               Ignatius thus;An. c. 10
                        •
                     
                  
               There is one fleſh of our Lord Ieſus, and one Bloud, one bread and one cup. Epiſt. 2.
            
               Iuſtine Martyr thus;133. When prayers are finiſhed, Bread and Wine is offered: And elſewhere thus; Chriſt hath giuen the bread to the end wee ſhould remember that He was made a body for ſuch as ſhould beleeue. In Dial. contra Tryphon. and Apolog. 2.
            
               Irenaeus Martyr thus;
                  An. 172. As the Euchariſt conſiſting of two natures, the earthly and the heauenly,

ſo our Bodies, &amp;c.
            
               
                  An. 196.
               Tertullian thus; Calling the bread His body, to the end you may vnderſtand that He hath giuen bread to bee a figure of His body. Contra Marcion. 3.19.
            
               Clemens Alexandrinus thus; The Wine ſignifies the Bloud allegorically. Lib. de paedagog. 10.6.
            
               An. c. 207.
               
               Origen thus; If you take this ſaying, [Except ye eat the fleſh of the ſonne of man, &amp;c.] according to the Letter, the Letter killeth. Hom. 7. in Leuit. &amp; elſwhere thus; After we haue giuen thankes, we eat the Loues preſented. Contra Celſun. 8.
            
               
                  An. 250.
               Cyprian thus; Our Lord gaue with His owne hands bread and wine, which He called His Body. De vnct. Chriſ. and elſwhere thus; This bread is conuerted into our fleſh and bloud, and ſerueth

for our life. Epiſt. 2.
            
               Euſebius Caeſarienſis thus;
                  An. 308. Chriſt and His Miniſters doe repreſent the myſteries of His Body and Bloud by bread and wine. De Demonſt. Euangel. 5.3.
            
               Athanaſius thus;
                  An. 327. How few would his Body haue ſufficed that it ſhould be meat for all the world. In illud [quicun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   &amp;c.]
            
               Concilium Nicenum thus;
                  An. 329. Wee muſt not baſely [humiliter] be intent vpon the bread and the eup, but lifting vp our mindes by faith, &amp;c. Concil. 1.
            
               Macarius Egypt, thus;
                  An 360. In the Church bread and wine is offered being the figure of his fleſh and bloud. Homil. 27.
            
               Epiphanius thus;
                  An. 379. Chriſt ſpeaking of a loafe which is round in figure, and cannot ſee, heare, nor feele, ſaith of it, This is my Body.

               In Anchor.
            
            
               
                  An. 384.
               Ambroſe thus; Thou ſaweſt the Sacraments vpon the Altar, and wondredſt at the creature; yet is it a ſolemne and knowne creature: De Sacram. 4.3. And elſewhere thus; In the Law was a ſhadow, in the Goſpell an image, in Heauen the truth. Lib. 10. ex offic. C. 48.
            
               Gregory Niſſen, thus; Whoſe hath abundantly drunke of the Apoſtles ſprings, hath already receiued whole Chriſt. In vi
                     •
                   Moſ.
            
            
               
                  An. 385.
               Chryſoſtome thus; If it be dangerous to transferre ſanctified veſſels vnto priuate vſes, where in not the true Body of Chriſt but onely a myſterie of that body is contained: how much leſ
                  •
                ought wee to giue the veſſels of our owne bodies to the deuil
                  •
               
               
which God hath prepared for himſelfe to inhabit. In Matth. 5. Homil. 11. and elſewhere thus; It is counted worthy to be called the Lords Body, though the nature of bread remaineth there ſtill. Ad Caeſar. Monach. citat. à 
                     •
                  arijs Author. And againe, thus; Wooll when it is died, is called no longer wooll, but Purple or Scarlet, though the nature of wooll ſtil remaineth. In Pſal. 22.
            
               Gregory Nazianzen thus;
                  An. 378. We 
                  •
               ow partake the Paſſeouer, 
                  •
               hough in a figure, yet much more cleare than in the old Law. De Paſch. Orat. 2.
            
               Hierome thus; Chriſt is not corporally in the Church. In Prou, 1.
                  •
               . and elſewhere thus; Chriſt left bread and wine, as he that goes 
                  •
               voyage leaues a gage: In prim. 
                     •
                  d Corinth. 11. and againe, thus;

I take the Goſpel to be the body of Chriſt, and that more truly than the Sacrament. In Pſal. 147.
            
               
                  An. 394.
               Auſtine thus; If we looke to the viſible ſignes, by which the Sacraments are performed, who can bee ignorant that they are corruptible. De Bapt. Lib. 3. Cap. 10. And elſewhere thus; By reaſon of the reſemblance betwixt the Sacraments and the things, the Sacraments often times take the name of the things. Epiſt. 23. And elſewhere thus; this is a perfit rule to vnderſtand whether a ſpeech be figuratiue, that whatſoeuer in Scripture cannot bee referred vnto integrity o
                  •
                faith, or verity of manners, that reſolue thy ſelfe is figuratiue. D
                     •
                   doctr. Chr. Lib. 3. Chap. 10. Where upon hee inferres our Sauiour ſpeech, [of eating his fleſh] to be

figuratiue, becauſe according to the Letter, it is a ſinfull act; calling it a carnall ſenſe to take figuratiue ſpeeches properly, and a miſerable bondage of the ſoule.
            
               Theodoret thus;
                  An. 424. He honoured the ſignes which we ſee, with the name of His body, not changing the nature, but caſting grace vpon nature. And elſewhere thus; The myſticall ſignes after ſanctification doe not depart from their nature, but remaine in their former ſubſtance, figure, and 
                  •
               orme. Dial. 2.
            
               Cyril thus; Our Sacrament a
               
                  •
               oucheth not the eating of a man. Ad obiect. Theod. And elſewhere thus; He gaue peeces of bread to His Diſciples. In 4. Io
                  
                     •
                  n.
            
            
               Gelaſius thus;
                  An. 490. By the Sacraments

we are made partakers of the heauenly nature and yet for all that ceaſeth not the nature of bread and wine. Contra Eutichenſ.
            
            
               
                  An. 550.
               Fulgentius thus; How did He goe vp to heauen but as he is very man, contained in a place? Or how is Hee preſent with the faithfull, but as He is very God without all meaſure? Ad Thraſimach. Regul. 2.
            
               
                  An. 526.
               Ephrem thus; Taking bread into His hands, He bleſſed it, and brake it for a figure of His body. Contra Inquiſ. Diuin. Natur.
            
            
               Vigilius thus; To goe to His Father, and from vs; was to take from the world that nature which he receiued of vs. Contra Eutichenſ.
            
            
               
                  An. 550.
               Concilium Conſtant. thus; Chriſt commanded the whole ſubſtance of bread, choſen for His Image

to bee ſet on the table, leſt if it reſembled the ſhape of a man, Idolatry might bee committed. Extat in Concil. Nicen. 2.
            
               Procopius Gazeus thus; There is now giuen an Image, a Type, a Figure of His body, receiuing no more the bloudy Sacrifices of the Law. Super Gen. 49.
            
               Beda thus; Hee ſubſtituting the Sacrament of His Fleſh in the figure of bread and wine. In Luk. 22. And elſewhere out of Auſtine thus; That which you ſee, 
                  •
               is bread and wine, which your very eyes can tell you. In 1 Cor. 10.
            
               Druthmarus thus; Wine maketh glad, and increaſeth blood; and therfore the blood of Chriſt is aptly figured thereby. In Mat.
            
            
               Rhabanus Maurus thus; The Sacrament is turned into the bodies

nouriſhment. Lib. 1. Chap. 13.
            
               Paſchaſius thus; What finde they which taſte theſe things, beſide bread and wine, otherwiſe than by faith and hearing? De corp. &amp; ſang. Dom.
            
            
               Bertramus thus; The ſignes, as touching the ſubſtance of the creatures, are the ſame after conſecration that they were before. De corp. &amp; ſang. Dom.
            
            
               Bernard thus; What is it to eat His fleſh, and drinke His blood, but to communicate with His paſſions, and to imitate His conuerſation. In Pſalm. [qui habitat &amp;c.]
            
               Bonauenture thus; The Sacraments are ſaid to containe Gods Grace, not as a veſſell does water, but becauſe they ſignif
                  •
                Gods Grace. In 4. Sentent. Diſ
                     •
                  
                1.9.3.
            
               And his Text-man Lumbard thus; Chriſt offered Himſelfe vpon the Croſſe, and his remembrance in the Sacrament. Lib. 4. diſt. 12.
            The gloſſe vpon the Common-Law (a principall witneſſe in this cauſe) thus; It is His body improperly after a faſhion, not in truth but in ſignification, quoting Auſtine for it. Super Canon. Hoc eſt corpus meum. Decr. p. 3. diſt. 2.16.
            Moſt true therfore our ground is, that whoſoeuer inforceth men vpon paine of death, to grant that there is no other Chriſt but he which is ordinarily preſent amongſt men in the forme of common bread, he forceth men 
                  •
               o blaſpheme Chriſt. All the na
               
                  •
               ures, properties, and attributes of Chriſt being blaſphemed by 
                  •
               uch aſſertion.
            
               But the Pope of Rome does force men vpon paine of death (both ſpirituall and temporall) ſo to grant: Their Tridentine Councell inforcing it vpon paine of ſpiritual death, in theſe words; viz. Whoſoeuer ſhall deny that in the moſt holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, is truly and really contained the Body and Bloud, together with the Soule and Diuinity of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore whole Chriſt; but ſhall ſay that it is there onely as in a ſigne, or in a figure, or vertue, let him be accurſed. Concil. Trident. Seſſ 3. And one of their Synode enioyning Berengari
                     •
                  
                thus to ſay; With my mouth and with my heart, I profeſ
                  •
                that the bread and the wine afte
                  •
                conſecration, is not onely a Sacrament, but alſo the true body

and blood of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſenſually in truth is handled and broken with the hands of the Prieſts, and torne (atteri) with the teeth of the faithfull. Decret. p. 3. diſt. 2.16. Ego Berengarius, &amp;c.
            
            And as for temporall death which the gaine-ſayer of this poſition did thereupon vndergoe; what Nation vnder their authority hath not records thereof written in bloud? Not to cite their ſecular lawes, which condemne all, heretikes (amongſt which, the reſiſter of this poſition they count the cheefe) ad poenam ignis: i.e. To bee burnt to death, and to vndergoe all kinde of penalties beſide, in their name,  friends, fautors, poſterity, goods and fortunes that can bee imagined. Summa Angelica. Litera here
                  
                     •
                  icus.
            
            
               Or if our Engliſh Admirers of Rome will beleeue nothing concerning the Diſcipline of that Church, but ſo farre forth as they can be aſſured thereof within the bounds of England; they may haue recourſe to the ſix Articles eſtabliſhed in Engliſh Parliament▪ the firſt whereof enacteth thus▪
            
            Whoſoeuer ſhall ſay, that in the Sacrament of the Altar vnder the forme of bread and wine (after the conſecration thereof) there is not preſent, really, the naturall Body and Bloud of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt; conceiued of the Virgine Mary; or that after the ſaid conſecration there remaineth any ſubſtance of bread or wine, or any other ſubſtance but the ſubſtance of Chriſt, both God and man, &amp;c. then he ſhall be adiudged an heretike, and ſuffer

death by burning, and ſhall forfeit to the King, all his lands, tenements, &amp;c. as in caſe of hye reaſon. An. 31. Hen. 8.14.
            For though this law was enacted when the Popes authority was ſuppreſſed, yet did it take the beginning from the Church of Rome: and a little after, in the reigne of Quene Mary, was executed to the full, by vertue of the Romiſh authority.
            Our Demonſtration therefore is moſt plaine, and let hea
               
                  •
               en and earth bee Iudge of it.
            Hee that profeſſeth himſelfe the Supreme head of the Church of Chriſt, and yet forceth men 
                  •
               pon paine of death (both temporall and eternall) to blaſpheme Chriſt; hee is Antichriſt.
            
               But the Pope of Rome ſo profeſſeth, and ſo inforceth.
            Therefore En &amp; ecce Antichriſtum.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

