
   
      
         
            A publication of Guiana's plantation Newly undertaken by the Right Honble. the Earle of Barkshire (Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter) and company for that most famous river of the Amazones in America. Wherein is briefly shewed the lawfulnesse of plantations in forraine countries; hope of the natives conversion; nature of the river; qualitie of the land, climate, and people of Guiana; with the provisions for mans sustenance, and commodities therein growing for the trade of merchandise and manner of the adventure. With an answer to some objections touching feare of the enemie.
         
         
            
               1632
            
         
         Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02325
            STC 12456
            ESTC S119063
            99854270
            99854270
            19680
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02325)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19680)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1103:01)
         
         
            
               
                  A publication of Guiana's plantation Newly undertaken by the Right Honble. the Earle of Barkshire (Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter) and company for that most famous river of the Amazones in America. Wherein is briefly shewed the lawfulnesse of plantations in forraine countries; hope of the natives conversion; nature of the river; qualitie of the land, climate, and people of Guiana; with the provisions for mans sustenance, and commodities therein growing for the trade of merchandise and manner of the adventure. With an answer to some objections touching feare of the enemie.
                  Day, J., attributed name.
               
               [2], 24 p.   
               
                  Printed by William Iones for Thomas Paine, and are to bee sold in Trinitie Lane at the signe of the Horse-shooe,
                  London :
                  1632.
               
               
                  A prospectus.
                  At end: initials "I.D.", i.e. J. Day, one of the adventurers?--STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Guyana --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.
               Amazon Valley --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-09
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
PVBLICATION
OF GVIANA'S
PLANTATION
Newly undertaken by the Right
Honble. the Earle of BARKSHIRE (Knight
of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter)
and Company for that moſt famous River
of the Amazones in America.
            
            
               Wherein is briefly ſhewed the lawfulneſſe of plantations
in forraine Countries; hope of the natives
converſion; nature of the River; qualitie of
the Land, Climate, and people of GVIANA;
with the proviſions for mans ſuſtenance, and commodities
therein growing for the trade of
Merchandiſe: and manner or the
Adventure.
            With an Anſwer to ſome objections touching feare
of the Enemie.
            
            Like as I have watched upon them, to plucke them up, and
to roote out, and to throw downe, and to deſtroy, and to
plague them; ſo will I watch over them, to build and to
plant them, ſaith the Lord: IER. 51. 28.
            
            He that obeyeth me ſhall dwell ſafely, and be quiet from feare
of evill: PRO. 1. 33.
            
            LONDON
Printed by William Iones for Thomas Paine, and are
to bee ſold in Trinitie Lane at the ſigne of
the Horſe-ſhooe. 1632.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            A
PVBLICATION
OF GVIANA'S
PLANTATION.
            To all faithfull, and well affected Chriſtians.
            
               FOR as much as diverſe of this
Nation are departed hence into
forraine Countries, as well for
the propagating of Gods truth
(moſt likely) as their owne private
benefite, whereby the word
of the Lord might bee fulfilled in thoſe Heathen
(through Gods infinite goodnes &amp; mercy) as in us
Chriſtians formerly ſaying,Rom. 9. 25. 26. 
               I will call them my people
which were not my people, and her beloved, which was
not beloved, and it ſhall be in the place where it was ſaid
unto them, yee are not my people, that there they ſhall be
called the children of the living God. Neither is it to be
doubted, but that there are divers yet remaining,
which retaine the like Chriſtian reſolution, but

want of true knowledge of a plantation (that may
proove profitable to the Church of God &amp; themthemſelves)
cauſeth ſuch to live heere like plants,
which many times prove leſſe fruitfull in their naturall
ſoile, then when they are removed to places
better liking them, for which cauſe I have thought
good at this preſent, to diſcover briefly (to all ſuch
as are wel affected) the knowledge of a moſt hopefull
plantation newly undertaken by the right
honorable the Earle of Barkeſhire (Knight of the
moſt noble order of the Garter) and company,
for that famous river of the Amazones in
America, as by that which followeth may appeare.
            But before I proceede further herein, I thinke it
not amiſſe to ſpeake ſomewhat of the lawfullneſſe
of plantations in forraine countries, whereby ſuch
as make doubt thereof, may be beetter ſatisfied
herewith.
            Now in plantations there are theſe two principalls
to be conſidered: firſt, whether it be lawfull
to remove from one place or countrey to another,
ſecondly, whether it be lawfull to poſſeſſe a countrey
already inhabited by others: touching the former
it hath theſe two ſeverall heads, namely, ordinary,
and extraordinary; extraordinary is that
when God ſhall pleaſe immediately to cauſe any
man to depart from one country to another, as hee
cauſed Abraham to depart from Haran to Canaan
and Iacob to returne from Padan Aram to the land
of his fathers,Gen. 12. 1, 4, 5, 31. 3. 18. but no man may now expect any

ſuch removall and calling as theſe formerly
had.
            The latter of theſe which I call ordinary, is that
when men ſhall be either moved themſelves, or by
others to leave their ancient habitation, and goe
and inhabite ſome other place: and this I take to be
warrantable from that place of the Kings, where the
children of the Prophets ſaid unto Eliſha,
               2 King. 6. 1, 2, 3, 4. ☞ Behold
now, the place where wee dwell with thee is too narrow
for us, Let us goe now to Iordan that wee may take thence
every man a beame, and make us a place to dwell in; and
hee anſwered goe, and one ſaid, vouchſafe I pray thee to
goe with thy ſervants, and hee ſaid I will, goe ſo he went
with them, and when they came to Iordan they cut downe
wood. Which worke of theirs (without queſtion)
was no other to them then a new plantation, for
they ſeing the inconvenience that was like to enſue
by ſtaying longer in their ancient habitation, did
thereupon remove to a place more ſpacious, and
commodious for them. ☞ In which progreſſe of
theirs, wee may learne not to conceale any thing to
our ſelves, which may as well prove profittable
to others, but diſcover the ſame for their good, as
doubtleſſe the Children of the Prophets heere
did.
            From hence then wee may gather, th
                  •
               
men may lawfully remoove with their familyes
from one place to another, and that for
divers cauſes; as here the Children of the
Prophets did, by reaſon of the ſtraitneſſe of the
land wherein they dwelt: and it is to be feared that

many alſo among us have as great cauſe to doe the
like, by reaſon of the daily increaſing of all ſorts of
people, whereby cittyes townes and countries, are
ſo thronged, that men can hardly live well one by
another, appeareth by the generall complaint of
many in theſe times.
            Neither hath the ſayd ſtraitneſſe alone,2 Kings 8. 1, 2. cauſed
a removall from one place or Country to another,Ruth. 4. 1. 2.
but alſo famine,
               1 Chro. 10. 7. 
               ſword, and other alterations, happenning
in the world:Ier. 14. 18. And to ſpeake truely, if that ſome
in all ages had not departed into other countries
with their families (as God was pleaſed to moove
them by his divine providence) the world aſſuredly
had not beene ſo much inhabited abroad as now
it is,Heb. 11. 37, 38. and men had beene more burthened at home,
then now they are: therefore ſuch men deſerve rather
to be commended, then condemned by any, ☞
&amp; that becauſe they do nothing herein, but what
God hath commanded, to be done, as appeareth
Gen.
               Gen. 9. 1. 1. 28. Bring forth fruit and multiply and fill the
earth: and this againe is ratified, to Noah and his
ſons, ſaying, bring forth fruite and multiply and repleniſh
the earth, which places, being no way contradicted
in all the ſcriptures (as I coulde ever perceive)
are ſufficient to proove the Lawfulneſſe of plantations
in all ages. And the rather, when Kings ſhal
bee likewiſe pleaſed to allow the ſame freedome
to their naturall ſubiects, and that not onely to the
poore, but alſo to the rich, who have the like priviledge
of removal, as appeareth by the places before
mentioned,Gen. 13. 2, 5, 6, 1
                     •
                  . and by that of Abraham and Lot, who
departed one from the other, becauſe the Land

wherein they dwelt were ſo ſtrait that it could not
beare them, by reaſon their ſubſtance was ſo great.
            So then wee ſee all men have a like liberty of
removing from one place to another, excepting
ſuch onely,Rom. 12. 7. which for the time being have any office,
or ſhall bee married,
               1 Cor. 7. 5. in which caſe men ought
not to depart from their wives without conſent,1 Pet. 3. 7.
nor children from their parents without their liking,Colo. 5. 20. 22.
nor ſervants from their Maſters without their
leave.
            It remayneth in the next place, that I ſhew the
lawfulneſſe of poſſeſſing a countrey already inhabited
by others, which is our ſecond queſtion:
            True it is, that all men through Adams fall were
deprived of the glory of God, and worlds good,
until by Chriſt the uſe of the creatures was againe
reſtored to all beleevers, therfore the right of that
which we poſſeſſe, commeth now to us by Chriſt,
for which cauſe, the heathen have no right to that
which they deeme theirs,Pſal. 115. 16. notwithſtanding, the
Lord hath beene pleaſed to ſuffer ſuch to live on
earth with his,Gen. 2. 32. and not to be rooted out from the
place of their habitations untill the day of harveſt,Iſay. 27. 13.
during which time the Land wherein ſuch have lived
hath beene called theirs:2 Chron. 32. 21 
               As the land of the Philistims,
the land of Egipt,
               Ier. 37. 7. 
               and of Aſhur, of whom it is
ſaid,Iſay 13. 14. that he returned with ſhame ☞ to his owne land,
and of the Egyptians it is ſaid,Iſay. 19. 17. 
               they ſhall returne
☞ into their owne lande:
               2 Kings 5. 2. 
                     •
                  
                In like manner, the lande
of Iudea and Iſrael,Pſal. 44. 1, 2, 3. being taken from the Heathen
(by Gods ſpeciall command and aſſiſtance) was
afterward called ☞ their owne Land:
               Ezech. 36. 17. for as the

Iſraelites land was not the heathens as ſaith the Prophet,Eſa. 14. 1.
               Lo I raiſe up the Caldeans to poſſeſſe the dwelling
places ☞ that are not theirs,
               Habak. 1. 6. 
               neither was the heathens
land the Iſraelites,
               Gen. 24. 37. as God telleth Abraham;
ſaying, know for a ſuretie that thy ſeed ſhall bee a ſtranger
in a land ☞ that is not theirs;
               Gen. 15. 13. from whence we
may gather, that God permitteth not his to diſpoſſeſſe
a people or nation of their ancient habitation
for the enlarging of their owne borders; nevertheleſſe,
if ſuch ſhall bee willing that Gods
people ſhall inhabit with them, as Abimelech was
willing that Abraham ſhould dwell with him in his land
where it pleaſed him,
               Gen. 20. 15. &amp; 47. 5. 6. and Pharaoh liked well that Iacob
and his ſonnes ſhould dwell with him in the beſt of
the land of Egypt. In ſuch a caſe men may doubtleſſe
poſſeſſe a country already inhabited by others:
            ☞ But the inhabitants of Guiana are willing that
our nation ſhould inhabit that goodly and ſpatious
country with them (as appeareth more fully in
Mr. Harcourts relation of Guiana dedicated to the
Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie, 1626) Therefore
without all queſtion, the plantations there made of
late by our nation are lawfull.
            Thus having briefly ſhewed the lawfullneſſe of
plantations in forraine Countries, for the better
ſatiſf
                  •
               ing of ſuch as make doubt thereof, I come in
the next place to ſpeake ſomewhat of the nature of
the river, qualitie of the land, climate, and people
of Guiana, with the proviſion for mans ſuſtenance,
and commodities therein growing, whereby ſuch
as are ignorant of the ſame, might bee encouraged
to adventure for the good of themſelves, and of

thoſe poore natives, which ſit ſtill in darkneſſe,
and in the ſhadow of death.
            As touching that great and famous River of the
Amazones in America,
               Harcort. it is called for the excellencie
thereof, (by Ioſepus A coſta) the Empreſſe
and Queene of all Flouds, and for the large extent
of the ſame, it is called by others the ſweet Sea,
ſuppoſed to bee the greateſt River (not onely of
all India, but alſo) of the whole world; it is ſaid
to ſlow from the Mountaines of Peru, and runneth
with many windings and turnings for the ſpace of
1500 leagues, containing at the mouth thereof
neare ſixtie leagues in breadth; in it are many Ilands,
divers of which are inhabited by the Indians;
it doth ebbe and flow neare three hundred
leagues, and hath in it greate ſtore of excellent fiſhes
for the uſe of man: of which more ſhall bee
ſaid hereafter, when wee ſhall come to ſpeake of
the proviſions of the country for mans ſuſtenance.
            The quality of the land is of divers kindes; as
low, middle, and mountainous, (as here with us)
it aboundeth in woods of divers ſorts, having
plaines in ſome parts thereof, with plentie of graſſe,
beſides pleaſant ſtreames of freſh waters, all which
are very needfull and fitting for a plantation.
            The earth in thoſe parts is of ſundry mixtures,
as blacke mould, clay, roſſey, and ſuch like, beſides
ſtone for building if occaſion ſerve.
            The ſeaſons there differ much from ours, for the
dry weather which wee call there ſummer, beginneth
about Auguſt, and the raines and windes,
which we account there winter, begin about Februarie;
               
which latter ſeaſon is termed by us their winter,
by reaſon of the raines then falling extraordinarie,
and not by reaſon of the coldneſſe of the
weather; for there are no froſtes or ſnowes, as
with us here, ☞ but a continuall ſpring and ſummer
ſeaſon: for no ſooner doe the leaves wither
and fall away, but preſently it beginnes to ſpring
againe, as here with us ſome yeares it ſeemeth the
like; for when our autumme proves ſomewhat
warme, then commonly appeareth a ſecond ſpring,
which yet never commeth to perfection, and that
by reaſon of the ſuns declining from our horizon,
and the cold winters preſent approaching, which
cauſeth alwayes our latter ſpring to keepe backe,
untill the time of our ſummer ſeaſon: ☞ which in
Guiana is not ſo, for there is little difference of
heat and cold throughout the yeare, but a moſt
pleaſant growing weather, which commonly cauſeth
thoſe parts to bee much more fruitfull then
many other parts of the world.
            ☞ The day and night are there alwaies equall, the
Sunne riſing at ſix of the clocke in the morning,
and ſetting at ſix in the evening or neare thereabout
the yeare throughout.
            The proviſions for diet are many, as firſt, the
roote called Caſſavie, of which the Guianians
make their bread; there is likewiſe a kinde of great
wheat called Maix, it yeeldeth great increaſe, and
maketh excellent meale, or flower for bread: of
the aforeſaid Caſſavie, and this wheat, is made a
ſort of drinke called Paranaw, much like the beſt
march beare here with us; other ſorts alſo they

have, which for brevity ſake I omit here to ſpeake
of.
            There are Deere of divers ſorts, wilde Swine,
Hares and Conies in great plenty, beſides which
there is a great beaſt called Maipnry which in taſte
is like beefe, and will take ſalt; there is alſo another
creature which uſually commeth into the freſh
waters, and feedeth upon the graſſe and weedes in
the marſhes, (and is called by us the ſea-Cow) being
in taſt like beefe, and will alſo take ſalt, as the
former; of theſe there are great ſtore in their ſeaſons,
they wil ſerve wel for the victualling of ſhips
homeward bound, as of late hath beene proved.
            Of fowles there be divers kindes, namely, wild-duckes,
wilde-geeſe, hennes, herons, cranes, ſtorkes,
pheaſants, partridges, pigeons, ſtockdoves, parrats
of ſundry ſorts, beſides ravenous fowles, and
hawkes, with divers other ſorts not knowne in
theſe parts.
            The variety of fiſh is great, as firſt, mullet, ſeabreame,
ſoale, ſcate, thornebacke, ſwordfiſh, ſeale,
a fiſh like a ſammon, but differing in coulour,
ſhrimpes, lobſters, and oyſters, other ſorts there
are, beſides freſhwater fiſh of many kindes, which
in theſe parts of Europe are not knowne to us.
            The fruites there growing are the Pina, Plantana,
Medler, Plumbes and Nuts of divers kindes, beſide
ſtore of Potatoes, as for the Pina, it exceedeth
all other fruites in thoſe parts, being in taſte much
like ripe ſtraberries with clarret wine and ſugar; the
Plantana taſteth like an old pippin, the medlers
exceede ours in greatneſſe, and the nuts in ſweetneſſe.
            
               
Having thus briefly touched the ſeverall ſorts of
proviſions neceſſary for mans ſuſtenance, it remaineth
I ſhew the varietie of commodities therein
growing for the trade of Merchandiſe, which in
ſhort-time (by Gods aſſiſting our endeavours) may
bee brought to returne great profit to the undertakers.
            The firſt commodity of eſtimation there growing
are ſugar-canes, whereof in ſome parts there
are ſtore, which by orderly planting and erecting
of convenient workes, for boyling and making of
ſugars, may (through Gods bleſſing) bee returned
yearely great profit to the adventurers, ☞ as the
plantation of ſugarcanes made hertofore in Barbary
by the Moores, and ſince that in Braſſeile by the Portugals
may witneſſe.
            There is alſo cotton wooll growing of the fineſt
ſort, it is a profitable commodity, for making of
ſuſtians, callicoes and candle-wicke.
            There is a naturall hempe, or flax, of great uſe,
it is much like raw ſilke, and is called of ſome ſilkegraſſe.
            There are likewiſe many commoditie
                  •
                for
diers, as namely a red berry called Anotto,
which dieth a perfect oringe-tawny in ſilke, and a
yallow in cloath, of which there may bee gotten
good ſtore every ſeaſon▪ for my ſelfe with ſome others
ſetting forth a ſhip formerly for thoſe parts,
(by way of trade) received upon returne, above
three thouſand waight of the ſaid Anotto, which
then bore a good price here, but much better in

the neatherlands, other dyes there are (beſides
hope of Cutcheneale) which at this preſent I purpoſe
briefly to paſſe over.
            There are likewiſe found of late, ſtore of Nutmegs
growing, with their Mace, ſome of which
I have recevied upon returne of my foreſaid adventure,
which noe man (I ſuppoſe) but my ſelfe can
ſhew the like, excepting ſome gentlemen, which
upon requeſt have received ſome of mee, which
no doubt may in ſhort time bee brought to a more
fuller perfection, by either cropping the old trees
and dreaning the waters from them, or by tranſplanting
the young trees, as by experience is commonly
ſeene, how that nature is much helped by
art and induſtry.
            There is likewiſe Gumma, Lemina, Barrata,
Ginnipepper, long Pepper, Caſcia fiſtula, Tobacco,
ſpleene ſtones, ſpeckled wood, Hony and wax▪
            
            As for mineralls, or mynes of mettals, it is very
likely, this Country affordeth many, not onely
of the baſeſt, but alſo of the richeſt, which hereafter
may come to bee diſcovered, if God ſhall be
pleaſed, which hee grant to his glory, and our
good, or that otherwiſe they may ever lie hid.
            Now as touching the nature of theſe people they
are generally held harmeleſſe, tractable, truſty,
and ſomewhat laborious; in which reſpect they
differ much from all other Americans, and which
is better to bee liked in them, there is good hope
conceived of their converſion to the Chriſtian
faith,Act. 16. 9. 10▪
                
               for as the man of Macedonia prayed St. Paul
in a viſion, to come into Macedonia and helpe them;
               
ſo have ſome of theſe poore ignorant ſoules deſired
Captaine Charles Leigh,
               Purchas. p. 1021. to ſend into England
for ſome men to teach them to pray; ſince which,
one being converted,Harcourt. p. 9. and became a Chriſtian, being
at the point of death, deſired ſome of our nation
then preſent, to ſing a Pſalme with him, which
being ended, hee told them hee could not live,
&amp; did withall acknowledg, that he had been a wicked
ſinner, but did hope that hee ſhould bee ſaved
by the precious blood of our Saviour Ieſus
Chriſt; and moreover, hee deſired all of them there
preſent, to beare witneſſe that hee died a Chriſtian;
☞ yea ſaid hee, a Chriſtian of England.
            A happy worke no doubt it were to recover
thoſe poore ſoules out of Sathans ſnare, who are
taken captive of him at his will;2 Tim. 2. 26 may wee not well
feare, that as hee murthers the body that denies
it nouriſhment when extremity requires it, ſo doth
hee no leſſe to the ſoule of whom nouriſhment is
implored,Alſted chron. in tit. deconuer. and yet hee denieth it; was not the Nubians
caſe moſt miſerable, (once a Chriſtian
people in Africa) when having not able Miniſters
of their owne, they ſent to the Abaſſines their
neighbours for teachers, and were denied; did
not ſuch deſerve worthily the calamity of a perpetuall
ignorance, who ſo uncompaſſionately ſlighted
the reaſonable requeſt of others?Heylin 
                     •
                  . 121. on the contrary
when ſome of the Eaſt Indians ſent their
Embaſſadours to Demetrus Patriarke of Alexandria
for teachers to inſtruct them in the faith of
Chriſt, hee willingly condeſcended thereunto,
and ſent not onely ſuch as preached true doctrine,

but alſo adorned the ſame by a holy converſation,
ſo that by their pious diligence, they wonne many
of them to the faith, which was the crowne of their
reioycing: and who knoweth, but that he that infuſed
ſuch deſires into an inhabitant of the Eaſt indies,
may worke as powerfully in them of the weſt,
and may likewiſe bleſſe theſe as he bleſſed them
with the 
                  •
               leſſed light of his moſt holy word, to
which let every faithfull Chriſtian ſay, Amen.
            Now ſeeing that the hope of worldly gaine cauſeth
moſt men to adventure in one kinde or other,
and that the gaine conceived of this plantation may
prove very profitable both to the Church of God
and all adventurers, it may therefore the better incourage
&amp; ſtirre up men of all ſorts, to become adventurers
herein, ☞ and chiefly ſuch as have received
of the Lord both grace, and ability, for the further
ſetting forth of his glory.
            And although it cannot bee denied but that our
nation of late yeares, hath beene very forward in
ſetling of divers plantations beyond the ſeas,
yet have they not all thereby ſo much glorified
God, as could be wiſhed, nor dealt ſo faithfully
with ſome adventurers, as was expected, which
thing no doubt being conſidered by many, hath
beene the onely cauſe of keeping them backe from
being adventurers; and no marvell, if when wee
conſider the perſons commonly ſent (I ſpeake not
of all, but of ſuch onely) whoſe lives being baſe
and idle here at home, can hardly bee expected to
be much better abroade in forraigne plantations,
which to ſpeake truely, have beene no other (for

the moſt part formerly) then common ſinkes,
wherein too many grieved fathers have caſt forth
their deſperate ofſpring, and the commonwealth
her moſt lawleſſe inhabitants, ſuch as by their converſations
cauſe the good name whereby they are
called,1 Pet. 2. 12. to be rather evil ſpoken of amongſt the Gentiles,
then otherwiſe: by meanes whereof it hath happened
that the heathen have deemed that God as evil
as their owne, whoſe ſervants were worſe then
themſelves, doth not God and nature teach, that
whatſoever a man ſoweth,
               Gal. 6. 7. 
               that ſhall hee alſo reape, not
grapes of thornes,
               Matth. 7. 16 
               nor figgs of thiſtles can men expect.
And now, though plantes of grace (like fruitfull
trees) are chiefeſt to be wiſhed for in al plantations,
yet no doubt may civill men be ſent in caſe of want,
as natures flowers for ornament: I wiſh therefore
that care were had, ☞ to ſend thoſe plants, and
leave the bad.
            As for the temper of the climate it exceedeth not
ſo in heate as ſome men have thought of it, for
though the ſcituation be in part under the equinoctial,
yet is it habitable, as appeareth by the experience
of our countrimen, which have lived in thoſe
parts, and found it both healthfull, and pleaſant; for
God in wiſdome hath ſo ordered the heavens in
their horizon, as that by meanes of a brieze (or
freſh gale of winde) blowing in the day time, it
quallifieth the heate, ☞ and maketh the climate
much more temperate, as with us is often felt the
like in heate of ſummer.
            Beſides the dewes there falling commonly in the
night, addeth much to the cooling of that climate,

and which is to bee noted, the continuall abſence
of the Sunne from the horizon, for the ſpace of
twelve houres every day, cannot but cauſe the
temper of that clymate to be moderate, there being
a perfect mixture of heat and cold, each qualifing
the other in the ſpace of twentie foure hours
by an equall diviſion of day and night, as before
hath beene ſhewed.
            Their houſes are built (moſt commonly) in
length, like our barnes here with us, ſome of which
are ſo large, as that they containe in them above an
hundred perſons, having therein hanging beds, (in
which they lie) called hamackoes, made of cotten
woll very artificially, their veſſels for uſe are
made ſome of clay, of which ſort ſome are ſo great
as that they will containe more then one hogſhead
of water.
            They will worke a month or more for an axe of
eighteene or twentie pence price; for which they
will fell your timber, cleare your ground, plant
your ſugar-canes, Anotto, and Cotten trees, and
build your houſe after their faſhion: ☞ which in
other plantations is not ſo, for in all other our
plantations, the adventurers are enforced to carry
men over to doe their worke for them, leaſt otherwiſe
they bee driven to worke themſelves, as
Virginia, St. Chriſtophers, and new England;
with others can witneſſe.
            Beſides which, in moſt former plantations except
new England, men have adventured onely upon
hope of one commoditie (as namely Tobacco) but
here are many more commodities then one, (as

hath beene ſhewed) ☞ therefore is this plantation
more hopefull then all others: the foundation
of which being already laid, may give men better
incouragment to become ioynt adventurers herein,
eſpecially being thereupon preſently intreſſed
in the ſhipping ſtocke, and profits of the ſaid plantation;
for the preſervation whereof, wee have
not onely ſent divers honeſt and able men (marren
and other) but alſo ſome peeces of great ordnance,
with amunition, and other materials very
uſefull towards building of a fort, for the better
ſecuring of our planters perſons from the danger
of an enemy; having moreover cauſed a pinnace
to bee ſent to abide with the Colony in the river,
for their better ſafetie and trade in the country;
☞ intending likewiſe this ſummer (if God ſhall
bee pleaſed) to ſett out a new ſupply of more men
(as artificers and others) beſides women, as alſo
more ordnance, amunition, and other materials,
fitting for the defence of the plantation, beſides
another ſhipp, greater then the former, to ſtay and
abide there together with the Colony in the river,
for their better defence and trade in the country aforeſaid:
in which ſupply I alſo purpoſe (God
willing) to goe with my wife and friends, to inhabit
ſome part of that ſpacious and goodly countrie.
            But here ſome may obiect feare of the enemy.Object.
               Anſw.
               Anſw. it is no other then what hath bin uſualy vented
at the firſt ſetting forth of al our plantations for
America, as Virginia and others can witneſſe; and
if there were ſo great cauſe to feare (as ſome have

ſuppoſed) men would not aſſuredly have adventured
ſo freely; but this plantation here mentioned
is farre from the Spaniards habitation, and
therefore leſſe cauſe to be feared.
            But yet it may bee further obiected,Object. that though
the Spanyard bee ſomewhat farre diſtant, yet the
Portugals in Braſill (being neare vnto it) may
prove as ill neighbours as the other.Anſw. Anſwer, if
wee conſider the ſpatiouſnes of the country (being
ſuppoſed to bee more then twenty times greater
then this kingdome of England) wee have no ſuch
great cauſe to feare them; for if wee like not their
neighbourhood, (there being roome enough,
and divers goodly rivers beſides in the country)
wee may (if we pleaſe) goe further out of their
reach, where no doubt (through Gods aſſiſting
of our indeavours) wee may come to returne as
great profit (by meanes of ſugar canes and ſuch
like commodities growing in thoſe partes) as in the
river aforeſaid: for to ſpeake truly, it were great
weakneſſe in any to preſume to ſit neare an enemy,
and have not ſufficient ſtrength to oppoſe him, or
having roome enough to go out of his reach, will
notwithſtanding abide neare him; yet I deny not,
but that a Colony may bee able to ſubſiſt neare an
enemy by meanes of fortification, and eſpecially
when they are ſuch as feare God, being provided
with amunition, victuall, and all other things needfull
for the defence of the ſame: for to raiſe a fort
for the reliefe of a Colony, and not to victuall it,
(as ſome haue careleſly neglected through indiſcretion)
were to make it (with ſuch) our peoples

grave, and not their preſervation: and if an hundred
of our nation, or thereabout (having neither
fort, nor artillery for defence,) were able (not
long ſince) by meanes of the natives, to cauſe about
eighteene hundred of the enemy to retrayte,
and abandon the river, with loſſe of many of their
lives; how much more then being fortified, and
fitted with all things needfull for the defence of the
ſame, may wee bee better able, (through the helpe
of the almighty) to repell and beat backe a more
potent power.
            Now as the raiſing of forts for the defence
of Colonies, and neglect of ſtoring them with
victuall, and other things needfull for preſervation
of the ſame, ſheweth the great indiſcretion of
ſome ſort of people: ☞ So in like manner, is
their folly as great, who looking after preſent
profit, neglect planting proviſions needfull for
the preſervation of their lives: which wee taking
into conſideration, have given expreſſe charge,
that firſt of all they take care to plant proviſions
needfull for ſuſtentation, whereby they may bee
able in ſhort time to ſubſiſt of themſelves, without
helpe of the natives, which uſually furniſh our
Engliſh plantations with ſtore of proviſions for
diet, at marvelous low rates; yet notwithſtanding
wee have ſent thither ſome few cattell for
breed, befids other creaturs, which in thoſe parts
have not yet beene heard of by us to have beene amongſt
them.
            And if any man ſhall deſire to bee further ſatisfied
concerning the proceed of the ſaid plantation,

or ſhall make doubt of any thing, they may pleaſe
to repaire to the place of meeting (hereafter mentioned)
and there receive further ſatisfaction.
            Now as touching the manner of the adventure,
it is as followeth.
            Every one that ſhall be admitted into the Colony,
or company of the Right Honourable the Earle
of Barkſheire for his plantation in Guiana, is to be
admitted one of theſe three wayes, that is to ſay;
either in perſon and purſe, or in purſe, or in perſon
onely. The firſt are called perſonall adventurers,
the ſecond, purſe adventurers, and the latter are
ſervants to the Collony.
            Concerning the former, they are ſuch as not
onely adventure their perſons, but alſo their
purſes; of which ſort none may bee admitted under
fifty pounds at leaſt, put into the ioynt ſtocke
(being a ſingle ſhare) in conſideration whereof, every
ſuch adventurer is to have for his perſonal ſervice
(over and above the profits of his ſtocke
of adventure) his tranſportation and diet free,
(both in the paſſage and country,) beſides a certaine
ſtipend or yearly allowance (as others) toward
the maintenance of his apparrell &amp; bedding,
and alſo aleventh part of a twelfth, of all the profits
that ſhall ariſe by the induſtry and labours of
the Collony beyond ſea; and laſtly, a proportion
of land over and beſides his ſtocke of adventure
of fifty poundes, or more as every one pleaſeth to
put in, ☞ whoſe reſpect in the Collony, is held
fitting to be meaſured according to the greatneſſe
of every mans adventure, worth and qualitie.
            
               
As for thoſe which are called purſe adventurers,
they are ſuch which adventure their monies but not
their perſons, ☞ whoſe names, and ſummes adventured,
are not onely regiſtred, but alſo acknowledged
by indenture under ſeale, by Authority from
the ſaid Earle, (for their better ſecurity, and more
aſſurance of faithfull dealing) to become ioynt adventurers
with the ſaid Earle and company, for his
plantation aforeſaid, and that at every returne, (during
the terme of five yeares) after the firſt returne
from the plantation, every adventurer, his heyres,
executours, adminiſtratours or aſſignes, ſhall receive
the profits of his ſtocke of adventure, and ſhal
the firſt returne from the plantation (after five
yeares ſhall be expired) receive out the iuſt reſidue
and remainder of his ſtocke of adventure, &amp; profits
therof, or may if he pleaſe, continue the ſame longer
in the ioynt ſtocke then the terme aforeſaid,
for his further benefit: and ſhall have moreover,
ſet forth for his uſe a proportion of lande correſpondent
to his ſaid ſtocke of adventure: and to
the ende that every adventurer, his heires, executors,
adminiſtrators and aſſignes may clearely ſee,
that they have the due proportion of the profits of
their adventure, it is covenanted in the ſaid indenture,
that the heires, executors, adminiſtrators &amp; aſſigns
of thē ſhal upon every ſetting forth &amp; return,
ſee the full ſumme of all the diſburſements, and receits
from time to time, paid and received, touching
the proceede of the ſaid ioynt ſtocke, and
plantation: which in like manner, every adventurer,
as well perſonall, ſervant, as other, hath the

like indenture for their better ſatisfaction, and more
aſſurance of faithfull dealing, as aforeſaid.
            Now concerning the latter, which are ſervants
to the collony, they are ſuch, which adventuring
onely their perſons, are bounde by indenture to
ſerve the ſaid Earle and company in the plantation
five yeares, in conſideration whereof, the ſaid ſervantes,
(as well wives, maides, as men) are to have
their tranſportation thither free, as alſo their diet,
lodging, apparrell, and all other materialls needfull,
provided for them, at the charge of the ioynt ſtock,
for the terme aforeſaid (apparrelling themſelves
here for the firſt yeare) and to receive moreover,
(for their beter incouragement) a twelfth part of
all the profits that ſhall ariſe by their labours and
induſtry, and the women a fifteenth (as of ſugars,
nutmeggs, mace, cotton wools, Anottoes, honey,
wax, tobacco, mineralls, and all other ſuch like
commodities, as ſhall be gotten in the plantation,
in manner aforeſaid) as alſo at the end and
terme of five yeares, every man ſervant to have livery,
and ſeaſon of thirty, and ſome forty acres of
land, and women twenty, which ſaid landes are to
be ſet forth for their uſe, by the governour, or governours,
and councell then being.
            And to the end that every one may know what
profits are due unto them by reaſon of their ſervice,
it ſhall be free for them to make choyſe of any two
or three amongſt themſelves, which ſhall once in
the yeare, or thereabout (upon reaſonable requeſt
made to the governour, or governours then being)
ſee the accompts, and what is due unto them upon

the foote of the ſame, ☞ for their better ſatiſfaction
and avoyding of ſuſpition.
            And furthermore all ſuch ſervants, as ſhall bee
artificers. As Suger-cane, and Vine planters: Sugar
bakers, Druggiſts, Dyers, Lapidaries, Minerallmen,
Refiners, Founders, Potaſhe makers, Barberſurgeons,
Ingeners, Gunners, Survayers, Ship-wrightes,
Mill-wrightes, Carpenters, Ioyners,
Coopers, Turners, Wheelers, Sawyers, Oare makers,
Blacke-ſmiths, Locke-ſmiths, Gunn-ſmiths,
Pike-makers, Armorers, Cutlers, Edge-toole-makers,
Ropers, Sayle-makers, Mariners, Net-makers,
Fiſhermen, Bakers, Butchers, Brewers, Diſtillers
of hot-waters, felt-makers, Spinſters, Weavers,
Taylers, Tanners, Curriers, Tawyers of
Furres, Fellmongers, Girdlers, Glovers, Shoomakers,
Potters, Maſons, Bricke-makers, Bricke-layers,
Basket-makers, Thatchers, and ſuch like;
are to receive a ninth part of a twelfth (more then
others, which are no artificers, of all the profits
that ſhall ariſe by their labours, and induſtry) as a
recompence of their ſeverall arts for their further
incouragement.
            And laſtly, it ſhall and may bee free for every
ſervent appertaining to the colony, to put into the
ioynt ſtocke ſuch ſummes of mony, as they ſhall
be able from under fifty pounds to five (as already
ſome have done) the receit of which ſummes being
acknowledged by indenture, ſhall be as ſufficient
a warrant for them to receive the iuſt profits of the
ſame, correſpondent to their ſeverall ſtockes of adventure,
as to any other before mentioned.
            
               
And now to conclude, ſeeing that workes of this
nature require ſome time for preparation of ſhipping,
and all other things needfull for tranſportation,
and that the ſummer ſeaſon is moſt convenient
for the performance of the ſame: it is therefore
thought fitting to give notice to all ſuch, as ſhal become
willing adventurours with the ſaid Earle and
company, to bring in their ſtockes of adventure,
(ſo ſoone as conveniently they may, and the ſooner
the better, for the reaſons aforeſaid) to the place
of meeting appointed to be kept (for the receiving
in of adventurers, and ſervants to the company) at
the houſe of Mr. Edwards the Kings Pikemaker in
Phillip lane neare Cripplegate: London: which
firſt meeting is appointed on thurſday the firſt of
March (at two of the clocke in the afternoone) and
ſo to continue every thurſday after, untill ſuch time
as the ioynt ſtocke, number of adventurers, and ſervants
ſhall be full.
            Thus having briefly ſhewed the hopefulneſſe of
this plantation, above others, whereby ſuch as
are faithfull (having ability) might become chiefly
adventurers herein, and that ſuch as are outwardly
poore (yet rich in faith) might likewiſe adventure
their prayers with them,Iam. 2. 5. for the proſperous ſucceſſe
of this new plantation, that it may bee as a
Vineyard which the right hand of the Lord hath
planted, and may growe up before him in the wilderneſſe
(being filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe,
which are by Ieſus Chriſt, unto the glory and
praiſe of God) amongſt the Heathen, who ſeeing
our pure converſation may bee wonne thereby to

the knowledge and love of God our Father, and
the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: which that they may ſo do,
grant O moſt gracious God, that as thou waſt pleaſed
to love us, when we were enemies as theſe, ſo
likewiſe bee pleaſed to love theſe with us, that we
and they may both agree to worſhip thee in ſincerity
of heart, and vnity of faith.
            Which worke of grace and power being thine,
            
               
                  O let thy worke and power appeare,
                        Pſal. 90. 18. 19.
                     
                  
                  and on thy ſervants light,
                  And ſhew unto thy children deare,
                  thy glory and thy might,
                  Lord let thy grace and glory ſtand,
                  on us thy ſervants thus,
                  Confirme the workes we take in hand,
                  Lord proſper them to us.
               
            
            Amen.
               I. D.
            
            
               
            
            
         
      
   

