
   
      
         
            A collection of some modern epistles of Monsieur de Balzac. Carefully translated out of French. Being the fourth and last volume
            Correspondence. English. Selections
            Balzac, Jean-Louis Guez, seigneur de, 1597-1654.
         
         
            
               1639
            
         
         Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 144 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02324
            STC 12455
            ESTC S103517
            99839269
            99839269
            3675
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02324)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3675)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 989:16)
         
         
            
               
                  A collection of some modern epistles of Monsieur de Balzac. Carefully translated out of French. Being the fourth and last volume
                  Correspondence. English. Selections
                  Balzac, Jean-Louis Guez, seigneur de, 1597-1654.
                  Marshall, William, fl. 1617-1650, engraver.
                  Bowman, Francis.
               
               [48], 249, [9] p.   
               
                  Printed by Leonard Lichfield for Francis Bowman,
                  Oxford :
                  MD.C.XXXIX. [1639]
               
               
                  Translated by Francis Bowman?.
                  With an additional title page, engraved, signed "W. Marshall sculps:": A new collection of epistles of Mons: de Balzac.
                  Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: pi¹ A-T.
                  With two final contents leaves followed by a blank leaf.
                  Running title reads: The letters of Monsieur de Balzac.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2006-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-11
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-02
            Celeste NgSampled and proofread
         
            2007-02
            Celeste NgText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  Balzacum hoc tandem dignemur honore.
                  Doctarum proemia frontium.
                  A NEW COLLECTION OF EPISTLES OF MONS: DE BALZAC.
                  BEING THE Fovrth and laſt Volume.
                  Newly Tranſlated.
                  
                     Non amet hanc Vitam, quiſquis me et.
                     Mar: lib: 1 Ep: 
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     —Magnus es Ardalio
                     Mart. lib: 2 Ep: 7.
                  
                  OXFORD Printed for Francis Bowman Stationer. 1639.
                  W. Marshall ſculps:
               
            
         
         
            
            
            
               A COLLECTION OF SOME MODERN EPISTLES OF MONSIEƲR DE BALZAC. CAREFVLLY TRANSLATED OUT OF FRENCH.
            
            
               Being the Fourth and laſt Volume.
            
            
               Mart. L. 10. Ep. 4.
               Non hîc Centauros, non Gorgonas, Harpyaſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Invenies: Hominem pagina noſtra ſapit.
            
            OXFORD, Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD for FRANCIS BOWMAN. MD.C.XXXIX.
         
         
            
            
            To the READER.
            
               THe name of Balzac is not confin'd within the Orbe of one Kingdome: his pen hath made him known unto all that pretend to Eloquence and politer Learning: And had his language been more generall, his worth had been more known. It is then a duty we owe to Virtue to unfold it, when it is contracted within too narrow limits, and to unlock the cabinet and make it communicable, when it is reſtrain'd from that freedome

which is part of its eſſence and nature. Wherefore ſome of our own, finding that our Authors language was too narrow for the merits of his works, have rendred ſome peeces of his in Engliſh. Nor did their travailes fall ſhort of their hopes, but ſucceſſe hath crown'd their endeavours. By the incouragement of their auſpicious flight abroad, I made Augury touching the fortunes of this freſh peece, which I now expoſe to the common light, without the countenance and patronage of any great Name, but guarded only with its own fate: It hath a Genius, and carries the name of Balzac in every page, that is enough.
            For know (Reader) that he is Maſter of the pen in France,Pierre Math. Hiſt. de Hen. 4. Liv. 3. L'Aigle de l'Eloquence Francoiſe, as one ſtiles the great Chancellour Du Vair, a

touring Eagle, whoſe ſtrength of wing bears him aloft above the tracts of common flights. I may ſay of him, with ſome variation, what Pliny ſaid of Cicero, that of later times, and for his own language,L. 7. nat. Hiſt. c. 30. 
               ſolus in toga triumphum meruit, linguae
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   lauream, and if the Muſes ſpake French, they would uſe no other Dialect, than that of Monſieur de Balzac.
            
            Jf thou doſt not finde the ſame thread runne through all his Letters, think it a peece of his Art, to vary the Idea, &amp; character of his ſpeech according to the quality of his ſubject. Wherefore we finde him ſometimes lofty and magnificent, and ſometimes grave and moderate: now he is calme and ſmooth, and anon he thunders and lightens: Here his words fall like haile, and there

—
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,Hom. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . like ſtill and gentle ſnow, or the ſilent feet of time. And though they be but 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , strictures, and excurſions of his pen, yet upon due examination, thou ſhalt finde they be decoctions of pureſt Rhetorick; and take away Monſieur, &amp; voſtre tres-humble, they be ſo many quaint Orations, and diſcourſes politick and morall.
            
            But never did any beauty gaine all ſuffrages, nor any wit a generall applauſe. Our Author in his Hermitage,
               Mart. l. 4. Epig. 32. like that Bee, intomb'd in amber, —Dum latuit, luxit: he ſhin'd through the vaile of obſcurity, wherein he involv'd himſelfe: but ſome owle-eyes could not brook the ſplendor of his light, though at ſuch a distance and declination; and he had more Enimies in this ſolitude to moleſt him, then the Goute
               
and Stone. It was ever the fate of eminent perſons to have Antagoniſts, and Envie, like the Athenian Oſtraciſme, ever perſecutes the beſt. A teſty Frier, under the name of Philarchus, comes out of his cloiſter, and raiſeth the Hue and Crye after him, as an errand Theefe, and avoucheth that our Mounſieur here, is but a Mountebanke, and a Plagiary, that ſtrutts in borrowed plumes, and makes a great ſhew with the frippery &amp; brokage of other Authors: — pudet haec opprobria, &amp;c. But Balzac found a learned Apologist, to refute theſe imputations; ſo that this ſingle encounter grew up into a faction, and the Pen-men came ſo faſt into the field, that the Philarkes, and Anti-philarkes divided all France.
            
            There hapned ſome diſguſts between him and Father Garaſſe a Jeſuit,
               
and a man of able parts: But the French King himſelfe did ſo farre tender the studious Repoſe of Monſ. de Balzac, (that by theſe altercations he might not be diſcouraged or diverted frō greater Deſignes) He interpos'd his Authority to make a Reconciliation, and becauſe it makes for the honour of the parties litigant, I have prefixed here the Kings Act, and their mutuall letters, as I find them at the beginning of Garaſſe his Somme Theologique.
            
            And now (Iudicious Reader) Balzac, ſtands at thy Tribunall, expecting thy doome: He hopes to finde more Candor, and better dealings in England, the Region of peace, as he calls it, In the 13. letter of this. than among his own: preſuming upon the goodneſſe of his cauſe, and thy Iuſtice, I have adventur'd ſomething upon thy cenſure.

If thou contracteſt thy brow, it is no ſingle fate, thou condemneſt at once a multitude of Dependents, and Admirers of his virtues, and among them, in an humble diſtance
            
               F. B.
            
         
         
            
            
            An advertiſement of Monſ. the KING.
            
            
               VNderſtanding of the bad intelligence, which by the unhappineſſe of the times hath grown between Monſieur de Balzac, and the Author of this book, we could not but partake of the diſcontents of ſundry honourable perſonages; and judging it very reaſonable, that men that continually doe good ſervices to the Commonwealth, and from whom it ſhould expect better yet hereafter, ſhould be divided in wills and affections. We have endeavoured to diſpell thoſe clouds by the evidence

of truth; the buſineſſe was not very difficult for Vs, being we were to deale on the one ſide, with a Religious man, who by the rule of his profeſsion, takes a glory in deſpoyling himſelfe of all intereſts, and to deſire the love of all the world; on the other ſide, with a man of a franke and noble Courage, whoſe diſcretion guided him to put a difference between the faults of men, and the unhappineſſe of the age.
            So that We thought fit, to tye again the knot of friendſhip, which (by accident) had been untied. It is commonly an eaſier taske to reconcile old friends, than to make new ones. Having then happily effected that buſineſſe, We thought that good men, who are ever well affected to the ſweetneſſe of peace, would gladly receive ſome authentick
               
teſtimonies of their good intelligence, and for this purpoſe, We have got interchangeable letters under their own hands, that confirme the ſincerity of their hearts, for to preſent them to the publike, which cannot be diſtaſtfull to any, but to thoſe that are pleaſed with nothing but diſorders and contentions.
            
         
         
            
            
            IOHANNI LUDOVICO BALZACO. V.C.S.P.
            
               
                  Q
                  Ʋòd ad te jam ſcribo, (V. C.) mirari desines, ſi me, ut Religioſum, &amp; tui amantem eſſe memineris: &amp; animam, puto, 
                     〈◊〉
                   manum hanc facile agnoveris, ſin minus, ſaltem ignoveris, quod utrin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   geſtum eſt. Nonnihil inter nos longi frigoris fuit, ſeculi potiùs vitio, quàm noſtro. Septennium est, fateor, ex quo mutua inter nos Epiſtolarum miſsio interrupta ceſſavit; ex hoc ſilentio torpor, ex torpore glacies exorta: vel patere ſuis, ut ad to verbis ſcribat ſapientiſsimus Hebraeorum Doctor dicat
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  :
               Eccleſ. 43. Chriſtallus gelavit ab

aqua: ſed nôſti quid rei eſt Chriſtallus, cui precium facit ipſa fragilitas? vel frangatur, vel indomita glacies benigno tepore ſolvatur: favent omnia, &amp; tempus, &amp; amicorum vota communium, &amp; imprimis deſiderium meum. Nolo retegere quod o dioſum eſt, rixarum inter nos argumenta &amp; fomites; fatalia iſta ſunt, &amp; diſſolvendis amicitiis nata▪ In litibus nullus (ut nôſti) finis eſt: dum
               ▪
            
            —Liticulas lis ſeminat unica plures. Verſiculos ad te extemperaneos &amp; rudes mitto, ſed ſcienti loquor &amp; occupationes meas, &amp; Epiſtolarem in verſu formam; nihil enim ab Heroico retinet preter pedes, quos habet formica etia cum homine communes, ſed quo plures eò pejores. Tibi uni propè datū est Heroicas graveſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   literas condere; ſoripſit Ovidius Heroidas, ſed Balzacus Heroicas. Pluribus abſtineo, ne quod
            
            
               〈1… pages missing〉
            
         
         
            
               〈1… pages missing〉
            
            
            and profeſſe; Among theſe ſevere ſpeculations, you ſhall ſee ſome flaſhes of wit break forth, which will ſerve to entertaine you with much delight; I ſpeak of the French Epiſtles, for as for his Latine, I reſerve them to the judgement of thoſe that doe better underſtand the beauty and delicacy of that language▪ I am content to believe that Cicero never entertaind his friends with better grace and contentment▪ nay, that the very cloſe and compacted ſtile, and the ſtrong and vigorous expreſsions which Brutus found wanting in the writings of that great Orator, are here to be found; But I feare I ſhould detaine you too long, from the pleaſure of theſe novell Lectures, if in commending rare Epiſtles, I ſhould arreſt you any longer, in reading this

poore one of mine. Indeed (my Lord) for to ſpeak nothing that were unworthy of you; it were requiſite, that Monſ. de Balzac would lend me ſome of the graces of his ſtile; or, as he will be raviſht with joy, that I have made choice of you to be the Patron of his writings, he would come himſelfe to make the Dedication; It ſufficeth me, if my deſigne and undertaking for to performe ſomething that might be acceptable to your Greatneſſe, doe not give you any diſtaſt, and that you believe, that I am ſincerely
            
               My Lord
               Your moſt humble and moſt obliged ſervant IOHN CAMUSAT.
               
            
         
         
            
            TO MY LORD the Chancellor.
            
               My Lord,
            
            I Have underſtood of your deniall, for the publiſhing of a Libell, lately fram'd againſt me. And though (perhaps) the harme that I ſhould have received thereby, would have been but ſmall, yet my obligation unto you, never ceaſeth to be great; and this argueth a ſpeciall care in you of my tranquillity, not to ſuffer that any, the leaſt noiſe ſhould diſquiet it. I know not (my Lord) if this be not to handle with too much niceneſſe and tendernes, a man that makes profeſſion of Philoſophy; it were enough

that publike Authority ſhould ſhelter me from the tempeſt, without exempting me from the wind and duſt, and that it would guard my Retrait from ſavage beaſts, without frighting away the flies alſo, and ſuch importunate Inſects. But (my Lord) the goodneſſe which you reſerve for me, extends farther then to ordinary juſtice. You take not only care for my repoſe amidſt the hurry and tumult of Europe, but you would have the world alſo ſhew a reſpect unto my retiredneſſe, and that being ſequeſtred from men. J ſhould be alſo placed beyond the levell and reach of Detraction. Yet this Fiend did purſue S. Hierome even unto the Grotts of Bethlehem, and to the foot of our Saviours cradle, there ſhe found him (as he relates himſelfe) although he had

thought to hide himſelfe. If this inſolent Thing had no regard of an admirable ſanctity, and a place guarded with Angels, me thinks a vulgar innocence, retired within an ill fortified village, muſt not expect any favourable treaty. But to paſſe from common conditions to the learned Tribe; If in all ages, there aroſe ſeditious ſpirits, that rebelled againſt the Chieftaines of Arts and diſcipline, and if in the memory of our fathers, it was ſpoken openly at Paris, that Ariſtotle was a ſimple Sophiſter, J think they deale courteouſly with me in this Country, if they be contented to call me a ſimple writer. That great blaſphemer of the name of Aristotle (my Lord) was D. Ramus, who afterward, though he was a Catholique, was taken for a Huguenot, at the maſſacre;

And indeed, ſome did believe that God permitted this to come to paſſe by a juſt judgement; and that the Tutelar Angell of good Letters, took the pretext of Religion, for to revenge the injuries that were done to Reaſon. There is one this day alive in Germany, a petty Tyrant in Grammer, an enimy of common and generall verities, and an accuſer of Cicero; who (not long ſince) hath put forth ſome obſervations, where he preferres a bill againſt his own Judge, and queſtions the precedency ever allowed unto that Prince of Latine Antiquity. So that (my Lord) the univerſall conſent of all the world, ſtrengthned by a preſcription of 18. centuries of years, is not a ſufficient title for to warrant the reputation of that Roman, againſt

the prevaricating quirkes of this Barbarian. Indeed, this is a buſineſſe of no good example, but yet ſince it is ſo, and that it doth litle availe Virtue, to be conſecrated by time, and to be crowned by the people, for to make it inviolable againſt the practiſes of ſome private Humors. There is no reaſon that I ſhould complaine before ſo many Worthies, that have bin ſo ill intreated themſelves, and that I ſhould be had in any conſideration, where Ariſtotle and Cicero are not in ſafety; an ordinary man ſhould not make moan, for ſuffering the ſame deſtiny, which extraordinary Perſonages have undergone; and I cannot with modeſty, deſire or expect from you, that you ſhould reforme the world for the love of me; nay, J know (my Lord) that this litle

diſorder, is of ſome good uſe in a common-wealth; and it were to be wiſhed, that malice would buſy it ſelfe thus, about things of ſmall importance, that it might not think of buſineſſes of higher conſequence. Thoſe that have hitherto beſtowed their pains, in depraving the ſence of my words, and in falſifying my works, had (perhaps) ere this time, forged mens Teſtaments, and minted falſe coines; And he that now deſires from you a priviledge, would have ſtood in need of a Pardon, it may be, if it had not been for me. It is better by farre, that injuſtice ſhould exerciſe it ſelfe upon my books, than that it ſhould vexe and implead againſt all that is good and ſacred in a civill ſociety; that unjuſt men ſhould rather toſſe and tranſpoſe words, invert and

pervert periods of ſpeeches, than remove the bounds of lands, or demoliſh their Neighbours houſes; To ſay the truth, this is the moſt innocent way that vice can imploy it ſelfe in, and I believe I have not a litle deſerv'd from the common-wealth, for keeping at worke theſe ten years, ſuch an infinite number of idle companions, who (certainly) would have been dangerous Commonwealths-men, if they had not choſen rather to have been ridiculous Cenſors. It is well, that the heat of their braines, is exhaled out this way, and that their intemperance takes this courſe; and that to prevent their fury, men give ſome ſcope and liberty to their folly. Permit them therefore this exerciſe (my Lord) they cannot chooſe but make uſe of their time, which they will

imploy farre worſe, if you doe not permit them to imploy it thus. Permit giddy Youth to ſpend their heat and fury upon a ſenſeleſſe ſubject, and a dead letter, which is not capeable either of joy or ſorrow. As long as theſe Pen-fencers only beg the Seale of your Authority, be no niggard of the Prince his grace and favour, and abate ſomething of your wonted ſeverity and rigour. If it were anew &amp; unuſuall thing, it may be, I ſhould be contented to have the firſt Libell, which branded me with injuries be ſuppreſſed, but ſince there is now a pretty Library of them, I am in a manner well pleaſed it ſhould ſwell and increaſe, and I take a delight to build me a moniment with thoſe ſtones, which Envy hath hurl'd at me, without doing me harme. I account

it no diſgrace to be cenſur'd by ſome men, becauſe I account it no credit to be favour'd by them: I intend not to canvaſſe for voices, nor labour a myſterious ſecret, whereby I may gaine the generall applauſe of the world. I have obtained what I deſired, (my Lord) if I have obtained your approbation, as being derived from an un-erring principle, and from an Jntelligence moſt perfectly illuminated. God hath beſtowed on you, a ſoveraigne judgement, before the King had committed to your hands, his ſoveraigne Juſtice. And you were moſt powerfull in Reaſon, before you were ſo in Authority. J need not have recourſe to this, knowing that the other is no way againſt me, and I eſtime it more glory to me, to have pleaſed you, than I would

think it ſatisfaction to have my enimies proſcribed by you. Your ſpeeches of me upon every occaſion ſo full of reſpect, your own pourtraiture that you beſtowed upon me a yeare agoe, for a pledge of your Affection, your imparting to me the riches of your writings, I mean thoſe writings, that were animated with the ſpirit of the State, and were full of the greatneſſe of your Maſter, which ſeemed to me ſo farre to tranſcend the ſtrength and vigor of this age, and ſo nearly reſembling the Roman Majeſty. In a word (my Lord) each moment of that happy afternoone, which I had the honour to paſſe away within your cloſet, are priviledges, which I doe value above that which you denied a Fantaſme, or the Succeſſor of Philarchus. I dare not rehearſe

my other obligations, by which I ſtand bound unto you. You have herein injoyned me ſilence, and believe, that your favours would looſe ſomething of their purity, if my thanks ſhould ſtill attend them. Nevertheleſſe you muſt not ſtifle in me the intentions of an honeſt man, or ſmother the conceptions of gratefull thoughts; you have debarred me from divulging my acknowledgements, but you ſhall not debarre me from acquitting that ſecret part of duty, and from being, (at leaſt in my ſoule) and that while I live
            
               My Lord
               Your moſt humble, moſt obliged and most thankfull ſervant BALZAC.
               
               From Balzac the
1 of Iuly 1637.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               A COLLECTION OF SOME MODERN EPISTLES OF MONSIEUR DE BALZAC.
            
            
               LETTER. I. To Monſieur CONRART.
               
               
                  SIR,
               
               
                  BEing arriv'd home but this morning, I could not before the evening frame an anſwere to your Letter which you honour'd me with, and was delivered me at

my arrivall; it is ſo full of baits to feed both the eyes and the underſtanding, that it were impoſsible I could refraine from reading it more than once. It is ſo judicious, and withall ſo paſsionate, that J cannot think of it without congratulating with my Country that we have ſeen Philoſophers even in our own language, and thoſe Philoſophers ſuch as profeſſe goodneſſe as well as wiſdome; the time, you ſee is now paſt for to ſatisfie your deſire; but though the King by the activity of his courage could not render thoſe remedies unuſefull, which you expect from my idle meditations; yet J meane not to act the bold Empyrick of Mountebanke in your preſence. It would argue too much impudence to ſend any drugs and receipts from a

country village to Paris, and to undertake the cure of afflicted minds in a countrey of good books and great Doctors. Nay I have ſeen Sir in your own houſe▪ a Magazin of rare inſtructions &amp; examples, both printed, and in hand-writing. And Justus Lipſius (had hee been your Neighbour) might have made a purchaſe of a Conſtantia of a ſtronger and better temper, then her that he hath beſtowed among us. Since then the whole maſſe and mine is in your own power, J cannot perſwade my ſelf that you could have deſir'd thoſe few Graines that J could furniſh you with, and that being ſo rich your ſelfe, you were reſolv'd to exhauſt my poore ſtock too. Taking view from hence at ſo farre diſtance of the eſtate and affaires of our Frontiers, J cannot diſtinctly

and cleerely beſtowe my judgement on them. J am content to carry about me the thoughts of an honeſt man, &amp; to remove from my mind the diſguſts of ill ſucceſſe with good hopes. J know Sir, that the faireſt kingdomes have ſuffered the viciſsitudes of good and evill; and that the brighteſt fortune hath ſome ſpots &amp; ſhadowes; and knowing this, J cannot think ſtrange of any diſaſters that may happen, or be ſurprized with the newes of a revolt, or be any thing amazed with loſſes more than with gaines. Flanders J confeſſe is advanced pretty farre into Piccardy, and would have given the like alarme to France as France had given it the yeere before. But it may be, they that plunder it freely to day in the field will be to morrow

blockt up in a ſiege▪ your good Brothers J know will revenge the quarrell, and they that Pillage the Citties of others, will be glad to get them home to ſave their own habitations againſt their Ancient ſubjects. We muſt then confeſſe that Antiquity hath wiſely term'd the God of warre Communem Martem, that Homer never gave it a fitter Epithet then that. It is certaine that it never favours the ſame cauſe long. This is a Fugitive in all Armies, and a starter from all parties, ſometimes a Guelphe, and ſometimes a Gibellin, ſometimes wearing the white ſcarfe, and ſometimes the red. This is too much Sir concerning Publique Affaires. Doe me the favour as to ſend to M: du Moulin the anſwere that J have made him, the later words thereof

will call to your mind thoſe three verſes of our Hieruſalem.
               
               
                  Torq. Taſſo la Gieruſal. Liberata.
                  Amando in te ciò, &amp;c.
                  
                     By loving that in thee, which others feare doth move
                     And envious hate, he ſeemes thy virtues to approve:
                     And willingly with thee could make a league of love.
                  
J beg of you the good favours of that grand Adverſary of the Romaniſts, but yours above all, ſince J am with all my ſoule
               
                  Balzac.
30. Octob. 1636.
                  
                  Sir
                  Your, &amp;c.
               
            
            
               
               LET. II To Monſieur du MOULIN.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               
                  COurteſie never denies reſpect to any man, and thinkes no mans Preſents meane but her owne. This was it (no doubt) that made You ſpeake of mee in ſuch a high ſtraine and ſet ſo great a price upon my booke, which (indeed) is but the worſt part of your Library. J ſee you will not alter your courſe, or forget your ancient civility, for the which J am infinitely obliged unto you. And if ſome men would needs perſwade me that at other times you handle me ſomething rudely, yet I cannot believe you doe it with a hoſtile hand; on the contrary, J ſuppoſe

that in your familiar letters you give a true coppie and character of your ſelfe, but in actions of Ceremony, men require another countenance &amp; more ſtudied gravity; otherwiſe Sir, my nature can beare with my friends, and J am not of ſo delicate a ſenſe as to complaine of pettie wrongs which J ſuffer. Beſides, that J doe not at all medle with that ſcience of diviſion which teaches to rente our Saviours Coat into 1000 peices, &amp; to implead and cavill againſt every word of his Teſtament. This commonly doth rather exaſperat mens ſpirits, than compoſe affaires, and multiply doubts, inſteed of encreaſing charity. If J were put to my choyce, J would take a litle leſſe of that which puffeth up, and a litle more of that which edifieth. Truth
                  
is not the purchaſe of hot blood, or of incenſed choller, or a diſturbed imagination. The Labyrinthes of Logick are not the eaſieſt way to heaven, and oft-times God hides him-ſelfe from them that ſearch him with over-much curioſity. You will avouch (J am ſure) all that J ſay, and this too Sir, that the beſt quarrels prove nought, and of bad conſequence, and that the contentions of Doctors prove the murthers of their Brethrens ſoules, if they tend not to the peace of the Church; for my part, J can with other vulgar Chriſtians, but wiſh for it; but you can with the Worthies of Chriſtian Religion, contribute much towards it, &amp; whenſoever you ſhall preach and teach this, J ſhall aſcribe unto you one of the principall parts of that holy

work: But while we expect that this peace be advanced through the grace of God, &amp; that we draw neerer every day one to another, nothing hinders, but that we may maintaine innocent commerce, &amp; traffick in things lawfull. There is no law rightly interpreted that is repugnant to that of Humanity, &amp; doth not accord with the law of Nations. If our opinions differ, it is not neceſſary that our affections ſhould diſagree; the head and the heart have their ſeverall motions, and actions diſtinct; and morall vertue can reconcile &amp; unite what the intellectuall might ſeparate. Love mee therefore ſtill if you pleaſe, ſince you may doe it lawfully, and J believe alſo, that J may be without ſcruple, while J live
               
                  Sir
                  Your; &amp;c.
                  Balzac. March 30. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. III. To Monſieur L' HUILLIER Counſellour to the King, and Ordinary Mr of his Accounts.
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOU can make men happy, and procure them Sun-ſhine daies, where, &amp; when you pleaſe. Let us ſpeake no more of misfortunes: there is nothing here within but proſperity, ſince the Ordinary hath arriv'd: and J muſt recall a language which J have forgotten, ſince you doe reſtore a paſsion to me which J had loſt. J thought there was no diſpoſition to any joy left in me, yet notwithſtanding from a litle ſparke rak'd up in my boſome, you have kindled ſuch an exceſſe, that J never felt the like;

ſuch inebriations of the ſpirit, and ſober tranſportments Philoſophy hath obſerv'd in extraordinary ſucceſſes. There is no way Sir to ſuppreſſe or keep this joy conceal'd, &amp; if it be lawfull for me to ſpeake it, my heart is ſo full and▪ high that it mounts up to my face. J am like to looſe by it all the gravity and demurenes, which J have theſe many yeares contracted by my melancholy life. And ſince there is no apparēt cauſe that might ſtirre ſuch a paſsion in ſuch a languiſhing ſpirit as mine, men may imagine that I paid ſome Arreres, and that I have received an acquittance patent, but that I call it your letter. They ſtill deceive themſelves and take me for another mā than I am: for my Intereſts touch me not ſo ſenſibly as my paſsions doe, and

                  Fortune is not ſo rich as to preſent me with any thing that might countervaile the leaſt pledges of your Amity. The world and I, doe not agree in the rate of things that are beſtowed &amp; received. That doth eſtimate them by an Arithmeticall, and I by a Morall proportion, according to which, Sir, all your words to me are weighty and pretious, becauſe all true; and becauſe Truth cannot be ſufficiently eſtimated in a time when Oracles doe faine, whē we have reaſon to miſtruſt even Faith it ſelfe, and when the great Cato ſhould not be taken without caution and ſecurity. I doe infinitely cheriſh thoſe ſpeeches of yours, ſo full of verity, and preſerve them as the titles of a poſſeſsion, which I paſsionatly deſired before J went to Paris, and which I account

for the greateſt buſineſſe that I did dureing my abode there. Jn lieu of theſe, I will forgive Paris for all the unquiet nights, and other miſchiefes I ſuffered there. I complaine no more of its impure aire, or the jangling of bells, or of the juſtling and dirt of the ſtreets. And though I could not carry away thence but the bare Idea of your entertainment, yet beſides that you defrayed the charges of my journey in it, J can live here (yet awhile) upon your charges, &amp; feed my thoughts a long time with what I have received from your mouth. Yet J know not whether a provident managing of remnants, may make them laſt alwaies, or whether old Ideas, doe not at the laſt fade and vaniſh out of the memory, or whether

an expired felicity may denominate a man ſtill happy. What ever joy your letter ſprang in me, yet (being a marke of your abſence) it doth but advertiſe me, that I am ſix-ſcore leagues diſtant from the Author of my wellfare, and that therefore I can receive but imaginary painted ſatisfaction, and enjoy but forraine pleaſures. You cannot repreſente unto me the happy houers that I have ſpent in the cloſet of Meſsieurs de Puy, and the fine things that I have heard there, without tacitely upbraiding me with the penſive howers of my ſolitude, and the gibbriſh of my Neighbourhood. In truth Sir, if you know it not, J muſt tell you, that Balzac is the frontier of Barbary. But one daies journey from hence, (Monſieur des Cordes can tell you) the honeſt

                  Swaines doe not eat bread, or ſpeak French but upon ſundaies; The moſt underſtanding men there, believe that Preſter-Iohn ſaith Maſſe; and that the ſnow in the country of the Moores is black, the moſt gentle and affable find in an innocent word, the tenth part of a lye; and are offended with the very aſpect and ſilence of a man that paſſeth by. Are not theſe the right Antipodes to the lodgings of Monſieur de Thou, and eſpecially of the Gallery, which is not only full of the nobleſt ſpoiles of Antiquity, and and of Greek and Romane Treaſures, but which is (otherwiſe) inhabited by all the Graces of the preſent Age, and all the ſociable and civill Virtues. Yet notwithſtanding theſe, it might deſerve the curioſity of the remoteſt Nations of the

Earth, and invite the inhabitants of Cadiz, and thoſe beyond them, for to ſee there the great Preſident of Counſels and humane actions, and the grand Doctor of Kings and Common-wealths. But although this famous and learned Head appears not there but by the benefit of paint, yet his memory ſtill keeps its place, and preſides in all the Aſſemblies that happen there. Me thinks, that of Maſter of the houſe, He is become the Genius of the place, and inſpires all thoſe that ſpeak there, that ſo they might not ſpeak any thing unworthy of his preſence. Indeed this is the cauſe of my happineſſe here, that my poore conceptions give you ſome content, as you would make me believe; and that my adventures in print, have the allowance and approbation

of thoſe excellent Brothers, my deare and loving Friends. Now Sir, that I begin to grow ſober againe, and to recover my ſelfe from that extaſie, which you have caſt me into; take good heed, that you make no doubt of the ſeriouſneſſe of my ſpeeches: aſſure them therefore, if you pleaſe, that the favours that I have receiv'd from them, are not let fall, into a barren and ungratefull ſoule, and that it is impoſsible to honour Them more perfectly then I doe. You ſhall doe me the favour alſo; as to believe, that you never lov'd a man that could ſet a higher rate upon your amity, or would be more then I am
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
Nov. 23. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. IV. To Monſieur the Abbat of BOIS-ROBERT.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               SInce my departure from Paris, I have received two Letters of yours, that is to ſay, two ſingular Emblemes, or tokens of your goodneſſe: for it is certain, if you be not expos'd to the danger of warre, you are (at leaſt wiſe) obnoxious to the cumbrances &amp; moleſtations of it: and in this plight to have found the leaſure to remember me, and to ſend from the fartheſt skirts of Piccardy, but a thought as farre as Guyen, is a thing that could not be expected, but from a friend that is extremely ſollicitous of thoſe things that he

loves. According to your order, I communicated the newes unto my Father, who doth profeſſe himſelfe much obliged unto you for it. We doe daily groane for that of peace, and if you ſend us intelligence of this before Eaſter, I will anſwer you with a publike thanksgiving, and with the benedictions of all our Arrierban. That Virgin which your Authors call Astrea, was at other times, courted and ador'd by them (only) of the long gowne: now even Gladiators and Pirats think her handſome and comely. J doe not ſee any man of the ſword, but doth at ſome time of the day miſlike and beſhrew his own trade. I doe not know whether this be either the Cowardice of the age, or the Impatience of the Nation, or the feare of poverty

and famine preſented to their imagination; or (to ſpeak more favourably of the preſent occaſions) a chriſtian tenderneſſe and common ſenſe of humanity; ſo vehemently doth all the world deſire peace, that I think Heaven cannot ſend a better Preſent to the Earth. I think that — ſhould be imployed upon ſuch a pious occaſion, and choſen one of the Agents for Coloigue. If he would bring us that excellent Donative of Heaven, he deſerved to enter the Academy in triumph, and that Monſieur the Preſident ſhould make the ſpeech himſelfe: For my part, J ſhould receive him after ſuch a Negotiation with more reſpect, then if he came from commanding an Army; And to tell you the truth, the pacifique Angels doe pleaſe me farre better than the deſtroying

                  Angels. Think it not ſtrange Sir, that the deſire of glory is not the paſsion of Villagers; and that dreaming (ſometimes) of the Crabbats, I pitch upon the ſame thought with the Poet:

                     Impius haec tam culta novalia Miles habebit?
                     —Barbarus has ſegetes?
                  
Theſe are thoughts which are bred in my rurall walke, and which ſpring from lowneſſe of ſpirit; into which I am apt to fall, as ſoone as I have loſt the ſight of you. Therefore be pleaſed to take the paines to fortify me from time to time, and to ſend me ſome preſervatives againſt the bad newes which fly about. Theſe would help to entertaine good thoughts, while we expect the concluſion of the Treaty, and make my Neighbours know,

that a man cannot be ill inform'd that maintaines intelligence with you, and make them beleeve, that J am in deed what I profeſſe my ſelfe to be, which is
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac. 17 Oct. 1616.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. V. To my Lord, the Earle of EXCESTER.
               
               
                  My Lord,
               
               HAving not enjoyed my health, or at leaſt having had no leaſure at all, ſince the time that your Letter was delivered me; I could not any ſooner render you

thanks for the teſtimonies of your eſteeme and affection, which you vouchſafed me therein. I will not any way ſeeme to ſuſpect or doubt of a newes that makes for me; and I doe readily believe, that my works that were ſent you from the Queene your Miſtreſſe, have been your welcome-home among your friends. But herein, I doe acknowledge their good fortune, farre beyond my deſerts, and the Influences that deſcend from the Court, beyond all the favours they can receive from a coūtry-village. Thoſe hands ſo great and powerfull, that gave you this ſmall Preſent, doe ennoble whatſoever they touch and are able to effect rarer tranſmutations, than thoſe which Alchymy boaſts of; with their marke, a triviall Fable may paſſe for▪ Authentick

Hiſtory, and the Nether-Britton ſhould ſurpaſſe the native Frenchman. I have therefore my Lord, no thought of deſerving that Elogy, which I owe to ſo illuſtrious a circūſtance nor doe I mean to glory in the travels, which my book (as you informe me) hath made beyond the Rhine. Your name (being one of its principall ornaments) is that to which J muſt owe my fame in thoſe climats, and it was upon your recommendation and credit, that all the Courts in the North, and ſome of their Schooles too, have entertain'd my books. I doe here ſolemnely promiſe you never to abuſe this favour, at leaſt wiſe, never to write any thing of your Iland, that might give any diſtaſt in the reading, and that will not teſtify

particularly of you, that I am moſt intirely
               
                  My Lord,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac. Sept. 20. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. VI. To my Lord the Duke de la VALLETTE, Governour &amp; Lieutenant Generall for the King in GUYEN.
               
               
                  My Lord,
               
               I Doe not mean to tempt your valour, it were precipitate raſhneſſe to dare it; yet I ſhall make bold to tell you, that you have no leſſe Art and dexterity in conquering, than in winning men; and that

in you, that which intreats &amp; perſwades, hath no leſſe efficacy than that which commands and enforceth. Jt doth nothing availe me to ſhun the world, the better to enjoy my ſelfe in the deſart. Three words from your mouth, make me looſe all the freedome I enjoy there; and J ſee my ſelfe ſurpriz'd in that Sanctuary, in which J thought to ſave my ſelfe. J muſt confeſſe my Lord, that there is no ſuch abſolute independence, over which you cannot claime ſome power; that there is none ſo diſcontented and averſe that you cannot allure, or ſo wild and diſorderly that you cannot tame. Since you have done me the honour as to write, that you have ſent me your heart, J ſhould betray very litle skill or judgement in rare and excellent

things, if J were not raviſht with ſuch a preſent, and if J did not eſteeme it above all that ambition can deſire, or fortune beſtow. It may be, the hearts of Giants were more vaſt, and leſſe limited by reaſon, but the hearts of the Heroes were not more noble, or of any other elevation than yours is of; and he that ſpeaks of this, ſpeaks of a place hallowed, and purged from all the vices of this age, and where all the ancient Virtues have taken Sanctuary
                  ▪ Loe here, my Lord
                  ▪ what gift you have ſent; after which, I have nothing to wiſh for in this world, which J have abandoned, ſince this is the moſt pure and refin'd part of it; in which, goodneſſe cohabits with power, and greatneſſe combines with love▪ To which J muſt of neceſsity, ſtoope

and yeeld; and my heart were more vile, than yours is generous, if I were not
               
                  My Lord
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
Ian. 10 1637.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. VII. To Monſieur Drouet, Doctor of Phyſick.
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOur ſorrow is too accurate, and ſtudied, to be true; and an afflicted perſon that writes ſuch brave things, hath no great need of any thing of mine to ſolace him. J will therefore forbeare a taske▪ which I conceive to be ſo

nedleſſe; and will be contented to tell you, that J know how to diſcover counterfeit ſorrows. No man could act a Deſperato better than you. Panigarola made not ſuch exclamations when hee preacht, that there will be ſignes in the Sunne and in the Moone. And it is a pleaſure to ſee you write of the end of the world, of the falling of the ſtarres, and the finall ruine of Nature, &amp; all this, upon occaſion of my Niece, labouring of a feaver. This is to give Virgil the lye, that calls your profeſsion a dumb Science. For indeed, to finde ſo many ornaments &amp; Tropes upō ſuch a vulgar Theme, could not be without having a treaſurie of words, and without teaching this Mute, Rhetorick. Yet me thinkes, you ſhould husband and manage this treaſure more thriftily, and

have more care, than you had, of the modeſty of a poore Maid. Are you not afraid to make her fall into vaine-glorie, and marre all the paines of that good Father that guides her conſcience? If J did not furniſh her with counter-poiſon, you would infect her minde, &amp; caſt her into a worſe maladie than that you cur'd her of. But J haue taught her, that there are a ſort of Enchanters that bewitch by commending, and that the wanton Court-ſhip of Sirens hath allur'd many to their ruines, and filld the Seas with frequent ſhipwracks. She believes her Glaſſe, &amp; me too, who are more true to her thē you, and who (without much difficulty) can rectifie her opinion of herſelfe, which you would have ſtrained too high. For my own particular,

J ceaſe not to be your debt or for the quaint extravagances &amp; hyperboles, wherein you expreſſe your Affection towards me; and for her part, ſeparating your commendations from her name, and conſidering them aſunder, by thē
                  ſelves, ſhe eſteemes them as the wealth of a Jewellers ſhop, which indeed may delight her eies, but ſhe findes nothing there that belongs to her. Receive this complement as from her, if you pleaſe, J am meerely but her Secretary in this point, and J ſhall remaine
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
12. Octob. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. VIII. To Monſieur DE-BONAIR.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               THE Honourable mention that you were pleas'd to make of me in your booke, is a moſt ſingular favour, and I cannot behold my ſelfe in ſo faire a ſeat without ſome temptation of vaine glory. J know not as yet, whether my teſtimonie be to be admitted or rejected; and whether J be an Apocryphall or Canonicall Author; but ſince you have cited me, it is not lawfull for me to doubt any more of the good ſucceſſe of my writings; and after this, J dare claime a place in the nobleſt Libraries. It is true, I dare not owne that Title you beſtow on me, of the Genius of Eloquence.
                  
Beſides, that this would be a wrong to Mercury &amp; Pytho, who have for many ages poſſeſt the Chaire, and ſweyed the Art of Elocution; it were neceſſary alſo that J had the ſuffrages of all the Preachers and Advocats of the Realme; and you know Sir, that there is none of them ſo meane, that doth not perſwade himſelfe that he is the God of Perſwaſion, and would very hardly confeſſe a ſuperiour. J muſt not therefore entertaine an Elogie which would bee challenged from me by two ſo great Nations, equally terrible and potent, and J am content to be leſſe Prized by you, ſince J am ſure of the ſame affection; you ſhall preſerve that for me, if you pleaſe, ſince J am willing to give it its true eſtimation,

and to be really
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac:
20 Dec. 1635.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. IX. To Monſieur HUGGENS Counſellour and Secretary of the Commands of my Lord the Prince of Orenge.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Have received with your Letter the Diſſertation of Monſieur — in Print; but to write my opinion thereof, would be too dangerous an enterpriſe. J never mean to doubt of the certainty of his doctrine; and too bad conſtruction was made of me at the beginning

of our commerce for to adventure farther in that way. It ſufficeth me to confeſſe that J was loſt in all probability, had it not been for your protection, ſince even under that, J could hardly be ſecure. This is a Buckler that hath been pierced in a thouſand places, and (to ſpeak freely) hath ſerved me rather for a ſhew, then defence. My great Adverſary (as you call him) would faine have made an example of your poore Suppliant, and ſhewed that he did not either believe that you did love me ſo deerely, or that he did not much regard the perſons whom you ſo loved. Nevertheleſſe Sir, If J had been of a quarrelſome humour, that matter (perhaps) would not have been ſo appeaſed; and men would perſwade me, that my perſon onely was injur'd, my

                  Aſſertions being as firme &amp; as ſound as they were before the battery. But let the field be his, ſeeing he cannot endure an encounter, that J ſay not a reſiſtance; and J doe willingly yeeld him all the advantages of this action. He choſe rather to take me, then receive my ſubmiſsion, and preferr'd a trophey before an homage. Nevertheleſſe, J am reſolv'd not to alter my condition or forget my wonted civility. Yet J doe make a ſtand at the very ſame bounds that he hath leapt over, and give reſpect to that Character, which he hath violated; J ſpeak of your Love and good opinion, which are more precious to me then my writings or my reputation, and which J cannot diſeſteem whereſoever J meet them. Sir; there will be alwaies in the world Oppreſſours

and men oppreſſed, &amp; J muſt be one of the Innocents that muſt ſuffer the perſecutions of a Herod. But there is nothing ſo hard that love cannot digeſt. J pardon (for your ſake) all my injuries and ſufferings, withall my heart, &amp; am contented to be ill intreated, as long as J give evidence that J am
               
                  Sir
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
10. Sept. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. X. To Monſieur de RACAN.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Render You thanks for your Shepheardeſſe; with whom J enjoyed ſuch raviſhing pleaſures that

the Voluptuous never enjoy the like, and yet ſo chaſt and honeſt, that J think not my ſelfe bound to make Confeſsion, She hath reviv'd my ſpirits that were rebated with eager ſtudy and tired with diſtinctions and Syllogiſmes. J cannot diſſemble, J have not this long time Sir, ſpent a day more happily then whē J entertain'd Her. And if J haue thought Her ſo beautifull in her own ſimple weeds, &amp; naturall habiliments, without the addition of thoſe helps which ſerve to embelliſh &amp; adorne; what will it be, whē 
                  She will appeare in the pompe and luſter of the Theater? and when thoſe things that are of themſelves ſo powerfull, will be mended with the help of the voice and the graces of pronunciation? If J thought She were to come forth ſuddainely in

that Equipage, J would ſtraight begin my journey for to be preſent at that joyfull ſpectacle, and to give you the applauſe which you doe juſtly deſerve. But ſince you have ſent Her me, being yet, warme frō the birth, and that Shee muſt grow up a while and gather ſtrength in your hands, J hope J ſhall be time enough at Roche to behold her in her glory. J underſtand Sir, in the meane while, that there is a great contention between the Ladies about the names of Orante, &amp; Oriana, &amp; that they are more ambitious of the ſcrip and ſhepheards hook then any thing. It lieth in you to doe them Juſtice and ſatisfie their ambition: yet notwithſtanding, if youl'e beleeve me, you muſt caſheere this rurall Equipage, and adapte your ſelfe to Crownes and

Scepters. That active and ſtrong Spirit which doth ſweye you, hath too much vigor for to dwell on weaker Themes; it would break all the furniture of horne-pipes and hau-bois that you ſhould fill it with; moreover, the countrey and cabbin is not the proper ſpheare of magnificence, and Shepheardeſſes muſt not dance to the ſound of a Trumpet. J have therefore choſen for you an heroick ſubject indeed, and worthy the courage and majeſty of your ſtyle; Which ſtyle carrieth all the exactneſſe of rules, and hath been already uſed with good approbation by the Masters of Antiquity. But the ſport is, to ſee you diſpute and contend with them for their own vitory, and to challenge them at the ſame carreeres &amp; courſes that they have gain'd their

glory by. This kinde of Imitation is more noble and hardy then Invention it ſelfe, and which you are very capable to undertake, How-ever, if you ſhall ſtand in need of ſome aid, I am ready to doe the office of a Grammarian, and to give you the literall interpretation of the Texts of ſuch Authors, which you meane to follow, with a reſolution to outgoe them. I know that herein I ſhall not betray any great care of their reputation, nor doe any good office to any of them. But Sir, there is nothing that I would not doe for you, to whom I cōfeſſe infinite obligations, &amp; will be everlaſtingly
               
                  Sir,
                  A moſt humble, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
3. Sept. 1633.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XI. To Monſieur de St CHARTRES.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               THe diſorders of a crazie, &amp; ruinous body, and the paines I ſuffer by it, are the eternall hindrances of my devoir: Theſe alſo ſhall be (if you pleaſe) the ordinary Apologies for my ſilence. You may believe, that J doe not uſe to make great preparatiōs for to treat with you, in reſpect of the familiarity we profeſſe each to other; and if I could have rendred you thanks ſooner for your courteſies, I would not have ſav'd the expence of a few ragged lines, ſo long a time. I have received the Tranſlation of your friend, who doth me more honour then I can deſerve. J cannot ſufficiently

acknowledge the paines that he was pleas'd to take for me, being not ignorant how unpleaſing a thing is Dependance. J confeſſe that it is more than a probable argument of a mans love, to ſubmit himſelfe to the fancy of a man that holds no ſuperiority over him. This ſervitude is irkeſome, and ſo heavy a yoke to good wits, that they have ſeldome borne it as they ſhould; and Victorius obſerves a number of paſſages of Ariſtotle, which Cicero did not underſtand in his tranſlation. And yet to underſtand an Author aright is not all: things rendred in another language, muſt retaine the ſame degree of goodneſſe, (if it be poſsible) as was in the Originall: the ſtrong muſt not be enfeebled, nor the well attired be deveſted or clad in raggs, nor thoſe

that are well moūted be unhorſed, and made to ſerve on foot. Moſt Interpreters (indeed) deale with books in that manner, and doe violate the lawes of ſacred hoſpitality, towards the Perſons of the nobleſt ſtrangers that they meet with. Commonly they write French after the Latine mode, and Latine after the French; &amp; J have ſeen more Authors ſtript and excoriated, than Authors tranſlated. Jt is by your good favour, that J am not of the number of thoſe Martyrs; but on the contrary, your Friend hath done me many courteſies which J needed, and furniſht me with a thouſand ornaments which J had not of my owne. J am very much obliged unto him in this behalfe, and J owe you alſo much thanks, for the regard you ſhew'd to my counſailes,

preferring them before your firſt inclinations. Accompliſh Sir, that which you have begun, and let us ſee a Senator worthy the ancient Republicke, and the age of genuine and legitimate Romans. Jn our time, men doe beare a great opinion of their eloquence: and a certaine Author (whoſe name J have forgot) talkes of the purple of their language, as well as of that of their gownes. I doubt not but you will adorne them: both with the one and the other livery; And that you will make the drieſt thornes of thir pettifogging Dialect, look freſh and flouriſhing againe, if you will take the paines to dreſſe and manure them. Monſieur Chapelaine followes my counſaile, and thanks me in all his Letters for the friendſhip contracted between you. Preſerve

                  Sir for me that good which I doe for others, and think me not unworthy of it, ſince that I am withall my ſoule
               
                  Sir.
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
4. Nov. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XII. To Monſieur BAUDOIN.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Received the alarme of your ſickneſſe: but your Letter did ſoone ſettle and compoſe my mind; if it be as you write, but an attachmēt without griefe, J believe that J am not bound to keep much adoe in bemoaning you; this neceſſary

reſt and reſidence is good for ſomething: it doth (at leaſt) priviledge a Philoſopher from performing a thouſand petty offices, which doe diſtract a Contemplative life, &amp; which a Civill life doth ſeem to exact from him, that hath the free uſe of his leggs. So that in the ſtate that you are in, you doe oblige the Publick in deſpight of you; and doubt not, but diverſe Nations doe bleſſe your Goute, that is the cauſe of your leaſure; ſince that indeed it doth not handle you rudely, and that I doe (as others) reape much profit thereby; I know not whether I ought to call it good or bad, except my own intereſt ſhould be more conſiderable, then the liberty of my Friend. Hereupon, J ſhall conſult with my Morall Philoſophy, upon that part which treateth of Duties, which

you (I am ſure) will not have call'd Offices. You ſhall underſtand Sir, in the meane while, that I have received the ſecond impreſsion of my Letters, and that my eyes are not ſo bad, but that I could eſpie at the firſt glance, that which they owe unto your care. I ſhould be uncivill (not to ſay unknowing) if I did not render you thanks for this favour, and if that my book (having received better order and Oeconomy by your hands) J did not confeſſe that it is you that did beſtow upon't its laſt graces. We muſt confeſſe that you are an admirable Chymick to refine that which is groſſe and droſſy in my writings; and that you are a great exterminator of our ſuperfluous characters. But J ſhould have been yet more deeply ingaged unto you, if that you had

throughly plaid the Aristarchus, and with that hatchet which is ſo formidable to SSs, which you deem unuſefull, you had hewne off my other faults, as well as that of Orthography. This ſhall be reſerved for another time, and for a work of greater conſequence, whereof you ſhall be the Iudge, upon condition Sir, that you ſhew no pitty or favour in your cenſures, and that my ſtile undergoe all the rigor of your lawes, as long as my perſon be had in conſideration, and that J be ſtill
               
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
25. Oct. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XIII. To Monſieur de COIGNET Gentleman in Ordinary to the moſt Illuſtrious Queene of great Britaine.
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Was much diſcontented that J parted from Paris, without having the honour to bid you Adieu: But it is very difficult to live regularly amidſt ſuch confuſions, and to be punctuall in a time when all things are out of order. I thought I had done much, that I had not forgot my ſelfe, being in the place where I was; and that I did put ſix ſcore leagues of land between Me and Iohn de Werth. Being able to make but a ſorry ſouldier, I thought that no body had any

thing to ſay to me in Picardy, and that the Kings Army, would not be the leſſe compleat for my abſence. Loe now Sir, J am arriv'd here, this ſide of the Loire, buſy in fortifying, as well as J may, my village with Philoſophy; and intrenching my ſelfe againſt the Enimies with good books. If the tempeſts which threaten the Frontiers of Bayon arrive at us, we muſt think of another way of ſafety, and reſolve (in any caſe) to paſſe the Sea, and goe and dwell in that Region of Peace, and that happy climate where your divine Princeſſe reigns. But the good conduct and leading of the King her Brother, and the good Fate of France forbid us to harbour any thoughts of deſpaire; and the opinions of Sages, that expect a calme and ſerenity after a

ſtorme, are farre different from the Dialect of the vulgar, that think that all ſtormes are everlaſting. It ſhall be then a viſite of complement (in deſpight of Iohn de Werth) that J ſhall performe, and not a voyage of neceſsity which J muſt make; and I hope my words ſhall finde no evaſion, and that I ſhall tell you in London that which I ſay here, that I am entirely
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
20. Sep. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XIV. To Madam DESLOGES.
               
               
                  Madam,
               
               TAke it not amiſſe, that I doe much rejoyce at your removall from Paris, ſince that thereby I doe regaine the glorious beatitude of your neighbour-hood, and that I am now but fifteen leagues diſtant from Virtue retired: Monſieur d'Auvila did confirme this newes, whereof I had otherwiſe an intimation formerly; and he hath farther aſſured me (Madam) of the good ſucceſſe of your journey, and of your victory in the Chamber of the Edict. Since the guerdon of this conqueſt lyeth in Aunix, I beleeve it will repent you to have offended the Angoulmois
                  
ſome five years agone. J ſay it is ſome pleaſure to me to think that you will not digreſſe anymore out of the roade in contempt of us; and now ſhortly will be the time when you will dignify thoſe men with your preſence, which doe ſo paſsionatly deſire to ſee you. J am not ſo preſumptuous as to alleadge here my own wiſhes. But me thinks (Madam) that the Duke of Rochefoucaut deſerves one of your ſtages; and if it be ſo, I have reaſon to hope to be happy in ſome houres of the two or three daies, which you cannot deny to afford Him. J was about to ſend to you — to learne ſome newes of you: But this excellent Bearer, hath promiſed me to relate ſome at his returne; and you need not be troubled, in that he did forbeare that crude Oration that

was provided for you. This is a man (Madame) in whoſe mouth are Temples and Altars erected for you, and who adores you in every word he ſpeaks; He hath no vulgar conceit of your virtues, and he being alſo a man of parts, is worthy of that regard you beare to him. I hope he will love me a litle for love of you, and that you will doe ſo likewiſe; and adde this favour to the infinite number that I owe you, and which oblige me to bee more then any man in the world,
               
                  Madam
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac. 7. Oct. 1636.
                  
               
               
                  J ſend you (Madam) the complement which you deſire to ſee; It was ſent ere this, but was not received, becauſe my packet was loſt.

Since that time, J have never thought of it; but your curioſity finds out things that are loſt, and J am ſo good a Courtier, that none ſhould have ſeen it beſides your ſelfe.
               
            
            
               LET. XV. To my Lord Keeper of the Seales Seguier, ſince Chancellor of France.
               
                  My Lord,
               
               IF I had not been advertis'd that it was my bounden duty to write unto you, J ſhould not have thought it needfull ſo to doe. And though J have ruminated as much as any other, upon the choice that the King hath made of your perſon, I conſidered it, as one of the felicities of his reigne, and as a generall influence of favour upon

all the world. Calling to mind the definition of Ariſtotle, that calls Justice the good of another, I thought it not ſo congruous to congratulate with him that muſt be the Guardian of the lawes, touching a preferment that will put him to a perpetuall care and vigilance. But rather to partake in ſilence of the common felicity of thoſe people that ſhall wholly rely upon his watchfulneſſe. But my Lord, ſince cuſtome commands it, and that congratulations from the remoteſt parts of the Kingdome doe poaſt towards you, J ſhould be thought unwotthy of that ranke which J hold among your humble ſervants, if I did not ſequeſter my ſelfe from the Crowde to deliver you (apart) ſome teſtimony of my joy, and to make you ſee, that in places of ſilence

&amp; ſolitude there be not wanting acclamations for you and affections for the Countrey. I ſhall therefore make bold to tell you that the joy which ſeiſeth me at this time, is mingled with a kinde of vanitie; and having accompanied you with my thoughts and eies even unto the place of your Advancement, I doe imagine I have (in ſome ſort) conducted you, whether the judgement of the Prince hath advanced you. Wherefore my Lord in your Promotion, I doe rejoyce for the good ſucceſſe of my Imagination, &amp; take no ſmall pleaſure to ſee my own Divinations verified. Certainly it is a matter of delight to ſee a 
                     Ʋertue ſo laborious &amp; active as yours, brought into the moſt wide and ſpacious Carreere that Fortune could make

choice of; and this is a ſpectacle worthie the ſight of Heaven, and of the bleſſed ſoule of the late Cato of your race. The importance is, my Lord, that you begin in a very good ſeaſon, for to continue long; and that you are in the verdure &amp; vigor of your age for to uphold the crazy &amp; decrepit weakneſſe of our State. In this Elevation both of Merit and Dignitie, each man will be your Adorer &amp; Votary: But you will give me leave to aſſure you that none will approach unto you with a purer &amp; more diſ-intereſſed Devotion then mine, and that I am without much pompe and flouriſh, yet in much ſincerity
               
                  My Lord,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac. 1. April 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XVI. To Monſieur de Morins, Counſellour of the King in the Court of the Edict, at Agen.
               
               
                  My Lord,
               
               YOu are noble enough to love a man without any merits, but I were too looſe and forlorne if I were ſo loved, and yet had no ſenſe or regard of it; and yet you have ſome cauſe to call me by that bad title; and if Monſieur Girard hath not had a care of his friend's reputation, all circumſtances condemne me. It is true that my fault was but the omiſsion of a Complement, which had ſlipt out of my memory; &amp; yet I avow to you, that this omiſsion is ſuch a ſin that hath (a long time) burdened my

conſcience, and cauſeth ſuch gripes and remorſe Sir, that except the ſame goodnes that hath ſhewed me favour doe grant me a pardon, I cannot make attonement with my ſelfe. But I am apt to believe that for the appeaſing of my thoughts you will not runne the hazard of your former benefits, and that you will by your perſeverance adde to my obligations. Knowing this moreover, that you are a right Honeſt man; I muſt neceſſarily conclude that you are no Formaliſt or a man of Ceremonie, and that you doe not tye your ſelfe to thoſe petty obſervances &amp; Rites which make the friendſhip of this Age more perplext and difficult then ſincere. If Yours may be gain'd or merited by a true and perfect valuation of your worth, I will not be an unfaithfull

                  Depoſitary, beſeeching you to believe that I am alreadie as much as any man in the world
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
Feb. 20. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XVII. To Monſieur de-Vaugelas Gentleman in Ordinary to Monſieur the Kings onely Brother.
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Did read my own thoughts in your Letter; I ſubſcribe unto all that you have writ unto me, &amp; confeſſe that in the Elogie of Monſieur Arnold the Abbat, you doe (indeed)

but give your friend his due, &amp; lend him never a graine. This is (in truth) a moſt accompliſh't man, &amp; who at the age of 22 yeares, was reputed wiſe even by the Italians, that lately thought wiſdome was their own free-hold. He hath with his great knowledge mingled much goodneſſe: the ſharpneſſe of his underſtanding is tempered and allaied by the ſweetneſſe of his behaviour, and his modeſtie doth repreſſe and conceale much of his abilities. He never pardons himſelf, though he doth beare with all humane infirmities in others; and that Piety which he doth practiſe, gives reſpect unto all, but ſtrikes a terror in none. Loe Sir, the teſtimonie which I adde unto yours: which I would beſtow upon an enimie that deſerv'd it, but would not upon a

friend that wanted merit. His knowledge is attended on by other vertues, and it hath furniſht him with excellent moralitie: for without this, it ſhould be ſolitarie and of litle uſe. I tell you nothing of the late experiment I have found of it in your Letter which he wrote unto you: Beſides that my beſt language would be farre below my apprehenſion of if; I know withall too well the power of his Rhetorick to conteſt with it; ſince he hath got ſo many advantages over me, he muſt needs have that of civility and complements too; and my ſilence muſt not be accounted any more the effect of modeſty but of the Eloquence of his Letter. I ſend it you back becauſe you would have it ſo, and becauſe you may make ſome uſe of it in your Cabinet; but I

ſhall reſerve a coppy of it under your favour, that it may afford ſome comfort &amp; reliefe to my diſcontents. I have ſeen the ſiedge of Tyre, the Death of Darius, the Voiage of the Jndians, and I have read them with wonder. All theſe ſeem to me ſo good French and ſo naturall, that it is impoſsible to pick out any line there, that doth ſavour of, or ſhew any affinitie with Latine, or wherein the originall Author hath any advantage above the ſecond. What would you have more Sir, or what ſentence can you crave of me? I have but one word to adde in commendation of your Travels. The Alexander of Philip was invincible, &amp; that of Vaugelas is inimitable. It is that (to ſay no more) that will deſerve the affection of your incomparable Marchioneſſe, and the

faire Beavy or Troope that doe often aſſemble at her Houſe. Monſieur — calls Her a choice and reſplendent Court, and the great World refined, and reformed: and ſaith, that there is no Tribunall ſo ſoveraigne that we may not appeale from, unto the Manſion of Ramboûillet. Since I cannot know what kind of work it is that my Stationer ſhall give you, untill this divine Romane Dame ſhall paſſe her cenſure upon it; I dare not as yet, declare my ſelfe for a Book which I muſt not acknowledge, although I have compoſed it. It ſufficeth to tell you, that I had an ayme to ſpeake French, and to write ſome Letters which ſhould not put Her to the trouble of deciphering. I did heartily deſire that my Deſigne might take effect; and I ſhould believe I had not gain'd a

litle, by the commerce of many yeares, if what you ſhall preſente her with, in my name, may entertaine her thoughts for a few houres; the nobleſt labours of the underſtanding cannot aſpire to a higher bliſſe than that; Philoſophy her ſelfe ſhould betray too much preſumption to think to take them up wholly and imploy them; ſhee cannot claime to be any more than her diverſion and by-thought. I ſhall be very well contented Sir, if I might ſerve for that purpoſe handſomely; &amp; I ſhould boaſt, after this, that I were (though in my abſence) very good company. That timorouſneſſe that did ever poſſeſſe me that I could not be ſo, any other way, and the feare of troubling the ſerenitie of another mans viſage by the ſullen cloudineſſe of mine, have

made me to refrain from all Feasts and Aſſemblies, and hindred me frō bringing heavy looks to thoſe places which I eſteeme ſacred, &amp; before thoſe eyes which I doe revere. So that it is a pure reverence in me, that I abſtaine from acceptable and delightfull converſation, and from the pleaſures of thoſe Cabinets that appertaine to them only that be happier than I. And I doe chooſe rather to adore a farre off with awfull regard, than be importunately, and ſaucily familiar. I leave it to you to excuſe and juſtifie this timorouſneſſe which proceeds from reſpect, not from a Stoicall ferocity. And you will doe me a favour, if that while you repreſente the beſt part of your friend, you wil take the paines to excuſe the worſt. Whereunto, J doe earneſtly conjure

you, and to believe firmly, that I am
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac. 26. Feb. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XVIII. To Monſieur de la Motte-Aigron.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               THe Jndian Canes which you ſent me were pretty, but you have ſo embelliſht them at Rochell, that I doubt me they are not for my turne. They are not made for a private mans uſe: They are Emblemes of ſoveraigne command; &amp; a bolder Orator then I, would render you thanks rather for your Scepters
                  
then your Canes. By what name ſoever we call them, they are the more precious to me becauſe they came from You, more then for any other conſideration; and though you have not made me rich, yet you have made me very glorious. It is a Maxime in Ariſtotle that Ambition is no more ſatisfied with benefits received, then Covetouſneſſe. But me thinks, he ſhould have added, whē it receives from him, from whom it deſired to receive: For all ſorts of Benefactors doe not farre oblige thoſe that are ambitious of the better ſort only. For my part, I ſhould believe that the Preſents of Monſieur — would pollute me, &amp; I would be as much aſham'd of his favours as I glory in yours. In truth Sir, I have quitted the Countrey &amp; am come purpoſely to the Towne

to ſhew them. With them, I doe ſuſtaine my old age with credit, and look as trimme as upon ſolemne daies of Ceremonie. They ſerve me both for to ſupport and to adorne▪ for moveables of neceſsity, and oſtentation too. But the worſt is, that I have nothing here for to requite ſo rare a Preſente, but the ſhape and lineaments of a vulgar man, and the ſad repreſentation of my own viſage. As it were very unjuſt that I ſhould pretend to beauty: ſo it is a very ſoleciſme that Philarchus calls me a Narciſſus. But there are alwaies fooliſh paſsions, and idle curioſities in the world. My friends at Paris would needs urge me to have my Picture drawn, and I to give them contentment, did yeeld my ſelfe for one halfe-houre to be tranſcrib'd, &amp; granted

them this meager delight. Some Coppies were ſent me: one whereof I beſtow upon You, ſuppoſing that it will not ſcare you; &amp; knowing that Affection is a better flatterer yet, than the Painter. This is it that will beare falſe witneſſe for me to prove me faire, and which will allow me a place in the Claſſe of your Illuſtrious men. Such a place in your Cabinet, is indeed a high advancement, and which I cannot obtaine but by meere favour; But that which you have given me in your heart is no leſſe precious to me, and I thinke I have good right to the poſſeſsion, ſince I am really
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Angouleſme
15. Ian. 1637.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XIX. To Monſieur de BORSTELL.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Durſt not undertake the great and hazardous voyage, which I did impoſe upon my ſelfe ſome foure years paſt, without taking leave from our noble Lady. J have therefore ſent unto her to beg it, by the man that ſhall deliver you this Letter; &amp; that ſhall bring me back (if you pleaſe) ſome directions for my journey, which I beg of you. Being provided of ſuch ammunition, I ſhall not feare the rigor of February, nor the unconſtancy of March, nor the inundations of the Loire, nor the waies of Beauſſe. I am ſure to arrive happily at Paris: where Sir, if you have any buſines,

J can furniſh you with a Sollicitor, who (though but a ſorry one) is very ambitious to doe you ſervice. Alte non temo, &amp; humili nonſdegno: I neither feare the high nor diſdaine the low. You cannot think of any imployment that ſhall not be very welcome to me; and though I love ſloath and make a profeſsion of Idleneſſe, yet I will change my inclination, and of a ſedentary man become a Currier; Except this, I am commonly deſirous of privacy, and never bring into the Aſſemblyes of men but my eyes, and my teſtimony. There muſt be Spectators at ſuch times as well as Poets and Actors; and ſome that muſt doe nothing for the intereſt and honour of thoſe that act. But to the purpoſe, Sir; what are become of your Actors of the Low-countreyes. I doe

verily think that there is no more Holland in the world, and that the ſea hath drowned the famouſeſt part of the Earth. There was never ſuch a dearth of newes; And the Carthuſian Monks doe not meditate with more ſilence, than they doe wage warre in that Countrey. Jf you are more learned than the Gazettes, J pray impart your knowledge by this Bearer, who hath a chardge to give you an account of many things, and will acquaint you particularly how farre I am
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac:
18. Feb. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XX. To Monſieur — the Chiefe Advocate.
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Am impatient untill I can hear of the eſtate of your health, and learne by the returne of my Lacquay, whether your legges be better then they were wont. It is no wonder if they bend under the burden of ſo many brave things which they ſuſtaine; and being to carry the counſailes of a whole Province, if they be ſomewhat incommodated with ſuch a weight. Yet I doe hope well of the wholeſomneſſe of that Aire which you breath; and that, being out of the reach of that malignant Iupiter, (that noiſome mildew, J would have

ſaid) which over-runnes the hilles of Angouleſme, you will have the leaſure to travell to your breaches, and fortify your ſelfe againſt winter. This is a neighbour that doth threaten us upon the Frontiers, and if I can, I will fly from him, as far as Africk. But this remedy is ſomething too farre. Without undertaking ſo great a voyage, we will endeavour to make reſiſtance as well as we may; and I am already reſolv'd to uſe all humane induſtry, to barricadoe my chamber, and to block up all approaches towards it. If I can maintaine it bravely againſt ſo terrible an Enimy; I ſhall account my ſelfe no mean Engineer, and ſhall think my Sconces and Fortifications as regular as thoſe of the Hollanders. After this, this ſhall be, if you pleaſe, the Campe of our

riotous diſcourſes and extravagances; of our peacefull diſputations, and all other exerciſes that an honeſt man may performe in a chaire; I doe therefore deſigne you for it about mid-November, and remaine
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
18. Oct. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXI. To Monſieur De MAURY.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOu have ſent me a Preſente which was extreamly deare and welcome to me, and which J muſt highly prize, both for the manner of ſending, and the

matter ſent; the Affliction which you paint out and emblazon, is ſo Christian, that all the Ioy in the world is not able to countervaile it; and you complaine in ſuch a learned forme, that we muſt forbid men to comfort you, leaſt you ſhould ceaſe complaining. J am, you know, but a ſimple French Doctor; yet J doe now and then, make excurſion into the Latine Countrey, and take a view of the Frontiers. But this is too litle for to know the juſt valew of your Muſe, and to give you the commendation that you deſerve. You have an ancient Roman neere you, that can diſtinguiſh between the Native, and the Forrainer; and makes it Religion to confound the modeſty of the age of Auguſtus, with the intemperance of ſucceeding times. He hath

a ſmack of the primitive Poetry, which the Spaniards had not yet vitiated, and made immodeſt; and of that pure Latine, which the Declamators had not yet corrupted with nice ſubtilities. He it is, that can give you ample and juſt commendation, &amp; can make a juſt eſtimate of the riches of your ſtile: For my part, J can but teſtify unto you my deep apprehenſion of your courteſies in this behalfe, and aſſure you that J will be while I live
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
23. Oct. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXII. To Monſieur De MONDORY.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOur Letter was to me an old novelty, and J received it but in the begining of December, though it had been at my houſe ſince Auguſt: To unfold this ridle, J muſt tell you, I am newly return'd from a long voyage, and that I found your Letter here at my arrivall. You may believe, that the name of a man that is deare unto me, did, at firſt encounter of my eye affect me with joy; and that it is no ſmall ſatisfaction and contentment to me, to ſee that I hold a place in a memory, that is ſo occupied and fully fraught as yours. This is to lye downe among a bed of Roſes,

when I lye among ſo many brave Poems, and rare diſcourſes which you containe, is a walking Library. And if it be lawfull to tell out the reſt; to be the friend of Monſieur de Mondory, is to be a Favorite of a thouſand Kings; for indeed you doe ſo lively repreſent unto us the majeſty and magnificence of former ages, that we muſt confeſſe that your repreſentations, are the glorious Reſurrections of thoſe Princes, which you doe perſonate. And things being thus, take it not amiſſe that in my anſwere I muſt contradict you. You cannot compare the bonnet of Herod with that of Monſ. the Advocate — without doing ſome injury to Royall dignity, and avileing their Purple and Diamonds; without doing your ſelfe a bad office, in leſſening, and

obſcuring in me thereby (if you could) the great Idea which I conceiv'd of you, the day that I ſaw you with that Bonnet. But you may be pleaſed to humble your ſelfe; you cannot deface or blotte out of my memory that firſt impreſsion and Image of majeſty which you there left; and J cannot figure you in my thoughts, but with a commanding accent, and the eloquence of a Master, farre tranſcending that inferior Rhetorick, which works but by intreaties and remonſtrances. Yet J ſpeak not this, as though J would alwaies conſider you under the name and ſhape of another; or that I beleeve, if that you ſhould quit the Theater, you would be out of all imployment in the world. The Letter which you were pleas'd to write unto me,

doth ſufficiently witneſſe, that Eloquence is your naturall endowment, and that without borrowing from any, you can traffick in very good things of your own. Suſpect not then that I ſhould recant to your prejudice, after this new occaſion of extolling you. On the contrary, J am ready (if need be) to adde ſomething to my former teſtimony. I have many reaſons to reſpect you, and J think I may doe it with the licenſe of our ſevereſt Schooles. Since that having reform'd the ſtage, and purg'd it from all obſcenity, you may glory in this, that you have recōcild Comedy with —Pleaſure with Virtue. And though for my part I ſtand in need of recreations, yet ſince I deſire not to enjoy but thoſe that are cleanly and which doe not violate honeſty, I

doe (with the common voice) give you thanks for the care you have taken, to provide fit remedies, and Antidotes againſt Melancholy, and other untoward paſsions. But farther, calling to mind that you propoſed my contentation ſometimes, for the end of your action, and that you aimed oftentimes at me alone, I were ungratefull if I did not confeſſe that I am
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
15. Dec. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXIII. To Monſieur LE. GVAY.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOu had an intention to performe an act of Humility, when you did dedicate your Poem to me; for to expect protection from a man that is not reckoned of the world, and light from a name ſo obſcure as mine, you could not (ſure) forget your ſelfe in this ſort. The ſame virtue which obligeth the Saints to acknowledge Superiors where ever there are men, hath carried you to this depth of lowlineſſe, and you have choſen an unhappy man, for to beſtow honour upon, that you might looſe that, which you would faine beſtow.

I muſt confeſſe, that no man ever commended his neighbour more Chriſtian-like, and doth more decline the trade of thoſe Mercenaries, who ſell their teſtimonies and credit to any, that have wherewith to requite them. Theſe are Huckſters of Poetry and Rhetorick; that proſtitute to the firſt commers, even thoſe whō you ſtile the Kindred of the Gods &amp; Daughters of Iupiter; and make Pegaſus a very hackney of commendation, (as I may ſo ſay) for all the world. You have a heart of a farre better mould then theirs; and though men conſider not as they ought, the graces ces and elegancies of your Muſe, we muſt notwithſtanding infinitely commend their nobleneſſe and generoſity. I confeſſe for my part, that J am a debtor to them as farre

as any, and that J know not how to requite in any meaſure, the favours that I have received from them. Yet notwithſtanding, J forbeare not to loade my Porter with a pretty groſſe▪ bundle; not pretending thus to acquit my ſelfe, or thinking that I am hereby leſſe then before
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
1. April 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXIV. To Monſieur De SILHON, Muſqueteer of the Kings Company.
               
                  Sir,
               
               HAving your perſon in great admiration, I cannot miſprize

or undervalue your friendſhip. The faire tokens whereof, which I have receav'd in the Letter, that you were pleas'd to write unto me, have obliged me ſo farre, that I confeſſe that I owe you already that which you are pleas'd now to promiſe me. I will tell you but this, that if Princes could beſtow health and vertue, I ſhould be a more ſedulous Courtier then I am, and ſhould ſtand in more neede of your teſtimony and the recommendation of your friend. But truly in the caſe that I am, my deſires are ſo feeble, and my pasſions ſo cold and languid, that I could hardly bee perſwaded to take up a Croſier, if I found it on the earth. Though Philoſophy doth not teach, that wee muſt ſeeke for happineſſe out of the wheeling Orbe of the Court;

my owne lazineſſe would cauſe me to apprehend it as a fortune, under whoſe weight J ſhould perpetually groane and not a place of any eaſe; and J doe leſſe eſteeme of a place of Government that might cumber me, then a field of liberty that may ſolace me. Jf you goe any time into Gaſcony, and doe me the honour to take my houſe in the way, you will verify what J ſay to you; and avouch, that if J were as well cured of all maladies as that of Ambition, I had not many wiſhes to commence. Jt is true that ſome company (like that of Monſieur your Brother) is wanting unto me; and if this were added to my Hermitage, J durſt contend with Jupiter for happineſſe. This is a ſpeech of Epicurus which Seneca doth alleadge, but which I doe mean to

apply better then it was by the Author; ſince Bread and Beare (which this Philoſopher made the two Elements of ſoveraigne Good) are not ſo rare or ſo good, as thoſe excellent Inſtructions and perfect honeſty, which I ſhould finde and injoy in the perſon of my friend. I doe charge you to aſſure him, that I doe ever honour and eſteeme him infinitely, and for your particular, you may believe, that you cannot affect a man that could be more ſincerely then I am,
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
19. Dec. 1635.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXV. To Monſieur De la Foſſe.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOu judge too ſeriouſly of my Recreations &amp; beare too high an opinion of my Eſſayes. It is no Roman Cittizen that you thus reſpect, it is a Barbarian diſguiſed. I haue drawn ſome rude lineaments and miſhapen figures, and you would allow them for juſt works and exact Pieces. Your Eloquence herein doth favour me, but alters me not a whit. You are powerfull in language, but I am hard of perſwaſion; and I have learnt from a mous Author, that to give things honourable appellations doth coſt us nothing: And I ſee well that Illuſtrious &amp; Excellent which you grace

me with, doe ſignifie (except by way of Civility) but things vulgar and meane. It is true Sir, that J doe adventure ſometimes to coppy out good Originalls. J have an eye as much as poſsibly I may, to ancient examples, and I doe ſcarce ſeek thē beyond Terence or this ſide Livy. But theſe are but idle Speculations (perhaps) and impotent deſires which leave an infinite ſpace betweene my abilities and my Idea; if it be ſo, as I feare it is, Monſieur de Prieſac doth heedfully obſerve this diſtance &amp; pittieth in his ſoule the vaine attempts &amp; raſhneſſe of my pen. Yet he is ſo good &amp; loveing, that he will not, I ſhould learn this diſtaſtfull truth from him; and loves rather to commend a fault, then diſcover it, in a man that is deare to him. He hath written ſuch

                  polite things to me, and in ſuch abundance, that I dare not ſend forth any replie after his anſwer, leaſt I ſhould be undone by ſo unequall a compariſon. I muſt not attempt this great Deſigne, for the ſucceſſe thereof muſt needs be unlucky, though I ſhould make uſe of Auxiliaries and demand ſuccours of all the Latiniſts of our Province. You ſhall tell him then, if you pleaſe, that I doe acknowledge the advantage his ſtyle hath over mine, and I think it no diſparagement that I muſt ſtill owe him what I ſhall never be able to pay him. You are kind enough yet Sir, to aſſure Monſieur Habert the Abbat, &amp; Monſieur de la Chamber, of the conſtancie of my ſervice; and how impatient I am, that the world doth not yet know, in what regard J hold their

vertues. It ſufficeth me that they accept and allow of my affection, and that they teſtifie it unto you with a nod. For to deſire Letters &amp; not tickets from them, were to be ignorant of the preſent condition of their life, and the homage that they performe to our Monarch, who beſt deſerves it. J have received ſome Verſes from Monſieur D' Eſpeſſes, and you ſend me ſome more of other mens, together with a Letter, which my Servant left to grow ſtale upon the Table in my chamber. You will doe me the favour as to deliver him my Packet, &amp; readily take ſo much paines for my ſake: who will account my ſelfe happy to be made your Agent in theſe parts, and be able to expreſſe that none is more intirely
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
3. Ian. 1637.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXVI. To Monſieur D' Eſpeſſes Counſellour of the King in his Counſaile of State.
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOU make me (truely) to languiſh, &amp; it is more then foure months, ſince J have expected our Tranſlation: J call it ours, becauſe you made it in my Chamber, and on my paper; and J might call it mine too, by a rule in the Law, which doth adjudge the ſurface to goe along with the profunditie; but that J remembred the exception of the Emperour which he adds in favour of excellent Artizans. Nobis contrà videtur, meliùs eſſe Tabulam▪ cedere Picturae: Ridiculum enim eſt picturam Apelli
                        •
                      vel Parrhaſií in acceſſionem
                  
                  viliſsimae picturae cedere. We muſt not urge a man that is intent upon more important affaires. Yet when your leaſure ſerves, be pleas'd to perfect that ſame Tranſlation, &amp; try if our language can expreſſe Terence in that nobleneſſe of ſtyle, and the Character of Scipio and Laelius, which the Roman Nation obſerve to be in it. Jn the meane time Sir, to have the more colour to demand of you, I ſend you here a ſmall gift; ſome Verſes which I received lately from one of my friends in England, who doth chardge the Muſes of the Low-Countreyes with the making. You are in ſome ſort intereſſed in't, ſeeing they queſtion the credit &amp; trueth of an Author who among you, is cryed for Indubitable; and ſeeme to thwart your judgement of him, as concerning the certainty

of his Teſtimonie. But (in good ſooth) the Flemmings have reaſon to require ſuch a ſcrupulous and punctuall truth in our newes: They who are the moſt fabulous Hiſtorians of this Age, and for the moſt part, truck away nothing but Apocryphall Relations. By changing the proper names only in their Verſes, we might retort all their Sarcaſmes upon them-ſelves; wee could ſpeake truely of their Gazet, what they have falſely written of ours; and tell them farther, that that which they deride ſo, is well eſteem'd all over by the moſt ingenious Nation of the world; It is certaine that the fine wits of Rome doe admire the acuteneſſe and appoſite expreſsions therein; and Monſieur the Abbat of — upon his return from Italy did aſſure me, that it was

pronounc'd in the Academy of the Humoriſts, that each ſection of the Pariſian Gazet was worth a Chapter in Florus, or Valerius Maximus. They are Sir, as you know, Epigrams in proſe: and the determination of ſo famous a Tribunall, is a ſufficient Countermure againſt the aſſaults of this new Poem. I would deſire you to impart it to Monſieur Gaulmim, and ſome other grave Judges of Latin learning. That we may know the guſt of your great world, and what we are to believe in the Provinces. The Deſcription of the Bureau d' Adreſſe,
                  The Cuſtome Houſe in Paris. Lib. 12. M
                        •
                     ta. ſeemes to me to have been drawn upon the plaine, or modell, of that Palace which Ovid hath erected to Fame. But you will make us upon this, &amp; all the reſt moſt large and learned Obſervations; and I doe promiſe

my ſelfe to receive from you at once, both a Tranſlation and a Commentary. I am perfectly
               
                  Sir
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
25. Nov. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXVII. To the ſame.
               
                  Sir,
               
               Since I wrote my Letter, it comes to my head that for a Counter-cuffe to the Gazeta Pariſienſis, we might ſend to the Low-Countrey-men, Hiſtoria Hiſpana, and fill it with Comicall ſport enough. Firſt we muſt make it to be the inceſtuous Off-ſpring of the Giants, begotten upon their own ſiſter

                  Fame, for the high and mighty lies wherewith it doth abuſe the credulity of the ſimple; and (in truth) the naturall pride of that Nation which appeares, even in the wandring Begger in extreameſt miſery; and thoſe Rhodomontades which to them are ſo proper and uſuall, that their very complements reteine a ſmack of them, are worthy of ſo Illuſtrious an Extraction, and to deſcend in a direct Line from Enceladus and Mimas, and Briareus. This premis'd Sir, and enricht with your art, I would have this monſtrous Iſſue gaine upon the beleefe of the Jndians &amp; the Cockneyes of Europe, that the beginning of the univerſall Monarchy promiſed to Spaine will betide juſt the next yeare, which is the climactericall yeare of all other States; that God's will is, that there

ſhould bee but one Monarch upon earth; &amp; that the Pope himſelf for his better accommodation, doth mean to reſigne Rome to him, &amp; exchange it for the Arch-Biſhoprick of Toledo. That the Battle where the King of Sueden was ſlaine, was the laſt ſigh of dying liberty; that this Prince was no ſuch thing as we took him to be; and for thoſe atchievements of his, which we entertain'd with ſuch wonder, nothing was performed without the help of Magick, by vertue only of ſome charmes, &amp; characters, and the aſsiſtance of the Powers of Hell, which at laſt were found too weak againſt the Houſe of Austria. That to the end that ſecond cauſes and humane meanes might concurre with the Deſigne of Providence, forreine affaires doe ſeeme to comply of them-ſelves to

this great change. That the King of England is not ſo brave, but that he would be contented to be a Feudatary of the King of Spaine; and if it goes to the worſt, that there will not be wanting ſome Gun-powdermen to make him caper in the ayre with his whole Realme. That the cinders of the Holy-League, and the remainder of the Huguenot Party begin to flame a new in France by the bellowes and Libells of St 
                  Germains; that they have bargain'd with ſome ſecret Engineers, who have undertaken to fortify Rochell in one night. That Duke Charles muſt be revenged upon Nancy, and that he doth hold Paris already in extremity; that if there be not a Spaniſh Garriſon already in Turin and Caſall, there will be one, when it ſhall ſeeme good to his Catholike

Maieſty, and when the Dukes of Savoy and Mantua, ſhall be received into his favour. That he will none of Venice or Amsterdam, becauſe that an Illuminatée of Madrid, and a Sybille of Naples have aſſured him that the Sea will one day ſwallow up theſe two great Citties; and the loſſe of his Spaniards that ſhould be their Commanders, would be a cauſe of great griefe unto him. That he had long ſince chaſtis'd the Rebells of Holland, if ſome conſiderations of ſtate had not hindred him from it. But let him preſerve that land of contradiction, for a Fencing-ſchoole for his owne Subjects, to keep them from idleneſſe, and to breathe them by continuall exerciſe. That for the reſt, if the world will not be ſo eaſily conquered, hee hath in his coffers

wherewith to buy it. And hereabouts, this Daughter of Fame and Enceladus her Brother, muſt raiſe her tone higher, and out-bid her firſt figure or number; ſhee muſt with one daſh of the pen make more gold, then the Sun can make in a thouſand years; ſhe muſt make the windes laboure, and force the Ocean to groane under the new Fleet, which according to her computation, muſt arrive every moneth punctually at Lisbon and Sivill; ſhe muſt make a diſcovery (if needs be) of the third Indies, &amp; find out all the hidden mines there; not thoſe within the Demaines of Anti-Chriſt excepted, &amp; cauſe them to be guarded by thoſe evill Spirits, which S. Auguſtin cals (for this reaſon) Incubones Theſaurorum, &amp;c. Behold Sir, a rude draught of a work

which expects from you its conſummation and perfection, which you might ſoone finiſh, if your Poeticall fancy ſhould once ſeize you. Here is matter (you ſee) for an excellent Irony, and wherewith to continue it to a hundred verſes and more, though the Comoedy did affect you ne're ſo litle, eſpecially when you ſhall adde forme and faſhion to the ſtuffe which I preſente you with, who am
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
27. Nov. 1637.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXVIII. To Monſieur de Couurelles.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Cannot write unto you but tumultuarily▪ my hands and head are ſo full of buſineſſe, that being to take a journey to Paris, I am bound to bid farwell to the Clergy, the Nobility, and the Commons. It is now foure yeares that I have deliberated upon this voyage, and being at laſt reſolv'd, I am like by your favour to be better accompanied then I did expect, Comes facundus in via, &amp;c. I think I may give this attribute to your Book, after the Elogy which you vouchſafe me therein: and if I had not already taken part and declared my ſelfe for the Author of the Flandrian Hiſtory
                  
(who is one of my good Lords and friends) J ſhould have entred blindly into a new faction, which (as it ſeems) you doe abette and patronize; But Sir, you will not take it amiſſe that I profeſſe conſtancy, and that this ſecond Author, hath not wonne my firſt affection. This evening I ſhall begin to entertaine him, and to taſt of thoſe delicacies whereof you were pleas'd to make an Eſſay. Theſe will not be painted Cates, I am ſure, nor Pageants of good; no nimble juglings and impoſtures practis'd upon the eye and imagination, as moſt part of thoſe things are, that come from that Country. There is no impoſture ſo finely contrived, as to be able to cheat ſo cautious a judgement as yours. And I will follow you, whether ſoever you ſhall pleaſe to lead

me, (I mean ſtill to except matters of faith) and J believe you will not be offended with ſuch an exception, ſince the lawes of friendſhip will allow it me, and ſince I never ceaſe to be moſt affectionatly
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Angouleſme
March. 8. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXIX. To —
               
                  Sir,
               
               MY willingneſſe to relieve afflicted men, deſerves not the thanks which J have reapt thereby. This is a paſsion which on my part doth but produce fruitleſſe

deſires, and which cannot by you be had in any eſtimation, but out of a ſuperlative nobleneſſe in you. In that J have given harbor to a man that was perſecuted, J did but that which the Law of Nations required of me, and what I would not have denied to the misfortunes of an — or a Spaniard. If you take this to mind, and become my debtor, you doe aſſume the intereſt of all mankind, and acquit the honour of the whole world; for my part, J am twice rewarded for an act, which J thought was ſufficiently rewarded in the doing, and for which I expected neither honor nor acknowledgemēt. You ſee Sir, that I am not privy to your ſecrets, and if you were obliged hereby, it was by an innocent and blindly ignorant man. For the Cavalier,
                  
touching whom you aske ſome newes; I believe that he hath prevented me, as being unwilling that any other then himſelfe ſhould be the Hiſtorian of his adventures. He will (no queſtion) write unto you, what hath hapned unto him in the Refectory of the — Fathers, and the notable advantages he hath gotten over a Gladiator of the long gowne. J am not troubled a whit that he hath got him ſome credit in ſo good a place, and gain'd the reputation of a man of valour. Yet, J muſt tell you, that his credit is dearer unto me then my own intereſt; and that if he have not the mind to diſpute, it is not my deſire he ſhould turne for my ſake. He may be my friend at a cheaper rate▪ and I can content my ſelfe with the calmeneſſe and tranquillity of his

paſsion, not needing that it ſhould break forth and appeare through noiſe and jangling. Many men (you know) never doe a good turne, but that they may have occaſion of upbraiding. Poverty is more tolerable then ſuch Creditors; &amp; there are ſome Patrons of ſuch harſh diſpoſitions, that I would chooſe perſecution before their ſuccors. Upon our firſt meeting, I will declare my ſelfe more particularly to you, and in the mean while, reſt
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Paris
May 3. 1631.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXX. To my Lord the Biſhop of ANGOULESME, chiefe Almoner to the Illustrious Queene of great Brittaine.
               
                  My Lord,
               
               I Have ſeen in a Letter that you have written to Monſieur — that my name is not unknown unto you, and that J have ſome ſhare in your good Graces; this is a favour which I owe to your courteſy only, and I dare not believe, that my more then ſmall deſerts, could have acquir'd me ſuch an ineſtimable good as that. I cannot juſtly enjoy it, if you would not admit of that perfect devotion and reverence which J offer you, and which I

were bound to pay to your 
                     Ʋirtue, though I ſhould never reflect upon your Dignity. You have at firſt boording, ingaged my obſervance. It will be (my Lord) an incredible contentment unto me, to enjoy that happy entertainment and diſcourſe which you have done me the honour to promiſe me. And J am confident, that I ſhall ſtill depart thence a better man, and more learned, though my inclination be never ſo untoward, and unapt for good purpoſes, &amp; my memory never ſo ſlippery to retain the impreſſiō of faire Ideas. But I begin to fear that your Flock ſhould in the mean while languiſh for you, and that the intereſts of France, will croſſe and oppoſe themſelves againſt the wiſhes of our Province. The feare of that was it, that caus'd

me to ſend to England a Book, which I did heartily deſire, I could have preſented to you there, togither with the Author. He is one of the great Votaries of that great Cardinall Perron your Unkle: He doth celebrate his memory without intermiſsion, and adores his learned Reliques. He doth glory in being his ghoſtly ſonne; and, you will not (I am ſure) make any difficulty, to avow this ſpirituall alliance that is between you and him, being joynd with the condition, that he deſires to live in all his lifetime; which is to be
               
                  My Lord,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
20. Dec. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXXI. To Monſieur De —
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Write unto you with a heart wounded with ſorrow, and make my moane to you, for the ſiniſter opinion, that you have conceiv'd of me, upon the firſt evill report that was ſuggeſted to you concerning me. J thought I had given you a ſufficient aſſurance of the ſmoothneſſe and plainneſſe of my ſoule, that you ſhould not have ſo eaſily doubted of it, and entertaine a beleefe ſo injurious to amity, before you had communicated your jealouſies to your friends, and made them cleere enough. You know Sir, more then any other, that my paſsions are not cloſe and

reſerved, but I carry my ſoule ſtill in my forehead. When I was not as yet, ſo farre your ſervant as now I am, I did not uſe much Artifice, and diſsimulation to perſwade the contrary; and thence you might have deduc'd an infallible concluſion, that if J had chang'd my inclination, J would not have deceived you with new proteſtations of fidelity. I doe therefore religiouſly proteſt unto you, that honouring you with that zeale as I doe, you could not inflict a greater puniſhment upon me, then the forfeiture of your favours. But moreover, I doe ſweare to you by all that is ſacred in the world, that I have committed nothing that might deſerve ſuch a cruell puniſhment. After this me thinks you might be confirm'd in the truth, but pardon me if I tell

you, you ſhould have been ſo before; and that I doe extremely wonder, that a weak and groſſe calumny, ſhould quite ruine and deface in your thoughts, the good impreſsions, which J thought I had left there. J cannot hinder mens miſ-conſtructions of me, or binde Interpreters from doing violence, and putting my words upon the rack, to make them depoſe things which were farre from my intentions. Sophiſters make uſe of a true propoſition to inferre an erroneous concluſion; and Pettifoggers ſtill cite the Law, to authoriſe their injuſtice, &amp; yet none will taxe Truth to be the cauſe of Error, or Law the mother of injuſtice. I cānot warrant, but my own thoughts (which are ſound and innocent) not thoſe of my adverſaries, which are full of

malice and rancor. J am reſponſable for the things that J have written, and ready withall to maintaine them. But all the viſions and fancies of men are not in my power. Every man can make a nimble and ſubtle decipherer of another mans intentions. The ſame picture, according to ſeverall lights and poſtures, may have ſeverall repreſentations; and oftentimes there is a great difference between a Text and the Commentaries, the meaning of the Author and the Criticiſmes of Grammarians. I ſaid that I knew ſome ſtrange inſufferable humors, and no way fit to poſſeſſe and ſway free-borne men. Therefore I ſaid, that a man, whom J doe infinitely eſteeme and honour was of that humor. Loe here Sir, (not to ſay halfe of what I think of it) a concluſion

very unworthy a Logician, and which is as farre from common, as from my particular ſenſe. Indeed it was not you, that deduc'd it, yet you ſhould not have entertain'd it at ſecond hand; and if it did not ſeeme to you to be palpably falſe, yet you might have demurr'd a while, and ſuſpected it; you have done your ſelfe wrong and me too, in conceiving ſo bad a thought of your own merit and my fidelity; in expreſsing that you have ſome diſtruſt of your ſelf, who are of no mean value, and but very litle confidence in me, whoſe freeneſſe is ſomething worth. I have but litle skill in fallacies, and a mean Jugler may ſometimes gaine credit with me▪ nevertheleſſe, I ſhould never have been thus ſurpris'd and deluded, and when you

have wrote to me in a dozen Letters at leaſt, that you knew ſome men that wrote pernicious Books, and maintain'd Hereticall Propoſitions
                  ▪ I did not yeeld to ſuch an imagination that this did reflect upon me; and when you ſent a Lackey into this Province, I did not forbeare to ſend you commendations by him. You ſee that I am ſtung, and therefore am ſenſible. If your love were not deare unto me, I could well-enough beare your neglect of me; and if my zeale to you were not ſtrong, I ſhould endeavour to ſolace my ſelfe, after your ill intreating of me. But becauſe I love, I would be requited with love; and I cannot brook to be taxt with a fault, which I thought did not deſerve ſo much as ſuſpition. Sir, I am upon the point to publiſh a

new Volume of Letters, where there be ſome which I have written unto you, and others, where I make mention of you, as your virtues did oblige me; and where will be one alſo, wherein (as ſome would perſwade you) I am injurious to you. How I pray, can all theſe agree? can I be both your friend and your foe at once? can I blow with the ſame mouth, both hot and cold? can the literall ſence favour you, and the allegoricall injure you? can I doe you wrong, when J muſt needs wrong my ſelfe? ſhall I give an occaſion of diſtaſt by ambiguous termes, where I muſt make my ſelfe ridiculous by apparent contradictions? This was it Sir, that was ſuggeſted to your credulity, and which you did not reject at firſt acquaintance, as J had

reaſon to expect from your good diſcretion. Theſe were the falſe ſurmiſes which were brought before you, wherein you found more ſemblance of truth, then in the ſincere proteſtations which J made to you. I cannot conceive (knowing that you have continued your friendſhip towards me, and that I too have not loſt my reaſon) how you could imagine, that I intended in a bravery to diſingage you, and by thoſe aukeward ſpirits which I had knowne, I aim'd directly at you, and might not deſigne ſome other as well. J know a great many of the Gaſcons, and as there be ſome of them very moderate, ſo alſo there be others that are not ſo. I know ſome of Provence and Corſica, and J am not ignorant of their naturall gentleneſſe; I know ſome Spaniards,
                  
and I know how agreeable is their Yoake with that which they call Caſtiga-vellacos.
               
               Laſtly you may believe that I have not travel'd blindfold, and I had in vaine converſed with men, if I had not endeavour'd to know them; and yet in this particular, men would faine make all my acquaintance to be terminated in you, and that I have pardoned a thouſand Humorists in the world (to whom my propoſition might be applied) for to violate you. They ſurmiſe, that having an aime to wound ſome body, I made choice of one of my chiefeſt friends for my marke; and that I have murmur'd cloſely and in darke language, that He is rough and violent, whom J proclaime every where, and with loud accent, ſo completely wiſe and noble.
                  
I will not cite unto you mean teſtimonies, for the confirmatiō of this truth. I can alleadge My Lord, the Duke of — and My Lord the Count of — of whom is here queſtion made. They know both of them, how farre J am your ſervant, and with what fervency J did maintaine your honour, and intereſts, on a time when occaſion was preſented. J am willing to believe that your other friends, might ſerve you in ſome ſteed in ſome other encounters, but in this here, all the whole company (J except no man) was mute. There was not any there, but my ſelfe that ſpake ſtrenuouſly in your behalfe, concerning thoſe things that did reflect upon you; and the boldneſſe of my affection carried me ſo farre, that the Lords, whom J now nam'd unto

you, did give me a publicke teſtimony, and profeſſed, (though with a litle diſguſt) that I was too good a friend to make a Courtier of I am therefore ſomething aggrieved at this time, to be requited thus with obloquie, where I thought I had deſerved thanks; to have preſerv'd my fidelity inviolable towards you, and now to be accuſed of treachery; to be the only man in your defence on that occaſion, whereof you have cauſe to boaſt, and now to be the onely man of whom you complaine. I doe not uſe to value my ſervices which I performe to my friendes, and I am content to ſtand up for them manfully, without making unto them an account of my proweſſe. Moreover Sir, this betraies griefe, more then preſumption, and may bee

term'd defending, rather then upbraiding; Theſe are reſentments which accompany innocence that is offended; and which your facility (abuſed by the malice of another) doth force from my heart againſt my will. I will not conceale it from you, you have made a deep wound in it, it makes me think in all my dreames of the injuſtice which I ſuffer at your hand, &amp; you had utterly loſt any friend, that had been leſſe firme then my ſelfe, by putting him to ſuch a hazard. Wherefore Sir, for all the revenge that I deſire for the injury which I have received, take it not amiſſe, that I give you this Advice, that you give leſſe credit hereafter to another, and more to your ſelfe; that you would be more jealous of thoſe opinions that you have conceived

upon your firſt acquaintance of a buſineſſe, and leſſe affected to the rumours of the Citty, which are not grounded upon any ſolid foundation. You ſhould conſider the place frō whence theſe quaint Newes have travelled; weigh the circumſtances of the thing, examin by what ſpirit the accuſer was led thereunto: and not examine His perſon onely, and paſsion, and intereſts, but alſo the deſervings of the party accuſed, his manner and behaviour of life, and his former actions: ſuſpend your judgement at leaſtwiſe, untill time ſhall give you a more exact and particular information of buſineſſes; otherwiſe you ſhall never want diſquiet &amp; vexation, and you ſhould thus but feed upon ſuſpicion and diſtruſt, which are very unwholſome viands. Men

muſt not ſend you relations of whatſoever an undiſcreet friend or ſome rude ſturdy ſervant, or ſuch and ſuch a neighbour ſhall report unto — they muſt have more care of the tranquillity of your minde; and likewiſe for your part, you muſt not ſweare unto the teſtimonies of all the Informers, that have a plot upon your credulity, and take pleaſure in the paine and exerciſe which they put you unto. If you allow an open gate for all tales and ſuggeſtions to enter in, they will throng into your houſe apace, and firſt come, firſt heard. To day, they will inform you (and perhaps with ſpecious colours too) that your Privado's doe divulge your ſecrets; &amp; to morrow that your Domeſticks doe rob and rifle you; and at laſt that all the

world is your enimy, &amp; all private conferences are but conſpiracies againſt you. I conjure you Sir, for your owne peace, not to give ſo much credit to thoſe things which doe no way concerne Religion, nor to abandon your ſelfe to thoſe Relators, who pretend to diſpell melancholly, when they are fit for nothing but to whiſper follies into your eares, and to calumniate with a good grace: make a diſtinction betwixt the fraudulent Arts of Paraſites and the freedome of ingenious men; betweene thoſe that adore Fortune, and thoſe that regard nothing but Vertue. For my part, I declare freely unto you that if Monſieur the — were rais'd againe, and would commit his omnipotency to your hands, I ſhould not doe that to regaine your favour.

what I doe now performe in regard of our friendſhip. At leaſtwiſe I ſhould be more ſtern &amp; ſtubborn (then I am) in my diſpleaſure, and more obſtinate in ſeeking to you, &amp; leſſe ſollicitous of the event of my ſeeking. But I have not yet the skill to complie with the times, and to be ſtill on Fortunes ſide; I profeſſe ſuch an austere honeſty &amp; goodnes that is not of the preſent times. I would take a pleaſure to be a companion of my friend in exile, and be his fellow-priſoner, I would runne under his Ruine to beare it off, whē I could not help him to ſtand faſt &amp; ſubſiſt. Your Fortune being ſo well eſtabliſhed as it is, doth not require any ſuch proofe and triall of fidelity. But it is certaine that you cannot deſire of me any experiments of love ſo hazardous, but I would willingly

undergoe them with pleaſure, for your ſake, and teſtifie unto you that I am (beyond compariſon) more then all my Informers
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
7. Iune 1633.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXXII. To Monſieur de Serizay.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               THere is no way to beare any longer with the contumacy of your ſilence. I have ſent this meſſenger of purpoſe to make you ſpeake, and to tell you (though with ſome diſtaſte to you) that you have loſt your memory; &amp; that is no leſſe then the third part of your ſoule. So

that there remaine but the Vnderſtanding &amp; the Will, wherein I have (perhaps) ſome nook &amp; ſeat. You have promiſed me wonders and perform'd juſt nothing; you did owe me a viſit immediatly after your voyage to Sainctes, and ſince that, you might have gone to Rome and come backe againe. You ſee here great cauſe of diſcontent; nevertheleſſe I am ſo facile, that if you would but bereave your ſelfe of the pleaſures of the Court for three or foure daies, I would ſeale you a generall Pardon for all that is paſt, &amp; account you as honeſt a man as ever I did before. While I expect this reaſonable ſatisfaction which you cannot deny me, be pleaſed to acquaint my Lord the Duke of Rochefoucaut that Monſieur de Nantes is extremely troubled, that he cannot

receive the honor which he would willingly pay him by comming to viſit him in theſe parts. He expects this morning ſome tidings from my Lord the Duke of Eſpernon for to render himſelfe where he ſhall appoint him to finde him; and I looke upon him as upō a bleſsing which I expect to looſe every moment. If he were not preparing to Maſſe he would ſignifie unto him his diſcontents himſelfe, and the earneſt deſire he hath to make his Sonne one of the Luminaries of our Church. He finds the buſineſſe ſo farre advanced, that there will be no great difficultie to effect the reſt, and that his Extraction is ſo happy, that a litle cultivation will produce rare &amp; excellent fruits. Doe me the favour as to deliver to Monſieur his eldeſt Sonne the Panegyricke fram'd for

the King of Sueden, together with the Letter which I wrote the laſt ſummer to poore —. This is not to recommend unto him the memory of her: I know that She is infinitely deare unto him: nor to put him into any affright; for men of his ſort doe apprehend nothing but diſhonour. I deſire onely that hee ſhould ſee that my poore judgement doth ſometimes jump with good underſtandings, and that J had the honour to be his Rivall in one paſsion that he hath harbour'd. If you doe not ſend me by my Man the Diſcourſe of — garniſhed with Notes and Commentaries, I ſhall have a new cauſe of quarrell; and doe not you thinke that I betake my ſelfe to Monſieur — for them, this is an Oracle (indeed) that is alwaies ready to anſwer, but

I feare me, that you have not alwaies devotion enough to conſult with him. Adieu Sir, I am abſolutely
               
                  Balzac:
30. May. 1633.
                  
                  Your &amp;c.
               
            
            
               LET. XXXIII. To Monſieur Habert, Abbat of Cerizy.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Beleeve that you will not be offended with a petition that this Bearer ſhall commence unto you in my behalfe. Your goodneſſe carrieth you ſo farre as to love your Perſecutors; and you have entertain'd ſo favourably my firſt importunities that I ſtand not now in

feare of making motions. If you had givē me the repulſe at firſt, you had taught me the Vertue of diſcretion, &amp; provided better for your own quietneſſe. But the force of example is dangerous: the evill doth ſuddainly inſinuate &amp; grow familiar, and treads oft that way, which it was wont to meaſure. So that I think that I have now ſome colour of juſtice to torment you; and it is habituall unto me to abuſe a thing, when I have not found difficulty enough to make me uſe it with moderation. I ſhall continue Sir, an importunate Begger till you forget to bee generous: and doe not doubt, but I knowe how to make uſe of a good ſo diffuſive, and beneficiall, as is your Amity. You ſhall travell to day for the good of my eſtate, becauſe there

is a Councell; and to morrow for the good of my ſoule, becauſe there is a Sermon; that I may acknowledge you my friend, for my ſpirituall as well as temporall good, and that you may receive my thanks, both in this and the other world. That which you are to pronounce with gracefulneſſe of Action, &amp; cannot well be communicated in writing, hath notwithſtanding already given me infinite delight upon paper. I have never ſeen our Mysteries illuſtrated with ſo much light of eloquence, nor Reaſon ſo ſucceſſefully imployed in the ſervice of Faith, nor Christian Morality better ſeaſon'd, to make it reliſh well in profane palates. But in this particular, J would faine be leſſe beholding to you, that J might have the more freedome, and be able to aſſure you

(without any ſuppoſition of engagement, or ſigne of acknowledgement) that I admire all your Muſes univerſally, both the politer and the ſeverer ones; both thoſe that can compoſe Hymnes and Anthems, and ſing the praiſes of our Saviour Chriſt: and thoſe that can reſolve Problems, and deale in Chriſtian learning. J bid you good day, and remaine with all my ſoule
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Paris
29. Apr. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXXIV. To Monſieur De GAILLARD.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               BE of good courage, and ſtart not at the opening of my packet; I doe aſſure you beforehand, that it is not my Ghoſt that talkes to you, &amp; that the Letter that I write unto you, doth not come from the other world. The rumor which was ſcattered concerning my death, hath not killed me; and I am yet, (ſince it is the pleaſure of God) a witneſſe of his works, and an Adorer of his power. I have ere this, received the alarme of the like newes; but J am no longer credulous to dreams and preſages; my ſoule doth not labour with thoſe popular infirmities: and I doe conſent

with that Grecian, that all the wiſhes of enimies, all the imprecations of Poets, and all the falſe bruits of Fame, are not able to bring on our destiny one houre the ſooner. There is a Gentleman in Gaſcogne, who is Chronicled to have been ſlaine in the Battle of Yury; &amp; he is yet very well notwithſtanding, and means to live long. J am Sir, of the ſame humor too, and confeſſe to you, that J doe not much hate my life, though J have litle cauſe to love it. Your Stationers indeed, did not beleeve this: they have handled me as though I had been dead indeed, and have imagined withall, that they be my rightfull Heyres ex aſſe, having ſeiz'd upon the firſt papers of mine that they could meet with. J am ſomething apprehenſive of this injury,

and it ſhould grieve me if Monſieur — ſhould be the Author of it; becauſe J ſhould then endure it with more impatience yet. To ſay truth, if this be not to wound &amp; violate (downeright) the law of Nations, it is (at leaſt) to deflowre and taint it: and you will confeſſe with mee, that it could not bee pleaſing unto me, that the — ſhould be publiſht without asking my conſent thereunto. Had it been ſo, J ſhould not have been (perhaps) very averſe, and J ſhould have deſired him only to alter ſomething for my ſake, and ſomething for his owne. For though his underſtanding be paſsing good, yet you know well, that our Grammarians doe not allow his ſtile for regular; and though their ſcruples be ill grounded, yet they muſt be conſidered.

That which I would faine have changed, and where I thought I had ſome ſmall intereſt, was one word, which my ancient Enimy had already miſerably mangled; and which, (not wanting ſpirit and life in its naturall place) doth reſemble thoſe delicate plants, which dye as ſoone as they be tranſplanted from their own banks. But remedies come now too tardy. J muſt comfort my ſelfe againſt this, as well as other injuries. This is but dallying to former wrongs; and ſuch pinches ſhould well be borne with, by a man that never uſeth to complaine of Treaſons and Aſſaſsinates. For your ſatisfaction Sir, let it ſuffice that I have a perfect knowledge of your wiſdome and Honeſty, and that I would truſt you with my life, my honour, and my

fortunes. If J had had ſo baſe a thought as to ſuſpect you in this dealing, J ſhould believe that J were bound to doe penance for my ſuſpition. J know that you are every way virtuous, and my firme friend, as I am very really
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
10. Jan. 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXXV. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Have received your incomparable Book: in the which (after a long and tedious peruſall) my Grammer could finde no conſtruction,

nor my Logick common ſence. This is not the firſt time that that poore Wit hath ſtrayed ſo. He hath been, this long time ridiculous without being facetious, and hath been a laughing-ſtock to the vulgar, and an object of pitty to the wiſe. The late Monſieur — did uſe to call him the greateſt enimy that ever Reaſon had, betweene Cales and Bayonne; and ſaid, he was a foole in two ſciences, and in foure languages. Nevertheleſſe if our friend ſhall think him worthy of ſome traces of his pen, let us indulge him that exerciſe, with this proviſo, that he be not violent, and that he put not himſelfe to a heat; that (if it pleaſe him) he doe not deal ſeriouſly with him, or arme himſelfe at all points, againſt an Adverſary that deſerves not any encounter

but with pinnes. As for the — you wrong your ſelfe, for to miſtruſt the moderation of my ſpirit. Jn the eſtate that J have ordered and ſetled it in, I have leſſe paſsion then the King of the Stoicks; and J muſt be excited for eight daies togither, to the cruelty of hateing any man whatſoever, for one halfe an houre. It is not my intention to write againſt Monſieur — but to diſcourſe with him; and I have not ſo litle wit, but that J can diſtinguiſh his perſon from his cauſe. He hath obliged me with ſo good grade, and ſpoken of me in ſuch high language &amp; ſumptuous termes, that I cannot doubt of his reſpect, or his affection towards me. And he ſhall likewiſe ſee my reſentment of it, through the whole file of my Diſcourſe; wherein I am reſolved

to temper my ſelfe ſo diſcreetly, that if I perſwade him not to my opinion, I ſhall not make my proceedings odious; and if I doe not reſt ſatisfied with what he ſaith, I ſhall contradict him but obliquely, and with a kind of Biaſſe, which ſhall not be diſtaſtfull unto him. This will be (perhaps) the firſt example of modeſty, that hath been heard of among the Diſputants of this age; and we will demonſtrate to thoſe of that ſide, who talke outragiouſly in Problems of ſmall importance; that the altercations of honeſt men are without choler, and that generous enemies live better togither then malicious Burghers. For the reſt Sir, I deſire you to continue the paines that you have begun, &amp; to ſend me wherewith J may fortify all the Approaches
                  
that are liable to aſſault and battery. I ſhall feare nothing being ſtrengthned with ſo powerfull ſuccors; and you will juſtify my cauſe if it be good, or give it a colour of juſtice, if it be not ſo. See what an enterpriſe it was in you to love me: You could never have conceived a more pernicious deſigne for your ſelfe. It will repent you more then once, and you will renounce at any time (I am ſure) the ſorry purchaſe which you have made in the acquaintance of a troubleſome man. Nevertheleſſe he is one that is moſt affectionately
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
20. March. 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XXXVI. To Madam DESLOGES.
               
               
                  Madam,
               
               IT is now three Months that I have expected Monſieur d' Auvila, that I might be informed of the ſtate of your health: But haveing lately underſtood that it is not ſo currant as I could wiſh it, and mine being not ſo firme, that J could adventure upon a journey, J have diſpatched one towards you to learne the truth thereof. It will be an incredible eaſe to my mind, if I finde that it was but a falſe alarme, or that your ſickneſſe by this time be over-paſt. J doe hope for one of the two (Madame,) becauſe J doe paſsionatly deſire it; but J beſeech you to beleeve that it is long

of my crazie body that J am no ſooner clear'd of my feare, and rid of the paine it put me to; and that you doe not ſee me in perſon in ſteed of the Meſſenger that I have ſent. He hath in charge to preſente you with my fine Cuts or ſmall Ingravery, which J have newly received from Paris; J thought meet to ſend you this dumbe viſit that it might not oblige you to any compliment that might put you to trouble; you doe receive (indeed) more troubleſome ones, ſometimes; And if the ſullenneſſe of my countenance, be an object of bad preſage, you will confeſſe that the perpetuall ſilence that doth accompany it, is a great commodity: at leaſtwiſe it can never be offenſive to you, ſince it leaves you ſtill at quiet, and demanding no ceremony

from you, it muſt perplexe you leſſe then the Antiquities and Originals of La Marche, and Limouſin. Finally Madame, it lyeth in you to preſerve your bounties for me▪ and maintaine me in my poſſeſsion. I know that Monſieur d' Aillé is of infinite value, and I believe I cannot looſe him, ſince it was you that gave him me; you have too good a hand to doe any thing that ſhould not laſt, and there is no accident that can menace and ſhake that friendſhip, whereof virtue is the cauſe, and you the Mediatrix. I eſteeme that of this rare Perſonage as a treaſure, and J would be well pleaſed that he ſhould know by your means, that J admire the Eloquence of his Dogmaticall &amp; peaceable Divinity, though J doe not ſubſcribe unto the Doctrine of his

                  polemicall writings. J moſt humbly kiſſe your hand, and remaine
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
16. Ian. 1637.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXXVII. To Monſieur de —
               
                  Sir,
               
               TAke pitty on a man that hath not the leaſure to live, that is alwaies buſy and alwaies ſickly, whom a thouſand griefes ſeize upon in his chamber, and a thouſand perſecutions throng upon, from without. Monſieur de — knowes it well that I am no diſſembler, and will teſtify unto you

(I aſſure my ſelfe) that in the ſtate that I am in, I can but admire thoſe letters, to the which I ſhould frame an anſwere. I avow unto you Sir, that it coſt me ſome paines to decipher them: But yet I doe not complaine of my travell, which found moſt happy ſucceſſe. J have diſcovered infinite rarities under the riddles of your Scribe, and I did not miſtake the Graces, though He had begrimed them all over. I ſend them back to you, ſince it is your requeſt▪ and yet notwithſtanding I ceaſe not to deteine them; my memory is not ſo unfaithfull, but it preſerves the better part of your faire compoſitions, as well as of your excellent converſation. It is certaine that this gave me ſome guſts and appetites, which I never had, before you came hither. I am not

good, Sir, but by your goodneſſe, &amp; if I have any degree of holy heate in me, it is neither proper nor naturall unto me, J have it from your communication. You are at this day one of thoſe Authors whom I cite ſtill with a grace and an Emphaſis: I doe arme my ſelfe with your reaſons againſt the enimies of Truth, &amp; you are all my French Divinity. What a harveſt might be reapt (think you) of devout meditations, and Spirituall Treatiſes from leſſe ſeed thē are your Diſcourſes and Letters? A man might extract from them more ſapp and juice then from many Quadrageſimall Sermons of Spaniſh Postillers; and were they but a litle amplified, they might ſerve for compleat Apologies of Chriſtian doctrine, and ſolid refutations of unſound Philoſophie. Your acquaintance

then, is no ſmall purchaſe, &amp; J owe you more thē vulgar thanks for it. But ſince you deſire none other but my edification: inſteed of minting faſtidious complements for you, J will labour to put your wholſome counſailes in practiſe. J will become a good man if J can, that you may be celebrated in my works, being not contented with words. The curing of a diſeaſe doth ſufficiently proclaime the ſoveraignty of the remedy; and it is a farre better way to magnifie your ſtile by performing actions of vertue, which it doth propoſe as its end, then to cry out Euge at every period. There is no hopes to goe beyond this. Remember me if you pleaſe in your Sacrifices, that is, love me effectually, after your way, ſince

J am after mine, and that very ſincerely
               
                  Sir,
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
30. Decemb. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXXVIII. To Monſieur Girard, Officiall of the Church of Angouleſme.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOur favours have exhauſted my thanks. I cannot chooſe but acquaint you that I doe repoſſeſſe my old pieces againe, and that your Love is ſtill ingenious in obliging thoſe whom you affect. I doubt not but that that Courteſies that I have received from Monſieur de — are the effects of your teſtimonies

of me; &amp; I muſt aſcribe all the contentment that I have received thereby to your preparation and induction. There is no ſubject ſo vile and meane but gaines price by your eſtimatiō. You have found the trick or ſecret to make objects ſwell beyond their proportion ad infinitum; and to ſtampe a man Illuſtrious, though of a very abject cō
                  dition. I came to know him by the civilities of —, which are farre different from the bravado's of —. Are not theſe the moſt tyrannicall Spirits in the world? that ſhould ſay that I could hinder, that any Bookes ſhould bee written or publiſhed, at a hundred leagues diſtance? that is, that I ſhould maintaine an Agent in all the Printing-houſes of France, that ſhould prevent the publication of Antiphilarkes.
                  
Theſe Meſsieurs that have handled me in ſuch a ſort, that fire and poiſon would ſeeme to an Italian too gentle tortures to revenge their cruelty, are, at this time, offended (forſooth) that I ſhould be furniſhed with ſo much as a buckler, and that I ſhould be offred a Sanctuary. They demand a reaſon of me why a man, whom I never knew, ſhould take compaſsion on Innocence oppreſt, &amp; could not endure the noiſe &amp; inſolence of their falſe triumphs. which J ſhould not doe neither, deare Friend, if I would give vent &amp; liberty to my griefe, &amp; that Nature ſuffer'd not in the ſuppreſsion of ſo juſt complaint. And yet J muſt continue to doe her violence &amp; deſerve the approbatiō of Monſieur our Prelate. J beg from you his good favours, and deſire you both to believe

that J am affectionately
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
20. March 1633.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XXXIX. To the ſame: —
               
                  Sir,
               
               IT is not your Will that I ſollicite, but your Memory. For amidſt the preſſe of buſineſſe of the whole Province, which you doe willingly take the charge of, mine happily may ſlip out of your memory without your fault. The importance is, to commence it with an opinion that it is feaſible, and with a reſolution to carry it; for if reaſon be urged timorouſly, and if a man doe

not deſcend ſtreight from generalities to particulars, a thouſand journeies unto the — will not bee worth one; and we ſhould but take much paines to litle purpoſe. Monſieur de — ſhall pardon me, if J doe not find my ſelfe either hardy, or ſtrong enough to undertake the worke which he hath done mee the honour to deſigne me for; and for ſuch a taske, a more peaceable and happy retreate, and a more practis'd and expert quill then mine, are requiſite. J have uſed my hand and minde to write but toyes, &amp; things un-neceſſary. For the future, I purpoſe not to write any workes of ſupererogation, but what the Church preſcribes, and God doth reckon as meritorious. I am extremely troubled at my Couſins miſchance, and the burning of his Study. Hee cannot

chooſe but be very ſenſible of this loſſe▪ ſince it was the chiefeſt part of his wealth, and thereby ſaw the Iſſues of his brain periſh before his face, without being able to redreſſe it. This muſt be his comfort, that he is young and laborious, &amp; that Fortune cannot raviſh from him thoſe true goods which he is Maſter of. The loſſe of a veſſell is not valued, if the Pilot be ſaved; and Captaines have been ſeene to triumph after the loſſe of many Armies. Miſer &amp; nudus Imperator invenit exercitum
                  ▪ Our Advocate is more cruell then the Warre, &amp; more ſevere then Iuſtice: He hath ſlaine in his Letters my Lord the Marſhall of — &amp; my Lord the Duke of —, who are yet alive to pardon him. Tell him (if you pleaſe) that he doe not trafficke any more in ſuch newes,

for he will be reckoned among the fabulous Authors elſe, and men will taxe mee for bad intelligence. I know well that he is not ſurety for the newes that flyes abroad, but he is anſwerable for the aſſeveration wherewith he doth recommende them unto me; and hee muſt talke of ſomething that is not knowne, or at leaſtwiſe with the cautious forme of the Poets, when they ſay, ut fama eſt, ut perhibent, ſi credere dignum eſt. I bid you good even, and remaine perfectly
               
                  Sir
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
4. Feb. 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XL. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOur friend doth not well to take the Alarme, ſince it is not J that gave it him. I was never uſed to promiſe but with an intention to performe; &amp; thoſe that have ſoveraigne power over me, have not power enough to make me falſify my word. As for thoſe idle Cō
                  templators that talke according to their fancy, concerning the occaſion of my Voyage; I doe not think it any part of their office to render an account of my actions; I ever thought that the liberty of going &amp; comming was tolerated as lawfull in this Kingdome; and when a man departed out of Paris, he was not

bound to publiſh a Manifeſto, to make it knowne to all the world. It is not without reaſon that Monſieur de Silhon doth much eſteeme the eloquence of Maffaeus. The late Monſieur Scaliger, who was none of the beſt friends the Jeſuits had, did ſo before him; and ſee here one trace of his pen concerning it, in one of his Letters. Maffaeus ille quiſquis est vir eloquentiſsimus eſt, ambitioſae tamen magis quàm caſtigatae facundiae. Hee commends him (you ſee) though not without exception, yet in my judgment without envy; ſince in this particular the moſt Intelligent of the Society concur with him in the ſame opinion, &amp; namely the Hiſtoriographer of the Low-countrey-warres, who in his Dialogues, ſpeaks of him thus; though it be in the perſon of another: Miratus
                  
                  ſum florem &amp; numeros Orationis. Dixi Scriptorem mihi videri non huius aevi, ſed è veteri illo Ordine &amp; quidem Patricio Hiſtoricorum. Nihil uſpiam incultum neglectum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     ; concinna perfecta
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      omnia; niſi fortè eo peccat, quòd nihil peccat, nam &amp; ingenium Scriptoris anxium apparet interdum, &amp; dictio videtur exquiſita adſonum, eum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ſimili modulatione crebrò fuſum. Quare monui ut orationis culturam ſaepius libentiuſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      diſsimularet, nec verba ita trajiceret quaſi complementa numerorum. I am yet in the ſame ſtate, that you left me in at parting, but that I have ſtill the ſame malady though not the ſame conſolation. My Ague viſits me every night, though (indeed) not in the ſame pompe and ceremonie as it uſed, when its acceſſes were regular. But yet, it doth ſtill handle me rudely,

and J doe much feare the conſequence of this cuſtome. Come Sir, and exorciſe this evill ſpirit out of my body, by the infuſion of ſome mirth into my minde, &amp; think not that I can receive any true joy, being ſo farre diſtant from you. I am
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
7. Apr. 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XLI. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               SInce it is impoſsible to withſtand it, I have ſent you the Letter, that you deſired to ſee. But you ſhall read it (if you pleaſe) to your own eares only, that it may not awake Envie. And that ſome Philarchus
                  
doe not over-heare you. Loe here withall, the three lines of Cardinall Bentivolio's Letter, which you did ſo often demand of me, and which J can no longer deny you without incivility. Di nuovo prego V. Sria 
                  a 'ringratiar, &amp;c. I doe againe intreat you to thanke Monſieur Balzac in my name, and by the ſame opportunitie to make him an ample teſtimonie of my great affection towards his deſerts; &amp; tell him this withall, that no pen doth more diſcourage me then his, for J ſee too well how farre it doth ſurpaſſe mine. I muſt confeſſe that in this particular, to doe mee grace he hath been unjuſt to himſelfe, and that the ſame motion of humility that prompts Princes of his ranke and parentage to waſh poore mens feet, hath moved him to uſe me ſo reſpectfully▪ Neither

doe J pretend to take a pride in it; but yet I think, it will not be denied, but that I may derive ſome comfort from it. And (indeed) it ſeemes that the goodneſſe of this brave Worthy, would needs make me amends for the malice of my Adverſaries. Theſe few lines doe weigh downe the ſwelling Volumes of my Opponents, and I ſhall uſe no other refutation of all that hath, or ſhall be written againſt me. For the preſent Sir, I am not of that man's opinion who cenſures that paſſage, La noire mere des eſtoiles; the Poet that ſo ſtiles the Night, is not ſo bold &amp; raſh as the Grammarian ſuppoſeth, that reprehends him. And if this be as he ſaith, a A Dialect ſpoken in Gaſcoigne different from the French and of neer affinity with the Baskiſh lā
                     guage which is ſpoken in Biſcay.
                   
                  Gaſconiſme, Tibullus was a Gaſcon when he ſaid,

                     Ludite, jam Nox jungit equos: currum
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         ſequuntur
                     
                        Matris laſcivo ſydera fulvachoro.
                  
The Night there is mother of the ſtarres; as in another Poet the Nurſe of them.
                  
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        .
                     Nox, aureorum furva nutrix ſyderum.
                  
Our Man writes to me oft enough, but he puts me to hereafter in all his Letters; &amp; doth ever promiſe what he never performes. Nevertheleſſe I doe believe, that Hee will certifie me by the firſt Poſte touching the event of that buſines which makes you ſo anxious, and I will not fayle to impart unto you the newes, as ſoone as ever the Carrier bringeth them. I am
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac:
20. Iuly. 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XLII. To Madamoiſell de CAMPAGNOLE.
               
                  My deare Niece,
               
               YOu did not well, that you did not keepe that floury Chaplet, which J had the favour to receive from your Lackey; the winter would not have budded but for you, and by conſequence you ſhould have better valued this favour, and managed your Roſes more ſparingly. They ſhould have been beſtowed about your temples, for an honour to its pregnancy, and not have been beſtowed on an Hermit: for this were to hide a miracle. J ſee well your drift herein, you would needs be liberall in a time of ſcarcity; and looſe your

owne right, that you might pleaſe my paſsion with ſomething; which is ſo much affected with true and lively floures: Which J doe terme ſo, becauſe the other, which men doe ſo much eſteeme, having not any odour which animates, are in my judgement but faire pictures, or ſpecious carkaſſes. But J beſeech you to reſolve me one ſcruple that doth trouble me; and eaſe me of my perplexity. Tell me, was this becauſe there be ſome already, or becauſe there be ſome yet left? are theſe remainders, or fore-runners? was it the last ſpring that was tardy, or the new that is haſty and forward? loe here a Problem worthy to be diſcuſſed by the Philoſophers of your Sexe, and it would not be amiſſe to propoſe it to Her whom you ſpeak of, for to have her reſolution.

I profeſſe, that if ſhe be very expert, ſhe is a very diſſembler, for I could never diſcover her to this houre. Shee hath ſuch a heavy dull apprehenſion, that a man had need interpret twice or thrice over what ever he ſpeaks to her. It were eaſier to converſe with a deafe woman, and I would chooſe rather to make my ſelfe underſtood by a Cornet, then to be my own Interpreter. Yet if this ſtupidity be without malice, it is more tolerable then malicious cunning God permits himſelfe to be intreated, (ſometimes) by a ſimple thumping of the breaſt, and often rejects eloquent and loud prayers. It is a miſerable light, that, whoſe glory and luſter flowes from vice only, and yet is not offenſive to great men. A good Beaſt is of more worth thē a bad Angell.
                  
This is the upſhot of all (my deare Niece) that you muſt lay a foundation of Bounty, upon which it is allowed you to raiſe a Structure of other virtues, that are more high, and more glorious. You did not ſtand in need of this leſſon, but I would needs fill up my paper, before I would put a period, and tell you that J am
               
                  Balzac.
15. Dec. 1637.
                  
                  Your &amp;c.
               
            
            
               LET. XLIII. To Monſieur the Abbat of Bois-Robert.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               THe world is full of darſtardly friends, but you are none of

                  this world. You can love dareingly and reſolutely; and J ſee that my injuries are (commonly) more apprehended by you, then by my ſelfe; nevertheleſſe I am much vexed with the language which you received from Meſsieurs the — Theſe are men, that doe underſtand too well the points of honour, for to give me any ſatisfaction; and for my part, I carry ſo much goodneſſe about me, as to demand nothing from them but my life. J never beleev'd that their Superior had promiſed me nothing. Jf he hath left them no other debts to pay but this, they have great cauſe to commend him for his good providence and thrift. Jn the mean while, J cannot diſſemble my ſorrow to you for his death, nor forget to tell you, that in all his ill carriages towards

me, he hath never done me a greater affront then this, to dye. If J had had ſome particular Revelation concerning it, or if he had advertiſed me thereof by the Spirit of Prophecy, which is ſpoken of in his Elogy, he ſhould have ſeen his prating long ſince condemned, and ſhould not have carried away into the other world, that great opinion of ſufficiency, which his Fraternity did ſooth him with. For the other extravagant Doctor, which you mention, it would not be acceptable to God almighty, that J ſhould undertake his reformation; it were needfull to create him anew, for to amend him▪ Jt were no mean enterpriſe but to examine his book, and to make a breviary of all the abſurd things therein contained. J would chooſe as ſoone to be condemned

to be a Scavenger for the ſtreets of Paris, and to carry away all the dirt out of that litle world. His impertinencies are infinite, and would puzzle a better Arithmetician then I am to calculate them, and he that would goe about to count them,

                     Conterâ ancora in ſùl'ombroſo doſſo &amp;c.
                     Will count the Trees on top of ſhady Appennine
                     
                     Aſſoone: or waves, when windes doe chafe the curling Brine.
                     
                  
               
               Jf this Bearer ſhall ſtand in need of recommendation to the Councell, J doubt not, but knowing his name, and what a ſhare J beare in his intereſts, you will effectually asſiſt him for love of me, who am more

then any man in the world;
               
                  Sir,
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
30. Ian. 1629.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XLIV. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Am (ever this Month) confin'd to my bed, where I received your Letter directed from Roan. To read there the continuation of your ſickneſſe, could not (you muſt think) be any aſſuagement of mine. J beſtow a thouſand curſes upon the waters of Fórges, for impairing your health. Propertius hath not been more liberall, or beſtowed

more upon the Baiae that kill'd Augustus his Nephew. But a maine difference is, that this man was a Poet, and did but act griefe: but I am truly afflicted; and true friendſhip doth really ſuffer more, then flattery can perſonate. J am very ſorry that — hath not demean'd himſelfe towards you ſo well as he ſhould have done; and if you have reſolv'd upon his ruine, I doe not mean to ſtep in between him and it, and undertake his protection. I doe ever ſide with all your paſsions without premeditation; and that man that doth not pleaſe you, hath no allurements ſo powerfull, as can render him pleaſing to me: nevertheleſſe if this mans offence were veniall, and your juſtice could be ſatisfied; J would adventure to beg his pardon, and would

become his ſurety, that he ſhould willingly undergoe all the puniſhments that you would inflict upon him, to regaine your favour. There are ſome buſineſſes betweene us, that force me to diſſemble a litle, and doe not permit an apparent rupture, if there come not from you an expreſſe order to the contrary. But being once freed out of this turmoile, if he be ſo unlucky as to offend you againe, I declare unto you that I doe even now renounce him; and J had rather forget my obligations to him, then to carry affections repugnant to yours. Your Couſen is too generous to oblige (ſo nobly) a man whom he never knew; and J had rather beleeve, that his eſteeme of me, is but the conſequence of your love, then to imagine it to be an apprehenſion of any

merit in mee. J doe purpoſe a voyage beyond the ſeas the next year; If J take ſhip at Diepe, as J hope to doe, J ſhall not faile to goe and kiſſe His hands at Röan; &amp; to make him ſee that the Monſter, that Father Goulu ſpeaks of, is a tame Beaſt, (at leaſt) and capable of knowledge. If J did exceedingly rejoyce at the newes, when a Canonſhip was beſtowed upon you, J forgot how farre this Dignity was below your deſerts. It ſufficeth me, that I give you ſome teſtimony that I am not ſorry for it; and that J conſider it (as in the croude) among other Benefices that ſhall fall upon you; knowing that ſome few mens lives (that be not yet dead) are the onely obſtacles to your Virtues. J expect by the firſt Poſt, ſome better

newes concerning your health, and ever remaine with all my ſoule
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
10. May 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XLV. To the ſame.
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOur laſt meſſage did give me exceeding content, &amp; though I am well aſſured of your affection towards me, yet I take a ſingular delight to read in your Letters that you love me. Theſe be words, whoſe fragrancy time cannot weare away; and which will

be as pleaſant to me many years hence▪ as when they were firſt ſpoken. I am (indeed) raviſhed with your laſt proteſtations: But I rejoyce with you the rather, for the felicity of this new age, ſince you are in part the cauſe of it, and that by your ſuggeſtions, Monſieur — doth purpoſe to allot a conſiderable Tenement of lands for the releefe of poore and diſconſolate Muſes. We ſhall ſee this year Sonnets, and Odes, and Elegies enough. The Almanack doth promiſe wonderfull plenty, and Parnaſſus muſt not yeeld leſſe then it did under the Pontificate of Leo the Tenth. For you Sir, if you believe me, you ſhall never take pen in hand againe, but in caſe of neceſsity, and only that commerce may not decay. Hitherto you have been a Horace, now you are a Mecenas;

and if we doe not celebrate you (every Scribler of us) and addreſſe our Works, both in proſe and verſe to you, you have juſt cauſe to indict us of ingratitude. For my part, I would willingly both live and dye under your patronage; and I doe provide an Oration for you in genere demonſtrativo; wherein (at firſt ſalute) J ſhall aſtoniſh the world with this great prodigy. That you are both a complete Courtier, and a perfect Friend. Since you would abſolutely have it ſo, that J come to Paris, it is to you, that J ſhall make my moſt frequent reſorts to doe my reſpects; and it is in your Cabinet that I ſhall (by your good leave) redeeme the time, which J have loſt in the Country, but we muſt give place (a while) to the anger of ſtormeing Iove; or to

ſpeak the language of men, we muſt permit it to raine and freeze in Beauſſe; and not goe to out-brave the month of February. J have no great need to dye out of too much dareing. My health is ſtill very infirme and unconſtant; and if J did not take incredible care, (I ſay not to preſerve my perſon, but only to continue my ſleepes) you had loſt me a great while ſince. Since J am wholly yours, you will allow me the uſe of this word, and take it not ill, that J reckon my ſelfe in the number of thoſe things, that are not to you indifferent. You have infinitely obliged me in aſſuring Monſieur the Count of — of the continuance of my zeale and fidelity. J have made him ſo eminent and publike a marke, that as J can never recant it, ſo can he never ſuſpect it.

I omit a thouſand things that I ſhould tell you of: but this will be imploiment for the next weeke: and I am forced to conclude that I am
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
10. Feb. 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. XLVI. To Monſieur de Savignac.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               EIther I have not well interpreted my ſelfe or Monſieur de — hath not well underſtood me. I doe ever value the merits of Madame d' Anguitar, and if it muſt be, that I muſt (by a ſecond act) cō
                  firme

                  that teſtimonie which I have given of Her, I am ready to declare my ſelfe a new, and to commende once more a Lady that is ſo praiſe-worthy. It is true, that for the intereſt of her Honour, it will be ſome thing materiall, to underſtand the cauſe that made my intentions to be miſ-conſtrued, and that I leade you to the very ſource of this jealouſie; Whereas, it ſeem'd to certaine Cavaliers, my friends, that I did too much approve of her ſingular humour, and frequent retirings, one of the moſt eloquent of them took a fancy to publiſh his diſlike in this point; and to write a reproachfull Letter unto me in the name (as he ſaith) of the whole Corporation of Honeſt men. Wherein he proclaimes open warre againſt me in their name, as though I had

conſpir'd againſt faire Society; and calls me the Common enemy; the univerſally jealous mā, the Tyrant to both ſexes. He doth imagine that it is my intent to ſhut up in Priſon all faire and delectable things, for to puniſh curious eyes. He cryes out, that I would faine abrogate the ſweeteſt lawes of this Realme, and bring in the cruelty of that cuſtome in Spaine, where honeſt women are mewd up in cages, and honeſt men adore but doores and windowes. From Madrid, he paſſeth to Conſtantinople, and tells me in a great rage, that I am good nothing but to be a Counſeller of the great Turk, for to adviſe him to raiſe the walls of the Seraglio higher, &amp; to double the Guard of the Sultana; Then he doth accuſe me for a thouſand miſchiefs and takes me for Him that invented

the iron grates, the locks, the vailes &amp; maskes: &amp; for the Author of all thoſe things that oppoſe his intruſion &amp; ſaucy curioſity. Inſomuch that he imagines that I muſt render him a reaſon of the ſecrets and difficulties of all riddles, of the darkneſſe of all ancient Oracles; of the Allegories of Poets; and of the Myſteries of all Religions. To make anſwer to farre leſſe then this, it behooved me to ſtudy a long Apologie; &amp; (as ill luck was) when I received his Letter, I was not in the humour of making Books. Wherefore Sir, I profeſſe to you truly, I choſe rather to yeeld thē defend my ſelfe; and abandon my Maxims to the verboſity of my good friend, rather then maintaine them with the expence of ſo many words as he did plye them with: But if I be not deceaved, there is a good

deale of difference betweene my Maximes &amp; the praiſes of Madame d' Anguitar; and he muſt take heed of confounding in the deſigne that I have, that which I diſtinguiſh'd in the See this Letter in the ſupply to the ſecond part of his Letters. Let. XVIII
                   Letter which I wrote unto Her. To ſay that She is one of the Perfections of the world, is an immoveable truth, for which I would fight all my life time: But to ſay that ſuch Perfections muſt be ſequeſtred from the eyes of men, is (I ſuppoſe) a problematicall opinion, which I may revoke without prejudice to my own conſtancy, or to the worth of theſe Perfections. But on the contrary, moſt will bee apt to believe, that this will be ſufficient amends, and juſt ſatisfaction for the injury I did them, in condemning them to Solitude and Retiredneſſe; &amp; will call it their revoking

from exile, and releaſing out of bondage. Thus Sir, I preſerve ſtill my firſt Deſigne; and my commendations remaine whole and intire among the ruines of my Maximes. Nay out of their demolitions, Trophies might be erected to the honour of Madame d' Anguitar, and a Theater built, where Shee might be gazed upon, by thoſe that can but divine and gueſſe at Her; and that the Deſart might no longer have ſuch advantage over the Citty. This is not then to rebell againſt her Vertues, but to wiſh Her a more ſpacious Empire, and a greater number of Subjects then She hath had; nor to goe about to eclipſe her light, but to adjudge, that Shee ſhould iſſue forth out of the cloudes, for the benefit and comfort of the 
                     Ʋniverſe. I pitty thoſe Criticks that take it otherwiſe;

and am ſorry that Monſieur — is fallen upō a thought ſo far diſtant from mine. He might have underſtood me well enough, without putting me to the paines of interpreting my ſelfe; and might have ſeen (moreover) that though in this occaſion I would not at all conſider the intereſts of another, yet I ſhould have conſidered my owne at leaſt. Doth he imagine that I could have been perſwaded to ſpoile at one daſh, one of the deareſt Iſſues of my Braine? and to bereave my ſelfe of the acknowledgements of one of the greateſt Perſonages of the world, who thinks Herſelfe in ſome meaſure beholding unto me? I am no ſuch Enemy to my ſelfe, or ſo prodigall of the good that I have acquir'd. I doe not mean to throwe dirt upon that piece, where I have

beſtowed ſo many and ſo rich Colours; and believe not you, that I would have razed out (being thereunto intreated by none) thoſe words that did no way diſlike me; you that know how Heliodorus denied to doe the like, though earneſtly ſollicited thereunto, by a whole Councell. If you doe me the honour as to make a journey to morrow to Balzac, I will tell you more; though negociating with an underſtanding ſo ſerene as yours, I think I have ſpoken enough already concerning it. This is
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
26. March 1637.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XLVII. To Monſieur Chapelain.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Am newly out of a fit of an Ague; and though the ſhaking &amp; toſsing be paſt, yet it is not yet calme. My head is ſo numb'd, and deafned with yeſter-daies tempeſt, that I am for no reaſonable uſe; and in the eſtate that J am, I am not fit for any Society. Nevertheleſſe there is no way to put off ſo juſt an office as this to another time, and (though with hazard of incongruities, and offending againſt Grammer rules) you muſt receive from me theſe three or foure ragged lines. You have obligations upon me, both new &amp; old, which cannot by me be ſufficiently acknowledged. I am aſham'd to be

beloved ſo much and deſerve it ſo litle; and if you be not contented with an honeſt Heart, I can offer you nothing worthy ſo noble and pure affection as yours. The laſt Letter which you did me the honour to write unto me, hath given proofe thereof beyond all queſtion; and J have kiſt each line thereof as ſo many traces or footſteps of the golden Age, and ſo many pictures of the ſincerity of the old World. Your coū
                  ſells are moſt wiſe and loyall, and I would moſt punctually render them obedience, if J were in caſe to doe it. But beſides that it is impoſsible to appeaſe and conjure downe Envy, &amp; that I am too weake to grapple with it: Phyſitians doe prohibite all ſtudy and labour of the ſpirits; and tell me, that I cannot meditate one halfe an houre, without

running the hazard of never meditating more. So that Sir, it is more expedient that my cauſe ſhould periſh then J; and that I ſhould be beaten at Paris in my abſence, then that I ſhould die here in perſon. You will (no doubt) be of my opinion, and ſince the occaſion (which is preſented) of dying, is none of the moſt glorious: you will not take it amiſſe if I make ſome more uſe yet of my life, to be
               
                  Sir,
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
30. Ian. 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XLVIII. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOU doe wrong to that Paſsion or regard which I beare towards you, to call it Civility. It deſerves a better name then that; and we are not acquainted in the countrey with thoſe vertues, countenance and Shew. I deale very ſeriouſly with my friends, and I ſpeak nothing but what I meane to make good; &amp; by the principles of ancient Philoſophy, I doe think that a Complement doth as much oblige me as a Contract. Think not then that I deale with you out of Common places: they are the true motions of my ſoule, which I ſhew you, and if I

could exhibite my very ſoule, you would confeſſe, that the expreſsions of my tongue are farre inferiour to the Idea by the which they were fram'd. It is you alone Sir, that can content thoſe that demand ſatisfaction, and make my intereſts even what pleaſe you. J have neither liberty nor election when J ſee the bent of your deſire. Teare, burne, ſcatter the aſhes of my Books in the wind; I doe ſubmit them to all the rigour of your juſtice; Tibi in me, mea
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      aeterna authoritas eſto. You are no more my Counſellour but my Soveraigne, and by conſequence, deale not with me by Arguments &amp; Remonſtrances, but impoſe Laws upon me and preſcribe Commands. You ſhall never finde a more docile and ſupple nature then mine, no not if you went to ſeek in Aſia, that

countrey of perfect Slaves. Nevertheleſſe, I think that my Humility will not take off the edge of perſecution, but on the contrary, it will make my Adverſaries to ſwell and grow inſolent: But I have comforts ready at hand againſt all the ill fortunes which I expect. In this, I deſire onely the glory of obeying you. It is enough for me that I have ſhewed that friend-ſhip can doe more with me, then Tyranny, and I would acknowledge your Juriſdiction, when I might decline all Other. J am
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac▪
                     20. Iuly. 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. XLIX. To the ſame—
               
                  Sir,
               
               HItherto I have beheld (without diſturbance) all the aſſaults of my enemies; and they have but ſcratcht ſome lines of my Books, &amp; at moſt have call'd to queſtiō ſome things of ſmall conſequence. But now that they wounde me in the tendereſt part of my heart, I profeſſe to you, J begin to have ſome reſentment▪ I cannot forgive them the injury they have done me, to raiſe jealouſies and make a breach betweene vs Two. And I have conceived ſuch indignation againſt this impoſture, that it is impoſsible I ſhould write unto you ſoberly and moderately. If J doe not exerciſe vindicative justice,
                  
there is no reaſon J ſhould deſire it. That which doth moſt of all trouble me is, that I doe runne after a Fantaſme, and that I knowe not whom to lay hold upon. And truly, if there were any meanes to diſcover this honeſt Secretary that was beſtowed on me without my knowledge, I think it were very juſt to pay him his wages. How ever, here is a man that would gaine a name by ſuch an occaſion; &amp; doth pronounce againſt him that terrible Arrest. Ligno pereat qui fumum vendidit. Theſe men ſhould be made an example; and whereof a civill Society ought to be quickly purg'd. They are the moſt dangerous Theeves of all, that rob us of our friends: which be goods, that ſhould remaine ours, after the loſſe of all other. J confeſſe, that J have

many infirmities, and am ſubject to erre a thouſand waies, but J am not capable of an offence of that high nature that J am charg'd with; and the goodly Letter, which you ſent me a coppy of, carries neither my ſtile nor my Genius; nevertheleſſe, your faith hath betrayed a weakneſſe, and you have ſtaggerd a litle upon the opening of this falſe packet. Aſſure your ſelfe Sir, if J have forfeited your good Opinion and favour, that J would not outlive ſo ſmart an Affliction; and you may believe, that J doe not raſhly hazard a thing ſo precious as that. J make not onely Sincerity and Zeale the companions of my Friendſhip
                  ▪ but Diſcretion alſo and Reſpect. The Perſons whom J love, are to me almoſt in the ſame degree of veneration, as thoſe things which J adore:

I approach them not but with awe, which accompanies Religion; and it is certaine, that I am ſo fearfull to offend them, that (leaſt J ſhould diſtaſt them with my ſullenneſſe) J doe force and faine ſmiles when I am moſt ſad. You ſhall know more of this in the progreſſe of my life; and avouch, that I know how to practiſe thoſe maxims, which J hold, and approve my ſelfe, with courage and conſtancy
               
               
                  Sir
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
1. March 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. L. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               SInce I have arriv'd here, I have received the Letter, which you did me the honour to write unto me; which is, a continuation of your courteſies and bounty, and an entrance upon a commerce, where I muſt take all, and you give all. While I expect to make benefit of your Proſe, I feaſt upon your verſes, which have diſreliſht all that I took for excellent before. I never ſaw boldneſſe more diſcreet, courage better maintain'd, or ſweetneſſe leſſe effeminate. Theſe are Sir, worthy Harbingers of your Damſell. But you doe her wrong to ſeeme to doubt of her good Fate,
                  
and doe not beleeve the auſpicious omens that appear'd at her Nativity, which promiſe long life. If you have patience enough to conſummate this work, all the reſt is ſufficient: your naturall wit is ſtrong and pregnant; you have the perfection of Arts; your Cabinet is a Magazin of ornaments and riches, to adorne the Subject. What more is wanting to you? Be not nice any longer: you are condemn'd to goe forward with it; except you meane to quit one paſsion for another, and abandon Poetry for the Politicks: wherein (to tell you the truth) J believe you will prove admirable. I am of your opinion, that fifteen hundred verſes at one breath, goe farre; and that it would not be amiſſe, to ſet more reaſonable bounds to every Book. But touching all this, you

may conſult with Vida &amp; Fracaſtorius; and if they be not of the ſame opinion, Scaliger may be the ſuper-numerary. Our Doctor ſaith, that he hath not ſo much need of counſell as of aide, and ſince things paſt, fall not under deliberation, it is no time now, to know whether he hath err'd; he deſires you only to teach him how to deny it with ſome faire probability; to perſwade the people that Pericles is not fallen, though the people ſaw it. For my part, J am confident of the good ſucceſſe of all your enterpriſes. Haveing found the bel motivo in favour of the Poet Marini, there is no ſuch Monster which you cannot ſhape and make handſome; and without doubt, you have ſuch precious Oyle, that one drop thereof is

ſufficient to blanch a Moore. It is
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
1. Aug. 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. LI. To the ſame—
               
                  Sir,
               
               MY ſilence is not the effect of Sloth; and you may believe that it is againſt my will that J deprive my ſelfe of the contentment that J took in entertaining you. The reaſons that obliged me to ſilence, were more juſt then J wiſht they had been; and a troubleſome Defluxion which fell upon my eyes hath fail'd to charge you with a blind friend: For in that caſe, I think you could not have

choſen but to have been my Guide; and I did already make account to learne to ſing, that J might chante your Poëme. But (by the great mercy of God) J recovered my eye-ſight yeſterday; and you are freed from the ſad office, which my diſtreſſed Fortune might have requir'd from your good nature. Now that I doe ſpeak, and doe not rattle in the throat; J muſt give you an account of the voyage that J made; and I muſt tell you with as much ceremony and eloquence as heretofore, that I have been to meet the Court as farre as Cadilliac. I had the honour there, to doe my reſpects to my Lord —. But His ſickneſſe, that took him the very day that he arriv'd thither, and mine, which would waite no longer to attach me, did force me to

take my way back to my Village; where I found your meſſages, and my coffers. I render you once more, moſt humble thanks, for the care you took to keep them for me; and ſince you are pleaſed that J make uſe of you, with ſuch familiarity, you muſt permit my thankfull acknowledgement thereof. The newes you wrote unto me, concerning the ſickneſſe of — was told me at Bordeaux, when I was there; and J ſweare unto you, J have not ſlept a good ſleepe ſince. This is as good a man as ever I was acquainted with, and I doe mainely eſteeme him; becauſe I know him to the very heart: where (without faineing) I have found nothing, but what was noble, and (I dare ſpeak it) magnanimous. J know that his ou ſide hath been diſpleaſing to

many; But men muſt not alwaies, be judged by the lineaments of the face, and that averſation is unjuſt, which ſprings only out of deformity. J doe much wonder that two words which I have written to my Stationer, being halfe a ſleepe, are floune out of his ſhop already. I aſſure you I am no — nor doe not uſe to put on ſeverity in reading theſe kinds of Relations. But (in-truth) this here, did give me much content; and though I meet with ſome paſſages that might be altered without any harme, &amp; where a decorum was not ſo exactly obſerved as it might have been; nevertheleſſe (to ſpeak in the generall) the invention, to my thinking, was handſome, the narration neat and ſmooth, and the ſtile all ſavouring of the Court and Cabinet. When you

have read it, I will think of it, as you ſhall pronounce the ſentence; in the mean while, J uſe the liberty allowed in points not yet decided; and the interim, that you are too good to agree with me, untill you have made the truth manifeſt unto me. For the Dutch Orator, remember (at leaſt wiſe) that J ſpake nothing but touching his phraſe, for J doe infinitely eſteeme his learning and judgement. Be pleaſed therefore to manage this petty ſecret according to your ordinary prudence▪ ſince J am ſo unfortunate, that I cannot utter one word, but it will ſtraight finde ſtrange Gloſſes and Commentaries, and that there be people ſo charitable, as to ſtirre up warre againſt me, and create me enimies in all parts of the world. J have never received the

Letter of Monſieur de — neither did I need them to aſſure me of his love. I know that he is good and noble; wherefore relying hereupon, it ſufficeth me to underſtand that he is well; and it is not materiall to me, whether J learne this from him or from you. J forgot to tell you that J received from Monſieur the Duke of — many careſſes &amp; favours; he hath uſed me like ſome great Perſonage, or mighty Signor; and I have been his Favorite the ſpace of foure daies. I deſire no more, nor doe I labour to promote my good fortune any farther. I am content to bound it Sir, with the fruition of your good favour, and J am moſt affectionately
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
1. Dec. 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. LII. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Have returned no anſwere to your Letter, in regard J have been cumbred (lately) with ſome domeſtick affaires, which would allow me no leaſure to write; it is your Prerogative, to be able to intend ſeverall things at once: you injoy a ſpirit ſo calme, that you can read a Dialogue in Plato, and diſpatch a dozen buſineſſes too at once, with a reſolve to dye an houre after. For my part, one object is enough to imploy me, and it is impoſsible for me to reconcile Recreation and Buſineſſe. That which you tell me of Monſieur — is true. The Letter which he wrote unto

me is an abridgement of all his Books; and J cannot returne anſwer to it, though J would, but by the meſſenger that goes the next year from Angouleſme. But though it hath been told you, yet be pleaſed not to believe it, that this Letter offends me, or that mine hath given any offence. Only upon occaſion of one litle word, he took a hint to ſport it after his ordinary manner, and to make a new ſhew of his old manner of boording. We muſt be indulgent to our friends mirth, and give way (a litle) to their jolly humor. Nay, a man ought not to doe his enimy all the diſcourteſies he can; and to be very ſenſible of a wrong, is to adde weight and meaſure to it. Satisfy your ſelfe, J pray, touching my ſpirit by theſe maximes of peace▪ and feare not that any

man can raiſe my paſsions to an humor of contention. A thouſand Chartells cannot tempt me to one Duell, and J can be more coward, then the Hott-ſpurres of the times are quarrelſome. J feare not their ſtrength, nor ſubtlety, but J feare my owne trouble, and I doe infinitely love my Rest: Honour it ſelfe would ſeeme unmanerly to me, if it came to diſquiet it. And I would faine paſſe for an Jncognito even in my owne Province, and my owne Village. You cannot believe how much J am fallen out with the world, and how diſtaſtfull J am to my ſelfe. What was wont to tickle and pleaſe me, hurts me. An Almanack and an Hiſtory I eſteeme alike. Thoſe ſimple termes of ſtile, phraſe, and period, are ſo harſh to my ears, that they make my head ake. If it

were Gods will, that I ſhould be ſentenced to looſe my good or bad Reputation, J would reſigne it (with all my heart) to any that would deſire it; and J have a deſire to change my name, that J might not any more ſhare in any thing that is ſpoken of Balzac, nor intereſſe my ſelfe either in the praiſes or diſpraiſes that are beſtowed on Him. Js not this Sir, a pretty reſolution? &amp; which J ſhould long ſince have undertaken. This is almoſt the panoplie of that Philoſopher, that patiently took a boxe on the eare in a publike place at Corinth. He profeſſed he had a helmet to ward future blowes, that if any ſhould chance to give him another boxe, it might fall on an iron face and not his. Apply this how you pleaſe; As for my part, I doe but laugh at Rhetorick,
                  
and all its Tropes; and have nothing to doe with that Art, which hath created me ſo many vexations. J am with all my ſoule
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
10. Ian▪ 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. LIII. To the ſame.
               
                  Sir,
               
               GOd doth beſet me on all ſides; and ſends me afflictions by troopes: To comfort me for the deceaſe of Monſieur de — newes is brought me of that of Monſieur de — So that J begin to make a conſcience to love you, ſince my

Friendſhip is (in a manner) fatall to whomſoever J give it; and that I poſſeſſe nothing but I looſe it in a moment. But there is no need of doing bad offices about you, or to affright you with any Planet, whoſe malignity (J hope) you are able to correct. I paſſe it over therefore, to tell you, that as long as Monſieur de — was here, I performed my part with wonderfull aſsiduity, ſo that I was aſtoniſht at it my ſelfe. We have had long and particular diſcourſes upon all good ſubjects, and by conſequence, you may believe that You have not been forgotten. J never preach well, but when you are my Text. As J prize nothing more juſtly then your love ſo I praiſe nothing more willingly then your virtue; and this ſubject pleaſeth me ſo well that I never

want words, if I doe not want Auditors. Yet I doe not pretend to engage you hereby. To reck on you in the number of Illuſtrious men, is only to leave you in your own ſeat; &amp; and to ſay that the Damſell will be your work, is to ſay, that Pallas will iſſue out of the head of Iove. She is at this time the ſweeteſt hope and expectation of honeſt leaſure; She is the deſire of the Cabinet &amp; will be the great labour of the French Muſes. I haue threatned (this long while) a voyage to Paris; which I intended of purpoſe to ſee it; and I hope to ſurpriſe you both together, one day when you expect me not. But remember Sir, that even your Purpoſe is a vow; and that you can have no ſuch Diſpenſation, that can take away all ſcruple, if you have a tender conſcience and will believe ſome

                  Divines (that I can name) concerning it. I cannot conclude my Letter before J acquaint you, that J am raviſhed with the good opinion you beare towards my Nephew. J aſcribe more to your predictions then to them that make Horoſcopes and calculate nativities; &amp; the conjectures which your good judgement doth ſuggeſt, are more certain then thoſe which They derive out of their Art. My Siſter is ſo proud of the teſtimony you gave her, that ſhe would have return'd you a Complement, if ſhe durſt adventure to ſpeake to you. But her reſpect did check her deſire, and I have promiſed to excuſe her ſilence; which (I know) you will pardon, becauſe it will ſave you the paines to reply. we deſire Sir, the continuation of your good admonitions to this gallant

man; and doubt not, but a glance or caſte of your eye now &amp; then, will edifie him much. I think you ſhould conſider him as ſomething that concernes you. For my part, I make no difference between your affection and mine; and I am without all reſervation
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
25. May 1633.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. LIV. To the ſame —
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Know not how to preſente my ſelfe before you: though my cō
                  ſcience doth acquit me, ſome appearances

condemne me; and you ſee my fault, but know not my affaires; I have had variety of them ever theſe three months which have ſtrangely exerciſed me; and whereof I am yet ſo weary that I muſt have a great while to recover my ſelfe. All that I can, is to uſe my Idleneſſe well, and to make ſomething of my Leaſure. Now that I have got it in poſſeſsion againe, I meane not to be diſſeiſed of it: If it be poſſible, I bid eternall farwell to all contracts, tranſactions, &amp; Aquittances. Theſe are ornaments of our language which muſt not (in my opinion) enter into your Poems. You have more care of the chaſtity of your Damſell then to violate her with theſe villanous termes; &amp; this were of a 
                     Ʋirgin to make a Strumpet of her. But I can never obtaine

that ſmall favour of you, or prevaile ſo much as to ſee here (at leaſt) the firſt hundred verſes that doe concerne her. I doe preſerve carefully all thoſe things that you have ſent, and never produce them out of my Treaſury, but to impart them to choice Wits. The invention of your firſt Metamorphoſis is ingenious. Ovid had ſwell'd up and dilated that ſubject which you have contracted and preſſed together. But the importance is, that in this litle, you appeare great; and I behold you intire in every parcell. The ſecond part doth pleaſe me no leſſe yet then the firſt, and I hold that Lionneſſe happy that hath heaven for an Amphitheater, and hath been placed there by ſuch a hand as yours. You make her jarre ſo well and tunably; and her roaring is ſo ſweet and melodious

in your Verſes, that there is no Muſick comparable. Thoſe of — doe not flow in ſuch numbers. Longe
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      pulchrius ſpectaculum est, &amp; dignius oculis eruditi, videre nobilem illam feram, quàm miſerum &amp; febriculoſum Annaei Lucani Simium With the laſt Letter I received Bembus which you ſent me. In truth he is not ſo well poliſhed and digeſted as thoſe Authors in the Library of Monſieur —. But all tattered &amp; confuſed as it is, I can aſſure you, it likes me infinitely. J never love luxury, &amp; am nothing curious for gay cloathes. The beauty of Chariclea did ſhine through her ragges; and your Marini hath made a Sonnet, wherein he tells us, how he fell in love with a canting Doxie. J thanke you therefore for 
                     Ʋenus and the Graces (though ill attired) which J met

with, in your Books, and remaine
               
                  Sir,
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
3. Iuly. 1633.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. LV. To the ſame—
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Entertaine your commendations like ill gotten goods; the fruition whereof is ſweet, although unjuſt. It is ſome honour to me to have ſo excellent a Flatterer as you are; and I ſuffer my ſelfe willingly, and take a pleaſure to be deceived by a man that can doe it ſo neatly. J think (indeed) that the Verſes which you have ſeen, are not bad in their kinde; but J think withall, that this

is the ſhorteſt of all kinds. I durſt not engage my ſelfe in a wider carreere; my ſtrength ſerves but for a ſhort tugg; and I walke at the foot of your Parnaſſus; but I ſhould want breath, if J ſhould attempt to moūt the top. You doe (indeed) Sir, bear the name of a great Poet, &amp; ſucceed equally in all ſorts of Verſes; and though you ſpeak with extreame modeſty of the laſt work, which you ſent me: I doe not find that it oweth any thing to the faireſt Pieces that you have ſhewed us. There is no ſtanza that hath not its particular value; nor no Piece but is remarkable for ſome beauty. But that which did chiefly reliſh with me was the Prayer which you direct to Apollo; and that admirable Muſick, (which proceeding out of the clouds) heals your malady in a trice.

This is not the effect of ordinary Poetry; it is a fit of that divine rapture and furie, which Plato hath acknowledged; and which the firſt Poets were ſometimes poſſeſſed with. Send me ſuch Preſents often, if you would have me rich in my Poverty; and have good company in my ſolitude. But above all, love me well, if you would have me happy; and aſſure your ſelfe, that no man in the world is more then I am
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
9. Aug. 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. LVI. To the ſame—
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Know that you love me, and I know that you are in health, but this is not enough; I muſt learne ſomething more concerning it; and you muſt tell me ſome newes of your brave Meditations. Doth the Girle wage warre, or doth ſhe keep at home in the countrey with her Father? Doth Charles grow ſoft in the embraces of the faire Agnes, or doth he quit Love for honour? In what ſtate are the affaires of England? How doth Hire and Potho? What doe your Achilles and Ajax? are you for a battle or for a ſiedge?

                     Jam nunc minaci murmure cornuum
                     Perſtringis aures, jam litui ſtrepūt:
                     
                        Audire magnos jam videor duces▪
                     
                     Non indecoro pulvere ſordidos, &amp;c.
                  
See queſtions enough at once; but you are not bound to anſwere to them punctually, and provided, that you ſatisfie me in one Article, you have to deale with a man of a facile diſpoſition, who will not be rigorous for the reſt I am now more a Hermit then ever; and for having here a litle Court but two daies onely, I had the Megrim by it for three weeks. Tranquillity &amp; ſilence Sir, is a precious thing; and if Epicurus had ſome reaſon to complain of his very friends that they did break his head with their applauſe &amp; acclamations: what muſt be ſaid of the bawlings and exclamations, of a mans enemies, of the firſt &amp; ſecond part of Philarkes of their times. Thoſe that write, are ſubject both

to the one and the other perſecution. But for my part, I avow to you, that hitherto Complements have done me more harme then injuries. I uſe none towards you Sir, for fear you ſhould complaine of me in the ſame manner; and J am content to tell you, that I am without complement, that is, intirely
               
                  Angouleſme
1. Sept. 1634.
                  
                  Your, &amp;c.
               
            
            
               LET. LVII. To Monſieur de Sithon.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               YOU ſhew a ſort of humility that is not ſufferable; and though it be the proper ſtile of Saints to talke of their vileneſſe, and

their nothingneſſe; yet to reject all teſtimonies indifferently, that come from another, is in my opinion rather a contempt of our neighbor thē a modest conceit of our ſelves. I am no flatterer, but J praiſe or diſpraiſe, according as J am perſwaded of the merit of things, or their default; &amp; if I talke often of the great lights that you have, whither in ſacred or prophane Learning, it is becauſe I have been dazled therewith. Your three Diſcourſes doe pleaſe me infinite; ly and I am very well pleaſed that mine did not diſpleaſe you: But I am the more glad that you are of my opinion touching the putting downe quite of all Anſwers, Replies, Defences, Apologies, and the like. Since I have but laughed at the attempts of a Legion. I doe not meane to complaine of the inſolence of a

                  Carbine; A man were better to pick out an enimie; and this here, may fight all alone, if it pleaſe him: It is not fit to ſhew anger againſt a man that deſerves pitty, nor to looſe patience upon an occaſion ſo obſcure, that it were hard to make it appeare. You ſend me no newes concerning the affaires of Italy, and I am very deſirous to heare ſome. It hath been told me that Monſieur Maynard hath not appear'd in Paris, though Monſieur de Mailles be arriv'd thither. He will (perhaps) be ſtaied a longer time. If it be ſo, my Affection is ſo farre ingenious as to torment my ſpirit. I ſtand in feare (for his ſake) of all the dangers both of ſea and land. I doe apprehend at once that he is fallen ſick by the way, and that he is lead captive into Barbary, and that the Spaniards
                  
have ſurpriſed him. That which muſt comfort me in this diſtraction is, that a good ſpirit doth paſſe undauntedly through all; and that they were the Poets his Predeceſſours that made wings for Daedalus. How ever you will confeſſe, that if Epigrams be current among the Millamois, and that he wants but 2000 of them for his ranſome, hee hath wherewith to ſatisfie them without dammage to himſelfe. In truth, I am ſollicitous touching this my deare friend; and you will oblige me, if you will be pleaſed to ſend me a relation of his Adventures, whē you ſhall come to know them. I am
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
30. Dec. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. LVIII. To Monſieur GERARD Secretary to my Lord the Duke of Eſpernon.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               HAppy are thoſe actions that fall under your Pen and Hiſtory. Since you doe extoll one mans idleneſſe even to the envy of the world, and ſo farre, as to propoſe it for an example, what Will you talke of the life of the Suediſh King, and other Miracles of our age; if you will take them in hand? The miſchiefe is, that thoſe, that have heard you, ſhall ſee me; and you have ſet me at ſo high a rate, that J cannot hold after it, but upon your credit, &amp; by my own abſence. If Monſieur the Duke of — paſſeth

by Balzack, the legend that you have fram'd of me, will at firſt daſh looſe that probability that it carried; and I ſhall be no more that famous Hermit, that hath been related and deſcribed unto him by an officious Impostor. Jn vaine will he ſeek among my papers the fine things that you have promiſed him; and it will repent him (perhaps) that he turned out of the rode, for ſuch a ſad ſpectacle that J ſhall exhibit him. In any caſe Sir, I will preſent my ſelfe; and if hitherto you have deceived him, yet you ſhall acquit your ſelfe of the name of Cozner, when you ſhall aſſure him on my behalfe of an inviolable fidelity, and hearty acknowledgement. Theſe are qualities which I poſſeſſe in a ſoveraigne degree▪ and which I preſerve for

him in the bottome of my ſoule. But the paſsion which I beare to his Honour, muſt not be ſtill kept as a ſecret; and, J will at length profeſſe, what I have this long while ador'd in particular manner. Doe me the favour, as to tell him thus much, and beleeve withall, if you pleaſe, that I am
               
                  Sir,
                  Your, &amp;c.
                  Balzac.
30. May 1635.
                  
               
            
            
               LET. LIX. To the ſame—
               
                  Sir,
               
               I Love no kind of quarrelling, much leſſe with my friends. But it is a thing worthy pitty, that a

man ſhould receive continuall wrong, and yet muſt not open his mouth to complaine, but he ſhall be cenſur'd for a troubleſome and untoward fellow. I know the eager ſpirit of that man that ſpeaks ſo loud, when my intereſts are in agitation. I know he is carried with the hot vapours that exhale from that ſulfury veine, which (you ſay) lyeth about his heart. But you will confeſſe notwithſtanding, that the bottome of this heart is not bad. His laviſhneſſe proceeds from a faire ſpring, and in acts of friendſhip an inundation is better then drouth. J forgive the intricated zeale, incident goodneſſe, and impetuouſneſſe of a man that cannot love with moderation. Wee muſt doe him ſome right, and not hate his paſsion, though we approve
                  
it not; for my part, I doe permit it, but not imploy it; and though he tells me, that he hath a fierce Satyre to come forth to kill our meſſer, if he doe not ſave himſelfe in the litle Cottage; J give him thanks for his good will, but J deſire him to deliver the Satyre into my hands, and for this purpoſe only, that none might ſee it. You ſhall finde in my packet ſome latine compoſitions that were ſent me, and particularly, the later Teares of S. Peter, which have been commended unto you. In my judgement, (and I think you will ſubſcribe to it) he is too ſubtle, and ſhewes too much punctuality in delineting a true Penitent. Nature doth not ſpeak thus, nor its paſsions either, which are the daughters of nature, as ſubtleties are the wantons of Art. S. Peters
                  
ſorrow is admirably well expreſſed by Grotius; and theſe foure verſes of his, which I remember, doe weigh downe the foure hundred that J have ſent you.

                     Quae me recondet Regio? quâ maestū diem
                     Fallam latebrâ? quaero nigrantem ſpecum
                     Quâ me ſepeliam vivus; ubi nullū videns,
                     Nulli videndus, lachrymas foveam meas.
                  
Are not theſe worthy of the Heroicke times &amp; pureſt Antiquity? the reſt of the Diſcourſe is animated with the ſame Genius; and is a leſſon for Orators, that ſorrow muſt not be elaborate, or at leaſtwiſe muſt not betray any ſtudied care. I leave your Brother to relate newes; he hath in charge to informe you of all occurrences, and therefore I have nothing to ſay, but that I am
               
                  Sir
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac
15. Iun. 1636.
                  
               
            
            
               
               LET. LX. To Monſieur De la Mothe Le Vayer.
               
               
                  Sir,
               
               MY ſpirits have been ſo dull and heavy theſe three daies, that it is beyond imagination. Never did any man looſe the reliſh of all Books and Arts as I did; and hence you may gather that that which you ſent me, was very delicate, when it procur'd an appetite to a languiſhing man. You have ſtrangely altered me in a moment: my ſoule is touched to the quick; and you have made it ſo hungry after knowledge, that I have no mind to any thing but to your Philoſophy. If you will ſet up a Sect, J am ready to enrole my ſelfe, at leaſt wiſe I

will ſubſcribe willingly to that franke doctrine, which maintaines its liberty againſt the uſurpations of Ariſtotle; and is contented to acknoledge lawfull power, but not to be ſlave to the Tyranny of one particular man. I ſpeak Sir, as J believe: Doubtleſſe your work will laſt, and to give you your full due, J muſt give it in your own language: noble an act of the Soule, is not the weakeſt argument we have of its immortality; and if any ſhall hereafter take in hand this ſubject, he will be beholding to you for this new argument, which your modeſty would not permit you to make uſe of. Certainly there were no reaſon nor colour, that the offſpring ſhould be of a better condition then the mother, and that thoſe productions which muſt encounter

                  Time, and conquer Fate, ſhould flow from a corruptible principle. But ſince J have ſped ſo well in my firſt ſollicitations, J deſire not to ſtoppe there. This good ſucceſſe doth encourage me to redouble them, and in the name of all the Learned to begge yet more worke of the ſame vigour. Though J ſhould performe no other office in the common-wealth of Learning then this, J were not an unuſefull member; and this will be (one day) honour enough for me, when it will be ſaid, that I gave the counſaile for thoſe labours which you have undertaken. Acquire for me Sir, this reputation, that J may adde it to that which I would gladly deſerve all my life time, which is to be
               
                  Balzac.
29. March 1637.
                  
                  Your &amp;c.
               
            
            
               
               LET. LXI. To Monſieur de —
               
                  Sir,
               
               THe Diſcourſe which you did me the honour to ſend me, is full of an infinite number of good things; and none can deny but your friend is both learned and judicious. Nevertheleſſe I doe not think that he will find in that place whither he goeth, that approbation which he promiſeth to himſelfe: I think that (for his ſpeaking Latine after the French manner) his meaning is better then his expreſsion▪ He is not alwaies ſo regular as I would deſire; and his words doe ſometimes doe wrong to his thoughts. True it is, that in theſe times we are very nice and delicate
                  
in the purity of expreſsions. We can brooke no ſtile that is licentious be it never ſo litle; and whatſoever is not after the garbe of the Court is accounted barbarous. This is not, that I am of the opinion of Monſieur de — that ſaid that the good man Iudgement could never paſſe beyond the Garond; and that He was put into ſuch a fright at Blaye, that he durſt not adventure any farther. When he ſpake this, he forgot (ſure) that Monſieur de Pibrac, Monſieur de Montagne, and the Cardinall d' Oſſat were Gaſcons; and their ſolid judgements which are admired to this day over all Europe, doe ſufficiently refute that poore jeſt which paſſeth among ſome for excellent. It is certain that Reaſon is common to all Countreys, and conſequently is of that,
                  
where they ſay Adieu-ſias, as well as when they ſay Dieu vous conduiſſe. It is confin'd to no place, and we may finde ſubtlety among the Switzers, and ſtupidity among the Florentines; but indeed, for the language, it is not all alike: without queſtion in ſome places, they ſpeak better then elſewhere, and whereas a Courtier of Rome did taſt ſome thing of Padua in the Hiſtories of Titus Livius, it is not impoſsible to obſerve in the writings and converſations of your men ſome tincture of their Province. Ever and anon, you ſhall obſerve them to let ſlip vouſiſt for vouluſt, fauſiſt for faluſt, couſin mien, &amp; ie ſuis esté a Thoulouze, which marre all good ſpeech: and their allarent, donuarent armarent, have runne over their

banks, &amp; come as farre as our coū
                  trey. The late Monſieur de Mal herbe hath told me oftē that he did what poſsibly he could for to correct the dialect of Monſieur de — &amp; purge it of Gaſconiſme, but could never bring it about: ſo difficult is it, to wipe off our naturall ſtaines, and utterly to weare out the badge of our Countrey. Nevertheleſſe for all this, neither the Patavinity of Titus Livius, nor the Gaſconiſme of ſome of our times, doe hinder them from being reputed Eloquent
                  ▪ And for one petty fault, either of uſe or of Grammer, I condemne not thoſe works which in all other reſpects, are excellent. To ſatisfy your deſire, I have ſent by Monſieur de — the Letters of Monſieur Heinſius, one whereof preceded my Diſſertation,
                  
the other followed his anſwer. Now that I have furniſhed you with theſe two Letters, to entertaine you a while; be pleaſed not to take it amiſſe that I take leave of you, and all the world for two years. I am forbid to write any thing for ſo long a time, and this is an oath that J have taken by the order of my Confeſſor; and upon good and waighty conſiderations. I hope God will give me the grace to obſerve it:
Nec mihi ſcribendi veniet tā dira cupido;
And you will not (J am ſure) tempt me to ſinne, and provoke me to break that ſilence which J have ſworne to. But though you ſhould ſolicite me a thouſand times, and aſſault me every day in two or three languages, I am reſolved to

be inexorable, and not to be moved with that happy abundance of your words. Jf you terme me uncivill, and expoſtulate with me in the words of your Poet,
                  
                     
                        Ʋnde îſtam meruit non faelix charta repulſam?
                     Hoſtis ab Hoſte tamē per barbara a verba ſalutē
                     
                     Accipit, &amp; Salve modiis intervenit armis;
                     Reſpondent &amp; ſaxa homini.
                  
J will make anſwere with an audible voice both to your Poet and You, that Religion muſt ſway Civility, and that a leſſer duty muſt yeeld to a greater. Finally if there be an abſolute neceſsity, that we have ſome commerce with each other: in this caſe, I will chooſe rather to make a journey then write a letter, and expoſe my ſelfe to the hazard of ſhipwrack by going to ſee you, then violate my Faith by

writing to you. Adieu then untill the year of 1639, which we will begin (by Gods grace) by the renewing of our ancient Trafick. Is is
               
                  Sir,
                  Your &amp;c.
                  Balzac: —
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            A TABLE OF THE LETters (as they lye in order) which are contained in this Volume.
            
            
               TO Monſieur Conrart Let. 1.
Pag. 1.
               
               To Monſ. du Moulin. let. 2.
p 7.
               
               To Monſ. L'Huillier. let. 3.
p. 11:
               To Monſ. the Abbat of Bois-Robert. Let. 4.
p. 19.
               
               To my Lord the Earle of Exceſter. Let. 5.
p. 23.
               
               To my Lord the Duke De la Valette. Let. 6.
p. 26.
               
               To Monſ. Drovet; let. 7.
p. 29.
               
               Te Monſ. De-Bonair. let. 8.
p. 33.
               
               
                  To Monſ. Huggens let. 9.
p. 35.
               
               To Monſ. de Racan. let. 10.
p 38.
               
               To Monſ. De St Chartres let. 11.
p. 43.
               
               To Monſ. Baudoin let. 12.
p. 47.
               
               To Monſ. De Coignet. let. 33.
p. 51.
               
               To Madam Deſloges. let. 14.
p. 54.
               
               To my Lord Keeper of the Seales Seguier &amp;c. let. 15.
p. 57.
               
               To Moſ. De Morins. let. 16.
p. 61.
               
               To Monſ. De Vaugelas. let. 17.
p. 63.
               
               To Monſ. De la Motte Aigron. l. 18.
p. 70.
               
               To Monſ. De Borſtell. let. 19.
p. 74.
               
               To Monſ. the chiefe Advocate. let. 20.
p. 77.
               
               To Monſ. De Maury. let. 21.
p 79.
               
               To Monſ. de Mondory. let. 22.
p 82.
               
               To Monſ. Le Guay. let. 23.
p. 87.
               
               To Monſ. de Silhon. let. 24.
p. 89.
               
               To Monſ. De la Foſſe. let. 25.
p. 93.
               
               To Monſ. D'Eſpeſſes. let. 26.
p. 97.
               
               To the ſame: let. 27.
p. 101.
               
               
                  To Monſ. de Couurelles. l. 28.
p. 108.
               
               To — let. 29.
p. 111.
               
               To my Lord the Biſhop of Angouleſme Let. 30.
p. 114.
               
               To Monſ. de — let. 31.
p. 117.
               
               To Monſ. De Serizay. let. 32.
p. 133.
               
               To Monſ. Habert Abbat of Cerizy. let. 33.
p. 137.
               
               To Monſ. De Gaillard. let. 34.
p. 141.
               
               To the ſame. let. 35.
p. 145.
               
               To Madam Deſloges. let. 36.
p. 150.
               
               To Monſ. de — let. 37.
p. 153.
               
               To Monſ. Girard. let. 38.
p. 157.
               
               To the ſame. let. 39.
p. 160.
               
               To the ſame let. 40.
p. 164.
               
               To the ſame let. 41.
p. 167.
               
               To Madamoiſell de Campagnole. let. 42.
p. 17
                        •
                     .
               
               To Monſ. the Abbat of Bois-Robert. let. 43.
p. 174.
               
               To the ſame. let. 44.
p. 178.
               
               To the ſame. let. 45.
p. 182.
               
               
                  To Monſ. de Savignac. let. 46.
p 186
               
               To Monſ. Chapelain. let. 47.
p. 194.
               
               To the ſame. let. 48.
p. 197.
               
               To the ſame. let. 49.
p. 200.
               
               To the ſame. let. 50.
p. 204.
               
               To the ſame. let 51.
p. 207.
               
               To the ſame. let. 52.
p. 213.
               
               To the ſame. let. 53.
p. 217.
               
               To the ſame. let. 54.
p. 221.
               
               To the ſame. let. 55.
p. 225.
               
               To the ſame. let. 56.
p 228.
               
               To Monſ. de Silhon let. 57.
p. 230.
               
               To Monſ. Gerard Secretary to the D. of Eſpernon. let. 58.
p. 234.
               
               To the ſame. let. 59.
p. 240.
               
               To Monſ. de la Mothe le Vayer. let. 60.
p. 240.
               
               To Monſ. de — let. 61.
p. 243.
               
            
            
         
      
   

