
   
      
         
            A maruelous hystory intitulede, beware the cat Conteyning diuers wounderfull and incredible matters. Very pleasant and mery to read.
            Beware the cat.
            Baldwin, William, ca. 1518-1563?
         
         
            
               1570
            
         
         Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02306
            STC 1244
            ESTC S117270
            99852485
            99852485
            17809
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02306)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17809)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1226:21)
         
         
            
               
                  A maruelous hystory intitulede, beware the cat Conteyning diuers wounderfull and incredible matters. Very pleasant and mery to read.
                  Beware the cat.
                  Baldwin, William, ca. 1518-1563?
               
               [8] p. : ill.  
               
                  In Fleetestrete at the signe of the Faulcon by Wylliam Gryffith: and are to be sold at his shop in S. Dunstons Church-yarde,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  Anno. 1570.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: G. B. [i.e. Gulielmus Baldwin].
                  In 1864, Halliwell printed a manuscript transcript of an edition with colophon: J. Alde, sold by J. Arnold, 1570.--STC.
                  Imperfect; lacks all but 4 leaves.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Cats --  Fiction --  Early works to 1800.
               Satire, English --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2000-00
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-02
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-02
            TCP Staff (Michigan)Text and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-03
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
            
            A MARVELOVS Hystory intitulede, Beware the Cat. Conteynyng diuerse wounderfull and incredible matters. Uery pleasant and mery to read.
            
               
                  GEVE GOD THE GLORYE NOWE AND EVER MORE
               
¶ IMPRINTED AT LONDON, IN Fléetestrete at the signe of the Faulcon by Wylliam Gryffith: and are to be sold at his shop in S. Dunstons Churchyarde. Anno. 1570.
         
         
            
            
               
            
         
         
            
            ¶ Loue and Liue.
            ¶ To the Right worshipfull Esquier maister Iohn Yong, Grace and health.
            I Haue penned for your masterships pleasure one of the stories which maister Streamer tolde the last Christmas, and which you so faine wold haue heard reported by master Feres him selfe. And although I be vnable to penne or speake it so pleasantly as he could, yet haue I so nerely vsed both the order and wordes of him that spake them, which is not the least vertue of a reporter that I doubt not but that he and maister VVillot shal in the reading thinke they heare master Streamer speake, and he him selfe in the like action shall doubt whether he speaketh or readeth. I haue deuided his oration into three partes, and put the argument before them, and an instruction after them with such notes as might be gathered therof: so making it booke like, and intituled. Be ware the Cat. But because I doubt whether master Streamer wilbe contented that other men plowe with his oxen, I meane penne such thinges as he speaketh, which perhaps hee

would rather do him selfe to haue (as he deserueth) the glory of both therfore I besech you to learne his mind herein. And if he agree it passe in such sorte, yet that he peruse it before the Printing, and amend it if in any poynt I haue mistaken him. I pray you likewise to aske master Ferres his iudgement herein, and shewe him that the cure of the great plague of master Sreamers translation out of the Arabicke, which hee sent me from Margets, shalbe Imprinted assone as I may conueniently. And it I shall perceaue by your tryall, that master Streamer allowe my endeuours in this kinde, I will hereafter as Plato did by Socrates penne such things out of the rest of our Christmas communications, as shalbe to his great glorie, and no lesse pleasure to all them that desire such kinds of knowledge. In the meane while I besech you accept my good will, and learne to beware the Cat. So shal you not only performe that I seke but also please the Almightie who alwayes pres you:
            Amen.
            
               Yours to his power. 
                     •
                   B.
            
         
         
            
            The Argument.
            IT chaunced that at Christmas last I was at the Court with master Ferres then master of the Kyngs maiesties pastimes about the setting forth of certaine enterludes, which for the kynges recreation we had deuised and were in learning. In which time among many other exercises among our selues we vsed nightly at our lodging to talke of sundry thinges for the furtheraunce of such offices wherin ech man as than serued. For which purpose it pleased master Ferres to make me his bedfellowe, and vpon a pallet cast vpon the rushes in his owne chamber to lodge master willot and. M. Streamer, the one his Astronimor the other his diuine. And among many other thinges to long to reherse, it hapned on a night which I thinke was the. xxviij. of December after that M. Ferres was come from the court and in bead, there fell a controuersie betwene M. Streamer who with M. willot had already slept his first slepe, and I that was newly come to bead the effect wherof was whether birdes and beastes had reason, the occasion wherof was this. I had heard that the kings players were learning a play of Esops Crow, wherin the most parte of the actors were birdes, the deuice wherof I discommended, saying it was not commicall to make eyther spechles things to speake, or brutish things to common reasonably. And although in a tale it were suffreable to Imagine and tel of somthing by them spoken or reasonably done, which kind Esop laudably vsed, yet it was vncomly sayd I and without example of any author to bring them in liuly peirsonages to speake, do, reason, and alaege au
                  ••
               orities out of authours. M. Streamer my Lo
                  ••
                
               
                  ••
               uine, being more diuine in this poynt than I was ware of, held the contrary parte, affirming that beastes and foules had reason, and that as much as men, yea and in some poyntes more. master Ferres him selfe and his Astronimer

wakened with our talke harkened to vs, but would take parte on neither side. And whan M. Streamer had for profe of his assercion declared many thinges of Oliphants that walked vppon cordes, Hedgehogges that knewe alwayes what weather would come, Fores and Dogges that after thoy had bene all night abrode killing Geese and Sheepe would come home in the morning &amp; put their neckes into their collers, Parates that bewayled their kepers death, Swallowes that with Selandine open their young ones eyes, and an hundred things more which I denied to come of reason, and to be but naturall kindly actions, alleging for my profe authority of most graue and learned Philosophers, well quod master Streamer I know what I know, and I speake not onely what by hearsay of some Philosophers I knowe, but what I my selfe haue proued. why (quod I then) haue you profe of beastes and fowles reason? yea (quod he) I haue heard them &amp; vnderstand them both speake and reason aswel as I here &amp; vnderstand you: at this M. Ferres laughed. But I remembring what I had read in Albertes workes, thought there might be somwhat more than I knew, wherfore I asked him what beastes or fowles he had heard, and where and whan: At this he pawsed a while, &amp; at last sayd: If I thought you could be content to heare me, and without any interruption till I haue done to marke what I say, I would tel you such a story of one piece of my own
                  •
                experimenting, as should both make you wonder, &amp; put you out of doubt c
                  ••
                this matter. But this I promise you aforet I do tell it, that as sone as any man curiously interrupteth me, I will leaue of and not speake one word more. When we had promised quietly to heare, he turning him selfe so in his bead as we might best heare him, sayd:
            ¶ FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ The first parte of master Streamers oracion.
            
            BEing lodged as I thanke him I haue bene often, at a frends house of mine, which more rowmish within than garish without, standeth at Sainct Martins lane end, and hangeth partly vpon the towne WalWhy Alde
                     ••
                  gate was so named. that is called Aldersgate, eyther of one Aldricke, or els of Elders, that is to say auncient men of the Citie which among them builded it, as Bishops did Bishopsgate:
               Bish
                     ••
                   builded 
                     •••
                  shopsgate. or els of Eldern trees, which perchaunce as they do in the gardens now ther about, so while the cōmon there was vacaunt grue aboundantly in the same place where the gate was after builded, and called therof Elderngate: as Moregate toke the name ofWhy moregate. the feeld without it, which hath bene a very Moore. Or els because it is the most auncient gate of the Citie, was therof in respect of the other, as Newgate, called theWhy Newgate. 
               
                  •••
               ergate. Or els as Ludgate taketh theWhy L
                     •••
                  gate. name of Lud, who builded it, so moste parte of Haroldes (I know) will sonest assent that Aluredus builded this. But they are decesued. For he and his wife Algay
               Why Algate.
               
builded Algate which therof taketh the name, as Criplegate doth of a Criple who begged so much money in his life as put toWhy Cryple gate. the siluer Wethercocke which he stole from Poules steple, after his death buildedPowles weather cocke was siluer. it.
            But wherof so euer this gate Aldergate tooke the name, which longeth chiefly to Historyes to know, at my frendes houss which as I sayd standeth so nere it that it is ouer it, I lay often times, and that for sundry causes. Somtime for lacke of other lodging, &amp; sometime as while my Gréeks Alphabets were in printing to se that they might be truly corrected. And sure it is aAgaynst yong mens negligence. shame for all young men that they be no more studious in the tounges, but the world is now come to that passe, that if he can prate a litle Latine, &amp; handle a RacketAgaynst vnlawefull games. and a payre of fire square bowles, he shall soner obteine any liuing than the best learned in a whole Citie: which is cause that learning is dispised, and bagagical things so much aduaunced.
            While I lay at the forsayd house for the causes aforesayd, I was lodged in a Chamber harde by the Printing house, which had a fayre Bay window opening
            
         
      
   

