
   
      
         
            A sight of the Portugall pearle, that is, the aunsvvere of D. Haddon maister of the requests vnto our soueraigne lady Elizabeth by the grace of God quene of England Fraunce and Irelande, defendour of the faith. &amp;c. against the epistle of Hieronimus Osorius a Portugall, entitled Pearle for a Prince. Translated out of lattyn into englishe by Abraham Hartwell, student in the kynges colledge in Cambridge
            Gualtheri Haddoni pro reformatione Anglicana epistola apologetica ad Hier.Osorium, Lusitanum. English
            Haddon, Walter, 1516-1572.
         
         
            
               1565
            
         
         Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02469
            STC 12598
            ESTC S112464
            99847717
            99847717
            12774
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02469)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12774)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 463:09)
         
         
            
               
                  A sight of the Portugall pearle, that is, the aunsvvere of D. Haddon maister of the requests vnto our soueraigne lady Elizabeth by the grace of God quene of England Fraunce and Irelande, defendour of the faith. &amp;c. against the epistle of Hieronimus Osorius a Portugall, entitled Pearle for a Prince. Translated out of lattyn into englishe by Abraham Hartwell, student in the kynges colledge in Cambridge
                  Gualtheri Haddoni pro reformatione Anglicana epistola apologetica ad Hier.Osorium, Lusitanum. English
                  Haddon, Walter, 1516-1572.
                  Hartwell, Abraham, b. ca. 1542.
               
               [132] p.   
               
                  By Wiyllyam Seres dwelling at the west ende of Paules Church, at the sygne of the Hedgehogge,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1565?]
               
               
                  A translation of: Gualtheri Haddoni pro reformatione Anglicana epistola apologetica ad Hier.Osorium, Lusitanum (Paris,1563).
                  A reply to: Osório, Jerónimo.  Epistola ad serenissimam Elizabetam, Angliæ reginam.
                  Publication date suggested by STC.
                  Preface (C4r) dated 27 May 1565.
                  Answered by STC 18889.
                  Signatures: A-B (-1 leaf, A2?) C⁴ [2nd]A-E F⁶.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Osório, Jerónimo, 1506-1580. --  Epistola ad serenissimam Elizabetam, Angliæ regiam.
               Elizabeth, --  I, --  Queen of England, 1553-1603 --  Early works to 1800.
               Osório, Jerónimo, 1506-1580. --  Pearle for a prynce.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-07
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-08
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2004-08
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A sight of the Portugall Pearle, that is, THE AVNSVVERE OF D. Haddon Maister of the requests vnto our soueraigne Lady Elizabeth by the grace of God quene of England Fraunce and Irelande, defendour of the faith. &amp;c. against the epistle of Hieronimus Osorius a Portugall, entitled a Pearle for a Prince.
            Translated out of lattyn into englishe by Abraham Hartwell, Student in the kynges colledge in Cambridge.
         
         
            
            Ad amicum P. Sextum.
            
               A. H.
            
            QVod me (Sexte) rogasdū conor dicere, ludū:
            Paparū
               
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                (puto) fulmen inane putas.
            Priscis papicolis plus an minus Anglolouani,
            Deteriora ferant an meliora rogas.
            Cum dico, meliora: negas rides
                  
                     
                  
                  que
               . papismo
            Qui meliore valet deteriore valet.
            Tu
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                idem rides cum dico, deteriora:
            Tam spurcis peius deterius
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                nihil.
            Plus nonuis (quamuis corradant omnia) posse,
            Nonuis (cum rapiant omnia) posse minus.
            Ergo eadem scribunt, pucris irrisa fabris
                  
                     
                  
                  que
               ,
            Quae
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                omnis passim nouit &amp; odit homo.
            Cur eadem scribunt, Latij
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                opprobria cultus,
            Anglo ter mittunt proijcienda solo?
            Cur modo pulsa recèns mittūt pellenda, Latini,
            Ac non omniloqui, dogmata vana Petri?
            Esurit externus praelus, praeli
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                magister:
            Haec, inquis, lucri (Sexte) repertavia est.
         
         
            
            To Mayster Shacklock.
            
               
                  BEfore I opē my mouth vnto you (M. Shacklocke) I may do ryghte well to aduertyse the godlye reader in anye wyse not to be ignoraunt of the occasiō by you ministred,Loke maister Shaklockes preface vnto his translation. in your vnaduysed preface and Epistle vnto mayster D. Haddon, that he may duely consyder your deseruinges, and also the necessity of this mine aunswere. Which I wolde willynglye so frame that I might kepe as much within the limites of modestye as you are wythout. And that so much the more, because I easely conceiue, that which I willing lye and dutyfully conceyue, how that these serious mattiers, nay rather diuine and heauenlie misteryes, oughte not by our lewdnesse thus to bee prophaned, turned into Comicall brawles, made quarrelles of contention, &amp; singularity. And yet, lo, these matters of weight, this worde of power, thys

gospell of newenes of lyfe is made so gamesome a thynge, that in steppeth Danus and Syrus to determine beetwene doctours. I speake not now against the libertye of good profession, in any estate or degree, least it myght be saide, I spake againste the knowen trueth. Trueth and sooth it is, that God may be &amp; is glorified by the riche pore, high low, yong olde. But where are facings beyonde reason, tauntes beside occasiō, triumph without conquest, rashe claymes of prerogatiue, assurance of your owne doinges, contēpt of other not onely meant but also blased in writing, in worde vngodlye, in dede vncharitable, vnfruitefull vnto your selues, vnpleasaunte vnto your owne deare frendes, &amp; commonlye laughed at, the Actor thoughe he sweare for him selfe, shall vneth saue his honesty. Wherefore let vs thinke it (as it is) a piece of duetye to speake within a compasse, consideringe that if our owne name and fame be by any man rashlye impugned, we accoumpt it vyolence, we complayn that we are

iniuried. Namely if I should beginne with your beginning (M. Shacklock) and call you as you call your selfe, a morter maker, a durte dawber, a carman or basketbearer, I suppose you wolde thincke I doe you small worship, yet (of a bluntnes) I can skarcelye take you otherwyse then you are. Onely I meruayle who is mayster of the workes in Louayne, that suffreth euery pratyng pioner and inferior labourer to vse his tongue for a pytcheforke, and to bestowe such durty dealynges vpon men of renowmed learning and worthy authority. But that you shall not thinke you haue cast anye man into an agonye, I sende you word from Cambridge, that nothing is so heauely taken, as the whole is vnseemely in a man of your occupation. A labourer quoth you? not in al Erasmus de copia so fitte a title. Euen so (as you haue shewed your selfe) for al the worlde, is operarius taken in Tullie 1. de oratore. There were in Tullyes time, in tharte of Rhetorique certaine vpstartes, which of that excellent science

made nothinge but a vaine clatteringe, &amp; became operarii, that is, not men of learning, but plaine mechanicall or handcraft Orators, lyplabourers. When such artificers steppe in, they geue men occasion to scowre olde rusty prouerbes such as these: A sowe gaue a leape, a popyniay pyped, an asse braied, a match made betwene an Egle and a Iackedawe, a Sowrer aboue his latchet. &amp;c. And this I speak not for your translation, whiche had it not bene (as it is) hemde in with your vngentil and loueles additions, might haue lesse displayed ye imbecillitie of your inuentiō. Me thynks, beinge both an Orator and a Poet, you shoulde not haue bene ignorante that playne dunstable raysing is the sclenderest shyfte in all Rhetorique. Thys your blynde boldenes with so worthy a man (wythout all good proportion as I maye saye) maketh manye men muse who appoynted you for a Captaine, and withall putteth theym in mynde of the olde prouerbe: Multitudo imperatorum Cariam perdidit. While euery

peasaunt matched him selfe with peeces, the whole land of Caria went to wrecke. And yet this is the vayne and preposterous practise of our maisters, Louainers. Vaine in that they thinke a mattier singulerly handled when it is well craked, preposterous in defaminge those persons whose puissance they inespecially dread &amp; feare. Turne your selfe vnto better mattier maister Shacklocke, and as for Osorius hys nerte ishew, doe not so preiudiciallye forspeake it, least you lay to much vppō the mannes shoulders. And if you loue to stick in comparisons, looke ix. degrees lower, and there seeke you a playfellow. As for your lauishing Epistles, if you sente theym for a tast of your witte, I will saye no more, but they haue beene considered. Onely (of modesty) sytte not an vncalled iudge betweene D. Haddon and Osorius, not that you are vnworthye, but for inclination. To be shorte, vnderstand (I praye you) that you are wyshed to goe too some mattier, or if you haue none other faculty but that is already

shewed, to stay your selfe vntyll your muse be better schooled. Surely syr, to say none otherwise then your own catorcozins saye, you haue taken neyther the best way nor the wysest. And the moste mylde excuse that can bee made for you is, that in this doynge, you doe but sauor of the soyle, &amp; fede ye naturall vaine of your aūcientes, Louainers. Whose people blīding plaies &amp; stratagēmes in sowyng of rumors, defaming of the persons, hastninge of prynted papers, myghte not (of reason) so wel lyke them, in that they are but crepitacula, childrens toies. But (by goddes good grace) they shall be seene one by one, and such a vew is already taken of some of them, that none nede bee deceyued, no not the lyttle ones. As for those your dartes in your Preface, or rather presumptiōs of the Religion not yet reuealed vnto you (such as these, the smoke of ignoraūce in England, great flames of heresyes burning mennes soules, furyous fyeres, mistye vales of heresyes, false doctrine, cockryng bote of sismaticall noysomnes, waueryng fantasyes, sydewinde of deuelyshe suggestion, colde northwinde of dyssention

or discorde. &amp;c.) wyth such other largises of your pleasure, and tauntes some of a foote and an halfe long, ioyned with so small shewe of learnyng and aduysemente, haue (I assure you) encroched very lyttle or nothing vnto you, but rather make men now doubt of your knoweledge, and enquire of your maners. As for your learned cō
               parison, I wyll leaue it (in the nexte leafe) to the discrete iudgement of the reader learned and vnlearned, praysing god for this swete lyttle treatise, and (notwithstandyng your vngentle dealinges) requiring nothing but the fruyte of reasonable and godly iudgemente. Whiche that it may not (after your example) be buylded vpon vayne wordes or anye priuate inclynation, more then an orderlye and due conference of both authours. D. Haddon &amp; Osorius, I haue vsed in myne epistle vnto the reader a playne and euident way, such as seemed meete and pertinent in my symple iudgemente, &amp; that (I truste) no man can (without suspytion) defame. Which my doyng so indifferente

and by you forced, I truste D. Haddon will pardon, and consyder the necessitye. Who because he hath ben absent about our Englysh affayres in Bruges aboue the date of your doynges, I doubte fyrste whether he haue hard of you, then whether he wolde haue you ones looked after, or your melancholy any more prouoked. But I truste (euen for gods sake &amp; the symple professours) he will be contente to se how your greate woordes nowe (as from time to tyme) in the triall wil be consumed. Fare you well, from Cambridge
            
               A. H.
            
         
         
            
            ¶THE PREFACE.
            
               IT IS FVLL WELL knowen, that Hieronimus Osorius of Portugal, by the helpe of Shacklocke, speaketh now as plaine English as we our selues, and thincketh to preuayle by course, as much now with the vnlearned, as before with the learned. And so doth he. He deceyueth now his deare frindes on both sides, as well the learned as thunlearned. But it could not otherwise be, and his epistle was not eyther at the first compiled, or at the last translated so much for argumēt as for eloquence. Forsoothe in the vertue of the seuen sciences, they will openly vanquish &amp; confoūde this new founde arte of gospellinge. They fyrst founde out the holly land of Rome by geometry,
                  Looke in m. Shacklockes preface his nedelesse auauncing of his own parti, with the imbacyng of the contrary.
                they laide syege vnto the whole worlde by Cosmography, they tyed together their seruice by Arithmetry, fensed it with bulwarkes of logicke. &amp;c. And now in Retorique they onely passe, euen in master Ri. Shacklocks owne iudgement. As for Diuynitie, I wyll tell you what. it is so handled of .ii. men, in .ii. bookes,

within these .ii. yeres, that better it had bene the gospel had neuer peped out, so many thousandes of protestantes bookes had neuer bene borne, so many hūdreth martyrs had neuer cast awaye theym selues in Englande, the Byble hadde neuer spoken inglyshe worde, S. Paule had neuer vttered his minde so bluntly, the .x. Cōmaundements had neuer perked in the pixis place, the communion table had neuer bene so waueringe and moueable, the churche or tē
               ple of god had neuer ben so prophane for lacke of censyng and sparginge. Yea it had ben better for S. Peter to haue ben Pope of Rome, and to haue left good testimonye thereof. For it shal be proued vnto his face,
                  Vain bostynge rumors commonly sowen by Papysts emong the people.
                yea though it weare neuer so. you will not thincke, you can not ymagine what shall bee proued, more then euer was proued, yea x. tymes more then euer was true. And all this shall come De profundis. Yet there is more, and that I gesse by mayster Shacklocks nedeles translation. No lattin wryter a Papyst but shalbe Englished shortlye, no Englishe wryter a protestant but shalbe confuted, no proofe but shalbe reproued, no reproofe but shalbe proued. Nothing so sone imprinted

but shalbe matched with a contrary printe, nothing wag but it shalbe seasoned on, nothinge so soone set out, but it shall haue an onset. And all in haste, in speede: or elles were all disgraced. Then must the ghospell nedes fall downe, Papistry be hoysed vp and restored againe, rowme made for Idolators througheout all Inglande, letters flye in haste from the M. of the Postes, the sincportes all be spread open, shyppes pressed,
                  As had Vlisses, saylinge towarde Ithaca.
                and a syde winde knytte fast in a woolsack to be ready at an howre. All this may be. For, I tell you, an impossybylitee with a Papyst is no straunge thinge. That is, is not: and that is not, is. And that cannot be, shalbe. And many things are there, that passe our symple wittes. As for example: the Popishe Byshoppes wear endewed with byshoprikes, and were thereof lawfullye defeated, and our Byshoppes are nowe in possession, by as good authority royall warranted, and yet are the Papisticall Byshoppes the dewe owners, yea no man may say, nay: and it hath bene pleaded by the common lawe. For example againe: one Papyst fyndethe deepe faulte with the mouinge and remouinge of the Communion table, and cryeth out vppon thinconstancy

of these protestantes: and yet another for the proofe of his Pyx, may without spotte of vnconstancy alleadge, that here it was hanged vppe, there it was harboured in a Chappell, in some place it was clasped vp in a little shyppe of syluer or gold,
                  M. Shaklockes idle comparisō in his preface.
                and otherwhere otherwyse, To the purpose nearer: Osorius hath shaken all Englande, Osorius hath spoken ynough to turn water into wyne, no man goeth from the reading of Osorius without remorse. D. Haddon he passeth as farre as this passeth that, and nothing passeth I cā not tell what. And yet doubt I not (by the grace of god and pacience of the reader) streight way to proue a contrarye conclusion. And for that purpose haue I collected out of Osorius his whole booke many flowers of this his chiualrye, wherewith in M. Shacklockes simple iudgement he hath so tryūphed ouer the truth, and wonne vnto him selfe the lawrell of all eloquence. VVhich I haue seuerally written that euery man may take thereof a second vew, &amp; (that done) define me eloquence.
         
         
            
            CERTAINE SENTENCES COLlected out of Osorius in Englyshe.
            AFter that by the naughty perswasion, and Bedlem boldnes of some, men for soke that religion whych from the Apostles time, euen to our age hath continued inuincible, that they myghte walke in that path, whych with a shew of licenciousnes did draw foolishe and vnaduised men vnto it, I say, after that thys new deuised religiō was spred abroade by meanes of many sedicious sermons, and erronious bookes, wee haue seene shamefastnes sodenly to be shaken of, honestye to be chased out of the countrye, man hys lawe and God his law to be troden vnder foote, holy things to be prophaned, godlines to be iested at, boldnes euery where to scape scotfree, vnshamefastnes☞ to be maynteyned, many opiniōs contrary one to the other, to be scattred abrode, the vnitye of Chryst to be torne wyth sutes of diuers sectes, and in euerye place where these mad mē haue come, the fier of horrible discord to haue ben blowen vp.
            Out of thys root haue sprong deadly displeasures,☞ often vprores, perilous dagger drawinges: hereof many bloudye battelles haue bene fought, manye slaughters done, manye spoyles commited, many mennes possessions destroyed wyth fyer and sword.
            What crueltye appeareeth in many of them, which haue ben the authors of these opinions, wyth what disdainfull arrogancy do they iette vp and down, with what malipertnes and cursed

speaking they rayle vpon good men?
            ☞Adde now hereunto, the breach of lawes, the contempt of rule, the hatred of kingly authority, the vnmercifull treasons whyche these men most diuelyshly deuise against Princes. Reckē here also, their secrete whisperings, when they cast their heades together how to destroy and vndo their kings, whylst most shamefully they worke their wo, for whose wealth and good estate, they ought to serue and cal vpon God.
            ☞All these people pleasers, for so much as they te men of no wysedome or discretion, but be led with an inordinate desier of libertye, they loue not law, they defye iusticers, they wish in their hearts that kinges were at the deuil, that they wythout controlment might liue as they lyst.
            ☞They couet to be set fre frō law &amp; order, that they may be bōd slaues to their own wil &amp; naughty affectiōs, is there any mā can deny this?
            ☞Doth not euery man see that they shoote all at this marke, that Princes beinge dispatched out of the way, there might be none left which should once say, blacke is their eye? Therefore some kings they haue poisoned, some they haue attempted to kil with the sword, and haue cast manye mischeuous fetches, howe to pull them out of their seat.
            It is the entent and meaninge of this newe deuysed religion, by hooke or by crooke to seke the death of those Princes, which wyl not forsake the religion in whych they haue bene vertuously and wysely brought vp, to come to the

lure of the madde people.
            The ende of this secte, is ouermuche lybertie, whiche can be kepte in no order, then the whiche, nothinge can be more contrary to the office and regiment of kynges.
            The ignoraunte people, so sone as they haue gotten people pleasing captaines, which with their rayling sermons may puffe them vp as it were with windye blastes, and raise mightye waues of folly and madnesse, &amp;c.
            At the last being growne to a headd, it wyll☞ pull kynges oute of their throne, and so when it is to late, they shall se that they haue bredde their owne bane, whiche they shall not be able to remedy when they wolde.
            Doth not this sect euery where styrre vp sedition?☞ doth it not breake the bandes of al iustice and lawes? doth it not resist rule &amp; kyngely regymente? doth it not put al men in hope of to muche lewde libertie? For where is rule most despised? where are the Prynces had in most derision of the common people? surely in those places where this pestilent learning doth gett the vpper hande. Therfore if this madde enterprise taken mischeuously in hande of these people pleasers, and vnaduysedly winked at of Prynces, shall grow to a ripenes, which way so euer it taketh, it wyll quite ouerturne al the☞ defence and strength of kyngly estate.
            This sect is the vndoinge of common wealthes,☞ the marring of good manners, the spoylinge of kingedomes, and the destruction of all

kyngly honour.
            What manner a fellowe was this Luther? surely that I maye speake the beste of him, he was a man neither sobre, neyther dyscrete, but ☞hedlonge, rashe, mischeuous, seditious, and of al other the greatest people pleasure, and what manner of men were they whiche afterwarde spronge out of his schole as out of a well? vndoughtedly, bolde, standinge in their own cō
               ceyte, puffed vp with pryde.
            How commeth it to passe that god now contrary to his accustomed manner, should ouerhip symple and humple men, and shewe theim this newe and straunge light, whiche haue no ☞sparke of shamefastnes or modestie?
            How commeth it to passe, that these fellowes who as it appereth by many tokens, be geuen to worldly delightes, haue onely most wittely spied out that which was vnknowen to so holy fathers.
            They whiche are not to be reuerenced for any notable vertue, be not able to performe that whiche they do pretende.
            O These be men worthy to be wondred at, &amp; with cap and knee to be worshipped.
            They forsoth, haue mortified all their sences with fayth, they haue parted the foule from the body, neither do they onely defye man his nature, ☞but also they despise all the authorities of holy men. For beinge losed from the lynkes of nawghty desyres, they be flowen vp in to heauen, that they may beholde none other thynge

but god, and that they may make none other of their councell but the holy ghost.
            If theyr shameful doinges, do disproue their shameles sayinges, shall we beleue them, so often as they make their vaunt that they follow onely the worde of God?Proue your selfes by this rule. for if in all their doinges they do according to God his word, then they followe not couetousenes, hatred, wrath, ambition, but they be al together made perfect with vertues whiche springe out of the worde of God. If they be not indued with suche heauenly vertues, then do they lie in sayinge, that they only and altogether do frame them selues to the worde of God, for wyckednes and the worde of God can not dwell together. Therfore eyther they direct not theyr lyffe after the worde of god, eyther they do not commyt any abhominable or shameful sinne, for if they sinne shamefully, and abhominably, vndoughtedly they be not squared to the worde of God.
            They committ many heynouse offences and synnes, as all the worlde can witnes, therfore☞ it is false to saye that they be gouerned with God his worde, and the inspiration of the holy ghost.
            Nowe then, I wold wyllingly heare of thē whether these many yeres they haue wrought any notable feate, whiche maye inforce vs to confesse that they ground onely vpon the word of God.
            O say they, we will rushe in to those howses, in whiche holy virgins being inclosed, day

and night do singe hymnes to the glory of god, and praye to Christ for the good estate of kinges and prynces,Many fair wordes, where indeede was the cōtrary and for the sauegarde of the whole communaltie. We wyll pull downe the fences of shamfastnes, we will breake open the inclosures of charitie, and we wyll no longer suffer well fauoured vyrgins to be barred of their solace and pleasures, to lacke the comfort and ayde of their chyldren, and to spende theyr younge yeares in sorrowfull solytarynes, and myserable vnfrutefulnes.
            We will make a lawe for Monkes, or solitarye lyuers, whose howses we will pull downe likwyse, or let theym out to hyer, it skilleth not to what lay men, and charge them vnder paine ☞of deathe that hereafter, none presume for religious sake, to wrastle continually agaynst hys lecherous lustes. For why? It is an heynous offence, and in no sauce to be borne withall.
            Who doeth not see, when the religious rules whiche be conteyned in the Popes constytutions, be taken awaye, that all feare is putte to fiyght, and lycencious lyuing doth reigne with out controlment? As who wold say (say they) we shote at anye other marcke, then to pull all feare out of mennes myndes? For we be the ☞patrones of perfect liberty, and it is so farre of, that we will suffer those whiche be our descyples, to stande in awe of anye thinge, that wee will quite sette them free from fearing of God. For the whiche thinge verely our scollers are muche beholdinge to vs, for it was to sore an

hart breake day and nyght to feare god, and by that meanes, to pine awaye with consuminge carefulnes. Therefore we haue commaunded all those that beleue in Christ, to sette cocke on☞ hoope, and cry care away. For we beare theym in hande, that fayth is of such force, that laying once hande of it, though he be neuer so mischeuous a lyin of the Deuyll, yet he may warrant himselfe the fauour of Christe, and blesse euerlastinge.
            I pray thee, who euer was suche a people☞ parasite, so seruiceable to please the madnes of the common sorte, that he durste be so bolde as to encourage men from fearing of god.
            Such people pyke thanckes, haue oftentymes reiected ye rule of princes, haue disanulled lawes whiche abridged and restrayned the people of their wanton wyshes, with promising them to lyue as they lyste.
            None of them all dyd once open hys mouth,☞ or make any proffer to perswade the people.
            These men from true religion, haue fylched all feare, whiche might kepe menne within the lystes and bowndes of their dutye.
            Oure men, whiche crake that they came out of god his bosome, and knowe all his secretes, do plye the box busely, that they may seale christian☞ men a quittance from all feare of god, and so make them lyke blinde bayardes boldelye to leape into the myar of all myschiefe.
            They seme to haue this drift in their heades, hat they maye stoppe all the highe wayes of

health and saluation, that they which be shackled with any synne, maye haue no safe passage or entraunce. For if they haue shaken of all feare, which of them will syghe for his synnes?
            That faythe, by perswasion of whiche, anye man warranteth him selfe euerlastinge blysse, setting apart sorowfulnes for hys synnes past, leauyng of to doe good workes, and hathe the loue of charitye cleane quenshed in him,Replying vppon a maisterles error. I say that faith, is not worthy the name of fayth, but rather to be called foolishe hardynes, hedlonge hastines, and proude presumptuousnes.
            Moreouer, all men may see that the profyte of wholsome repentaunce, is taken away, that the ardente loue of charitye is made key colde, when menne take this for a sure staffe to leane on, that their synnes be not forgeuen, for theyr mournynge, for their godly sorrowing, for any holy working, but rather that in so doing, they heape newe synnes vpon their olde.
            ☞They take it to be a sinne to lament for their synne, and they holde that no good worke can be done without synne.
            What reason is it, that I for the synne which I dyd not of myne owne accorde (for I was constrained of necessity to do it) shoulde suffer euerlasting paynes? or what ryghte is there, that I shoulde be rewarded with euerlastinge ioy, for that fayth which I kepte onelye enforced and spurred forwarde of god, without any wyll or diligence of my parte? And that which is horrible, and to be detested, if we wyll leane

to these ioly fellowes authority, all the cause of☞ iniquytye is to be laide to God his charge.
            They haue also remoued out of the way for stumblinge, all modestye and obedience, by the whiche all Christyan men did stande in awe of the chiefe ruler of the Church: it hath made all the lawes of the Church of none effect: it hath wyped away the feare of god: it hath chased away sadnes conceyued for synne: it hath grated out the griefe whiche the gylty concyence dyd smyte into mennes myndes for their offences: it hath made men slacke to do good workes.
            The more any man doth applye hym selfe to☞ this doctrine, the wurser he waxeth, the more he flowteth those whiche be plaine and ryght dealing men, the more he is set on fyre with hatred against common peace and quietnesse, and is puffed vp with moste fantastycall vanityes. For he taketh that wysedome vpon hym whiche neuer man coulde yet obteyne. And so standing in his owne conceite, what so euer toy taketh him in the heade, that he so ernestlye doth defende, as if he shulde alleadge any worde cō
               ming out of God his own mouth, with so hedlong boldenes he disquieteth all thinges, as in dede he should seeme to couet nothing more thē to see an hochepoche made of all the worlde.
            They make all thinges in worse case then they founde them: they banishe shamefastnesse, and☞ let carnality raunge lose abroade, and takynge away the feare of God, withoute punishmente they geue men leaue to liue so wickedly as they☞ lyst.
            
               ☞So it commeth to passe, that wilfulnes doth more vehemently burst out, that lecherous lyfe doth more soone consume mennes ryches, that boldenes doth more bragge, and goeth aboute more heynous enterpryses. For what shall I speake, howe daungerous trtuaylinge it is by the high wayes for feare of robbing? what shal I recken the disagreinges &amp; furyous fallinges out whiche raygne euery where? what shall I sett out the conspiracies, treasons, &amp; murders enterprised agaynst Prynces?
            ☞The more this religion encreaseth, the greter offences are committed, and more vnshamefastly attempted euen of those which desyre to be called the disciples of such maysters.
            ☞These men leaning to their owne wytt and inuention, take vppon them to be doctors and teachers.
            ☞These men with their naughty example and lycencious doctrine, doe set mennes teeth more on edge to all kynde of vnhappynesse.
            ☞These men for the most part doe teache their scollers, pryde, crueltye, scoldynge and cursed speakinge.
            ☞These men inioyning no penaunce or penaltye to theym whiche are ioden with synne, doe harten and encourage theym to all vnshamefastnesse.
            ☞These menne do surrender their scollers fast bounde to bodely delyghtes, to the entent they may wayte, and geue attendaunce vppon their lecherous lustes.
            
               These men, for so muche as euery one accordyng☞ to hys owne fyckle fancye, dothe blab out and tell for trueth what so euer he doth dreame of, and by meanes of that are dispersed into dyuerse &amp; innumerable sectes, they breake peace, they rayse vppe debaytes, and procure bloodye battayles.
            They put out all shamefastnes and religion,☞ and they enter no sooner into anye place, butte straight way contempt of lawes buddeth out, wantonnesse, wilfulnes, madnes, crueltye, and other myschiefes do corrupt good maners, and rayse vprores and hurly burlyes amonge men, haue they such brasen faces, that they dare once open their mouth, and speake of the Ghospell?
            What other waye is their into heauen, but☞ that whiche is opened with good workes, and wyth excelent innocencye of lyfe.
            He which vnder the name of godlynes, doth striue agaynst the exercyse of godlynes, and dedes of charitie, doth not leade vs to euerlasting lyfe, but bloweth the cooles of vnquencheable fyre, intendinge to make vs roste meate for the dyuell.
            They quite them from of all feare, which be defyled with soule synnes, and they warrante all them whiche be at dagger drawynge wyth godlines, that all thinges shall chaunce well &amp; luckely vnto them.
            Whiche of them to the intent he might turne away the destruction hanginge ouer his deare frendes, hath with many teares bowed god to

take mercie?
            ☞Whiche of them dyd euer burne so with charytie, that for the lyfe of other he wolde offer him selfe to deathe?
            Neyther the Prophetes, neyther the Apostles, neither other most holy men, whom God did make partakers of his councels, haue come to that degree of moste highe perfection, wyth leadinge their life in suche pleasures, as these deintie toothed and sugresop gentlemen be delighted with all, but rather in marueilous and excellent holines of maners, in incredible sharpenes of lyfe, in many laboures, watchinges, prayers, wepinges, in suche egre desyre of heauenly thinges, in suche feruente charitie, that they desyred to be kylled, and to be tormented with most greuous peines, so that other might ☞be saued. Of the whiche vertues, where as these men haue not one sparcle, but lyue so, that it may appeare by many tokens, that they take delight in those pleasures whiche the common sorte of men do couet, and that they be geuen to those entisementes, and prouocations, whiche naturall appetite doth greatly desire. &amp;c.
            If by meanes of this religion, rashenes, vnshamefastnes, vnclenlines of life, dothe more boldely flye rounde about, if vntollerable pride and arrogancie be much more established then it was before, if seditions, contentions, &amp; fallynges out, be more easely stirred vp, if traytours be more ventrouse to laye violent hands vpon their Kinges, and to laye wayte howe to

murther their prynces, if neyther shame, neyther☞ feare, neither awe of God his displeasure, can hold them from doinge of mischiefe, which haue yelded theim selues vppe to this newe doctrine.
            This learnynge, suffereth the lustes to run☞ at ryot, and that whiche is next dore to it, prouoketh hedlonge to all kinde of wyckednes.
            This puffeth vp mennes hartes with pride, and teacheth them to despyse all antiquitie, auncient religion, and holynes of olde tyme.
            This learning dothe breake peace, and teareth the body of Christe his churceh, with inwardly consuminge and wasting sedition.
            They disagree with them selues moste inconstantly, they to daye holde one opinion,In mouīg and remouing the Communion table. to morrow an other, cleane contrary one to an other, and can not rest longe in one minde, and that is the deuylles duetie, to scatter and pull a sundre, those which agree well together, and to breake the bande of all faithfull and fryndly fellowshippe,
            Seing the doctrine of these goodly Gospellers, doth rayse vpprores, dothe breake peace, doth spred one secte into innumerable sectes, &amp; causeth one secte to be at defiaunce with the other, is it not playne that their religion is not drawen by Christ his rule, but all together is inuented accordinge to the crafty deuise of subtyll Sathan.
            What greater argumente can we haue, then their deadly hatredes, their contencions, theyr☞

stamblinge by the eares, their tauntinges and ribauldry raylinges,
            ☞They haue this fetche, that they maye quyte take away all the knowledge of god.
            They so farre leape ouer the lynes of vngodlynes, that they not onelye hate the Crosse of Chryst, and in steade of God worshippe theyr owne lustes and wickednesse, but also beleue that the lord and Creator of all thinges, whose powre and ryght iudgementes, euen the deuelles in hell and damned soules doe feare, eyther ☞not to be, or elles not to rule and gouerne the whole worlde?
            Alas, they are so farre gone in madnes, and tumbled heedlong into all folly, that so often as it taketh them in the heade, with wicked wordes, ☞they scoffe and mocke those thinges, which be written of god his iudgemēts, as though they were but Canterbury tales and grym visardes onely deuised to fray yong children.
            ☞Certeinly that religion which causeth pride, prouoketh anger, letteth the lustes lose, defyleth the soule with synne, taketh away shamefastnesse, remoueth the feare of God, worketh treason against kinges, troubleth comon peace, bloweth the cole of hatred, thrusteth our myndes downe to the earthe warde, and drowneth them in the seas of worldely troubles, is no religyon, but false, pestilent, and damnable.
            Alluring the people with a iolye shewe of to much lyberty, it armeth them agaynst officers, agaynst their kinges authority and regiment,

and hardenth the hartes of the multitude with a false perswasion of Religion.
            If it did only procure destruction of kings, so that it brought no daunger and damnation to the soule, and by all meanes didde not ouerthrow the lawe of God, it were some thing to be wrne wythal. But this is greatlye to be lamented,☞ it putteth oute the loue of vertue, the brightnes of honesty, the light of most true religion and deuocion, defileth all commendable comlines with vnpure liuing, and vtterly stoppeth vs for entring into euerlasting glory.
            There is no more sworne enemy to Prynces,☞ then that is: besibe thae, it doth vndoo ye people which couet it, and spoyleth them of all lyberty.
            I haue plainlye proued, that by meanes of☞ this religion, men be entised to wantonnesse, to vnshamefastnes, to vnlawfull lustes, that troublesome tumults and dissentions be stirred vp, that manye naughtye enterprises bee taken in hand, that inumerable mischiefes be forged, and last of all, that the remembraunce of godlinesse is quite blotted out.
            They haue not only left the Christtan common weale vnheled, but also wheresoeuer they came, they haue bestowed their trauell to thys☞ end, (chat if there were any helth in it) to take it away, and to infect all the members of Christ his Church with most vncurable diseases and maladies.
         
         
            
            The Preface.
            THus, reading M. Shacklockes tryumph in the behalfe of Osorius and other hys leaguelowlers, ioyned with so vniuersall disabling of all gospellers and namely D. Haddon, I thought good to make this search, which I haue here set before all mennes eyes, takynge the beginning therof at Osorius his first proposition or entrance vnto his mattier, and so continuinge the chase vnto his pytyfull conclusion. Which collections runne so much on one figure called Rixa or Conuicium, &amp; are such declamatorie and generall stuffe, that a man maye trulye say, they haue one especial property, that is, they may serue more martyrs then one. For euen so, as he in these his centons or fragmentes impugneth our religion, might he thunder against Herostrotus for burning the Temple of Diana, euen so against the wilfull murther of Orestes, Nero, Mithridates, Cambises: euen so against the sensualitye of Xerxes or Sardanapalus: against whom and what he pleased, euen so. besides that in diuers places he merueilously mistaketh our doctrine, beating downe manfullye that we neuer set vppe, like a counterfeyt Hercules, making monsters vnto him selfe whiche

he may easely vanquish, and so losynge his dayes labour to the greate pitie and compassion of the godly reader. thus much (and what so euer elles) whether it may bee trulye saide or no, let other men iudge. This I dare depose, that there is not halfe so much here vttered, as is forced by thimportunity of his Subscriptor M. Shacklock. In the whole what I haue pretermitted (that excepted which you shall here fynde by D. Haddon confuted) let euery man loke. fewe Doctors (I warrant you) or scriptures, which in Osorius his Epistle are very straunge gestes (and as they sticke not commonlye to say, in that engyne of pollycy needed not. Which his Epistle so trusting (as you wold say) vnto a mother strength, al good helpes of Scriptures, Doctours, or coū
               celles set aparte, for eloquence so well thought of, by the trāslatour so priced, &amp; that syngeth in the eares of all Papistes so incōparable harmony, (for so much therof as I haue layd together in my preface) I dare auouch it to cōteine so nedeles braules, idle &amp; friuolous replyes, cō
               trarietye with goddes holye worde .iii. fowle faultes, regardinge eyther the man or the martyer, that (as you maye see in the margine,) I

thought them worthy to be poynted at. Whyche .iii. whether they be there to be founde or no, I besech the reader to looke, freelye deposinge that I haue in those collections vsed plain dealing, not chaunging or adding one iote, onelye here and there pretermitting that I thought needelesse. What I haue done is all for Mayster Shacklockes sake. I will not go farre, nor vtter that whyche I hardelye conteyne, onelye for Mayster Shackelocke a lyttle curtesye. Nowe in good faythe, haue I not for his good comparison, verye good occasion to take one of his funeral verses,
                  The beginninge of a brainsicke verse of in. Shacklockes. of the buriall of b. Scot, in Louain.
                and sing Hei mihi ridiculis? What no comparison? not of charitye? not so much as a wyde comparison? no fauour? no bowelles of mercy, but starke naught in comparison of you and yours? I feare me I see your face and facyng euen through your vysard. I se how all men see, that at Louaine it hath bene agreed on, not to sticke for craking, I se, (that is, is not) a prouerbe that will neuer fayle in them. Yet haue we one veine of comfortable bloud, that they shal neuer perswade al, neuer shal the deuill go further then his cheine. They may doo what they will and can. Their bokes and bodyes

haue they and must haue at scope vnder Antichrists banner, according vnto the Prophecyes, and wide woundes both in word &amp; dede must we beare for a time. Yet of modesty, let not M. Rich. Shacklock so churlishlye set him self against M. D, Haddon, euery peasant against euery Peere, euery iangler against euery sage, euery shackled Papist against euery good Gospeller. O, this is a secure perswasion, &amp; the high way to blind bussardly boldnes, some thing to say and to thinke wel of them selues. And this rule (I may say) is now wel taken vp. Els wold not such a man as M. Shacklock, hauinge seene such streames of bloudshed in his natiue country, of poore pined Protestants,
                  An other of Maister Shacklockes funerall verses, lackīg nothing but witt &amp; mattier.
                haue crossed ouer the seas, &amp; there haue piped vp: Haeresis effuso nondū satiata cruore. That is: Haeresy hath not yet droncken bloude ynoughe. Neyther wolde Osorius euer haue wasted winde wyth this vayne question, whiche of vs euer offered hym selfe vnto deathe. Osorius I saye, alwayes ignorāt in our English affaires,
                  M. Dorman that for lacke of great fyndeth smale faultes in D. Haddons boke.
                although a feere and friend of his will take stomack if he be so termed. Wherein I remember who leaped at a fly, and catched nothing fast in his teeth. Euen

that yong Caluinist and old Papist that vouchsafed to call the History of their owne late tyrannye, a doūghill of stinking martyrs. A thing soone sayde. And yet is that notable cronicle (so lightly tearmed) such a monument as shall vnto the worldes ende, not with wordes, but liuely recordes of tormentes, imprisonment and horrible murther of good persons and vertuous refute all their lyppe labour. Auaunt with thys your barkynge after your bloudye bittes, you monstruous howlyng wolues. You haue by your accursed crueltye geuen mattyer vnto that hystory which now maketh you to yerne, which causeth your teeth to grate &amp; chatter in your mouthes. You your selues made those Antychristian fyers, you behelde the naked bodyes burning so long as the synewes wolde contein them, and now they are all lyes, or elles you are lyers. Which registers and rowles of your Cains actes, require and chalenge, by stronge reason, to bee beleued, because they bable not Romyshe bastarde miracles comminge after the date, but testifye vnto all generations to come thaccusations, tormenting and tossing of good men by the hande of their stepmother the fleshe and

the world, from piller to post, frō pain &amp; agon
                  •
                vnto death. Whiche thynges are suche as dayly happen, and are commonly practised of the euil against the symple and iuste. Whereof also are witnesses yet lyuinge infinite, and partlye that were partakers of the same in their fleshe and bloude, hauing sette aparte all will and vanitye of lying and fablinge, muche vsed in tymes past of the wanton and idle Cloisterers. Who being alwayes warme and quiet, nor hearing of anye such blusteringes and tempestes, turned theym selues vnto lewed &amp; light inuentions, the right fruites of munkishe ydlenes. Nowe sir, what bitchfox was it that bibbed vp all the bloude? heresy. heresy? what meane you by that, papystry? no mary, but the ghospell so called. Fy, M. Shacklock, for pure shame. Mentiris egregiē. the ghospell (I dare say) hath bene a sower maistres: Haec vapulando illa verbarando, vs
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , amhae defessae sunt. Charme your rauing muse vntil she be sober and vtter truthes. Play not the hypocrite thus bothe to byte and whine. As for cruor (that is bloude) it is the papistes peculier and lineal badge. Popelinges they are of whom it is written: Effuderunt sanguinem sanctorū
                  
et in eo inebriati sunt: They shede the bloud of sainctes, and sucked thereof, vntill they wear droncken. We sillye soules on thother syde alwayes suffring, and euer forbearing, the sworde now put into our handes, strike not one stroke, being content to beare in our banner the fishe called Gladiolus, a sworde fishe, whiche hath growing in his forehede a long sworde, but he lacketh a hart, he woūdeth not, he striketh not, ne profereth one blowe. But let go the rest, and winke we at the rest of that licencious stile. I beseche thee (good reader) to accepte this my translation of M. D. Haddon against M. Hieronimus Osorius, &amp; to gather by dew conference of euerye percell, all dewe and Christian fruite. Consideringe that all payne eyther of wrytinge or translating is employed to quench thy thirst, and to geue the a depe tast of that swete worde which must be thine endeles comfort. And let it not come to passe, that when the incessante payne and trauaile of godly learned men desyryng euen to sweate their bloude for thy sake, tendeth all vnto thine edifying and instruction, thou stil continue deafe &amp; blind, tarying nothīg but goddes vengeaunce and wrathe perpetuall.

So both reade and heare, that thou kepe one eis fixed on the worde of god, who is thy best father &amp; wil not beguile thee. the sonnes of men are deceitfull, but god is truth. Neyther attend vnto the preachinge Papist, that monstrous Sphynx, which hath already beaten &amp; boūced thee with the stone in one hand, and now offreth bread with the other. Take hede, I say, of that bread. it is offred with the left hād. Repose thy trust in god, &amp; take vnto thy soules vse that parcell of his deuine pleasure, that is conteyned in this lyttle treatise. Fare well and remember to worshyppe in spyrite and truthe. Dat. at Cambridge the .xxvij. of May. 1565.
            
               Abraham Hartwell.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            GVALTER HADdon Englishe vnto Hieronimus Ossorius a Portugall wysheth healthe.
            
               I 
               Haue perused your epistle, mayster Hieronimus, whiche is directed principally vnto the Quenes most excellent Maiestie, but (in that it is in prynte and walketh cōmonly in euery mans hand) towcheth all vniuersally. You are (I confesse) in wordes and sentences a lykely workeman, and thervpon haue presumed accordyngly, that you a pryuate man, disneighboured from vs by sea and lande, &amp; in our affayres vnacqueynted, haue so homelily opened your mouthe

vnto the Quenes highnes, streyned the aucthoritie of our lawes, &amp; charged our whole realme with a certaine vngodly &amp; lothed newnes. Wherfore you must of reason pardon mee, that I an Englishe man borne, one of the quenes maiesties suppliauntes, &amp; enfourmed in my countrie fashions, do make you aunswere, and vse my penne somwhat franckely, not so muche vpon an angry pange, or a bytter contentious harte, as to correcte this your mistakīg of the englishe state, sprōge of false surmises, and to restore the truethe vnto them, whō peraduenture this your letter hath peruerted. And to geue you plaine vnderstanding that I am not blowen vppe with anger, but of duetie moued, I confesse

your kynd of writing worthy singular cōmendation, and besydes gyue you thankes that (beyng so well endewed) you haue extolled our renowmed Quene, whose excellencie althoughe it farre surmount the heapes of your praise, yet a forraine testymonie beautyfied with eloquence, no doubte is very plausible. Of thestate of a Monarchie you play the Phylosopher handsomly within the bā
               des of knowledge, &amp; reason deepely of the choyse of Religion, but sir, in both you haue a foule fault, that is, ouercharging &amp; beatinge our eares with thynges vulgarely knowne, and plentie of proofes where no doubt is. This waye fyrst taken, your penne by stealthe crepeth on to the purpose, namely

to rifle such religion as (by your saying) we haue receyued. And, lo, howe in the very entrance you wittingely trippe, or rather take a cleane fall throughe grosse ignorance of our English customes, fatherynge vpon the multitude &amp; common people the ratefyinge of our Religion authorised by publike decree, and feyning the exclusion of the Royall estate from affayres of the Churche. Where as with vs it is an vnfallyble custome, that no lawe come forthe wherevnto the whole common wealthe shall stande bounde, bu
                  •
                the people fyrst geue their voyces therevnto, secondely as well the temporall nobilitie as the clergie do subscribe, &amp; last of al the prince confyrmeth it. The contrarye if

any man haue whispered in your eare, then are you both in faulte, he for his lowde lye, and you for swift credit. But if you haue builded this out of your own braine, to disfygure our lawes as rawe &amp; halting, inuented of peasauntes, I may saye it was doone of small curtesie, before you haue geuen vs halfe a tast of your matter, to blow out vpon our englishe lawes so heynous a slaunder. Then followeth a weyghty and strong supplication to the quenes grace, that if you can by sounde reason and open profe lay before hereies in religion what is pure &amp; vnleauened, that then her grace wolde not be so stif and vnmoueable, but yelde her selfe, acknowledge the blasing light of the trueth, and be

contented of you to be guided out of the wyndinge by walkes of errour. Herein you speake reason, and therfore I require the lyke of you, that if I trie this your accusacion to cōteine more wrangling then good argument, lesse trueth then stomacke, double malice for syngle reason, no fryndely conference grounded on religion, but a plaine taunt cōpounded of slanderous wordes, hereof when I haue made a solemne proofe, that then I may geue free sentence of you, that you are too busie a seruitour in a forrein Realme, vnaduisedly carpynge, where no man knoweth lesse then you. You step in with a deadly complaint, exaggerate with most select and precious wordes, how certaine routes

of men (God knoweth who, and where they be) haue reuolted frō the apostolike trueth, and fetched in a newe fayth, a straunger vnto vs, craking of lybertie, yea suche a one, as is moste pestilente, swelling with the waues of mischifes out of all number. Then fall you vppon the authours therof, ouer whom you thunder and lyghten with suche thicke flasshes &amp; taunting terrible clappes, as though they were in earthe of all other most detestable. Where are these your monstrous babes of Religion? whiche be they? howe longe haue they contynued? or howe might I come to the knowledge of them: where are such wonders to be founde vnder the shape of mē? what do they, how do they?

howe did you fyrst knowe them? Certifie vs of the thinges, pointe to the persons, subscribe the time leaue not out one circūstance, that we maye haue some sure grounde to pitche vpon, and so to susteine your encountringe. You hallowe as loude as you can againste religiō, with her capitaines you will fyghte, you speake bitterly vnto both, and are content to shew vs neither of them, what it is, wher it is. This your accusation is to be pitied, which if I dashe in the teethe with one contrary worde, must nedes commend it felfe vnto silence. You crye, naye you make an outcrie, and that ful ruthfully, that there is a fourine of religion newely admitted, accursable, detestable, abhominable, whose authours

are vnhallowed persons, ruffyans, sorcerers, vndoers of common wealthes, and professed enemyes of mankynde. I on thother syde do depose that there is nothinge lesse, I credite you not, I demaunde your proofe. Nowe what saye you? what proue you? You crye with open mouth, there is no wyckednes but you haue ye termes of it, which (I smell) you had gathered together, therwith to deface your imagined Religiō, and to wounde suche persons as no man knowethe but your selfe. Nowe surely, to disquiete with suche chaunge of tauntes, euen to the princes face, the most famous Isle in Christendome, to you vnknowne, vpon the false ianglyng either of our ilwillers or your parasites,

and not to determine eyther the cryme or persons, argueth in a man small aduisemente, &amp; foule mispending of time in belyinge of other. But to go further: you terme this our Secte by the name of a people pleaser, cauilling that they do not subdue vices, but set men on fyre with sensualitie, yea with madnes, and that there are examples enough of their sorcerie and treason against princes. A horrible allegation, yea a detestable kinde of men, if there be any suche liuinge. If there be no such at all, then great is the rashnes of thaccuser, in an estate wholsomly setled, to rayse suche vpperores. Mary (to speake a trueth) now that you haue vncouered vnto mee this platte of poysoninge

and conspiracies, looking a lyttle backe vnto the recordes and hystories of our predecessours, I beginne to call to mynde Henry the fourth of that name, Emperour, vnto whom a Moncke of monstrous and wicked monckysh crueltie, euen in their late godefyed Eucharist ministred poison, whervpon he died, and whose counsell was intermedled herein, the hystories do tell. By the lyke accursed enterpryse of the like ghostlye person, was king Iohn of Englande murthered, as our Cronycles do testifie. But to sticke in the recitall of particulers, especiallye vnto you, is nedeles, who borderynge nearer vpon such practises then I, maye of likelyhod, with more speede learne out of the Registers

of your neere neighbours, what poysoned drafts haue walked too and fro, betwene the supernatural demigods and proude patrones of the Romish churche, and howe or by whom the pryncypall seede of warres haue bene sowen throughout all Realmes christened. But I wil not procede in accusatiōs as you doe, nor vrge you with suspicions, but in moste humble sort wyll lift vp my handes vnto the euerliuing god, soū
               dinge out vnto hym all thankes possible, that hath vouchesafed to putte a side the depe mistes of the former tymes, with the sonnlyght of hys gospell rysen vppe emong vs, through thignoraunce whereof, and former affiaunce in blinde superstition we wallowed

in the syncke of synne wythout any remorse, thinkynge all to be raunsomed, what so euer we did in our lyfe wickedlye, by a leaden charter of popish pardon, and the muttringe of prayers whiche we vnderstoode not. Then came the authoritye of the holy scriptures, thundrynge at the doore of oure eares, and sente into our consciences such shiuering and feare, that nowe we fixe our whole trust and ankerholde in the free mercye of God, all humaine inuentions reiected and set a part, alwaies hauinge an eye to the counsell of the Prophete, to fashyon &amp; shape our conuersation vnto holynesse and righteousnes. Whiche being so, I meruaile what should be thende of your tedious discourse vnto the

Queene wherein you wyshe all Prynces to prouide and to bee in continuall watche, least throughe this newe borne secte (not yet by you well expressed) they treade awry. Doubt you not but that our Royall Queene is surely enough planted in al prosperity, &amp; louyng her people is eftsones loued, felinge not one breath of these stormes which you harp vpō. Other cōmon welthes haue taken their rest, and presentlye I truste are in quiet. I knowe nothing vnto the contrary, vnlesse you obiecte the late broyle in Fraunce, whiche now is appeased, and whence the firste blaste thereof came it is a thinge sone toulde. but sithe you name nothing, let it goe. There ensueth in your treatise a vulgare

and olde beaten quarrell of the frailetie of this present lyfe, whiche your aduise is to contempne, &amp; to make a way vp into heauen, to set the world farre from vs, to thende we may attaine vnto euerlasting felicitie. Then fall you into admiratiō, that herein we wil cleaue vnto newe shepeheardes, where as in your mynd, the olde may suffice. yet are you contente to suspende your verdicte, &amp; that inquiraunce be made of our grene Pastors newely chopped in, whiche wil in no wise be coūted newfangled, taking vppon them (the schoolemēs drowsy dregges wyped away) to scoure &amp; clense the Churche, and to trymme it vppe according to thinstitutiō of the apostles, so to represente vnto all

Christendom the veritie founded in the gospel of Iesus Christ, this longe tyme ouermaistered by couetise and ambitiō, to blase with the starry brightnes of holy scripture gods glory so darkned with mannes dreames and fansies, to vndoe the yoke of superstition, &amp; fynally to reedifie the sincere worshyp of god after thauncient rule &amp; discipline of ye primitiue church. These mennes profession you so well lyke, that you loute &amp; scorne their enterpryse: these be they whom you vex and tosse at wyll, one while scoffing, another while fuming, nowe cryinge, and then yellyng out. Very well. Now at length I see what new secte you meane, againste whom you haue so busylye discharged and let flye

all this eloquence. I haue nowe espied your aduersaries, whō you must needes haue pruned of, and cast on the dounghill, as the very poyson of a common wealth. Me thinckes on the cōtrary side, that these preachers of the gospell are the seruantes of the hyghest god, sent euen of God him self, to quicken our assedlike slouth in these slyppery tymes and latter cast of the world, to spurre our loytring, to refute our falshode, &amp; to checke and taunte our wickednes. And therfore such men ought to be serched out of the prynce, and had in estimation througheout the common wealth. Se what differēce is betwene your opinion &amp; myne. Wherfore we must march on, and consyder what you, (a graunde

doctour for a prynce forsothe) can eyther alledge truely, or vntruely forge against gods reuerende ministers and seruauntes. And although (as it may be,) this slaunder procede of some other: yet shal you beare double blame for rashe credite, and more rash puttyng of the same in wrytyng. I wyll not trauise all the corners of your accusation, which almost powreth out nothinge but an vnfruitefull ringing in peinted wordes. Onely I wyll runne ouer your chiefe pointes, and, if I be able, shake the verie pillers of this your accusation. Fyrst you say there muste be note taken of the persones, bycause they promise franckely, and tryall made what their habilitie is, what pith they haue, what is

their vertue and integritie of lyuinge. Then you demaund whether in godly life they be more absolute then Athanasius, Basill, Ambrose, Hierome, &amp; Augustin weare. I wis there are many of them of incomparable learnynge and most godly demeanour, and I see nothynge you brynge, why they may not be equal with these auncient sages. But to bring you out of your odyous comparisons, me thincke you moue an vnreasonable question in an vnfyt place. For I auouch that these our preachers whollie agree with those reuerende fathers, treade in the same pathe, and exhibite all one tenour of Religion. If this be so, then make you a vaine comparyson betweene them that be frendes,

if it be otherwise, enfourme vs wherin they disagree. S. Austine lamēteth that his time was so drowned with flouddes of ceremonies, that christians were thē in worse case thē were the iewes before them. Saincte Hierome wyssheth that the sacred scriptures, whiche were in your churche so locked vp &amp; smoothered, should be learned by harte both of weomen and children. S. Basill employed all possible leysure vppon that good worke of learning and also teachinge the gospell. And if the pampered Monckes of oure tyme had lyued in sainct Basiles order, they had not ben once touched. Athanasius his creede standeth in ful estimation, &amp; betwene hym and our men no squarynge.

But I thincke I maye be boulde to kepe these our auncients in reuerence, vntyll you brynge contrary euidence. Of those auncient fathers of the churche, seinge your selfe able to bringe nothinge but their naked names, remembryng your self, you passe ouer vnto the men of our age, and leaping firste vpon Luther, you teare the dead man in pieces, firste callyng hym blinde hassard, then a people pleaser, &amp; last (for your pleasure) starck staring madde. This man of god whom you so falselie charge with frenseie, in open auditorie and in presence of Charles themperour, exhibited a sober &amp; discrete soome of his faithe. This franticke fellowe in spite of all the wyseste of your Churche, stoode all salfe and

haile the space of .xxx. yeere, they notwithstanding all raginge and cauing for his deathe. Erasmus giueth this lunatike man no base record of innocencie in these wordes: Luthers doctrine many doe defame, his life al men extol with one consent. You say moreouer he was popular. How expound ye that? If you call hym popular that carketh &amp; careth for the peoples health, then no man is more. If you meane a prycker of rashe lightnes amonge the communaltie, reade his booke wherein he controuleth and taunteth the vprores in Germanie, &amp; leaue your slaundering. And that men may not thincke you haue played this naughtie parte onely in Luther, you recite other as though, after

you haue spoken the worde, they were straighte way transformed out of pereles godly mē into most vyle vyllaines. Emong other I wil name you two principall professours of the gospell, Martine Bucer, and Peter Martyr, which of goddes good gyfte, arryued in this Ilande: Let all our cankerd enemies laye together their heades. Let se what one thing euen malice it selfe can note in these reuerend graues amisse. O golden couple of greyheadded fathers of most happye memorie, of whose learninge right good witnes we haue, euen the bookes by them compiled. whose pure conuersation so many commende, as euer happened into their company. Wherfore (if you be wise) temper

your tongue, and stay your style, and take heede of inconuenience. Deeme not them so largely to be presumptuous persons, vnaduysed, and lofty, sithe there is a nū
               ber of theim well knowne, then whom nothing can be foūd, more milde, sober, and aduised. Two I haue named, the like testimony mighte I geue of whole hundrethes. But the sobre conuersation of two persons, bruted farre and nere, maye plentifullye refell one particular mans rash and shameles cauillation. Then againe you make transition vnto our mens doctrine, mislykinge therein that they vrge nothing but scripture, they call to counsaile nothing but the holy ghost, reiectynge and abandoning all humaine authorytie.

who if they dyd as you saye, they shoulde therin treade in the very steps of our sauiour Christe, thapostels, and olde fathers that were in the infancy of the church. But it is farre otherwise. They do sorte and chuse out the assertions of al approued interpretours of all ages, as declare their bookes, whiche are able vnto all the worlde to detecte this your falsehood. You scoffe graciousely, and (in your own fansie) prosecute an inuincible reason against such perfectnes of liuing, as our men take vpon them selues, which you say by their abhominatiō is hourely reproued. Vntrue it is that they presume any iote beyonde manns strengthe, and thother is an olde slaunderous cast, to defame men,

not opening any one spot of theyr vncleannes. Name it if you can, what so euer it be, worthy this your stormie and vehemēt replie. If you can not, leaue for shame, so pestilently to tatle against the reputation of moste graue persons. You require to haue it specifyed, in what one pointe our men haue refourmed thestate of the church. I neede not tell you▪ you name enough your selfe, sauing that we differ in meaning. You laye vnto our charge that Nunnes &amp; Monkes cloystered to attende the seruice of God, &amp; to continue in chastitie, are now let out and fully licenced to all wyll: that their palaices are openly cried to sale, and howe lawes are come forth, that vnto luste there be no let in Religion.

O hoorishe impudencie in lyeng, and wyll lawles beyonde measure. We graunte, and that freelie, that vpon aduertisement of our pastors, we let fal vnto the ground those dennes of stincking poyson, wherin were pestered vp young wenches and syllie boyes, to suche ruine of vertue in theim, as for shame I can not discouer. What was there in those shamefull shoppes of synne, but onely a pharisaicall length of seruyce in a straūge tongue? as for other their misteries they most liuelily resembled vnto vs the droncken hollie daies of Bacchus. Wherevppon God (no doubte) stirred vppe the mindes of our countrymen, that these infynite routes &amp; swarmes shrowdynge in secrete corners of

abhomination should be rowsed, by their exhortations, from slepe to worcke, from vice to vertue, &amp; from their horryble practyses of fornication vnto lawful wedlock. Not that we enioin any cōstraint of maryage, but plucking our consience out of the yoke of mannes traditions, we restore the lybertie of ye gospel, wherin the authoritie of Iesus christ hath planted vs, by the warrant of his worde. Of their howses there were bestowed to good and godlye vse of scholes, vniuersities &amp; hospitals. with the reste lawfull order was taken, leste the swynishe generation shoulde once agayne tumble in their durtie dunghilles. This was a worthy &amp; singular blessing of god, wherby there is more abbridged

of the hellishe tyranny of Sathan, then by al your canons, layinge them all together. You weepe ouer the pluckinge downe of ymagerie and tableworke, whiche monumentes once displaced, you affirme that ther is nothing lefte to enflame our spirites vnto the contemplacion of heauenlye thinges. We on thother syde remembring the grosse ignoraunce euen of late tymes, sorely mistrust dotage in idolatrie, agaynste the whiche there are playne textes, yea the gospel geueth vs a watch worde concerning ymages. Whiche were it not to be passed vpō, yet among Christians ought the written worde of our lord Iesus Christ, to beare great sway, whiche pronounceth that God is a

spirite, and that they stand in the right way of praier that worship in spirite and trwethe, and suche beadmen the Lord loueth. This is the moste wholesome waye of praying, if we consider eyther the originall or ende of it, which needeth not thundersettinge of these outwarde ceremonial thinges, so to clime vppe vnto the throne of God the father. Nay while our outward Adam is to much occupied, about these superficial stuffe, the inward mā waxeth keiecold, drincketh in the venemous ioice of a basterdlie Religion, forgoeth the sounde fruite of heauenly meditation. Let vs bind vp al with examples: The former auncient churche of apostles and martirs had none of these your costly iewelles,

&amp; yet was there most whot zeale burnynge in their breastes. In baser times of religiō, by fote and foote in stepped peintrie, and so died in the former loue of gods seruice yt was so kendled in mens harts. At last rushed in the scholemens diuinitie by whole cartloades, a birde of an other nest, ouglie mishapen with superstition: anon all places were stuffed with peinted stockes and idolls, which being euery where risely worshipped, the true &amp; spirituall honour of God was troden vnder foote. Nowe powre out your Philosophie concerning the weakenes of oure capacitie, extoll youre holy blockes vntil you sweate withal, yet is this deepely groūded in the scriptures, that the vndoubted

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
knowledge of god is in his worde, and sincere worshyppinge in spyrite. As for your pyctures, where the spyrite is present they neede not, where that wanteth they auayle not. It were a tedious matter for you to make of euery thyng a seuerall discourse, and therefore with one breath you say that all holly seruice, ceremonies, and sacramentes ar by vs cleane sacked and destroyed. What is it that I heare? Is there lyuing any such broode of diuynes, that spoyleth and destroyeth all holly seruice, al ceremonies, all sacramentes? Either it is so, orels muste this bee, as it is in deed, a shameful excesse in lying. For forreine Churches I can gage nothinge, but I haue a good opinion of them? Of our

orders in diuine affayres I wyll make you a briefe accōpt, not suffring you eyther to be ignoraunt youre selfe, or to bewytche other. First (bycause fayth commeth by hearing) we send into al coastes of the Realme Preachers to edifye the people in their duties toward God, and to enstructe them in the true worshipping of ye same. Thē haue we an order of commō prayer collected out of Scriptures, by Parliament (for so we terme the consent of the three estates of our Realme) authorised, frō the whiche we suffer no man to wander, forseing (wyth all diligence) two pointes, fyrst the holy ghost to be obeyed, warning that whosoeuer open his mouth in the congregacion, speake the worde of God, secondly

that in al things be found an vnity wythout dyscorde. The sacramentes we cause to be ministred very precisely after the prescript of holy writ, and the liuely paterne of the former Churche, wherin the Lorde Iesus Christe first in his own person instituted them with his Apostles. And all these are propoūded in ye vulgare toung, for that it is a brutish folly and plainly excepted in the testament, in the presence of God to clatter out that wee vnderstande not our selues. The geuing of orders, hallowing of wedlock, churching of childwiues, visitynge of the feble, and burying of the dead corses, we execute with solemne and publike rites according to ye veritye in the Gospell, whych we

spice with ceremonies so far forth as al things may procede in order and decently within oure Churches, as we are certainly aduertised out of the gospel. Of ye times, places, dayes &amp; other circumstances, we haue made no alteration, neither in the whole body of religion innouated anye thing, but yt eyther abhorred from all reason, or was stayned wyth open impietie. Thus haue I rypped vp vnto you the rites and manners of our Churche, whych you see is cleane strypped neyther of holy seruice, sacraments nor traditions, but of eche sort hath reserued so muche, that who so chargeth vs to bee voyde of all, wantinge in dede no parcell requisite vnto the peculier anauncement of Gods honor, shal

shal offer vs vnreasonable iniury. You saye we haue shyfted of the yoke of the imperial Bishop, and you saye well. It was to heauy and broosyng, for either vs or our fathers before vs, any lōger to susteine. Neither acknowledge we any one high superintendent, but only our lord Iesus Christ, which honor the scriptures assigne vnto him alone. And herein do we not part Christs coate (as you gesse) but wee touse and hale the Popes gaberdine, neyther vnlocke we the doore vnto sedicion, but stoppe the hyghe waye, wherein vpon his lawlesse bulles of leade we rode stepe downe into perdicion. You rake together many vnities, and therof packe vp an argument, that in any wise there must

be in the Church one spiritual souereigne or hyghe regent. What nedes that? sith euen in the soundest age of the Church there was one God, one fayth, and yet notwithstanding had Peter one prouince, Paul another, and Iames another, and diuers other had seuerall charge, whereas the seuering of the persōs was no breach to the vnity in fayth. In sequele of time, diuerse prelates of Rome were holy Martirs, put to death by heathen Princes, vsurping no other crowne but the crowne of martirdome. As for this extraordinary popish regalty, they knew it not, and S. Gregorye by name doth defie it. Wherfore if the most floryshinge tyme of the Churche were voyde of thys your Monarchy,

we also may wesleaue if out, nay we ought so to do, not onely for the streight charge of ye scripture, but also the suggestion of all good reason. We cannot abide to haue the head so far distant from the body, especially hauinge thys souereigne power (for the which you labor so harde) here at home in England, that no nede it is to seke any abrode. We haue the full authority of a regall power, conteyning the whole vertue of king lye iurisdiction ouer the whole Realme. But thys, this is it that you cry away withall, thys hath set you in such a glowinge, that vnto Princes you impute sacrilege, bicause they extend their authoritye ouer the Ecclesiasticall lawes, &amp; dare auenture to touche

things consecrate. What I praye you, M. Hieronimus, come out of thys traunce, fie vpon this impacience, in a professed wyse man, let in a littell breath, &amp; chere vp your spirites, you shall se al things in a cleare case. The Quenes maiesty reygneth ouer all her subiectes of Englande. And reason it is. So haue the Frēchmen theyr French king, and the Scottes their scottish souereigne. Yea, but she presseth in vnto church matters. Not a whytte. Al politike affayres, ar gouerned by ciuill magistrates, &amp; spiritual matters by bishops. In spirituall exploites if any publike order be to be taken, the diuines determine the same, whose determination is by the Quenes Maiesty authorised. Now what mislyke

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
you? vnder these ordinaunces did the kinges of Israel (in those daies) gouern the proper and peculier people of God. Then ensued the gospel, which also making in powers a distinction, fyrst hoyseth vp the Regal estate, and subdueth thervnto al other degrees, by the mouth of Peter &amp; Paule, whose names and titles by false vsurpaciō you deriue vnto thestablishing of your Romishe Seignory. As for you, you bidde battel not only in behalf of the Romish Scepter, but also for the holy holy decretalles, whose abolishinge you think hath bene the vtter decay of godly feare within mennes heartes. Certes I alwayes deemed that the feare of GOD had sprong by ye vertue of holy scriptures,

and not by the Romish decrees, by whose Canons I heare say whole routes haue bene enriched, but a sclēder sort trayned to dread God rightlye. Wel, to yelde you so muche, that diuers of your Canons teache reasonable good and wholsome moral doctrine (as I confesse they do) what vaūtage you thereby? we admit bothe decrees and decretals in our Ecclesiastical consistories and courtes, and of neither sorte disanull anye poinct sauing thauthor, and hym reiect we not as bishop of Rome, but as King of Bishops, and supreme hed of our church. We yeld vnto no supreme hed within England, but vnto the Quenes highnes, and out of forrein monumentes, we borrow whatsoeuer may

serue for the enhauncing of godlines and vertue, yea whēce soeuer it be. Not knowing thys our custome, you bewayle the ruine and decay of the decrees, which (so far forth as they varie not frō Gods worde) stand with vs in full vertue and force. You vpbrayde oure preachers as the very fountaines of vnbrideled and wanton libertye, and father vpon them such a dissolute and wilfull kind of talk, as the like neuer was in Epicurus or Diagoras. Whom being thus disguised in new colors of your inuention, you lout &amp; flout al at pleasure. Cal to minde, I besech you, how your good master Cicero (he yt lent you al your eloquence) saith it is il dealing of iestes with god, whether it bee in sporte or good

sooth. If verye nature did teache the gentilles thys, then had you nede beinge a Christian, to looke with both eyes, what it is like a sycophant with scoffinge to tryumph agaynst Chryst. But to the purpose, we are contente (wyth Sainct Paule) to build vpō that liberty wherin Christ hath planted vs. And this libertye of the spirite we qualifye in suche sorte, that we make exception agaynste the libertye of the fleshe, as S. Paule againe teacheth. We beleue in ye gospell, that euerlasting death is farre from them whych are graffed in Christe Iesus (addinge also that foloweth in the same treatise) whose walkinge is not after the fleshe, but after the spirite. I do not roue out of the

very letter, to take away al suspition of treachery or iuglinge. S. Paul after lōg &amp; serious disputations, concludeth yt we are iustified by faith, without the workes of ye law. Let vs subscribe herevnto, and in no wyse let vs derogate from the gospell one iot: mary this is to be learned out of the same leafe, by a lyuely and charytable fayth. These two thus linked together if we doe holde and maintaine, (as no doubte we do) you ought not to diuorse them, &amp; reply vppon a maisterles errour, which hath no Patrone except it be your selfe. It is no gentlemans practise (that I may vse the termes of the Ciuill lawe) to catche thone ende of a statute, and there by to iudge the whole matter.
            
               Mangle not our doctrine thus, but repete it as it is. Which done, there shall ye see good worckes standing in their due reputation, &amp; store or graue exhortacions vnto penitence, and laste of all proue that (for lacke of an aduersarye) you haue made a verye wyse conflicte with your owne shadowe. Forthe ye goe in your lycencyous stile, horriblye cryinge out, that through this dulnes, nai madnes of our men, all mannes reason is clogged and tied vp, free wil hath no scope nor liberty, and all mankinde made so bare and so blynd, that there is lyttle dyfference betweene a man and a stone, that they make god thauthour of sinn, and bring al thinges to confusion and distemperaunce. Finally that

it argueth iniustice in god, to take vengeaunce of thē whom he hym selfe hath depraued. Suerelie I doe not commonly yelde to any pange: But this once I must nedes be bolde with you. You haue vttred not onely a dissardlye and vnskilful cauillation, but blasphemous withall, and suche one, as the very stones wherof you talk, if they coulde speake, woulde not cast out agaynste our preachers. Dippe your witt and vnderstandinge in a little scripture, and reclaim your error. God the father chose vs in Christ before the foundations of the worlde were laid, that we might be hollie &amp; blameles in his sight. You heare recyted out of the gospell this diuyne election, which you in wordes so

greuousely detest, and you heare the time also. Neither is that any necessary fruite of thelectiō, to breake downe the pale vnto all lustes and abhomination (as you scoffe most vnreuerently) but to make vs appeare hollye and irreprehensible before the face of god by charitie, as is worde by worde expressed in the gospell. God it is that worketh in vs bothe ye good will and the worke of good wyll. In fewe wordes hath S. Paule clogged and captyuated all our strength and power. How now? is there no difference betwene vs and stones or stockes. O headde made of a blocke that so woulde gather. S. Paule againe calleth vs ioynct workers with Chryste, and commaundeth vs to labour

about our owne sowles health in feare and tremblynge. Howe can that bee (wyll you saye) sithe we leaue all in gods handes: Learne howe in .iii. wordes. I can do all things in Christ which doth fortifie me. And S. Austine in other wordes compriseth the selfe same sentence very eloquentely. God crowneth in vs his own workes. Now sir. Marck ye well the holly and twise holly purpose of god, surely fensed with the bulwarkes and rampiers of the Scripture? And can ye yet conceiue how we make the prouydence of God not the mother of synn, but the nurce of all obedience? Let vs haue recourse vnto the very fountaynes, whiche not withstandynge that they flowe wt streames as sweete

as honny, yet are your hart stringes so intoxicate, that you haue sucked therout the blacke poyson of adders and vypers. And that I may haue ineuitable processe against you, I will recite the very worde of the gospell. The chyldren being yet vnborn, when they had done neyther good nor euyll, that the purpose of god by electyon might stande, not by reason of their workes but by grace of the caller, it was saide, the elder shal serue the younger, as it is writtē. Iacob haue I loued, Esau haue I hated. What sayes your wysdome vnto this? Beholde once againe the purpose of god, whiche is by election: note the tyme, that is, the children being yet vnborn. What shal we say in this case? Is

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
there any vnrightuousenes with god? that doth S. Paule defye, Hieronimus Ossorius will abyde by it. God by his owne mouthe saide vnto Moises: I wyll haue pitie vpon whosoeuer I take pytie, and wyll haue compassion vpon whom so euer I take compassiō. Wherunto S. Paule addeth that it is neyther in mannes will nor cunning, but in the free mercy of God. and this doth he stablish with the example of Pharao, and maketh finall euidence, that god where he wyll taketh pitie, and whom he wyll he maketh harde harted. What saye we hereunto? forsothe we let downe the saile of our owne iudgement, and bowe vnto theternall prouidence of god lying so open in the scripture, and

taking S. Paules counsell by the way, remember that we are creatures. Neyther doe we chop logique with our creator, but walke in our vocation, betake our selues vnto our bounden duetie, day by daye craue with submission the grace of the hollie ghost, permytt the residue vnto ye botomles mercie of god, &amp; in his misteries wade no further, then we haue placket. What saies Hieronimus Ossorius? Suerly (saith he) if humaine reason be so clasped vp, al free deliberation forspoken, and our wil hath from euerlasting bene gods prysoner, it must needes followe that the whole mā is cleane shriuen of all iudgemente, yea of hys senses, that he is no better then a stone, yea god is made the author

of synn. and that against all good reason it is, that we shuld be punyshed for that synne which wyllingly we neuer cōmitted. Do I belie one sillable of your wordes, do I misalleage one heare? do ye recognise the words of your own lippes, other starke false orelles blasphemous? you are he, that proude pecocke, checkemate with god, whose sollen stomacke sainct Paule bitterly taunteth and beateth down, you being but an earthen vessell lately purtraited out of moulde and claye, wyll knowe of the potter to what vse he hath tempered you. Downe, I saye downe with this presumption (if ye wil be wiser then erst ye were) lesse of this arrogancie, remember ye are the handye worcke of

your GOD, as we are all, leaue at home your owne awarde, and cast down before the footestole of god your selfe &amp; all that is yours in poorenes of spirite. Or if you haue purchased at gods hande any priuie seale, or extraordinarye facultie, which ye can by no meanes geue ouer, kepe it to your self to haue &amp; to holde, suffer vs with quietnes whyning wretches and pulyng soules swathed in sinnes, vnburdened of all humayne affyaunce, or hope of drowsie deseruinges, wholie to clinge vnto the immortall prouidence and free offred mercie of our good god. At length after a volume of raylynge &amp; vncharitable checkes, you knyt vp a kynde of conclusion, makyng a collection of those thinges, whiche

our men haue toppled down, the remembraunce whereof maketh you to yerne, demaundynge what is set vppe in their place. Both whiche thinges I haue alreadie vnwrapped vnto you, but I will not sticke for a worde, In steed of leysie loytringe of miscreant hippocrytes vnder the mistie cloke of superstition, is substitute the dutiful labouryng in christian profession: for raunging lecherye, the honourable state of wedlocke: for the dreaming driftes of mans braine, the written wil of god the father, and our Sauiour Iesus christ, &amp; ye therein comprised treasures of christian perfection. Here I woulde you had dated your reprochefull and loueles letter. For although you are neuer weried in

darting out whole quiuers full of sleueles slaundering and hedlesse hatred, yet yrketh it me to recyte them. To what ende or purpose is it, thus without proofe, pythe, or likelyhode to iterate in the eares of the Queenes highnes, nay in the face of all Christendome to auouche so importune and so hedles errours. But I perceyue you are inspired with that poynte of raging Retorique wherof Tullie maketh mention, that is, after one shamelesse shyfte to be cleane shifte of all shame. Wherefore seeynge you so myldelye mynded, I wil hereafter tread in your owne steps, and as I haue alreadye set my foote agaynst your mysreportes, so will I fight against theym vnto the ende. You geue fierse assault

with freshe wordes, but all your puissaūce leaneth vnto olde &amp; stale vices, such as be common vnto all sortes of men. You chyde their pryde, you bid auaunt with their impudencie, you finde them giltie of robberies, poysonynges, high treason, you bring vpon thē so long rowles of enditement as neuer did Cicero vpon Verres, &amp; in thend you frame a reason, that the good vertue of their doctrine sheweth it selfe vnto all mennes eyes in their execrable conuersation. For (say you) of wholsome doctrine buddeth out amendmēt of manners, whiche rule because now it faileth, this fruitles &amp; dry diuinitie of right shoulde be rooted out. False is this your presumption of their loose liuynge,

whiche if it were true, yet should it neuer be gathered of your premisses. There hath euer ben darnel mingled with the wheate, neuer was there seede sowen but it hath had dyuerse successe, some choked vppe with thornes, some parched with the heate of ye son. The Prophetes were gaine saide by false prophetes. Our sauyour Iesus Christ founde a cruel Cayphas. the apostles were neuer free frō the tyranny of Nero, no more were the Martyrs of latter yeres salf from deuilishe Decians. But these proofes are too auncyente. Com home I pray you vnto your owne church. In your own churche is there not trippinge cōmonly? Nay is there not frailtie openlie? yes, (saye you,) then, say I,

repeate your owne reasons, which are either as weake as water, orels preiudiciall vnto your selfe, and your pretensed church. This thus agreed on, if you aske where is the perfection of Aungelles, if you exact innocencie as white as snowe, in vaine seeke you in this vale of myserie, the spirite without fleshe. But if you wyll stand to the cōparison of the lyuinge of our men and yours, or way their learning and knowledg in equall ballances, wee are at your becke, go too, compare theim from the toppe vnto the toe. And for a breathing while charme your taūting tongue, so like a wanton lauysheinge braineles brawles, dumme &amp; mum in graue argument, nothing tastinge of Scriptures, not ones

smellyng of doctours, onely runninge in mayne streames of reasonable good wordes, but of sentē
               tious pithines welnigh destitute. Of the same stampe is that counterpoīt of yours, which you haue so curiously framed. On the one side wherof you recken vppe in a rancke thapostles, whose renowmed vertue and doctrine (as reason is) you haue garnyshed with pretie pearles of wordes and sentences. On the other syde haue you placed our spiritualtie, whose outragious naughtines you curse as lowe as hell pitt. Which peinted pageauntes of your eloquence (had you ben as wyse as you are taken) you shoulde haue hurded vpp vntill some other seasonable weather, for at this presente you

haue lost a fayre long tale. As for vs althoughe we maye without pricke of conscience affirme that the doctrine of our churche commeth lineally from the apostles, and also the scryptures beare recorde that thapostles them selues sometimes stombled, and shewed theim selues to be but men, yet graunte we that in eche respecte they farre ouerwent the common frailtie of mannes nature. They were scholemasters picked out by gods owne wysedome, they had our sauiour Christ amonge them euen in their dayly conuersation, they were first possessed of the holy ghoste, and therefore are theyr names vnto vs as names of dignitie and reputation. Come vnto latter tymes, one degree lower.

Let your churche shewe her face, and there let truthe trye whether of bothe is neerer cosyn vnto the apostles churche, be it for integritie of lyfe or doctrine. This bargaine made, we wyll forthwith, sewe our processe wt you, &amp; therin geue you a large licēs to make the rewes of your comparisons (if ye will) one hundreth folde. But I auaile not, I find you nothing reasonable, you die if you be barred bytyng and backbityng, outragiously stretching your wyndepipe against our gospellynge, and therein settinge abroche all your sower eloquence. Storme vntyll you stare, crie out while your iawes wyll holde, yet shal you not by importunitie proue any other sede sowen by our preachers, saue onely

the liuely auncient and syncere gospell. In the whiche poynt except your Romishe See bethinke it selfe, by calamitie and fatall desolation it shall once learne, at the time when we shal all appeare at the dreadful assise of gods iudgement, &amp; in our owne person geue an heauie accompte of our fayth, not out of decrees or decretalles, which be your owne sweete darlinges, neyther oute of Iulius or Bonifacius his popishe pedlerye, (whose autoritie so pleaseth you) but euen oute of this golden gospell, which you so sawcely deride, whiche you so longe whyle pestered in your darke dungeons, whiche is by gods good inspiration, &amp; the chiualrie of our souldiours restored againe vnto all Chrysten

Realmes. At that dolefull daye what wil betide you, which haue set your teeth so deepe in vs, whiche haue laide violent holde vpon the Prophet Ieremie, &amp; by force of armes, after much strugglynge and kicking, brought him to geue euidence against our men. Let vs here that man of god whom you haue cyted, and vpon his prophecie examine the truethe: beware, saith he, how you geue care vnto Prophetes preaching pleasaunte thinges and beguiling you, vttering the fansie of their own hart, and not brynginge their message from goddes mouthe, for so they speake which dyshonor me, peace shalbe with you, and vnto those which walke after their own hartes lusts, they haue said, no harm

shall befall you. Here you triūph like a conqueroure, here you crye we are taken halfe oute halfe in. And I crye againe as loude that herein your visardes are pulled of your faces, and how it may so be, I will discrie it to all the worlde. In your temples reignethe this reastie peace, in your synagoges, and in none elles, encampeth and kepeth sleeping holliday this deuelishe drowsynge, wherein you haue so hushed and rocked vp all other, and then layde your selues downe by them, that neyther you see the poynt of the sword leueled at your owne harte, neyther crye vnto other to eschewe the deadly stroke. The office of publike preachinge, so straightly requyred in the gospell, you haue wholly bequeathed

to certaine silly &amp; fruitles fryers, who on prescript daies declaime within their compasse, further forth they speake not one word. In their exhortatiōs they vse suche a lengthe, with so small suite and chaūge, that they much sooner seale vp their eyes whiche be wakinge, then styrre theim vp that are on sleepe. O how quyet they be at their seruice and sacramentes. Firste the people muste stand without the rayles of their roodeloftes, then syr priest whippeth vppe all in a tongue that no man vnderstandeth. Howe shall the people knowe to addresse thē selues to battaile, when no man knoweth the sound of the trump. These are the wordes of s. Paul. Looke vnto the masse, that naturall

&amp; sweete marrowe of all your hollines. No man hath any part in that playe but the priest, as for the poore people they may see for their loue. The Scripture doth not there ouercharge any manne wyth hearynge, but husheth on sleepe all hir exhortations. Ones in a yeare is the lordes supper celebrated, wel censed with ceremonies, God knoweth wyth what troubled conscience. And there lacketh one chyefe point which christes institution requireth, namely that hys death shoulde be had in remembraunce vntill his cōming▪ What maladyes of synne soeuer haue poysoned your foldes, you apply no open soul sa
                  ••
               e Priuate satisfaction is made by whisperinge in the priestes eare, and if it

be more then a veniall trespasse, the popes leadē bul must be wayed downe with siluer. Of ceremonies there are so many, so sutable, so pompouse shewes, that to the outwarde manne there can be no suche paradise, but for the sowles slender edefyinge, nay nothinge but staruinge cheare. Thus are your hollye orders displayed and layed open. Nowe may it please you to heare ours. Fyrste haue we according to the very veine of the gospell dayly preachinges, whose authority eyther with the threates and menacynges of the lawe breaketh our stubburne synnefull harts, or for the precious treasure of gods promises, doth allure vs vnto vertue. Which if any lewde personnes more rechles then the

rest, do cōtemne or set light by, thē doth the Magistrate by cōstraint driue vnto diuine seruice, there to attend, not vnto mannes glosses, but vnto the certein voyce of god the father &amp; our Sauiour Christ, one whyle terrefying vs and putting in feare the vyle leprousye of our synfull fleshe, another whyle spreading vpen vnto vs the wide gates of mercy. Here vnto are added so many Psalmes &amp; Himnes, and such variety of readinges out of both Testamentes, that whosoeuer among so heauenly peales of solace &amp; comfort, cannot conuey awaye one lyne for his owne learning, is to be thought of all other most vnhappy. Thē followeth the last supper of our lord, of most worthy &amp; vnspeakeable reuerence, frō
               
no festiuall daye excluded. There doth the minister wyth an audyble voice cal forth al such as haue deuoutlye prepared theym selues vnto so heauenly a Table. Forth come the therunto minded, humblinge them selues on their knees seuerally, in the face of the congregation, and at a moment by publicke confession renownce all vngodlie wayes, &amp; in vnity of praier betake theim selues vnto goddes mercy. The minister pronounceth vnto them certeine principall and chosen sentences of scrypture, eyther shootinge at them the thunderboltes of goddes vengeaunce for their polluted wayes, or opening the flowinge fountaynes of goddes clemencye, that the communicantes of that heauenlye table

maye oftentymes quake and tremble, and at the laste refreshed againe with hope of pardon, receyue a sweete comforte. If there be any whose defamed lyfe maye shewe a perilous example of parcialitye, or whose wickednes may no longer be borne, those doe we excommunicate, that shame and destitution maye reclayme theym vnto their duetye. Here haue I good occasion to frame a counterpoint, as you did before, which if I wold do, I could haue as good store of wordes to polishe and adourne the same. Lastlye I wolde moue a question whether of both diuine seruices more pricketh and galleth all wickednesse. Where is that husshinge at open impietye, yt the prophet speaketh of, where

is that depe silence &amp; mumming? and on thother side what galling is to be seene of polluted consciences? with what nippinge wordes are they wounded vnto the hart? what percing sentences are there to stirre vp their slowe blouddes? But I wyll leaue all vndone, I haue profered a tast of the matter, let him be iudge that wyll. This (to conclude) I wyll be bolde to say, that in one assemble at the holy Communion, there are deeper syghes &amp; sobbes, then in sixe hundreth of your riotous Massinges. Wherfore it was labor more then neded, out of the Prophet once againe to inculcate, that no earthly man hath bene of gods counsel, that no man hath seene or harde hym open his mouth. But thys

pryde is a birde of your owne bosome, as I declared before. you it is yt laboureth to be one of goddes pryuie councellours. As for this controuersie, whether telleth his tale out of goddes booke, you or we, the lykelyhood surely enclineth to vs warde, which be cōtinually serching and tourning the scrptures. Your champions waueringe with the wyndes vppon the wyde seas of glosses and interpretacions, and totterynge as it were in a slyppery grounde, walk in the wide deserts in great perill of loosing their way. Well ones againe you make bold with Ieremy, not permitting the reuerende prophet to rest. First you alleage these words of his: If they had walked in my wayes or had

declared my wil vnto my people, surely they had reuoked them frō theyr euyll waies, and from their wicked ymaginatiōs. Very wel. Let vs begin with Ieremy, who was a famous Prophete, and no man wyll say the contrarye. Did he scare all the Iewes from their vyces: did he bowe theyr backes, and winne them all vnto vertue? wey and consider the whole time of his prophecienge, and ponder wythal the mourneful gronings and wailing of his lamentaciōs. with the forechosē people of god, this man of god easely preuailed, (for my shepe here my voyce saith the gospel) as for the residue they were hardened. Dyd not Paule proue the like in the Romains &amp; the Corinthians? Peter in the

churches of Asia, and our Sauyour Chryst in infynite numbers of the Iewes, and namely in the Capernaites? Wherfore let Ieremy goe, and leaue youre trifling. Paul planteth, Apollo watreth, but God geueth thencrease. And (as s. Paul witnesseth) this shal be an infallyble rule: God knoweth hys owne. We must labour wyth all intent, but what good gyfte so euer befalleth vs, it commeth from aboue, and descēdeth downe vnto vs, from the father and god of light. But you still folowe the chase, inculcating the lewdnesse vnmeasurable of oure men, that is, you inculcate youre owne cankred charitye, and that whyche hath done you so muche good seruice in this Epistle, a singuler

sprite of slaundering. I say slaundering, sythe the most part of our men walketh in most perfect wayes, and associateth vnto the true worshypping of god many thousādes, &amp; as much abhorreth that accursed conuersatiō of you pretended, as thys your talk is void of all shame and modesty. And if you wyl do that is chiefly to be done, conferre wt the light of our gospell the palpable mistes of your times, and consider what difference there is. Youre last beneuolence is, yt our whole cōfederacy swimmeth in sectes, &amp; hath made vnlawfull conspiracies to pull in peces all due worshipping of God. But notwythstandinge your cauil, they are linked in perfect vnity, whych if you doubt, I

betake you vnto thapologie set foorth in the face of all Christendome, as an open and vndoubted pledge of our Religion, disgrace it if you can. But you can not for your lyfe, nor any of all your complices and adherents, howsoeuer within these few daies one good man hath made hys barkynge brags. Our men (God wotteth) entend no ouerthrow of religiō, beleuing certainly in thimmortalytie of our soules. If there be any realme christiā not throughly persuaded therin, turne your tale vnto them: and if ye be not thus satysfied, call to minde that oure men haue geuen earneste of their profession, not alonely with their tongues and pens, but wyth exyle, nakednesse, pyning, yea wyth

spēding their bloud &amp; life. Which suerly they wold not haue done, if the grim terrors of this present lyfe could haue foyled theym, or crased their constancye in maineteining the knowen trueth. But you say you haue made lōger discourse thē you minded. Yea truly much longer then beseemed you, especially in the hearīg of a most learned and prudent Pryncesse. Whose subtilitye in iudgement might haue put you in some honest feare if you had considered ye ground of her good gifts. Whose highnes continually is addict vnto the reading of scriptures, the comparyng of the most approued expositors, &amp; drawyng out of the opinions of ye best deuines, whose grace hath atteyned an excellency

in the tounges, ioygned wyth readines and quicknes of reason, &amp; all thys she so gouerneth with Princely wisdom, as in a womā vneth is credible. She gladly frequenteth publique sermons &amp; by continual reading &amp; hearing is so wel applied, that her grace is no lesse able to instructe you then she nedeth your instructiō. Were you euer in hope that such a princesse, of al other most godly &amp; prudent, might by your smooth tale be corrupted, or with sugred words beguiled? It is nothing so, it is far otherwise, &amp; they haue fowly abused this your kindnes, whosoeuer sēt you in for an opē accuser, especially vnto the queenes presens. But now haue at your conclusiō, wherin I thinke you wyll neuer

conclude anye thing. One flinge more you must haue at the fruits of our doctrine. As for the persōs themselues, those you require to be loked on, and bi them must the religion be valued. What fruites (in Goddes name) misseth youre church in vs, that sinagoge of all other most fruitelesse. But we refuse no chalēge, your wil be done. Compare England in what case it nowe is, feeding on the sweete Mannah of Gods worde, wyth that whych was so monstruous to behold before, wyth ougly deformityes of humain tradicions. Let vs serch the chronicles, let vs discusse ye Chronographie of our times, let the Quenes hyghnesse sit in iudgement, and, conferring both tymes, geue sentence accordinglye.

This offer if you refuse, then learne at my handes the present estate of Englande, and here after seale vppe your eares at the vnhonest babling of our enemies. A Princesse we haue of absolute power royal, in al pointes incomparable. Whose court is destitute of no ornament, touchinge either the honor of thestate souereigne, or the saulfegarde of the common wealth. The Archbishops &amp; Bishops in their owne persons perfourme the offyce of preaching, &amp; laye theyr owne handes vnto the gouernement of their Churches, alway residēt in them. No variance is ther among the nobility, no breache of dutye in subiectes, peace and tranquillitye through out the whole Realme. In these

things perchaunce you haue ben misenfourmed. But your frēd Cicero putteth you in minde, that euery man speaketh hys pleasure, but nedeles it is to credit euerye man. These our fell frendes loue well to blowe out not that they knowe to bee true, but that they wish to be true, bicause our good successe and felicity is vnto them a grieuous eyesore. Therfore syr, cheare your selfe, and set a parte thys sorrow so depely prynted in you brest for our sake. Take hede you stryde not out of all pacience, cast not your selfe down I say. If all be well in Portugall, care not for Englād. But it is no meruail that you take these paines, syth we are of alyaunce and kynred. Surelye what knot of kinred so

euer is betwene oure kingdome and yours we gladly embrace it, and desier hartilye to be nearer cosins, knit euen in an heauenlye league. But (I pray you sir) if we be so deare friendes, as you saye, and I beleue you, what toye of frendship is it, thus vnto the very crowne to heape vs vp with accusatiōs. How dare ye say that through vs men are diuorced frō that ryght auncient &amp; pure religion which was ratifyed by christs bloudeshed &amp; euer sence hath continued vntill these dayes, and led aside vnto an other kinde of relygion both execrable and horrible. Do you thinke as you say? wythout doubte you doe not. For in those auncient and flourishing times their was no Papacy or Popes

holynes, no leaden graces, no purgatory martes, no worshippīg of Images, no gadding pilgrimages, no sacrifyces for the quicke &amp; the dead in Masses, nor any such trumpery. These misshapes of religion what tyme they spronge, &amp; who begat them you cannot but knowe, but that you dissemble &amp; speake to please. Therefore notwithstandinge the terrours that you thūder in the Quenes eares, wyth commemorations of Gods maiestye &amp; the latter iudgement, your long tale so inflammed with fierye wordes, hath not thauthoritye that followeth truth and efficacye. For why? into a malicious harte entreth no wisdome. As for your malice how sauage it is and hartbent, it is euident not onelye

in euery leafe of your libell, but in one place beyonde shame, wheras in pestilent wordes you denounce sedicion &amp; vprore, you cry to weapons, &amp; blow vp the bloudy trumpet to Ciuill warre. You requyre of the Queenes highnes in posthast, to tumble downe the religiō by common consente erected, and to make place for yours. The way therunto (you say) is easye &amp; redy troden, for that the greater number enclineth vnto you, yt she shall purchase euerlasting renowne, &amp; all the world will clap their handes for ioy. This is your exhortation vnto the Queene, a wicked &amp; witles exhortation. What? no remedy, but forth wt must we throw from vs the heauenly doctryne of the gospell, wherin, sauing one six

yeares tēpestuous rage, we haue continued aboue xxx yeres, wherin the Queenes grace hath led all her life, wherein god hath geuen her a blisfull &amp; peasible reygne of fiue yeres, which was by consent of all estates publyshed, whereof haue ishued decrees and lawes of inestimable policy? This inculpable state of religion, ye true paterne of gods due honour, on euery side so circumspectly fensed &amp; trenched by the Quenes maiestie, shal one worde euen of one Portugall riue in peeces? shal the epistle of Hieronimus Osorius breake the rancke of it? were you euer in this hope your self, or they that craued your helping hand? beleue me you were vnwise when you setled your selfe vnto this enterprise, &amp; they were

not well prouided in wyt yt fyrst moued you to so high mattiers. Write as manye thousande inuectiues as you please, call to counsel al our aduersaries and yl willers, whō (as it seemes) you haue learned by hart. God wil preserue our Quene out of their mouthes, euē that God that hathe before often times bene her deliuerer. God wil strengthen her in the verity of the gospell, euen god that geueth her hourely strēgth, &amp; for the auauncemente of the testamente and laste will of his son our sauiour christ, wil endew her with honour that shall neuer perishe. As for thys your costly garded theatre, wyth vaūting wordes piled vp as high as heauen, neyther is it so precyous a pearle for a prince, or so wel

tuned a songe as to moue her to turne away from the truth euangelicall, reuealed vnto her and hir kingedome, and to sette vp newe stages for your Popishe brauery. Therefore you doe like a naturall orator, in the latter wing to place a whyning conclusion, fetched frō the depth of your faculty, wherin for the loue of all holynes, and all halowed thinges, you cry out and adiure our Quene to exterminate these newe Apostles, and to retire vnto your mother church, wherein you painte and set out the blessed beauye of vertues, with all fine and farre fetched elegancy of speach, and yet (the more pity) all is not worth one halfe peny. Forsoth yt you tearme vpstert errour, the Queene certeinelye knoweth

it to be olde furrowfaced veritye, and for the same offereth vppe in humble wyse her orysons &amp; prayers, fullye mynded not to forsake it vntil death, no not at the houre of death, perfectlye knowing that she shall out of the holy gospell of our sauiour christ, render streight accompt of her gouernment. And you she deemeth but a smatterer in gods worde, if these thinges bee straunge vnto you, or (if you will not knowe them) a deepe dissembler, which faulte was wont to bee farre from a Philosopher. Wherfore in my mind (good mayster Hierome) you may do muche better in these religious matters, to see what diuynes can doe, and to take vppe your place againe amonge Philosophers &amp; oratours,

whose misteryes you haue better tasted of. Your stile runneth in a good veine, &amp; (to all appearaunce) nature hath done her part in you. Hereunto is added arte, whiche hath set forwarde the dexteritee of nature. These good aydes of your studies emploied vpon your vsuall and acquaynted matters, wonderful may be your commendation. I haue sene your booke entituled of nobilitye, fyne wyth the fynest. God graunt you to reserue your self vnto such monumē
               tes, whiche breede none offence openlye, but commoditie and profyte vniuersally. Hereafter if you fall vnto bostinge, and minde too geue freshe assaulte, take it as a forewarninge, to come better fensed. What mortalitye so euer betyde

me, you shall fynde a number in Englande not alonelye in the churches and vniuersities, but also in the Quenes maiestyes Courte, farre surmountynge me in scyence and knoweledge, with you in all thinges cōparable.
            (❀)
            God be glorifyed in all thynges.
         
      
      
         
            A fault escaped.
            In C. leafe. 8. page 2. line. 9. for eloquentlye, reade elegantly.
         
         
            
            ¶Imprinted at London by Wyllyam Seres dwelling at the west ende of Paules Church, at the sygne of the Hedgehogge.
         
      
   

