
   
      
         
            Certaine English verses penned by Dauid Gwyn, who for the space of eleuen yeeres and ten moneths was in most grieuous seruitude in the gallies vnder the King of Spaine, and nowe lately by the wonderfull prouidence of God, deliuered from captiuitie, to the ouerthrow of many of the Spaniards, and the great reioycing of all true hearted English men. Presented to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie in the Parke at Saint Iames on Sunday the xviii. of August 1588. by Dauid Gwyn, as foloweth
            Gwyn, David, fl. 1588.
         
         
            
               1588
            
         
         Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02421
            STC 12556
            ESTC S105999
            99841724
            99841724
            6324
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02421)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6324)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 345:01)
         
         
            
               
                  Certaine English verses penned by Dauid Gwyn, who for the space of eleuen yeeres and ten moneths was in most grieuous seruitude in the gallies vnder the King of Spaine, and nowe lately by the wonderfull prouidence of God, deliuered from captiuitie, to the ouerthrow of many of the Spaniards, and the great reioycing of all true hearted English men. Presented to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie in the Parke at Saint Iames on Sunday the xviii. of August 1588. by Dauid Gwyn, as foloweth
                  Gwyn, David, fl. 1588.
               
               [16] p.   
               
                  By [i.e. for] Richard Hudson, dwelling in Hosier Lane, at the signe of the Wool-sacke,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1588]
               
               
                  Hudson's function and publication date supplied by STC.
                  Signatures: A.
                  The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A.j.".
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-03
            Pip WillcoxSampled and proofread
         
            2008-03
            Pip WillcoxText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            CERTAINE Engliſh verſes penned by DAVID GWYN, who for the ſpace of eleuen yeeres and ten moneths was in moſt grieuous ſeruitude in the gallies vnder the King of Spaine, and nowe lately by the wonderfull prouidence of God, deliuered from captiuitie, to the ouerthrow of many of the Spaniards, and the great reioycing of all true hearted Engliſh men.
            Preſented to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie in the Parke at Saint Iames on Sunday the xviii. of Auguſt 1588. by Dauid Gwyn, as foloweth.
            Imprinted at London by Richard Hudſon, dwelling in Hoſier Lane, at the ſigne of the Wool-ſacke.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  Certaine Engliſh verſes, preſented to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, in the Parke at Saint Iames, on Sunday the xviii. of Auguſt 1588.
               
               
                  SVch Rebels as do meane to ſell,
               their crowne to forreine foes:
               Againſt their Queene for to rebel
               whoſe ſecrets God diſcloſe.
               Marke well, and read this ſtory mine,
               though ſimple and rude it be:
               And to your Queene with heart encline
               let treaſon from you flee.
               For I am one that captiue am,
               and know the Spaniards heart:
               Although he loue the traitors name,
               at length hee makes him ſmart.
               He giues the traitor daily pay,
               while treaſon is a working:
               But afterwards to his decay,
               he cuts him ſhort from barking.
               Which is the due and iuſt reward,
               that doeth belong to treaſon:
               The hangman takes him by the beard,
               to cut his head with reaſon.
               
                  Examples many I could bring,
               which lately hath bene prooued:
               Of thoſe that wrote to Philip king,
               whoſe hearts to treaſon mooued.
               The youthfull Duke of Bragan ſoile,
               
                  Barganſiae cald by name:
               Who gaue the Portugall the ſpoile,
               and brought himſelfe to ſhame.
               Alſo the Coundie of Caſkails,
               did ioine with him in treaſon:
               Pretending for to purchaſe vailes,
               being void and cleare of reaſon.
               And ſo they ſold their natiue land,
               to Philip king of Spaine:
               Who hauing Portugall in hand,
               as king therein did raigne.
               Who ſudainly did turne his face,
               from this good duke and Coundie
                     •
                  
               
               And gaue no credit to their race,
               wherein they knew the follie.
               Therefore good Chriſtian countrimen,
               take heed, beware betime:
               Let no falſe treaſon mooue you then,
               to Pope, nor Spaniſh king.
               
                  Let not affection blind your eies,
               nor popiſh tales deceiue:
               Let not the Spaniards tales nor lies,
               conſtraine you to beleeue.
               For they are deuils, and are not gods,
               ſeeing people they deceiues:
               I wiſh you well, beleeue him not,
               if you will liue at eaſe.
               Therefore you Saxon ſorte,
               that rebels meane to liue:
               Marke well, and reade the euill report,
               that Portugals do giue.
               The Southerne Spaniſh race,
               that mankinde would ſubiect:
               To turne vs all from Chriſtes lawes,
               to liue in Popiſh ſect.
               Repent therefore in time,
               and call to God for grace:
               To Queene Elizabeth doe incline,
               and flie from Spaniards race.
               Be true vnto the Engliſh Crowne,
               and doe the Pope deteſt:
               Procure to beat the Spaniards downe,
               the Romanes, and the reſt.
               
                  Examples good you may well take,
               of Italie, and Cicilia ſoyle:
               By ſpaniards, Flanders all doth quake,
               they Portugale did ſpoyle.
               Therefore, good Engliſh knightes,
               be true vnto your Queene:
               In noble mindes ſet your delights,
               and flie from treaſon cleane.
               Marke well a Captiues plaint,
               that doth lament your caſe:
               To Queene Elizabeth be you not faint,
               and call to God for grace.
               And thus with mournefull heart,
               from Galley I doe end:
               Where I doe feele the bitter ſmart,
               of Popiſh Spaniſh men.
               Farewell good natiue ſoyle,
               farewell good Countrey mine:
               Defend your land from Spaniſh foyle,
               and flie from Spaniſh line.
               I write with dolefull pen,
               my leaue of you to take:
               My life I lead in Galley cheyne,
               from whence my moane I make.
               
                  Viuat Regina Elizabetha▪
                  
               
            
            
               
               An other at the ſame time deliuered to her Maieſtie by DAVID GWYN.
               THe Eagle and the Lyon fearce,
               doe ioyne their ſubiects all:
               Againſt the Saxon ſoyle to pearce,
               their counſell they doe call.
               To knowe the way for to obteine
               their long deſired will,
               In iudgement ſeate they ſit againe,
               to vtter all their ſkill.
               And as the commons bragge and boaſt,
               a fleete they meane to make:
               To ſaile vnto the Engliſh coaſt,
               the Queene and land to take.
               With helpe of Rebels they doe thinke,
               the Saxon land to ſpoyle:
               If Queene and Counſell do not winke,
               the land can haue no foile.
               But thoſe that lurketh in the denne,
               and did not know the ſmart:
               I meane ſome kinde of Engliſh men,
               which beares a Spaniſh heart.
               
                  They thinke the Crowne of ioy to win,
               by treaſon and by guile:
               Againſt the Chriſtian Engliſh Queene,
               to pleaſe the Spaniards wile.
               Therefore good nobles play your part,
               defend your Queene and land:
               Againſt the Spaniards ſhewe your art,
               your force and mightie hand.
               Good Chriſtian Clergie, ſend abroad
               your preachers for to ſhowe:
               Howe bondage is a deadly rodde,
               in winters time you knowe.
               The Spaniardes make the Chriſtian ſlaue,
               and bondmen vnto thrall:
               Their heads &amp; beards they daily ſhaue,
               which is a dreadfull fall.
               They meane with force of fiery ſword,
               your Saxon land to runne:
               They ſay it is for Chriſtes word,
               and Romaines lawes among.
               They ſweare by Chriſt, and by their beards,
               the Engliſh Queene to take:
               The Counſell and the Nobles heads,
               to make them all to quake.
               
                  The merchant and the venterers,
               with Spaniſh bragge they threate:
               The officers and the labourers,
               with fiſts they meane to beate.
               Therefore you worthy wightes,
               that paſſe the ſoutherne ſeas▪
               
               Man out your princely ſhippes,
               your foes for to diſpleaſe.
               And keepe your Engliſh coaſt,
               from Phillip King of Spaine:
               And from all thoſe that daily boaſt,
               to put you all to paine.
               I write no more, I wiſh you well,
               my minde you may well knowe:
               From captiues chaine where I do dwel,
               with bitter paynes and woe.
            
            
               
               An other preſented to her Maieſtie by Dauid Gwyn in commendation of Sir Francis Drake.
               
               O Noble knight, O worthie wight,
               O prince of nauigation:
               In martiall affaires is thy delight,
               for countries preſeruation.
               Thy noble fame like Phebus trim,
               in all the world is ſpread,
               As eclipſe the ſun and moone doth dim,
               ſo Spaniards do thee dread.
               Thy valiant actes and worthie hart,
               deſerues eternall fame:
               Thy knowledge and Aſtrologies art
               doth verifie the ſame.
               Thy happy courſe that thou didſt runne
               vnto the weſterne land.
               Did make the Spaniards all to ſhunne,
               as fearing of thy hand,
               
                  Sanda Domingo makes great mone,
               
                  Carthagena eke doth crie,
               The weſterne Iles do greatly grone,
               thy force hath bin ſo nie.
               
                  
                  Kalles likewiſe doth greatly feare,
               with reaſon thereunto.
               The narrow ſtraites do daily care,
               becauſe thou art their foe.
               Thy enterpriſe hath bin ſo high,
               that Turkes could not compare,
               Nor with his gallies come ſo nigh,
               which makes them all to feare.
               The Graund Engliſh they thee doe call
               of famous good report,
               The Spaniards and the Portingall,
               to England will reſort,
               To ſerue the Queene &amp; thee, good Drake
               
               for thy good famous acts,
               The Spaniſh King they will forſake
               with England to compact.
               Thou art ſo dread as God is feard,
               in ſoutherne coaſt and land:
               The Spaniard daily ſhakes his beard,
               and feares thy mightie hand.
               Therefore good worthie Drake,
               
               ſerue thou thy ſoueraigne Queene,
               And make the Spaniſh foe to quake,
               and Engliſh force be ſeene.
               
                  For helpe and aide thou ſhalt not want
               thy vertuous queene is bent,
               Money and victualles is not ſcant,
               and men will not repent.
               If thou wilt follow victorie,
               as firſt thou diddeſt begin:
               All Proteſtants will pray for thee,
               and for our gracious Queene.
               The Spaniards brag and make greate boaſt
               as thou doſt partly knowe,
               A huge great fleete they make in haſte,
               as letters mine did ſhowe.
               Wherein I writ a warning good,
               to thee and to the queene,
               Rehearſing all both bad and good
               that in their fleete was ſeene.
               Alſo I wrote the ſumme of men,
               as neare as I could learne,
               And ſent it by an Engliſhman,
               whereby thou mighteſt diſcerne.
               To knowe thy foes, and what they be,
               all kind of generation:
               The dukes and earles in their degree
               rehearſed by relation,
               
                  Their ſhips and force I daily wrote,
               and all their preparation:
               To name them all I miſſed not,
               as void of deſperation.
               And thus, good noble knight,
               my ſimple verſe I ende,
               Vnto thy hand good worthie wight,
               my helpe I do commende,
               And wiſh all Engliſh chriſtian men
               to pray for me poore Gwyn,
               
               That lieth in bondage and in chaine
               with popiſh Spaniſh king.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

