
   
      
         
            A learned sermon handling the question of ceremonies, controuerted in our church: by Roger Hacket Doctor in Diuinitie
            Hacket, Roger, 1559-1621.
         
         
            
               1605
            
         
         Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02456
            STC 12588
            ESTC S119068
            99854275
            99854275
            19685
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02456)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19685)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1103:13)
         
         
            
               
                  A learned sermon handling the question of ceremonies, controuerted in our church: by Roger Hacket Doctor in Diuinitie
                  Hacket, Roger, 1559-1621.
               
               [2], 57, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Felix Kyngston, for Cuthbert Burbie, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Swan in Pauls Churchyard,
                  At London :
                  1605.
               
               
                  Running title reads: A sermon.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A LEARNED SERMON HANDLING THE QVESTION of Ceremonies, controuerted in our Church: By Roger Hacket Doctor in Diuinitie.
            AT LONDON Printed by FELIX KYNGSTON, for Cuthbert Burbie, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Swan in Pauls Churchyard. 1603.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  Pſal. 122. v. 6.
                  O pray for the peace of Hieruſalem, they ſhall proſper that loue thee, &amp;c.
               
            
            
               THE Hebrew word 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                ſignifieth either to deſire to pray for, &amp; that earneſtly: or diligently to enquire and ſeeke after. In the 
                  ••••…
               nce Dauid, one thing I haue deſired of the Lord▪
               
                  Pſal. 27.4. and that I will require euen that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the daies of my life. Likewiſe Anna ſpeaking of her ſonne Samuel,1. Sam. 1.20. I deſired him of the Lord, and in this ſence the word is fiue times vſed in one verſe, in that anſwer God maketh to Salomon:1. Reg. 3.11 
               becauſe thou haſt asked this thing: and haſt not asked for thy ſelfe long life, neither

beſt asked riches for thy ſelfe, neither haſt asked the left of thine enemies, but haſt asked for thy ſelfe vnderſtanding to heare iudgement: and that it importeth an earneſt deſire may the better appeare: becauſe that from this roote is deriued 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                the graue of hell, which ſtill craueth but is neuer ſatisfied,
                  Hab. 2.5. as the Prophet Habacuck ſpeaketh, he hath inlarged his deſires as hell.
            
            Or this word ſignifieth ſometime to aske and inquire after, in which ſence the Princes to Baruch, when he had read out of a booke, that which Ieremie called him to write,
                  Ier. 36.17. they asked, and as commonly it is read, they examined Baruch, ſaying, hour didſt thou write theſe words, out of his mouth? ſo when the Gybeonites had told to Ioſhua, &amp; the gouernors of Iſrael, a faire tale about their old bottles and garments; It is ſaid of Ioſhuah and the Gouernours, that they gaue credence to their ſpeech;
                  Ioſhu. 9.14. and did not aske and enquire of the mouth of the Lord. In which ſence alſo God ſpake by his Prophet Iſaias, I was found of

them which did not ſeeke or inquire after me. Whether this?
                  Iſa. 6
                     •
                  .1. to ſhewe vnto you that out of this two fold ſignification of this word,Austin, Ierome, Proſper, in their comment. on this place. the auntient Fathers, as other, read: ſome pray for the peace of Hieruſalem, regate, ſome inquire after Interrogate. The word 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                that ſignifieth peace, noteth ſome time, that outward peace, in which men freed from all ſcare of the enemie, liue in quietneſſe: ſometime that inward peace of ſoule and conſcience, in which the godly; are at peace with God. In the firſt ſence, this word is taken in the 29. pſalme, where Dauid ſaith, the Lord ſhall giue ſtrength vnto his people▪,
                  Pſal. 29.11. the Lord ſhall giue vnto his people the bleſſing of peace. In the ſame ſence Ieremies place is to be vnderſtood, where he aduiſeth the Iewes, to ſeeke for the peace of Babel, into which they were to be carried captiue;
                  Jer. 29.7. becauſe in the peace thereof they ſhould haue peace.
            So againe in ſome places it is taken for that inward peace of conſcience, in which the godly are at peace with God. In which ſence: Elipha
                  •
                to Iiob,

acquaint thy ſelfe,
                  Iob. 22.22. I pray thee, with thy God,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                and make peace; thereby thou ſhalt haue proſperitie. So God to Ieremie,
                  Ierem. 16.5 mourne no more, nor pray for this people, becauſe I haue taken away my peace from theſe people, euen my mercie and compaſſion. Whether this? euen to ſhew, that they muſt pray and ſeeke after, not onely for the outward peace of Hieruſalem, in which beeing freed from feare of outward violence ſhee may liue in quiet; but for Hieruſalems inward peace, by which ſhee is at one; and peace with God.
            From the word 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                here, which ſignifieth loue, is deriued 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                which ſignifieth loue, and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                which ſignifieth holineſſe, out of which we may gather, that they that loue Hieruſalem muſt loue her with an holy loue 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                is deriued from 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , which ſometime ſignifieth to be peaceable, or to pacifie; in which ſence Tremellius here readeth tranquilli ſunt amātes tui: that is, the louers of thee are of a peaceable diſpoſition. The Chaldee Paraphraſt, they ſhall reſt in peace.

Somtime to be happy or fortunate, to abound; in which ſence the Septuagints here read 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                aboundance to them that loue thee. Our tranſlation, Let them proſper. Ierome, Proſper, in their commentaries on this place, let it be well with them.
            This then is the meaning of the Prophet Dauid, Pray, and earneſtly deſire, yea and by ſeeking inquire after thoſe things which may make for the outward and inward peace of Hieruſalem: ſurely they that loue her, in an holy loue, they are of a peaceable diſpoſition, and ſhall abound with all things that are good. Yea O Lord giue to them of thy peace, and let it alway goe well with them.
            In the vnfolding of which the Prophets meaning, that we may the more orderly proceede: conſider I pray you with me, firſt the occaſion which moued Dauid to deliuer this ſpeech; ſecondly to whome he deliuered this ſpeech; It was to the Prieſts that attended on the arke; to the people, that by their tribes came vp to Hieruſalem, and to the Gouernours of the

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
people, that ſate vpon the thrones of Dauid the ſeates of iudgement. Thirdly, the ſpeech deliuered to the Prieſts, O pray for, to the people earneſtly deſire, to the rulers and gouernours, by diligent inquirie ſeeke after, for thoſe things which make Hieruſalem to be at peace, principally with God, then with the world. Fourthly, the reaſon of the exhortation, they that loue Hieruſalem, they will be of a peaceable diſpoſition, and will ſeeke for her peace: or as ſome read, they ſhall not onely be hereby knowne to be louers of Hieruſalem; but it ſhall be well with thē, they ſhall abound with all things that are good. Of which whē we haue briefly ſpoken, we will ſeeke to fit it to theſe preſent times.
            Of the firſt let vs firſt entreat: The occaſion which mooued Dauid to deliuer this ſpeech of exhortation, to the Prieſts, People, and Rulers. When the Lord God had 
                  Deut. 12. 5.6. &amp; 7. v 16. c. 14 v. 23. c. 16. v. 2.11. c. 31. v. 11. often ſpoken by his Prophet Moſes, concerning the arkes that he would chooſe him a place amidſt the tribes of Iſrael, to put his name there; where the arke the Sacrament

of his preſence ſhould for euer abide. And when Dauid a thouſand yeares after that the arke was made, 
                  Pſ. 132.2.had vowed a vowe to this mightie God of Iacob, that he would not goe vp to the tabernacle of his houſe, nor come vp vpon his bedde; that he would not ſuffer his eies to ſleepe, nor his eielids to ſlumber, vntill he had found out a place for the Lord, an habitation for the mightie God of Iacob. And when he 2. Sam. 6.1. with thirtie thouſand choſen of Iſrael, 
                  v. 5.with Pſalteries, ſinging, and much melodie, tooke the arke of God out of the houſe of Abinadab, with a 
                  v. 9. purpoſe to place it in Mount Sion: but feared then to doe it, becauſe 
                  v. 6. &amp; 17 the Lord in wrath had killed Vzzah, for ſtaying the arke with his hand, when the oxen ſhooke it. And when after he had heard from many that God bleſſed the houſe of Obed-Edom, where for three moneths after the death of Vzzah the arke remained,1. Chro. 15 3. he charged the cheife fathers of the Leuites (whoſe office it was and none others to carry the arke of God) 
                  v. 12. to ſanctifie themſelues, and their

brethren, 
                  v. 1
                     •
                  . for the Lord had made a breach amongſt them, becauſe they were not there at the firſt, and becauſe then they ſought not God after a due order,
                  v. 27. who beeing ſanctified and hauing on them linnen garments, like as had all the ſingers, yea and Dauid the king, 
                  v. 25. they together with the Elders of Iſrael, and captaines of thouſands, brought the arke of the couenant, with ſhooting, melodie, great ioy, and the ſound of trumpets, and 1. Chr. 16.1. placed it in the middeſt of the tabernacle, which Dauid in Mount Sion had cauſed to be pitched for it. And although euen then 2 Sam. 6.16. Michol Dauids wife, did therefore deſpiſe him, becauſe ſo arraied he daunced before the arke, ſaying, 
                  v. 20. O how glorious was the king of Iſrael, which was vncouered to day in the eies of his maid ſeruants, as a foole: yet he did not onely approoue his fact by reproouing her, but glad to ſee, that after a thouſand yeares the Lord had accompliſhed his promiſe; that the 
                  Pſ. 132.8. arke of his ſtrength was come into his reſt,
                  v. 14. that the Lord had choſen Sion and loued to dwell in it,

ſaying, this is my reſt for euer, here wil I dwell. Ioying alſo at the heart to ſee the readie obedience of the Elders, Worthies, and people, in ſeconding the command of God, and furthering him in his godly deſires: he maketh this congratulatorie pſalme of praiſe and thankſgiuing; ſaying, 
                  Pſ. 122.
                     •
                  
                I was glad when they ſaid vnto me, we will goe into the houſe of the Lord: and after in this pſalme ſpeaking to the prieſts that attended on the arke, to the people that by their tribes were to come to Hieruſalē, there to offer before the Lord: and to the Elders, which on the ſeates of iudgement gaue ſentence there; to them all he ſaith, O pray for the peace of Hieruſalem, let them proſper that loue thee.
            This was the occaſion that moued Dauid to deliuer this ſpeech. Now let vs in the ſecond place conſider to whome he ſpake it, euen to the prieſts, people, and rulers. To the prieſts, for ſince the arke was now placed in Hieruſalem, there to continue his aboad, 
                  Exod. 28.1.vpon which it was their office to attend, not onely there to offer the daily

ſacrifice, but there alſo to make attonement vnto God, for the ſinnes of the people. It behoued them greatly, to pray for the welfare of that holy citie; yea and aboue the common maner of the vulgar people,1. Sam. 2.8. Exod. 29.4. to ſanctifie themſelues; leaſt for their ſakes God ſhould abhorre the ſacrifices which he himſelfe ordained, 1. Sam. 2.17. as in the daies of Helie, or make a breach with his people, 2. Sam. 6.17. as in the late ſlaughter of Vzza. And yet not to them onely doth the Prophet Dauid here ſpeake, but to the people alſo; for when 
                  Exod. 23.17.34.23. God had appointed them that thrice euery yeare on their ſolemne feaſts, they ſhould appeare before the Lord Iehouah, in that place which the Lord ſhall chooſe to put his name there: and accordingly they did, 2. Chro. 8.13. the feaſt of vnleauened bread, at the feaſt of weekes, and at the feaſt of tabernacles, to which Dauid in this pſalme giueth witneſſe,
                  v. 4. thither the tribes, euen the tribes of the Lord goe vp, a teſtimony vnto Iſrael: to giue thankes vnto the name of the Lord. Theirs it was alſo, as wel as the prieſts, in their godly deſires,

to wiſh for the peace of Hieruſalem, and in their holy obedience to procure that God might ſtill continue fauourable vnto her. And becauſe the welfare of Hieruſalem conſiſted, not onely in the praiers of the prieſts, obediēce of the people, but in the wel-ruling of the cheife gouernours: to them as to the third and cheife eſtate of this bodie politique, Dauid here ſpeaketh, that they ſhould carefully ſeeke for thoſe things which ſhould make for Hieruſalems peace: for 
                  Deut. 16.18.17 5.21.19. Ruth. 4.1. although in their ſeuerall cities, the tribes of Iſrael had their rulers, and ſuch which heard the cauſes of the people yet 
                  Deut. 17.8.21.19. in Hieruſalem was placed the cheife ſeate of iuſtice, there was the Senadrim, the counſell of the ſeauentie Elders; vnto whome were referred all cauſes of weight, both in matters concerning God, and his worſhippe,
                  v. 5. as the ſtate ciuill of the kingdome: the which Dauid in the verſe before ſheweth, where be faith there is ordained the ſeate for iudgement, euen the ſeates of the houſe of Dauid. Therefore called

the ſeates of Dauid, becauſe he was then their king, and from him had they power to command. Thus much for the perſons, prieſts, people, and rulers, to whome he addreſſed his ſpeech.
            Now thirdly, let vs ſpeake of the ſpeech it ſelfe, of that which he requireth of them Of the Prieſts, that they ſhould pray; of the people, that they ſhould deſire; of the rulers, that in the beſt of their indeauours they ſhould ſeeke for thoſe things that ſhould make for the inward and outward peace of Hieruſalem: that ſhould make Hieruſalem at peace with God, and at peace with the world. Not onely for her outward peace and happineſſe, that ſhee may be freed from violence, and liue in ſecuritie, without all feare of forraine enemie, as Comment. on this place. Chryſoſtome ſpeaketh: but that her children, as the twinnes of Rebecca, doe not ſtruggle within her; for that cannot be but with her great paine, and greater griefe: nay abode all that ſhee may be at peace with her God. The which all Caluin fitly expreſſeth, ſaying,

               Comment. on this place. he exhorteth all the Chriſtians, worſhippers of God, that they make their praiers for the happy eſtat of that holy citie: forparaphraſt on this pſalme. ſince as Beza truely obſerued, the ſafetie of Prince, Prieſt, and People, ſeemed to conſiſt in the preſeruation of that citie: let all ſorts pray for Hieruſalem, and for the ſafetie and wel-fare of all them that loue and fauour her. As if he had ſpoken firſt to the Prieſts, O ye Prieſts which ſhould be peace-makers, and ſeeke to reconcile the people to their god, by whoſe holy praiers, 
                  Ex. 17.
                     ••
                  
                as by the prayer of Moſes, not onely Iſrael preuaileth, and Amalech is put vnto the worſt; but by whoſe holy life, and louely conuerſation, the people of God are mightily perſwaded to honeſtie of life, and a brotherly vnitie; ſeeke ye the peace of Hieruſalem, and doe not yee either by your variance trouble and make muddle her pure and ſiluer waters, or cauſe by your ill liues and diſhoneſt conuerſations, the people to abhorre the ſacrifices of the Lord, and therefore to be abhorred of the Lord. As Moyſes to Aaron, 
                  Ex. 32.21 what did this people to

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
you, that you ſhould bring ſo great a ſinne vpon them. And to you O yee people of God, ſeeke yee the peace of Hieruſalem; doe not yee by your vnconſiderate zeale, your vnholied hāds, ſeeke to ſtaye the tottering arke of Gods troubled Church; 2. Sam. 6.17. lay to your hearts the death of Vzza. Your good intents muſt haue warrant from the Lord, goe vp to Hieruſalem, there cō
               ſult with the mouth of the Lord; for fleſh and blood are ill aduiſers in matters concerning God. As the Lord ſpake to Iſrael, ſo to you, if ſo be you will preuaile with him; 
                  Exod. 23.1. Deut. 5.1.27.9. heare O Iſmael and hold thy peace, reſt content with his good pleaſure, and ſay with Samuel, 1. Sam. 3.10. ſpeake Lord thy ſeruant heareth: And to you the Gouernours of the people, 
                  Deut. 1.16 which ſit on the ſeates of iuſtice to judge for God in the cauſe of right: the peace of Hieruſalem muſt be the ſcope of your iudgements, the forth and end of your deſires. 2. Chron. 19.6. Let the feare of the Lord bee alwaies with you and ſince you are the eies of the kingdome, prouidently foreſee the armes of authoritie, powerfully

procure the peace of Hieruſalem: it is not inough for you with the Prieſts to pray, or people to deſire; but you muſt, in the beſt of your indeauours ſeeke, and ſeeking finde, and finding worke forth the peace of the Church and kingdome which you gouerne: for you execute not the iudgements of man, but of the Lord. Therefore 2. Chro. 19.9. thus ſhall ye doe in the feare of the Lord, faithfully, and with a perfect heart. In this manner Dauid aduiſeth Prieſts, People, and Rulers, to ſeeke the peace of Hieruſalem. Thus much for the exhortation: now let vs ſpeake of the reaſon, why Prieſt, People, and Gouernours ſhould ſeeke the peace of Hieruſalem.
            The reaſon is twofold, which is gathered out of the words that followe, They that loue her ſhall proſper. Firſt, if they ſeeke her peace, it will be an euident argument that they loue her. Secondly, they ſhall not leeſe the fruite of their labour, God ſhall make them to proſper: as if he would haue ſaid, ſeeke the peace of Hieruſalem, thereby ſhew forth your loue vnto her, and

cauſe the God of bleſſing for the peace you procure her, to poure down his bleſſings vpon you and yours: they that loue her ſhall proſper. Otherwiſe knowe, that as there were many in the daies of Dauid, which for all their faire ſhewes, as Chryſoſtome ſpeaketh comment. on this Pſalme. had euill will at Sion, yea and that as Muſculus obſerueth, Comment. on this Pſalme. who in hearts were ioyned with the profeſſed enemies of Hieruſalems peace, and vnder hand fought to trouble and vnquiet her eſtate: ſo certainely, although for a while they were not ſeene nor diſcerned of men, but were honoured of many, as men of a deepe reach and politique carriage; yet were they then deſpiſed of the Lord, and in the appointed time, God ſhall cauſe them to be taken in their owne wiles, and will preſerue his Hieruſalem from harme. This is that which Iſaiah after prophecied of the Church, 
                  Iſa. 54.15. 
               Behold the enemie ſhall gather himſelfe, but without me ſaith the Lord, whoſoeuer ſhall gather himſelfe in thee againſt thee, ſhall fall. Behold, I haue created the ſmith, that bloweth the coales in the fire, and him

that bringeth forth an inſtrument for his worke; I haue created the deſtroyer to deſtroy; but al the weapons that are made againſt thee, ſhall not proſper: and euery tongue that ſhall riſe againſt thee in iudgement, thou ſhalt condemne. Pray for therefore, and ſeeke the peace of Hieruſalē, in ſo doing, you ſhall ſhewe that you doe loue her, &amp; for this your loue in ſeeking her peace, God ſhall make you proſper. Thus much for the opening of this text: now let vs ſeeke to fitte it to theſe times.
            This Hieruſalem is a figure of our Church, this Dauid a figure of our king, the placing of the arke on Moūt Sion, which before wandred here and there, through the tribes of Iſrael, and had no ſetled and abiding place; a figure of the Goſpel of Chriſt Ieſus, which although it hath had long aboad in this land, (as the arke in Iſrael) yet it ſeemed to many of vs, to haue no ſure ground of a continuall abode: till the Lord God in loue to our nation, and fauour to his Church, ſetled (as the arke on Mount Sion) the imperiall diadem of this kingdome, vpon the

perſon of our renowmed Soueraigne, and of his moſt royall and euer bleſſed iſſue. The which, as it hath of all ſorts of people beene moſt gladly acknowledged; ſo the better to remember vs of this and other our loyall duties, let me ſpeake vnto you as ſometime did Dauid vnto his people, O pray for the peace of our Hieruſalem, the Church of England, let them proſper O Lord that loue her.
            
            In which my diſcourſe, that I may the more diſtinctly proceede: obſerue with me, firſt, the cauſe of this my exhortation; ſecondly the exhortation it ſelfe: firſt to you my brethren of the miniſtrie, as Dauid to the Prieſts: ſecondly to you of the people, as Dauid to the tribes of Iſrael: thirdly to our Gouernours, as Dauid to them that ſate on the ſeates of iuſtice. Thirdly, the reaſon why all eſtates ſhould receiue this exhortation, becauſe they that loue Hieruſalem and ſeeke her peace, they ſhall proſper.
            Concerning the cauſe of this my ſpeech, ſince this Hieruſalem reſembleth the Church whereof we are mē
               bers;

which as Ierom ſpeaketh Ierom comment. on this pſalme. is not fully builded, but is daily a building: wherein, not dead but liuely ſtones are laid, on the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Chriſt Ieſus being the head corner ſtone. And wheras during this our building, many the 
                  Ezr. 4.2.aduerſaries of Iudah and Beniamin (of God and of his trueth) haue come to our Zerubabell and cheife fathers, and ſayed vnto them, we will build with you, for we ſeeke the Lord your God as ye doe: But purpoſe indeede
                  Ezr. 4.4. to diſcourage the people, and trouble this building: Nay ſince we cannot ſay of our Church and builders, as Dauid there of that Hieruſalem, 
                  Pſ. 122.2 that it is a citie which is builded at vnitie in it ſelfe; but we may euery where heare men complaining of, and taxing our many iarrings &amp; idle diſagreements; Let no man aske the reaſon, why I take vnto me theſe words of exhortation, O pray for the peace of Hieruſalem, let them proſper that loue her. Whē many in our Church walke after the fleſh, not after the ſpirit; ſeeking to ſerue their owne phanſies and worldly

reſpects, and not the trueth of Chriſt Ieſu in the ſingleneſſe of their hearts. When many as we may ſee ſtumble at ſtrawes and leape ouer blockes, ſtraine at gnats and ſwallow camels, tithe minte and commyn, &amp; leaue the greater matters of the lawe neglected. Nay when many in ſtead o
                  •
                a good zeale, for Gods glorie and for his truth, bring ſtrange fire, ſuch which neuer burnt on Gods altar, but was fetched from the fire of hell it ſelfe; as though without it Gods truth could not ſtand, nor we be known to be the ſeruants of God, except we weare the cognizance of the deuill. When the words and deeds of many are full of malice, hatred, and bitter ſpeakings; Let no man maruell that I plead the cauſe of our common mother, I mean the Church of England, which is racked, nay torne with our diſſentions; &amp; yet which carefully ſeekes the quiet of her children, but they will not be quieted. And yet without offence, let me ſpeake vnto thy motherly affection, O mother Church,1 
                     〈◊〉
                   3.25. which canſt not abide to haue thy life-child devided, nor

canſt brooke in patience the cries and skreeches of thy naturall children. Although thou lulleſt them in the lappe of thy motherly compaſſion, &amp; danlieſt them in thy armes of ioy; although thou feedeſt their eies with goodly ſhewes, and their cares with pleaſing ſounds: nay although thou giueſt them to ſucke of the teates of thy breaſt, yet thou ſhalt not ſtill their cries, nor aſſwage their ſorrowes, except by thy diligent inquiry thou ſeekeſt, and ſeeking findeſt, and finding pluckeſt out the pinnes that ſticke in, and are ſo grieue ſome to the fleſh. Ariſe O Lord, and come vnto thy reſt,
               
                  Pſal. 1 32.8. 
               thou and the arke of thy ſanctuarie, let thy Prieſts he cloathed with righteouſneſſe, and let thy Saints reioyce For ſo long as Ionah be ſuffered to ſleep in his ſinne, to goe to Tharſus when he ſhould be at Niniueh, there to doe the worke that he hath vowed, &amp; the Lord hath inioyned him: So long as many congregations are as ſheepe without a ſhepheard, and doe neither heare at home, not may well beare abroad their Chhriſtian duties, the things that

make for their peace. So long as many of our brethren, haue put themſelues to ſilence, or are ſilenced by other, leauing to preach, nay to inſtruct their flocke in the firſt elements and principles of Chriſtianitie: So long as thoſe monthly ſermons impoſed by Canons are not performed; and thoſe wonted Lectures in the head townes of this 
                  〈◊〉
               , where the congregations are great and the preaching ſeldom, are wholly neglected. Inſomuch that with vs it is nowe come to paſſe, that we haue leſſe preaching, but no more praying. Howe can we but complaine our ſelues vnto our mother Church; and ſhewe vnto her that the Ieſuites, ſeedmen of ſedition, and brochers of impietie, by this our ſilence doe make their aduantage: and that the enuious man whileſt we thus ſleep ſoweth amongſt vs the tares of prophaneneſſe and wickedneſſe of life by which the peace of our Hieruſalem is in likelihood greatly to be impeached, and the ſhippe of this Church and kingdome to be troubled? Maruel not then, why to you; I vſe theſe words of

exhortation, O pray for the peace of Ieruſalem, let them proſper that loue her. In a word, ſince the recuſants &amp; halfe recuſants are multiplied in this land, make mention with ioy of the fall of our brethren; and euen towards vs, men otherwiſe conformable, but impugners of their errours; by their falſe ſuggeſtions and ſlaunders doe ſhewe their enmitie: ſeeking by the diſgrace of our perſons, to worke a diſlike of the truth we teach: Since there are many Michols ſooffing at our Dauids, becauſe they are arried in white linnen garments: many Vzzaes of the lay people, which in a blinde deuotion thruſt themſelues too farre in Cleargie cauſes: many oxen which in quiet ſhould beare the arke; the Church of Chriſt Ieſu, which through their boyſterous and troubleſome carriage, doe cauſe it euen to ſhake and totter; Let no man farther ſeeke and inquire, why as Dauid then, ſo I now, to the prieſts, people, and rulers ſhould ſay, O pray and ſeeke for the peace of Hieruſalem, 
                     〈◊〉
                   them proſper that loue thee. Thus much for the cauſes of this exhortation:

now let vs ſpeake of the exhortation it ſelfe.
            Firſt to you my brethren, which do refuſe to yeild vnto conformitie, remember you are the maſons which haue in your hands theſe liuing ſtones, which are to be laid in the houſe of your God: for your brethrens ſake, &amp; the loue you haue vnto the houſe of your God, neglect not your calling: you knowe that the enemies of our Church are many, that your ſilence giues way to their proceedings; why ſhould this be ſpoken of you in Gath and Askalon, that you will no more labour in the vineyard of the Lord? Why ſhould you withdraw your bleſſed helpe, and defraud the people of your charge, of that ſweet comfort which by your miniſtry they once receiued? Should a croſſe and a ſurpleſſe thruſt you from your needfull labo
                  •
               , and make you forget what Paul ſaid, 1. Cor. 9.16. 
               Wee is me if I preach not the Goſpel▪
                ſhould a croſſe and a ſurpleſſe cauſe you to rend the ſeameleſſe coate of Chriſt Ieſu, not to regard the peace of our Hieruſalem.
            
               What is a linnen garment? for let me firſt ſpeake of one, when with one breath I cannot ſpeake of both: is it ſimply ſinnefull? thou doeſt not ſo thinke. For then 
                  Exod. 28.40. 1 Sam. 2.18 God would not haue commanded it vnto the Leuites, neither would 1. Cro. 15.27. Dauid beeing no Leuite, in bringing the arke vnto Mount Sion, of his own proper motion, without any ſpeciall warrant from God, haue worne it. Feare not 2. Sam. 6.21. Michols ſcoffe; although ſhee therefore repute thee a vayne man, yet was Dauid therfore approoued of the Lord. It is true, the Leuiticall lawe, together with her rites and ceremonies are aboliſhed; neither hath Chriſt or his Apoſtles, expreſly commanded the vſe of a white linnen garment vnto vs: what then? ſhould nothing be vſed, or receiued in the Church, which is not warranted by the expreſſe letter of the word? where then, as Auſtin ſpeaketh, Auguſt. Nebridio epist. 1 17. Baſil de Spirit. Sancto. c. 27.
                doeſt thou read in the ſcripture, that good friday, the feaſts of Chriſts Natiuitie, reſurrection, aſcenſion, and comming of the holy Ghoſt are to be celebrated? which yet of all Churches are kept &amp;

obſerued. Where that thou ſhouldeſt receiue the ſacrament of Chriſts body in the morning and not after ſupper? where that it ſhould be miniſtred to women? where that children ſhould be baptized? where that they ſhould be baptized in the Church? where that water ſprinkled on their faces ſhould ſerue for baptiſme? where that there ſhould be ſome, which at their baptiſme ſhould witnes for them? all which and many of the like qualitie, are not expreſſely ſet downe in the plaine letter of the word; yet are they, and from all ages haue bene continually vſed in the Church of God. In regard wherof, although the vſe of this linnen garment be not diſertly mentioned, and ſo warranted in the expreſſe letter of the word; yet ſince god 
                  Loui. 8.13 16.4. commanded it to the Iewes, and 
                  Ren. 4.4.the foure and twentie Elders, a figure of the Church triumphant, were arraied all in white: ſince it ſerueth to decency and order, which are alwaies commendable in the houſe of God: ſince the miniſter by his white garment, is remembred to bring a white heart,

when he is to offer the prayers of the people vnto God: and that a ſmall ſin in him, as a ſmall ſpot in his garment is ſoone diſcerned: the fathers in the Primitiue Church might well command, and ſo put in vſe the weare of the ſurpleſſe, or ſome ſuch linnen garment to be vſed of the miniſter, in the time of diuine ſeruice in the Church. Yea vnto the vſe of this S. Bernard aduiſeth, ſaying, Bernard of the reſur. ſer. 2.
                
               Ad altaris officium, nemo accedat in veſti communi, ſed quiſquis acceſſurus, albis induatur: Let no man come to miniſter the ſacrament, in a common garment; but whoſoeuer is to come, let him be cloathed in white. Yea not onely the miniſters were arraied in white, but ex catechumenis competentes, ſuch which came to be baptized in thoſe great weekes of Eaſter &amp; whitſontide, were alſo cloathed in white linnen garments. In ſo much, that Ioannes Diacon. de vit. D. Gregor. lib. 2. c. 49.
                
               Gregorie the great ſent certaine ſummes of money to Boniface (the firſt conuerter of the Saxons to the faith) to be imployed for ſuch of the poore, which deſired to be baptized, but yet lacked money to buy thoſe

garments. Yet did not the Fathers enforce this garment, as abſolutely neceſſarie to be worne in the Church, but commended it rather as fit, by ſeruing to decencie and order: the which may appeare out of Auguſtine, ſpeaking of theſe garments. Auguſt. ſer. de temp. 163.
                
               Oftentimes there may lie hidde a pure ſoule vnder a blacke habite, neither doeth it matter much, if any hath not a white garment. The reaſon of this Celeſtinus, the firſt of that name, biſhop of Rome, giueth, in an Epiſtle that he writeth to certaine biſhops of Fraunce, when vnder their charge ſome cloathed in cloakes ſerued in the church, leauing that garment which in former times was vſed. Caranzu. epit. concil. inter decret Celeſt. 
               We are to be diſtinguiſhed from the people and other by our doctrine, not by our veſtiment; by our conuerſation not by our habite; by the puritie of our mindes, not by the ornaments of the bodies. And therefore ſhortly after inferreth, wee are not to induce the ſimple mindes of the faithfull vnto theſe, for they are rather to be taught, then to be illuded. Since thē this garment hath beene in this manner commanded and vſed by the godly

fathers in the firſt Church, why may it not in the ſame ſort be commanded to vs, and vſed of vs? If here thou ſhalt infer, becauſe it hath beene ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed, many putting that holineſſe in the garment, that without it they thinke no ſeruice or ſacrament can bee rightly adminiſtred. That is their errour that are ſo miſcarried; whoſe miſinformed conſciences are to be inſtructed in the truth. Yet I pray thee ingeniouſly ſpeake, muſt nothing be vſed that hath beene ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed? then muſt we haue no Church, no word, no ſacraments, no praiers, for they haue all beene moſt fowly abuſed. When Auguſtine was conſulted, whether the temples of the Pagan Idols might be turned to the Churches of the liuing God? Auguſt. publis. epiſt. he asketh whether of Pagan men there are not made beleeuing Chriſtians: therby inferring, that as the worſhippers of idols may become true worſhippers of God, the temples of idols churches for God: ſo things ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed may be freed from their ſuperſtition, and retained in their vſe.
            
               But other reformed Churches, haue not thought meete that in the time of diuine ſeruice they ſhould be vſed. Be it ſo. Yet thou heareſt that our Church is of another minde: to weare or not weare is a thing indifferent, we giue no lawes to them, neither may their fact preſcribe in matters of this nature a lawe to vs. They doe that which in their ſeeming beſt fitted the politie of their Church: and our gouernours that, which beſt fitteth ours. When Monache the mother of Auguſtine came to Millan, ſhee was troubled in conſcience, becauſe that at Rome on the ſaturdaie they faſted, at Millan they did not faſt: whoſe troubled conſcience Ambroſe ſoone eaſed, ſhewing vnto her in things of that nature, that when ſhee was at Rome, ſhee ſhould doe as they did at Rome, and when in other places, as they did in thoſe places. Vnto what Church ſoeuer ye ſhall come,
               Aug. epiſt. 88. Caſula. 
               obſerue the cuſtome of that place, if ye will not haue other to be offenſiue vnto you, or you become an offence vnto them. Marke the reaſon of his aduiſe, in the end he concludeth,

               doe not reſiſt the biſhop herein, but without all ſcruple or diſpute, followe that, the which thou ſeeſt him do. Which aduice of Ambroſe, Gregorie the great in the like approoueth; for being conſulted by Auſtin the conuerter of our Engliſh nation, whether he might not bring into the Church of England, certaine rites then in vſe in the church of Fraunce, which yet were not vſed in the Church of Rome; receiued for anſwer, It pleaſeth me that whether in the church of Rome, or in the French church,
               Greg. Auguſt. interrogat. c. 3. Beda de geſt. Anglor. lib. 1, c. 27.
                
               or in any other Church, thou haſt found any thing, that may more pleaſe almightie God; thou wouldeſt carefully chooſe it: and that which thou haſt gathered out of many Churches, thou wouldeſt aboue all other eſtabliſh in the Church of England, which is but newely conuerted to the faith: for not the things for the places, but the places for the good things (that come from them) are to be loued. Much rather would Gregory haue approoued thoſe rites, which had beene before in England receiued; although they neither had bin nor were in vſe, in the Churches of Geneua and Scotland.

The which alſo Hierom confirmeth, in his epiſtle he writeth to Licinius,
               Hierom. Licinio. epiſt. 28.
                ſaying, This I thinke briefly to admoniſh thee of, that thoſe rites of the Church (eſpecially which are not hurtſome to faith) are ſo to be kept, as they haue beene deliuered from their Elders: and that the cuſtomes of ſome, are not to be ſubuerted and ouerthrowne, for the contrarie vſage and maner of other. But aboue thē all, notably Auguſtin cleareth this queſtiō, in a diſcourſe he maketh of the vſe of ceremonies: for hauing ſhewed that ſome were generally receiued, ſuch which were either by the Apoſtles appointed, or concluded on in general coūcels:Auguſt. Nebrid. epiſt. 117.
                at lēgth he ſaith, there are other alſo, which doe varie according to the diuers vſe of ſundrie places and countries: as that ſome doe faſt on ſaterday, others doe not: and of which after he thus concludeth: all this kinds hath free obſeruations (may be vſed, or may not be vſed) neither is there any other ride (or caution to be giuen) to a graue and wiſe Chriſtian, then that he ſo doe, as he ſeeth the Church to doe, vnto which ſoeuer he ſhall happen to come. For

when that which is inioyned, is not againſt faith, nor againſt good manners, it is to be reputed indifferent, and to be kept for the peace of them amongſt whome we liue. Since then it cannot be denied, but that the ſurpleſſe is commanded, &amp; for the moſt part vſed in the church of England; that Ambroſe, Auſtin, Gregorie, Hierome (ſometime reputed the foure pillars of the weſterne Church) aduiſeth you, for the peace of the church in which you liue, leaſt you become an offence vnto other, and other vnto you, notwithſtanding the contrarie vſages of other Churches, to conforme your ſelues, and to vſe the ſame. And vnto them all, which aske the reaſon, why ſome Churches vſe this garment, others doe not: I anſwer as Auſtin, who beeing demanded why Paul circumciſed Timothy, but did not circumciſe Titus, although therevnto he was required:Auguſt. epiſt. 27.
                
               that he might ſhewe thoſe ſacraments, neither as neceſſarie ought to be deſired, neither yet as ſacrilegious ought to be damned. So I to them which aske the reaſon why ſome churches receiue this ceremonie, others

doe not: ſurely that the faithfull of God may knowe, that this ceremonie ought not to be required as abſolutely neceſſarie, nor yet to be damned as ſacrilegious and naught.
            Yet thou inſiſteſt and alleadgeſt as a reaſon of thy refuſall, that many good men will not weare the ſurples, or miniſter baptiſme with a croſſe; my loue towards them perſwades me that many of them are good, and that they doe appertaine vnto the Lord. Yet I pray thee anſwer, are they all bad that haue conformed themſelues, and vſe theſe ceremonies? thy Chriſtian charitie will not harbour ſuch thoughts: nay I am perſwaded, that if God ſhould ſend among vs a fierie triall, that as this kingdome did affoard in the daies of Queene Marie, Cranmer, and Ridley, Hooper, &amp; Latimer, Biſhops then varying euen in theſe ceremonies, to giue their bodies to be burned for Gods truth: ſo this Church would affoard many, whereof ſome yeild to conformitie, &amp; ſome do not, which with ioynt conſents would witneſſe the truth, that hath beene, and is

nowe preached amongſt you, with the loſte of the liuelihoods and their liues, Wherefore looke not alwaies ſo much on that which good men doth, but cō
               ſider rather whether they are in that good, they doe: neither let this ſeeme ſtrange vnto thee, that God ſuffereth his ſeruants to fall in iudgement, and although they would, not to ſee his trueth; call to minde the errours of the holy fathers: and why doth God this? euen that all fleſh, as Chryſoſtome obſerueth, might giue glorie to the lord, and not aſcribe to the worthe of man the bleſſed worke of mans ſaluation. Wherefore, ſince the vſe of the ſurples is meerely indifferent, which the magiſtrate may command to be continued in the Church: ſince it is no newe thing, but auntient, which a long time hath beene vſed in the Church, and approoued of the fathers, as ſeruing vnto deconci
                  ••
                and 
                  ••
               der: ſince it doth not contrarie any principle of faith, or any way impugne the honeſtie of mā
               ners; although it was ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed, and of ſome reformed Churches therfore not admitted, and of ſome

good men therefore refuſed, let it in al obedience &amp; loue be vſed of vs, &amp; for it, let vs not breake the peace of our Hieruſalem, or trouble the Church in which we liue.
            Yet thou ſaieſt, thou canſt not for thy conſcience: what of the thing? thou canſt not that art learned be ſo groſſely deceiued; it is in his nature meerely indifferent, neither good not euill: for if it had beene abſolutely euill, the holy fathers &amp; martyrs would not haue vſed it, or approoued it as lawfull in the Church of God.
            Why then doeſt thou refuſe it? thou ſaieſt for thy conſcience; what thy coſcience? that haſt ſo much laboured in the word, thy conſcience that haſt taught the magiſtrate commanding in things indifferent is to be obeyed. No man knoweth thy conſcience but thy ſelfe; gloſe not with God, nor with thine own ſoule: but if thy conſcience doe miſ-giue thee, aske of her her reaſons, weigh them with thy ſelfe in the ballance of Gods word, thou knoweſt ſhee may erre and be deceiued. It is no ſhame well to vnſpeake that thou haſt

ill ſpoken, or to retract with praiſe that thou haſt fondly iuſtified. Follow wiſe and wel minded Auſtin, ſeeke to guid thy zeale with knowledge, and in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe conferre with thy diſcreete and learned brother, and aboue all, in the humblenes of thy well meaning heart, pray vnto God, that he would open thy eies, and teach thee his truth: it may be he will ſhewe to thy miſinformed conſcience, that he did to Peter, 
                  Act. 10.15. 
               that which I haue ſanctified call not thou vncleane: but if the Lord ſhall withhold this grace from thee, and thou 
                  Rom. 14.5. canſt not in this be reſolued in thy minde, I may not perſwade thee to ſinne againſt thy conſcience. But as Paul of meates that were ſacrificed to Idols, ſo I of theſe; although in their natures they bee cleane, yet 
                  Rom. 14.14. to thee that iudgeſt thoſe things to be vncleane, they are vncleane. And yet then remember whoſe thou art, and in all meekenes poſſeſſe thy ſoule, and ſhew to vs that are contrarie minded, that although thou cāſt not weare this white linnen garment, nor brooke the croſſe required in baptiſme,

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
that yet for the peace of Hieruſalem which thou doeſt ſeeke, thou art content to take vp Chriſts croſſe and follow him. And yet when thou heareſt that they
                  Mat. 5.10 are bleſſed that ſuffer perſecution, remember it is added, as Augusſt. epiſt. 50.
                Auſtin obſerueth, for righteouſnes ſake. It is not the puniſhment, but the cauſe that makes a martyr.
            But it may be as ſome pretend, they refraine from this, not for conſcience of the thing, for they hold it indifferent; nor for their conſcience, for of it in their minde they are well perſwaded; but for conſcience of their weake brethren, which with the vſe of the ſurpleſſe are offended: vnto whoſe waking ſoules thus I anſwer, that 
                  Ro. 14.15. although Chriſtian libertie ſhould yeild to loue, that 1. Cor. 6.12.10.13. that which is lawefull to them is not alwaies expedient, nay 
                  Ro. 14.21. that they may not eat fleſh, not weare a ſurpleſſe to offend their brother: yet when the magiſtrate commands them in the things of this nature, then is their libertie reſtrained; &amp; that, which if they were free they would not doe, nor indeed ſhould with the offence of

their brothen 
                  •••…
               e they are bound to doe, leaſt they ſhould be deſpiſers of him, whome God hath ſet ouer them: for as thy libertie muſt veild to loue, ſo muſt thy loue and libertie to the rule of faith, which requireth of thee, 
                  Rom. 13.5 to obey the magiſtrate commanding in things indifferent, not onely for feare, but for conſcience ſake.
            At the which thy diſcreete carriage, if thy weake brother ſhall: be offenned, it is an offence taken, not giuen: better it is by thy word 
                  〈◊〉
                enſ
                  •
               mple to lead him to the truth, then by thy nice mammering to confirme him in an vntruth: as 
                  Act. 5.19. Peter, better to obey God then man; ſo I, better to obey thy magiſtrate lawfully commanding, then thy brother fondly ſweruing: the Canons of our church thus decreeing, then the fancie of ſome fewe
                  •…
                otherwiſe ſpeaking. Whe
                  ••••…
                to conclude, finde neither for the conſcience of the thing, thy conſcience, nor the conſcience of thy weake brother, thou muſt 
                  〈◊…〉
                by the command of the magiſtrate, in things of this nature as Dauid in this 
                  〈◊〉
               , ſo I 
                  〈◊〉
                you, O
                     •••…
                  
                  
and ſeeke for the peace of Hieruſalem, let them proſper that loue her.
            
            Now to you my fellow labourers, which haue yeilded your obedience to theſe outward ceremonies, &amp; haue conformed your ſelues vnto the time: ſeeke for the peace of Hieruſalem, reioyce not at the fall of your deceiued brethrē, neither let your egar tongues, be ouer-fretting in their ſmarring ſoares: as Chriſt to his diſciples, ſo let me to you,1 Luk. 9.55. 
               If at any time you ſuffer in you the affections of men, remember of what ſpirit you are: as it is good that your zeale ſhould be guided with knowledge, ſo much better if it be moderated with loue: let your fire come from heauē, not from the earth: And when you haue to deale with any either of your charge, or appertaining to the ſtocke of Chriſt Ieſu, whoſe mindes are diſtaſted with theſe newe conceits,
                  Gal. 6.1. inſtruct them with the ſpirit of 
                  〈◊〉
               ; and although at the firſt they admit no counſell, yet let your words of wiſdome, as the ſweet dewes of heauen ſtill ſhewer vpon them, till God by your miniſtie open their

hearts, and they with you ſeeke for Hieruſalems peace. Yea and ſince the Lords vineyard hath loſt many painefull labourers, whoſe mouthes ſpake for God againſt the corruptions of the world; and for his truth againſt the errours and ſuperſtitions of Poperie:1. Tim. 6.5. ſtirre vp the grace of God that is in you, double your diligence, enlarge your zeale, that their wants by your labours may be ſupplied: for if (which God forbid) this our Church of England be ouergrowne with the corruptions of ſinne, or poyſoned with the ſuperſtitions of deceiuing poperie, Hieruſalem will neuer be at peace. And to you alſo let me ſpeake, which haue the roomes of Gods meſſengers, but cannot carrie his meſſage vnto his people, which in your blacke liues, do not anſwer the whitenes of your garments; and who, although you vſe the croſſe, yet are a croſſe vnto the Church of God, and a ſcandall of your calling: ſeeke for the peace of Hieruſalem, enlarge not you your mouthes againſt the afflicted, their falls wil not iuſtifie yours: and if you will needs be

medling 
                  Mat. 7.
                     •
                  . with the motes in their eies, forget not the beams that are in yours, leaſt you heare from ſome like ſpirited to my ſelfe, as Iehoram did of Iehu, when he asked whether it were peace,2. Reg. 9.22. what peace? whilſt the whoredomes of thy mother Ieſabel and her witchcrafts are in great number, what peace can you procure for your ſelues and for your people? when by your ignorance, ill enſample, and neglect of dutie, you lead and confirme them in your ſinne. Awake therefore with Ionah out of the ſleepe of your ſinne, and although it be ſomewhat to your loſſe, with him ſeeke a calme for our ſhippe, a peace for our Hieruſalem in which you liue. Thus much to you my brethrē of the miniſtrie, ſeeke the peace of Hieruſalem.
            
            Nowe let me ſpeake to you of the people (as Dauid did to the tribes of Iſrael) which are beholders and hearers of the troubles of our Church, ſeeke for the peace of Hieruſalem; and whē you come into the houſe of god, to talke of matters belonging to god, and to his Church:
                  Eccleſ. 4.17. take heed to your

feete, as the Preacher ſpeaketh, and be more readie to heare, then to offer vp the ſacrifice of fooles, for they knowe not that they doe euill. Remember what the Lord ſpeaketh by his ſeruant Malachie, the 
               
                  Mal. 2.7. 
               Prieſts lippes ſhould preſerue knowledge, and men ſhould ſeeke the lawe at his mouth: if at our mouths ye will ſeeke it, then heare O ye people: the things in queſtion, the croſſe and ſurpleſſe are meerely indifferent, ſuch which may, yea and ſhould be vſed, when authoritie commands, and againe may be diſuſed, if authoritie forbids: if any herein deſpiſe authoritie, and will not obey the decreed orders of our Church, he is not wholly fit to be a guide and leader vnto other; he procureth trouble to our Hieruſalem, and to himſelfe. But as for you my brethren, walke in the light that hath beene ſhewed you, and ſhewe your holy obedience vnto the Lord: remember the times not long ſince paſt, when God tooke from vs our late bleſſed Soueraigne, how gladly then you would haue beene contented, (if ſo be there had beene any

that could haue aſſured you) to haue enioyed the religion now profeſſed, although it had beene with the purchaſe of much money, and with many inconueniences, from which you are now freed: and ſhal we now, as though we had forgotten thoſe times, ſhewe our vnthankfulneſſe to God, diſloyaltie to our Prince, ſo waywardly impugne his princely proceedings in the croſſe and ſurpleſſe, as though all our religion were corrupted by theſe; the Lord giue vs better mindes, yea be hath giuen, and therefore as yee haue begun, ſtill ſeeke you for the peace of Hieruſalem in which we liue. The peace of Hieruſalem you doe then truely ſeeke, when 
                  Heb. 13.17. you ſubmit your ſelues to them which haue the ouerſight ouer you in the Lord, and ſuffer the good word of God, not onely plentifully to dwell, but to fructifie amongeſt you: for as when they of Iudah and Ieruſelem 2. Chro. 36.16. mocked the meſſengers of God, deſpiſed his wordes, and miſuſed his Prophets, the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his people: inſomuch that he gaue Hieruſalem to

be ſpoyled by the Chaldees, his temples to be burnt, his people to be ſlaine or carried away captiue. So whē they hearkened to the Prophets, and ſet their hearts to ſeeke the God of their forefathers; then God made their enemies tributaries to them, &amp; themſelues to proſper in all things that they tooke in hand. Hearken therfore vnto God ſpeaking vnto you, by the mouth of his ſeruants, for this is to ſeeke the peace of Hieruſalem, and to make her proſper. But whereas it cannot be, that in our congregations all ſhould be obedient vnto the heauenly voyce; but that there ſhould be ſome which by their lewde liues, and croſſe behauiours, ſhall diſturbe and trouble the peace of Hieruſalem. Yours it is which are the guerdiōs of the church, and Sidemen choſen to ſecond them in that office, diligently to ſee, &amp; faithfully to preſent whatſoeuer crime and offenſiue diſorder: for as the ſinne of ſome fewe, cauſeth the Lord to be angrie with many; ſo doeth the puniſhment of the wicked, reconcile the Lord vnto his people againe. Seeke

therefore the peace of Hieruſalem in making preſentment of the notorious offendours. Many good lawes, both lately, and long ſince hath beene made, for the ſuppreſſing of ſinne; yet when you, which are the eies of the Iudge, will not ſee the diſorders, nay when you, which are ſworne to detect, will not preſent them, how can ſinne be ſuppreſſed; and in the ſuppreſſing of ſinne, how can the peace of Hieruſalem be procured? When Iehoſaphat was much commended for his forward zeale in the cauſe of the lord; yet it was ſaid, that in his daies the high places were not taken away: and the cauſe is ſhewed, 2. Chro. 20.33. for the people had not yet prepared their hearts vnto the God of their fathers: euen ſo, if we aske why in the daies of our Iehoſaphat, theſe crying and offenſiue ſinnes goe vncontrolled, are not puniſhed, but ſoothed vp, continue as before: one cauſe is in you the churchwardens and ſidemen, you doe not prepare your hearts vnto the God of your fathers, you will not take nor giue notice of them. Wherefore as

Chriſt to the angels of the ſeauen Churches, ſo he ſpeaketh vnto you.
                  Reu. 2.4. v. 14. v. 20. I haue ſomewhat to ſay againſt you, in that you foſter the wicked in their ſinnes, nay in that ye make the ſinnes of other your ſinns, and by your winking at, and cloaking of them, plucke the curſes of God vpon your heads, and vpon his Church:
                  Ier. 48.10. for as Ieremie ſpeaketh, Curſed is he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently: this is Gods worke, and the cauſe of his Church you haue in hand: ſhew your diligence in the ſearch of ſinnes, that God may turne his curſes from you, and you may ſee Hieruſalem liue in peace. Neither let the offendour take to wrath, that for his crying ſinnes he is preſented; but rather let him humble his ſoule, bewaile his faults, and thanke God, that this occaſion is giuen him to amend. Thus let them that preſent, ſeeke the peace of Hieruſaem by preſenting the offendour; and let the preſented ſeeke the peace of Hieruſalem by repenting their ſinnes; and let the god of peace be at peace with our Church, becauſe ſhee wincketh

not at the faults of her children, but reprooueth and puniſheth them, in them; to the example of other, and for the amendment of their wicked liues. Thus much to you of the people, the tribes of Iſrael, pray and ſeeke for the peace of Hieruſalem.
            Nowe are we to ſpeake vnto the gouernours of the people, facti eſtis ſedes domini iudicatis,
               Aug. comment. in Pſal. as Auſtin ſpeaketh, ye ſittel on the ſeates of the all-iudging God, and haue authority to command from the throne of Dauid, the ſcepter of the king: becauſe they that iudge doe aske (as Auſtin there noteth) they that are iudged are asked: Interrogate, inquire after thoſe things which make for the peace of Hieruſalem. For as Proſper after him writeth,Proſp. comment. in punc locum 
               ad ipſas ſedes propheticus ſermo dirigitur, vobis ait, qui iudicaturi eſtis, per quos fiet conſciētiarum interrogatio: diſcernite à ſuperbis humiles ab implacidis ſeparate pacatos: that is, to the very ſeats (of iniuſtice) the propheticall ſpeech is directed; vnto you be ſaith which are to iudge, by whome is to made the examination of conſciences, diſcerne ye the humble from the proud,

and put a difference between the troubleſome and the quiet. It is not enough for you with the prieſts to pray, or people to deſire; but you muſt by diligent inquirie ſeeke, and ſeeking finde, and finding, further the peace of our Hieruſalem, which is of God. The vnquiet of our Church makes vs to pray, and the people to deſire, that the God of peace would diſpoſe your hearts, to ſeeke for the things that make for our peace: as Athanaſius, Non pugnamus Caeſar, ſed rogamus, O ye rulers, we doe not fight, the weapons of Chriſtians are prayers and teares.
                  Gen. 18.27. Yet as Abraham to God, ſo I to the Gouernours of our Church, Behold I haue beganne to ſpeake vnto my Lords, and yet am but duſt &amp; aſhes: yet not with my words,Hierom. comment. in hunc locum but with the words of Hierom, Seeke after thoſe things which make for the peace of this citie, and followe it; that by the loue of peace, ye may attaine the fruit of euerlaſting bliſſe. Remember you muſt giue an account of your doings to the Lord. Wherefore let vs make bould to remember you of your duties, and vpon what diſturbers of our

peace you are principally to looke. Firſt, vpon the whole and halfe recuſants, and other fauourers of the Romiſh ſuperſtition, which if they come, are drawne to our Churches; which backbite our perſons, depraue our preachings, and ſpeake in corners againſt the profeſſion of the trueth: let them not boaſt themſelues of your fauours, for of them many vnto this day haue ſhowen, that they ſeeke not the peace of this Church and kingdome, in which they liue. Secondly looke to the open and notorious offendours, which are either publikely infamed, or detected in your courts: whoſe euil enſamples imbolden other to ſinne, and are an offence vnto the godly with whome they liue, and a note of rebuke and ſhame vnto our church, when they eſcape vnpuniſhed: for by their crying ſinnes they diſturbe the peace of our Hieruſalem, in prouoking the Lord to be angrie with this land. Laſtly, looke to the proudly wilful &amp; forwardly diſobediēt, which ſpeake euill of authoritie, and contentiouſly broch and maintaine their follies,

contrarie to the wholſome lawes and orders of our Church: theſe are ſeedes-men of Schiſme, fathers of cō
               tention, whoſe troubleſome and euer varying humours, cannot brooke the quiet of our Church. Thus ſeeke yee the peace of our Hieruſalem, O ye our Gouernours, and then doe yee which thus ſeeke, the prieſts that pray, the people that deſire her peace, hearken to the words that follow, They ſhall proſper that loue her.
            
            This is the ſoule and life of the exhortation, and a forcible motiue to mooue all eſtates to ſeeke Hieruſalems peace: they ſhall proſper that loue her. Heare ye my fellow brethren, and yee the people of God, the tribes of Iſrael, and yee the fathers and Gouernours of our Church, and looke into the boſome of your hearts; if ye loue our Hieruſalem which is our Church, yee will ſeeke for her peace, nay if ye loue her ye ſhal proſper, and all things ſhall goe well with you: but if yee doe not loue her, nor yet in truth, for all your faire ſhewes, doe ſeeke for her peace; you ſhall not proſper. And if

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
for a while God ſuffer you to flouriſh, yet the ſunne of your proſperitie ſhall ſoone ſet, and all your glorie ſhall be as the flower in the field, which is ſoone withered and gone. Heare O ye ſinners, which with your crying ſinnes trouble the peace of our Hieruſalem, and cauſe the Lord to be angrie with his people, what the Lord ſpake to Achan by the mouth of I
                  ••••…
               h (for whoſe ſinne Iſrael turned his backe before his enemies) when he willed the people to ſtone him, and his, euen to the death. 
                  Ioſh 7.25 In as much as thou haſt troubled Iſrael, the Lord ſhall trouble thee his day. They that loue not Hieruſalem nor ſeeke her peace: they ſhall not proſper. Heare O ye Seminaries and Ieſuites, and you Romiſh fauourites, which with your ſeditious practiſes, and vnholy deuotions, haue hindred the ſucceſſe of the worde, interrupted the peace of our Church; and haue furthered, if not fathered, many the rents and diuiſions, that haue ſprung vp amongſt vs: that they that 
                  Ezr. 4.4. hindred the building of the Temple, in the

daies of Zerubabel, diſcouraged the people of Iudah, and procured 
                  v. 23. of the Kings Counſaile to worke the King to forbid the work; heard after to their rebuke, 
                  Ezr. 6.11 the decree of Darius, that the Temple ſhould bee builded, and that whoſoeuer ſhould after ſeeke to alter this ſentence, the timber ſhould bee pulled from off his houſe, and ſhould be ſet vp, and he to be hanged thereon. They that loue not Ieruſalem, but ſeeke to hinder her peace, they ſhall not proſper. Let ill ſpoken Martin heare &amp; Martius Apes, which through their ſcandalous libels, and ſcurrilous ieſtings, haue ſought to inſame the Fathers of our Church, and haue ſet the ſonnes againſt their fathers, and the fathers againſt their ſonnes, to the great vnquiet of our Church and kingdome: that dutie lacking Cham, 
               
                  Gen. 9.23 the diſcouerer of his fathers ſhame, for euer beares in his vnhappie race the curſe of his father: and that railing and ſeditious Shemei, 
               1. Reg. 2.9 was by wiſe Salomon not reputed innocent, but adiudged to carrie his hoary head with blood into his graue.

They that loue not Ieruſalem, but hinder her peace, they ſhall not proſper. Yea let all heretikes heare, which make faire ſhewes to colour their errors, and make ſemblance to one thing, when they meane another: that Arius, the trouble of the Church, (ſwearing to maintaine the Nicen faith in open ſhew,Zozom hiſt. Eccl. lib. 2. c. 28. Epiph. haereſ. 69.
                but priuely meaning in truth that confeſſion of his, which vnder his hand he couertly had hid) that very night in ſteed of his excrements voyded his guts, and died in a filthie place a filthie death. They that do not ſeeke the peace of the Church they ſhall not proſper. Yea heare, O yee my brethren which thruſt your ſelues out of Gods worke, and ſeeme to make a rent in this our Church; that the Meletians which ſeuered thē
               ſelues from their Patriarke of Alexandria, becauſe in the time of perſecution, hee receiued ſome vpon their repentance, and penance giuen, which for feare of torments had denied the faith: that this fact of theirs is noted by godly Epiphanius,
               Epiph. haereſ 63.
                the ſixtie eight hereſie, and they heretikes without an

error. Nay their followers (although they tooke vnto themſelues the title of the holy Church) yet were ſo farre forſaken of the Lord, that they ioyned with the Arians to perſecute the Catholikes; and were the greateſt procurers, by their falſe ſuggeſtions and vntrue reports, of all the troubles of Athanaſius, which in the reigne of Constantine hee ſuffered. They that ſeeke not the peace of Ieruſalem, they ſhal not proſper. 1. Sam. 
                  
                     •
                  , 30. Yea and let wincking Hely heare, which would not ſee the lewdnes of his children, nor regarde the people abhorring for his ſonnes vilenes the very ſacrifices of God; that God will ſay vnto him: I ſaid vnto thy houſe, and to the houſe of thy father, Ye ſhall walk before me for euer: but now it ſhall not bee ſo: for them that honour me, thoſe will I honour, and as for them that deſpiſe me, thoſe wil I deſpiſe.1. Sam. 4. According to this which the Lord had ſpoken, Hely broke his necke, Ophny and Phyneas were both ſlaine in one day, the Arke of God was taken, and the glorie was departed from Iſrael. They that doe

not ſeeke the peace of Ieruſalem, they ſhall not proſper. Yea let Ieroboam heare, which hath erected his calues of gold in Dan and Bethel, and ſaid to the people, 1. Reg. 12.28. it is too much for you to goe to Hieruſalem, come worſhippe here: that 
                  v. 30. this thing ſhall turne vnto him for ſinne, that a man of God ſhall crie againſt the altars that he hath made, nay that 1. Reg. 14.6. Ahliah ſhall be ſent vnto him from the Lord, with heauie tidings, euen that God will bring ſo great an euill vpon his houſe, 
                  v. 10. that he will ſweepe away his whole familie, as a man ſweepeth away dongue, till it be all gone. Thus as Dauid ſpeaketh, 
                  Pſal. 129.6. are they confounded and turned backward; as many as haue euill will at Sion, thus ſhal they be, as the graſſe that groweth on the houſe toppe, which withereth before it be plucked vp. On the contrarie, they that loue Hieruſalem and ſeeke her peace, they ſhall proſper. This you may ſee verified in this kingly prophet Dauid, to whome 2. Sam. 7.9. God gaue a name like to the name of the great men of the earth, and of whoſe loyns concerning the fleſh, our

Sauiour came. This in Conſtantine the great, the peace-maker of the world, Zozom. hiſt. Eccl. l. 
                     •
                   c. 16.
                who did not onely for the quiet of the Church, aſſemble the firſt &amp; great councell of Nice; but before the Biſhops faces burnt their inuectiue libels, which to him the one had tendered againſt the other, and deliuered vnto them that worthy ſpeech, moſt worthy himſelfe, Eccleſia dei diſcenſionem quonis malo graniorem cenſeo:
               Zezom. diſt. Eccl. lib. 1. c. 16.
                
               I repute the diſcenſion of the Church of god, more grieuous then any euill. Vnto whoſe graue ſentence let all eſtates ſubſcribe, and as much as it is poſſible ſeeke the peace of the Church &amp; kingdome in which we liue. Yea O Lord let this be in our praiers, deſires, and beſt indeauours, that ſo we may proſper, and it may goe well with vs. Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

