
   
      
         
            Newes out of Powles Churchyarde now newly renued and amplifyed according to the accidents of the present time. 1579. and otherwise entituled, syr Nummus. Written in English satyrs. Wherein is reprooued excessiue and vnlawfull seeking after riches, and the euill spending of the same. Compyled by E.H. Gent. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.
            Hake, Edward, fl. 1560-1604.
         
         
            
               1579
            
         
         Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02477
            STC 12606
            ESTC S106141
            99841865
            99841865
            6480
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02477)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6480)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 546:11)
         
         
            
               
                  Newes out of Powles Churchyarde now newly renued and amplifyed according to the accidents of the present time. 1579. and otherwise entituled, syr Nummus. Written in English satyrs. Wherein is reprooued excessiue and vnlawfull seeking after riches, and the euill spending of the same. Compyled by E.H. Gent. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.
                  Hake, Edward, fl. 1560-1604.
               
               [128] p.   
               
                  By Iohn Charlewood, and Richard Ihones,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  [1579]]
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Edw. Hake.
                  Partly in verse.
                  Place of publication and printers' names from colophon.
                  Signatures: A-H.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               London (England) --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.
               London (England) --  Social life and customs --  Poetry.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-09
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2004-09
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ❧Newes out of Powles
Churchyarde
Now newly renued and amplifyed
according to the accidents of the
present time. 1579.
and
Otherwise entituled, syr Nummus.
Written in English Satyrs. Wherein
is reprooued excessiue and vnlawfull seeking
after riches, and the euill
spending of the same.
            Compyled by E. H. Gent.
            Seene and allowed according to the
order appointed.
            
               Horatius.
               Aetas parentum peior auis, tulit
               Nos nequiores, mox daturos
               Progeniem vitiosiorem.
            
            
               Well get thy goods, and spend them well:
               well gotten, keepe the same.
               Beware of hoorde, hoorde hate doth bring,
               and vile reprochfull name.
            
            
               Non mordet qui monet,
               Non vulnerat, sed sanat.
            
         
         
            
            
            
               ❧To the high and Honorable,
and his especiall good Lorde,
Lorde Robert Dudley, Earle of Leycester,
Baron of Denbigh, and Knight of the most
noble order of the Garter, high Stewarde
of her Maiesties Burrow of new Windsore,
Edw, Hake, vndersteward there,
wisheth dayly preseruation with
increase of honor to Gods
glory.
            SIth grace hath graffed in your Noble brest,
            Farre grater gifts then tipe of mundane gle
                  •
               :
            Sith high renowme, your Honour, &amp; the rest,
            To Vertue yeeld, and counteruayled bee
            With great effect of Vertues worthy vew:
            I make it bolde for vertues ayde to sew.
            And though my gift (as slender to the shoe)
            Vnworthy seeme to shrowde himselfe as now
                  •
               
            
            In blessed Bay from force of deadly foe:
            Yet Vertue may your Lordships pitie bowe
            To fense the Booke beset with deadly hate,
            For that the same explanes the present state,
            And sets to vew the vices of the time
            In Nouell Verse and Satyrs sharpe effect
            Still drawne along and pend in playnest rime
            For sole intent good liuing to erect:
            And sinne rescinde which rifely raignes abroade
            In peoples harts full fraught with sinfull loade,
            
               
Sith so (I say) therefore your Noble hart
            Let grace so guide and bend to Vertues bayte,
            That Satirs these (though seeming somwhat tart)
            May shielded be from such as lie in waite
            The same to shend and bring to fowle decaye:
            To deadly shame, and mortall malice aye.
            So shall your Lordship shewe your selfe to bee
            Sole vertues stay, and friend vnto the good:
            So hate to sinne shal men apparaunt see,
            And loue set forth to saue the sinfull bloud.
            And so shall I encouragde in my paine,
            Proceede, and set my Pen to Booke againe.
            And euer pray the liuing God of might
            Your Lordship so to guide by gift of grace,
            That you may stande accepted in his sight
            Whilst here you liue, and in the ende a place
            Receiue with such as vertues path haue traste:
            And liue with them that vertue haue imbraste.
            
               
                  Your Lordships most
humbly at commaundment.
Edw. Hake.
            
         
         
            
            To the Gentle Reader.
            
               
                  IT pleaseth the Printer,
(Gentle Reader, as thou séeist)
after twelue yéeres scilence,
to hale againe into the
lighte, this my litle booke of
englishe Satyrs, which else mighte haue
soonge vnto it selfe, 
                  
                     •
                  cce nunc in puluere
dormio: what his gaine shalbe, I knowe
not: and I am perswaded, that gaine is not
the onely, no nor the chiefest ende hée respecteth.
But on the other part what I shal
gaine that am the Author of the book, none
can be so ignoraunt, but hée maye easilye
ghesse. Once, money I gaine none at this
time, either for writing altering or correcting
of the same: &amp; hereof I stand so cléere,
that bothe I and my booke may be bould to
exempt our selues from the reache of mine
owne Argument which consisteth in the
reproouing of those who (by male engine) lie
in wait for sir Nummus. And thus much be
spoken to preuent the obprobry &amp; reproche
that this way might be raysed against me.
            As for prayse and commendation, if the
sharpnes of my Satyrs were not matter
sufficient to settle me against the expectation
thereof: yet I am not so farre from
Judgement I thanke God, but that I

know (in part) what is lackinge (aswell in
the inuention as in the verse of the booke,)
that shoulde carye away commendation amongst
the better sort of english Poetes of
our tyme: And indéede, it is a matter that
I stryue nothing at all to attaine vnto:
            For if I did, I woulde frequent the meanes,
which are reading and practise, neyther
whereof, I haue bene acquainted with
to any purpose since the first thrée yéeres
which I spent in the Innes of Chauncery:
being now aboue a dosen of yéeres passed.
And so longe is it sithens these Satyres
were first made and set foorth, euen (as I
maye saye) in my childishe yéeres, whereof
notwithstanding verye lyttle or nothing
I repent mée. Only I wishe that all that I
haue written &amp; published heretofore were
by me reuised, and that I might haue lycense
and laysure to runne them ouer againe,
hereby to make them a little more
substanciall if my habilitye serued thereto:
which being once done and performed, how
forwarde I woulde bée from thensfoorth in
setting forth of bookes, shoulde appeare vnto
the worlde by the continuance of my silence.
For (to speake a truthe) it is not
méete we shoulde cloye the worlde with

to many bookes of weake handling: especially,
whiles the learned trauailes and profitable
labours of worthye wryters are
fayne to kéepe the doore (as I maye terme
it) or, which is more, to lie buried in silēce.
            But touching this my booke: I haue not
abridged it of any one Satyre that was in
the first edytion thereof, neyther haue I
added vnto it any other whole Satyr: But
I haue enlarged here and there one, and
haue corrected yt whole booke in many places.
I confesse I coulde haue béene wylling
to haue increased the number by ij. or
iij. Satyrs at the least: Namely of vndershreeues
and Baylliffs one: And of Informers
and Sompners or Apparitours
other twoo. Which offycers (if they all so
be) how they abuse the Subiects and people
of this Realme at this daye, by intollerable
Extortions bryberies trecheries and
deceyts, what whole Shier, and in euerye
Shier, what Cytie Towne or Uillage, is
not hable haboundauntly to declare? But
these, togither with the exquisite handling
of mine allowable Argument, I muste be
contented to omitte, as neyther hauynge
laysure, nor (through want of laysure) skill
sufficient to accomplishe the same: For I

tell you, it is no matter of meane ymportaunce,
firste to searche and syfte owte the
wrenches and wyles, shyfts, practises and
deceytes that the lewde sorte of this people
(which I feare me are the greater number
of them) doe vse to gette money with. And
then hauing so searched and syfted them
owte from nooke to crooke, to sette foorthe
the same in apt and conuenient discourse:
            For which causes (gentle Reader) be contented
and affoord me thine indyfferent
Judgement in this that I haue alreadye
done: And if thou finde therein any matter
or reprehension more fytte to haue bene
handled by men of grauer Censure and
more agréeable callinge: Forasmuche as it
reacheth no farther then to the reprouing
of vice, and the same also wrytten in that
age of mine, when as vice (withoute the
grace of God) mighte rather haue drawen
me to her league, then haue had me for hir
enemye: I thinke thou mayest well
enoughe (without endaungeringe
of Justice) assent to my request,
and so I hope thou wylt
do. Fare well.
            
         
         
            
            Ad authorem, Ioannes Long
Londoniensis minister.
            QVarit opes hominū mens improba, querit honores:
            Sed quid diuitiae? quid decus omne valent?
            Insidiis quaeruntur opes, quaeruntur honores:
            Ista breui fugiunt, &amp; peritura volant.
            Perge tuos igitur foelici tramite gressus:
            Sistere ne retrahat Zoilus istud opus.
            Insidias ostende virùm, quos nulla mouere
            Heu pietas poterit: queis pador omnis abest.
            Sic tu Nestoriae traduces stamina vitae
            Hakê, tuam famam sydèra summa canent.
         
         
            
            The same to the Citie
of London.
            A Great conquest of sinne hath made
            a Student Edward Hake.
            O London learne for to beware,
            from sinne arise and wake.
            Of wanton Maydes he did also,
            the slights a late detect:
            Learne to be wise, and looke to them,
            the worst alwayes suspect.
            Hée hath redusde to vulgare tongue
            the Imitation true
            And following of our Captaine Christe,
            good liuing to renue.
            A Touchestone for the present tyme
            hée eke set forth of late,
            Wherein the ruynes of the Churche
            with zeale he doth debate.
            A brief memoriall of our Quéene
            
               
                  •
                and of her blessed raigne
            He also wrote in dewe discourse
            first once and then againe.
            At length these newes are now come forth
            wherein thy sinnes he showes.
            Repent (therefore) and call for grace
            of God eche thing that knowes.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            The Author to the Carping
and scornefull Sicophant.
            
               AS plated Finne of slender slycing Oare
               Wherwith the Seaman cuts the crooked wa
                     •
                  e,
               Is scant of force tattaine the happy shoare
               When check of tyde back beares the mighty Naue:
               So I (no lesse) long lodgde on mounting surge,
               Was kept aloofe by cankerd caytifes gurge.
            
            
               Though true intent did slyce the streame so swift,
               Sea beaten Barck could scantly yet obtaine
               The shoare tyll now: by subtile Zoyls drift
               And Uipers tongue that beat my Boate amaine.
               What then? perforce, and maugre Momus head,
               I skyp on Stroud, as free from daungers dre
                     •
                  d.
            
            
               Let Sicophaunts and Minotaurus broode.
               Let Ciclops Feere, and subtyle Ciren Hagges,
               With grinning Jawes and gasping gyddy moode
               Go shake their eares, and shut their shameles bagges.
               I force them not, nor Neutrall, Papist, nor
               Uile Janus Jacks: their league doo I abhor.
            
            
               Thou Papist, thou, false harted to thy Prince,
               That wouldste bereaue her grace of princely powre,
               To thee I say that checking, doost conuince
               (As seemeth thee) my poynaunt poore deuowre:
               For that thou deemst me dampned by thy doom,
               Stand back sir Brock, let Bandog take thy room.
            
            
               Shall brockysh Badger beare as now the sway,
               Or Shepherdes Dog that bringeth in the Sheepe?
               Shall wooluish mates that woont the same to slay,
               Rebuke the Whelpe? no, no, take thou no kepe.
               To my poore powre yle barck thee from the fold,
               And shepherdes shall rehayte thee to thy holde.
            
            
               
               Wherefore, withdraw thy raging spoyle by day
               And see thou lurck (at least) within thy caue
               Whyle Sunne to vp, for feare of Hunters pray:
               What tyme thy craft is not of force to saue.
               And eke at night, beware ift be thy hap,
               And keepe thy foote from slipping Hunters trap.
            
            
               And now to thee thou double faced drudge,
               That plyes thy selfe so plyaunt vnto chaunge,
               And vnder hand dooste beare thy face so Budge:
               Thou Tyme sclaue thou, y• sayst my pen doth raunge:
               To thee I say (for that thou moanst my case)
               Restraine thy tongue, least I descry thy face.
            
            
               Thy hooded head that doth two faces beare,
               I see how closely vnderhand it nods,
               And triple tongue that byds me ware this geare,
               Least chaūge should come. But twene vs .ij. be ods,
               And therfore (Janus) once againe I say,
               Go charme your tongue, least I take hood away,
            
            
               And last of all, I turne my tale to thee,
               Thou Nunquam sanus vyle reprochfull mate
               And carping carelesse cankerd churle, whom hee
               That writes ech where, reproues with worthy hate.
               For that thou belkst with belly bursten paunch,
               Gainst them that haps from ydle shoare to launch.
            
            
               To thee, to thee my flytting Muse auerres,
               And bound by Oathe of Fayth, I doo auowe
               That neyther hate nor harbraynd toy inferres
               This worke of myne which I doo publysh nowe.
               Nor meede at all, though where it bringeth gaine,
               It pleaseth some for to requite my paine.
            
            
               
               For well thou wotste, if thyrsty were my minde
               To bend the same to wynne by gaynsome trade,
               Then would I wryte the thing that Authors finde
               A gaine within: and whereby Sommes be made,
               I meane vaine 
                     •
                  estes to stirre vp filthy game.
               But I protest my harte doth hath the same
            
            
               And onely seekes how to sequester sinne,
               And Sathans dryfts that driue men downe to hell:
               My thoughts be cleere, my conscience cleane within.
               Thus knoweth God, that eche ones thought can tell.
               Wherfore, beware and let thy carping lye.
               Else, sure my pen my gyltlesse hart shall trye.
            
            
               And to conclude, to all that wysh me well,
               And loue by tongue, do vtter to my fate,
               I make request that rancour they depell
               And let their verdict to the Trueth geue place.
               Else, let them cease to beare of friend the name.
               For I refuse to take them for the same.
            
            
               Once (sure I am) with quipping querks herein,
               I haue not meant to taunt, or check the good,
               Nor (rayling bent) I slaunders doo begin:
               Though trueth I say, to such as wyll be wood.
               For gyltie man findes eche thing to his shame.
               Where good men can their owne offences blame.
            
            
               But well, for fine and finall ende I saye
               To all such Snakes as styng by stealing pace
               And boughing Curs that barck and winde away,
               I holde it best that they no more deface
               An open trueth: For then, as they deserue,
               Enbarckt I lye to launch when tyme shal serue.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            
               ❧Ad authorem Ric. Mathaeus,
Londoniensis minister.
            TVus probatur à pijs labor bonus:
            Qui quod pium est non diligit,
            Noli put are vincere hunc virum tibi
                  •
               
            
            Huic sit loquela libera.
            Quis Zoilum fugit pius? Tu nec potes:
            Bonis mali nam detrahunt.
            Tibi beata sit precor solatio
            Vita ea, Deus quam tunc dabit,
            Cum tua fides Christo vt facit des obuiam
            Regno patris summi sui.
         
         
            
            The Noueltie of this
Booke.
            SUch Noueltie as time doth bring,
            I yéelde in méeter héere:
            Euen newes that to the Godly hart
            may noysome newes appéere.
            But yet what then? such is the state
            of this our present time,
            That now no daye doth passe without
            some new deuised crime.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            ¶The Glory of the Honorable, is
the feare of God.
            
               
                  The Beare doth beare me now in hand
                  that Noble is thy race.
                  The vertues of thy worthy minde,
                  shevve forth the gifts of grace.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The first Satyr.
            AS late I walked vp and downe,Auct
                     •
                  or.
            
            in Pawles for my repast,
            And there (as many woont to doo)
            about the Church had traste
            Long tyme alone to view the route,
            and great confused noyse,
            With pleasaunt that (a world to se
                  •
               )
            at length I heard a voyce.
            And casting backe mine eye, I spyde
            a pretie wymble lad,
            Who saluing of his mate, dyd aske
            what newes were to be had.
            His fellowe (lyke a gentle swaine,
            and to ly headed chylde)
            Conioyned 
                  •
               andes, and sighing, sayde
            a slaue hath me beguilde,
            But scarcely had he spoken this,
            or eare his faithfull feere
            Faste claspte his arme, and him besought,
            to be of better cheere
                  •
               
            
            And let not chaunce (quoth he) afright,
            nor so molest your minde,
            As thus to seeme a Wight that hath
            his woonted ioy resygnde.
            
               
Tell tell, quoth Bertulph
               Bertulph. (so be bight)
            By whome you are beguylde
            And eke what cause and cruel chaunce
            your comfort hath exylde.
            O friende (sayde Paule
               Paule.) full soone would I
            expresse to thée my griefe,
            But so peruersely falles it foorth
            that I sée no reliefe.
            But yet sith thou so vrgent arte
            and earnest of the case,
            I graunt thereto if thou attende
            and walke about the place.
            Content is pleasde, quoth Bertulph tho,
            and then they walckte yfeere,
            And I perceyuing all their talcke,Aucthor.
            
            approc
                  •
               ed very néere:
            And ioyning close vnto their side,
            I walckt with equall pace
            (Without offence as I suppose
            their talcke had such a grace.)
            Then Paule began with visage palePaule.
            
            and handes conioyned fast,
            To settle forth him selfe to speake,
            and thus be spake at last.
            The highest God that fyttes aboue
            For aye in heauenly Throne,
            That Prince of might that rules she hea
                  •
               uens
            and Welkin wéeldes alone,
            
               
He knowes if I do falsely speake,
            or (mooued through affect)
            If I through hate or fauor, lye
            in any one respect.
            But first, before my tale begyn,
            Ile tell you howe the slaue
            Hath many one beguyled earst
            that sought the same to haue.
            His name also I wyll not sticke
            to tell you with the rest.
            And to be short, He Nummus hight
            (a passing proper guest,)
            He lodgeth ofte with Marchauntmen
            and eke with men of Lawe,
            And lightly where he hosteth, there
            are people kept in awe.
            Ile eke declare howe that as he
            doth often men beguyle,
            Euen so him selfe is often catcht,
            with fraude and filthy wyle.
            And howe ofte tymes by force they wrest
            and wring him to their handes
            And howe from fooles he often flyes
            and breakes his tynsell bandes,
            Now, whiles y• 
               Paule was speaking thus,Aucthor
            
            his mate gan me espye.
            He knewe my minde, I gaue a becke,
            he wynked with his eye
            
               
And helde his fynger on his mouth,
            suspecting sore the man:
            He thought that fancies fed his braine,
            his visage lookte so wan
            And word
                  •
               s so voyde of woonted sence.
            But yet (for that he hight,
            And promisde had to heare the ende)
            his he
                  •
               t he kept aright.
            And forth proceeded Paule at large.Paule.
            
            This Nummus nowe (quoth he)
            Is straightly watchte, and hardly kept
            with men of each degree.
            He wanteth none to wayte for him,
            although he scapt from mée.
            The Laytie and the Clergie bothe,
            if 
                  •
               aply him they see:
            Will talke with Vobis eare he parte,
            theyle plucke a Crowe with him.
            Theyle shut him vp, or sende him forth,
            seme greater gaine to wyn.
            Or else to worke their neighbors woe,
            by wagin
                  ••
                sutes at Lawe,
            To bring them selues in prease and price,
            and to be had in awe.
            But as for Clergie,Clergie. some of them,
            they knowe his nature well,
            They knowe his false corrupting force,
            with him they will not mell,
            
               
Except it be where neede requires,
            and for a iust intent.
            And surely some, though not the swaye,
            right so to gaine are bont.
            Although that some againe doo séeke
            excessiuely the same,
            And some do hoorde it vp in store,
            to their rebuke and shame.
            But (if I should vprightly speake)
            Their lyuinges are so lopt,
            That from th'inferiour Clergie men,
            long since syr Nummus hopt▪
            
            I meane not pompous Prelates here,
            nor Chaplens of degree.
            These flaunting fellowes by your 
                  •••
               ue,
            will haat ift had maye bee
            I meane, I meane poore Ministers,
            some plaste and some disperst▪
            
            Whome powling Patrons and such lyke,
            haue gréeuously amerst.
            And yet forsoothe our Baldockes bleate,
            and say they kéepe no chéere.
            They catche syr Nummus from them still,
            and yet would haue him héere.
            But well they are no small fooles nowe▪
            
            that robbe the Clergies meede.
            Wherfore to sylence were I best,
            such wordes may rancor bréede.
            
               
And here you must aduert it well,
            that iustly men maye séeke
            For Nummus to releeue their neede,
            if so their fancie leeke.
            And also bow that they right well
            the same may styll retaine,
            So that they doo not 
                  •
               oord him vp
            for sole intent to gaine.
            But such as I shall here recite,
            cannot without offence
            The same or séeke, or kéepe, or spend
            what so be their pretence.
            Bicause their mindes are all peruerse:
            they spende for spyte or gaine:
            And through the lust of lawlesse boorde,
            the same doo they retaine.
            And what are they that séeke it so?
            Euen most men now a dayes.
            In Countrey, Citie and each where
            they finde sinister wayes
            T'obtaine the same, and spende it yll,
            or else to kéepe it worse:
            And euer aye their mindes are bent
            to fyll their farsed Purse.
            But nowe, for that the scope is large
            where we may finde them out,
            And time but short, I rather meane
            to leaue the Country rout,
            
               
And medle with our Townish lade
            in London sole precinct,
            Except (as néede) the Suburbs must
            be with the Citie Linckt.
            Wheras, when I haue reckned vp
            of them the most estates,
            Then tell howe many kindes of folcke
            ne lyue within the rates
            And bounds of honest seeking store.
            of spending well the same,
            Of closely couching vp their hoord
            as bedlem bugs to tame.
            Why syr (quoth Bertulph) now me thinksBertulph.
            
            you talke not of the man
            That seru'de you of that sluttish touch
            of late I wot neare whan.
            O Friende (quoth Paule) is this the faithPaule.
            
            and this thy late behest?
            I stickt not to begin my tale
            at thy alone request:
            And thou therefore didst promise mée
            thy silent eare to giue.
            And yet thou interruptst my tale.
            Howe should I thee beleue?
            Of friendly faith attende a while,
            and marke me to the ende:
            Then shalt thou thinke that I disclose
            to thee as to a Friende.
            Finis.
         
         
            
            The second Satyr.
            AS promise presseth me to showPa
                     ••
                  .
            
            my minde to thee at large:
            Euen so t'obserue due order is,
            belonging to my charge.
            
               
                  〈◊〉
                therfore (first) how Nummus doth
            beguile eche kinde of men:
            Howe it through force and vyle effect
            doth noysome humor blen:
            His beautie (first) and pregnant show,
            and then his mighty force,
            Enchaunteth so the peoples hartes:
            that (voyde of all remorse)
            They fawue &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                watch and prie,
            they leaze and off for weare,
            They worke the t
                  •
               ing that wicked is,
            they cursse, they ban and teare
            The blessed name of great Iehoue,
            and all to wyn the 
                  〈◊〉
               
            
            They put 
                  〈◊〉
                they practise still
            to get the golden
                  •
               ame.
            And first beholde our men of low:
            let them haue chiefest place,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
            
            Sith by the lawes 
                  〈◊〉
                comm
                  •
               n weath
            doth runne his 
                  〈…〉
               
            
            
               
And for that Lawes accoumpted are,
            eche where the chiefest staye:
            Let Lawiers then be principall,
            and first within my playe.
            But as for Judges now to iudge,Judges.
            
            my iudgement will nor saye:
            I wote full well, their prayse was spread
            by me this other daye.
            And Trueth it is, our Judgement seates
            such Uyrent beades possesse,
            As former dayes for men of choyse,
            had neuer such I guesse.
            What then? no sort, no one degrée,
            no place, no function so
            Uprightly standes, but with the good
            some wicked weede doth growe.
            With vertues league, som vice doth lyuk
            and forme of godly v
                  •
               w
            Oft equall makes with men of troth,
            some Hypocrites vntrue.
            I knowe friend Bertulph, s
                  •
               we there be
            whose hands regarde no meede,
            Whose hartes Dye no deceypt at all,
            from whome no harmes proceede.
            And sure I am, when cause of troth,
            before such men is tryde,
            With simple troth, they Justice yéelde,
            and iustly do decyde.
            
               
But nowe, although with these there syt
            no one that doth dissent
            Though all of them in publicque place
            doo sing Amesine lentent
            
            Yet vnderhande perhaps there are
            that nowe and then denoure
            The sugred sappe that Justice yeeldes:
            And where they lyst to lowre
            For spyte or gayne, or priuate wreke,
            there Justice course is stayde.
            And where they lyst to smoother troth,
            there, right is cleane dismayde.
            Such such there be (or haue bin some)
            who when they rule alone,
            When scope &amp; course hath hoyst them vp
            and set them chiefe in Throne
            From Censors sight, and priuate made
            their swaye and supreme place:
            Then then they wring &amp; wrong the right,
            then then they truth deface.
            Ah Bertulph, be there not thinke you,
            In place of Justice sette
            Some fained sortes of fawning Spreetes
            that course of Justice letts?
            That frame a semblaunce sound and good,
            that iuste and holy seeme,
            
               
                  •
               nd yet in harte are fraught with guyle,
            and ofte vniustly deeme?
            
               
I feare I feare me falsehod lurkes
            in lappes of learned syse
            I feare me Nummus oft peruerts
            in some that go for wyse:
            So then, some chiefe and some besides
            so smally ponder me
                  •
               de,
            That where they syt in common swaye,
            there, Justice doth procéede.
            But some againe where place hath made
            their powres distinct, I feare
            Of popish willes, through grut
                  •
               h or gaine
            with much enorme do beare.
            And hence, from hence I feare me come
            these cryes of common sort
            That oft lament and oft affyrme
            their Judgement to be 
                  •
               ort.
            One here be wayles his wofull case
            and wisheth him vnborne,
            Another cryes with wringing handes,
            alas, I am forlorne
            My sute thus long depended hath:
            The Lawe is on my syde,
            And yet in harde delayes I lye
            true Judgement to abyde.
            Another thus: be friended is,
            the Judge doth loue him well
            And me (as poore and needie) they
            doo dayly thus depell
            
               
Two hundreth myles and more I come:
            My Wife at home (alas)
            Lyes with my Children halfe forepynde:
            (O lamentable case.)
            My goods are spent, which labor brought,
            through long and carefull toyle:
            The Lawe hath lyckt vp all my wealth
            for which I dyd turmoyle.
            Oh, I can haue no Law nor right,
            ne Money haue I nowe:
            I must go beg, my goodes be gone,
            to lyue I knowe not howe.
            These eares of mine abhorred haue,
            mine eyes haue wet my plants.
            My hart hath ye
                  •
               nd in Judgement true,
            to see such wofull wants.
            Tys harde to saye, Ile holde my peace.
            But if these playnts be true,
            Syr Nummus swayeth there with some,
            (a woorthy cause to rue.)
            But vnto him that highest syts,
            and sées eche secrete yll,
            With prayer I commytte the same,
            t'amende it at his wyll.
            And nowe to Lawiers that do parle,Practisers at the Law.
            
            and pleade in cause of right.
            To such as for syr Nummus wyll
            turne darknesse into lyght,
            
               
And lyght into obscured sence,
            and arsiuersie turne eche thing:
            To such wyll I procéede as now,
            and to my matter bring.
            I wyll not speake of fine deuise,
            nor fowle deceyptfull clause,
            In Leases, wyls, and other lyke,
            but wresting of the Lawes
            And foding of the Clyent forth:
            for though that fraude abound,
            And though by falsely framing so,
            eche where are beggers founde:
            Yet I as nowe will blason forth,
            and geue you well to sée,
            Howe these men ioyne in matters false,
            retayned for a fée.
            And so for N
                     •
                  mmus long delays
            a poore and needy soule,
            To fleese and slea the simple wretche,
            to pylfer and to powle:
            To shred him cleane from all his wealth,
            and then perhaps 
                  •
               elent,
            And ware full colde to ayde his right,
            when Nummus all is spent.
            Yea lykewise tys in doubte with some,
            when Nummus so doth fayle,
            If they through brybe of thother syde,
            let not the sute to quayle.
            
               
A Fée of Forma pauperis
                     •
                  
               
            
            no no it hath no sent.
            Such formall Fées finde smal reliefe
            they buy no lande ne rent.
            My friend (therfore) if you haue nought
            wherewith to see me styll
            But formes and showes, Take formes againe
            for Counsayle if you wyll.
            But what sayde I? was promise made
            to paint such practise heere?
            No no: If so, I must relent:
            Great matter doth appeare
            Therein: and therefore will I leaue
            them to the worldly vewe:
            I meane the false and subtil ones,
            I speake not of the true,
            Nor such as are affected well
            (as many there are such
            Although the false in number doo
            excéede them very much.)
            But well, go too▪ this gotten good
            howe is it spent I praye?
            Forsooth, no poore man must haue lande:
            for so wyll they assaye
            And practise, that in tyme they wyll
            gette all into their handes,
            And turne the poore men headlong forth
            of all both house and landes.
            
               
A shame it were and great reproche
            to sée a poore man dwell,
            Or haue a house not farre from theirs:
            their Noses hate the smell.
            And long (no doubt) their Noses be,
            right mischeuous of Sent:
            For that which once was lande demeas
                  •
               e,
            is holden nowe for rent.
            They smell it forth, though farre it be:
            they haue a vengeaunce hooke:
            Both Parsuage and ought besides
            theyle haue by hooke or crooke.
            Their Princely Places stately be,
            their houses buylt for aye,
            Their Turrettes vp alo
                  •
               t are raysde,
            foundations déepe they laye,
            So thus (no doubt) and farre more yll,
            they let syr Nummus wagge,
            Reseruing still some mightie Masse
            to rust within the bagge,
            And here you sée what wayte they laye
            and eke what wayes they vse
            To get this pelfe: and gotten, sée
            how they the same abuse,
            The next are PetypractisersAno
                     ••••
                   and Petypractisers.
            
            and Petyfogging mates
                  •
               
            
            Yea, Clarkes, Attorneyes, such of them
            as lyue of lewde debates,
            
               
Eache honest calling towardes Lawe,
            so pressed is from Sise,
            That hardly can an honest man
            with honesty aryse.
            And twise as hardly may he stande,
            to stoppe eche strayned shyfte.
            Such force hath falsehood, more thē truth,
            so deadly can they lyfte.
            What crewes of greedy griping crowes,
            what fowle infecting rowte.
            Good Lord, what store of gleaning Jacks
            dispersed are through out?
            Can Lawes reliefe be easily got,
            or gotten, can't do ease,
            Where such great troupes of bribing fists
            must fyrst syr Nummus cease?
            Of trueth such 
                  ••
               aines, of truthles mates
            such heapes of monsters dwell
            Tweene playnts and fynall Judgements seate,
            that greater woes in hell
            If hell were as the Poets wryte,
            I thinke coulde not be felt.
            Care S
                  •
               les haue ende, such chardge, such toyle,
            as make my harte to melt.
            But whence aryse these rauening rowtes?
            whence spring they? Sure from guyle
            And of disdaine to vulgare state,
            wherein their Parents toyle.
            
               
Well, these be they, that what for tale
            and what for falsehod great,
            Doo taynt the Realme with stryfes, &amp; stop
            the waye to Justice seate.
            That make the iuyce of Justice sowre,
            that turne the Lawes to wreake,
            That make true Judgemēt taste like gall,
            that nought but falsehod speake.
            That liue and lustily lashe out
            in purchase or in pride
            More largely then of Countrey States
            doth any State beside.
            But here to shew what prowling means,
            what pranckes this pylfring sort
            Doo vse to gette syr Nummus with,
            and so holde vp their porte:
            This this to doo, were to to harde.
            Naye, this were such a woorcke
            As if one only man should prease
            to fight against the Turcke.
            But greater, yea farre greater t'were
            to clense this Chanell cleane.
            I thinke Augaeus Oxestalles were
            to this a worcke but meane.
            I knowe good Judges haue begoonne
            and waded verie farre
            I knowe that some, to helpe these hurtes,
            right godly carefull are.
            
               
But new found Clerckes and Officers
            so prease with might and mayne,
            That (Hydra like) one head cut of,
            for eary head springs twayne.
            Good Lord, &amp; shall these wandring Spréets
            aye walcke abroade at wyll?
            Shall Nūmus no where start, but streight
            these Catchpolles catch him styll?
            Shall no mannes eye that lyues this day,
            beholde a better state?
            Ah, out alas, and shall this rowte
            feede alwayes of debate?
            Why then, what man shall lyue in peace?
            whose porcion shall be fast?
            Whose land and lyuing shall be frée
            where these men once are plast?
            And where almost, or in what Soyle
            do not these Monsters swarme?
            What coast frend Bertulph can you name
            where these men do not harme?
            I knowe in thissame calling are
            a sort of seemely Wights
            That lyue in peace, and further peace,
            that so their Countrey dights
            With sounde examples of good life,
            with Justice and with truth,
            That scarce from any state of men
            a better lyfe ensuth.
            
               
And in this speache of mine, I meane
            and eke do comprehende
            Not only Clerckes and Practisers
            But also do intende
            That Counsaylers haue equall praise
            and higher praise in deede
            By howe much they in higher place
            and higher thinges proceede.
            But these, all these are nowe so matcht
            and ouerswayde with swarmes:
            That seeld and seldome can they helpe
            to keepe the good from harmes.
            I wishe to God some Theseus
            
            might giue a choppe or twayne
            And rather then these heads should stand,
            to choppe and choppe againe.
            Nowe, wheras Bertulph here perhaps
            you looke I should declare
            How this great Rabble rakes for coyne,
            and howe they Nummus snare:
            I tell you as I tolde you earst,
            this is too much for me:
            The pennes of twenty skilfull men
            for this would néedefull be.
            In briefe, yet thus I dare affyrme
            that these superfluous traynes
            In Lawyers state, vse fowle deceytes
            t'inlarge their priuate gaynes,
            
               
Which gotten once, is lewdly spent
            in pompe and prowde araye,
            To whose fowle rapine séely wightes
            are ofte and ofte a praye.
            I leaue them as I lefte the rest,
            I touche and go my wayes.
            This short discourse shewes well enough
            howe here syr Nummus swayes.
            Finis.
         
         
            The thyrde Satyr.
            ADuert we nowe who else there bePaule.
            
            that grasping gape for gaine,
            And let vs place them in the cue
            amongst this gréedy traine.
            PhisitionsPhisitions. take the seconde roome,
            for worthy so they be:
            They stately stalcke, and beare a port
            in London now we see.
            With reuerence and worship great,
            with cap and eake with knee,
            Wee must beseche his Maistership
            our Patient to see,
            
               
And what of this? will this suffice?
            No: Nummus doth the deede,
            
               Vnguentum Aureum or such lyke
            will make him'runne with speede.
            Go Symon go, or Gilbert else,
            go cast my footecloth on?
            No néede to byd to Doctor go,
            he will be gone anon.
            And when hées there, with solempne face
            and graue deuised porte
            He frames his talke for to perswade
            or else for to dehorte
            As lykes him best: he both can doo,
            and both so finely frame,
            That Nummus shall be nymmed streight,
            O passing pretie game?
            Who would not blushe to sée such frawde,
            and such fine framed knacks?
            Who would not hate the falsehoode vyle
            of these so pieuish Jackes?
            And (soothly if I should affirme)
            I heare so much deceat
            Of theirs in progging after gaine,
            as tongue can not repeat.
            And (as of course) I doo demaunde
            howe they doo spend the same?
            Forsooth, I heare no good they doo:
            No man can iustly blame
            
               
Or ought accuse them of good déedes.
            But this my selfe can saye,
            That most thereof that I sée spent,
            is on apparell gaye.
            For but of late, ene thus I heard
            a worthy Doctor say:
            My matters frame not as I would,
            Ile worke some other way.
            I see these wéedes be not to weare.
            Ile henceforth so prouide,
            That I will haue a pretie Nagge
            about the Towne to ride.
            Ile haue a footecloath, and each thing
            belonging to the same:
            My felow Doctor hath the lyke,
            and passing flyes his name.
            A Gowne with graundcape will I haue,
            a swinging Ueluet Cap,
            A Coate according verie braue:
            and then ift be my hap,
            With mighty lookes, and learning such
            as God hath giuen mée,
            Ile hooke syr Nummus to my handes,
            and make the Ruddockes flee
            For feare almost into my purse.
            Ile leaue my simple gate,
            Ile rather frame my selfe to ride
            lyke one of high estate.
            
               
And what? were these but scoffing words?
            Yes sure, hée (earnest bent)
            Hath so purueyde, that now he hath
            euen all for that intent.
            And thus you sée with how great care
            they séeke t'enrich their store,
            You sée the pride that they mayntaine
            through this excessiue lore.
            And (well I wote) none other meanes
            of spence at all I sée,
            But only such as wicked are:
            (if any else there be.)
            Wherefore, it séemes they hoorde it vp
            and hyde it from the Sunne:
            They couer't close, and lock it fast
            tyll more thereto be wonne,
            They giue small almes as I can heare,
            for beggars barcke apace,
            And say that they of all men woorst
            relieue their wofull case:
            Their pride is great, and high they looke
            for feare of waxing lowe:
            Theyle giue no place to any man
            where ere they hap to go.
            I well recorde a pretie tale
            alluding to a truthe:
            I force not much to tell it you.
            Harke how the same ensuthe?
            
               
Once hapt it (through a fowle mischance)A Ciuilian, or a Canonist, or both.
            
            that great debate did ryse
            Betweene a Doctor in the Law
            (for so th'example lyes)
            And Doctor (eke) of Phisick, who
            should haue the vpper hande
            In each assembly where they met
            to walke, to syt or stande.
            The Lawyer layed for him selfe
            and sayde well to the case,
            Phisition dyd full wisely to
            and with a goodly grace:
            Alledging well (euen both of them)
            lyke handsome learned men.
            But nought could be agreed vpon.
            So fell the matter then,
            That they vnto the Pretor would
            for to decyde the same.
            They made relation of the case
            and finely gan it frame.
            The Pretor when he heard the dolts
            contend about a Straw,
            Was soone content to iudge the same,
            and askte the man of Law
            Who went vnto the Gallowes first,
            the Hangman or the Thiefe?
            Who formost was of both them two
            and which was there the chiefe?
            
               
The Hangman quoth the Lawyer tho,
            for he doth kyll the man:
            The Hangman he must go before,
            the Theefe must follow▪ Than
            Quoth Pretor harke. This is my minde
            and iudgement in the case.
            Phisition he must go before,
            and Lawyer giue him place.
            Why then (quoth Bertulph) by your taleBertulph.
            
            Phisitions men doo kyll.
            And Lawyers liue by robbing men,
            and so their Cofers fyll.
            Whereby with pride emboste they swell,
            and whereby (raging) they
            T'advaunce themselues to honors type
            vnlawfull meanes assay.
            Yea sure (quoth Paule) and so they dooPaule.
            
            a number of them now.
            But as for our Phisitions,
            their cunning knoweth how
            Aswell to kyll,Such are the euyll sort. as to purloyne:
            they are expert in all.
            And force not (so that Nummus come)
            which way their staffe doo fall,
            One hath a Potion for to serueA Potion to cure all kinde of diseases and grief
                     ••
                  .
            
            and cure eche kinde of griefe,
            Héele sell a quart for fortie pence.
            This fellow is the chiefe
            
               
And finest chylde in casting of
            mens waters when they néede.
            Héele byd the healthy get him home
            and make his Wyll with speede.
            Although he liue from that tyme long,
            without all kinde of paine.
            Héele make him doubt and dread his life,
            and all for filthy gaine.
            
               Carnifitia potius Medici quàm no
                  
                     ••
                  ne dig
                  
                     ••
                  . He wyll perswade that men haue lyu'de
            in whordome and excesse,
            Where neuer raigned fond affect,
            and whoredome much the lesse.
            Another is so Doltlyke séene
            and learnedly beguylde,
            That when he seeth your vrine, he
            wyll say you be with childe
            Although you be a man: for sur
                  •
               
            
            but hittie missie he
            And so full many of them play,
            so Bussardlike they be.
            O Paule, quoth Bertulph, giue mée leaue
            to interrupt you here.
            For by your patience, yle requite
            the tale you tolde whyle ere.
            Content quoth Paule (and with good wyll)
            I am right well apayde
            To heare thy tale: my talke shall cease
            tyll thou thy minde haue sayde.
            
               
There dwelt (somtime) where I was bornBertulph.
            
            a perfite cunning man,
            A good Phisition well beseene:
            and so it happed than,
            That he should ryde abroade to see
            a Patient of his.
            He had a man that roade with him
            (a ioly Knaue ywis.)
            The Doctor draue his Horse apace
            and roade with mery cheere.
            He longed sore to see the place
            where Nummus should appeere.
            But as he pricked forth in haste,
            by chaunce he did espie
            A sort of Felons in a Carte
            adiudged there to die.
            And musing what y• prease should meane,
            he sent his man with speede.
            To knowe the cause of all the crowde:
            his man performde the deede.
            And posting, soone he did perceyue
            the Theeues to hanging prest.
            He turnd his Horse at sight thereof:
            To flye, he thought it best.
            And so he dyd with sturdie pace,
            He gallopt on his way.
            And as a man halfe skarde, he fled
            as nought might make him stay.
            
               
His Maister lowdly askte the cause
            why he dyd ryde so fast.
            O Maister saue your selfe (quoth he)
            I vize you make good haste.
            The Doctor swallowde vp with feare,
            spurde Cut and made away.
            And tyll he came within a myle,
            his Horse did neuer stay.
            But when hée came vnto himselfe,
            be called backe his man
            And him demaunding cause of griefe,
            the fellowe thus began.
            O Maister, thanke we God (quoth he)
            for this our good escape:
            Else surely had we swinged both
            within an hempen Tape.
            For yonder, where the prease was so,
            I sawe thrée handsome men
            Which for the death of only one,
            were to be hanged then.
            But when I sawe that they (for one)
            were all adiudgde to dye,
            No neede to byd mée haste me thence,
            no neede to byd mee flye:
            For well I wyst, if you were séene
            which haue a number slaine,
            You should haue bene trust vp in haste
            and neare returnde againe.
            
               
The Doctor being thus informde,
            knew not what best to say.
            He thought as chyldish him to take
            and lightly him to way.
            Wyse man you are no doubt, (quoth he)
            the Uicar of saint Fooles
            Go shriue you: for you haue bene taught
            in some well learned schooles.
            Shrewde foole quoth Paule, I warrāt you,Paule
            
            but fooles and chyldren oft
            Doo tell the truth: for all men know
            their tongues are very soft.
            But well, no doubte, yet some there be
            in London (whome I know)
            That both do gette syr Nummus well,
            and well the same bestowe.
            That leade no doubt a vertuous lyfe,
            and lyue in Godly feare:
            That goodes to get by meanes peruerse
            at all times wyll forbeare.
            Of those I haue not talcked here,
            nor of the honest sort.
            But such as (galled) seeme to kicke,
            herein I doo exhort
            To kéepe their patience when they sée
            their faults reproued heere.
            For sure I am that in my tale
            gainst good doth nought appeere.
            
               
And so I leaue them to the Lorde,
            and bid them all adue.
            My tongue in order must recorde
            such things as do ensue.
            Finis.
         
         
            The fourth Satyr.
            THapothecarie here I leaue,Apothecaties &amp; Surg
                     •
                  ons. Paule.
               
            
            which so for Nummus 
               
                  •
               ugges,
            That he y• people noyes with pelfe,
            and filthy stincking drugges.
            So let I passe the Surgeon,
            who with his fowle deceyte,
            Doth hooke syr Nummus to his handes
            and takes him at receyte.
            The pelting patches will presume
            to practise Phisick, and
            Will minister lyke learned men
            in places of the Land.
            Let go such Squibs: I know them not.
            Yet people do complaine:
            And well I wote, they vse such wayes
            for meare intent to gaine.
            A rablement of raskall Roges
            as if weeld harrow hell,
            I thinke we should not finde the lyke
            in Plutoes house to dwell.
            
               
But let them packe, Ile passe them ore.
            Perhaps there many be
            Both honest, good, and expert men,
            they shall goe by for me.
            And now yle turne me to my tale,
            and (as my course doth tende)
            To euyll sort of Marchaunt menMarch
                     •••
                   men.
            
            the sequele wyll I bende.
            Lets see (I praye) howe they turmoyle
            and fixe their whole intent
            To catche syr Nummus by the coate.
            Let's see how they be bent
            And sole addicted vnto gaine.
            One runnes me to the Indes,
            To Gynnie, Spaine, and Calecut:Not the deede but the inte
                     ••
                   is to be misliked.
            
            where he such chaffare findes,
            As (there although it cost him small)
            wyll bring him here a pounde:
            Yea, ten perhaps, or else they lye
            which in such welth abounde.
            Another skuds me ore the Seas,
            and fully fraught with toyes,
            He brings them into London, where
            a
                  •
               length he welth enioyes.
            The people are so fondly bent,
            theyle chaunge their Cheese for chalck.
            And for such pelting pienish trashe,
            the yle let good chaffare walck.
            
               
O foolishe,
                  
                     •
                  ueros pue rilia decent. fonde and doltishe momes,
            oh men deuoyde of wit,
            O Capons cramde with barly corne:
            howe farre are stones vnfit
            For such pyld palting pieuish Cockes?
            howe yll bestowde is welth
            On such new fangled fondish foltesA Foole wyll not giue his hable for the Tower of London.
            
            which chaunge the same for pelth?
            One bringes mee ore a painted Priest,
            another bringes a Nunne,
            And shops are fraught with toyes, wherewith
            are English people wonne.
            Another grounded well in wealth,
            (acquainted with the guyse)
            Doth bring vs in such daynties, as
            the man can best deuise.
            Some else there be, and many such
            (chiefe Marchaunts in the Towne)
            That for our Peacocks plumes doo bring
            and sylcks the streame adowne:
            They knowe the Lawes doo lymit where▪
            
            and what such should be worne,
            And they such Lawes to execute,
            haue eftsoones office borne.
            And yet for that their gaine is such
            and wealth so great therby,
            They must forbeare, and wincking walk.
            The Lawes must lawlesse lye:
            
               
And Uarlets vaunt about the streate,
            lyke men of high estate:
            Their Hosen strowting forth with silcke,
            and plumes vpon their pate.
            The Raskalles now must roame abroade
            lyke men of honest port:
            And Strumpets stately in attire
            lyke Ladies must resort
            To places where them selues thinke best
            without all kinde of doubt:
            They customde are about the Towne
            and shall be borne out.
            It seemeth so vndoubtedly:
            for nothing is amended.
            Although the Lawes haue sharply set
            and punishment extended.
            Nowe, other some vagaries fetch
            abroade I wote ner where,
            And they bring in most pleasaunt spiceSuch as bring them in for intent aforesayde are to be blamed.
            
            with Hops and other geare:
            These make fine mouthed Gentlemen.
            For who but Marchaunts now?
            Who wallow more in wealth than they
            lyke péeres I wote 
                  •
               er how?
            Yea,I speake not of the trade but of the corruption of who are they but Marchauntmen
            that haue the costly fare?
            Who now in banquets with these men
            are able to compare?
            
               
For such straunge store of diuers meatesthe trade &amp; abuse of the same.
            
            and dishes finely wrought?
            Who hath the lyke? no man besides.
            Welnigh it costes them nought.
            They sell so deare and take such gaine,
            that well they may afoorde
            To set fine Marchpanes and such lyke
            vpon their seruaunts boorde.
            Thus may we sée these kinde of men
            how they for Nummus prodde:
            A man would thinke that soothly they
            take Nummus for a Godde.
            They labor so with might and maine,
            they so besturre their stumpes.Although they haue money in such price, yet euyll gotten goodes shall be ill spent.
            
            They exercise such ackward wayes
            to bring it in by lumps.
            They scratch, they scrape, they mise, they muse
            at night when they should rest.
            They searche their senses and bethinke
            howe to obteyne it best.
            And ah alas, some do deuise
            to let it out for gaine:
            Such gaine as at the length will bring
            to them infernall paine.
            And (not content with fowle deceyt
            that they in sale do vse)
            Some of them do in lone alas
            their countrymen abuse.
            
               
Let Preachers crye and tell them o
                  •
               t,
            but nothing will preuayle:
            They flocke, they floute, and iest at it.
            They bid them kisse their tayle.
            They haue no shame, but (brasen fasde)
            they stick not it to callA lament
                     ••
                  ble ca
                     ••
                  .
            
            A gainesome Occupation.
            And so the people fall
            From honest state, to plaine banckrowte
            through such their Wooluish wayes.
            The Commons neare were so opprest
            as in these wofull dayes.
            They hooke, they hawke for Nummus so,
            they cogge, they foyst and powle,
            They lay such snares by broking meanes,
            that thus they Nummus towle.
            A thousande meanes sinistre, they
            account and call exchaunge,
            Although thereby be men vndone:
            the case is verie straunge.
            And wofull tys no doubt to sée
            how lightly they do way
            Th'account which must be made by them
            to God another day.
            They are right wise in worldly wytte:
            surpassing is their braine.
            But oh, they do applie the same
            to nothing else but gaine.
            
               
And when they haat, how is it spent?
            Attende a whyle, and you
            Shall haue it layde before your eyes
            and set vnto the vew.
            This day, my Lorde his speciall friende
            must dyue with him (no naye)
            His Partners, Friendes and Aldermen:
            wherefore he must puruaye
            Both Capon, Swan, and Her
                  •
               shoe good,
            fat Bit
                  •
               ure, Larcke and Quayle?
            Right Plouer, S
                  •
               ype, and Woodcock fine
            with Curlew, Wype and Rayle:
            Stoneti
                  •
               ets, Teale, and Pecteales good,
            with Busterd fat and plum,
            Fat Pheasaunt Powt, and Plouer base
            for them that after come.
            Stent, Stockard, Stampine, Tāterueale,
            and Wigeon of the best:
            Puyt, Partrich, Blackbirde and
            fat Shoueler with the rest.
            Two Warrants eke he must prouide
            to haue some Uenson fat.
            And meanes héele make for red Déere too,
            (there is no nay of that.)
            And néedefully he must prouide
            (although we speake not o
                  •
               t)
            Both Peacock, Crane, and Turkicock,
            and (as such men are wont.)
            
               
He must foresee that he ne lacke
            colde bakemeates in the ende:
            With Custards, Tarts, and Florentines,
            the bancquet to amende.
            And (to be short and knit it vp)
            he must not wanting sée
            Straunge kindes of fysh at second course
            to come in their degrée.
            As Porpesse, Seale and Salmond good
            with Sturgeon of the best
            And Turbot, Lobster, with the lyke
            to furnish out the feast.
            All this theyle haue, and else much more,
            sydes Marchpane and gréene Cheese,
            Stewde wardens, Prunes, &amp; sweete conserues
            with spiced Wine like Lées.
            Gréeneginger, Sucket, Suger Plate,
            and Marmaladie fine:
            Blauncht Almonds, Peares and Ginger bread.
            But Peares should we assigne
            And place before (as méete it is)
            at great mens boordes: for why,
            Rawe fruites are first in seruice styll,
            Else Seruing men doo lye.
            But now me thinkes, one quips me vp
            and spurs a question héere.
            He sayes (forsooth) that I mislike
            to haue men kéepe good chéere.
            
               
In déede, the stomack ouerchardgde
            and man full gorgde with meate,
            Doth make the minde and inwarde man
            vnfit for reasons seate.
            For chaunge no doubt annoyes the man,
            and meate not well indewde,
            Doth make the same scant halfe a man
            it reason be renewde.
            And what of this? shoulde this reformde,
            house kéeping now depell?
            No sure, for hospitalitie
            becomth them very well.
            But that this chéere is alway such,
            I plainely do deny.
            Some feast great men for frendship sake,
            and let the poore go by.
            They rather doot to oppresse the poore,
            and by such friendship got,
            The poore haue nought within their hands
            which they get to them not.
            For what through frendship welth &amp; force
            no one enioyes the thing,
            That (if they lyke) some will not soone
            into their clouches bring.
            But goods yll gote, are euyll spent.
            And howe can they bestowe
            Their welth on poore and Preachers true
            Which through deceyt did growe?
            
               
No f
                  •
               e, t'were shame and fowle reprochs
            t'aue beggers at their borde:
            An't seemes (some think) all yll bestowde
            that's spent t'encrease Gods worde.
            For (worse then this) some cannot byde
            t'aue beggers at their gate,
            Nor not repine when Preachers lyue
            in meane and simple state.
            O Labirinths of lothsome lust,
            O hellish humane harts,
            O beastly belching bely gods
            that thus their store conuarts:
            O lumpishe Luskes, that lieffer had
            to haue of Uiands store:
            To winne the Rytchman, then to féede
            the begger at their dore.
            O stony harts, that more estéeme
            a Monckey tyde with chaine,
            Then their poore brother, for whose sake
            Christe Jesus sufferde paine.
            O wicked Wights of wooluish kinde,
            which so the Lambes denowre,
            And crāckly cram themselues with spoyls
            of needy soules each howre.
            And (more then this:) for how doth walck
            Sir Nummus day by daye?
            How trudgeth it to buy the Wife
            and Daughter fine arraye?
            
               
They must not go as other doo.
            Wherefore, they must deuise
            To haue them knowne from cōmon sort
            by some newfangled guise.
            T'is méete therefore, as they do not
            with courtlyke Dames compare,
            Euen so they should from townish wiues
            their garments new repaire.
            And so (forsooth) his wife must haue
            prepared out of hand,
            Gaye garments of the finest stuffe
            that is within the land.
            She must haue Partlet, Square &amp; Lace,
            with Chaine about hir neck:
            She must haue costly kinde of chaunge,
            and all thinges at hir beck.
            Hir Daughter also must be clad
            well lyke a Ladies féere,
            And all to walcke about the streate
            with hir true Louer déere.
            What tho? Forsooth, she must not wed
            but with some wealthie man,
            And one that must be grounded rych,
            though honest when he can.
            And thus I say (aswell t'is séene)
            fayre Par
                  •
               ell must be pranckt
            And walcke at wyll: whereby it haps
            oft tymes that she is banckte.
            
               
And all through meanes euen of hir Sire
            which so consumes his good,
            And ioyes therein, more then to giue
            the hungrie wretch his foode.
            Chaunce some men sée good déedes they do.
            But in good sooth not I
            (Though many naught) can vnderstand.
            T'were sinne on them to lye.
            And nowe, as some you sée to scrape
            by vyle sinistre wayes:
            So may you sée them spend as yll
            in these our later dayes.
            I meane for so much as they spend,
            But well haue we to weete,
            Their hoording and their Chesting vp
            is all as farre vnmeete
            As this their spence and filthy trade,
            as this their prowling guise,
            As this their building all for gaine
            and profite to aryse:
            As this their hatefull vyle contempt
            of poore and needy Wights:
            As this their robbing and their stealth.
            As these their sinfull slights.
            The poore complaine and wanting, crye
            through hunger halfe forepinde:
            And some through want, about them haue
            their fainting breath resignd.
            
               
And yet their Cofers farced lye.
            Their Bags are filde at full.
            But wote you what? it is reseru'de
            For Tib his pretie Trull,
            And Dick his Boy that dappart ladde:
            which for his sake, perchaunce
            Euen both of them, when he is gone,
            wyll make syr Nummus daunce.
            But alwayes this is not the cause
            of such their spitefull hoord.
            For certs I thinke they neuer looke
            at all to come aboord
            In crooked Charons vgly Boate:
            Or else perhaps they thinke
            (As long they haue) the Pope shall purge
            and saue them all for thinke.
            And in the meane time weene they best
            to couer't close and fine,
            And bring more toot, t'encrease the heape.
            This iudgement is of mine.
            Else thinges amisse, before exprest,
            should nere so yll remaine,
            But soone they would reforme them well
            and make them streight againe.
            Which so to do, God graunt them grace.
            And clense their fylthie mindes:
            That Auarice maye once decay
            which so their body bindes,
            
               
And subiect makes to vyle deuise,
            to Usurie and deceate,
            That naught they are, and wyll persist
            tyll grace do blow retreate.
            I ende with them: protesting styll
            I touch no good man héere,
            But such as through these words of mine
            shall wrathfull bent appéere.
            For sure I am that many iust,
            and men vpright remaine,
            Exempted from this talke of mine.
            Who neuer yet with staine
            Or spot of beastly Usurie
            or vile notorious vice,
            Were once corrupted or infect.
            which are discrete and wise.
            And (truth it is) they nill disdaine
            at this troth telling tale.
            And for the rest, let them adue,
            my tongue must further vale.
            Finis.
         
         
            The fift Satyr.
            TIs straūge to sée what small account
            men nowe a dayes do make:
            How slightly they let slip the paine
            of Brimstone burning lake.
            
               
How fondly they perswade them selues
            (at least how they suppose)
            That griesly death shall neuer strike.
            That ey
                  •
               e shall neuer close.
            O sottish sinfull brittle age.
            O mad and blockish Mome.
            O doltish foole, and wilfull wretch
            that here dost hope for home
            And dwelling aye vnto thy selfe.
            Howe art thou wilfull blinde?
            I tell thee, I, thou hence shalt flit
            lyke dust blowne forth with winde.
            Let wearish wimpled age growe on:
            let head be hoarie white,
            And olde be thou: yet at the last
            blackwinged death shall smite.
            But what is he can promise heere
            him selfe to liue a day?
            No doubt not one. Death vnawares
            shall take our life away.
            And when we thinke vs surest, then
            most often doth he strike.
            O then why do we lyngre on
            to sleepie sluggerds lyke?
            O, why should men thus mucker vp
            such falsely gotten gaine?
            Or why should they by wicked wayes
            seeke wealth for to obtaine?
            
               
But soft a while,Banckrowtes. what neede these words?
            as good to bolde my peace:
            For loe how Banckrowts ginne for gaine
            to put them selues in prease.
            Shall fraude lye hid vnfriended now?
            Shall fowle Deceyt be gon?
            Shall Wylie want? No, barcke a while,
            and you shall heare anon.
            Some men there be that beare a porte,
            and liue lyke to the best.
            That feast, y• flow, that chop, that chaūge,
            and practise with the rest.
            That Office beare,I haue made a dyfference betweene the wilfull and the cōtrarie. and worthy seeme
            through welth to weelde the charge.
            That saue, that spende, &amp; bargaines make,
            that keepe their trade at large.
            That warte worke, and winde to them
            good credite in the ende.
            That get such friendes as wyll not stick
            a thousand pound to lende.
            Oft more oft lesse: almost as much
            as they can well demaunde.
            For why, their credite now is such,
            that they may men commaunde.
            But what of this? Euen this forsooth.
            Theyle shut vp doore anon,
            Theyle giue vp office, trade and all:
            farewell, they will be gone.
            
               
When they haue gote the most they can,
            they wyll become banckrowte,
            They wyll no longer styfeled be
            amongst the honest rowte.
            They can no longer byde the trade
            which honest men do vse.
            They keepe at home amongst their bags,
            Theyle honesty refuse.
            Theyle lurking lye lyke Theefe in denne,
            lyke Drane vpon the spoyle.
            Theyle grease their lips, &amp; fat their paūch,
            with honest Marchaunts toyle.
            O dreyrie dregges of dampishe caue,
            O fowle infernall fiendes,
            O tryple stinged Uipers broode,
            O hagges of hellishe mindes.
            O Cyctops such as styll deuoure
            the sheepe of forreine foldes,
            O brockish beastes with rauine gorgde:
            that lurcke within their holdes.
            Shall duskie drosse of Dytis ca
                  •
               e
            denie infecting death?
            Shall Oreus spare with skalding skortch
            to noye their vitall breath?
            No sure, the pitchie burning pit,
            and Limboes flaming Lake
            Shall yolpe them vp, except they yéelde
            the goodes which they did take.
            
               
Or else to powre requite the same,
            But this they neuer thinck:
            For marck how they do still bestowe
            this beastly gotten chinck.
            And here I must aduertise you
            that some besides there bee
            Which oft by meanes becom banckrowte
            (as dayly we may see.)
            For some exceede and so abounde
            in Epi
                  •
               ureous fare,
            That so at length they banckrowte be
            and bring them selues full bare.
            And othersome through great excesse
            and prowde surpassing charge,
            In braue arraye do bring them selues
            into Cock lorrels Barge.
            When ere sawe you their Dames so nice,
            and wines so richly clad?
            When wīst yo
                  •
                Women ere so proude,
            or Husbandes ere so mad?
            O where are Matrones now become?
            O where are Husbands graue?
            Where are y• Wiues that tooke such care
            their honesty to saue?
            Woulde Matrones walcke or Wiues discreet
            with syluer shining browes
            From streat to streat? no, rather they
            would kéepe within their howse.
            
               
Would Matrons skud to common games
            and prancke in earle prease?
            No, tys to vyle, I loath to tell.
            Ile therefore holde my peace.
            Tys this, tys this, y• Banckrowts breede.
            This brings the wife yll name.
            The husband thus is bare through spence,
            and wife naught by the same.
            And nowe you see a difference
            twéene him that banckrow
                  •
               e is
            Of vyle intent, and him that falles
            through great excesse of his.
            But both of these perhaps a lyke
            by fraude haue Nummus gote,
            Though both in care and wanting pine
            syng not lyke dolefull note.
            And now
                  •
               , (as to my promise made
            at fyrst when I began)
            Ile place syr Nummus caught by Foole
                  •
               
               Fooles and Roysters.
            
            and Roysters now and than.
            A wise man dyes, and welthy leaues
            his sonne in goodes and lands.
            The young man (when he is of age)
            takes all into his handes.
            And streight to Court, or Innes of Court,
            he goes to leade his lyfe)
            Where franck he is, and youthfull bent
            for why, haas Nummus ryfe.
            
               
Or else, if not: So he ban lande
            or ought that's Money worth,
            He shall not want of Marchauntmen
            fine silcks to set him forth.
            Nor Money will they stick at all
            to lende him at his néede.
            As long as ought he doth possesse,
            theyle neuer cease to feede
            My yonker and yong Maister so.
            And he (when once he sees
            The bridle layde vpon his necke)
            is loath much time to léese.
            For why, he wisht it long before:
            And sith he doth espie
            The matter wholy in his handes,
            why should he longer lye
            Lyke blunt John Whoball all at home?
            No fie, heele haste him now.
            Both lybertie and Chinck ynough
            himselfe he will allow.
            And streightway (else the world is hard)
            He meetes with Copesmates, such
            As to exalt and set him forth,
            at all will nothing grutch.
            And hée forsooth must foremost be
            in euery braue attempt.
            Who eare be one, yong Maister must
            at no time he exempt.
            
               
Héele be the chiefe within the Masks
            and chiefe in bancquet: hée
            Shall syt exalted to the Sunne,
            Euen to the tenth degrée.
            And now and then (else scapes he well)
            heele haue a spyrt at Dice.
            He wantes no mates to bring him too't
            by slight and fine deuice.
            He must haue walkinges in the night:
            he must be braue and fine.
            He must be of the hoygh no doubt.
            He neuer must repine
            Although it be to sit it oute
            all night in costly game.
            And (more then this) he must not stick
            to paye for all the same.
            And when he seemely seemeth once,
            and thinks well of himselfe,
            Then, then no doubt he is stird vp
            to spende this noysome pelfe.
            And then (I saye) with posting speede
            he must be gaylie dect
            In colours of his Ladie, and
            therein not 
                  •
               ught neglect
            That's incident to euery sute:
            Of chaunge he must haue store,
            And frame himselfe full scatly then
            to euery lusty lore.
            
               
And doubtlesse then he is so drownde
            in pleasure and in pride,
            That nought at all may him withdrawe:
            It hath bene often tride.
            Yea, though at length he féele great smart
            through that he made away:
            Yet is his minde so hawtie then,
            that he can make no stay.
            For wo
                  •
               e you what, vse custome brings,
            and yong
                  •
               er thus doth say:
            Shall I make spare whyle ought is left
            and so lyue wanting? Naye,
            It were a shame and great reproche,
            if I that euer haue
            As yet lyu'de lyke a Gentleman,
            should now lyue like a slaue.
            And so my chylde no chaungling is,
            tyll all be spent and gone:
            And till his mates him needie leaue
            and comfortlesse alone.
            From which time forth if ought he haue,
            whereof may Nummus ryse:
            He will lyue shi
                  •
               ting til't be gone.
            Then forth of Towne he flyes
            And kéepes the high way side (perchaunce)
            to lyue by theft and spoyle:
            Till Tyborne twitch him by the neck
            and Hangman giue the foyle.
            
               
So that's the ende of all his wealth
            and ending of the man.
            But goods perhaps were euill gote:
            and who can maruaile than
            Though that the same were all consumde
            in filthy vaine exspence?
            And who will doubt that gallowes should
            such Dingthrifts recompence?
            But one thing I do here lament
            and tys most wicked sure,
            Tys noysome, vyle and beastly trade,
            yet most of all in vre.
            A Gentleman his childe doth sende
            t'apply his studies here,
            With hope to haue him do the same
            as daylie doth appere.
            The youth oft tymes declyneth streight
            as apt to youthly guise:
            And sets his minde to make him braue
            with all he may deuise.
            The Citizen when that he sées
            the bruite so brauely bent,
            Doth closely search the yong mans state,
            and learnes the whole extent
            Of all his possibilitie,
            which knowne, he will not spare
            For friendship sake vnto the same
            of loane to let his ware.
            
               
The yong man hauing welth at wyll
            and all thinges at request,
            Byds booke adue, and cuts it out
            as brauelie as the best.
            How vyle this is, let all men iudge.
            how oft it comes to passe,
            The yongmen brought to naught therby,
            are witnesses alas.
            Oh, where is loue or feare of God?
            Wher's faith for to be found?
            Wher's friendship, truth and honestie?
            Where doth not Fame resound
            The beastly pranckes of wicked men?
            Wher's one that thinks of God?
            Wher's one that doubts or feareth ought
            the sharpnesse of his rod?
            How few be there that tread the pathes
            or trace Dame vertues steps?
            How many rather be there now
            that quite from vertue leps?
            O wofull case: the best almost
            do much account it now
            If they from vile notorious faultes
            at any time do bow.
            How talke our tatlers of the truth
            and Scripture still discusse?
            How lyue they quite contrarie yet
            for all their talking thus?
            
               
How earnest bent are men as now
            to heare the worde of God?
            (I meane professors of the trueth.)
            How farre yet liue they od?
            They crie Lord Lord, and God be praysde:
            but streight within an howre,
            That heate of theirs is colde as stone.
            Such heate hath made them sowre.
            O thou good God and Father kinde:
            were not thy mercies great,
            Thou wouldst destroy these men with fire
            from thy supernall seat.
            O heauenlie Prince of glorie: and
            O thou alone Iehoue,
            
            Thou God of grace, oh louing Christ,
            yond whome we can not roaue
            Or raunge aright: yond whome no man
            can perfite blisse attaine:
            Thou only one, and all in one,
            yond whome doth nought remaine:
            Giue grace vnto thy wandring sheepe.
            Fetch home the same againe,
            Sith blood of thine hath them redéemde
            from sharpe infernall paine.
            Graunt graunt (O God) thy holy spréete
            to guide, defend and kéepe
            All such as in most lothsome sinne,
            are yet not falne sléepe.
            
               
Saue thine elect from noysome trade
            of worldly minded men:
            Let not the custome of the worlde
            their lyfe with vices blen.
            From place to place, from streat to streat,
            from house to house, alas:
            Yea, and well nigh from man to man
            doth sinfull lyuing passe.
            Not words preuaile, nor preaching ought,
            can turne the peoples harts:
            No kinde of thing can moue their minds.
            O, death is their desarts,
            O, Hell their hire, and burning flame,
            is guerdon of their déedes:
            No one almost in hart doth beare
            the true repentaunt séedes.
            O, horror doth possesse my heade,
            And whyle through towne I trace,
            Deepe cutting cares annoy my hart.
            to see such want of grace.
            No sparckle, iote or small remaine,
            no signe of godly feare,
            No badge at all of christen men
            doth any person weare
            Or kéepe almost throughout the Towne,
            O, what a case is this,
            Not one to finde that feareth God,
            but all to do amisse?
            
               
And all to wander from good lyfe
            (full few alas exempt)
            And all to worke that wicked is
            and beastly vile attempt?
            O God, howe often do I wishe
            to be deuided cleane
            From all the dealings in the worlde,
            and to God only leane?
            How often do I seeke some trade,
            and solitarie lyfe.
            How fayne would I depart the place
            where sinnes be now so ryfe.
            The world doth tempt, &amp; nought remains
            in his due practise now:
            Eche kinde of trade corrupted is,
            alas, I know not how.
            Nothing almost is exercisde
            without some vile deceyt:
            Fraude, falsehood, theft and pilfring, oft
            in matters are of weyght.
            The worldings wéene &amp; thinke no doubt
            there is none other place
            But ground and graue, and so they runne
            and kéepe their woonted race.
            What helpen teares or wayling griefe?
            what ought at all preuayles
            Gods worde sincere? They kéepe theyr course:
            they haue set vp theyr sayles
            
               
Of deadly sinnes and hatefull hellish lyfe.
            They runne and will not stay.
            They keepe themselues in darksom holes.
            They hate to see the day.
            Looke looke throughout their dealings all,
            and you shall nothing finde
            But couen, craft, and fylthy lore.
            They haue good lyfe resignde.
            Lets sift &amp; searche our selues throughout.
            Lets rippe our inwarde man:
            Let's way our selues euē with our selues.
            And we shall see vs than,
            And finde our selues but drosse and death
            and fowle infected Swine.
            Most vgsome snapes, and creatures, such
            as I can not define,
            What faith in bargaines can be found?
            What store of othes must bee
            In eche compact? And yet in ende
            what falsehod do we sée?
            Not Marchaunt vseth onely fraude:
            nor men of greatest méede.
            But eche one now that bargaine makes,
            hath falsehod in his déede.
            How oft and daylie haps it now
            that chyldren do begin
            Where Parents ended, and do ende
            where Parents did begin?
            
               
The parents beggers first began,
            They ende great men of wealth,
            The sonne begins a welthy man:
            and endes his lyfe by stealth,
            Or wofull wanting simple state.
            How oft comes this to passe?
            Tys daylie seene of common course.
            it happ
                  •••
                still alas.
            Shall welth that's woonne by fraude, be kept?
            shall riches such descende
            From heire to heire? No no, such welth
            shall quickly haue an ende.
            It cannot bide, nor prosper well.
            But who doth that regarde?
            Who yet for welth most vyle deceyt
            at any tyme hath sparde?
            No one well nighe: (the world is such.)
            And here doth come to minde
            The passing pride in common sort
            which now eche where we finde.
            Such is their rage, and fowle affect,
            that though their bellies want:
            Their backs must brauely clothed be:
            apparell nothing scant.
            For what cause else they do reserue
            eche where the Saboth day,
            But for to iette about the streates
            in passing braue array?
            
               
The welthy sort excéede their state,
            and meane degrée the same:
            The common sort wyll do the lyke.
            So all goes out of frame:
            And Roysters ruffle all about
            and tosse the Bylbow blade,
            And to maintaine such vyle excesse,
            beholde what shifts be made?
            Such cogging, foysting, cossening:
            such fylching, theft and guile:
            Such pelting, pylfring, pieuish drifts,
            as are almost to vyle
            And beastly to be named once.
            Ile therefore silent bée:
            For sure I am such lyfe of theirs
            all men may plainly sée.
            Ther's brothel baytes, &amp; whoring dēnes:
            Ther's lurcking strumpets lodge:
            Ther's stuffe eche where for lusty Swash
            for Simkin, Dick, and Hodge.
            Looke looke the Lanes about the Towne,
            and search eche corner through:
            And you shall finde I doubt not I
            of broken ware ynough:
            Corrupt at least much seemes to be:
            so brightly shine the browes,
            So prickt &amp; pranckt, so lyckt and trimde
            is Banckrowtes pretie spowse.
            
               
Search Tauernes through, and typling bowres,
            eche Saboth day at morne:
            And you shall thinke this geare to be
            ene too too much forborne.
            Take care a whyle to vew the Skowtes,
            and wanton walking trulles:
            And you shall sée howe suffraunce nowe
            good lyfe awayward pulles.
            What should I saye? Marke eche where well,
            and you shall vnderstande
            And plainely sée how sinne is sparde
            and cloked vnder hande.
            What else but gaine and Money gotsBeare bayting
                     •
                  on the Saboth day.
            
            maintaines each Saboth day
            The bayting of the Beare and Bull?
            What brings this brutish play?
            What is the cause that it is borne,
            and not controlled ought,
            Although the same of custome be,
            on holy Saboth wrought?
            Now sure I thinke tys gaine or spite,
            gainst good and godly lyfe:
            It seemes it is t'ynuegle men,
            whyles Gods worde is so ryfe:
            I cannot any where perceyue
            where gaine is gotten well:
            I can not sée where well tys spent.
            I thinke no man can tell
            
               
Or iustlie saye, here goeth one
            (for most part now I meane)
            That iustly lyues and leades his lyfe:
            that doth to vertue leane.
            But well, to God I leaue this geare.
            I haue bene somewhat long:
            Ile turne my tale to other talke:
            Ile sing some other song.
            Finis.
         
         
            The syxt Satyr.
            WHat think you (Bertulph) of this placePowles Church abused.
            
            (this Church of Powles I meane)
            How thinke you of th'abuses here,
            In talke and tales vncleane,
            In fearefull oathes and vile compacts,
            in vaine expence of winde,
            In vilely spending tyme therein,
            in ydle chat to finde
            Men occupyde at prayer time,
            and other tymes vnmeete,
            In toyes, and diuers noysome trades?
            (As thou thy selfe dost wéete.)
            And soothly tell mée, what thou déemst,
            and how it séemes to thée,
            In place reseru'de to heare Gods worde,
            such Chaos vyle to sée?
            
               
Of truth,Bertulph. to shew my minde therin
            (at least what I haue seene)
            The tyme (as now) wyll not permit:
            tys to farre spent I weene.
            Againe, sith you haue well begonne
            of Nummus to intreate,
            T'were pitie (sure) that want of tyme
            should let you to repeate
            Such things againe with briefe discourse,
            of well proposed Theame:
            Returne therfore, and make some ende
            of this thy faithfull dreame.
            And I at else appointed time
            (for time it doth demaunde)
            Will nothing fayle, in eche respect,
            wherein you shall commaunde.
            Well, well (quoth Paule so shall it be.Paule.
            
            Ile ende my tale begonne.
            Ile not be long: giue silent eare,
            the same shall soone be donne.
            And now, besides the great abuse
            that I whileare did name,
            Here in this Temple (day by daye)
            themselues do likewise frame
            A number of our foraine FeeresGentlemē.
            
            and men of grounded welth,
            Our cawtie countrey Gentlemen
            to wyn this noysome pelth.
            
               
The fertile soyle that foyson bringes
            of goodly sheaued graine,
            The Medow ground that plenty yéeldes
            of Haye through little paine,
            And ranckly springing pasture, which
            doth fat the fleesed sheepe,
            Will not suffice their greedy mindes,
            nor them contented keepe.
            Not gaine inough by gainsome trade,
            to them will now arise,
            Nor welth inough can quench their thirst:
            too much will not suffise
            Or stay their lust: styll lust they more.
            Not highly raysed rents
            Not lofty fines can humors purge,
            nor extreame whole extents
            Can fyll their hungrie gaping gulles,
            nor staunch their fowle desire.
            They are so fell, that more they haue,
            the more they do require.
            Their Graūdsires great, of lōg time since,
            their Auncestors of yore,
            With sole reuenewes of their lands,
            haue maintainde euermore
            Right worthy portes, forgetting nought
            the stay of their good name:
            Well gote they welth, in bountie, and
            well spent they still the same.
            
               
They neuer (most of them I meane)
            encrocht on neighbors ground,
            Nor ere inclosde vniustly ought,
            They lyu'd within the bound
            Of Charitie and reasons lawe,
            contented with their owne.
            They fedde within their Tedure still:
            fowle fraude was then vnknowne.
            At least the fraude that's nowe in vre.
            They neare enhaunst their rentes,
            Nor found such beastly practises
            as this vyle age inuents.
            Their own suffisde: they sought no more,
            they lyu'de well of the same:
            Yet lyu'de they not vnto themselues,
            as their successors frame.
            They well could byde that beggers should
            haue comfort at their gate:
            They were cōtent, though that they dwelt
            by men of meane estate.
            But now not so. That Age is spent,
            and Charitie withall:
            These men are not contented now:
            to spoyle eche one doth fall.
            They racking stretch their liuing so:
            such wooluish wayes they frame,
            That through fine force, &amp; pilfring shifts,
            twise doubled are the same.
            
               
And double twise decayed yet
            howsekeping is no doubt.
            They liue lyke Misers to them selues.
            Their neighbours rounde about
            Of poore estate may not approche
            nor come within their gates:
            Sometimes perhaps for fashion sake
            they doe inuite their Mates,
            And such as doe the lyke to them:
            or else by whome dooth ryse
            Some hope of gayne or getting ought.
            And thus their bountie lyes.
            But this not all: for wote you what?
            They shame not now to say
            That beggers doe so eate them vp,
            that they no longer maye
            Be able to keepe ope their doores,
            nor howsekeping maintaine.
            Perhaps they sée some other trade
            where lyes some greater gaine.
            And soe they doe, for when they haue
            once gotten to their handes
            By purchase, fraude, and subtile meane
            their néedy neighbours landes
            About them rounde (whereby of trueth
            they come to great decaye)
            Then shut they doores &amp; howsehold breake
            they turne their men away.
            
               
And hither come they tag and ragge:
            here must the gaine be had:
            Here be their charges verie slight:
            yet pelting twise as bad
            As eare it was. The Countrie house
            is broken vp through charge,
            The lands are let, and fines are raysde:
            whereby comes in at large
            Graund sūmes of Coine: which gottē once
            is straight to London broughtUserers are Caterpillers in a comon weelth
            
            To bring increase. (O hellish trade)
            and thus the meanes are wrought.
            In bancke is layde the mightie Masses
            the gaine whereof may bée
            Enough to maintaine them at ease,
            Nay thalfe thereof we sée
            Doth well suffice: for but one man
            or two at most they haue.
            And they themselues doe Tables haunt,
            and so sir Nummus saue.
            And at a meane and slender price,
            themselues, their men and all,
            Haue meate and drinke euen of the best
            well serued at their call:
            And with reuenewes of the stock,
            right richly are they clad.
            And so from thence their brauing state
            and all the rest is had.
            
               
The ste
                  •
               ke as whole reserued still.
            and oft (such is the trade)
            That frō the graunde stock flowes so much
            as petie stockes are made.
            And here the caterpillers haunt.
            In Powles forsooth they vse
            To spende the day to make their mart
            and hearken after newes.
            Was euer séene such state confusde,
            such monstrous kinde of men,
            Such vomite, reffize, Dunghill drosse?
            what man can tell me when
            such watch, such ward, such winking wiles
            were euer put in vrs
            In time to fore, or such foule fraude
            sir Nummus to procure?
            In faith, and by my sauing health,
            full hardly can I finde
            A man amongst a number now
            of vncorrupted minde,
            And such a one as hope of gaine
            will not procure to sinne.
            I think full fewe be lyuing now
            whome méede may nothing winne:
            Or whome that wealth may neuer winde
            from Gods prescribed lawe.
            O earth, O sinne, Oh Sathans thralles:
            Howe doe we still withdrawe
            
               
The grace and loue of God from vs?
            O how doe we regarde
            More, noysome coyne, then helth of soule
            or hope of good rewarde?
            I thinke if I could perseuers
            one Month in this my tale,
            I scantly should the halfe discrie
            Of fraude, (for why) in sale
            And eche compact, the sole regarde
            of gaine is alway had:
            And thirst of score, eache where almost
            doth make the people mad.
            O where are bits to bring them in,
            and lawes to lay their rage?
            O where is faith, or feare of God
            in this presumptuous age?
            Eache one dooth liue as lykes him best,
            the lawes doe lye for gayne.
            Besides deceit and vile deuise,
            dooth nothing now remaine
            Within the harts of English men,
            farre fled is all remorse:
            All loue of God, all feare of plague,
            and Keysers mightie force.
            How prodde our Papistes priuily?Papistes.
            
            How doe these men puruaye?
            How prowle the Caytiues now about,
            for Nummus day by daye?
            
               
Here, in this Church a walck there is
            where Papistes doe frequentThe Papistes walke in Powles.
            
            To talke of newes among themselues:
            and oft the time is spent
            In glad recounting of their state:
            which though not at the best,
            Yet ioy they still to see how men
            in ayde thereof be prest.
            And now comes one and cheeres them vp,The walke is in the south Ile.
            
            he telles them with great ioy,
            That Pope and Spaniard ioyned be,
            Gods people to annoy.
            By solempne protestation comes
            an other by and by
            He tels how that in Flaunders still,
            the Gospellers doe dye
            For sole professing of the truth:
            and with a cheerefull face,
            He shewes how fast the Sheepe are slaine,
            abroade in eary place.
            And what great townes are now bes
                  •
               egde
            and Cities rounde about.
            And how Gods worde decayes apace,
            euen all the worlde throughout.
            Another new fonde fellow comes,
            and he beginnes to tell
            How Popishe Champions landed are,
            and Irish men rebell.
            
               
How holye fathers blessing brought
            in Bishops sacred bres
                  •
               e,
            Hath made the lande before profane,
            nowe holy as the reste.
            And how that Stukeley lost his life,
            among Barbariens late,
            A Marquesse of the Romish marke,
            O too vntimely fate:
            His part (alas) was yet to play
            in places neerer hande.
            He ment and bent his forces he,
            against the Irish landes
            But what this Marquesse left vndone,
            
               Mack Morice he contryu
                  •
               d:
            And hotly gan pursue the charge,
            But ah, it neuer thryu'd.
            For Martyrlyke▪ he lost his head,
            a losse (in deede) to wayle:
            Sithe holy Father, through this losse,
            of his intent dooth fayle.Haue you not seene the knacke to knowe knaues by. compiled by many kanues?
            
            Great Sacks of newes are poured forth
            in that same worthy walke.
            And knauish knackes are there de
                  •
               nsde
            whilst that they stately stalck
            About the place lyke honest men,
            and subiects true of hart.
            From that same place doe rumors rise
            Gods truth to ouerthwart.
            
               
From that same place doe slaunders come
            and vile reprochful lyes
            Against Gods word and Preachers true.
            From that same corner flyes
            Lewde skoffing testes and taunting tales:
            there doe these Rebels coyne
            Their suttle drifts and noysome tales.
            Yea, there doe they conioyne.
            And cleaue like burres with solemne vow
            the truth for to resist.
            And doubt thers none, for why? I thinke
            that they will so persist.
            Untill that Sathan snatch them hence,
            the Graundsire great of lyes:
            And till through want of vitall breath,
            they may no more deuise.
            What kinde of men be these (I praye)Bertulph.
            
            that thus themselues in vre?
            What, are they open foes profest
            that by these meanes procure
            The slaunder of the certaine truth
            and teachers of the same,
            Or Ipocrites that couertly
            the Ghospell doe diffame?
            Once, Bertulph, tys well knowne to théePaule.
            
            that small restraint there is
            For papistes tongues that proudly prate,
            (how ere they gabbe amisse.)
            
               
They talke from feare of check at large.
            But yet of them there bée
            That prease amongst professors true,
            and well with them agrée.
            For why, their lyuings so doe lye,
            that but they seemed such,
            They neuer coulde aspire so high,
            nor yet obtaine so much
            As now they doe. O Ianus Jacks
            and double faced Dogs?
            O wylie wincking wyzard Woolues,
            O grunting groyning Hogs?
            These men (I say) forsweare them selues
            (As periurde Papistes do.)
            They graunt the Quéene is supreme head
            and murmure at it to.
            But what of that, fine fled heads
            well fraught with trim deuise
            And ciuile sleights, without remorse,
            suche scruples count vnwise.
            And so through sharpe and wylie wits,
            And through farre fetching braines,
            They mount aloft to honors tipe,
            and come by greatest gaines.
            And these be they that vnder hande
            the trueth do still annoy,
            And let the working of the worde
            in such as might enioy
            
               
The sweetest salue of sauing health.
            Such lay the lothsome snares,
            And when good seede is sowne, forthwith
            such men sowe noysome fares.
            Yea, such I say (as to my tale)
            lay waite by wylie wayes
            For Nummus: and to get the same,
            are prest at all assayes.
            These be supporting purueyors
            for Papistes nowe supprest
            These ranckly feede the pamperd Swyne
            vpstalled in their nest.
            These foyson bring, and brokers set
            through bend of popishe crew,
            And these men foster Balamites
            To whome reuenge is dew.
            These men are sale abettors of
            the cursed Priests of Baall:
            And these men shauelings doe suffulse,
            which else wolde haue a fall.
            Ist meruaile though they cranckly crowe
            well lodged in their cage?
            With prouen prickt, yst meruaile now,
            That thus the Tigars rage?
            What neede haue they to yelde thēselues
            vnto their lawfull Queene?
            For what intent should subiectes they
            at any time be seene?
            
               
They want nothing, no pleasant lodge:
            of viands they abounde,
            Both Uenion, Wine, and finest cates.
            almoste that may be sounde
            They doe enioy: yea, and such store
            as true report doth saye,
            That (rather than the poore shoulde haat)
            they cast their scraps awaye.
            And in good sooth, their welth is such
            and dainty fare so ryfe,
            That worldlings wil not blame their wit
            to leade such captiue lyfe.
            And fooles they were if they woulde not
            be persecuted so:
            Yea some of them so sore be hurt
            that broade they ryde and go.
            They walke and wallow at their will:
            they hawke and hunt yféere
            With such as haue the charge of them:
            they quat
                  •
               e and make good chéere,
            Set Cock on hoope, with hoape that once,
            a dare shall paye for all:
            Meane time they wil not die through care
            nor from their treason fall.
            Why Pawle (quoth Bertulph) mercy willBertulph.
            
            perhaps so pierce their hart,
            That through the mercye of the Prince
            they will to trueth conuart.
            
               
Nay Bertulph, tys so farre that theyPaule.
            
            with mercye shoulde be wonne,
            That vauntingly they bragge and saye
            bounde dutie will haue done
            All that is done: and (thus) they crake
            that if the Queene by lawe
            Or conscience coulde them gyltie dampne,
            she woulde not stande in awe
            To send them to their doome: nor to
            restraine their tongues so loose.
            Thus bleate the Popish Balamites,
            thus creakes the Romishe goose.
            And what, should mercie here be shewde,
            or can the sante preuaile?
            No no, as long as mercy is,
            their tongues shall neuer quaile,
            Nor harte obdured once relent:
            nor common state be sounde.
            For how can gentle salue doe good
            or cure the festred wounde?
            How can the body be in health,
            that is with Biles infect?I meane those of the only that haue bene distained with the bloude of the Lordes Saintes.
            
            Or Trée sprīg well that hath dead spraies
            vnlesse you doe resect
            The braunches of? What man so mad
            will shewe himselfe to bée,
            As ought to hope for leaues or fruite
            to come from rotten Trée?
            
               
How can the state of Christ his flock,
            be fenced from decay:
            Unlesse the higher powers doe cast
            the stumbling stocks away?
            How can the Lord of truth be pleasde,
            when such false Prophets liue?
            How will he like to haue them kept
            his siely Lambes to grieue?
            And doubt the Tiraunts now to say
            that time shall come againe
            Wherein the blessed Saints of God
            by them shall suffer paine?
            No no, they feare not to protest,
            that where they put to death
            Of late but few, for earye such
            shall twentie loose their breath
            In time to come. O bloudie beastes
            and foule infected Swine?
            But these be they for whom (no doubt)
            men scrape and so purloine:
            For whome these factors haue such care
            and passing great regard:
            For whom they powle the Preachers true
            these Monsters to reward.
            And hate of theirs so haynous is,
            their 
                  •
               ancor hath such force
            Against the Ghospell of the Lorde,
            that (voyde of all remorse)
            
               
They eft procure Pluralities
            For vile disguised Jacks.
            They glad and ioy, to see the Church
            sustaine such wofull lacks.
            And they againe, a Priesting sort,
            attyred in theyr kinde:
            Doe creepe into Cathedrall Celles.
            theyr charge they haue assignde,
            To be dischargde per auters mains,
            
            themselues will liue at ease,
            They force not what become of flock,
            so they sir Nummus sease,
            And Nummus do they seise in deede,
            which seised buyldes no Schooles:
            Nor makes no stockes for men decayde,
            no Bertulph so playes fooles.
            But here you may not take me so
            as if I did defase
            Without respect, the good with badde
            in eache Cathedrall place.
            Much lesse that I depraued haue
            all Preachers so attyrde
            In Priestish weedes, as Popelings were,
            and as theyr state requyrde.
            No: farre and farre, be this from me,
            for why I knowe right well:
            That in these Priestish weedes there are,
            full many that excell.
            
               
Naye Bertulph naye, then blame haue I
            if so my wordes be meante:
            For some of these attyred thus,
            in peacefull wise are bent:
            And brawle not with their brethren, who
            neglecte or cleane refuse:
            And therefore great vniustice t'were,
            such Preachers to accuse.
            Although I wishe (that's all I maye,)
            that Preachers might be knowne
            From Popish Jacks in wéedes and words
            a thing confused growne.
            But husht, Ile haste me to the shore:
            Ile shonne such mounting waues.
            Ile leaue this Sea for to be swomme
            of tryple tongued Naues.
            FINIS.
         
         
            The seauenth Satyr.
            NOw harken Bertulph to the endePaule.
            
            of this my present tale.
            I am enforst my floting Boate
            to shore from course to hale.
            The time runnes on, the day is spent,
            The night awayward pulles,
            And endlesse scope of my pretence,
            downe pressed pallate dulles.
            
               
O endlesse powre, O welspring, whence
            all wisedome wisely flowes:
            O God, whose grace doeth guide the good,
            in whome all bounty growes:
            Thou knowst the harts, &amp; séest the raynes
            yea, thinwarde thoughts of men
            Doe open lye before thy face:
            Thou knowst how, where and when
            Ech thing hath, is, or shall be done
            or else committed: thou
            Haste perfite vewe and insight good
            which waye mans hart doth bow.
            Thou, thou, I say, sole God of might,
            beholdst the harts of men,
            What they pretend, what yll they worke:
            so iustly iudge me then,
            And shut thy mercy from my soule,
            if slaundrously my lyps
            Doe ope at all: or if my tongue
            of vaine presumption skyps
            From this to that, or rashly run
            more then the truth doth vrge,
            Or more then that through extreame rage
            and force of sinfull surge
            I am constrainde with déepe remorse
            and moaning plaint to tell.
            O, oh, how many brothell Bawdes
            within the towne doe dwell?
            
               
How many filthy scudding scowtes,
            besturre their crooked stumpes?
            For gaine, for gaine, olde mother B
            how shee still lymping lumps,
            And proddes about with ackwarde pace
            vnto her beastly haunt?
            How doe these subtile groyning Sowes
            poore siely girles enchaunt,
            And oft abet the loued spouse
            to start from husbands bed?
            Beholde I saye, how by these Bawdes,
            are women captiue led
            And simple maydes vnto the spoyle.
            Beholde and see their trade,
            See, see, what wyly winking shiftes,
            by cliffe browde beasts are made.
            Of course and custome, common Innes
            they watch with warie eye
            If that at any tyme they may
            (as oft they do) espye
            The countrey maides that come from far,
            as straungers to the towne:
            Whome still the Trottes doe tittle so,
            that straight all shame layde downe.
            They yelde thē selues as captiue queanes,
            vnto some whorish caue:
            Where trotting Iade for filthye gaine
            doth vrge them to behaue
            
               
Full soone themselues vile strumpet lyke
            to lyue by whorishe trade:
            And she hir selfe doth let them forth
            that gaine by them be made.
            But (out alas) the Maidens mindes
            and comming was tobtaine
            Some seruice where to spend their times
            as seruaunts to remaine.
            O ardent force of flaming sinne.
            O rage, O riot, O
            That euer such should be sustainde
            or once on grounde should goe?
            Beholde beholde how good mens wyues
            Inuegled are by them?
            Behold howe seruaunts they support?
            Beholde how they doe hem
            And hooke to them through crooked guile
            And vndereating craft,
            Great store of Truls? Beholde I say
            how often is beraft
            By them alas the fruitfull wife,
            of her moste louing mate:
            And husband bearing honest port,
            of wife in that same rate.
            Beholde also how honest Maides
            and seruaunts they entyce
            To whoredome, theft, and filching by
            their diuilish vile deuice.
            
               
But wher are these? how should we know
            where such lewde Lossels lodge?
            Where is their haunt, &amp; where are they
            accustomde thus to dodge?
            Rounde, round about the Citie walles.
            Within and eke without.
            The Alleys, Lanes▪ yea open streates,
            and places all about
            Are now replenisht with such stuffe,
            and filthy broken ware.
            And (wo begone) the Officers
            thereof doe take no care.
            For if they did, how durst the Drabs
            and Callets be so bolde
            As limpe about in lawlesse times
            or take into theyr holde
            Yong fillock Iylles, and bawdie Jacks
            at inconuenient tides:
            And still retaine for storeware some
            within their house besydes?
            How durst the Dunghils daunce about
            with blinde vagaries so,
            And with close colours leade their trulls
            where that they list to go?
            Behold, behold, how camoysed queane
            and craftie crooked crib
            Doth vnder vile and lewde pretence,
            (most like a suttle gib)
            
               
Pretende to place in seruice still
            yong maydens here and there.
            And maidens hauing refuge such,
            beholde how they ne feare.
            To pilfer, filch, and to purloyne
            from Maister and from Dame,
            And in the ende to giue the slip
            and serue no more the same.
            Which all doth spring from wimpled B:
            and olde deceitfull Bawde,
            And how to her the gaine doth rise,
            which shée by theft so drawde
            Besides reuenues of the taile,
            and forreine filched good:
            Beholde how thus lyke carrein Crow,
            shée liues by filthy foode.
            An other sorte of them aduert
            some olde, some yong yféere,
            That walke about with Brushes, Pins,
            with Tape and other geere.
            But well, sith that the campes be wyde,
            wherein as now I walck:
            I leaue them here, entending once,
            at large therein to stalck
            And seuer places by themselues,
            with styles and parting stakes:
            And as I can, to my poore skill,
            rescind the noysome brakes.
            
               
For treating now of broking Bawdes,
            and filthie Panders, I
            Haue cause therein full many such
            vile persons to descrie.
            For why the husband now is prest,
            to put his wife for gaine
            Unto hir choise to be an whore,
            or honest still remaine.
            And so it is: else how coulde they
            thus strumpet like attyre
            And set them out? tys too too true,
            they let their wiues to hire.
            O great excesse, how long could I
            retaine your eares herein,
            If I but briefely shoulde discourse?
            (So great a scope hath sinne.)
            But as I sayde, so shall it be:
            I leaue it to my pen,
            Which (graunting God) hereafter shal
            at large dilate it: when
            Both time shall yeelde hir selfe thereto
            and minde (as onely bent
            Upon the same) shall beate at full,
            with perfite true intent.
            Meane time, with one thing more, I e
                  •
               
            
            which (sith the day is past)
            Ile comprehend in briefest wordes:
            and this shall be the last.
            
               
Whereas before, of broking Bawdes
            my former tale was tolde,
            Of Brokers likewise now to tellBrokers.
            
            my Pen shall be so bolde.
            For why, their deedes be damnable:
            and they in number so
            Doe still increase, that day by day
            by them deceyts doe grow
            In such aboundance, that (alas)
            I feare, I feare as now,
            All dread of plagues cleane set apart,
            to fraude mens mindes doe bow:
            Sequestred cleane from Godly loue,
            and so from Godly feare,
            That rich to poore, where gaine doth lye,
            will rauine nought forbeare.
            And (out alas) where heretofore,
            (prickt forth by thirst of gaine)
            Within the Towne, of Brokers, they
            did thirtie such ordaine,
            Or thereabouts, shrewde wylye Mates
            and wittie wincking Colts
            (Although in wisedome sure I think,
            they showde them selues but dolts)
            To vse the trade of broking, and
            discréetly so the same,
            That if the worlde should vewe the Act,
            they might be voyde of blame:
            
               
Whereas (I say) of late this act
            decreed was for intent,
            That Broking trade might practizd be
            by men so well ybent,
            That reason ruling them therein,
            (though Gods worde doth forbid,
            And cleane condemne all loane for gaine)
            their fact might so lye hid.
            Now now alas,I speake of the intent as it hath falne out sithens such order made. (O sinfull fact)
            the Magistrates, herein,
            Not so content for to dispence
            with such an haynous sinne,
            Doe altogither cleane neglect
            by them such order made:
            Whereby whole hundreds now doe liue
            by beastly broking trade.
            And in such sort doe they demeane
            themselues, and so deuise,
            That horrible it is to tell
            which way their gaine doth rise.
            Our gentlemen in these our dayes
            (as soothly goes report)
            In time of néede, to Marchantmen
            are woonted to resort
            
               Gentlemē, when they can get no Money of loane, are glad to take, wares whereof Money maye be made. And take of loane such wares, as they
            best like of: yéelding theare
            Themselues to bandes, and suraunce good
            to paye for all the ware,
            
               
Which whē they haue with thirsting hope
            once taken to their handes,Note the subtiltie of the Marchaunt which vttereth his wares in such sort, and that also for v
                     •
                  une
            
            For ware, scant halfe may they obtaine
            for to discharge their bandes:
            And so perforce constramed are
            to sue for brokers ayde,
            By whom they thinke to saue themselues:
            And so the goodes are layde
            In brokers handes: who handle them
            so handsomly I trowe,
            That all the gaine that may be had,
            doth to the Broker growe.
            For (at the least) one part thereof
            he kéepes vnto his share:
            And yet vnto the gentleman
            he yéeldeth for his ware
            Perhaps muche more then he himselfe
            coulde haue obtainde therefore.
            He nicks him, and besides he takes
            a crowne in earie score
            For payment of his paines therein.
            O execrable crime?
            Were euer séene such subtile shifts
            in any former time,
            As are in this our present age?
            what should I thinke therein?
            No doubt, no doubt, that men as now
            doe snorting sléepe in sinne.
            
               
The Lethargie or some such yll
            doth rifely raigne abroad.
            They are downe prest wt monstrous sins
            and yet sustaine the loade.
            What craft is coyned day by day?
            what fraude affresh is founde?
            What new deuise and straunge deceyte
            doth in this age abounde?
            I feare, I feare, true dealing now
            deryded is with men.
            I feare me they doe practise Faith
            and Truth but now and then.
            But (as vnto my former tale.)
            Is this the worst they vse?
            Will Broker vse this onely theft
            and other fraude refuse?
            No no, the varlet vengeablye
            can coyne more noysome drifts:
            He hath his bouget fraught with fraude,
            and Foxie knauish shifts.
            Well scapes the dettor, if he doe
            thrée parts thereof obtaine.
            Nay, oftentimes hees glad to take
            one onely part againe.
            For broker when he hath the goodes,
            at laysure will repay
            The same by péecemeale: and perhaps
            for all his foule delay,
            
               
The detter shall be glad to take
            on quarter of the same.
            If this be well, (as true it is)
            then nothing's out of frame:
            And all may be right well forborne,
            as it hath bene full long.
            But hapt the same to Magistrates,
            they would redresse the wrong,
            And not set light by suche deceyt:
            nor wincking, let it lye.
            Had they such losse, they would I saye
            redresse full soone espye.
            But who cares ought, so gaine be had,
            and wares be made away?
            They vtter by such meanes their wares.
            Why then, what hurt haue they?
            They shall be payde, who eare do leese,
            and gaine shal they by lene.
            Although the detter loose the halfe,
            yet theyle take héede to one.
            And oftentimes (such is the fayth
            of these vile broaking knaues)
            When they haue gotte the dettors goodes,
            they wyll lyke roging slaues
            Some of them shewe a payre of héeles:
            the Rakehells wyll be gone.
            Theyle runne away with goodes and all,
            though lyfe lye thervpon.
            
               
And doubtlesse, many of them doe
            so practize now a dayes,
            That they come vp and rise to welth,
            by such vngodly wayes.
            Some of them vse such priuie shifts,
            and such close couched wyles,
            That they come vp and beare good port
            And only liue by guyles.
            And other some so slauishe be
            and cutthroate cullion léeke,
            That when they haue a bootie gote,
            theyle streight waye giue the gléeke,
            And pack away. As, now and then
            is brought into their handes
            A Chaine of Golde, a Tablet or
            some bracelet golden bandes
            By Gentlemen to lay to pawne
            For Nummus when they néede:
            Which, whē they haue once in their hands,
            theyle pack away with spéede.
            I tell you Bertulph, on my fayth,
            if I should now dilate
            The vile deceite of Brokers, and
            so set to vew their state,
            You scantly could abide to héer't,
            so horrible it is.
            But thus we must consider ont,
            and so I ends with this.
            
               
Where that the state corrupted is
            by them that beare the swaye,
            There meaner people will peruert
            and bring it to decaye.
            If Maiestrate doe winne with fraude,
            the commons will the same.
            If Magistrate must winck for feare,
            then all goes out of frame.
            And so I ende till time renue
            this tale of mine begonne.
            I tell you trueth, there resteth yet
            much more ere it be done.
            But here you haue vnto my hest,
            declared (as I can)
            How Nummus is awayted for
            by moste men now and than:
            And how the same is put to vse
            most wicked now a dayes:
            And how it is by men abusde
            in spending many wayes.
            You eke haue hearde expressed here,
            how often times it is
            For hoorde kept close and cofferd vp.
            I haue delated this.
            Now resteth that I doe declare
            how hée hath harmed mée.
            But this (as I intende) hereafter
            shall dilated hée:
            
               
For (doubtlesse) herein doth consist
            a thing importing wayte,
            To shew how Nummus doth deceiue
            by Sathans subtile sleight.
            And sithe I doe entende at large
            of this (God graunting grace)
            To write hereafter, now I ende:
            and (with erected face)
            Unto my God great thankes I yeelde,
            that so hath beene his will
            To guide my tongue the thing to speake
            wherein doth rest such ill.
            And praye we hartily vnto him
            to mitigate the paine
            And plague which for our monstrous lyfe
            as due doth now remaine.
            Amen.
         
         
            
            The. viii. and last Satyr.
            The Author.
            THough Muse haue made his finall end,
            and Penne haue runne his race,
            Yet carefull custome causeth me
            to waile the want of grace.
            And quaking quill renewes the plaint
            that lurckes in pensiue breast
            Commixt with cares that flow from head
            full fraught with great vnrest.
            The time backe beates mine idle braine
            that labour ginnes to leaue:
            And rage of sinne returnes the griefe
            my silent pawse to reaue.
            How shall I safely seeke the shoare?
            How may I shun the seas,
            Untill that Triton blow retreate
            and mounting waue appeas?
            The dawning day doth keepe aloofe,
            and Loades man loseth ayme:
            The ryffie rock doth lye in wayte
            my beaten barke to maime.
            And yet when daye shall once discrye
            the daunger of the surge,
            Then shall my puppe due course obserue
            and glide through crooked gurge.
            
               
Meane time betost with great turmoyle,
            and tempests bitter flawe,
            Ile kéepe my selfe amid the streame:
            and yet a while withdrawe
            My Pen from port of quiet pawse.
            For time doth vrge me so:
            The time alas infect with sinne.
            Yea time wherein doth grow
            The rage of sinne and ryots force,
            the raumping Serpents guile,
            With all deceyt that maye be founde:
            yea sinne almost to vile
            To be exprest or set to vewe.
            But such is Sathans force:
            Such are the harts of vanquisht thralles,
            cleane frustrate of remorce.
            Call call to minde you carelesse crewe:
            Lay custome now a side:
            And let your fayth with faithlesse fruites
            herein a while be tride.
            Confirme the lyfe that you doe leade
            And ratifie the same.
            And then lets sée how wilfully
            you wander worthy blame.
            First Auarice, what force it hath,
            what cursed cancre tis,The canker 
                     •
                  f couetous
                  
                     •
                  es is cause 
                     •
                  f all euill.
            
            What running rot and curelesse wounde,
            to men apparaunt is.
            
               
What great enorm this sin hath wrought
            What thirsting hath procurde,
            The block, the trée, the beggers bagge
            such sequeale hath inurde:
            And yet how ryfely now it raignes,
            how graft in gréedy mindes,
            How grounded tis in peoples harts,
            a proofe our liuing findes.
            No one abandons beastly trade,
            nor maketh staye at all
            To practise fraude and fliching lore
            so gaine therby may fall.
            The rich doth laye his goods for gaine,
            and gapeth still to gett
            The substance of the néedie soule
            that gote the same by swett.
            The néedie (not vnlike) deuise
            and seeke by subtile drifts
            To scrape for coyne, and gaine to winne,
            do séeke vngodly shifts.
            So charitie excluded is:
            and loue is kept aloofe.
            And right is wronged through rewarde,
            as falleth still in proofe:
            And Userie about the Towne
            is maintaind as a trade:
            And equitie to ease the wrong,
            in matters dares not wade.
            
               
But well, the Sinne shall not be hid
            nor cloked from the vew.
            I will explane the practise here
            in wordes that doe ensew.
            The Cormoraunt that coucheth 
                  •
               vp
            and crams his cankerd bags,
            Doth giue to hoord his gotten coyne:
            and bowte the towne he lags.
            To Broker doth he bende his course:
            or happly vnto him
            The Broker bannes and weanes a mate
            for purpose very trim.
            And twene them two are craftes conueyd
            and foxy falshoode wrought.
            Twene them are traps so framed, that
            thereby is Nummus caught.
            O God, what gaine doth guilefull gnuffe
            by loane of Nummus raise?
            How doth he nick the debter now
            by hault exacting wayes?
            Ten powndes in hundred, nothing is▪
            
            and twentie is but small.
            For halfe in halfe full oftentimes
            in loane among doth fall.
            A siely man constraind of late
            to borowe for his neede,
            Repaird vnto a Marchant man
            to borowe on his deede
            
               
The Marchant (as it is of course)
            had Money none to lende:
            But wares he proferd willingly.
            and Dettor in the ende
            The same became: and tooke to loane
            as much as did amount
            To thirty poundes of currant coyne
            by Marchantmans account.
            Which wares so taken vp to loane,
            to Broker are they brought:
            The Broker to the Marchaunt he
            (of whome the same were bought)
            Full falsely doth returne them streight:
            who now twise gaynes thereby:
            For fyrste he soulde and now eftsoones
            the same agayne doth buye.
            So that when this our siely soule
            should rayse thereof the summe:
            Aboue the price of twenty pounde,
            the credit will not come.
            For ten in thirty could vouchsafe,
            the Creditor to haue
            For recompence in Usurie.
            O carelesse cankerd slaue,
            O cawty cutthroate, cullion, wretch,
            O Caterpyllers Féere,
            O miserable Murtherer,
            Canst thou abyde this geare?
            
               
¶The time is now at hande wherein
            thou straight account shalt make:
            Wherin thou shalt Hell fire gain
            for gaine that thou didst take.
            O Userer, thou Sathans thrall,
            and Butcher of the Fiende,
            Thy Golde shall be transformde to muck:
            thy plagues shall neuer ende.
            But as thou doost thy Ocker vse
            t' oppresse thy neighbour héere:
            Euen so the scorching flames of Hell
            thy caytyfe corps shall déere.
            Thy rusty hoorde ascendes the skie:
            thy dettors harme doth mount
            Unto the high supernall seate
            to call thée to account.
            Thou greedy Gleade, thou hūgry Hawke,
            thou starueling Uultures mate,
            How darste thou thus by rauine séeke
            to maintaine thine estate?
            I sée how thou canst soare aloft
            like hungry Hawke tespye
            And catching Kite, when pray shal spring,
            for beste game bent to flye.
            I sée thy subtile lagging pace,
            and craftie colourde guile:
            I sée thy false dissembling sleight:
            I sée thy playted wile.
            
               
Thou hast deuised by the Month,
            for gaine to let thy ware:
            Thy money eke from month to month,
            thou canst right well forbeare.
            But for eche shilling (Caytife thou)
            in surplysage wilt take
            A penie: and of twentie shillings,
            twentie pennies make:
            And (in that rate) for fortie pounde,
            so lent out: in a yéere,
            Thou wilt receiue twise forty pounds
            of lawfull Money cléere.
            Thou wéenst to welter here for aye,
            and wallowe in thy welth:
            Thou neuer thinkst to sée the daye
            to part from this thy pelth.
            But I will tell thée Cormorant,
            thou fell and egre droane:
            Eche pennie shall accountaunt be
            which thou hast let in loane.
            And though as now the law be thine
            to laye beneath thy foote:
            Yet then the furyes by decrée
            shall rende thy hart at roote:
            When as the libell of thy lust
            and bayliwick abusde,
            Shall thée condempne to Limboe pit
            and scalding lake confusde.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            The Aucthor vpon the Booke,
in the defence of the gouernement
of the Citie.
            
               TWo sortes of men repaire vnto this Booke.
               The one to carpe and cauell at my wordes:
               The other through delyght, thereon doth looke:
               And reading it, true iudgement well afordes.
               He deemeth straight (when haply I reproue)
               That mine intent is vices to remoue.
            
            
               But nowe, tappease and satisfie the minde
               Of such as rashly ronne with open mouth
               At my reproofe which often here they finde,
               I thus much say to them in my behoue.
               I meane, I touch, I quip no priuate man
               For hate, ne spite since first my worke began,
            
            
               Nor yet doo I (with chyldish rage stird vp)
               Seeke to deface a worthy common state
               Of such as seldome drinke of sinfull Cup
               By matter such as I doo here debate.
               For I protest, I know no matter why
               I should so doo: sith no man can deny
            
            
               That in the Towne are diuers sortes of men
               By whome the vertuous are supported styll:
               With whome the wicked may at no tyme blen
               Their noysome drifts, nor work the thing thats yll:
               By whome the poore and needie are sustainde:
               And eke with whom true zeale hath styl remainde.
            
            
               I meane both Judge, Phistion, Lawyer and
               The Marchaunt (whom euen all I must commend)
               With other else which in my Booke do stande.
               I say, of them there be whome to defende
               I neede not here. Their lyues auoyde the blame,
               And through good lyfe, they wyn immortall fame.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            Gentle Reader, for the fillinge
vp of emptie pages, this letter written
by the Author to his friende lying at
the point of death is inserted.
            
               
                  SIr, howe and in what wise
euery man shoulde beare him
selfe towarde his friende in
time of health, in time of prosperitie
and strengthe, moste
men knowe: yea, suche is the vntruste that
is in man, moe men can speake plausibly in
time of good happe, as we terme it, then in
time of siknes iudge vprightly. Alas, in time
of sicknesse and in assaultes of death (wherin
the bodye is not more greuously oppressed
then the minde diuersly distracted and the
soule mightelye assaulted) how fewe doe
consider, or at the leastwise, do apply them
selues to the relief of the poore afflicted soule,
to the strengthning of the féeble mynde, and
to the repelling of those bytter temptations
and assaults of the common enemies of man
kinde, the olde Serpente, the vaine, wicked
and vnconstant worlde, and the fraile, peruerse
and rebellious flesh which alwayes
doe attend and attempt the sicke enféebled

and oppressed person? Surely, were it not
that God in time of suche extremitye dothe
mightelie comforte and confirme suche as
be his in the promises of his mercye, in the
death of his deare Jesus, and in the merytes
of his passion: it is not possible but that sicknes
shoulde be intollerable, death horryble,
Hel wictorious, the bodye liuing, to be a terrour
to the mynde, and the mynde so terrified
and brought to desperation, to be the perpetual
dampnatioun of the bodye and soule.
            Which thing considered, and from my verye
harte remembred, I cannot choose but in
this blessed battaile, and I truste (thoughe
somewhat sharpe and egre) yet most happy
conflycte whervnto (as a fellowe souldyer,
and adopted brother) you are called for your
tryall, I cannot choose I saye, but, to the increase
of your courage, endeuoure to make
plaine vnto you in all that I maye, the fruit
of affliction and the commoditye of death:
imparting with you suche weapons as for
mine owne store, the Lorde our Captaine
hathe alloted vnto me, to the ende, that being
conueniently appoynted, you may resist
and auoyde at all assayes, and become bolde,
valiaunt, constant and perseuerable to the
death. Touching which death, notwithstanding

it be gréeuous to the fraile flesh, yet is
it moste ioyfullye to be receyued as an vndoubted
ende of all griefe, for why? it is the
beginning of Joye and perpetuall tryumph
wherevpon a certaine godly man wryteth.
If thou haddest a good conscience, thou woldest
not flye death. And againe, why haste
thou pleasure in that wretched body, whose
felowshippe doth nothing els but violentlye
withdrawe and deteine thee from the king▪
come of euerlasting glorie? O cousen: what
else but a place of exile is the miserable bodie
to the Soule? And to what thinge else maye
this our lyfe more aptlye be compared, then
to an horswaie or stage playe where men do
assemble to behoulde sondrye feates, and
where euerye man laboureth in all that he
maye, to winne praise, promotion and authoritye
after the ende of his tragicall part:
God onelye is permanent immortall &amp; euer
lastinge: All things else are transitorye and
subiecte to corruption. They be constituted
corruptible and mortall, and must be consumed
of time, and ha
                  •
                their endes by corruption.
The S
                  ••
               e shall passe, for it was
made but for mans vse. The Moone, and the
starres shall perish, for they were created
but for the necessitye of man. Heauen and

earth shall decaye, for they conteine but a
place of exile and prison for the body of man:
yea, the body of man also shall perish, for it
is but as an enemy to exercyse the soule,
and to make it apte to apprehend by fayth,
the Joyes of heauen and crowne of immortalytie.
Moste certaine (I saye) it is that the
frayle body shalbe resolued to earthe, &amp; there
shall sléepe till the soule returne vnto it, and
tyll the members be restored to their right
places. Wherefore, sithe earth and corruption
is the ende of the bodye: yea, the end of all
things that were made &amp; created, and that
the same ende of the bodye is the beginning
of lyfe, wishe for death, wishe for a peaceable
departure, and finding the same, imbrace
it: saying in your hart: Come Lord, come Jesus,
make haste and tary not: Come Lorde
that I maye be one with thée and coheyre of
the kingdome purchased with thy precious
bloud. Deere Cosen and beloued in the
Lorde, lette not longe sickenesse discourage
you, neyther be you in anywise perplexed or
gréeued with the lowe state and constitutiō
of your body: And in and aboue all thinges,
let not hyndraunce in worldly affayres disquyet
you. As you haue begonne, so further
the will of the Lord, and be ready to receiue

whatsoeuer he wil lay vpō you. For the gretest
affliction &amp; misery that man may or doth
suffer in this lyfe, is not worthie the leaste
of those treasures which God will bestowe
vpon him in the lyfe to come, which is durable,
permanent, glorious &amp; altogither full of
blessednes. And assure your selfe (for so God
hath promised, and wyll not goe one iote
from his worde) that he wyll laye no more
vpon you, then by his grace and strengthe
you shalbe able to heare, althoughe he séeme
somewhat sharply to correct you, and somewhat
seuerely to deale with you: for who is
he whome the Lorde chasteneth not? Surely,
surely, whome he loueth, the same dothe
he chasten, &amp; in him is he delighted as the father
in his son, offering himself vnto him as
a déere father to his sonne: whereas if we refuse
chastycement, we are no sonnes, but bastards,
and not inheritable by any right. Ioseph
was afficted and delyuered by y• Lord.
Dauid was chastised, and he acknowledged
the Lorde and founde reliefe in his Soule.
Tobias was corrected, and he founde health.
Iob was tryed &amp; was made perfect. What
shoulde I say, euen all the Appostles, all the
Prophets: yea, and all the good men that euer
were, haue bine tryed by affliction, chosen

by persecutō, and crowned by patience,
abydinge the wyll and pleasure of God.
Wherefore, be strong in the Lord, &amp; desire of
him in your hart ye his will may be wrought
in you, &amp; that you may with a glad hart receyue
whatsoeuer his Maiesty shal lay vpon
you. Assure your selfe that this your present
sicknes is either for punishment of sinne, for
exercise of your faith, or to yt death. And therfore,
if it be for punishment, beséeche him to
giue you patienceand assure your selfe vpon
repentaunce, to haue frée &amp; full remission in
Christ: If it be for tryall, giue him thanks: &amp;
if it be to the death, reioise in it, &amp; thinke it is
y• greatest gift that euer he gaue you in this
world, being the very passage to the heauenlye
and Angelicall Paradice. And pray euen
from the bottom of your hart, that neyther
the loue of the worlde, nor the feare of the
same death, may distracte you from the desire
of it. Be not carefull to leaue your kinsfolckes,
friends, and acquaintaunce, let it
not gréeue you to part from your goods, nor
haue any loue depending vpon any earthly
thinge whatsoeuer. As for your Kinsfolkes
and worldly friendes, at your Graue they
wil leaue you, and within a while after forget
you: and shortlye after that, shall dye

themselues, and be forgotten themselues also.
Your goods wilbe fawning vpon other
men, assoone as the breath shalbe out of your
body: and euen as they serued you, so are
they readye to scrue an other, and perhaps
to his perdition, without the speciall grace
of God. To conclude, lift vp your harte, &amp; cal
together your wits, which are dispersed and
diuersely affected to things which are corruptible,
and fall not from God, for things
that are so deceytfull and vaine. A battaile
must be, no question: No triumphe is obteined
without fyghte, neyther any Garlande
giuen, but to him that manfully standeth in
the Lorde. If any sorrow be found in death,
it ariseth but of our owne infyrme or desperate
feare: for death is but a swyfte flyghte
or passage of the soule frō the corruptible bodye,
rather to be desyred then to be fled from
of men. God is the rewarder of this conflict,
&amp; heauen is the eternal stipend. Wherefore,
let these giftes prouoke you to esteeme this
battaile the lighter: for chéerefully shall you
passe after death, into y• pleasant Campes of
heauē, which place is conuenient for those y•
haue minded heauēly things. The saints of
heauē wil receiue you as a friendly cōpaniō
of theirs into y• portalles of cléerenes, wheras

you shall finde verye glorious abyding.
Thus shall you (at the last) come frō greeuous
cares and from large continuing troubles
into a peceable rest and mansion of quietnes.
In the Paradise aboue or like place
of pleasure among the departed Saints, shal
be your continuaunce, hauing all the heauens
at your pleasure. A celestiall song wilbe
vttered at those recreations, and so swete
melodies as are able to mooue the Starres.
With the Saints, I say, departed hence shal
you lyue, and with them shall you raigne in
heauen with your Redéemer: so much glorie
hereafter shall you haue, and so muche heauenlye
honour. What shoulde I saye? In
that place is eternall pleasure, and a lyfe
replenished with perpetuall felicytie: yea, in
that place shall the glorye of the Godhead be
reuealed vnto you, and séene with your very
eyes: euen with those your eyes of fleshe,
which from the foundations of the worlde
hathe bine hiddē from mankinde in this his
mortalitye. Fynallye, there shall you wayte
vpon the Lambe, your Sauiour Jesus, who
surelye loues you and reioyseth that he hath
saued you. God Cousen, assure your self that
in this blessed place you muste néedes bée.
            And that as surely as your Sauioure lyued

here vpon the earth, so surely you must and
shall raigne with him in the heauens. For
there is hée, there is that Sauiour your head
who can not nor will not be separated from
any of his members. As for the weight of
Synne, howe heauye, howe haynous, howe
huige and burthensome soeuer it be, caste it
all vpon him, for therefore he dyed, and not
for small sinnes onely, but for all the sinnes
that mankinde hath committed, doth or shal
committe from the begynninge of the
worlde to the ende of the same. It
is his onelye and greate glorye to be a
Sauiour. And for that cause is he ascended to
the heauens in our flesh, and will in no wise
deceyue those poore séely ones vpon the earth
that cling vnto him for helpe and saluation.
And whereas (haply) you may feare, because
of the weakenes of your fayth, which
nowe in your extreame and laste battayle
(if so to be the Lorde haue appoynted
it vnto you) is diuerslye assayled and assaulted:
Be of good comforte and plucke vp your
courage, for that méeke Sauiour wyll not
caste you of: no, he will not caste of his séelye
creature though he be hable to touche but
the hemme of his vesture. It is toulde vs
in the sacred scriptures that he will not

quenche the smoking flaxe nor breake the
bruised Réed. O, he is gentle, &amp; will make all
perfect that in the poore soule of mā is vnperfect.
He knoweth and hath felt how harde a
thing it is for poore man, to stande vpon his
legs, when he hath to deale with those ghostly
and ghastly emmies: Sathan, the world,
and the flesh: but especially in the Agonye of
death. O how well acquaiuted, is he with
those conflicts? Feare not Cowsē, feare not:
If your faith be but as a graine of Musterdséede,
you shalbe saued. That Sauiour hath
said it. And as for those wounds and skarres
that these bloudy enemies haue made or shal
make in your féeble soule, that heauenly Samaritane
shall binde them vp againe, and
shall supple them with the oyle of his grace,
so that they shall not hinder you a whit. He
will in no wise disdayne you, no: although
you were as fowle as a Leaper. For what
are they but sins? what are they (I say) but
sowle and lothsome sinnes that his precious
bloud hath washed and shall wash away in
mankinde, so longe as mankinde shall haue
place and abyding in the Tabernacle of sinful
flesh? He knoweth, yea, he knoweth and
that throughly, what poore man is &amp; whereof
he is made. And as he knoweth him, so he

pittieth him, and thereof hath giuen him a
a sure and euerlasting Testimony: For he
hath dyed for him: he hath dyed, (I saye) for
man, that man might liue with him for euer
be saued. In him therefore be comforted, and
vpon him only repose your whole confidēce,
to the last gaspe of your life: say vnto him, if
not with a lowde and strong voice, yet softly
in your sick soule. Lorde Jesu receyue my
spirit. Come Lord and make haste. Into thy
hands Lorde I commend my spirit. &amp;c. And
so saying, waight paciently when he shall
come vnto you, and put a finall end to
your happy conflycte. To the same
Lorde, being God in Trinitye,
with the father and the holy
Ghost, be all honor praise
and glory eternally.
            Amen.
         
      
      
         
            
               Imprinted at London by John
Charlewood, and Richard
Ihones.
         
      
   

