
   
      
         
            A doleful discourse and ruthfull reporte of the greate spoyle and lamentable losse, by fire, in the towne of East Dearham, in the countie of Norfolke vpon Tuesday the. 18. of Iulie, this present yere .1581.
            Gurney, Arthur.
         
         
            
               1581
            
         
         Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02401
            STC 12531.3
            ESTC S105908
            99841633
            99841633
            6231
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02401)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6231)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 379:08)
         
         
            
               
                  A doleful discourse and ruthfull reporte of the greate spoyle and lamentable losse, by fire, in the towne of East Dearham, in the countie of Norfolke vpon Tuesday the. 18. of Iulie, this present yere .1581.
                  Gurney, Arthur.
               
               [16+] p.   
               
                  Printed by Richard Bradocke, for Richarde Hollens: and are to be solde at his shop oueragainst the signe of the Bell within Algate,
                  At London :
                  1581.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Ar. Gurney.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A⁴, C⁴.
                  No complete copy known.
                  Running title reads: The most lamentable spoyle and burnyng of East Dearham.
                  Identified as STC 12531+ on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               East Dereham (England) --  History --  Fire, 1581 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-02
            Pip WillcoxSampled and proofread
         
            2008-02
            Pip WillcoxText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A doleful Diſcourſe and ruthfull Reporte of the greate Spoyle and lamentable loſſe, by fire, in the Towne of Eaſt Dearham, in the Countie of NORFOLKE: Vpon Tueſday the .18. of Iulie, this preſent yere .1581.
            
               HOSEA. 5. Verſe. 14.15.
¶I wil be vnto IPHRAYM as a LION, and as a Lyons whelp vnto the houſe of IVDA: I, euen I, wil ſpoile and go away, I wyl take away and none ſhal reſcue it: I will go and returne to my place til they acknowledge their fault and ſeeke mee.
            
               2. CRO. 36. Verſe. 16.
¶They mocked the Meſſengers of God, and diſpiſed his worde: and miſvſed his Prophets, vntyll the wrath of the Lord aroaſe againſt his people, and till there was no remedie.
            AT LONDON.
            Printed by Richard Bradocke, for Richarde Hollens: And are to be ſolde at his Shop oueragainſt the Signe of the Bell within Algate. 1581.
         
         
            
            
            ¶TO MY DEARE FRIENDE AND CHRIſtian Brother, Richard Atlee, Inhabitant of the deſolat Towne of Eaſtdearham, and to his vertuous wife, Alice Atlee: ARTHVR GVRNEY wiſſheth proſperitie, and all good thinges, in CHRIST IESV.
            
               
                  ABoute a fortnight ſince, it was my hap to vnderſtande of a Ballet (as I take it) then newly come from the Preſſe, conteyning a brief and doleful Diſcourſe of the late burning of Eaſt DERHAM. And (as for mine owne part) I both was and am a witnes of the wonderful euents therof: and therwithall (what for my continuall trauell of body and mind, the ruines of my friendes &amp; allies and mine owne ſmal loſſes) a fellow feeler of the heauy burthen impoſed vpon the townes eſtate: euen ſo, with ſo much the more good will I enterteyned the newes, expecting ſome better ſequell, and reſted not, til mine eyes were teſtimonies of the trueth. But when I peruſed the ſame, and approued the penning as ſufficient in that or ſuch like caſes, I was (neuertheleſſe) well aduiſed of ſundrie vntruethes, whiche the Author (no doubt) not ſo much vppon pretenced deprauation, as for want of neceſſarie inſtruction had inſerted. And allbeit, no important thing hath therin eſcaped, which (for mine owne part) I would not tollerate, of verie good wil in that reſpect: yet ſithe her Maieſtie, her honorable counſaile, many noble, worſhipful, &amp; common perſonages, bee otherwiſe infourmed of the matter: as alſo, the duetie of a chriſtian, requiring by all meanes to intercept the courſe of an vntrueth: and laſt of all, in diuerſities of wandring reportes to eſtabliſh ſome certaintie, I haue vndertaken in the diſcourſe of the matter, to ſet downe ſuch an aſſurance of his particuler errours, and inſtead therof, interpoſed ſuch trueth, as the diligent obſeruation of mine owne experience and the triall of many ſound iudgements can confirme and teſtifie.
            ¶One poinct (therfore) wherin he failed, is touching the nomber of Tenementes, Meſſuages, or manſion houſes ſubuerted and ſpoyled.
            The .2. cōcerning the diſſolution of our houſes neceſſarie for diuers domeſtical vſes.
            ¶The .3. his inſinuation of a totall loſſe and detriment ſuſteined.
            In theſe three (ſpeciallie) hath he left the matter deſtitute of true report: for, as I haue expreſſed in the ſequell of my treatiſe: the nomber of tenementes is. LII. whiche he calleth. LX. The houſes of office, 350. or there aboutes: which hee reducethe into the nomber of .80. The value of all together .8000. li. or very litle leſſe, which he reporteth to be .14000. The two firſt (without al controuerſie) are miſtaken, and publiſſhed falſelie: But as for the laſt, I muſt confeſſe, that (at a bluſh) it ſeemeth to carrie great appearance of truth: and I my ſelfe was therin greatly ouerſeene &amp; deceiued, vntill with certaine other (of good experience) I had made an eſtimate of euerye particuler loſſe, and brought them to a generall and groſſe ſumme.
            Neuertheleſſe, if we may recken the charge, which the towne (if euer ſhe be repayred) wil exact, to make returne of her former eſtate, I meane in nomber and quantitie of houſes, and (therwith) not pretermit her manifold loſſes, namely, of coyne, corne, implements of Houſhold ſtuffe, victuales, wood, Timber, chattell, fruict, wels, pumps, hay, ſtraw, time and trades, wherby euer ſince they haue declined and gone backward, which with the reſt are and ought to be brought into the rekning: It is certaine true, that of, 14000 .li. a ſmall remnant wyll remaine, if any deale be left at all.
            
               But this is an other caſe: for an accompt is rather to be raiſed accordinge to the rate of ſo much money as euery mans houſe and ſtuffe would yeald in ſale, if now it weare in STATV QVO PRIVS. For albeit the buildinges were ſuch as might haue ſerued many yeares and ages, if it had pleaſed the Lorde to permitte them to poſteryties: yet of a newe houſe, in quantitie of proportionable reſemblance with an old, and of an old, is not one and the ſelfe ſame reaſon: becauſe by how mvch it excedeth in goodnes, by ſo much ought it to be preferred in price and eſtimation.
            So then the whole loſſe which towne hath ſuſteyned is 8000 .li. or there abouts, &amp; the reedifiyng or reſtauratiō of the ſame in neceſſary maner with ſuch other reconings adhearent as I haue allready caſt ouer, will amount to litle leſſe then 14000. and ſo it ſeemeth not vainely ſaide.
            
               He that buyeth a houſe ready wrought,
               Getteth many a nayle fot nought.
            
            Thus much Sir, touching the cauſe that moued me to intermedle &amp; buſie my ſelfe about the affayres of this proceſſe.
            Now whereas the Lord of his owne eſpeciall grace from amongeſt the reſt of that part of the towne deſtroyed, hath gleaned out your houſe, as one eare out of a ſhocke of corne, and preſerued it alone amids the multitude of ſo monſterous flames, though I am in no caſe to exhort you whome I prefer before my ſelfe, or at the leaſt do make no inferiour, eyther in the due acceptation of ſuche a benefit at his Highnes hande, or in recounting the cauſes why he hath ben more mercyfull to you then the reſt of all that towne, and what purpoſes he ſeemeth to haue pointed and aymed at therein: yet ſith I dayely heare men more reddye to attribute occaſion vnto the meanes whiche the Lord vſed in that action of mercy, and to detract from him that honour and priuiledge that in all good thinges is due to him onely: then to waye and conſyder what it is to neglect the meryte of his grace herein: I am to craue your pardon if this my Epiſtle ſhall ſeeme any thing tedious and not facioned with that DECORVM that beſt might become ſo ſhort a diſcourſe as is the treatis it ſelfe.
            You knowe I am ſure that albeit the caſe of the towne in that diſmall daye wherein it was afflicted, was no leſſe myraculous in the eyes of good men, then feareful to the 
                  •
               ad whoſe tonges at the ſame inſtant could implore the ayde of God and attende vpon his ordinance, yet hath it pleaſed ſome ſince that time to make ſo diuers conſtructions thereof as dothe agree and ioyne with all vntrueth: and to take ſo ſlender taſt of true knowledge as if their ſences had eyther of late forſaken them, or as if they were newe drunke and lulled a ſleepe in their obliuion, as in truthe they ſeeme in all goodneſſe.
            Theſe be the mē that turn al things be they neuer ſo graue &amp; waightie vnto wantonnes, that are alwaies muſling with beaſts in the myre of worldly matters, &amp; neuer vouchſafe to lend ſo muche as half an eye to looke vpō the ſunſhine of Saluation, ne will be procured to put forth one poore nuger to take acquaintance of the power and prouidence of God: but readily proffer their hand &amp; the ſeruice of al the inſtrumē
               tal parts of their bodye to welcome &amp; enterteine Māmon that monſter their Maiſter.
            But it is no matter, thei ſhew euē the ſame modeſtie towards God whē he ſheweth himſelf vnto thē, that in the cōmō courſe of their life thei haue don towards thoſe that are preſēt with thē, namely the profeſſers of the Goſpel, &amp; in the ende, ſhal find their fault I doubt not, &amp; throughly vnderſtād it either vnto perpetual pain, or repētance: In the meane ſeaſō, ſith in their darkenes we perceiue faire daylight &amp; the glory of God

in their iuſt cōdēnation, if that be the reward of their ingratitude let thē accumelate their ſinnes, ſeing they wil needes be filthy, till they haue aſcend, the throne of iudgement, and we ſhal ſee and they feele the greatnes of their owne greeuous fall.
            Let vs I ſay, be ſure, that God reuealeth himſelf to no infidel, preordeined to perditiō, &amp; therefore cōfirme our ſelues ſo much the more in our hope, by how much the leſſe they make reconing of the trueth &amp; their own headines &amp; wretched cōditiō. For in truth, nothing can cōmend the good eſtate of a Chriſtiā to his own ſoule &amp; cōſcience with more vndoubted argumēts, thē whē he ſeeth himſelf cōtinēt in the wicked actions &amp; demeanour of worldlings, &amp; hath fayth in all the changes &amp; chaūces of this vnconſtant lyfe to pul true obedience vppon him for his protectiō: The reſt rowle euery waye &amp; tumble vp &amp; downe like reſtleſſe waues of water, allwayes relatinge the mercies and myracles of the Lord as accidents to prophane beginninges.
            And as they are ſeldome poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of humilitie, euen ſo they toſle and turmoyle them ſelues in affliction til they are windleſſe, and then breathe and to it againe, with infinit curſſinges and quarreles till tract of time hath worne awaye the ſorowe of their caſe, or made them feele the pricke that poſteth their danger, of ſickneſſe death, or deſperation.
            Theſe poore ſoules neuer learned of Dauid, Iob and the reſt, howe to behaue themſelues vnder the Croſſe and hand of God, they accompt him a God no longer then he pynneth proſperitie vppon their ſleeues, or wayghteth vpon them with aboundance of wealth and pleaſures if they accompt him a God at all.
            But if their eyes were not ſeeled that they might flye right vpp till they are wearie &amp; then fal ſtraight downe &amp; breake their neckes, they might gather a heape of myracles together paſſed in the ruines of this our towne, and by the ſame learne to knowe the prouidence of God.
            As the wall couered with drye &amp; parched ſtrawe, which although it be platted where the fire had free acceſſe and ſtood like a ſtake in the mideſt of ouerwhelming floudes, yet doth it ſtand whole and ſound, yea &amp;, which is more, with one of the corner poſtes burnt a good depth iuſt in the midſt of the top, with ſtrawes ſtroughtinge ouer it vnperiſhed. What? hath fortune care of ſtrawes? or could theſe (little wretches) laye hold on her heary ſide, &amp; a whole ſtreat of houſes ſo many furlongs long not miſſe the bald. Oh fine ſtrawes, if your dexteritie haue ſaued you, thanke your ſelues. If Fortune, fie on her harlot, that would be ſo freendly vnto you, who neuer did her good, and ſo froward to the reſt, that neuer wiſht her harme.
            Lykewiſe the winde which allwayes changed in defence of thoſe houſes that nowe ſtand, and then were in danger, may ſhew how farr the Lord did purpoſe to reache his rod, It cannot be denied with anye colloure of trueth, that when the fire had gotten the market ſtead, the wind from the ſowthweſt chaunced full weſt, whereby that ſide was preſerued, and when it had gotte, by your houſe and beyond it, ſo that had the fire taken the next rowe, the remnant, except God being able to do what he wil, had ſhewed a wonderful myracle: muſt of neceſſitie haue gon with the fore end of the pece, then I ſay he brought the winde from the weſt to the northweſt, which kept off both the blaze &amp; ſparcks &amp; turned them almoſt backe again, or at the leaſt, that way wherin lay no dāger. If any deny this, not only my ſelf who duly obſerued theſe alterations as I labored, but other credible witneſſes alſo can teſtifie with me, &amp; in the end when the fire was ſuppreſſed &amp; beaten downe, then lo, it returned into the ſame ſtead wherein it ſtode at the firſt.
            
               Moreouer, why cannot our fortune men gather nothing out of the preſeruation of your houſe, knowing that another was burnt to the earth whichin the on end, namli on the ſtree
                  •
                ſyde was ioyned to it and came ſomwhat within it, 
                  〈◊〉
                on the backe ſyde betwene the foūdations of the croſſe buildings was at the moſt but foure foot diſtance, ſo that by al likelihod of imagination the eues of ech other muſt concur within leſſe then thre quarters of a yard? if thei ſay your manſion hous (wherof the queſtion is) is a tiled houſe &amp; that you had the aſſiſtance of the pit &amp; great help of mans hand, I graunt. But I pray you who put that boldnes and courage in one only man, whom we neuer before knew deſperat in raſh attempts whē your hous was al redy fired, for want of ladders to break out betwen two ſpars, there to indure that great peril &amp; danger that not only his parents &amp; frends cried out on, but al the ſtanders by alſo for dread of his preſēt death? who I ſay in this notable diſtres made him the inſtrumēt of your good &amp; an incorage mēt to the reſt? was it God or fortune? now, al this ſay our Epicures was fortune forſoth: it was but good &amp; euil luck, it was but habardepas, it was but this or that, &amp; which for a penny. Alas if I ſhould go about to perſuade thē that before the pit was made, or er the hous was raiſed, or er you were born, God held the purpoſe of your defence, I think thei would iudge me mad, and yet is it greater madnes by oddes to denye it.
            Finallie in a world of ſuch witneſſes &amp; argumēts of the prouidēce of god to make ſhort with thē &amp; cōclude in a word: ſo ſone as the fire was ceaſed, who ſēt that notable ſhoure of rain? was it fortune to ſhow her ſelf in her pōtificalibus, or the lord to declare to vs &amp; proue what he cold haue don in time for our ſafty, if it pleaſed him? they which aſcribe theſe things to fortune, let them ſet her on the top of the pinacle, reſt in her cōtemplation &amp; ſeruice &amp; ſeek non other gods, for ſhe is euen good ynough to ſhow them experience of eternall ſhame.
            It repented godly Auguſtine that euer he diſhonored the name of God by talking of fortune with his tong, but theſe men are not afraid to rob God of his glory, &amp; honour her with their harts▪ But if thei happen to be hunted (like hogs that are led by the eares) from this fortres of theirs, ſo as they muſt eyther confes God or els be pointed out for blaſpheming Atheyſts, then ſtraight way theie ſay that indeed he ſuffered it, but neither willed it, nor did it: wherin alſo thei ſhape them out a God according to their own ſhadow, who by this reſō muſt ſuffer that which he wold not or be a careleſſe &amp; idle ouerſeer of worldlie maters. wel I leaue thē to their groſnes til the lord ſhal pleaſe to vouch ſafe their better knowledge or bring vpon them the iuſt effects of wilfull ignorance.
            Now for aſmuch as amidds ſo great deſolatiō he hath left you this notable trial of his loue, &amp; tumbled the reſt together before the owners faces as thogh he wold haue you to know &amp; cōfeſſe, &amp; the reſt to beare witnes of his fauour towards you: For the loue of god (for your parts) āſwere him again with your due obedience in that caling wherin he hath placed you, euen of a redy &amp; willing mind to bring glory to his name, profit to his church &amp; cōfort to your own conſciences. And as you haue hitherto ben countenaūcers of the poore profeſſors of Ieſus chriſt in this your town, &amp; louing frends to al other: ſo herafter, be not wāting (as I truſt you wil not) in reforming &amp; bridling thoſe, whoſe religion &amp; maners, you daily ſee too too far out of ſquare &amp; order, haling the iugdemēts of god vpō them &amp; others, who but for them wold be more teachable, &amp; in ſhort ſpace better taught. And the Lord (who in althings can ſee the ſecrets of your intents) ſhal bleſſe your labours &amp; reward you with the open liberalitie of his glorious kingdome: which I beſeeche him graunt vnto you both. Amen,
            
               ¶Yours, in the Lord, A R. GVRNEY.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶A LAMENTABLE DISCOVRSE of the Spoyle of Eaſt DEARHAM.
            
               WHo markes the ſteps of this vnſtayed ſtate,Leaſt they be reſerued for as great or greater Iudgement.
               
               And ſées the ſeas which ſink vs in our ſin,
               And wiſeli weies our wicked wādring gate,
               And floudes of filth that we lye frozen in,
               Maye mourne with me, our caſes are akinne.
               I tyed my truſt to trifling traſh and pelfe,
               He by my harme maye ſéeke to ſaue himſelfe.
            
            
               ¶ A Towne I was though bleſt, not braue, God wott,A Towne of meane report
               
               Ne of renoune, my name was allwayes ſmall,
               My treaſures thinne, yet trades which I had gott,
               Did hould me high vppon an happy ſtall:
               An ayde was I, but in no caſe a thrall
               To neighbour Townes diſperſed heare and there,
               My ſtate was ſound and ſtoode for ſtately chere.
            
            
               ¶My fields full faire, my paſtures pight for good,
               My waters cleare, my fruict ſufficient:
               My bounds both broade and well beſtad with wood,
               My Comons large and comly to content:Cōmodyties.
               
               But oh, my ſinne deſerued to be ſhent,
               And lowde did call the vengeance of my God,
               Who heard at laſt, and laſht mée with his Rod.
            
            
               ¶For lo, where late I was a Towne at néedes,
               VVhere Iudgementes &amp; where lawes were oft diſcuſt,
               Am now become a Nettle buſh of wéedes,
               Defaſte with fire and halfe returnd to duſt:Eaſtdearham.
               
               My name to ken, who ſo hath any luſt,
               
                  Dearham I am, ſcituate next the Eaſt,
               In Norffolk ſoile, full well for man and beaſt.
            
            
               
               
                  Meaning all other townes and warnyng them.¶Come foorth, therfore, both friend and foe I meane,
               I counſell all, and none would ouerpaſſe:
               Come learne of mée, that whylome ſounde did dreame
               Of happy ſtate, but ſaw not what it was,
               A world of ſinnes hath cauſed my diſgrace:
               Yea, comon faultes, and in no calme degrée,
               Therfore, I ſay, now ſée your ſelues by mée.
            
            
               ¶When as I ſtoode in peace and pleaſant reſt,
               Guarded with theſe and pleaſures many moe:
               My pleaſant pathes ſo promiſt mée the beſt,
               That (voide of dread) I doubted no ſuche bloe:
               For why? the tempeſt that hath wrought my woe,
               Was out of ſight and couerd with a clowde,
               which cauſd mée pranck, oh wretch &amp; patern prowde.
            
            
               ¶Why ſhould I count, the courſes of my cryme?
               Syth true it is, I plunged was moſt déepe
               In eche offence that doth reproch the tyme,
               And in theſe daies, ſo rocke the worlde aſléepe?
               My ſinnes, my ſinnes, haue cauſed mée to wéepe,
               Whome God hath made a Myrrour to them all,
               That ſée my ſore, or euer ſerch it ſhall.
            
            
               ¶A Drunkard (friends) was I with déepe delight,
               
                  Drunckennes goeth not alone.And pamperd vp my paunche with belly chéere:
               I left not ſo, but ſtyll came on foorthright,
               To thouſandes moe, then I haue cited héere:
               I cared not to cogge, to lye and ſweare,
               To boaſt and brawle, I thought no ſimple ſport,
               Ne yet the good, with ſpite to miſreport.
            
            
               ¶Thus, by degrées, I practiſed my parte,
               For (whirlyng now) came Whordome on withall,
               Selfe wyll, Hatred, and ſwellyng Pride of hart,
               The lacke of Loue, did throughly make mée thrall:
               I ſerud my ſelfe, and poaſted next the wall
               My neighbour, friend or foe, what ere he was,
               As though I raued, to ride on Mydas Aſſe.
            
            
               
               ¶Loe friends you ſée the cauſe of all my wrecks,Cauſe.
               
               Euen ſinne it was that ſtroocke this fearefull ſtroake,
               Nowe ſhall you heare the forme of ſuch effects,
               As do purſue them which the Lord prouoke,Effects.
               
               Theyr glory fades and falles away like ſmoke,
               Expert am I and witneſſe in the caſe,
               Whoſe fumeing faults haue thus beſmeard my face.
            
            
               ¶Attend therefore the ſequell of my tale,
               And I ſhall ſhowe the ſhape of my myſhapp.
               Beléeue me well I will not paſſe my pale,
               But truely touch the trueth in euery gapp,
               For why? to lull or luſke in lyers lapp,
               Ought duely of all men to be abhorde,
               Nowe lyſt I ſaye, and do the trueth recorde.
            
            
               ¶When Ioue my iudge the mighty Lord on highe,
               Had looked long and could not ſée me come,
               And when I card not for his call and crye,Without recouery.
               
               Ne would be ſ
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  de to ſtoupe vnto his doome,
               And when I ſhowde my ſelfe both deaf and dum,
               Then vp he ſtarts and ſtraight had pight the plott
               Which ſtaind my ſtate, and layd me to my lott.
            
            
               ¶For at the leaſt, more then a monthe right out,Drought.
               
               Before he blew the brand that burnt me thus,
               He ſent a ſeaſon of ſunneſhyne and drowghte,
               No day came downe to dewe my vtter cruſt,
               But parcht me like the perfect tunder duſt,
               So that the ſtéele no ſooner gaue the ſtroake,
               But flames flew out and I began to ſmoake.
            
            
               ¶The time of yeare, was truſtie to the touche,
                     This ſpoken. tantum ſecundum quid.
               
               For Iulie did her drie daies beginne:
               Who to the Matche. the Candle well could couche,
               And light the miſt of my miſfortune in:
               Now woes gan weaue the web which I did ſpinne,
               And ſith the Lorde hath iuſt ſet downe my time,Mans helpe vaine.
               
               I iumpt in vaine to ſaue mée by a ſhrine.
            
            
               
               
                  IVLY.¶The eightéenth day of that ſame mournfull moone,
               Within the yeare of thincarnation
               
                  A compariſō borrowed of the Moone 
                        ••
                     tring into the line of 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  Of Chriſt our Lord Gods welbeloued ſonne,
               One thouſand fiue hundreth eightie and one.
               Before eleuen a clocke in the forenoone,
               I tooke my courſe into Ecliptica,
               
               And leaft my lampe in lewde Saturnica.
               
            
            
               ¶For why, the Lord did hide him nowe behinde,
               The Center of his whole conſuming yre,
               
                  He alludeth ſtil vnto an eclipps.And nowe my ſinne the torture ſo vnkinde,
               Oppoſde me iuſt wherof aroaſe the fire,
               For looke howe much my flames encreaſed hier,
               So much they dimd and daunted my eſtate,
               And cauſd me crouch vnto a crabbed fate.
            
            
               ¶My ſtréets were longeſt twixt the South and North,
               
                  The cituation of the towne.And therin peard ſuch beauty as I bare,
               My breadth from Eaſt to Weſt did paſſe right forth,
               And as in townes croſſe ſtréets full comon are,
               Right ſo in me they went and planted were.
               Whereby fower wayes the fier ſoone was ſpred,
               All which at one muſt néedes annoye my head.
            
            
               ¶The winde (God wot) did waite at the ſouthweſt,
               
                  The wynde.To blowe the blaze into the market plot,
               All thinges were armde and redy to arreſt,
               My careleſſe corps, that all miſhaps forgot,
               Wherefore I ſerued am, full lyke a ſot,
               For lo, euen in the midſt of the high ſtreate,
               The cuilles were met which did me thus intreate.
            
            
               ¶As for the man with whome it did begyn,
               
                  Where the fire beganne.The heauens behold I would not hyde his cryme,
               Yet I ſuppoſe he hath committed ſinne
               Which lately gald him in a retchleſſe rime,
               For if I weare, his faultes for to define,
               I could not charge him with infamous actes,
               Ne treade the trace of his ſo filthy factes.
            
            
               
               ¶He is (no doubt) a ſinner with the reſt,
               And beares the Badge of Adames beaſtly parte,
               And broodes the bale, that bréedes within his breſt,
               And hoordes the harmes that hanges on eche mans hart,
               I know what I could ſay of his deſart:
               But let that paſſe, I am not here to tell
               Of praiſe, but how with mée it late befell.
            
            
               ¶Betwixt the wife and maide of that ſame man,
               Right true it is, my bane at firſt brake out,
               To whome (lykewiſe) no harme adiudge I can,
               In this their fact, for why? what man can doubt,
               But that they rued the ruine of this route?
               Beſides (my frendes) in all theſe flames and ſmoake
               We may be ſure, the Lorde did ſtrike his ſtroake.
            
            
               ¶This being thus, why ſhould I chalke his chaunce?
               With markes of mallice and of fowle deſpight,
               Full well I ſée, he did but leade the Daunce:
               For many moe were peſterd in that plight,
               Yet all (I déeme, with verie dull delight:
               And ſith I knowe, God eft with his beginnes,1. Pet. 4.17.
               
               Why do I poinct at this man and his ſinnes?
            
            
               ¶Admit the Lorde would wreſt from him my woe,
               And firſt of all, put him in for his parte,
               Shall I anone, my wayes and wantes let goe,
               As though my ſelfe had neare deſeru'd to ſmarte,
               None can ſo compt, but being fond in hart,
               Let me (therfore) ſtill as I ought beléeue,
               That he hath tane, which firſt to me did géeue.
            
            
               ¶But nowe againe, I turne me to my tale,
               My Belles were ronge, and I ſtraight waies aroaſe,
               My neighbours heard them both from Hill and dale,No helpe can intercept the work of God.
               
               Which way ſo ere the rumour ſpreads and goes,
               But all was one, were they my friendes or foes,
               They could not ſtint ne ſtay the ſtrong decrée,
               Which God had pitcht and plotted out for mée.
            
            
               
               ¶Yet ſith I ſay, I could not vnderſtand,
               
                  Meanes 
                        ••
                     d.Ne ſearch the ſecretes of his holy head
               Nor ſée how farre he would ſtretch foorth his hand,
               Nor what for mée he had afore decréed:
               I left no let that might mée ſtand in ſtead,
               But vſed thoſe my Maſteries in chiefe,
               That promiſt moſt, yet leaſt did eaſe my griefe.
            
            
               ¶Some water drewe, ſome did the ſame tranſporte,
               Some Ladders reard and ran to houſes toppes,
               Some ſpread wet cloathes, and ſome in wofull ſorte,
               Came headlongs downe from Eues where water drops
               Some counſaile gaue, and called other fops,
               Some cride allowde, do reare before the fire,
               And ſome bad rend, but where I would repaier
            
            
               ¶Some ſought to ſaue ſome lynnen cloth and ware,
               And ſome againe my coyne gan faſt convay,
               Some came with Carts, and with whole loades of care
               Some Gooddes did leade into the fields and way,
               Some for their déedes and Euidences pray,
               Some that were ſtoarde of vittailes and of graine,
               Did ſée it burne vnto their loſſe and paine.
            
            
               ¶Some from the field returned ſoone and faſt,
               But were ſhut out, and could no where get in.
               Some to ſcape out, with baggage ran in haſte,
               And could perceiue no ſawte where to begin,
               Thus ſome and ſome great wéerineſſe did winne,
               Vntyll the ſome was verie ſcant and ſmall,
               That idle ſtoode, and in no ſtead at all.
            
            
               ¶And what for this? where is the gaine I got?
               My meanes did fade, and fall flat to the grounde,
               And all my helpes and handes were ſtaid (God wot)
               Which ſought to ſaue me in that ſtate and ſtownde:
               Becauſe the Lorde would néedes me now confownde,
               And make mée taſt ſome triall of miſhap,
               Thus was I caught in trifling with the trap.
            
            
               
               ¶For loe, the Ladders that were ſoone ſet vp,
               The fier did force to fall right downe as faſt:Ladders burnt
               
               My ſtrength was ſtaid, that I mought ſup the Cup,
               And ken my ſelfe a captiue at the laſt,
               The winde did waxe, as though it made great haſte,
               To fling the flames of fowle fate aboute,
               And could reioyce my weale to ſcorne and flowt
            
            
               ¶And where my aide in water chiefly lay,
               As in a meane for ſuche diſtreſſe preparde,The 
                        ••
                     nifite of w
                        •••
                      loſt.
               
               And where I made my moſt recourſe that way,
               My footing fayld till all my Mart was mard,
               Full ſodenly therof was I debard:
               For why? the brandes, they whirld ſo faſt aboute.
               They burnt my Pumps, &amp; won my welles right out
            
            
               ¶And where my wares was poaſted too and fro,
               And leaft at large, for euery man to ſée,pylf
                        •••
                     s.
               
               Fewe bought (God knowes (but many borowed ſo,
               That I haue cauſe to curſe their knauerie:
               And ſhall no leſſe (I doubt mée) while I die:
               For though euyll windes do blowe ſome men to good
               Yet aro they lewde, that liues by others foode.
            
            
               ¶Nay, lowdly lewde, and moſt accurſed wighres,
               Be they who ſée the Thunderboultes of God,Th
                        •
                      
                     
                        •••
                     ckednes 
                        〈◊〉
                     .
               
               Aboute their cares, and ſtill dare vſe the ſleightes,
               And in their theſt and villanie thus plod,
               Where ſhall they haue their laſting place and boade,
               In heauen? no, here I pawne and pledge my ſoule,
               Except they turne, and tame ſuche fancies fowle.
            
            
               ¶Can any beaſt that féedes on carren vile?
               Or can the Dogge ſpew out ſuche filth as this?
               Or can the Deuyll more damnably beguile?
               Thoſe whom he traines to turne from laſting bliſſe,
               If all the Furies were agréed 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               They could ſcarſe coyne 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Then theſe haue found, by 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
            
            
               
               ¶If Pallas had ſet ouer all her ſkill,
               Or were my tongues more then were Argus eyes,
               Or had I got the trade of Tullies Quill:
               Theſe often tould, could me not halfe ſuffice,
               To paint and portray out in worthy wiſe,
               The ſore, the ſinne, the ſhamefull partes of man:
               Whoſe mind and moode no meane but madnes can
            
            
               ¶For though the Lorde imprints in clowde and ſkie,
               Right ſtrange Edictes, to call vs home from ſinne,
               
                  Natu
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     uſesAnd ſo by ſignes of Iudgementes dayly trie,
               The canckred caſe that we lie tumbling in,
               Yet nothing wyll our wandring ſences winne,
               We ſtraight, in nature, can diſcerne the cauſe,
               And ſo aſcribe eche thing vnto her lawes.
            
            
               ¶We diuerſie can deſcant of the Earth,
               And dull vs in ou
                     •
                   déepe deuices ſo,
               And ſhowe the cauſe of plentie and of dearth,
               And what doth ſhake the grounde, and manie moe,
               We are ſo farre betwitcht and gone in woe,
               That whē the Lord doth plead our plagues by word
               We ſhift it off, as though he did but bourd.
            
            
               ¶Doubtleſſe I déeme, or (rather ſée right well,
               That if from Heauen, we heard his voice and crie:
               Or if he ſent the ſéelie ſoules from Hell:
               
                  Diue
                        •
                      Lazaru
                        •
                     
                  To warne vs by t
                     •
                  eir wofull miſerie,
               We would accompt all this but fablerie,
               So that (alas) I can not iudge ne thinke,
               VVhat may vs ſaue, that haue ſuch mindes to ſincke
            
            
               ¶If fearefull Comete glide ouer our head,
               Or blaſing Starres ſhine in our ſhameles eyes,
               If Sickeneſſe haue our ſore both brought and bred,
               Or els the loſſe of landes cauſed our cries,
               Of theſe (I ſay) we daſell and deuiſe,
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   Nature, as our God,
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   and dayly nod.
            
            
               
               ¶Fewe prooffes herein may ſéeme ſufficient,
               For (out alas) how many way the trueth,
               Myne eyes, myne eyes, want no experiment,
               That maye me driue to dole and double ruthe,Note this wel
               
               For of my heauy harmefull hap enſuthe,
               Nought els with moſt, but diſcord and diſdaine:
               And of my loſſe, haue many made their gaine.
            
            
               ¶But if they feare the iudgements of the Lord,
               Or knewe from whence this paſſing plague did ſpringe,
               Or would not wrongly ſtill my caſe recorde,
               Ne ſhrowd my ſhame vnder their fortunes winge,
               They would be carefull of this cruell thinge,
               And rather learne to leaue for feare of paine,
               Then loue ſo long to liue by trayters traine.
            
            
               ¶But all in vaine I ſéeme thus to inuey,
               Their frozen heartes I feare not ſoone can thowe,The prechers after the fyer in fearfull maner, charged to reſtore all the ſtoln ſtuf.
               
               They haue ben taught and truely told the waye,
               How they might gaine, and in Gods fauour growe,
               But they are deafe, they loue to heare of ſnowe,
               Therefore I leaue them that will filthy bée,
               And ſo againe vnto my tale do flée.
            
            
               ¶When as I ſawe I was ſo ſore beſet,
               On cry ſide that now no hope I had,
               And that my meanes did fall into the net,
               And all was fiſhe that came, bothe good and bad,
               Right haſtily and all, in care yclad,
               I muckehild vp, my mooueables and ſtuffe,
               And ſhortely ſaued myckle mangled ſhruffe.
            
            
               ¶Alas the while, what ſight was this to ſée,
               I got a bed, the fier gainde a houſe,
               I chopt a chip, it tooke away the tree?
               It caught the head and I reacht backe a louſe
               For euery plume, I parted with a geeſe,
               And yet alas, it rag'de and ran ſo faſt,
               That lo, this lucke it ſuffered not to laſt
            
            
               
               ¶For after it had once begonne to fume,
               
                  No mercy in fyerAgainſt the winde, and with the winde it went,
               It leaft no ſide, bue eftſoones did aſſume,
               All that it toutcht, and no way would be pent,
               Till my long ſtréetes, on both ſides it had brent,
               And made them lowe and leauell with the grounde,
               And of my coyne, had molten many a pownde.
            
            
               ¶The Houſes Manſion, which it brought downe,
               Were fiftie two, euen there aboutes I geſſe,
               
                  The ſumme of houſes.And all the reſt, that burnt were in the Towne,
               Thrée hundred and fiftie, not many moe ne leſſe.
               So that the totall nomber I confeſſe,
               Is foure hundred and twaine, which I clearely loſt.
               And now do lacke, to my great griefe and coſt.
            
            
               ¶The Fiſh and fleſh, that I forehande preparde,
               
                  Hauocke.The Drinke, the drugges, the bread, butter and chéeſe,
               The Hay, the ſtrawe, the wood for whiche I carde,
               All at a clappe, I muſt forgoe dnd léeſe:
               The Catchpole caught them as his lawfull fées,
               Which laide me ſupperleſſe vpon my Bed,
               When I ſcarce fownde a Cowch to calme my head.
            
            
               ¶The Fruict that late I looued to pare and prune,
               
                  Hunger is good 
                        ••
                     uſeI nowe could reache well roaſted from the trées,
               Hunger with care, had harpt ſo ſwéete a tune,
               That Biſket Boxes, Carawayes and theſe,
               I leaft at large, for daintie waſpes and Bées,
               And now could leape alofte to catche a cruſt,
               And ſnap it vp with Appetite and luſt.
            
            
               
                  The moane of infants &amp; women with children.¶And doubtleſſe, who had heard the Infantes moane,
               For lacke of lodging and accuſtomed fare,
               Or of the bruſde and burnt, the grieuous groane,
               Or ſéene the ſhift, that poore eſtate and bare,
               Of women, that full bigge with children weare,
               Would neare forget the Pageants nor the plight,
               So long as he could knowe a wofull wight.
            
            
               〈1… pages missing〉
            
            
         
      
   

