
   
      
         
            A touchestone for this time present expresly declaring such ruines, enormities, and abuses as trouble the Churche of God and our Christian common wealth at this daye. VVherevnto is annexed a perfect rule to be obserued of all parents and scholemaisters, in the trayning vp of their schollers and children in learning. Newly set foorth by E.H.
            Hake, Edward, fl. 1560-1604.
         
         
            
               1574
            
         
         Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02480
            STC 12609
            ESTC S105953
            99841678
            99841678
            6276
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02480)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6276)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 546:12)
         
         
            
               
                  A touchestone for this time present expresly declaring such ruines, enormities, and abuses as trouble the Churche of God and our Christian common wealth at this daye. VVherevnto is annexed a perfect rule to be obserued of all parents and scholemaisters, in the trayning vp of their schollers and children in learning. Newly set foorth by E.H.
                  Hake, Edward, fl. 1560-1604.
                  Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536. De pueris ad virtutem instituendis.
               
               [104] p.   
               
                  By [W. Williamson for] Thomas Hacket, and are to be solde at his shop at the greene Dragon in the Royall Exchange,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1574.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Edvvard Hake.
                  Actual printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A⁴ B-G.
                  "A compendious fourme of education", a verse adaptation of "De pueris ad virtutem instituendis" by Desiderius Erasmus, has separate divisional title; register is continuous.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Education --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-10
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-11
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2004-11
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A Touchestone for this time present, expresly declaring such ruines, enormities, and abuses as trouble the Churche of God and our Christian common wealth at this daye. VVherevnto is annexed a perfect rule to be obserued of all Parents and Scholemaisters, in the trayning vp of their Schollers and Children in learning.
            ¶ Newly set foorth by E. H.
            
            ¶Imprinted at London by Thomas Hacket, and are to be solde at his Shop at the greene Dragon in the Royall Exchange. 1574.
         
         
            
            
            
               ❧To his knowne friende mayster Edward Godfrey Merchaunt.
            
               IT VVERE TO BE vvished (my deere friend) that euen the vvhole course of this our frayle and mortall life, vvere bestovved vpon the seruice and continual vvorship of God: and that vve coulde commit our vvhole vvill and dealings vnto the vvill and pleasure of God, both for that our ovvne thoughtes doe little preuayle about them, &amp; also for that the general felicity of man doth depend only vpon the obedience vnto Gods vvill and prouidence.
            It vvere also to be vvished that vve vvere not carefull for the chaunces to come, but that vve could submitte our selues vvithout staye to Gods deuine vvill and ordinaunce.
            But (alas) suche and so greeuous vvas the fall of our first father in Paradice, that besides the fragilitie of our state, and the vncertaintie of our life, vvhich of all thinges is most vncertaine, (Nam homo quasi bulla) there is also by the same his fall infused into oure fleshly hearts, a friuolous care, and as it vvere

acurious meditation of temporal and corruptible thinges: VVhich care as it is vnto the godly a very decrease of zeale, and hinderance to perfection, I meane to perfection vvrought by Gods spirite: so vndoubtedly the same vnto the reprobate, is an vtter extinguishment of pietie and vertue: For no man of vvhat estate soeuer he be, of himselfe hath anye habilitie at all, eyther to contemplate the goodnesse of God or to stande in avve of the terrour of iustice. No vve are not able I say to tast the benefyts of christ his death &amp; passion, except vve haue by the (instinct of grace) mortifyed vvithin vs the corrupt motions and naturall cares of the flesh: vvhich altogither vvitholde vs from the true contemplation of diuine and spirituall things, according as it is vvritten: Animalis homo non percipit ea quae sunt Dei: The fleshlye manne hath no feeling of those things vvhich belong vnto God.
            And although there be a certaine care commended vnto vs in the holye Scripturs, as the care vvhich Jzaacke had for the barrennesse of his vvife: the care vvhich Jacob had for the losse of Ioseph his sonne: the care vvhich the poore vviddovve of Sarepta hadde, fyrst for hir ovvne pouertie, and then for the death of hir onlye sonne: the care also

vvhich the Gospel declareth to be in Martha: vnto vvhome our sauiour Christ sayde, Martha, Martha, thou carest and art troubled about many things: Although (I say) suche kinde of care is set foorth vnto vs in the booke of our saluation: Yet deere friende vvee must not thinke but that there is another, and that a principall kinde of care, vvhich only and alone by the vvorde of God, to all suche as are regenerate, is commaunded and commended: euen a zealous and a feruent care to the building of Gods house: besides the vvhich care, al other cares (in vvhat respect so euer they be) are but corrupt and vaine: Yea, they are nothing else but dregges of the fyrst fylth and corruption that fell vnto man by the sinne of Adam, and of vvhich our sauiour Christ in the Gospell forbiddeth vs, euen so many of vs as by him desire to be righteous, saying: Take no thought for your lyfe, vvhat you shall eate, neyther for your bodye vvhat you shall put on: The lyfe is more than meate, and the bodye is more than the rayment. Consider that the Rauens neyther sovve nor reape. And againe: vvhich of you by taking thought, can adde one cubit to his stature? And againe in the same Chapter Therefore, aske not what you shall eate,

nor vvhat you shall drinke, neyther lette your mindes vvander about these speculations: For after all such things, the heathen people of the world seeke: and your father knovveth that you haue neede of these thinges. The Apostle also willeth vs to bee carefull for nothing but in all prayer and supplication to make our petitions manifest vnto God with giuing of thankes: To conclude, euen of this care our sauiour Christ in saint Iohns Gospel saith: Are there not tvvelue houres in the day? If a man walcke in the daye, he stumbleth not, but if hee vvalke in the night, he stumbleth bicause there is no light in him. Truelye, this care I saye is nothing else but dregges of infydelitie, and the verye frailtye of olde rebellious Adam, vvhich except it be mortified vvithin vs, vvill vndoubtedlye dryue vs from the true feele of saluation.
            Contrarivvise of the true christian care, which as it is sayd is the perfytte badge of regeneration: the kinglye Prophet Dauid speaketh in the Psame vvhen he sayth: The zeale of Gods house hath deuoured me: and againe: I had rather be a doore keper in the house of God This care vvas vvonderfully to be seene in Moyses the princelike Propht of Gods people, vvhen he desired rather to be razed

out of the booke of lyfe, than that God should forsake his people the Israelites: Yea, this care doth Christ himselfe commende vnto his seruaunts in this maner: Sell that you haue, and giue almes, and make you bags that vvaxe not olde, and treasure that can neuer fayle: and againe in the same chapter, Let your loynes be gyrt about you, and your lightes burning: and againe: Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after righteousnesse, for they shall be fylled. To bee short euen this and none other is that same care of the vvhich the Lord sayde to Martha: Thou carest for manye thinges: but one thing is needefull.
            
            VVherefore (beloued in the Lorde) seeing that this is the verye true care that vve ought to haue: and contrarivvise, the other care but a fleshly care, a vaine care, yea a care proceeding of infydelitie, and altogither a lette and stop vnto such as desire truly to be illumined: Alas vvhat and hovve muche haue vve to lament, that in this our vvretched time, so small remaine of that same christiā care, so streightlye prescribed and left vnto vs in the sacred Scriptures appeareth amongst vs: euen amongst vs that vsurpinglye take vpon vs the name of true christians? that neyther care of

Pastors tovvardes their flocke: of maiestrates tovvardes the people, nor of parents tovvards their childrē is almost any vvhere to be found? And that (contrarivvise) all men are careful for themselues, all thirsting after their ovvne priuate commodities, and no man almost caring for gods glorie, no man seeking after the righteousnesse thereof.
            To conclude, hovve much and hovv greatlie this christian care is at this day in all men generallie, and in these three estates especially contemned, hovv much it is set at naught and neglected, vvhereas notvvithstanding, it is the very erecting and repayring of Gods house and the propagation of his glorie: I haue in this litle booke briefely declared: being desirous in the onely respect of loue and good vvill to confer the dedication thereof vnto you: in vvhome I doe knovve (as by perfyt experience) to bee dvvelling a most godlie care vnto pietie and truth: and contrariwise an vtter hatred to falsehoode, and else whatsoeuer is shadowing of truth. Accept it J praye you, and be no lesse pleased with my hartie affection, than J my selfe am displeased with the basenesse of the gift, which notwithstanding, may suffice to expresse the aboundaunce of my loue.
            
               Your friend most trustily assured Edvvard Hake.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶A Touchestone, for this time present.
            
               
                  WHO so vvil bende him selfe but slightlye to beholde the dealinges of the worlde at this daye, hée shal perceiue (euen to the great horrour of his minde) the small habilitye of well dooing that remaineth scant superfitiallye rooted in the consciences of men: hée shall sée our willes altogeather bent to wicked actions, and our wittes to vngodly inuentions: our consciences loose, wide, and hipocritical, and our heartes full of dissimulation and fraude: that alas, euen the very principles, as wel practiue, as speculatiue, are quite and cleane forgotten, and gone, and the infallible doome of our conscience (which of the learned is called Synteresis) holdeth no place of terrour amongst vs: reasons aswel superiour as inferiour, aswell Diuine as Ciuile, haue no power to reclaime vs: Signes of Gods wrath and examples of vengeaunce maye nothing appalle vs: and (to conclude) euē humane mortalitye wil not, can not, nor (I feare) shall not withdrawe vs: so great is our libertie, so secure our liues, and so presumptuous

our hearts thoughtes and attempts. Looke what is good, the same wée deride, contempne &amp; refuse, and contrariwise, whatsoeuer is euil, if it bring eyther pleasure or profite, the same doo we wishe for, pursue and embrace: Auarice, wée account good &amp; honest desire: Usury (the sōne of Auarice) we account lawful trade: Excesse we cal bountie: whoredom, pleasure: swearing, Iolity: pride, Brauery: deceipt, policy: robbing, shifting: and (what should I more say) vice we account vertue, &amp; vertue precise foolishnesse. We seeke for new fashions, we desire new lawes, new rules and newe orders, and yet no man (al this while) hath minde of a newe life: no man séeketh to renewe the same, nor yet to amend the olde. Surely, surely, the consū
               mation of the world, the dissolution of the heauens, &amp; the dreadful doom of our soules &amp; bodies aprocheth &amp; is hard at the doore: I lament therefore the state of the world at this day. But sith wée are by the vnfallible worde certified, that the nigher the world doeth draw vnto his end, the more raging shalbe the Serpent, the more faithlesse and stonye hearted the people: Let vs

lift vp our heartes vnto the mercye seate, and crye vnto the Lord for his elect sake, to shorten the daye. I feare, I feare mée that when the Lord of the vineyarde shall come (as vndoubtedly hée wil come, and that very shortlye) that hée shal finde both Spiritual murderers and Traitours amongst vs: yea, euen amongst those that cal vpon the name of Iehoue. His ministers &amp; our felowe seruantes, we haue reiected, wée haue buffeted them, yea, wée doo daily cōtempne &amp; scorne them, &amp; there litle wanteth that his déere sōne Iesus christ is not torne in péeces, blasphemed and mocked in his most holy word. O Lord, what shall become of vs? what account shal we make before the terrible seate of vengeance, that thus do neglect the gouernment of Gods house, the wel bestowing of his goodes, &amp; the vnity of his seruauntes? For being by the death of his Christ, redeemed &amp; made frée from the perpetual bondage &amp; slauery of the deuil, death &amp; hel, we haue despised his Passion, we haue frustrated his cōming, &amp; contemned his lawe. The high Priests are elated, &amp; we are al fallen, euen from the highest vnto the lowest, a small

number onely exempt, which at home are contempned and derided: abroade, are daylye murthered, tormented and torne in peeces, consumed through fire, famine and sworde, for the profession of his holye name, and true worshippe of his eternall Godhead. The wicked deuoure them like Lambes, and consume them like stubble, them selues florishing as the Cedars of Libanon, and increasing in wealth as Lordes of the people.
            But woo, woo be to them, by whom offēces doo come. Bee thou fauourable (O Lorde) vnto Sion, build vp the broken vvalles of Ierusalem, forsake not thy Sanctuary, but saue thine elect from the pernicious customes of the vvicked vvorlde: the vvorld so full of poyson, so full of murther, so full of vvhordome, so ful of auarice, so full of contempt, and so full of securitye, that (alas) euen vvith horrour, it svvelleth to the toppe of the vppermost heauens, and it annoyeth the seate of the moste highest.
            
            Alas, what maye wée thinke, or what else maye wee looke for, but euen the very heauens too dissolue, and the extreame flames reserued for our sinnes, to make

an ende of our liues? Sinne is ripe, faith is dead: and saue deuilishnes and deceipt, there is nothing within our heartes remayning. The wicked are strong, the Godlye are weake, that what through securitye of the wicked, and the tormentes executed on the godly, almost no faith can bée founde. The wicked as liuing in delicacie, neglect the Lordes worke: and the Godlye (as afflicted continuallye) are afrayde to doo wel: that except it bée to talke and to bée mindeful of God and his word, there is nothing thought vaine, nothing thought sinne, nothing detested.
            And so the Temple of God, the Lordes house, Christ his Congregation, the very true spouse of our sauiour, lyeth ruinous, al to rent &amp; deformed. Alas, no faith, is left to fasten the worke to the corner stone, no moisture remaineth to knit vp the frame with the foundation, Christ Iesus, our only rocke, our only foundatiō, our only head and chiefe corner stone. Loue is cold, faith is dead: trueth is naught set by. And that same smal number which would fainc bée doing in the daungerous worcke, are eyther daunted by their enemies, or discoraged

by their felowes: The zeale of Iosiah is gon, &amp; Demas triumpheth: Amasiah &amp; Diotrephes doo beare vp their villanous breasts against the Lord &amp; his people: Demetrius is busy, &amp; Simon Magus doeth florishe: that hard it is to thinke whether the number is greater of feareful souldiers, faint workmen, &amp; féeble Christians, or the boldnes of the aduersary more vniuersal, or in tirāny more aboūding. How rageth, how roareth, how thundreth, howe threateth, how whispereth, how braggeth ye Babilonical strumpet, ye Romish Dragō, that bloodthirsty Ciclops, Minotaure, &amp; horrible mōster? how bustle her couetus chāpions? howe swel her vilanous rable of rakehel Termagants? how rage beyond ye seas her bloody Bishops? how crake the crew of her coalequēchy Cardinals? whose destructiō &amp; horrible fal, although I know to aproche, &amp; to be as it were begoon: Yet I do lament (&amp; so may al true English hearts) that our sinnes are so gréeuous, as by the occasion therof, the lord doth deny in the time of so chast, so wise, so godly, zelous, &amp; so learned a Prince (as is our most drad soueraigne Ladye Queene Elizabeth, whose life with ioyned harts &amp; hands let vs cry, cry vnto ye Lord to lengthen) within this Realme of

Englād to bring to perfectiō that which be hath begon: to abolish from her people al remnants of popery, &amp; to supplant the hipocritical &amp; vnlearned ministerye. But it is to be thought &amp; assuredly to be beléeued, that our sinnes, euen our sinnes so great, so greuous &amp; so manifold, (as that ye measure of them is immesurable, &amp; the burthē of them is intollerable) are the only cause that our aduersaries doo florish &amp; beare thē selues so bold against ye furtherers of this work as they do, &amp; that our iniquity is the very cause yt so many cold brethren do encrease &amp; remaine at this day. O where is Besaleel? wher is Aholiah? where is Hirā
               ? where are al those true workmē become, yt in the worke of ye material tēple, were so stout, so zealous, so artifitial, &amp; so wise? Is there nothing of theyr zeale remayning? nothing of their valeance abiding? nothing left of their skill? no alas nothing: almost nothing at al. And (o greuous case) as this worke is most diuine, most true, yea, &amp; as it is the selfe same Temple that was then prefigured: so is it in labour, in building, &amp; in erecting, most of al neglected and despised: nay, it is almost altogeather set aside.
            But if I shoulde saye that all men doo

neglect the building of this holy house (as the more is the case to bée lamented, very fewe as they ought, doo further the same:) then should it not appeare that the greatest workmen do more plucke downe by theyr ill example in life, than erect by their labour in building.
            Neuerthelesse, whether they worke for loue, for gaine, or for feare, so they doo the workes of hired workmen, it is not much to bée waied (I meane for so much as they doo:) For (as the Apostle sayeth:) VVhether they preache Christ for loue, or for spite, so they preache, it is to bee ioyed: although theyr true labours, aswell in life, as in doctrine, would bée more to the aduauncement of the worke, and to the winning of a great many others.
            But I would to God that the greatest parte of them were not (as they are) more careful in building of Pluralities, Trialities, Totquots, and Non residens, than in furthering of this sacred, spiritual and diuine Temple of the Lorde: I would to God they were not more geuen to gréedye gaping after promotions, than to the gathering together of the infected, weake,

wounded, and féeble shéepe: Yea, I woulde to God I saye, they did not more watche, and prye for worldlye preferment, than watche and praye for the Lordes people, the verye true house, churche, and Spouse of Christ.
            Assuredlye, euen nowe hath the Figge trée cast his Leaues, nowe is the Sunne darkened, nowe hath the Moone lost her Light, and nowe are the Starres fallen from Heauen. Hee that hath eares to heare, let him heare. But tel me (I praye you) yée ministers of this holye worke, yee Stewardes of this housholde, yée guides of the people: Is the kingdome of heauen a worldlye kingdome? Is the crowne of glorye a heape of Ritches? Is Christ his church a materiall Temple, or is the same sustayned eyther with Siluer or Gold? Is it not sayde:Luke. 13. 
               My Kingdome is not of this vvorld, If my Kingdom vvere of this vvorld, then vvould my seruauntes surely fyght for mee that I shoulde not bee deliuered to the Jevves:
               Luke. 13. 
               but novve is my Kingdome not from hence? Is it not also vvritten: The Kingdome of heauen is like to a Leauen vvhich a vvoman tooke and hid in three bushelles of floure

tyl al vvas leuened? Do not al the prophets, al the Apostles, &amp; al the faithful that euer were, doth not the whole volume of sacred scriptures, doth not christ him selfe, the verye true sōne of the father God almighty, affirme the kingdom of heauen to be a spiritual kingdom? not visible, but inuisible, not transitory, but euerlasting? yea, do not wée our selues at this daye: euen wée (in whom so smal fruict of godlines apeareth) affirme, hold, &amp; maintaine the same kingdom to be a kingdom intransitory, diuine, &amp; incomprehensible, &amp; the glory thereof to be immortal &amp; neuer vading? Do not wée (further) hold that the Church of God is ye congregatiō of ye faithful, &amp; the very frame building, &amp; foundation therof to bée the Apostles &amp; Prophetes: one body, &amp; the body of Christ: the same Christ being the head corner stone: according as it is writtē: You are no more strangers and foriners, but Citizens and Saints,
               Ephe. 2. 
               and of the houshould of God, and builded vpon the foundation of the Apostles &amp; Prophetes, Christ Iesus him selfe being the head corner stone: In vvhome all the building coupled togeather, grovveth to be an holy Temple in the Lord: In vvhome you are builded togeather to bee the habitacion of God by

the spirit? Is it not thus said? is it not thus writtē? is it not so beléeued? what should I say? if it be so writtē, if christ him self hath so taught you, &amp; you your selues cā not deny it: if you be assured I say, yt the kingdom of God is immortal, immutable and holy: why, why then (alas) doo you so greedily seeke after worldly primacies, transitory promotions, &amp; corruptible substance? If yt crowne of glory bée likewise immortal, &amp; permansible: why desire you earthly crounes? why hunt you after vaine titles, &amp; deceaueable honours? Hath God any felowship with Belial? Or may the world &amp; the spirite make friendly attonement togeathers? what agréemēt is there (I pray you) betwixt God &amp; Māmon? or how accordeth light &amp; darknes? It may not be, it may not bée I saye that the Minister of gods word should any other way of him selfe séeke to further the gospel of Christ, then by sincerity of life &amp; godly conuersation: from the which meane, whosoeuer he be that swarueth, the same vndoubtedly is no builder but a destroyer: no shéepherd, but a wolfe: no Minister of trueth, but a sclanderer of the same:Peter. 5. 
               I beseech the Elders that are among you (saith Peter) vvhiche am also an elder, and a vvitnesse of the suffering of Christ,

and also a partaker of the glorye that shalbe reuealed: that ye feede the flock of God vvhich dependeth vpon you: caring for the same, not by constraint, but vvillingly: not for fylthye lucre, but of a readye minde: not as thoughe you vvere Lordes ouer Gods heritage, but that ye maye bee ensamples to the flocke.
            
            O you Pastours, you Preachers, you Guides of the people, &amp; you pillers of the churche, O you maisters of this worke, &amp; Surueyours as it were, of this building, doeth then the kingdome of heauen stande in eating and drinking? Can the Temple of God bée sustained with Pluralities, &amp; Tot quots, with Deanries and Prebendes, with office and honour? hath not Christ ordained you as Lanterns of light, as salt of the earth, and ministers of saluation? Is it not sayde, you are Gods labourers, Gods worckemen, and the builders of Gods Temple? Howe happes it (then) that you bée builders of your owne stoare, and not builders of Gods churche? maintayners of your owne wealth, &amp; not susteiners of gods temple? féeders of your selues, &amp; not of your flocke? Howe haps it (I say) that a great number of you (for to

such extremitye is it come) wyl counterfaitelye séeme to bée carefull in féeding of soules, (which notwithstāding you do not as you ought to doo) and forget altogether the reléeuing of bodyes, to the discredite of your selues, &amp; to the detriment aswell of your owne soules, as of the soules of your flocke? and againe other some to bée so epicuryous in the pamperyng of theyr owne bodies, And so vaineglorious in a litle reléeuing of the bodyes of the néedy, that they thinke the same theyr counterfeit hospitality to be a sufficient discharge of them selues, and defence of their flock? Yea, I woulde to God, that the number were not great of suche Godlesse Hipocrites, suche vnlearned loyterers, and verye pieuishe pelting Parasites, which for liuing sake haue intruded and thrust them selues into the Church: who, if they were not cloathed with the counterfaite title of bountiful housekéepers, shoulde haue nothing at al wherewith to couer their blockishnesse, nor to hide their blindnesse, nor to cloake theyr lewdenesse and trecherye: whereby they shoulde incurre the iust reward of their naughtines, euen ignominy

and reproche: of whom the Apostle geueth vs warning in these wordes:Timo. 3. 
               This knovve ye that in the latter dayes shall come perillous times: For men shalbe louers of them selues, couetous, bosters, proud speakers, disobedient to father and mother, vnthankfull, vngodly, vnkinde, trucebreakers, false accusers, riotous, fearce, despisers of them vvhiche are good, traiterous, heady, high minded, greedy vpon voluptuousnesse, more then louers of God: hauing a similitude of godlinesse, but hauing denied the povver thereof. Would God (I saye) that the holye house were not pestered at this daye with such hipocrites and damnable sort of luskish loytering Lubbers, who (notwithstanding their great blockishnes their palpable ignorance &amp; extreme want of learning) doo kéepe within their clāmes the liuelyhood of true pastors, and painful laborers: which sustaine Ruffiās, to begger ministers: which maintaine routes of rakehel Roisters, to decrease the nūber of honest poore christians: which not only thē selues are contented to stop the roomes of learned preachers, but also deuilishly doo bring in most horrible crewes of cursed Chaplins, &amp; notorious numbers of monstrous vnlearned Sicophants, which take the fléece, &amp; starue the flocke: and which doo impaire the Church more in one day, then

the greatest workmen are able to repaire in .xx. yéeres, to the great ruine of the building, &amp; directly against the word of the Apostle, which willeth that none should bée admitted into ye ministery,Timo. 3. but such as are honest: not double tongued, not geuen to much wine, neither greedy of filthy lucre. Furthermore, I would to god, that besides ye number of such disguised monsters, this holye worcke were not likewise hindered with faint &amp; faithlesse brethren, which are fallen from the spirite to the flesh: frō God to the world: But I feare, I feare me that euē of the chiefe workmen, of the head laborers, &amp; Prepositours as it were of this building, not a few at this day are cooled in zeale, are fallen from sincerity, &amp; ouercom with ye world: so yt of som of thē, a mā may say: Albi an atri sint, nescio. But such alas is our state, such is our time. Frō the prophet to ye priest frō the hiest to ye lowest, frō the head to ye foot, we are al gone frō truth. we are fallē to vnrighteousnes. Howbeit blessed be ye lords name for euer, notwithstāding these abuses in ye Ministery, there is none can say that (euē maugre the head of ye enemy) the soūd of the gospel hath not passed throughout euerye coast, hath not

béen preached and taught in euerye place, &amp; béene rung into the eares of euery man, woman and childe. Al haue heard, al haue séene, yea, and al haue felt aswel saluation profered, as plague for sinne threatned: Ignoraunce may not bée pleaded, neither is there at al any excuse to bée receiued. But alas, of so muche séede, what is the fruite? of so muche trauaile, what is the gaine? Euen this forthwith to bée reaped: Stubble for the fire, and horrible sinnes for the scorching flames of hell. And for this cause, came light into the world, that men séeing, should not beléeue: and not beléeuing, should bée damned. From our verye Cradels are wée nourished in sinne, wée are practised in our infancye, &amp; made perfect in our Childhood. In mans age, are wée very sinne itselfe, in midle age monsters, and in olde age Deuils. O terror: O horrour, O rustye beaten age? O age wherin iniquitye so much and so mightely preuaileth, &amp; wherin Belzebub so greatlie beareth rule: what should I say of vs, but euen this? sinne, receiue thy guerdon: man receyue thy doome: thy doome (I say) to bée burned in the glowing gulphe of perpetuall

damnation. Non vult Panthera domari, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Phrix nisi plagis, emendabit.
            
            As for the gréeuous desertes in temporal gouernment, and the great abusions in ciuil Magistrates, theyr cold erecting of the Lordes house, theyr violent depression of the great and holy worke, theyr smal zeale to the Lordes people, and theyr Godlesse supportacion of false worckemen, cursed hyrelinges, and professed enemyes to the trueth? Assuredly I can not without great shame and sorrowe declare in wordes the very least part of that, that by some of them is committed in déedes: to the miserable decaye of the building, to the gréeuous ruine of the Lordes house, and to the manifest offence of Gods people.
            With silence therefore will I leaue them in theyr sinne, and with harty prayer commit theyr amendment to the wyll of our God: who, for Christ his sake, &amp; for his holy names sake, frame theyr heartes to more loue of his truth, that his gospel be by them no more hindred, nor the professors therof hated, nor the sounde of his word stopped.
            And as for the state of Ecclesiasticall gouernment, who séeth it and sorroweth

not? who beholdeth it, and lamenteth not? But what should I saye? I would to God that sinne were not more abetted through the féeblenes of discipline, than zelously reprooued by the voyce of Good Preachers. Naye, rather I would to God that feeblenes of Discipline were not a vizare vnto feareful Magistrates, and a preposterous shift vnto partial Iudges. But of this matter sufficientlye, though not to my selfe, yet to others of impatient hearing. Onely, I wishe that silence were the vertue to bring vice into subiection, that lenitye and mildnesse were the coraziue of sinne: that pitye had the power to put wickednesse to flight, and Pusillanimitye and tymorousnesse were the preseruers of pietye. Then should sinne bee subdued, then should vice bée extirped: then rotten soares should bee searched: and then the militant Church of Christ should abound in all kind of honour and quietnesse. For, silence, O who imbraceth it not? who will not bée milde? where is hée that will punishe? In whome doeth not partiall pitye abounde? Or at the least wise, who is not afraid and loath to displease? yea, and (that worse is) who

dareth to speake and is not punished? who sinneth and is not pardoned? Alas, so mightely preuayleth sinne at this daye, that as wée wil not say, that to sinne, it is not dangerous: so, must wée néedes saye and affyrme, that to bée an accusar of sinne and wickednesse, is the most daungerous thing in the world. To beare with sinne, it accuseth vs: To speake against sinne, it troubleth vs: To complaine of sinne, it vndoeth vs. To kéepe sinne secreate, is oftentimes periurye: to laye sinne open, is imminent daunger: to sue against sinne, is present destructiō. And what should wée more say? so large a scope hath sinne at this daye, &amp; so smal a succor hath vertue eache where, that sinne eache where is pampered, and vertue eache where subdued to importable bondage. And nowe, if al these thinges be true, and vppon experience founde to bée true: alas, where shall vertue bee shrowded? where, oh where alas shal sinne be restrained? Shal she flye vnto zeale? Oh, zeale can not helpe her: for why, so cold is zeale now euery where become, that none otherwise than as a dead corse is hée caried about vs. Zeale I saye is dead: vertue is become awiddowe: And as for sinne, so puissaunte

is hée waxen, that power can not vanquish him, whole Parishes can not put him to flight: &amp; where men thinke to haue most aduantage against him, there is he most mightily supported. If they bring him before the Commissary, the Cōmissary cannot, or wil not hurt him. If they folow him according to the order of ye lawe: alas, the Law doth enfranchise him: and what there wanteth in the lawe, that, aucthority supplyeth.
            The proofe of which mater, as it is so fresh amongst some, that it cannot be forgotten: So, is it so gréeuous, as that silence can not shrowde it. I haue heard of sundrye godly Parishioners that haue found al this to bée true: Who, by kéeping sinne secréet, haue felt the worme of theyr Conscience, besides the daunger of the lawe stil threatned vnto them: and by laying sinne open (namely, so farre forth as manifest suspitions were able to leade them) haue thereby (as it were by a direct meane) brought sin to full scope, &amp; them selues to great daunger and continuall vexations: some of them, followed with threates: some, endaungered through sodaine stripes that haue béene geuen them: &amp; other some, molested with

sutes brought vpon them, wanting all colour of equitye. But, as vncertaine where to inferre this fault, whether, in the weaknesse of the Law, or in ye partialitye of the Iudge for ouermuch mitigating the seueritye of so sclēder a law, in admitting (peraduenture) some féeble purgatiō by vnseemly compurgators, I will ceasse for this time: wishing neuerthelesse, that whēsoeuer any party accused, shall happen by such sclender purgation, to be acquited of suche crime, as in the eyes and by the oathe of godly men shal séeme not onely detestable, but also apparant: Some meanes may also bée found by the Godly and careful prouision of the Magistrate, that the accusars may be shielded from the mischeuous attempts of their aduersaryes, that they may bée quit from theyr continuall quarelles, that they maye walke in safetye from theyr malyce, and maye trauaile in theyr callinges without dread or hazarde of displeasure.
            But to returne: Loe, heare the negligent building of the ministery and the cold erecting of the Magistrate: Now behold wée in the middest of this Chaos, what helpe there is in Parents, or what hope in succession.
            
               Parentes do erre, and they do not onely continue their errours, but therin also do they nourish their children.
            Children by nature are euyll, and being euyll, they are by example of Parentes made worse. No loue towardes God, no honour of children to their Parentes, nor feare of Parentes in their Children is sought for, had, or regarded at all· If I should speak of the educatiō of daughters, (wherof in this third place I should writ) the verye Pagans, Infidels, and Turckes, woulde stand vp against vs. I can not tell whether through sorrowe, I shoulde crye out and bewayle them, or for shame commit them to scilence: so immoderate in apparell, so lasciuious in talke, so bolde in behauiour, and so vnséemely in iesture is the vniuersall state, almost as well of wiues as of damosels. And that which most of all should be regarded: I meane the prouident care of parents ouer their daughters in their young &amp; tender years: that is altogither neglected and set a syde. No sooner is the daughter of age of vnderstanding, but shée straight waye and therewithall learneth the highe path to

whoredome, and the principles of vanity and lewdenesse. Eyther shee is altogither kept from exercises of good learning, and knowledge of good letters, or else she is so nouseled in amorous bookes, vaine stories and fonde trifeling fancies, that shée smelleth of naughtinesse euen all hir lyfe after, as a vessel which being once seasoned, doth neuer forgo the sent of the first licour.
            In the time of infidelity, women by learning did attaine the very toppe and pricke of vertue and honesty, of which number I will recite a fewe according as they haue bene gathered, not by my selfe, but by learned wryters, which for their direct handeling of this matter I am perswaded sometimes to vse, and oftentymes to ymitate. Hortensia a Romain maide, was so profoundlye learned amongst the Romaines, that hir worthynesse was spreade throughout the whole Monarck, and she was not more famous for hir learning then loued for hir vertue, and honoured for hir chastity. Of such woonderfull learning, was the wife of the Poet Lucane whose name as I remember, was Argentaria, that after the death of hir husbād,

shée corrected his bookes, and made perfite all his workes. Diodorus the Phisition had fiue daughters, excellent in learning and renoumed in chastity. Corynna The
                     •
                  a a vertuous womā ouercame ye Poet Pindar fiue times in verses. What shoulde I speake of Cassādra &amp; Sulpitia? what should I speake of Paula the wife of Senec, which being once informed with the doctrine of hir husband, followed the same also in vertuous lyfe and conditions? All these were Paganish, Heathenishe and misbeléeuing people: And yet for all that, such was their excellency in learning, and their worthynesse in vertue, that the worst of them all (for prudēcy) was able to gouerne a whole country, &amp; to kéepe in order a whole kingdome. If we looke backe to the first time of Christianity, there also wée shall finde many godly zealous, and learned women and virgins. Tecla was the disciple of Paule the Apostle, and very perfit in the sacred scryptures. In the time of saint Hierome, Paula, Marcella, Eustachium, and others were greatly studied in the worde of God. And in the time of Saint Augustine, were Valeria, and Prob a, besides an

infinite nūber in all ages, which excelled as wel in learning, as in good life &amp; liuing.
            But euen as I doe see verye fewe, and almost none at all in this our extreme, and to too impious time, anye thing desirous to attaine eyther vnto vertue or learning: so, that same small number which haue anye knowledge at all, doe so greatlye abuse it, that much better were it they shoulde vnlearne that againe which they haue alreadie learned, then miserably to abuse it as they doe, or at the leaste wise (as we see them) to make equalle Pampheticall trifles with wholesome Doctrine and tryall of lyfe. That breade can neuer be wholsome and good breade which hath once bene spreade ouer with ratten bane or other poyson, be the venim neuer so muche scraped or pared awaye. That cloath can neuer attaine the olde hewe &amp; whitenesse, which hath once bene touched with tarre: and (no more) may those writings be good which are enterlaced with toyes and villanous fancies. I woulde to God that maydes at the least wise might be brought vp, if not in learning, yet in honest trades and occupations

as amongst the very infidels hath bene vsed, accustomed, and most carefully obserued.
            Nay, I would to God they did not spend their times like the women of Perse land: who after some slight and friuolous exercises, doe fall into more vaine and impious pleasures, as it were a malo, ad pe
                     •
                  us: after reading of pernicious, vnchaste and godlesse bookes, or after labours of lyke importaunce (for auoyding of tediousnesse) to accompany inpleasures and banquets, young amorous Roisters, &amp; mischieuous varlettes, making the ende of one pleasure to be the beginning of an other. Of a truth, I may saye of them now, as a learned and zealous Preacher sayd of the people in his time: it shameth me to thinke that they are not ashamed to speake: it shameth me to speake that they are not ashamed to doe: it shameth me to doe that they are not ashamed to reioyce at.
            On the other syde, it is to be lamented (as a case too too grieuous) such parents as doe bring vp their daughters in learning, do it to none other ende, but to make them companions of carpet knightes, &amp; giglots,

for amorous louers. If their intent were otherwise, how woulde they dare so ouer curiously, and carefully to maintaine and keepe them, at the least wise to wincke at them (as they almost euery where doe) in that vaine &amp; vngodly practise of daunsing? vaine and vngodly I say, only in respect of the present abuse of the same, which the very Pagans at all times and in all ages abhorred, especiallye being once growne into an occupation and trade as a practise most pernicious, wherein the sences are altogither captiuated and made subiect to vnlawfull fantasies, to vnreasonable thoughtes, and wicked deuises. O good GOD, sayth a certaine writer, what shaking, what bragging, what wringing of handes, what whisperings, what treading vpon the toes, what vncleanly handlings, gropings, kissings, and a very kindling of lecherye, doth their assotiate that trade and occupation of daunsing? And surely, as the same in the abuses therof at this daye, is cause of muche and excéeding greate impiety: so is it not (almost) possible for any one to attempt it, after the excesse of our common banquets, being sober

or in right minde, and perfite memorye: For it cannot be but that to daunce in such order, or rather in suche disorder as is now vsed, procéedeth eyther from excesse of drinke, or else of méere madnesse.
            But what maruell is it, if there be so many disordered places of daunsings and ministrelsey, sith that there are also houses of bawdry? And yt this our intemperat kinde of daunsing is a meane vnto muche lewdnesse and contempt of godly life, it is plainely to be vnderstoode: there was neuer séene any one of our notable daūsers zealous in good life: there was neuer heard of any that could hop, skip, &amp; tourne on the toe (as they terme it) that would scarcely come to ye church without carying. O good God, what kind of learning is this? what education of children is this to be called?
            And yet this is the vertue that nowe a dayes is vsed: yea, this is the skyl that Parents doo nowe a daies desire to bée in their Daughters. And whether for the learning heareof, they bestowe theyr goodes vpon them or not, all is one: For they neuer restraine them: no, they neuer forbid them▪ so oft as they see them of them selues to bée

thereunto geuen: And it is a world to sée, with what demurenes, some that bée Parentes doo sit in beholding the straunge Iestures, footing and countenaunce of theyr curious fantastical Daughters: yea, oftentimes, when the selfe same skill is the cause of defiling theyr bodyes, and vtter losse of theyr honestye and good name.
            A certaine Emperour ordeyned that no Daughters should goo out of their mothers doores, but in the company of theyr mothers, and that they should not daunse with Yong men in assemblies. Wée contrarywise, doo procure our Daughters to Bridales, to Maskes, and to other like companyes where Daunsing is vsed: yea, and so careful are Parentes to haue their daughters noted of excellencye in daunsing: that in al that they may, they adorne them with Iewels, and set them forth in costly apparel: suche, as the fonde, foolishe and enterchangeable fashions doo require.
            And this is the learning that Parentes nowe a dayes doo wishe for in theyr daughters, this is the vertue, these are the qualityes of them so greatly desired: that if time were euer a compound, I thinke it is euen

nowe at this daye and in this Age: Besides this, when the Daughter is in this wise noseled and brought vp, when shée is in this kinde of learning more than sufficiently instructed, or rather distructed, then is shee straight waye taken foorth a newe lesson, shée turneth ouer another leafe, and goeth on with euill spéede.
            And as before the learning thereof, shée was meete inough to receyue any kinde of Godly instructions: so, after shée hath once attayned vnto the knowledge of Daunsing, shée neuer afterward returneth backe to better thinges, shée quite and cleane forsaketh vertue, and for the most part, biddeth honesty adewe. Then shée must haue scope, then shée must haue her apparel after the fashion, then shée must haue paintings, Lickinges, Combings, Playtinges, Pitchinges, and all kinde of newe fashioned Trimminges: yea, then shée must haue walkinges, Feastinges, and watchinges, and al kinde of pleasure that maketh perfect the trade of a Strumpet.
            But as herein, I haue greatlye (and aboue the rest) occasion to accuse such Maydens, as haue beene, and are immoderately

geuen to daunsing: so, (the general confusiō is such) that as well the vnskilful daunser, as the cunning, as wel the one, as the other, are nowe altogeather geuen ouer to libertye, and there withal to pride, fonde loue, and worse.
            Of a trueth, I can not sée that for the education of Children, especiallye of Daughters, wée may almost in any point bee compared with diuers, and that a great many Infidelles and Pagans whiche neuer knew God nor Christ. Amongst the Egiptians there is a custome (and I suppose at this daye inuiolable) that women shal weare no shooes, for intent onely that they shoulde abide at home, and not (so much as once) bée séene out of the doores of theyr Parentes or Husbands. The Massagetes, a people amongst the Barbariens, lyke as they doo vse none other houses saue great Tubbes and Tunnes, so doo they prouide, that theyr Wiues and Daughters bée togeather abiding in one Tunne, and them selues and theyr Sonnes (when they are of age) in another Tunne: not accompanying theyr Wiues after the time of theyr conception nor resorting vnto them

a good time after their deliueraunce. I reade also that the Bragmans a people in the vttermost bounds of this vper world, do neuer assotiate thē selues, I meane the mā the woman, nor the woman the man, after such time, as their wiues haue conceyued, nor till they haue a certaine time gone after their deliueraunce: their yssue being alwayes brought vp, the male with the father, &amp; the female with the mother. And at suche time as they sée their children of sufficient yeres, &amp; mariageble (as they call it) then if it be a man childe, the father treateth with a certaine Officer amongst the men (which is as it were the heade of the people) a man approoued wise and full of pietie, for the marying of his sayd sonne, and they togither immediatly doe repaire to the place, where the women haue their abiding togither. And after that the magistrate hath chosen at his discretiō from among the rest of the virgins, foure damosels, agreeable to the young man aswell in age as otherwise: Foorthwith are called before them, the mothers of the iiij. maydens, and the mother of the sonne: and after that they all (being demaunded)

doe séeme to assent vnto the choyse of the young man, vpon whome so euer it shall happen the same to be made, then they altogither with one voice (falling groueling on the grounde) doe beseeche the Gods to prosper him in the choyse: and after certain prayers made according to the vse of the countrey, the sonne as is aforesayde, at his owne liking, doth choose one of the foure virgins, and (taking hir foorth by the hande from the other three) they all wyth the magistrate accompanyed with the other thrée wiues, who in the meane tyme doe leaue the gouernaunce of their daughters to some auntient matrone amongst the rest of the women, doe conduct the young couple to the father of the mayde: who after that he hath giuen his consent, which they neuer at anye time doe denye, with his wife and the other thrée women, (the magistrate going before) doth leade them to the people, which for the same purpose are called togither: whervpon the people with one voyce make a ioyfull showte and outcry to their Gods to blesse them, and to increase the fruites of their bodies. And when they are thus coupled

with assent of the parents, the mutuall liking of the persons themselues, and the good will of the people: The young maried folke are brought home againe by the magistrate, the parents and the other iij. women aforesayde, being also accompanied with so many of the men, as eyther then be maried, or haue at anye time before had wiues: leauing alwayes behind them gouernours for their children, as in that behalfe, it is also prouided.
            And this is the order of that countrey in bringing vp and marying their children. And they vse also this selfe same order in marying their daughters, not differing in any poynt from the mariage of their sons: sauing that the mother of the daughter alwayes accompanieth the husbande, aswel when he treateth with the magistrate, as also in all other dealings. Which order in marying and bringing vp of children, I do here write to none other ende, but bicause I doe see (euen to the great griefe of my heart) that neyther in the education of daughters, nor yet in the honest bestowing of them in mariage, parents nowe a dayes (at the leastwise very fewe) doe in

any point come nighe them.
            If this bée Christianitye, if this bée pietye, naye if this bée humanitye, that wée shalbe corrected by the Heathen, reprooued by Infidelles, and condemned by Pagans: Then to what ende hath our mercifull Sauiour denyed his moste holye word, his Diuine trueth and perfect doore of Saluation vnto his peculiar people, the Iewes, whome alwayes hée preserued, whome alwayes hée defended, yea, &amp; whom alwaies from the beginning, he loued and Fostered: and geuē the same vnto vs which were outcastes and bondslaues of the Deuill, Children of wrathe, and heyres of damnation? Naye, Tyre and Sidon shall stande against vs at the daye of Iudgement: Sodom and Gomorra shall accuse vs, and Nimue shall vtterlye condempne vs. What I coulde heare saye of the outrage of Women in theyr Apparaile, in Licking, Painting and Trimming them selues, I am ashamed, and doo tremble to vtter. Of a trueth, the substaunce whiche is consumed in twoo Yeares space vppon the apparaill of one meane Gentlemans

Daughter, or vppon the Daughter or Wife of one Citizen, woulde bée sufficient to finde a poore Student in the Uniuersitye, by the space of fowre or fiue Yéeres at the least. Mine eyes haue séene the experience, and with sorrowe haue I found out the truth thereof.
            O state confused, O people deformed and full of outrage? O time too too full of Iniquitie and sinne.
            O Englande, what hast thou imagined, or howe hast thou wrought, that euen the verye Turkes and Sarazens, the verye Pagans and Miscreantes, doo thus reprooue thée of iniquitye, and condempne thée of sinne? O Parentes, what hath your posteritye offended, that thus you conduct them to the Deuill, and make them fitte members for the Infernall gulye of damnation? Why restraine you not the horrible pride of your daughters? why reprooue you not theyr detestable Paintinges, Lyckinges and Pranckinges of them selues? why (I saye) doo you not teache them to kéepe home, and instruct them in vertue? And O yée Daughters, what meane (I pray

you) those straunge kinde of disguisinges, Starchinges and Trimmings? To what ende are these fashions, and for what intente are they vsed? If you doe them to please your selfe, it is vaine: If it bee to please Christ, it is a follye: If it bée to delite men, it is whorishe and vngratious: If it bée to gette you Husbandes, it is as muche, as if you would winne them with Uizars. Democritus sayth that the adornement of a Woman standeth in scarcetye of Speache and appareyle. The VVise man sayeth that the right apparell of Men and Women, is no maner of deceyptfull painting and Trimming, nor yet the Pompeous apparell and Iewelles, but it is theyr good conditions and manners. Saint Ambrose also sayeth that the Woman that painteth her face with material colours, doeth raze and put out the true Picture of Christ. Shée is not well appareilled (sayeth Plautus) that is not well manered: neyther loueth shée vertue that desireth her apparell to bee Braue and fine. I saye, O you Daughters, why then doe you thus without al measure, and beyond

al Godforbod, endeuour to tricke vp your selues and to alter your natural hewes? why séeke you for straunge attire? and why wishe you to bée séene? I woulde to God that worthy Lawe, which now beareth the name of Opius: I would to God I saye that Opius Lawe were established amongst vs, which doth prescribe a meane in Womens attyre, what they maye, and what they may not weare. Neuerthelesse, I doe beléeue that albeit there were ordeined a measure altogeather immeasurable, and an order altogeather inordinate, yet women in this time woulde not obserue it nor kéepe them selues within the compasse of it: such is their extreame rage and wilfulnes.
            And herein appeareth as wel the negligence of Fathers, as also the pernicious example of Mothers, &amp; the general excesse of al women, as wel in apparel, as otherwise: whome as we haue with great sorrow to lament, so must I leaue them in silence, for that their liues are so generally noysome, as to heare the same, it woulde abhorre any true and honest Christian.
            But euen as the liues of Parents and

elders are, so is the bringing vp of Children and Yonglings: not onely of Daughters, whiche I haue before touched, but also of Sonnes, of whose education in Learning I haue somewhat written, though briefely in a fewe quaires herevnto annexed. As into whose education in life and manners, I am muche loath to discende, the fielde being so large, and the hope of amendment so smal. Omitting therefore the first ill, handeling of them in their Infancye, the ouer great neishnes and dilicacye that by Parentes is infused into their litle sonnes, euen in those yéeres when as they shoulde chieflye bée framed vnto suche constitucion of bodye as the importaunce of Studye doeth looke for and requyre, and as throughe wante whereof, they become vnfit in after Age bothe for learning and all other good exercises tending to the succour of a common Wealth, as falling through theyr sayde yll Education into feminine delightes and vaine Curiosityes: I come onely to that loosenesse of maners wherevnto they are haled and sette at libertye, at suche time as theyr fraile youthe

ought chieflye and carefully to bée helde in and restrained, namelye, and vniuersally the contempt of Superiours and gouernmēt: whervnto they are directly procured or rather enforced by two spurres of wicked prouocation ministred vnto them by the meare vanitye of Parentes▪ I meane through excesse in their appareyl and libertye in theyr speache: whereof the first so outrageth now a daies in the heades of fantasticall Parentes, that were the dispositions of theyr Sonnes neuer so temperatelye sette, That one vanitye were of it selfe able violentlye to withdrawe them from vertuous Delites and forewardnes to learning, vnto a very Sea of fantasies and wicked behauiours.
            And as for that too too malapart boldnes and libertye that they so greatly delite to haue maintained in theyr sonnes, who seeith not what number of enormityes haue ensued, and doe daily fal out through the same? who seeith not howe it encreaseth with theyr Age, and howe many wickednesses it draweth on with theyr yeeres. Parentes them selues thereby disobeyed, all gouernment contempned,

al correction resisted, al liberty sought for, and all vertue forsaken. Wherevppon followeth and instauntlye ensueth with increase of theyr age, such monstrous increase of horrible abuses, suche continual disturbaunce of common tranquillitye, and suche yrkesome annoyaunce of the Churches felicitye, that who soeuer is (in deede) touched with the least consideration of any of the same, hée can not faile but finde matter enough of vnspeakeable sorrowe.
            And I would to God the Magistrates coulde ones bend theyr mindes, although not to the Originall preuenting of these sayde manifolde abuses (which truelye as natural Parentes they are holden to doe) yet at the least to shred of some part of the Braunches that so aboundantlye are increased through this ill kinde of education, and that so mightelye ouershadowe the banckes of all honesty, good order and gouernment.
            Amongst the which, as one most noysome to the Churche of God, and most hurtfull to the common Wealth, that bloody Brauerye in quarelling and fighting,

that sauadge practise in cutting and slashing, ought sharpelye and earnestlye to bée dealt withall: Which certainelye (if Magistrates doe not foresée and spéedelye reforme) I am fullye perswaded will bring more daunger to the state, then all the Lawes of the lande wil bring sauetye to the truth of mens causes. But this viperous bloody broode, this vnkinde and fierce Generation, what bloodye collours can it cast to cloake with face of manhood this more then boutcherlike kinde of behauior? Forsothe (saye they) and that with fearefull Oathes, wée are Gentlemen (I speake not nowe of common Hacksters, who are ready at al times and vpon euery slight motion to bidde battaile to al honestye and truth) and can not beare to bée abused of any man liuing: Who in déede, if they were right Gentlemen, would rather bée induced quietlye to put vppe the force of tenne Iniuryes, than witleslye and cruellye with rashnesse to pursue the reuengement of one, to the disturbance of the good peace of the Realme, to the sheadding of blood, and to the ouerthrowe of all good orders and pollicye.
            
               But to discende into the particular displaying of the manifolde Braunches that are daylye sprong vppe and increased from and by the meanes of this ill kinde of education of Sonnes, and not least of all from this one vayne of Saucines boldnes and libertye, wherevnto they are let loose without all respect of tyme and al regarde of Age: As I should take vppon mée a worcke infinite in it selfe, so, shoulde I conclude nothing elles in the same, but matter of sharpe and bitter reproofe vnto Parentes and Magistrates, who, of so many and great abuses so infinitelye arysing and so outragiouslye encreasing with continuaunce, no one doe preuent, no one doe suppresse, no one at all doe restraine, or appease.
            Wherefore, that I maye finishe, beholde thou Realme of Englande, thou olde Bruitish Nation, whome sometimes Forrein Peoples haue honoured for thy pietye, beholde I saye what is thy state, bethincke thy selfe of thine impietye, sée howe thou razest the walles of Christ his true Churche, consider thy horrible sinnes and offences, perpende thy contempt of

Gods diuine trueth, that heauenly Manna, and glad tidinges of the Gospell: sée, see how thou heapest vp wrath against thy selfe in ye day of thy visitaciō. If euer thou soughtest the meane to repentaunce, now cal for it, nowe séeke it, and with penitent prayer, craue it at the handes of thy déere Father: Now, now I say looke about thée, nowe is it high time: euen nowe (O Englande) is it most néedefull, when God as thou seeist, doeth plague for sinne euen all thy neyghbours about thée, and stayeth his angre towardes thée, deferreth his scorge, and withholdeth his indignation.
            If the excéeding and superabundant mercyes of thy God will not reclame thée, if his wonderfull benefites will not moue thée: If his great loue, and more then fatherly kindnes wyl not perswade thée, nor the extreame iudgement withdrawe thée: yet (as one of thy sinfull members). I beséeche thée, and as thou regardest thy good and quiet state, as thou desirest to auoyde thine owne desolation, thy vtter fall and ruine, I exhort thée that thou consider howe gréeuously thy brethren about thée, euen borderers on thy countrey &amp; neyghbors

to thy Nation, are deuoured of monsters, are murthered by Tirants, are persecuted, burnte, bayted, boyled, scourged, racked, paunched, pined, torne in peeces, and violently drawen vnto straunge, horrible and feareful kindes of death by their false brethren, Iudaical Traytours, execrable Papistes, cursed shauelinges and damnable sect of deuillishe Dunses. O, beholde the tragical and most gréeuous state of thy afflicted brethren in Fraunce, thy friends in Flaunders, and thy neyghbors in Scotland. Sée see (O England) how theyr sinnes haue heaped vp so mightelye the indignation of God against them, that the greatest reliefe whiche they finde, is spéedy death, and quicke dispatche of theyr irckesom &amp; miserable liues. Sée I say, and behold howe for contempt of Gods most holy Gospel, they are miserably afflicted &amp; plagued: how for theyr negligence in building, they are tormented and punished.
            And (O thou Realme of England) what hast thou to pleade for thy selfe in this case? what lawful excuse canst thou make for thy selfe? Hast thou not Iesus Christ the chiefe corner stone? Hast thou not his

blessed worde, fro whence necessarie matter maye bée ministred for the quickening of thy barren, drie and vnconstaunt faith? Hast thou not the same Fayth moystened by his long and excéeding great benefites? What wouldest thou more? His verye elect, his Apostles &amp; most familiar friendes haue not enioyed so great oportunitye by the thousand part, as thou hast at this day. They had no rest in theyr blessed bodyes, nor quietnes in theyr Sacred mindes. They wanted bothe place of assemblye, where they might heare and teache, and also place of reliefe where they might bée shrowded from theyr manifold &amp; exceding great number of enemies: whiche euen cōtinually laye in waite to spil theyr most innocent blood, and onely for the professiō of Christ and his sacred Gospel. Thou (contrarye wise) hast not onely the Gospell reuealed, but also hast libertye to Preache and to heare the same. Thou art not onelye defended from the enemie, but also hast the same vnto thy selfe in subiection. To conclude, thy wealth, thy goodes, and elles what so euer thou hast, is not onelye protected from ruine and

spoyle, but also thy Ritches, thy substance and prosperitye is mightelye blessed, and most amplye enlarged: All whiche being so, alas what remaineth for thée to pleade in defence?
            O thincke therefore of thy God, or at the least wise, tremble at thy state. Feare, feare I saye, and repent: Pleasure wil not preserue thée: Ritches will not saue thée: Honour wil not shielde thée: Aucthoritye maye not helpe thée: Renowme can not acquite thée. Awaye therefore with thy pleasure: abandon thy Ritches: contempne thine estate: Seeke not to beare rule: come downe to the lowest. It is good for thée to humble thy selfe: and most needefull it is to laye holde on the time. Though time bée infected, yet let it not passe thée. The time shall come, and is euen now come, wherin neyther time nor trade at al shalbe. And euen in this extremitye of time, thou shalt desire the mountaines to couer thée, and the Hilles to fal vpon thée, and shalt not escape. Binde not therfore one sinne too another, for one of them shal not bée vnpunished: Euerye man in his vocation shake of this Lethargye,
               
and awake out of sléepe: You Pastors, you Preachers, and spirituall builders of this heauenlye Tabernacle, set to your handes: away with ambicion, away with security, and aboue al thinges, let not couetousnes bee raygning amongst you. As you haue regard to the sauing of soules (which is chéefest) so forget not, therewith al to minister reliefe to the bodies oppressed and in néede: bée glad to distribute: doe good vnto al men, and especially to such as are of the housholde of Faith: and in any wise preache not for temporal prefermēt or gaine. Call to minde how Gehasi, Helias seruaunt was striken with Leprosie for receyuing of money in reward of his Maisters dutye:2. Regū. 5. Whereby you maye see howe detestable a thing it is in the sight of god to haue ministers of couetous minds. On the other side, you Magistrates, and temporal Rulers, down with al falsehood, let Lawe haue his force, let Iustice take place, let vertue bée ayded, let vice bee suppressed. Haue alwayes before your eyes the Touche stone of truth, which is the booke of Gods worde, and let not Bribes ouercome you, nor fauour entise you, nor

feare dismay you, nor affection withdraw you. And aboue all things, defende with all force the Gospell of Christ, and the power of the Scriptures: regarding therewithall the defence of his Preachers, the safegarde of his Ministers, and the maintenaunce of their estate. Plucke not from them, catch not from them: defraude them not. If they shake but the dust of their héeles against you, you shall neuer be able to aunswere it. Tyre and Sydon shalbe in better case then such of you shalbe at the dreadfull and extreame iudgement of soules and bodies. Consider howe Ioseph being put in aucthoritye, did make it for a lawe ouer the land of Egypt, that Pharao should haue the first part, except the lande of the Priestes, which was not Pharaos. To conclude, euen al you that cal vpon the name of Iehouah, that worship Christ in the deity, that haue spiritual feeling, &amp; that take vpō you the name of Christians: Away with negligēce, away with prating, awaye with hipocrisye, and put from you contempt of the Scriptures, by the which and according to the knowledge whereof, you shalbe Iudged, and that very shortly.
            
               Auoyde wicked companye, eschewe fained Brethren, and flye farre from the sinfull. If any that is called a brother, bée a fornicator,Corinth. 5. or couetous, or an Idolator, or rayler, or a drunckard, or an extorcioner, with such kéepe not company: nor vntil he repēt, haue any felowship at al with him. Feare not to doe wel: but bée afraid to doe euill. Maugre the head of the Deuill, doe wel: do well, &amp; cease not, doe wel I say, because it is gods wil that you should do wel: ye men séeing your wel doing, may glorifie your father which is in heauen. Of sinne commeth death: Of wel doing cōmeth life, the firme rewarde (although not for good deedes, yet) of wel doing. Bée not caryed away with pleasure, nor discoraged in sorrow. Forget not in prosperity: ne faint ye in aduersitye. The one cometh of too much cōfidence, ye other of dispayre: If thou haue welth, vse ye same to the profite of thy brethren, to the reliefe of the néedye, &amp; in due distribution. If thou haue scarsitye, or other affliction what soeuer, repine not ther at, neyther by sinistre meanes séeke to amēd thine estate: grudgingly refuse it not, nor frowardlye wishe thou of thy selfe, to auoide it. Remember how the Children of

Israel séeking without paines to come to the Lande of promise,Exod. 3. receyued not onely a more tedious wayte of trauayle and paines: but also (euen all of them except Iosua and Caleb) were quite and cleane excluded from that place so desired.
            Finally, you that be Parents, haue a special regard to the bringing vp of your children: Let theyr education be godly, &amp; theyr yong yéeres not carelesse: remēbring euermore that childers Children are ye crowne of the elders, and the glorye of theyr Fathers. Let your Sonnes haue correction,Prou. 13. and your Daughters be bridled: Teache them the commandementes of God, and haue regard to their waies: that your sōns may florishe, &amp; your Daughters bée fruitfull: by the one to haue Iustice, &amp; by the other, increase of housholdes &amp; people: Let them learne obedience, &amp; walke in humilitye: Let theyr vertues aduance them, and truth stil defend them: Let them marry for vertue and not for promotion: That that whiche hath béene, and is at this daye cryed out vppon in all places, maye nowe at the laste bée reformed: that no more it bee sayde, you sell your Daughters for money, as men sel their horses and shéepe:

That Matrimony no more bée accounted to Halte, nor Whoredome a pleasure: That earth maye bée peopled, and heauen styl enlarged: That wee maye staye (euen nowe at the last) the riottous race of our damnable liuing: And that to vs it bee not spoken, as it was sometimes sayd to the children of Israel. The people turneth not vnto them that smite them, neyther doe they seeke the Lord of hoastes: Therfore vvill the Lorde cutte from them in one daye, euen head and Taile, Braunche and Tvvig, the auncient and the honourable? Man is the head, the Prophete that Preacheth lyes, is the taile: for the leaders of the people do cause them to erre, and they that are led by them, are deuoured. Therefore vvill the Lord haue no pleasure in theyr yong men, nor. pitie theyr Fatherlesse and vvidovves. For euerye one is an hipocrite and vvicked, and euery mouth speaketh lyes.
            
         
         
            
               
               ¶ A Compendious fourme of education, to be diligently obserued of all Parentes and Scholemaisters in the trayning vp of their Children and Schollers in learning.
               ¶ Gathered into Englishe meeter, by Edward Hake.
               
            
            
               
               
               To maister Iohn Harlowe his approoued friende.
               
                  
                     AFter that the right honourable the Lord chiefe Iustice of the common plees had permitted vnto me the othe of an Attourney, thereby admitting me into the number of Attourneys in the common place, it vvas persvvaded vnto me by certain good friends of mine, for that the name of an Attourney in the common place is novv a dayes grovven into contempt, vvhether in respect of the multitude of thē, whiche is great besides an huge rable of Pettipractizers, or rather Petifoggers, dispersed into euerye corner of this Realme, or vvhether in respect of their loose and levvde dealinges, vvhich are manifolde, Or vvhether in both those respectes I knovve not: I say, it vvas for this cause persvvaded vnto me, to dedicate a litle time wholy and altogether to my professed studies of the common Lavves, that I might therby the better enable my selfe to do good in that calling. VVherevpon, resoluing my selfe determinately to follovve that purpose, I thought it conuenient to seclude from me all those forreine exercises

vvhich might any vvayes seeme to repugne, or to be (as it were) a proposito aliena.
               
               But (as in those my studies prefixed) being tied vnto solytarinesse in the Countrey, vvhich for my lot, hath hapned vnto me by mariage, after a vvhile I perceiued that, vvanting (as I there did) the benefite of mine accustomed conference, it vvas impossible for me, vvithout some exercise of the minde, to cōtinue, or vvith profite to go forvvarde in the same. In vvhich respect, I contented my selfe (betvvixt vvhiles and for recreation sake) to resort vnto mine accustomed exercise, but so, as (if it might be) some profite might redound therof vnto others.
               And happening by good lucke vpon a certaine Latine booke intituled, De pueris statim ac liberaliter instituendis, I gathered compendiously out of the same (as not being able to allovve my selfe time enough from my said studies, to accomplish the part of a Translatour) such certaine summary documents as might seeme sufficient to frame an orderly and good forme of education: vvhich also I haue turned into English meter and that for these tvvo causes especially: First, for that prose requireth a more exact labour then meeter doth, and could not haue been enterprised vvithout

going through the vvhole booke, vvhervnto my small allovvaunce of time (as is aforesayde) coulde not be aunsvverable. Secondly, because meeter vnto the vnlearned (vvhom I heartily vvish to be follovvers of this booke) doth seeme a great deale more pleasaunt then prose, and doth mitigate (as it vvere) the harshnes of the matter.
               VVhich litle booke I do offer vnto you (my approued friend) as a token of my good vvyll, in vvhom, as in my selfe, I do perceiue a special loue not onely vnto this, but also vnto euery other good forme of education: as being trained vp (together vvith me your poore scholefellow) vvith the instructions of that learned and exquisite teacher, Maister Iohn Hopkins, that vvorthy Schoolemaister, nay rather, that most vvorthy parent vnto all children committed to his charge of education: Of vvhose memory if J should in such an oportunity as this is, be forgetful, J might iustly be accompted the most vnthankefull person in the vvorld, considering that I haue franckly tasted of his goodnes in this behalfe: that (if it be not vnseemely so to vvishe) vvould to God J had liued at his feete euen dayes and yeres longer then J did. But to returne, in respect onely of good vvyll and

loue, I send vnto you these fevv quaiers, praying you to accept the same in equal part, resorting indifferentlye vnto the consideration of those common affections of loue, vvhich are vvont rather patiently to beare reproche, that any vvayes to lye hyd and vnknovven vnto the party so beloued. VVherein I rest.
               
                  
                     ¶Your owne assuredlye Edvvarde Hake.
               
            
            
               
               
                  ❧To the Reader.
               WHat age in Infantes is requirde,
               or ere they should bée taught,
               What sort of Teachers best agrées,
               what Schooles bée good, what naught,
               Dewe meanes also t'instruct them well,
               all these good Readers here
               Within this booke (though smal to vewe)
               in largest wise appeare.
               With other matters incident,
               which to my simple skill,
               For thy delite, I haue discourste
               and written with good will.
               My meaning doe accept for good:
               but pardon thinges amisse.
               So shall my penne for thy behoofe
               write greater thinges then this.
            
            
               
               
                  ❧The Speakers. Philopas. Chrisippus.
               
               
                  
                     CHrisippus, in these careles dayes
                  wherin the blinde are bolde
                  To force with wordes the truth of thinges:
                  wherin each man doth hold
                  His owne deuise for reasons rule,
                  his will for perfect lawe,
                  Wherein eache one accountes his words
                  for depthe of learned sawe:
                  What thinkst thou in this case of mine,
                  shoulde Infantes tender yéeres
                  Bee trained vp and taught in booke
                  eare wanton Childhood weares,
                  Or staye til time of greater strength,
                  that they then better maye
                  Bee able to sustaine the toyle
                  that learning lookth for aye?
                  And whereby theyr so tender sence
                  more capable maye growe,
                  To bring foorth fruite of better thinges
                  which carefull skill shall sowe?
                  Of truth, it séemthe, twere best that I
                  my litle sonne at home
                  Should keepe a while in childishe race
                  and suffer him to rome,
                  
                     To playe the wanton yet a while
                  vntill such time as hée
                  Through helpe of yéeres may labor beare
                  and more capations bée.
               
               
                  Chrisippus
                  ¶Philopas, I perceaue in you
                  as in eache father nowe:
                  You wishe for fruite of tender soyle
                  and yet forbeare the plowe.
                  At first, at first Philopas, when
                  the minde is voyde of cares,
                  When heape of vice for want of place
                  the witte of wanton spares,
                  While tender age is tractable
                  while minde is apte to take
                  Eache good precept, and it retaine,
                  then then your entraunce make.
                  For olde men nought remember but
                  suche thinges they learnde in youth:
                  If good therefore bée graft in time,
                  good fruite thereof ensuthe.
                  Estéeme for naught the wordes of suche,
                  as holde that infantes age
                  Hath neyther strength to wade with pain
                  ne witte for learning sage.
                  For first of all,Memory chiefly regarded to the obta
                           •
                        
                        ning of learning. thentraunce vnto
                  learning doeth consist
                  In memorye aboue the rest:
                  and all men well it wiste
                  
                     That Children haue the aptest wittes
                  both to retaine and holde.
                  To supple waxe the seale doth sticke,
                  not so to waxe that's olde.
                  And for so muche as nature hath
                  to learning vs begotte,
                  Why should wée thinke ye learnde to sone
                  that nature thinketh not?
                  Why should we déeme the study rashe
                  of that same thing to bée
                  Whereof by Nature séedes are sowne
                  in eache yong Babe we sée?
                  Dame Nature in our mindes hath sowne
                  the knowledge of eache thing:
                  Why shoulde wée then make nice those bloomes
                  to better state to bring?
                  Besides al this some thinges there bée
                  though néedeful to bée knowne
                  Of elder sort, yet those in Babes
                  more easilye are sowne
                  And soner setled than in such
                  as are of riper time
                  As Christ crosse rowe the skill of tongues
                  fine tales and Catoes rime.
                  For briefe, why is that age estéemde
                  for learning so vnfitte
                  Whiche all men sée so apte and prone
                  good nourture for to gette?
                  
                     Naye, what wyl children sooner doe
                  which once haue power to chatte
                  When as they sée no remedye,
                  than styll to thincke on that?
                  Howe much more profitable ist
                  that that same age shoulde bée
                  Stirde vp with learning than with toyes,
                  so meane haue his degree?
                  For if the Childe haue sense to learne
                  lewde thinges and trisles vaine,
                  Then thinck the same hath sense likewise
                  to learning so againe
                  For as vpon newe white lymde walles
                  Men painte what likes them best
                  (Béet good or ill:) so sure it standes
                  with Infantes tender brest.
                  At first (I saye) eare cares come on,
                  eare vice beginne to growe,
                  Let children learne. Such séedes encrease
                  as men in time shall sowe.
                  Unto the sheepes newe shorne fléese
                  whereon no dye hath fall.
                  You maye such perfect collour cast
                  as likes you best withall.
               
               
                  Philopas
                  Alas Chrisippus, small it is
                  (God wotes) that Children can
                  By helpe of tender sence obtaine:
                  and (praye) what bootes it than
                  
                     Therfore the same into theyr heades
                  which they can not retaine?
                  Nowe in good soothe, it seemth to mée
                  but trauaile spent in vaine.
               
               
                  Chrisippus
                  ¶Swéete licour may preserued bée
                  as well in brittle glasse
                  As in the pot framde out of stone
                  or vessell made of Brasse.
                  And why should sclender gaine bée lost?
                  to little geue you more:
                  And so shall litle gaine in time
                  increase aboundant store.
                  At least this profite shall ensue
                  to them through studies toyle,
                  Theyr mindes shal haue no place for vice
                  which tender skill doeth foyle.
                  For nothing better occupieth
                  the busye minde of man
                  Then earnest studye wrought with toyle
                  though happing now and than.
                  And sure, this gaine ought not to bée
                  contempnde in any wise:
                  For what though weake the body bée?
                  the witte to strength shall ryse.
                  And then the losse is counteruailde,
                  who would not rather craue.
                  Some losse of strength than losse of witte,
                  if wishing hée might haue?
                  
                     Nayth'lesse it is not ment to make
                  tough Champions of the same:
                  But only for the common weale,
                  good gouernours to frame.
                  Whereto their childish strength wil serue
                  and well suff
                        •
                     saunt be:
                  Far weaker state then Milos strength,
                  will therevnto agrée.
                  And yet if daunger ought appeare,
                  through pressing of the minde:
                  Why should not such as haue the charge,
                  some present easement finde?
                  Let nothing stoppe the care of skill,
                  and learning to be hadde:
                  It forceth not for lacke of game,
                  let little childe be sadde.
                  But parents fondely fray their sonnes,Abuse of fonde Parentes.
                  
                  from toyle that study craues:
                  Though vilely they neglect such things,
                  as bring them to their graues.
                  As filthy surfets in their meate,
                  wherethrough to them doe grow
                  Not only in the body hurt,
                  but in the minde also.
                  They bring their infantes vnto feastes
                  of straunge and diuers foode:
                  In banquets that tyll midnight last,
                  their presence doth them good.
                  
                     With salt and fresh they fill their gorge
                  with hote and colde aleeke,
                  Untill the stomacke ouerchargde,
                  through vomite ease doth séeke.
                  They pinche and crooke their bodies in,
                  the little corps they straine
                  With garments far vnméete such age,
                  and to be thought as vaine.
                  They cocke them vp with coates of pryde
                  they vse them for their squires,
                  They make them Cockneies in their kind
                  and Apes in their attires.
                  Not any wayes more tenderly
                  they doe mistrust their strength,
                  Then when they should be set to schoole,
                  and brought to booke at length.
                  Moreouer parents there be some
                  which when (in tender age)
                  They heare their children likde for ought,
                  they streight their state presage.
                  This child saith one wil proue wel learnd:
                  then sayth the father, sure,
                  I will for him some Prebende or
                  some Prouostship procure.
                  Or else I trust to sée him rise
                  to tipe of high degrée:
                  To be some Iudge, some man of lawe,
                  or man of dignitie.
                  
                     This childe sayth one will make a man,
                  sée how his limmes be pight?
                  The father straight way saith: this childe
                  shall be a courtly knight.
                  Thus thus, to wish in swathing bands
                  before the childe can speake,
                  They thinke it not to soone at all:
                  yet if a man man should breake
                  With them to haue that child brought vp,
                  and traind in learning so,
                  As he with skill might vse such thinges
                  as vnto him might gro,
                  They aunswere that he is to young,
                  though wordes be vtter plaine:
                  Of truth of truth (Philopas) I
                  adiudge these men but vaine.
                  As for the wordes that mothers vse,
                  my childe hath how to liue,
                  He shall (I trust) a liuing get
                  although he neuer giue
                  Himselfe vnto such néedelesse toyle
                  and trauell at his booke:
                  I force them not, they are but fonde,
                  good grounde they neuer tooke.
                  But let me sée? to aunswere here,
                  (for so I thinke it best)
                  These foolish wordes whereon their fond
                  opinion is increast.
                  
                     Shée sayth hir childe hath how to liue:
                  what, how to lyue right well?
                  Naye, there a strawe. I toulde you I
                  the mother cannot tell.
                  What néedeth lawe or logicque ought,
                  (sayth shée) er else such like?
                  My sonne hath landes whereon to liue:
                  hée néedth no learning séeke.
                  And hath he so in déede good wife?
                  what, shall he haue such staye?
                  So much the more he learning néedth,
                  to shield him from decaye.
                  The larger that the ship is framde,
                  and frayghted vp with wares:
                  So much the more vndoubtedly
                  should be the shipmans cares.
                  Yea, and so much the more it néedth,
                  a Stéers man hauing skill:
                  Thorow want of whom ye frayghted ship,
                  falth into daunger still.
                  Farre, far, therefore more bountifull
                  is he that learning giues,
                  Then he that yeldeth heapes of coyne
                  whereon the body liues.
                  Which Alexander great declares,
                  if I were not (quoth hée)
                  King Alexander, then I wish,
                  
                     Diogenes to bée.
                  
                     Wherefore, to fine this long discourse,
                  lette infancy be taught:
                  And euen such for whome great wealth
                  hath great preferment wrought.
               
               
                  Philopas.
                  ¶ Of truth Chrisippus, worthyly
                  you haue dilated this.
                  Now tell me whether priuate schoole
                  or publicke better is.
               
               
                  Chrisippus
                  ¶ Philopas to discourse this poynt▪
                  
                  what scooles were best to bée:
                  Fewe wordes shal néede the case is cléere:
                  all men may plainely sée
                  That many sooner are reformed
                  by the feare of one,
                  Then one instructed perfitly,
                  by onely one alone.
                  Wherefore I thinke there eyther ought
                  to be no schoole at all.
                  Or else that that same scoole should be
                  a scoole ingenerall.
                  Saue first to tell you by the way,
                  that common scooles require:
                  Such onely as haue gaind their grounds,
                  and greater things desire.
                  For why, where sundry sortes of wits,
                  are linckt in scooles degree,
                  There generall teaching must be vsdè,
                  wherewith all though we sée
                  
                     Some speciall wittes to profit well
                  and gather skill thereby,
                  Yet common sorte cannot therewith
                  the sondry poyntes espie.
                  But as the mayster holdeth on,
                  as néedes he must his course,
                  So doth the scholler still sticke fast
                  and growe from ill to worse.
               
               
                  Philopas.
                  ¶Declare this one thing more I pray.
                  if greater profit growe
                  Through many teachers to a childe,
                  or greater else through fewe.
               
               
                  Chrisippus
                  ¶ As parents ought most carefully
                  herein to make their choyse:
                  And as they ought most earnestly
                  to heare the common voyce,
                  And knowe report of him whome they
                  doe choose t'instruct their childe:
                  Euen so (no lesse) their héede shoulde be,
                  (least hope be soone beguilde)
                  That many teachers they refuse:
                  
                     
                        Multitudo Imperatorū 
                           
                              •
                           ariam 
                              •••
                           didit.
                     for (as the prouerbe is)
                  The country Caria was destroyd
                  in such a case as this.
                  So many men, so many wittes,
                  
                     
                        Quot homines tot 
                              ••••
                           entiae.
                     younge infantes are dismayde
                  When that the thing they learne to daye
                  to morrow are vnsayde.
                  
                     To séeke for reasons in this case,
                  no reason vrgeth so:
                  Suffiseth me to haue that proofe
                  that practizde parents know.
                  Yet one thing needely must I ope:
                        Tradendi ratio.
                     
                  
                  the onely meane to teache,
                  How neyther rough nor weery way
                  should tender mindes appeache,
                  For why, at first this infants age
                  with flattery shoulde be traynd,
                  Bycause it hath not skill to knowe
                  what proffite may be gaynd.
                  What honor, fruite, what dignity,
                  what pleasure in the ende
                  May happe to such as haue delyght
                  to learnings lore to bende.
                  Which both the maysters gentlenesse,
                  and eake the schollers witte,
                  For both their partes, may bring to passe,
                  and driue the paine from it.
                  For nothing is more profitlesse,
                  nought looseth labour more,
                  Than whan the maysters cruell trade
                  doth feare the childe before.
                  And make him hate or ere he know
                  wherefore it should be looude.
                  So loue to booke which should be first,
                  through feare is first remooude.
                  
                     The first degree to lerning is,
                  the scoole mayster to loue:
                  Whereby it comes to passe in time,
                  as skilfull teachers proue,
                  That li
                        •
                     tle childe which loued first
                  his booke for maysters sake:
                  In time through loue to learning doth,
                  like loue to mayster take.
                  For as those giftes are loued most,
                  which come from those we loue:
                  So babes that know not why to loue.
                  for maysters cause doe loue.
                  
                     Isocrates hath rightly sayd,
                  that he doth learne most,
                  That hath the most desire to learne,
                  and thinkes no labour lost.
                  And as to learne, we learne best
                  of those we best doe loue:
                  So loue to mayster is the cause,
                  that loue to booke doth moue.
                  For parents euen themselues cannot
                  preuaile if they shall vse
                  To breake them all by feare and force
                  and gentle meanes refuse.
                  Much lesse the maister may through feare
                  through foule and froward meane.
                  Once worke a will vnto the booke,
                  but soone vndoe it cleane.
                  
                     The chiefe regarde is to be looud,
                  then feately doth succéede,
                  No feare, but frindely reuerence,
                  which (to define indeede)
                  Hath greater charge then cause of feare,
                  hath care to shielde fro shame:
                  Hath doubt to drag and drawe behind,
                  not feare to suffer blame.
                  How yll therefore doe they foresée,
                  the safetie of their childe▪
                  
                  The bewtifying of his braines
                  with skill and maners milde
                  That tourne him in his tender age,
                  to gastly mazing scoole:
                  Where thronizd sits a mayster straunge
                  blunt, rude, and halfe a foole.
                  Oftetimes infected with disease,
                  inueterate and olde:
                  Which makes the waywarde testie foole
                  with little lambes to skolde.
                  And surely, we doe sée there can
                  be none so abiect fooles
                  So base and voyde of sence, but now,
                  men vse them for their schooles.
                  And thinke them meete to bring vp youth▪
                  
                  to traine them at their bookes:
                  Where expert men at first doe iudge
                  them Asses by their lookes.
                  
                     And they supposing to haue got
                  a kingdome in their kinde,
                  Aduaunce themselues with feareful lookes
                  and set aloft their minde:
                  Bycause they beare a rule, but not
                  in beastes (as Terence sayth)
                  But in that age which soone (god knowth)
                  a little terrour frayth.
                  A man woulde saye it were no schoole
                  but slaughter house in déede,
                  Whence sauing stripes and roaring out,
                  no learning doth procéede.
                  What else is this than soone to fraye,
                  the silly babes from booke,
                  who wanting pleasaunt flattering words
                  none other pleasure tooke?
                  And some a man shall sooner kill
                  then mende with cruell blowes,
                  Where he by fayre and quiet meanes
                  might bring to learning those.
                  But this lewde kinde of men (for truth)
                  ought not to beare the name
                  Of maysters, but of manquellors,
                  so brutish are the same.
                  And none more fell and frowarde are,
                  than those which nothing haue
                  Wherewith tinstruct and teache a childe:
                  whose doggishe déedes depraue
                  
                     The due successe of forwarde wittes:
                  whose roughnesse doth deface
                  The golden sparkes of natures giftes
                  which in the childe hath place.
                  A gentle Horse is sooner rulde
                  with sticke or litle wande
                  Then with a whippe or digging spurre
                  within the side to stande.
                  The Oxe likewise béeing to much prickt,
                  doeth soone caste of his yoke,
                  And bringes to daunger him that driues,
                  through hap of heauie stroake.
                  So men must handle forward wittes
                  as Lyons do their whelpes:
                  The huige and heauie Elephant
                  the skilfull person helps.
                  What should I saye? no beaste there is,
                  no sauage beaste in fine,
                  Whom violence will not prouoke,
                  and skill to will incline.
                  But some perhappes will here alledge
                  theise scriptures for their turne:
                  VVho spares the rodde, doth hate the childe,
                  and vvho in loue doth burne,
                        Eccless. 30.
                  
                  Doth vse the same vnto the vvhippe:
                  againe bovve dovvne in youth
                  His necke, and knocke him on the side
                  eare greater age accruthe.
                  
                     And this correction might perhaps,
                  agrée vnto the Iewes:
                  But christians to translate these wordes,
                  far otherwise doe vse.
                  That, if some one woulde binde vs now
                  vnto the letter bare:
                  What more absurdly can be sayd?
                  what wordes worse sounding are,
                  Than thus to bowe a downe the necke
                  of little children, and
                  To knocke and thumpe them on the sides
                  with sticke or with the hande?
                  What, thinkst thou yt we breake an Oxe
                  to frame him to the plowe?
                  Thinkst thou we teache an asse to beare?
                  or else that we séeke howe
                  The tender sence of silly babes
                  to bende to vertuous lore?
                  Whose slender handes with fearefull sute
                  Our fauour doth deplore.
                  Nay, let our roddes that we shall vse,
                  be admonitions mylde:
                  And if we chide, as chyde we must,
                  sée bitternesse exilde.
                  This whippe, this whippe accustome wée
                  our children still vnto:
                  That they being wel brought vp &amp; taught,
                  may learne what best to do.
                  
                     Maye finde at home an honest forme
                  of life, and neuer néede
                  To hange vpon our neyghbours sléeue
                  for counsell and for réede.
                  
                     Lycon, that olde Philosopher,
                  doth teache and well declare
                  How that to chéere vp childrens wits,
                  two spurres most sharpe there are.
                  The first is prayse, the seconde shame,
                  with which two spurs must wée
                  Toule on our children if we looke,
                  that learned they should be.
                  And now, if that you séeke to know
                  what thumps we ought to vse:
                  How we should knock our childrens sides
                  take these, the rest refuse.
                  Lets watchfull be ti'nstruct them well,
                  no labour let vs spare,
                  To teache and traine them vp to good,
                  Let that be all our care.
                  Some times to reade, and of things redde
                  againe for to require
                  A iust account: loe these be thumpes
                  that tender wittes desire.
                  First lette them learne to loue, &amp; haue
                  in admiration great,
                  Good letters and an honest lyfe.
                  Againe, with ardent heate
                  
                     Fowle ignoraunce and filthy life
                  to hate with single eye:
                  The one to loue and still to séeke,
                  the other to defie.
                  And let their eares be tyckled vp
                  to heare some one for good
                  Tenioy great prayse, and other some
                  of whome is vnderstood
                  Some lewde offence, to haue reproche
                  and still enduring shame:
                  So teache them still dame vertues prayse
                  and vices fowle defame.
                  This man (say thou) through learning skil
                  is come to high degrée:
                  This man to welth by learning, this
                  to power and dignity.
                  But this againe, through yll desert
                  through wante of learnings lore,
                  Reproche, contempt, and pouerty
                  hath gaind himselfe therefore.
                  These truely be the very battes,
                  these be the thumpes in déede,
                  That scollers of sweete Iesu Christ,
                  will take to them at néede.
               
               
                  Philopas.
                  ¶Chrisippus I doe well allow,
                  eche worde that you haue sayd:
                  And sure I thinke that gentle wittes
                  through terrour are dismayde.
                  
                     And yet to saye that ragged coltes,
                  that rude vnruely boyes
                  Wil be reclaimd through shame or praise
                  No no, they count them toyes.
                  That sauour not of smarting whippes,
                  which yet perhappes in some,
                  So neuer worckes, that they thereby
                  to goodnesse sooner come.
                  Muche lesse through fawning flattering (prayse)
                  for some much lesse doe waye
                  The losse of prayse, naye losse of skill,
                  than any losse of playe.
               
               
                  Chrisippus
                  ¶To such Philopas, vnto suche,
                  whome neyther milde request
                  Nor rough rebuke, nor prayse nor shame
                  to learning will inuest.
                  The smarting rodde (if néede so be)
                  must now and then be hadde
                  But so, as we doe coldely fight,
                  and not as we were madde.
                  Yea, bashefully we shoulde lay bare
                  their bodies when we fight:
                  For nakednesse to gentle boyes
                  if many are in sight,
                  A kinde of great reproche doth séeme▪
                  
                  and Fabius doth deny
                  That body of a gentle boy
                  in nakednesse should lye.
                  
                     But some perhaps will say to me,
                  what shall be done with those
                  Whome we to study cannot frame,
                  except it be with blowes?
                  To suche I aunswere in this wise:
                  what would you séeme to doe
                  To asses or to Oxen, if
                  they come the schoole into?
                  What? would you not soone driue them (foorth)
                  into the country soyle,
                  The one to'th milne, the other with
                  the plowe and cart to toyle?
                  And certainely, no lesse are men
                  vnto the plowstaffe borne,
                  Than is the Oxe: no lesse to'th milne,
                  than th'Asse with laboure worne.
               
               
                  Philopas.
                  ¶But so the maysters flocke decayes,
                  and therewithall his gaine.
               
               
                  Chrisippus
                  ¶Aha, there goeth the Hare away:
                  by this appeareth plaine,
                  That vnto such, farre dearer is
                  the fare of filthy méede,
                  Then is the care how they should make
                  their schollers good in déede.
                  But such no doubt, the common sorte
                  of Scholemaysters are now:
                  And yet as wise Philosophers,
                  doe flatly teache vs how
                  
                     A wiseman we should well discerne,
                  as Rhetoriciens eke,
                  An Orator doth well discribe,
                  when as they say: go séeke
                  And scarcely finde whome thou mayst call
                  a rightwise man in déede,
                  Whome thou mayst call an Orator,
                  (thereto belongth such héede:)
                  So much, and farre more harde it is
                  that we should well attone
                  What he the mayster ought to be,
                  as who should say such one
                  As scarcely may be founde the lyke:
                  such one as hardely will
                  The due prescribed forme accorde
                  or can the same fulfill.
                  But such should be the publique charge
                  of ciuill magistrates
                  And of the Ecclesiasticall:
                  yea, of the high estates,
                  That as the Souldiour trayned is,
                  and fitted for the fielde,
                  As singing men are taught to tune
                  the counteruerse they yelde:
                  So, much more should they sée that man
                  be taught, much more be traynde
                  That to the worthy teaching trade
                  hath any way attaynde.
                  
                     
                     Vespatian from his coffers gaue
                  a certaine yearely fée
                  To lerned men: that learning so
                  might well maintayned bée.
                  And Plinius Nepos did the like.
                  But if the publique care
                  Should happe to cease, then euery man
                  at home must néedes prepare
                  To haue a priuate teacher. But
                  thou sayst, how then should they
                  That are not able so to doe,
                  their children any way
                  Bring vp to learning? wherevnto
                  I nothing haue to saye
                  But this that Terence doth recorde:
                  when as we cannot doe
                  Euen as we woulde, then as we maye.
                  we shewe the trade vnto
                  Right teaching, as not able we
                  good fortune for to giue,
                  Except we wish the welthies ayde
                  to such as poorely liue.
                  Now to retourne, I doe mislyke
                  that mildenesse should expell
                  That feare and reuerence which a child
                  becommeth very well,
                  But these who nothing else doe know
                  
                     saue fiercely how to fight,
                  How would they doe if they should teache
                  Kinges children whome they might
                  Not iercke nor strike withouten blame?
                  But haplie twill be sayde
                  That children borne of noble race
                  More néerely must be wayde.
                  And is thy sonne or mine in fayth
                  lesse man then any they?
                  Is not eache fathers childe thinkst thou
                  as deere to him, and gaye,
                  As if the same a Kinges sonne were?
                  If fortune be but base,
                  Then learning and good bringing vp
                  must helpe releeue his case.
                  Contrariwise if welthy porte
                  doe happen to his lotte,
                  Then wisdome helpth to guide his welth,
                  and shielde his name from blotte.
                  And though we haue not welth by birth
                  though so not honors glée
                  Nor office, nor renowme, yet sure
                  thereto brought vp we be.
                  And here I leaue to brawle and chyde,
                  with cruell maysters: here
                  I wholy ende that poynt: so as
                  this one thing may appere:
                  
                     Namely, that lawes and magistrates
                  condemned are to be
                  Which euer séeke with paine to pinche,
                  and neuer doe agrée
                  T'allure with pleasures and reward:
                  which ponish still but so,
                  As they ne warne the fault whereby
                  the ponishment doth growe.
                  Right so I thinke of that same sort,
                  that common sort I say,
                  Of schoolemaysters which onely séeke
                  their silly boyes to paye,
                  To beate and bounse them for their faults
                  and not t'instruct their minde
                  So as they may both see and know
                  from what offence to winde.
                  Wherein I ende remembring this,
                  that in eche exercise
                  Our mindes delight is chiefest cause
                  that we to skill arise.
                  Lo, here Philopas, you haue hearde,
                  what qualities are méete
                  For him that shall instruct a childe
                  againe, what thinges vnféete,
                  Are wisely to be lookde vnto,
                  and in the same foreséene:
                  Whereby you may auoyde such faultes,
                  as heretofore haue beene
                  
                     Neglected in that kinde of men.
                  the scoolemayster you sée,
                  To winne the childe, should séeme a child
                  and childe againe shoulde be.
                  And yet I wholy doe mislyke
                  that that same crooked age
                  Wherein the second childhood dwelth▪
                  
                  should take the roome of sage
                  Instructors: for such men in truth
                  are children euery deale:
                  They faine not childehoode but in truth
                  they childehoode doe reueale.
                  They doe not seeme to stamber, but
                  they stamber plaine in deede.
                  I wish such men to be displast
                  and youngmen to succéede.
                  And howe this young man now shoulde (deale)
                  what forme the same should vse,
                  What meanes to teach he shoulde retaine
                  and what againe refuse,
                  This resteth here to be discust:
                  and as the proofe doth finde,
                  None otherwise the same should deale
                  in forming of the minde,
                  Then skilfull Nourse or parents deale
                  when they the body frame:
                  Which that he may so imitate,
                  Lo here insueth the same.
                  
                     To teache the Babe to speake, they first
                  doe tattle foorth their wordes:
                  And lispingly they frame their tongue
                  to that the babe afordes.
                  Dad dad for father first they giue,
                  and beade they teache for breade:
                  And when they teach him drinke to aske,
                  then din to him in sayde.
                  And pretily they lispe their wordes
                  Whereto it prates againe:
                  And thus at length as proofe doth teache
                  the Baby speaketh playne.
                  To teache it how to eate, they put
                  the pappe within their lippes
                  And from the spoone eftsoones they séeme
                  to drawe foorth prettie sippes.
                  Which done therwith they féede the babe.
                  And when they teache to go,
                  They bende their corpse, and frame their (pase)
                  before their infants so▪
                  
                  As what therwith, and with such meanes
                  as they with pulpits vse,
                  In time the childe hath perfite pase,
                  he can none other chuse.
                  And this thing worthy noting is,
                  their childe they neuer féede
                  With all that comes to hande, but they
                  obserue with carefull héede
                  
                     Both what to giue and howe to giue:
                  what quantity to vse:
                  And eke to féede it laysurely:
                  for if they should infuse
                  And poure it in with retchlesse handes,
                  they know they eyther should
                  Their baby choke, or at the least,
                  his cloathes woulde be fould.
                  Now therefore, as of lightest meates
                  and meates agréeing best,
                  They oft and litle giue them, so
                  the infants tender brest
                  In teaching should be framed like▪
                  
                  your selfe (Philopas) may
                  Thexample best apply, for I
                  haue something else to say.
                  You looke (I know) that I shoulde teach
                  what things do best pertayne
                  To childrens wittes: what first to learne
                  which onelye doth remaine
                  At this time to be handeled here.
                  this brieflie therefore knowe,
                  That loue vnto the lattine tongue
                  in childehood first should growe,
                  With vse thereof, which easily
                  without great studies care
                  To children comes: but hardely when
                  the same more aged are.
                  
                     Whereto (as hath bene sayde before)
                  the fables doe inuite
                  With morall sawes in couert tales:
                  whereto agréeeth rite
                  Fine Comedies with pleasure sawst,
                  which (as it were by play)
                  Doe teache vnto Philosophie
                  a perfit ready way.
                  Then sentences and prouerbs choyse
                  and Apothemes of men,
                  Wherin greate wisedome restes, wherin
                  great learning aye hath bene.
                  Which fables and which comedies
                  they better farre shall learne,
                  If once they know the arguments,
                  and summe thereof discerne.
                  The names of Trées, of plants also
                  and names of monsters straunge,
                  With natures of them finely taught,
                  doth cause their mindes to raunge,
                  To séeke abroade for farther sight
                  with longing mindes to know
                  Where this beast lines, where that birde bréedes
                  where this straunge trée doth grow.
                  In sine, it helpeth very much
                  the lattin tongue t'attaine,
                  T'associate such with whome good skill
                  in lattine doth remaine.
                  
                     Auoyding still as rockes and clyffes▪
                  
                  foule barbarous wordes to name
                  No latin rather lette them speake
                  than so to speake the same.
                  And here concluding, this I note,
                  that in the first degrée
                  Of teaching, this aboue the rest
                  must well aduerted bée.
                  That, whatsoeuer pleasaunt is,
                  what thing so euer eake
                  Is easie to be vnderstoode,
                  that children best doe lyke.
                  For surely as it is absurde
                  to looke for grapes in spring,
                  In haruest else to looke for Rose
                  or such like blooming thing:
                  So schoolemaysters must well adapt
                  such thinges as they shall teache,
                  Unto their childes capacity:
                  so as the same may reache
                  And it conceyue, with firme delight:
                  for pleasure profites much,
                  And nothing else but pleasure may
                  allure to learning such:
                  So as na'thlesse we carefull be
                  to auoyde all bawdie rimes
                  And wanton iestes of Poets vayne
                  that teache them filthye crimes.
                  Good stories from the Bible chargde
                  
                     and from some ciuil style.
                  As Quintus Curtius, and such like
                  to reade them otherwhile.
                  Where through by iust degrée of skill
                  from reading shall succéede
                  As eke of congrue vse of speach
                  a séemely forme indéede
                  Of writing well: which naythelesse
                  is difficile: but so,
                  As by the maysters skill the same
                  may farre more easie grow.
                  Rewardes he must prescribe for such
                  as shall performe their charge:
                  But such as neyther mylde request,
                  nor prayse nor promise large
                  Can bring to better forme of ski
                        •
                     
                  
                  with those, this practise he
                  Must put in vre: that is to wéete
                  though they vnlearned be,
                  To make them thinke and yet beléeue
                  themselues to be of might
                  T'encounter with the better sorte,
                  and put the same to flight.
                  And euermore we must auoyd
                  t'enioyne them thinges to harde,
                  Or things not needefull to be taught
                  or things that may be sparde.
                  For (Lorde) how are their mindes perplext
                  how troubled will they be
                  
                     When thinges they cannot vnderstande,
                  through much obscurity?
                  But though that something of it selfe
                  some hardenesse doth containe,
                  Yet may the maysters policie
                  make easie that againe.
                  For like as good phisitions that
                  doe bitter potions make,
                  With somthing swéete doe sméere the pot
                  that infauntes so may take
                  The Potion that they would haue drunke
                  whereby they are alurde
                  The same to drinke, which else to doe,
                  they coulde not be procurde:
                  Euen so the skilfull mayster ought
                  to deale in eche respect:
                  Thinges difficult with ease to teach
                  and leysure to direct.
                  And yet we may not too too much
                  mistrust our childrens strength:
                  For what they cannot learne at first,
                  that learne they at length.
                  Though strength they haue not as an Oxe
                  yet as an Ant they haue:
                  And oft vnto the Elephant
                  the little Flye doth scath.
                  Conceypt doth chiefly hurt a childe,
                  where if you make but play
                  Of things that you shall teach him, then
                  
                     Conceipt doth neuer fraye.
                  That one and onely scruple nowe
                  remaines to be discust,
                  Which many one full fondely doe
                  against all reason thrust.
                  They say the profite is so small,
                  that children doe obtaine
                  Before the same be fiue yeres olde,
                  that labour is in vayne,
                  And cost ill spent that is bestowde
                  to bring them vp to booke.
                  But these men which will this obiect.
                  these rather séeme to looke
                  More straightly to the parents purse,
                  and more to spare the paine
                  Of maisters, then to well respect
                  their little childrens gaine.
                  But graunt the profite be but small
                  admit it small in déede:
                  Take rather small than nothing yet,
                  for thats the wisemans réede,
                  And slender howsoeare it be
                  that that same age shall gaine,
                  Yet this aduauntage be you sure
                  shall thereunto remaine:
                  That greater thinges they shall atchiue
                  that yere, wherein if they
                  The smaller things had erst not learnd
                  they on the same shoulde stay.
                  
                     I néede not here repeate againe
                  that certaine thinges we sée
                  In infantes age farre better learnde
                  than when they greater bée.
                  And graunt we that they trifling are
                  and things of slender skill.
                  Yet they such tryfles first atchéeue
                  that greater thinges fulfill.
                  The painfull Crafts man makes account
                  euen of the smallest coyne,
                  For why in time, to that same small,
                  he greater store doth ioyne.
                  The Goldesmithes rise ere breake of day,
                  before they well can sée,
                  To winne some time before hand still,
                  (though nere so small it be)
                  The Plowman sometimes doth not stick
                  on dayes that holye séeme
                  To binde his sheaues, to shocke and oft
                  to set a worke his Teeme.
                  And shall we way for nothing then
                  the losse of fiue yeres time?
                  Shall we so hange on harder age,
                  that we neglect the prime?
                  When as thers nothing halfe so riche
                  as time, nor halfe so good
                  As learning is: oh nothing may
                  so high be vnderstood.
                  Here here Philopas, here should men
                  
                     most néerely pinch and spare:
                  Euen here (I saye) for losse of time,
                  shoulde be their chiefest care.
                  The husbandeman hath good regarde
                  that no part of his grounde
                  Doe lye vntilde: for looke what péece
                  vnfit for grayne is founde,
                  That he with Osiers sets and plants,
                  Or else to pasture layes:
                  And one way or another still
                  he fruite thereof doth rayse
                  Shall we permit the best part then
                  of all our time to flytte
                  Without all learnings profite had?
                  without increase of witte?
                  New fallowd grounde must néedes be (sowne)
                  with some one kinde of séede,
                  Or else (euen of it owne accorde)
                  it brings forth noisome wéede.
                  Like so the tender Infants minde,
                  except the same be taught
                  With good precepts, it will bring foorth
                  the thing that's meerely nought.
                  The minde doth eyther good things yéelde,
                  if good therein be sowne,
                  Or if thou nothing sow therein,
                  with vice tis ouergrowne.
                  And surely he not smally gaynes,
                  that vice can well eschewe:
                  
                     And he that shuts foorth vice doth not
                  to vertue least accrewe.
                  What? wilt thou know how much it helps
                  tinstruct a childe betime?
                  Why, then behold thou Ouid well:
                  marcke Lucan in his prime.
                  
                     Vrsinus but eleuen yeres olde,
                  so wonderfull was founde,
                  That straunge it is to make report,
                  how farre he did abounde
                  Great Alexander in his youth,
                  euen all the partes attainde
                  Of wisedome and Philosophie:
                  and with the same had gaynde
                  Such perfite forme of eloquence,
                  that had not kingdomes pryde
                  Withdrawne his mind from studies care
                  no man could haue denyde
                  But that amongst Philosophers
                  (the chiefest of them then)
                  Not seconde but the very chiefe
                  accounted he had bene.
                  But here to fine this long discourse,
                  your selfe Philopas I
                  Will haue to witnesse all such thinges
                  as earst haue passed by.
               
               
                  Epilogus.
                  ¶ Consider well what portion and
                  what déere possession eeke
                  A sonne is: and how flittingly
                  
                     mans minde doth knowledge séeke.
                  How wayghtie education is,
                  what hablenesse is founde
                  In tender childes capacity:
                  what quicknesse doth abounde.
                  How easily the same doth learne,
                  how Nature giues consent:
                  And how they profite most when they
                  to learned men are sent,
                  And vnto such as gentle are,
                  which teach them all by play:
                  Thinges easie first, and harder things
                  when harder thinges they may.
                  To these things adde how déere and of
                  what waight our time should be:
                  How much it helps to teache betimes,
                  what fruite thereof we see.
                  
                     Hesiodus doth flytting call
                  the wandring age of man:
                  Whose youth is busy, and whose age
                  is quite from learning gon.
                  These thinges if thou shalt well obserue,
                  sixe yeres, shall not be séene
                  Nor yet thrée yeres before thy sonne
                  which heretofore hath béene
                  Neglected (as to this intent)
                  shall eyther learning gaine.
                  Or else be well preparde at least,
                  good learning to obtayne.
               
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

