
   
      
         
            A sermon preached at St Maries in Oxford vpon Tuesday in Easter vveeke, 1617 Concerning the abuses of obscure and difficult places of holy Scripture, and remedies against them. By Iohn Hales, Fellow of Eton Colledge, and Regius Professour of the Greeke tongue in the Vniversitie of Oxford.
            Hales, John, 1584-1656.
         
         
            
               1617
            
         
         Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02497
            STC 12628
            ESTC S103638
            99839387
            99839387
            3801
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02497)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3801)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1351:04)
         
         
            
               
                  A sermon preached at St Maries in Oxford vpon Tuesday in Easter vveeke, 1617 Concerning the abuses of obscure and difficult places of holy Scripture, and remedies against them. By Iohn Hales, Fellow of Eton Colledge, and Regius Professour of the Greeke tongue in the Vniversitie of Oxford.
                  Hales, John, 1584-1656.
               
               [2], 41, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and William Wrench, printers to the famous Vniversitie,
                  At Oxford :
                  1617.
               
               
                  Running title reads: Abuses of hard places of Scripture.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-07
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-09
            Robert CosgroveSampled and proofread
         
            2005-09
            Robert CosgroveText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
SERMON
PREACHED AT St MARIES

                  〈◊〉
                OXFORD VPON
TVESDAY IN EASTER
VVEEKE, 1617.
            CONCERNING THE ABVSES
of obſcure and difficult places of holy
Scripture, and remedies againſt
them.
            By IOHN HALES,
FELLOW OF ETON COLLEDGE,
and Regius Profeſſour of the Greeke
tongue in the Vniverſitie
of Oxford.
            
            
               AT OXFORD
Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and William Wrench,
Printers to the famous Vniverſitie. 1617.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               2. PETER. 3. 16.
               Which the vnlearned and vnstable wreſt, as they doe
the other Scriptures, vnto their owne deſtruction.
            
            
               THE loue and favour which
it pleaſed God to beare our
Fathers before the law, ſo
farre prevail'd with him, as
that without any bookes &amp;
writings, by familiar and
frendly converſing with thē,
and communicating himſelfe vnto them, he made
them receaue and vnderſtand his lawes: their inward
conceits &amp; intellectualls being after a wonderfull
manner as it were Figured,
               In Pſal. 28. and Characterd,
(as St 
               Baſill expreſſes it) by his ſpirit, ſo that they
could not but ſee, and conſent vnto, and confeſſe
the truth of them. Which way of manifeſting his
will, vnto many other gracious priviledges which
it had, aboue that which in after ages came in
place of it, had this added, that it brought with it
vnto the man, to whom it was made, a preſervati
on againſt all doubt and heſitancy, a full aſſurance
both who the author was, and how farre his intent

and meaning reacht. Wee 
                  〈◊〉
                their of
               
                  ••
               ng
ought,Hom. 1. in Mat. as St 
               Chryſoſtome tells vs, fo to haue
demeand our ſelues, that it might haue been with
vs as it was with them, that 
                  〈◊〉
                might haue had
no need of writing, no other 
                  〈◊〉
                but the ſpirit,
no other books but our hearts, no other means
to haue beene taught the things of God Niſi inſpirationis
divinae internam 
                     〈…〉
                  , ubi
ſine ſonis ſermonum &amp; ſine elementis literarum, eo
dulciùs quo ſecretiùs veritas loquitur; as ſaith Fulgentius.
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,L. 3. Epiſt. 106. ſaith Iſidorus Pel
                     •
                  ſiota:
for it is a great argument of our ſhame &amp;
imperfection that the holy things are written in
bookes. For as God in anger tells the Iewes, that
he himſelfe would not goe before them as hitherto
he had done, to conduct them into the promiſed
land, but would leaue his Angell with them as
his deputie: ſo hath he dealt with vs, the vnhappy
poſteritie degenerated from the ancient puritie of
our forefathers. When himſelfe refuſed to ſpeake
vnto our hearts becauſe of the hardneſſe of them,
he then began to put his lawes in writing. Which
thing for a long time amongſt his owne people
ſeemes not to haue brought with it any ſenſible
inconvenience. For amongſt all thoſe acts of the
Iewes, which God in his booke hath regiſtred for
our inſtruction, there is not one concerning any
pretended ambiguitie or obſcuritie of the Text &amp;
Letter of their Law, which might drawe them into
faction and ſchiſme; the Divell be like hauing other

ſufficie
                  •
                advantages on which he wrought.
But ever ſince the Goſpell was committed to w
                  ••
               
               ting,
what age, what monument of the Churches
acts is not full of debate and ſtrife, concerning the
force &amp; meaning
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                thoſe writings, which the holy
Ghoſt hath left vs to be the law &amp; rule of faith?
St 
               Paul, one of the firſt penmen of the holy Ghoſt,
who in P
                  •••
               diſe 
                  〈◊〉
                wordes which it was not
lawfull for man to vtter, hath left vs words in writing,
which it is not ſafe for any man to be too buſie
to interpret. No ſooner had hee laid downe his
penne, almoſt ere the inke was drie, were there
found Syllabarum aucupes, ſuch as St 
               Ambroſe ſpake
of, qui neſcire aliquid erubeſcunt, &amp; per occaſionem
obſcuritatis tendunt laqueos deceptionis, who
thought there could be no greater diſparagement
vnto them, then to ſeeme to bee ignorant of any
thing and vnder pretenſe of interpreting obſcure
places laid gins to entrap the vncautelous: who taking
advantage of the obſcuritie of St 
               Pauls text,
made the letter of the Goſpell of life and peace,
the moſt forcible inſtrument of mortal quarrell &amp;
contention. The growth of which, the Holy
Ghoſt by the Miniſtery of St 
               Peter, hath indeavored
to cut vp in the bud, and to ſtrangle in the
wombe, in this ſhort admonition which but now
hath founded in your eares. VVhich the learned &amp;c.
In which wordes, for our more orderly proceeding,
we will conſider, Firſt, the ſinne it ſelfe that
is heare reprehēded, wreſting of Scripture: where

we will breifly conſider what it is and what cau
               
                  •••
               
and motioners it findes in our corrupt vnderſtandings,
Secondly the perſons guilty of this offence,
diſcipher'd vnto vs in two Epithets, vnlearned,
vnstable. Laſt of all the danger in the laſt
words, vnto their owne damnation. And firſt of the
ſinne it ſelfe, together with ſome of the eſpeciall
cauſes of it.
            
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . They wreſt. They deale with Scripture
as Chimickes deale with naturall bodies, torturing
them to extract that out of them which God
and nature never put in them. Scripture is a rule
which will not fit it ſelfe to the obliquitie of our
conceits, but our perverſe and crooked diſcourſe,
muſt fit it ſelfe to the ſtraightneſſe of that rule. A
learned writer in the age of our fathers,Fab
                     •
                  r. commenting
vpon Scripture ſpake moſt truely when hee
ſaid, that his Comments gaue no light vnto the text,
the text gaue light vnto his Comments. Other expoſitions
may giue rules &amp; directions for vnderſtanding
their authors, but Scripture giues rules to expoſition
it ſelfe, and interprets the interpreter.
Wherefore when wee wade in Scripture, non pro
ſententia divinarum Scripturarum, as St Auſtine
ſpeakes, ſed pro noſtra ita dimicantes vt tam velimus
Scripturarum eſſe quae noſtra eſt: When we ſtriue to
giue vnto it, and not to receaue from it the ſenſe:
when wee factiouſly contend to faſten our conceits
vpon God: and like the Harlot in the booke
of Kings, take our dead and putrified fancies, and

lay them in the boſome of Scripture as of a mother,
then are we guiltie of this great ſinne of wreſting
of Scripture. The nature of which will the
better appeare, if wee conſider a little, ſome of
thoſe motioners which driue vs vpon it. One very
potent and ſtrong meane is the exceeding affection
and loue vnto our owne opinions &amp; conceits.
For growne wee are vnto extremities on both
hands: we cannot with patience either admit of other
mens opinions, or endure that our owne
ſhould be withſtood.Scholiast. in Thucyd. As it was in the Lacedaemonian
army, almoſt all were Captaines: ſo in theſe diſputes
all will be leaders: and we take our ſelues to
be much diſcountenanced, if others thinke not as
we doe. So that the complaint which one makes,
concerning the diſſention of Phyſicians about the
diſeaſes of our bodies, is true likewiſe in theſe diſputes
which concerne the cure of our ſoules,Plinie. 
               hinc
illae circa agros miſerae ſententiarum concertationes,
nullo idem cenſente, ne videatur acceſsio alterius.
From hence haue ſprong thoſe miſerable contentions
about the diſtemper of our ſoules, ſingularitie
alone, and that wee will not ſeeme to ſtand as
cyphars to make vp the ſumme of other mens opinions,
being cauſe enough to make vs diſagree.
A fault anciently amongſt the Chriſtians ſo apparant,
that it needed not an Apoſtolicall ſpirit to
diſcover it, the very heathen themſelues to our
ſhame and confuſion, haue iuſtly, judiciouſly, and
ſharply taxt vs for it. Ammianus Marcellinus paſſing

his cenſure vpon Conſtanti
                     ••
                  
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                Emperour:
Chriſtianam religionem abſolutam &amp; ſimplicē
                (ſaith
he: and they are words very well worth your marking)
Chriſtianam religionem abſolut
                     ••
                   &amp; ſimplicē
anili ſuperſtitione confudit. In 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſcrutanda perplexiùs
quàm componenda grauiùs, excitauit diſsidia plurima,
quae progreſſa fuſiùs alu
                     •
                  t concertati
                     •
                  ne verborum,
dum ritum omnem adſu
                     •••
                   trahere conatur arbitrium.
The Chriſtian religion, a religion of great
ſimplicitie and perfection, hee troubled with dotage
and ſuperſtition. For going about rather perplexedly
to ſearch the controverſies, then grauely
to compoſe them, he raiſed great ſtirres, &amp; by diſputing
ſpread them farre and wide, whilſt he went
about to make himſelfe ſole Lord &amp; commander
of the whole profeſſion. Now (that it may appear
wherefore I haue noted this) it is no hard thing
for a man that hath wit, and is ſtrongly poſſeſt of
an opinion, and reſolute to maintaine it, to finde
ſome places of Scripture, which by good handling
will be woed to caſt a favourable coūtenance
vpon it. Pythagoras Schollers hauing beene bred
vp in the doctrine of numbers, when afterward
they diverted vpon the ſtudies of nature, fancied
vnto themſelues ſomewhat in naturall bodies like
vnto numbers, and therevpon fell into a conceit
that numbers were the principles of them. So
fares it with him that to the reading of Scripture
comes forepoſſeſt with ſome opinion. As Antipheron
Ori
                     •
                  tes in Ariſtotle thought that every

where hee ſaw his owne ſhape and picture going
afore him: ſo indivers parts of Scripture where
theſe men walke, they will eaſily perſwade themſelues
that they ſee the image of their owne conceits.
It was, &amp; is to this day, a faſhion in the hotter
countries, at noone, when the ſunne is in his
ſtrength, to retire themſelues to their Cloſets or
beds, if they were at home, to coole &amp; ſhadie places
if they were abroad, to avoid the inconvenience
of the heat of it. To this the Spouſe in the
Canticles alluding, calls after her beloued, as after
a ſhepheard: Shew me, O thou whom my ſoule loueth,
where thou feedeſt thy flocke, where thou doſt reſt at
noone. The Donatists conceiting vnto themſelues
that the Church was ſhut vp in them alone; being
vrged by the fathers to ſhew how the Church
being vniverſall, came on a ſuddaine thus to bee
cōfinde to Africke: they had preſently their Scripture
for it: for ſo they found it written in the Canticles:
Indica, quem diligit anima mea, vbi paſcas, vbi
cubes in meridie. In which text, meridies doubtleſſe
as they thought, was their Southerne countrie of
Africke, where the ſhepheard of Iſraell was, and
no where elſe, to feed his flockes. I may not trouble
you with inſtances in this kinde: little obſervation
is able to furniſh the man of ſlendreſt reading
with abundance. The texts of Scripture which are
eſpecially ſubiect to this abuſe, are thoſe that are
of ambiguous and doubtfull meaning. For as Thucydides
obſerues of the fat and fertile places of

Greece, that they were evermore the occaſions
of ſtirres and ſeditions; the neighbouring nations
every one ſtriuing to make it ſelfe Lord of them:
ſo is it with theſe places that are ſo fertile, as it
were, of interpretation, and yeeld a multiplicity of
ſenſe: they are the Palastra for good wits to proue
maſteries in, where every one deſires to bee Lord
and abſolute.
            A ſecond thing occaſioning vs to tranſgreſſe againſt
Scripture, and the diſcreet and ſober handling
of it, is our too quicke and ſpeedy entrance
vpon the practiſe of interpreting it, in our young
and greene yeares, before that time &amp; experience
haue ripened vs and ſetled our conceits. For that
which in all other buſineſſe, and here likewiſe doth
moſt eſpecially commend vs, is our cautelous and
wary handling it. But this is a flower ſeldome ſeen
in youths garden. Ariſtotle differencing age and
youth, makes it a propertie of youth, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
to ſuppoſe they knowe all things
and to be bold in affirming: and the heathen Rhetorician
could tel vs, that by this ſo ſpeedy entring
vpon action, and ſo timely venting our crude and
vnconcocted ſtudies, quod eſt vbi
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   pernicioſiſsimū,
praevenit vires fiducia, a thing which in all caſes is
moſt pernicious, preſumption is greater then
ſtrength, after the manner of thoſe, who are lately
recoverd out of ſome great ſickneſſe, in whome
appetite is ſtronger then digeſtion. Theſe are they
who take the greateſt myſteryes of Chriſtian religion

to bee the fitteſt arguments to ſpend themſelues
vpon. So Eckius in his Chryſopaſſus, a worke
of his ſo tearmed, wherein he diſcuſſes the queſtion
of predeſtination, in the very entrance of his
worke tells vs, that hee therefore enterpris'd to
handle this argument, becauſe forſooth hee
thought it to be the fitteſt queſtion in which hee
might luveniles calores exercere. The ancient Maſters
of ſence amongſt the Romans were wont to
ſet vp a poſt, and cauſe their young Schollers to
practiſe vpon it, and to foine and fight with it, as
with an adverſarie. Inſteed of a poſt, this young
fencer hath set himſelfe vp one of the deepeſt myſteries
of our profeſſion to practiſe his freſhmanſhip
vpon. Which qualitie when once it findes
Scripture for his obiect, how great inconvenience
it brings with it, needs no large diſcourſe to
proue. St 
               Ierome, a man not too eaſily brought on
to acknowledge the errours of his writings, amongſt
thoſe few things which hee doth retract,
cenſures nothing ſo ſharply as the miſtake of his
youth in this kinde. In adoleſcentia provocatus ardore
&amp; ſtudio Scripturarum, allegoricè interpretatus
ſum Abdiam Prophetam, cuius historiam neſciebam.
Hee thought it one of the greateſt ſinnes of his
youth, that being carried away through an inconſiderate
heate in his ſtudies of Scripture, he advē
               tured
to interpret Abdias the Prophet allegorically,
when as yet hee knewe not the hiſtoricall meaning.
Old men, ſaith our beſt naturall maſter, by

reaſon of the experience of their of
                  •
               en miſtakes,
are hardly brought cōſtantly to affirme any thing,

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , they will alwaies
cautelouſly interline their ſpeeches, with it
may bees, and peradventures, and other ſuch particles
of warines &amp; circumſpection. This old mens
modeſtie of all other things beſt fits vs in pervſing
thoſe hard and obſcure texts of holy Scripture.
Out of which conceit it is that we ſee St 
               Auſtine
in his bookes de Geneſi adlitteram, to haue written
only by way of queſtions and interrogations, after
the manner of Ariſtotle in his Problemes, that he
might not, (for ſo he giues his reaſon by being over
poſitiue preiudice others, and peradventure truer interpretations:
that every one might chooſe according
to his likeing, &amp; vbi quid intelligere non poteſt, Scripturae
Dei det honorem, ſibi timorem: and where his
vnderſtanding cannot attaine vnto the ſenſe of it,
let him giue that honour and reverence which is
due vnto the Scripture, and carry himſelfe with
that aw and reſpect which befits him. Wherefore
not without eſpecial providence it is, that the holy
Ghoſt by St 
               Paul giuing precepts to Timothie,
concerning the qualitie of thoſe who were to be
admitted to the diſtributing of Gods holy word,
expreſly preſcribes againſt a young Scholler, leaſt,
ſaith he, he be puft vp. For as it hath beene noted
of men, who are lately growne rich, that they differ
from other rich men only in this,Ariſt. Rbet. 2. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
that commonly

they haue all the faults, that rich men haue
and many more: ſo is it as true in thoſe who haue
lately attaind to ſome degree and mediocritie of
knowledge. Looke what infirmities learned men
haue, the ſame haue they in greater degree, &amp; many
more beſides. Wherefore if Hippocrates in his
Phyſician required theſe two things, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
great induſtrie and long experience,
the one as tillage to ſow the ſeed, the other
as time and ſeaſon of the yeare to bring it to maturitie:
then certainely by ſo much the more are
theſe two required in the ſpirituall Phyſician, by
how much hee is the Phyſician to a more excellent
part.
            I will add yet one third motioner to this abuſe
of Scriptures, and that is the too great preſumption
vpon the ſtrength and ſubteltie of our owne
wits. That which the Romane Prieſt ſometimes
told an overpleaſant and wirtie veſtall Virgin, Coli
Deos ſanctè magis quam ſcitè, hath in this great
worke of expoſition of Scripture an eſpeciall
place. The holy things of God muſt bee handled
ſanctè, magis quàm ſcitè, with feare and reverence,
not with wit and daliance. The dangerous effects
of this haue appeared, not in the greene tree only,
in young heads, but in men of conſtant age, and
great place in the Church. For this was that
which vndid Origen, a man of as great learning &amp;
induſtrie, as ever the Church had any; whilſt in
ſublimitie of his wit, in his Comments on Scripture,

conceaving Meteors and aery ſpeculations,
he brought forth thoſe dangerous errors, which
drewe vpon his perſon the Churches heavieſt cē
               ſure;
and vpon poſteritie the loſſe of his workes.
Subtile witted men in nothing ſo much miſcarrie
as in the too much pleaſing themſelues in the
goodneſſe of their owne conceits; where the like
ſometimes befals them which befell Xe
                     •
                  xis the
painter, who hauing to the life pictured an old
woman, ſo pleas'd himſelfe with the conceit of
his worke that he died with laughing at it. Heliodor
Biſhop of Tricca in Theſſaly,
               Nicepho
                     •••
                  . the author of the Aethiopick
ſtorie, a polite and elegant I confeſſe, but a
looſe and wanton worke, being ſummon'd by a
provinciall Synod, was told, that which was true,
that his worke did rather endanger the manners
then profit the wits of his reader, as nouriſhing
looſe and wanton conceits in the heads of youth:
and hauing his choice given him either to aboliſh
his worke, or to leaue his Biſhopricke; not willing
to looſe the reputation of wit, choſe rather to refigne
his place in the Church, &amp;, as I verily thinke,
his part in heauen. And not in private perſons alone,
but even in whole nations, ſhall wee finde remarkable
examples of miſcarriage in this kinde.
The Grecians, till barbariſme beganne to ſteale in
vpon them, were men of wonderous ſubtletie of
wit, and naturally over indulgent vnto themſelues
in this qualitie. Thoſe deepe and ſubtile hereſies
concerning the Trinitie, the divinitie of Chriſt &amp;

of the holy Ghoſt, the vnion and diviſion of the
divine ſubſtance and perſons, were all of them begottē
in the heat of their wits: yea by the ſtrength
of them were they cōceaved, &amp; borne &amp; brought
to that growth, that if it had beene poſſible for the
gates of Hell to prevaile againſt the Church, they
would haue prevailed this way. Wherefore as
God dealt with his owne land, which being ſometimes
the mirrour of the world for fertilitie and abundance
of all things, now lies ſubiect to many
curſes, and eſpecially to that of barrenneſſe: ſo at
this day is it with Greece. Where ſometimes was
the flow and luxurie of wit, now is there nothing
but extreame barbariſme and ſtupidity. It is in this
reſpect ſo degenerated, that it ſcarſly for ſome hū
               dreth
of years hath brought forth a child that carries
any ſhew of his fathers coūtenance. God as it
were purpoſely plaguing their miſerable poſterity
with extreame want of that, the abundance of
which their fathers did ſo wantonly abuſe. The
reaſon of all, that hetherto J haue in this point deliuered,
is this. Sharpneſſe of wit hath commonly
with it two ill companions, pride, and levitie. By
the firſt it comes to paſſe that men know not how
to yeeld to another mans reaſonable poſitions; by
the ſecond, they knowe not how to keepe themſelues
conſtant to their owne. It was an excellent
obſervation of the wiſe Grecian,Th
                     ••
                  yd. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
&amp;c. Sad and dull ſpirited men vſually mannage
matters of ſtate better then quicke and nimble wits.
               
For ſuch for the moſt part haue not learnt that
leſſon, the meaning of that voice that came to the
Pythagorean, that was deſirous to remoue the

                  •
               ſhes of his dead frend out of his graue, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               things lawfully ſetled and compoſed must
not be mo
                     •
                  ed. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
ſaith Iulian. Men over buſy are by nature
vnfit to governe. For they moue all things, &amp; leaue
nothing without queſtion and innovation, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
as Nazianzen ſpeakes, out of
deſire to amend what is already well. And therefore
we ſee that for the moſt part ſuch, if they bee
in place of authoritie, by vnſeaſonable and vnneceſſary
tampering put all things into tumult and
combuſtion. Not the Commonwealth alone, but
the Church likewiſe hath receau'd the like blowe
from theſe kinde of men. Nazianzene in his ſix &amp;
twentieth Oration, diſcourſing concerning the
diſorders committed in the handling of Controverſies;
ſpeakes it plainely: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
&amp;c. Great wits, hot and fierie
diſpoſitions haue raiſed theſe tumults. From theſe it is
(ſaith he) that Chriſtians are ſo divided. We are no longer
a tribe and a tribe, Iſrael and Iudah, two parts of a
ſmall nation: but we are diuided kindred against kindred,
family againſt family, yea a man againſt himſelfe.
But I muſt haſten to my ſecond generall part, the
perſons here accounted guiltie of abuſe of Scripture.
            
            The perſons are noted vnto vs in two Epithe
                  •
               s,
vnlearned, vnſtable. Firſt, vnlearned. It was

St 
               
                  〈◊〉
                complaint, that practitioners of other
arts could containe themſelues within the bounds
of their owne profeſſion, Sola Scripturarum ars eſt,
quam ſibi omnes paſſim vendicāt. Hanc garrula anu
                     •
                  ,
hanc delirus, ſenex hanc ſophiſta verboſus, hanc vniverſi
praeſumu
                     •
                  t, lacerant, docent antequam diſcant:
every one preſumes much vpon his skil, and therefore
to be a reacher of Scripture: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
(ſo Nazianzen ſpeaks)
as if this great myſtery of Chriſtianitie were but
ſome one of the common, baſe, inferior, and contemptible
trades. I ſpeake not this as if I envied
that all even the meaneſt of the Lords people
ſhould prophecie: but only that all kinde of men
may knowe their bounds, that no vnlearned beaſt
touch the hill, leaſt hee bee thruſt through with a
dart. It is true which we haue heard, ſurgunt indocti
&amp; rapiunt regnum coelorum: they ariſe indeed,
but it is as St 
               Paul ſpeakes of the reſurrection, euery
man in his owne order. Scripture is giuen to all, to
learne: but to teach and to interpret, only to a few.
This bold intruſion therefore of the vnlearned into
the chaire of the teacher, is that which here
with our bleſſed Apoſtle I am to reprehend. Learning
in generall is nothing elſe but the competent
skill of any man in whatſoever he profeſſes. Vſual
               
                  •••••
               
call by this name onely our polite and Aca
               
                  ••
               
micall ſtudies: but indeed it is common to euèry
one, that is well skild, well practiſed in his owne myſtery.
The vnlearned therefore, whom here our

Apoſtle rebukes, is not hee that hath not reade
multiplicitie of Authors: or that is not as Moſes
was, skilfull in all the learning of the AEgyptians:
but he that taking vpon him to divide the word of
God, is yet but raw and vnexperienced; or if hee
haue had experience, wants iudgement to make
vſe of it. Scripture is never ſo vnhappy, as when it
falls into theſe mens fingers. That which old Cato
ſaid of the Grecian Phyſicians, quandocun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   iſta
gens literas ſuas debit, omnia corrumpet, is moſt true
of theſe men. whenſoever they ſhall begin to tamper
with Scripture, and vent in writing their raw
conceits, they will corrupt &amp; defile all they touch.
Quid enim molestiae tristitiae
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   temerarij iſti praeſumptores,
               De Geneſi ad literam.
               &amp;c as S. Auſtine complaineth: for what trouble
and anguiſh theſeraſh praeſumers (ſaith he) bring
vnto the diereeter ſort of the brethron, cannot ſufficiently
be expreſt: when being convinced of their rotten
and vngrounded opinions; for the maintaining of that
which with great levitie and open falſhood they haue
averd, they pretend the authoritie of theſe ſacred books,
and repeat much of them even by heart, as bearing witneſse
to what they hold: whereas indeed they doe but
pronounce the words, but vnderſtand not either what
they ſpeake, or of what things they doe affirme. Belike
as he that bought Orphem Harp, thought it would
of it ſelfe make admirable melodie, how vnskilfully
ſoever he toucht it: ſo theſe men ſuppoſe 
                  〈◊〉
               
Scripture will ſound wonderfull muſically, if they
doe but ſtrike it, with how great infelicitie or incōgruity

ſoever it be. The reaſon of theſe mens offence
againſt Scripture, is the ſame with the cauſe
of their miſcarriage in civill actions. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
ſaith Th
                     •
                  cydides, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Rude men,
men of little experience, are commonly moſt peremptory:
but men experienced, and ſuch as haue waded in buſineſse,
are ſlowe of determination. Quintilian making
a queſtion, why vnlearned men ſeeme many times
to he more copious then the learned (for commonly
ſuch men never want matter of diſcourſe)
anſweres that it is becauſe whatſoever conceit
comes into their heads, without care or choice
they broach it, cum doctis ſit electio &amp; modus: whereas
learned men are choice in their invention, and
lay by much of that which offers it ſelfe, Wiſe hearted
men, in whom the Lord hath put wiſdome and vnderſtanding
to knowe how to worke all manner of work
for the ſervice of the ſanctuary, like Bezaleel and Aholiab
refuſe much of the ſtuffe which is preſented
them. But this kinde of men whom here our Apoſtle
notes, are naturally men of bold &amp; daring ſpirits,
quicquid dixerint, hoc legem Deiputant, as Saint
Ierome ſpeakes, whatſoever conceit is begotten in
their heads, the ſpirit of God is preſently the father
of it: nec ſcire dignantur quid Prophetae, quid Apoſtoli
ſenſerint, ſed ad ſuum ſenſum incongrua aptant

                     〈◊〉
                  . But to leaue theſe men, and to ſpeake a
little more home vnto mine owne auditorie: Let
vs a little conſider, not the weakneſſe of theſe men
but the greatneſſe of the buſineſſe, the manage of

which they vndertake. So great a thing as the skill
of expoſition of the word &amp; Goſpell is, ſo fra
                  •
               ght
with multiplicitie of authors, ſo full of varietie of
opinion, muſt needs be confeſt to bee a matter of
great learning, and that it cannot, eſpecially in our
daies, in ſhort time with a mediocritie of induſtrie
be attaind. For if in the Apoſtles times, when as
yet much of Scripture was fearſly written, when
God wrought with men miraculouſly to informe
their vnderſtanding, &amp; ſupplied by revelatiō what
mans induſtrie could not yeeld; if I ſay in theſe
times St 
               Paul required diligent reading, &amp; expreſly
forbad greenneſſe of ſchollarſhip: much more thē
are theſe conditions required in our times, wherein
God doth not ſupply by miracle our natural defects,
and yet the burden of our profeſſion is infinitely
increaſt. All that was neceſſary in the Apoſtles
times is now neceſſary and much more. For
if we add vnto the growth of Chriſtian learning,
as it was in the Apoſtles times, but this one circumſtance
(to ſay nothing of all the reſt) which
naturally befals our times, and could not be required
at the hands of thoſe who guided the firſt ages
of the Church: that is, the knowledge of the ſtate
and ſucceſſion of doctrine in the Church from
time to time; a thing very neceſſary for the determining
the controverſies of theſe our daies: how
great a portion of our labour and induſtrie would
this alone require? Wherefore if Quintilian
thought it neceſſary to admoniſh young mē that

they ſhould not preſume themſelues ſatis inſtructos,
ſi qaem ex ijs, qui breves circumfernutur, 
                     〈…〉
                   libell
                     •••
                  
edidicerint, &amp; velut dicretis technicorum tutor
put
                     •
                  nt: if he thought fit thus to doe in an a
                  ••
                of
ſo inferiour and narrow a ſphere; much more is it
behoofefull that young ſtudents in ſo high, ſo ſpacious,
ſo large a profeſſion, be adviſed nor to think
themſelues ſufficiently provided vpon their acquaintance
with ſome Notitia, or ſyſteme of ſome
technicall divine. Looke vpon thoſe ſonnes of
Anak, thoſe Giant like voluminous writers of
Rome; in regard of whom our little tractats and
pocket volumes in this kinde, what are they but as
Graſhoppers? I ſpeake not this like ſome ſeditious
or factious ſpie, to bring weakneſſe of hands, or
melting of heart vpon any of Gods people: but

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , to ſtirre vp and kindle in you the ſpirit
of induſtrie, to enlarge your conceite, and not
to ſuffer your labours to bee copſt and 
                  ••
               ed vp
within the poverty of ſome pretended method. I
will ſpeake as Ioſhua did to his people, L
                     •
                  t vs not
feare the people of that land, they are as m
                     ••
                  t vnto vs,
the
                     ••
                   ſhadow is departed from them
                     •
                   the Lord is with
vs, feare them not.
               Iivie. Only let vs not thinke, 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   &amp;

                     •
                  ot is d
                     •
                  bellari poſse, that the conqueſt will be gottē
by ſitting ſtill and wiſhing al were well or that the
walls of thoſe ſtrong 
                  〈◊〉
               , will f
                  •
               ll downe if wee
only walke about them, &amp; blow rammes hornes,
But as the voice of Gods people ſometime was,
by the ſ
                     ••
                  rd of God and of Gedeon, ſo that which here

giues the victory muſt bee the grace of God and
our induſtrie. For by this circumciſed, narrow and
penurious forme of ſtudie, wee ſhall be no more
able to keepe pace with them, then a child cā with
Hercules. But I forbeare and paſſe awaie vnto the
ſecond epithe
                  •
               , by which theſe rackers of Scriptures,
are by St 
               Peter ſtiled
                  •
                
               Vnſtable.
            
            In the learning which the world teaches, it were
almoſt a miracle to finde a man cōſtant to his own
tenents. For not to doubt in things in which wee
are converſant, is either by reaſon of excellency &amp;
ſerenitie of vnderſtanding throughly apprehending
the maine principles on which all things are
grounded, together with the deſerying of the ſeverall
paſſages from them vnto particular concluſions,
and the diverticles and blind by-paths which
Sophiſt
                  •
               ie and deceit are wont to tread: and ſuch
a man cann
                  •
               t 
                  •
               e never yeeld: or elſe it is through
a ſenſeleſſe ſtupiditie, like vnto that in the commō
ſort of men, who cōverſing among the creatures,
and beholding the courſe of heaven, and the heavenly
hoaſt, yet never attend them, neither ever
ſ
                  ••
               kes into their heads to marvaile, or queſtion
theſe things ſo full of doubt and difficultie. Even
ſuch
                  •
                
               
                  〈…〉
               , that learnes Theologie in the
ſchoole of 
                  〈…〉
                to participate of a
               
                  •
               y

                  〈…〉
                compoſedneſſe of conſcience.
Either it never comes into his head to doubt of any
of thoſe things; with which the world hath in
               
                  ••
               
               
                  〈…〉
                if it doth, it is 
                  〈…〉
                great purpoſe, he

may ſmother and ſtrangle, he can never reſolue his
doubt. The reaſon of which is this. It lies not in
the worlds power to giue in this caſe a text of
ſufficiēt authority to compoſe &amp; fix the thoughts
of a ſoule, that is diſpos'd to doubt. But this great
inconvenience which held the world in vncertaintie,
by the providence of God is prevented in the
Church. For vnto it is left a certaine, vndoubted;
and ſufficient authority, able to exalt every valley,
and lay low every hill, to ſmooth all rubs, &amp; make
our way ſo open and paſſable, that little enquirie
ſerues. So that as it were a wonder in the ſchoole
of nature to find one ſetled and reſolued: ſo might
it ſeeme a marvaile that in the Church any man is
vnſtable, vnreſolued. Yet notwithſtanding even
here is the vnſtable mā found too, &amp; to his charge
the Apoſtle laies this ſinne of wreſting of Scripture.
For ſince that it is confeſt at all hands, that
the ſenſe and meaning of Scripture is the rule and
ground of our Chriſtian tenents, whenſoever we
alter them, wee muſt needs giue a new ſenſe vnto
the word of God. So that the man that is vnſtable
in his religion can never be free from violating of
Scripture. The eſpeciall cauſe of this levitie and
flitting diſpoſition in the common and ordinary
ſort of men, is their diſabilitie to diſcerne of the
ſtrength of ſuch reaſons, as may be fram'd againſt
them. For which cauſe they vſually ſtart, and many
times fall awaie, vpon every obiection that is
made. In which too ſuddaine entertainment of

obiections, they reſemble the ſtate of 
                  〈◊〉
               , who
are 
                  〈◊〉
                recou
                  •
               ed out of ſome long ſickneſſe▪
               
                  〈…〉
               .Seneca.
Who never more wrong themſelues then by ſuſpecting
every alteration of their tempe
                  •
               , and being
affrighted at every little paſſion of heat, as if it
were an ague fit. To bring theſe men therefore
vnto an 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , and to purchaſe them a ſetlednes
of minde; that temper that St 
               Auſtine doth require
in him that reads his booke, tales meotum
Scriptorum velim iudices, qui reſponſionem non ſemper
deſiderent, q
                     ••
                  m 
                     〈◊〉
                   quae leg
                     •
                  ntur audier int ali
quid contradict: the ſame temper muſt be found in
e
                  •
               ery reader of Scripture, hee muſt not bee a
                  •
                a
ſtand and require an anſwer to every obiectiō that
is made againſt them. For as the Philoſopher tels
vs that mad and fantaſticall men, are very apprehenſiue
of all outward accidents, becauſe their
ſoule is inwardly emptie and vnfurniſhed of any
thing of worth which might hold the inward attention
of their minds: ſo when wee are ſo eaſily
dord and amated with every Sophiſme, it is a certaine
argument of great defect of inward furniture
and worth, which ſhould as it were ballace
the minde and keep it vpright againſt all outward
occurrents whatſoever. And be it that many times
the meanes to open ſuch doubts bee not at hand,
yet as St 
               Auſtine ſometime ſpake vnto his ſcholler

                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                concerning ſuch adviſe and counſaile as

he had given him: Nolo te cauſas rationes
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   rim
                     •
                  ri,
quae etiamſi reddi poſsint fides tamen, quae mihi credis
non eas debeo: ſo much more muſt we thus reſolue
of thoſe leſſons which God teacheth vs: the reaſons
and grounds of them, though they might be
giuen, yet it fits not that credit and truſt which we
owe him, once to ſearch into, or call in queſtion.
And ſo I come to the third generall part, the danger
of wreſting of Scripture, in the laſt wordes,
vnto their owne damnation.
            
            The reward of every ſin is death. As the worme
eates out the heart of the plant that bred it: ſo
whatſoeuer is done amiſſe naturally workes no other
end, but the deſtruction of him that doth it.
As this is true in generall, ſo is it as true, that whē
the Scripture doth preciſely note out vnto vs
ſome ſinne, and threatens death vnto it, it is commonly
an argument, that there is more then ordinarie,
that there is ſome eſpeciall ſinne, which ſhall
drawe with it ſome eſpeciall puniſhment. This ſin
of wreſting of Scripture in the eie of ſome of the
ancients ſeem'd ſo ougly, that they haue ranged
it in the ſame ranke with the ſinne againſt the holy
Ghoſt. And therefore haue they pronounced it
a ſinne 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,Iſidorus Peluſiota. greater then can bee pardoned.
For the moſt part of other ſinnes, are ſinns of
infirmitie or ſimplicitie, but this is a ſinne of wit
and ſtrength. The man that doth it, doth it with a
high hand; he knowes, and ſees, and reſolues vpon
it. Againe, Scripture is the voice of God: and it is

confeſt by all that the ſenſe is Scripture, rather thē
the words. It cannot therefore be avoided, but hee
that wilfully ſtriues to faeſten ſome ſenſe of his
owne vpon it, other then the very nature of the
place will beare, muſt needs take vpon him the
perſon of God, &amp; become a new indi
                  •
               e
                  •
                of Scripture:
and all that applaud and giue con
                  •
               en
                  •
                vnto any
ſuch, in effect cry the ſame that the people did
to He
                  •
               od, the voice of God, and not of man. If he then
that abaſes the Princes come deſerues to die, what
is his deſert that inſteed of the tried ſilver of Gods
word ſtamps the name and character of God vpō
               Ne
                     •
                  uſhtan, vpon baſe brafen ſtuffe of his owne?
Thirdly,2. Pet. 1. 20. 
               No Scripture is of private interpretation,
ſaith the Apoſtle. There can therfore be but two
certaine and infallible interpreters of Scripture: either
it ſelfe; or the holy Ghoſt the author of it. It
ſelfe doth then expound it ſelfe, when the wordes
&amp; circumſtances doe ſound vnto vs the prime, and
naturall, and principall ſenſe. But when the place
is obſcure, involu'd and intricate, or when there is
contain'd ſome ſecret and hidden myſtery, beyond
the prime ſenſe; infallibly to ſhew vs this, there can
be no interpreter but the holy Ghoſt that gaue it.
Beſides theſe two, all other interpretation is private.
Wherefore as the Lords of the Philiſtines
ſometimes ſaid of the kine that drew the arke vnto
Bethſhemeſh: If they goe of themſelues, then is this
from God, but if they goe another way, then is it not
from God, it is ſome chance that hath hapned vnto vs:
               
ſo may it bee ſaid of all pretended ſenſe of Scripture.
If Scripture come vnto it of it ſelfe, then is it
of God but if it goe another way, or if it bee violently
vrged and goaded on, then is it but a matter
of chance, of mans wit &amp; invention. As for thoſe
marvailous diſcourſes of ſome, fram'd vpon preſumption
of the ſpirits helpe in private, in iudging
or interpreting of difficult places of Scripture, I
muſt needs confeſſe I haue often wondred at the
boldneſſe of them. The ſpirit is a thing of darke &amp;
ſecret operation, the maner of it none can deſcrie.
As vnderminers are never ſeene till they haue
wrought their purpoſe; ſo the ſpirit is never perceaved
but by its effects. The effects of the ſpirit
(as farre as they concerne knowledge and inſtruction)
are not particular information for reſolution
in any doubtfull caſe (for this were plainely
revelation) but as the Angell, which was ſent vnto
Cornelius informes him not, but ſends him to Peter
to ſchoole: ſo the ſpirit teaches not, but ſtirres vp
in vs a deſire to learne: Deſire to learne makes vs
thirſt after the meanes: and pious ſedulitie &amp; carefulneſſe
makes vs watchfull in the choice, and diligent
in the vſe of our meanes. The promiſe to the
Apoſtles of the ſpirit which ſhould lead them into
all truth, was made good vnto them by private
and ſecret informing their vnderſtandings, with
the knowledge of high and heavenly myſteries,
which as yet had never entred into the conceit of
any man. The ſame promiſe is made to vs, but fulfil'd

after another manner. For what was written
by revelation in their hearts, for our inſtruction
haue they written in their bookes. To vs for information,
otherwiſe then out of theſe bookes, the
ſpirit ſpeaks not. Whē the ſpirit regenerats a mā,
it infuſes no knowledge of any point of faith, but
ſends him to the Church and to the Scriptures.
When it ſtirres him vp to newneſſe of life, it exhibits
not vnto him an inventory of his ſinnes, as hitherto
vnknowne; but either ſuppoſes thē knowne
in the law of nature, of which no man can bee ignorant;
or ſends him to learne them from the
mouth of his teachers. More then this in the ordinary
proceeding of the holy ſpirit, in matter of
inſtruction. I yet could never deſerie. So that to
ſpeake of the helpe of the ſpirit in private, either
in dijudicating, or in interpreting of Scripture, is
to ſpeake they knowe not what. Which I doe the
rather note, firſt, becauſe by experience we haue
learnt, how apt-men are to call their private conceits,
the ſpirit: And againe, becauſe it is the eſpeciall
errour, with which S. Auſtine long agoe charged
this kinde of men: tantò ſunt ad ſeditionem faciliores,
quantò ſibi videntur ſpirit
                     •
                   excellere: by ſo
much the more prone are they to kindle ſchiſme
and contention in the Church, by how much they
ſeeme to themſelues to bee endued with a more
eminent meaſure of ſpirit then their brethren;
whilſt 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
(as St 
               Baſils ſpeakes) vnder pretenſe of interpretation

they violently broach their owne conceits. Great
then is the danger in which they wade, which take
vpon them this buſineſſe of interpretation temeritas
aſſerend
                     •
                   incertae dubiae
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   opinionis, ſaith St 
               Auſtine,
difficile ſacrilegij crimen evitat: the raſhneſſe
of thoſe that averre vncertaine and doubtfull interpretations
for Catholike and abſolute, can
hardly eſcape the ſinne of ſacrilege.
            But whereas our Apoſtle ſaith, their owne deſtruction,
is the deſtruction onely their owne? this
were well if it ſtretched no farther. The ancients
much complaine of this offence, as an hinderer of
the ſalvation of others. There were in the daies of
Iſidorus Peluſiota ſome that gaue out that all in the
old Teſtament was ſpoken of Chriſti belike out of
extreame oppoſitiō to the Manichees, who on the
otherſide taught, that no text in the old Teſtament
did foretell of Chriſt. That Father therefore dealing
with ſome of that opinion, tels them how
great the danger of their tenent is. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               for if, ſaith he, we ſtriue with violence
to drawe and apply thoſe texts to Chriſt, which apparantly
pertaine not to him, we ſhall gaine nothing but
this, to make all the places that are ſpoken of him ſuſpected;
and ſo diſcredite the ſtrength of other teſtimonies,
which the Church vſually vrges for the refutation
of the Iewes. For in theſe caſes a wroſted proofe is
like vnto a ſuborn'd witneſſe. It never doth helpe
ſo much whileſt it is preſumed to bee ſtrong,

as it doth 
                  〈◊〉
                when it is diſcouered to bee weake.
St 
               Auſtine in his bookes de Geneſi ad litteram ſharply

                  ••
               proues ſome Chriſtians, who out of ſome
places of Scripture miſvnderſtood, fram'd vnto
themſelues a kinde of knowledge in Aſtronomie
and Phyſiologie, quite contrary vntoſome parts
of heathen learning in this kinde, which were true
and evident vnto ſenſe. A man would thinke that
this were but a ſmall errour, and yet hee doubts
not to call it 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  , &amp; pernicioſ
                     ••
                   &amp; maxi
                     ••
                  
cavendum. His reaſon warrants the roundneſſe of
his reproofe. For he charges ſuch to haue beene a
ſcandall vnto the word, and hinderers of the converſion
of ſome heathen men that were ſchollars.
For how, ſaith he, ſhall they beleeue our bookes of Scripture
perſwading the reſurrection of the dead, the kingdome
of heauen, and the reſt of the myſteries of our profeſsion,
if they finde them faultie in theſe things, of
which themſelues haue vndeniable demonſtration?
yea though the cauſe wee maintaine bee never ſo
good, yet the iſſue of diſeas'd and crazie proofes
brought to maintaine it, muſt needs bee the ſame.
For vnto all cauſes, be they never ſo good, weakeneſſe
of proofe, when it is diſcovered, brings great
prejudice, but vnto the cauſe of religion moſt of
all. St 
               Auſtine obſeru'd that there were ſome qui

                     〈◊〉
                   de aliquibus, qui 
                     •••
                  anctum nomen profitentur aliquid

                     〈…〉
                  , velveri putuerit,

                     〈…〉
                   vt de omnibus hoc cred
                     •
                  
                  tur
                     •
                  
               
               
                  〈…〉
                with religion it ſelfe, thē
               
it doth with the profeſſors of it. Diverſe malignants
there are, who lie in wait to eſpie where
our reaſons on which we build are weake, and hauing
deprehended it in ſome, will earneſtly ſolicit
the world to beleeue that all are ſo, if meanes were
made to bring it to light: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
as Nazianzen ſpeaks: vſing for advantage againſt
vs no ſtrength of their owne, but the vice and imbecillitie
of our defence. The booke of the Revelation
is a booke full of wonder and myſtery: the ancients
ſeeme to haue made a religion to meddle
with it, and thought it much better to admire it
with ſilence, then to adventure to expound it: and
therefore amongſt their labours in expoſition of
Scripture, ſcarſly is there any one found that hath
touch
                  •
                it. But our age hath taken better heart, and
ſcarſly any one is there who hath entertained a
good conceit of his owne abilities, but he hath taken
that booke as a fit argument to ſpend his
paines on. That the Church of Rome hath great
cauſe to ſuſpect her ſelfe, to feare leaſt ſhee haue a
great part in the prophecies of that booke, I think
the moſt partiall wil not deny. Yet vnto the expoſitors
of it, I will giue this adviſe, that they look
that that befall not them, which Thueydides obſerues
to befall the common ſort of men: who
though they haue good meanes to acquit themſelues
like men, yet when they thinke their beſt
hopes faile them, and beginne to deſpaire of their

ſtrength, comfort themſelues with interp
                  •••
               ati

                  〈◊〉
                of 
                  〈…〉
                &amp; abſcure prophecies. Many
plaine 
                  〈◊〉
                of Scripture are very pregnant, &amp;
of ſufficient ſtrength to overthrowe the points
maintained by that Church againſt vs. If we leaue
theſe, and ground our ſelues vpon our priuate expoſitions
of this booke; wee ſhall inſtly ſee
                  •
               e in
the povertie of better proofes, to reſt our ſelues
vpon thoſe prophecies; which, though in themſelues
they are moſt certaine, yet our expoſitions
of them muſt, 
                  〈◊〉
                except God giue yet further
light vnto his Church) neceſſarily bee mixt with
much vncertaintie, as being at the beſt but vnprobable
coniectures of our owne. Scarſly can there
be found a thing more harmefull to religion, then
to ven
                  •
                thus our own conceits, and obtrude them
vpon the world for neceſſary and abſolute. The
Phyſicians skill as I conceaue of it; ſtands as much

                  •
               n opinion, as any that I knowe, whatſoever. Yet
their greateſt maſter Hippocrates tells them directly

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , &amp;c. then the Phyſicians praeſumption
vpon opinion, there is not one thing that
bringes either more blame to himſelfe or danger to his
patient. If it be thus in an art which opinion taken
away, muſt needs fall; how little roome then muſt
opinion haue in that knowledge, where nothing
can haue place but what is of eternal truth? where
if once we admit of opinion all is overthrowne?
But I conclude this point, adding onely this generall
admonition, that we be not too peremprorie

in our poſitions, where expreſſe text of Scripture
faile
                  •
                vs: that we lay not our owne collections &amp;
concluſions with too much praecipitancie. For experience
hath ſhewd vs, that the error and weakeneſſe
of them being afterwards diſcovered brings
great diſadvantage to Chriſtianitie, and trouble
to the Church. The Eaſterne Church before St
               Baſils time, had entertained generally a conceit,
that thoſe greeke particles 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and the reſt,
were ſo divided among the Trinitie, that each of
the perſons had his particle which was no way appliable
to the reſt. St 
               Baſil hauing diſcovered this
to be but a niceneſſe and needleſſe curioſitie, beginning
to teach ſo, rais'd in the Church ſuch a
tumult, that hee brought vpon himſelfe a great labour
of writing many tracts in apologie for himſelfe,
with much adoe, eare matters could againe
be ſetled. The fault of this was not in Baſil, who religiouſly
fearing what by way of conſequence
might enſue vpō an error, taught a truth; but in the
Church, who formerly had with too much facilitie
admitted a concluſion ſo iuſtly ſubiect to exception.
And let this ſuffice for our third part.
            Now becauſe it is apparant that the end of this
our Apoſtles admonition is to giue the Church a
caveat how ſhee behaue her ſelfe in handling of
Scripture, giue me leaue a little, inſteed of the vſe
of ſuch doctrines as I haue formerly laid downe,
to ſhew you, as farre as my conceit can ſtretch,
what courſe any man may take to ſaue himſelfe

from off
                  •
               ing violence vnto Scripture, and reaſonably
ſettle himſelfe, any pretended obſcuritie of the
text whatſoever notwithſtanding. For which purpoſe
the diligent obſeruing of two rules ſhall bee
throughly availeable. Firſt, The litter all plaine, and
vncontroverſable meaning of Scripture without any
addition or ſupply by way of interpretation, is that alone
which for ground of faith we are neceſsarily bound
to accept, except it bee there where the holy Ghoſt himſelfe
treads vs out another waie. I take not this to bee
any peculiar conceit of mine, but that vnto which
our Church ſtands neceſſarily bound. When wee
receded from the Church of Rome, one motiue
was, becauſe ſhe added vnto Scripture her gloſſes
as Canonicall, to ſupply what the plaine text of
Scripture could not yeeld. If in place of hers, wee
ſet vp our owne gloſſes, thus to doe, were nothing
elſe but to pull downe Baal, and ſet vp an Ephod;
to runne round, and meet the Church of Rome againe
in the ſame point, in which at firſt wee left
her. But the plaine, evident and demonſtratiue
ground of this rule, is this. That authoritie which
doth warrant our faith vnto vs, muſt every way be
free from all poſſibilitie of errour. For let vs but
once admit of this, that there is any poſſibility that
any one point of faith ſhould not be true; if it bee
once granted that I may bee deceaued in what I
haue beleeued; how can I be aſſur'd that in the end
I ſhall not be deceaued? If the author of faith may
alter: or if the evidence and aſſurance that hee

hath left vs be not pregnant, and impoſſible to bee
defeated, there is neceſſarily opened an inlet to
doubtfulneſſe and wauering, which the nature of
faith excludes. That ſaith therefore may ſtand vnſhaken,
two things are of neceſſitie to concurre.
Firſt, that the author of it bee ſuch a one, as can by
no meanes be deceaued, and this can bee none but
God. Secondly that the words and text of this author
vpon whom we ground, muſt admit of no
ambiguitie, no vncertainetie of interpretation. If
the trumpet giue an vncertaine ſound, who ſhall provide
himſelfe to battle. If the words admit a double
ſenſe, and I follow one, who can aſſure mee that
that which I followe is the truth? For infallibility
either in iudgement, or interpretation, or whatſoever,
is annext neither to the ſea of any Biſhop,
nor to the Fathers, nor to the Councells, nor to
the Church, nor to any created power whatſoever.
This doctrine of the litterall ſenſe was never
greivous or prejudiciall to any, but onely to thoſe
who were inwardly conſcious, that their poſitions
were not ſufficiently grounded. When Cardinall
Caietan in the daies of our grandfathers had
forſaken that vaine of poſtilling and allegoriſing
on Scripture, which for a long time had prevailed
in the Church, and betaken himſelfe vnto the literall
ſenſe: it was a thing ſo diſtaſtfull vnto the
Church of Rome, that hee was forc'd to finde out
many ſhifts, &amp; make many apologies for himſelfe.
The truth is (as it will appeare to him that reads

his writings) this ſticking cloſe to the litteral ſenſe
was that alone, which made him to ſhake many of
thoſe tenents, vpon which the Church of Rome
and the reformed Churches differ. But when the
importunitie of the reformers, and the great credit
of Calvins writings in that kinde, had forced
the divines of Rome to levell their interpretations
by the ſame line: when they ſaw that no paines, no
ſubtletie of wit was ſtrong enough to defeat the
literall evidence of Scripture: it draue them on
thoſe deſperate ſhelfes, on which at this daie they
ſticke, to call in queſtion, as farre as they durſt, the
credit of the Hebrew text, &amp; countenance againſt
it a corrupt tranſlation; to add traditions vnto
Scripture; and to make the Churches interpretation,
ſo pretended, to bee aboue exception. As for
that reſtriction which is vſually added to this rule,
that the literall ſenſe is to be taken, if no abſurdity
follow, though I acknowledge it to be ſound and
good, yet my adviſe is that we entertaine it warily.
St 
               Baſil thought the precept of Chriſt to the rich
man in the Goſpell, Goe ſell all thou hast and giue vnto
the poore; to be ſpoken as a command vniverſally
and eternally binding all Chriſtians without exception.
And making this obiection, how poſſibly
ſuch a life could bee amongſt Chriſtians, ſince
where all are ſellars, none could be buyers: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
(ſaith he) 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , &amp;c.
Aske not me the ſenſe of my Lords commands. He
that gaue the law, can provide to giue it poſsibilitie of

being kept without any abſurditie at all. Which
ſpeech, howſoever we may ſuppoſe the occaſion
of it to be miſtaken; yet is it of excellent vſe, to repreſſe
our boldneſſe, whereby many times, vnder
pretence of ſome inconvenience, we hinder Scripture
from that latitude of ſenſe, of which it is naturally
capable. You knowe the ſtory of the Romane
captaine in Gellius, and what hee told the
ſhipwright, that choſe rather to interpret, then to
execute his Lords command: Corrumpi at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   diſſolvi
omne imperantis officium, ſi quis ad id quod facere
iuſsus eſt non obſequio debito, ſed conſilio non deſiderato
reſpondeat. It will certainely in the end proue ſafer
for vs to entertaine Gods Commandements
obſequio debito, then to interpret them acumine non
deſiderato. Thoſe other waies of interpretation,
whether it be by allegorizing, or alluſion or whatſoever,
the beſt that can bee ſaid of them is that
which Baſil hath pronounced: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
We account
of them as of trimme, elegant, and wittie ſpeeches, but
we refuſe to accept of them, as of vndoubted truthes.
And though of ſome part of theſe that may bee
ſaid which one ſaid of his owne worke, quod ad vſum
luſi,
               Auſonius in monoſyl. 
               quod ad moleſtiam laboravi, in reſpect of any
profit comes by them, they are but ſport, but in
reſpect of the paines taken in making of them
they are labour and travaile: yet much of them is
of excellent vſe in private, either to raiſe our affections,
or to ſpend our meditations, or (ſo it bee

with modeſtie) to practiſe our gifts of wit to the
honour of him that gaue them. For if wee abſolutely
condemne theſe interpretations, then muſt
we condemne a great part of antiquitie, who are
very much converſant in this kinde of interpreting.
For the moſt partiall for antiquitie cannot
chuſe but ſee and confeſſe thus much, that for the
litterall ſenſe the Interpreters of our owne times,
becauſe of their skill in the originall languages,
their care of preſſing the circumſtances and coherence
of the text, of comparing like places of
Scripture with like, haue generally ſurpaſt the beſt
of the ancients. Which I ſpeake not to diſcountenance
antiquitie, but that all ages, all perſons may
haue their due. And let this ſuffice for our firſt
rule.
            The Iewiſh Rabbines in their Comments on
Scripture ſo oft as they met with hard and intricate
texts, out of which they could not wreſt thē
               ſelues,
were wont to ſhut vp their diſcourſe with
this, Elias cum venerit, ſolvet dubia: Elias ſhall anſwer
this doubt when he comes. Not the Iewes
only, but the learned Chriſtians of all ages haue
found many things in Scripture which yet expect
Elias. For beſides thoſe texts of Scriptures, which
by reaſon of the hidden treaſures of wiſdome, and
depth of ſenſe &amp; myſterie laid vp in them, are not
yet conceau'd, there are in Scripture of things that
are 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , ſeemingly confus'd, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , carrying
ſemblance of contrarietie, anachroniſmes, metachroniſmes,
               
and the like, which bring infinite obſcuritie
to the text: there are I ſay in Scripture
more of them, then in any writing that I knowe
ſecular or divine. If wee meane not to ſettle our
ſelues till all theſe things are anſwered, let vs take
heed leaſt the like be ſaid to vs, which St 
               Auſtine
ſaid to ſome of the Gentiles, who refuſed to beleeue
till all obiections were ſatisfied: ſunt enim innumerabiles
quae non ſunt finiendae ante fidem, ne vita
finiatur ſine fide. The Areopagites in Athens, whē
they were troubled in a doubtfull caſe in which
they durſt not proceed to ſentence, were wont
cauſam in diem longiſsimam differre, to put it off till
a day of hearing for ſome hundreth yeares after, avoiding
by this meanes the further being importun'd
with the ſuit. To quiet our ſelues in theſe
doubts it will be our beſt way in diem longiſsimam
differre, to put them to ſome day of hearing a farre
off, even till that great day, till Chriſt our true
Elias ſhall come, who at his comming ſhal anſwer
all our doubts, and ſettle all our waverings. Meane
while till our Elias come, let vs make vſe of this ſecond
rule. In places of ambiguous and doubtfull, or
darke and intricate meaning, it is ſufficient if we religiouſly
admire and acknowledge and confeſse: vſing
that moderation of Auſtine: Neutram partem affirmantes
ſiue deſtruentes, ſed tantummodo ab audaci affirmandi
praeſumptione revocantes. Qui credit, ſaith
one, ſatis eſt illi quod Chriſtus intelligat. To vnderſtand
belongs to Chriſt the author of our faith to

vs is ſufficient the glory of beleeuing. Wherefore
we are to adviſe, not ſo much how to attaine vnto
the vnderſtanding of the myſteries of Scripture;
as how it beſt fits vs to carry our ſelues when either
the difficultie of the text, or varietie of opinions
ſhall diſtract vs. In the ſixth generall Councell
Honorius Biſhop of Rome is condemned for a Monothelite.
Two Epiſtles there are of his which are
produc'd to giue evidence againſt him. For the
firſt I haue nothing to ſay. For the ſecond) I ſpeak
with ſubmiſſion to better iudgement) notwithſtanding
the ſharpe proceeding of the Councell
againſt him, I vrerily ſuppoſe that hee giues vnto
the Church the beſt counſaile, that ever yet was
giuen for the ſetling of doubts, and finall deciſion
of controverſie. For that which he teaches in that
Epiſtle, at leaſt in thoſe parts of it, which there are
brought, ſounds to no other purpoſe but this:
That whereas there was lately raiſed in the Church a
controverſie concerning the dualitie or vnitie of wils
in Chriſt; ſince that hitherto nothing in the Church
concerning either part hath beene expreſly taught, his
counſaile was that men would rather ceaſe to doubt,
then to be curious to ſearch for any ſolution of their
doubtings; and ſo abſtaine from teaching doctrinally
either part, and content themſelues with that expreſse
meaſure of faith, with which the Church hath
hitherto reſt ſatisfied. This to my conceit is the drift
of his Epiſtle. How this adviſe of the Biſhops was
appliable or how it fitted the queſtion then in cō
               troverſie;

or what reaſon moued the Councell to
thinke that it was abſolutely neceſſary for them,
to giue an expreſſe deciſion, and determine for the
one part, belongs not to me to diſcuſſe. But I verily
perſwade my ſelfe, that if it had pleaſed thoſe,
who in all ages haue beene ſet to governe the
Church of God; betimes to haue made vſe of this
adviſe, to haue taught men rather not to haue
doubted, then to haue expected ſtill ſolution of
their doubtings: to haue ſtopt and damm'd vp the
originals and ſprings of controverſies, rather then
by determining for the one part, to giue them as
it were a pipe and conduit to convaie them to poſteritie,
I perſwade my ſelfe the Church had not
ſuffred that invndation of opinions, with which at
this day it is overrunne. Is it not St 
               Pauls owne
practiſe, when hauing brought in a queſtion concerning
Gods iuſtice in predeſtination, hee giues
no other anſwere but this, O man, who art thou that
diſputeſt with God? Is it not his plaine purpoſe to
adviſe the diſputer rather not to make the queſtion,
then to require a determination of it at his
hands? How many of the queſtions even of our
owne times, even of thoſe that are at home amongſt
vs, might by this way long ſince haue
beene determind? I haue, I confeſſe, the ſame diſeaſe
that my firſt parents in Paradiſe had, a deſire
to knowe more then I need. But I alwaies thought
it a very iudicious commendation, which is given
to I. Agri
                     •
                  ola, that hee knewe how to bridle his deſire

in purſui
                  •
                of knowledge, 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , qu
                     •
                  d eſt difficillimum,
ex ſcientia m
                     ••
                  um. Mallem quidem (as St
               Auſtine ſaith) eorum qua à me quaeſtni
                     ••
                  i habere ſcientiam,
quàm ignorantiam; ſed qui
                     •
                   id nondum po
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  i,
magis eligocantam ignorantiam confiteri, quam falſam
ſcientiam profiteri. It ſhall well befit our Chriſtian
modeſtie to participate ſomewhat of the
Sceptike, and to vſe their 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , till the 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and
remainder of our knowledge bee ſupplied by
Chriſt: In quem ſic credimus, vt ſi alique nobis non
apa
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  t et
                     ••
                  m pulſ
                     •
                  ntibus, nullo modo adverſ
                     •
                  s eum
mu
                     •
                  murare debeamus. To conclude. St 
               Auſtine in
his eightieth Epiſtle diſcourſing of the ſpeedie or
ſlow comming of our Saviour to iudgement, to
ſhew that it is the ſafeſt waie to teach neither, but
to ſuſpend our beleefe, &amp; confeſſe our ignorance,
ranging himſelfe with men of this tēper, obſecrote
(ſaith he to Heſ
                     •
                  chtus, to whō he writes that Epiſtle)
obſecrote vt me talem non ſpernas. So giue me
leaue to cōmence the ſame ſuit to you: obſ
                     •
                  cro vos
vt me talem nō ſpernatis. Let me requeſt you beare
with me, if I be ſuch a one, as I haue St 
               Austine for
example. For it is not depth of knowledge, nor
knowledge of antiquitie, or ſharpneſſe of wit, nor
authority of Coūcels, nor the name of the church
can ſettle the reſtleſſe conceits, that poſſeſſe the
mindes of many doubtfull Chriſtians: onely to
ground for faith on the plaine vncontroverſable
text of Scripture, and for the reſt to expect and
pray for the comming of our Elias, this ſhall compoſe

our waverings, and giue finall reſt vnto our
ſoules.
            Thus inſteed of a diſcourſe which was due vnto
this time, concerning the glorious reſurrection
of our bleſſed Saviour, and the benefits that come
vnto vs by it, I haue diverted my ſelfe vpon another
theame, more neceſſary as I thought for this
auditorie, though leſſe agreeable with this ſolemnitie.
Thoſe who haue gone afore mee in that argument
haue made ſo copious a harveſt, that the
iſſue of my gatherings muſt needs haue beene but
ſmall, except I had with Ruth gleand out of their
ſheaues, or ſtraind my induſtrie which is but ſmall,
and my wits which are none, to haue held your attentiueneſſe
with new and quaint conceits. In the
meane time, whether it be I or they, or whatſoever
hath beene deliuered out of this place,
God grant that it may bee for his honour,
and for the Churches
good, to whom both it &amp;
wee are dedicate.
To God the
Father,
&amp;c.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

