
   
      
         
            The arte of diuine meditation profitable for all Christians to knowe and practise; exemplified with a large meditation of eternall life. By Ioseph Hall.
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1606
            
         
         Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 110 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02513
            STC 12642
            ESTC S118419
            99853626
            99853626
            19018
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02513)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19018)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1175:07)
         
         
            
               
                  The arte of diuine meditation profitable for all Christians to knowe and practise; exemplified with a large meditation of eternall life. By Ioseph Hall.
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [16], 193, [3] p.   
               
                  By Humfrey Lownes for Samuel Macham, and Mathew Cooke: and are to bee sold in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Tigers head,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1606.
               
               
                  A2, title page (a cancel) is mounted; A1 and I12 probably blank, lacking.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Meditations --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-06
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-09
            David KarczynskiSampled and proofread
         
            2007-09
            David KarczynskiText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
               
THE ARTE OF DIVINE ME
               DITATION: Profitable for all Chriſtians to knowe and practiſe; Exemplified with a large Meditation of eternall life.
            By IOSEPH HALL.
            ¶ Imprinted at London by Humfrey Lownes, for Samuel Macham, and Mathew Cooke: and are to bee ſold in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Tigers head. 1606.
            
         
         
            
            
            
               To the right Worſhipful, Sir Richard Lea, Knight, all increaſe of true honour with God and men.
            
            
               SIr, euer ſince I began to beſtow my ſelfe vpō the commō good, ſtudying wherin my labours might bee most ſeruiceable; I ſtill found they could bee no way ſo well improued, as

in that part which concerneth deuotion, and the practiſe of true piety: For on the one ſide I perceiued the number of Polemicall bookes, rather to breede, than ende ſtrifes; and thoſe which are doctrinall, by reaſon of their multitude, rather to oppreſſe than ſatiſfie the Reader; wherein if we write the ſame things, we are iudged tedious; if different, ſingular. On the other part reſpecting the Reader, I ſawe the braines of men neuer more ſtuffed,

their tōgues neuer more ſtirring, their hearts neuer more emptie, nor their handes more idle. Wherefore after thoſe ſuddē Meditatiōs which paſſed me without rule, I was eaſily induced by their ſucceſſe (as a ſmall thing moues the willing) to ſend foorth this Rule of Meditation; and after my Heauen vpon earth, to diſcourſe (although by way of example) of heauen aboue. In this Arte of mine, I confeſſe to haue receiued more light from one obſcure

nameleſſe Monke which wrote ſome 112. yeeres agoe, then from the directions of all other writers: I would his humility had not made him niggardly of his name, that wee might haue knowen whome to haue thanked. It had been eaſie to haue framed it with more curioſitie: But God and my ſoule knowe, that I made profit the ſcope of my labour, and not applauſe: and therefore (to chooſe) I wiſhed rather to be rude than vnprofitable: If now the

ſimplicitie of any Reader, ſhall bereaue him of the benefite of my precepts, I knowe hee may make his vſe of my example. Why I haue honored it with your name, I need not giue account to the world; which already knowes your worth and deſerts, and ſhall ſee by this, that I acknowledge them: Goe you on happily (according to the heauenly aduiſe of your Iunius) in your worthy and glorious profeſſion; ſtill bearing your ſelfe as one that knowes vertue

the trueſt nobility, and Religion the beſt vertue: The God whom you ſerue ſhal honor you with men, and crowne you in heauen. To his grace I humbly commend you: requeſting you onely to accept the worke, and continue your fauour to the Author.
            
               Your Worſhips humbly deuoted, IOS. HALL.
            
         
         
            
            THE SVMME OF THE Chapters.
            
               THE benefite &amp; vſes of Meditation. Cap. 1
            
            The deſcription &amp; kinds of Medit. Cap. 2
            
            Concerning Meditation Extemporal. Cap. 3
            
            Cautions of Extemporary Medit. Cap. 4
            
            
               
Of Meditatiō deliberate: wherein firſt the qualitie of the perſon: of whom is required;
            
               1 That he be pure from his ſinnes. Cap. 5
            
            
               2 That he be free from worldly thoughts. Cap. 6
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        3 Conſtant
                     In the time ſet. Ca. 7
                     
                  
                  
                     In cōtinuance. Ca. 8
                     
                  
               
            
            Of other neceſſary circumſtances: and,
            
               1 Of the place fit for meditation. Cap. 9
            
            
               
               2 Of the time. Cap. 10
            
            
               3 Of the ſite and geſture of body. Cap. 11
            
            Of the matter and ſubiect of Medit. Ca. 12
            
            The order of handling the worke it ſelfe. Cap. 13
            
            
               
                  
                     The entrance into the worke
                     
                        1. Common entrāce, which is prayer. Ca. 14
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        2. The particular &amp; proper entrāce into the matter, which is in our choice thereof. Cap. 15
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
The proceeding of our Meditation, therein a Method allowed by ſome Authors, reiected. Cap. 16
            
            Premonitions cōcerning our proceeding in the firſt part of Med. C. 17
            
            The practiſe of Meditation: the firſt part wherof in the vnderſtanding: therein,
            
               1. We begin with ſome deſcriptiō of that which we meditate of. Ca. 18
            
            
               2 An eaſie and voluntary diuiſion of the matter meditated. Cap. 19
            
            
               3 A conſideration of the

cauſes therof in al the kinds of them. Ca. 20
            
            
               4 The Conſid. of the Fruits and Effectes. Cap. 21
            
            
               5 The Conſid. of the ſubiect wherin, or wherabout it is imployed. Cap. 22
            
            
               6 Conſid. of the Appendances and qualities of it. Cap. 23.
            
            
               7 Conſid. of that which is contrary to it, or diuers from it. Cap. 24
            
            
               8 Of Compariſons and ſimilitudes wherby it may bee moſt fitly ſet forth to vs. Cap. 25
            
            
               
               9 The Titles and Names of the matter conſidered. Cap. 26
            
            
               10 Conſid. of fit Teſtimonies of Scripture cōcerning our Theme. Cap. 27
            
            Of the ſecond part of Meditation, which is in the affections: wherein is,
            
               1 Firſt required, a taſte and relliſh of what we thought vpon. Ca. 28
            
            
               2 A complaint bewayling our want and vntowardnes. Cap. 29
            
            
               3 A hearty wiſh of the ſoule for what it complaines

to want. Ca. 30
            
            
               4 An humble confeſſion of our diſability to effect what wee wiſh. Cap. 31
            
            
               5 An earneſt Petitiō for that which we cōfeſſe to want. Cap. 32
            
            
               6 A vehement enforcement of our Petition. Cap. 33
            
            
               7 A cheerefull confidēce of obtaining what we haue requeſted and enforced. Cap. 34
            
            The concluſiō of our Meditation, in what order. Cap. 35
            
            Firſt, with thankſgiuing

for what we are confident to be granted. Ibid.
            
            Secondly, with a Recommendatiō of our ſoules and wayes to GOD. Cap. 36
            
            The Epilogue; reprouing the neglect, &amp; exhorting to the vſe of Meditation. Cap. 37
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE ART OF DIVINE MEDITATION.
            
               
                  Chap. I.
               
                  IT is not, I The benefit &amp; vſes of Meditation. ſuppoſe, a more bolde than profitable labour, after the indeuours of ſo many cō
                  tēplatiue men to teach

the Art of Meditation: An heauenly buſineſſe, as any belongs either to man or Chriſtian; and ſuch as wherby the ſoule doeth vnſpeakeably benefit it ſelfe: For by this do we ranſacke our deepe &amp; falſe harts, find out our ſecret enemies, buckle with them, expell them, arme our ſelues againſt their reentrance. By this wee make vſe of all good means, fit our ſelues to all good dueties; by this we deſcrie our weakeneſſe, obtaine redreſſe,

preuēt tentatiōs, cheere vp our ſolitarines, temper our occaſions of delight; get more light to our knowledge, more heate to our affections, more life to our deuotion: by this we grow to be (as wee are) ſtraungers vpon earth, and out of a right eſtimation of all earthly things, into a ſweet fruitiō of inuiſible comforts: by this, wee ſee our Sauiour with Steuen, we talke with God as Moſes▪
                   and by this we are rauiſhed with bleſſed

                  Paul into Paradiſe; and ſee that heauen which we are loath to leaue, which we cannot vtter. This alone is the remedie of ſecurity and worldlines, the paſtime of Saints, the ladder of heauen, and in ſhort the beſt improuement of Chriſtianitie: Learne it who can, and neglect it who liſt; hee ſhall neuer find ioy, neither in God nor in himſelfe, which doeth not both knowe and practiſe it. And how euer of olde ſome hidden Cloyſterers

haue ingroſſed it Which are vniuerſall to al Chriſtians and not to bee appropriated to ſome profeſſions. to themſelues, and confined it within their Celles: who indeede profeſſing nothing but contemplation, throgh their immunitie from thoſe cares which accompany an actiue life, might haue the beſt leaſure to this buſines; Yet ſeeing there is no man ſo taken vp with action, as not ſometimes to haue a free minde; and there is no reaſonable minde ſo ſimple, as not to bee able both to diſcourſe

ſomewhat, and to better it ſelfe by her ſecret thoughts; I deeme it an enuious wrong to conceale that from any, whoſe benefit may bee vniuerſall: Thoſe that haue but a little ſtocke, had neede to knowe the beſt rules of thrift;
            
            
               
                  Chap. 2.
               
                  THe rather for that whereas The deſcription and kinds of Meditation. our Diuine Meditation is

nothing elſe but a bending of the mind vpon ſome ſpirituall obiect, through diuers formes of diſcourſe, vntill our thoughts come to an iſſue; and this muſt needs be either Extemporall, and occaſioned by outward occurrences offred to the mind, or Deliberate, and wrought out of our owne heart; which againe is either in Matter of Knowledge for the finding out of ſome hidden trueth, and conuincing of an hereſie

by profound trauerſing of reaſon, or in Matter of Affection, for the enkindling of our loue to God: the former of theſe two laſt wee ſending to the Scholes and maſters of Controuerſies, ſearch after the later; which is both of larger vſe, and ſuch as no Chriſtian can reiect, as either vnneceſſary, or ouer-difficult. For both euery Chriſtian had neede of fire put to his affections, and weaker iudgements are no leſſe capable of this

diuine heate, which proceedes not ſo much from reaſon as from faith.
               One ſayes, (and I beleeue him) that Gods Schoole is more of Affection, than Vnderſtanding: Both leſſons very needefull, very profitable; but for this our age, eſpecially the later: For if there bee ſome that haue much zeale, little knowledge, there are more that haue much knoweledge without zeale. And hee that

hath much skill and no affection, may do good to others by information of iudgement, but ſhall neuer haue thanke either of his own heart, or of God; who vſeth not to caſt away his loue on thoſe, of whom hee is but knowen, not loued.
            
            
               
                  Chap. 3.
               
                  OF Extemporal Meditatiō 
                  Concerning Meditation Extemporall. there may be much vſe, no

rule: foraſmuch as our conceits herein varie according to the infinite multitude of obiects, and their diuers manner of profering thēſelues to the minde; as alſo for the ſuddenneſſe of this acte. Man is placed in this Stage of the worlde to viewe the ſeuerall natures and actions of the creature; To view them, not idly, without his vſe, as they doe him: God made all theſe for man, and man for his owne ſake; Both theſe purpoſes

were loſt, if man ſhould let the creatures paſſe careleſly by him, onely ſeene, not thought vpon: He onely can make benefit of what he ſees; which if hee doe not, it is all one, as if hee were blind, or brute. Whēce it is, that wiſe Salomon puttes the ſluggard to ſchoole vnto the Ant; and our Sauiour ſends the diſtruſtfull to the Lillie of the field.
               In this kinde was that Meditation of the Diuine Pſalmiſt, which vpon the viewe of the

glorious frame of the Heauens, was led to woonder at the mercifull reſpect GOD hath to ſo poore a creature as man. Thus our Sauiour tooke occaſion of the water fetcht vp ſolemnely to the Altar, from the Well of Shilo, on the day of the great HOSANNAH, to meditate and diſcourſe of the Water of life. Thus holy and ſweete AVGVSTINE, from occaſion of the water-courſe neere to his Lodging, running

among the pebbles, ſometimes more ſilently, ſometimes in a baſer murmure, and ſometimes in a ſhriller note, entred into the thought and diſcourſe of that excellent order which God hath ſettled in all theſe inferiour things; Thus that learned and heauenly ſoule of our late Estye, when wee ſate together, and heard a ſweet conſort of Muſicke, ſeemed vpon this occaſion carried vp for the time before-hand to the place of his reſt,

ſaying, not without ſome paſſion, What Muſicke may we thinke there is in heauen? Thus laſtly (for who knowes not that examples of this kinde are infinite?) that faithfull and reuerend Deering, when the Sunne ſhined on his face, now lying on his death-bed, fell into a ſweet meditation of the glory of God, and his approaching ioy. The thoughts of this nature are not onely lawfull, but ſo behooueful, that we cannot omit them,

without neglect of God, his creatures, our ſelues. The creatures are halfe loſt if wee only imploy them, not learne ſomthing of thē: GOD is wronged if his creatures bee vnregarded; our ſelues moſt of all if wee reade this great volume of the creatures, and take out no leſſon for our inſtruction.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 4.
               
                  WHerein yet Cautions of Extemporal Meditation. cautiō is to be had that our Meditatiōs be not either too farre-fetcht, or ſauouring of Superſtition. Farre-fetcht I cal thoſe, which haue not a faire &amp; eaſie reſemblāce vnto the matter frō whēce they are raiſed: in which caſe our thoghts proue looſe &amp; heartles; making no memorable

impreſſion in the mind. Superſtitious, when we make choice of thoſe grounds of Meditation, which are forbidden vs as Teachers of Vanity; or imploy our owne deuices (though well grounded) to an vſe aboue their reach; making them vpon our owne pleaſures, not only furtherances, but parts of Gods worſhip; in both which, our Meditations degenerate, and growe rather perillous to the ſoule: Whereto adde, that

the minde bee not too much cloyed with too frequent iteratiō of the ſame thought; which at laſt breedes a wearineſſe in our ſelues, and an vnpleaſantneſſe of that conceit, which at the firſt entertainement promiſed much delight. Our nature is too ready to abuſe familiaritie in any kinde: and it is with Meditations, as with Medicines; which with ouer-ordinary vſe loſe their Soueraignety; and fill, in ſtead of purging. God

hath not ſtraited vs for matter, hauing giuen vs the ſcope of the whole world; ſo that there is no creature, euent, action, ſpeach which may not afford vs new matter of Meditation. And that which we are wont to ſay of fine wittes, we may as truely affirme of the Chriſtian hart; that it can make vſe of any thing. Wherefore as trauellers in a forreine countrey make euery fight a leſſon; ſo ought wee in this our pilgrimage: Thou ſeeſt the

heauen rolling aboue thine head in a conſtāt and vnmoueable motion; the ſtarres ſo ouer-looking one another, that the greateſt ſhewe little, the leaſt greateſt, all glorious; the ayre full of the bottles of raine, or fleeces of ſnowe, or diuers formes of fiery Exhalations: The ſea vnder one vniforme face full of ſtrange and monſtrous ſhapes beneath; the earth ſo adorned with variety of plants, that thou canſt not but tread

on many at once with euery foote; beſides the ſtore of creatures that flie aboue it, walke vpō it, liue in it: Thou idle Truant▪ doeſt thou learn nothing of ſo many maſters? haſt thou ſo long read theſe capitall letters of Gods great booke, and canſt thou not yet ſpell one worde of them? The brute creatures ſee the ſame things, with as cleare, perhaps better eyes: if thine inward eyes ſee not their vſe, aſwell as thy bodily eyes their

ſhape, I knowe not whether is more reaſonable, or leſſe brutiſh.
            
            
               
                  Chap. 5.
               
                  DEliberate Meditation Of Meditatiō Deliberate: Wherein firſt, is that wee chiefly inquire for; which both may be wel guided, and ſhall be not a little furthered by precepts; part whereof the labours of of others ſhall yeeld vs, and part the plaineſt miſtreſſe, Experience: Wherin order requires

of vs firſt the qualities The qualities of the perſon. of the perſon fit for meditatiō, thē the circumſtances, maner &amp; proceedings of the worke.
               The hill of Meditation may not be climbed with a profane foote; Of whom is required: Firſt, that he be pure from his ſinnes. But as in the deliuery of ye law, ſo here, no beaſt may touch Gods hill, leſt he die: only the pure of heart haue promiſe to ſee God: ſinne dimmeth &amp; dazeleth the eie that it cannot beholde ſpirituall things: The gard of heauenly Souldiers was about Eliſhaes
                  
ſeruant before, hee ſaw thē not before throgh the ſcales of his infidelity: The ſoule muſt therfore bee purged, ere it can profitably meditate. And as of old they were wont to ſearch for, and thruſt out malefactors frō the preſēce, ere they wēt to ſacrifice; ſo muſt we our ſins, ere we offer our thoughts to God. Firſt, ſaith Dauid, I will waſh my hands in innocencie, then I wil compas thine altar. Wherupō not vnfitly did that worthy Chauncellour

of Paris, make the firſt ſtaire of his Ladder of Contemplation, Humble Repentaunce. The cloth that is white (which is wont to bee the colour of innocencie) is capable of any Dye; the blacke, of none other: Not that we require an abſolute perfection (which as it is incident vnto none, ſo if it were, would exclude all neede and vſe of Meditation) but rather an honeſt ſincerity of the heart, not willingly ſinning, willingly

repenting when we haue ſinned; which, whoſo findes in himſelfe, let him not thinke any weakeneſſe a lawfull barre to Meditation. He that pleades this excuſe is like ſome ſimple man, which being halfe ſtarued with cold, refuſes to come neere the fire, becauſe hee finds not heate enough in himſelfe.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 6.
               
                  NEither may the Secondly, that he be free from worldly thoughts. ſoule that hopeth to profite by meditation, ſuffer it ſelfe for the time intāgled with the world; which is all one, as to come to GODS flaming buſh on the hill of viſions, with our ſhooes on our feete. Thou ſeeſt the birde, whoſe feathers are limed, vnable to take her former flight: ſo

are wee when our thoughts are clingd together by the world, to ſoare vp to our heauen in Meditation: The payre of brothers muſt leaue their nets if they wil folow Chriſt: Eliſha his oxen, if hee will attend a Prophet: It muſt bee a free and a light minde that can aſcend this Mount of Contemplation, ouercomming this height, this ſteepeneſſe: Cares are an heauie lode, and vneaſie; theſe muſt be laid downe at the bottome

of this hill, if wee euer looke to attain the top. Thou art loded with houſholde-cares, perhaps publike; I bid thee not caſt them away: euen theſe haue their ſeaſon, which thou canſt not omitte without impietie: I bid thee lay them downe at thy Cloſet doore, when thou attempteſt this worke: Let thē in with thee, thou ſhalt finde them troubleſom companions, euer diſtracting thee from thy beſt errand thou wouldeſt

thinke of heauen; thy Barne comes in thy way, or perhaps thy Count-booke, or thy Cofers, or it may bee thy minde is before hand trauailing vpon the morrowes iourney. So while thou thinkeſt of many things, thou thinkeſt of nothing; while thou wouldeſt goe many wayes, thou ſtandeſt ſtill. And as in a crowde, while many preſſe forward at once through one doore, none proceedeth: ſo whē variety of thoughts

tumultuouſly throng in vpon the minde, each prooueth a barre to the other, and all an hinderanceto him that entertaines them.
            
            
               
                  Chap. 7.
               
                  ANd as our Clyent of Thirdly that he be conſtant: and that, Firſt▪
                   Meditation muſt both be pure and free in vndertaking this taske, ſo alſo conſtant in continuing it; Conſtant both in time and in matter:

Both in a ſet courſe and In his ſet Tymes. houre reſerued for this worke, and in an vnwearied proſecution of it once begun. Thoſe that meditate by ſnatches and vncertaine fittes, when onely all other imploiments forſake thē, or when good motions are thruſt vpon them by neceſſity, let them neuer hope to reach to any perfection. For thoſe feeble beginnings of lukewarm grace, which are wroght in them by one fit of ſerious meditatiō,

are ſoone extinguiſhed by intermiſſion, and by miſ-wonting periſh: This dayes meale (tho large &amp; liberall) ſtrengthens thee not for to morrow; the body languiſhes if there be not a daily ſupply of repaſt: thus feede thy ſoule by meditation; Set thine houres and keep them, and yeeld not to an eaſie diſtraction. There is no hardneſſe in this practiſe, but in the beginning; vſe ſhall giue it, not eaſe onely, but delight. Thy companion

entertaines thee this while in louing diſcourſes, or ſome inexpected buſineſſe offers to interrupt thee. Neuer any good worke ſhall want ſome hinderance: Either breake through thy lettes, except it be with inciuility or loſſe; or if they bee importunate, pay thy ſelfe the time that was vnſeaſonably borrowed; and recompence thine omitted houres with the double labors of another day: For thou ſhalt find, that differring

breedes (beſide the loſſe) an indiſpoſition to good; So that what was before pleaſant to thee, being omitted, to morrow growes harſh; the next day vnneceſſary; afterwardes odious. To day thou canſt, but wilt not; to morrow thou couldſt, but liſteſt not; the next day thou neither wilt nor cāſt bend thy mind on theſe thoughts: So I haue ſeene friends that vpon neglect of duetie growe ouerly, vpon ouerlineſſe, ſtrange; vpon

ſtrangenes, to vtter defiance. Thoſe whoſe very trade is Diuinity (me thinks) ſhould omit no day without his line of Meditatiō: thoſe which are ſecular men, not many; remēbring that they haue a common calling of Chriſtianitie to attend, aſwel as a ſpeciall vocation in the worlde: and that other being more noble and important, may iuſtly challenge both often and diligent ſeruice.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 8.
               
                  ANd as this Cō
                  ſtancy Secondly, that he be Conſtant in the Cō
                     tinuance, requires thee to keepe day with thy ſelfe, vnleſſe thou wilt prooue bankrupt in good exerciſes; ſo alſo that thy mind ſhould dwell vpon the ſame thought without flitting, without wearineſſe, vntill it haue attained to ſome iſſue of ſpirituall profit: Otherwiſe it attempteth much, effecteth

nothing. What auailes it to knock at the doore of the heart, if wee depart ere we haue an anſwere? What are wee the warmer if we paſſe haſtily along by the hearth, ſtay not at it? Thoſe that doe onely trauell through Africke become not Blackemores, but thoſe which are borne there, thoſe that inhabit there: We account thoſe damoſels too light of their loue, which betroth themſelues vpon the firſt ſight, vpon the firſt motion:

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
&amp; thoſe we deeme of much price, which require long and earneſt ſoliciting: He deceiues himſelfe that thinkes grace ſo eaſily wonne; there muſt be much ſuit and importunitie ere it will yeeld to our deſires. Not that we call for a perpetuitie of this labour of Meditation; Humane frailty could neuer beare ſo great a toyle. Nothing vnder heauen is capable of a continuall motion without complaint: It is enough for

the glorified ſpirits aboue, to be euer thinking, &amp; neuer weary: the minde of man is of a ſtrange mettall; if it be not vſed, it ruſteth; if vſed hardly, it breaketh: briefly, is ſooner dulled, than ſatisfied with a continuall meditation: whēce it came to paſſe, that thoſe auncient Monks who intermeddled bodily labor with their contēplatiōs, proued ſo excellent in this diuine buſineſſe; when thoſe at this day, which hauing mewd &amp; mured

vp themſelues from the world ſpēd themſelues wholly vpō their beads and Crucifixe, pretending no other work but meditation, haue colde hearts to God, &amp; to the world ſhewe nothing but a dull ſhadowe of deuotion: for that (if the thoughts of theſe later were as diuine as they are ſuperſtitious) yet being without al interchangeablenes, bent vpon the ſame diſcourſe, the mind muſt needes growe weary, the thoughts remiſſe

and languiſhing, the obiects tedious: while the other refreſhed thē
                  ſelues with this wiſe varietie, imploying the hands, while they called of the mind, as good Comedians ſo mixe their partes, that the pleaſantnes of the one, may tēper the auſterenes of the other; whereupon they gained both enough to the body, &amp; to the ſoule more than if it had beene all the while buſied.
               Beſides, the excellencie of the obiect letteth

this aſſiduity of meditation; which is ſo glorious, that like vnto the Sunne, it may abide to haue an eye caſt vp to it for a while, will not be gazed vpon▪ whoſoeuer ventureth ſo farre, loſeth both his hope and his wits. If we hold with that bleſſed Monica, that ſuch like cogitations are the foode of the minde, yet euen the minde alſo hath her ſatietie, and may ſurfet of too much. It ſhall be ſufficient therefore, that wee perſeuere

in our meditation without any ſuch affectation of perpetuity, and leaue without a light fickleneſſe; making alwayes not our houre-glaſſe, but ſome competent increaſe of our deuotion, the meaſure of our continuance; knowing, that as for heauen, ſo for our purſuite of grace, it ſhall auaile vs little to haue begunne well, without perſeuerance: and withall that the Soule of man is not alwayes in the like

diſpoſition: but ſometimes is lōger in ſettling through ſome vnquietneſſe, or more obſtinate diſtraction; ſometimes heauier, and ſometimes more actiue, and nimble to diſpatch. Sauing our iuſt quarrel againſt him for the Councel of Conſtance. 
                  Gerſon (whoſe authoritie I rather vſe, becauſe our aduerſaries diſclaim him for theirs) profeſſeth, he hath been ſomtimes foure houres together working his heart, ere hee could frame it to purpoſe: A ſingular patterne of vnwearied conſtancie, of

an vnconquerable ſpirit; whom his preſent vnfitneſſe did not ſo much diſcourage, as it wherted him to ſtriue with himſelfe till hee could ouercome. And ſurely other victories are hazzardous, this certaine, if we will perſiſt to ſtriue: other fights are vpon hope, this vpon aſſurance; whiles our ſucceſſe depends vpon the promiſe of God, which cannot diſappoint vs: Perſiſt therfore, and preuaile; perſiſt till thou haſt preuailed:

ſo that which thou beganſt with difficultie, ſhall ende in comfort.
            
            
               
                  Chap. 9.
               
                  FRom the qualities of the perſon, Of the Circumſtances of Meditation. we deſcēd towards the action it ſelfe: where firſt wee meete with thoſe Circumſtances which are neceſſary for our prediſpoſition to the work; Place, Time, Site of bodie.
               
               
                  
                  Solitarineſſe of Place 
                  And therin, Firſt, Of the place. is fitteſt for Meditation: Retire thy ſelfe from others, if thou wouldſt talke profitably with thy ſelfe. So IESVS meditates alone in the Moūt, Iſaac in the fields, Iohn Baptiſt in the deſert, Dauid on his bed, Chryſoſtome in the bath, each in ſeuerall places; but all ſolitary. There is no place free frō God, none to which hee is more tied: one finds his cloſet moſt conueniēt, where his eies being limited by the knowen

walles, call in the mind after a ſort from wandering abroad; Another findes his ſoule more free whē it beholdeth his heauen aboue and about him; It matters not ſo we be ſolitarie and ſilent; It was a wittie and Diuine ſpeach of Bernard, that the ſpouſe of the foule, CHRIST IESVS, is baſhfull, neither willingly comes to his bride in the preſence of a multitude; And hence is that ſweete inuitation which wee

finde of her; Come my welbeloued, let vs goe foorth into the fields, let vs lodge in the villages: Let vs go up early to the vines; let vs ſee if the Vine flouriſh, whether it hath diſcloſed the firſt grape, or whether the Pomegranates bloſſome; there will I giue thee my loue. Abandon therefore all worldly ſocietie, that thou mayeſt change it for the company of GOD and his Angels; The ſociety, I ſay, of the worlde, not outward onely, but inward

alſo. There bee many that ſequeſter themſelues from the viſible company of men, which yet carie a world within them; who being alone in bodie are haunted with a throng of fancies: as Ierome, in his wildeſt deſert, foūd himſelfe too oft in his thoughts amongſt the daunces of the Roman dames; This company is worſe than the other: for it is more poſſible for ſome thoughtfull men to haue a ſolitary mind in the midſt

of a market, than for a man thus diſpoſed to be alone in a wildernes; Both companies are enemies to Meditation; Whither tendeth that anciēt coūſell of a great Maſter in this Arte, of three thingsrequiſite to this buſines, Secrecy, Silence, Reſt: whereof the firſt excludeth company, the ſecond noiſe, the third motion. It cannot be ſpoken how ſubiect wee are in this worke, to diſtraction; Like Salomons old man whome the noyſe of

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
euery bird wakeneth: ſenſuall delights we are not drawen from with the threefold cords of iudgmēt; but our ſpiritual pleaſures are eaſily hindered. Make choice therefore of that place, which ſhall admit the feweſt occaſiōs of withdrawing thy ſoule from good thoughts: wherin alſo euen change of place is ſomewhat preiudiciall; and I knowe not how it fals out, that we find God neerer vs in the place where wee haue been accuſtomed

familiarlie to meete him: Not for that his preſence is confined to one place aboueothers, but that our thoughts are through cuſtome more eaſily gathered to the place where wee haue ordinarily conuerſed with him.
            
            
               
                  Chap. 10.
               
                  ONe Time cā
                  not Secondly, of the Time. bee preſcribed to al: For neither God bound to hours;

neither doeth the contrary diſpoſitiō of men agree in one choice of opportunities: the golden houres of the morning ſome finde fitteſt for Meditation, when the body newly raiſed, is well calmed with his late reſt, and the ſoule hath not as yet had frō theſe outward things any motiues of alienation: Others find it beſt to learne wiſedome of their reines in the night▪ hoping, with Iob, that their bedde will bring them comfort in their

meditation; when both all other things are ſtill; and themſelues wearied with theſe earthly cares, doe out of a contempt of them, growe into greater liking and loue of heauēly things: I haue euer found Iſaacs time fitteſt, who went out in the euening to meditate. No precept, no practiſe of others can preſcribe to vs in this circumſtance: It ſhall bee enough, that firſt we ſet our ſelues a time; ſecondly, that we ſet apart that time,

wherein wee are apreſt for this ſeruice: And as no time is preiudiced with vnfitneſſe, but euery day is without differēce ſeaſonable for this worke, ſo eſpecially Gods day; No day is barren of grace to the ſearcher of it, none alike fruitfull to this; which being by God ſanctified to himſelfe, and to bee ſanctified by vs to God, is priuiledged with bleſſings aboue others: for the plentifull inſtruction of that day ſtirtes thee vp

to this action, and filles thee with matter; and the zeale of thy publike ſeruice warms thy heart to this other buſineſſe of deuotion. No MANNA fell to the Iſraelites on their Sabaoth; our ſpiritual MANNA fals on ours, moſt frequent: If thou wouldeſt haue a full ſoule, gather as it fals; gather it by hearing, reading, meditatiō: ſpiritual idleneſſe is a fault this day, perhaps not leſſe than bodily worke.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 11.
               
                  NEither is ther eſſe variety Of the Site and geſture of the body. in the Site and geſture of the body: the due compoſednes whereof is no little aduantage to this exerciſe; euen in our ſpeach to God, we obſerue not alwaies one and the ſame poſition; ſometimes we fall groueling on our faces, ſomtimes we bow our knees, ſometimes ſtand

on our feete, ſomtimes we lift vp our handes, ſometimes caſt downe our eyes. God is a Spirit, who therefore being a ſeuere obſeruer of the diſpoſition of the ſoule, is not ſcrupulous for the body; requiring not ſo much, that the geſture thereof ſhould be vniforme as reuerēt: No maruell therefore, though in this, all our teachers of meditation haue commended ſeueral poſitions of body, according to their diſpoſition and practiſe;

                  Gerſon. One ſitting with the face turned vp to heauen-ward, according to the precept of the Philoſopher, who taught him, that by ſitting and reſting, the mind gathereth wiſedome: Guliel. Pariſ. Another leaning to ſome reſt towardes the left ſide, for the greater quieting of the heart: Dionyſ. Carthuſ. A third ſtanding with the eyes lift vp to heauen, but ſhut for feare of diſtractiōs; But of all other (mee thinkes) Iſaacs choice the beſt, who meditated

walking. In this let euery man be his owne maſter; ſo bee wee vſe that frame of body that may both teſtifie reuerence, and in ſome caſes help to ſtirre vp further deuotion; which alſo muſt needes be varied according to the matter of our Meditation. If we thinke of our ſins, Ahabs ſoft paſe, the Publicans deiected eyes, and his hand beating his breaſt, are not vnſeaſonable: If of the ioies of heauen, Steuens countenance fixed aboue,

and Dauids hands lift vp on hie, are moſt fitting; In all which the body, as it is the inſtrument and vaſſall of the ſoule, ſo will eaſily follow the affections therof; and in trueth then is our deuotion moſt kindly, whē the body is thus commaunded his ſeruice by the ſpirit, and not ſuffered to goe before it, and by his forwardneſſe to prouoke his maſter to emulation.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 12.
               
                  NOw time and order cal vs frō 
                  Of the matter &amp; Subiect of our meditation. theſe circumſtances to the matter and ſubiect of Meditation: which muſt be Diuine &amp; Spiritual; not euill, nor worldly. O the carnal and vnprofitable thoughts of men! We all meditate; one how to do ill to others; another how to doe ſome earthly good to himſelfe; another to hurt himſelfe, vnder a colour

of good; as how to accompliſh his lewd deſires, the fulfilling whereof prooues the bane of the ſoule, how he may ſinne vnſeene, and goe to hell with leaſt noiſe of the world: Or perhaps ſome better mindes bend their thoughts vpō the ſearch of naturall things; the motions of euery heauen, and of euery ſtarre; the reaſon and courſe of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea; the manifold kinds of ſimples that growe out of the

earth, &amp; creatures that creepe vpon it; with all their ſtrange qualities, and operatiōs; Or perhaps the ſeueral formes of gouernement, and rules of State take vp their buſie heads, ſo that while they would bee acquainted with the whole world, they are ſtrangers at home; and while they ſeeke to knowe all other things, they remain vnknowen of thēſelues: The God that made them, the vileneſſe of their nature, the danger of their

ſinnes, the multitude of their imperfections, the Sauior that bought them, the heauen that he bought for them, are in the meane time as vnknowen, as vnregarded, as if they were not.
               Thus do fooliſh children ſpend their time and labour in turning ouer leaues to looke for painted babes, not at all reſpecting the ſolide matter vnder their hāds. We fooles, when will we be wiſe, and turning our eyes from vanity with that ſweete ſinger

of Iſrael, make Gods Statutes our ſong, and meditation in the houſe of our pilgrimage?
               Earthly things profer themſelues with importunity; Heauenly things muſt with importunitie bee ſued to. Thoſe, if they were not ſo little worth, would not be ſo forward; and being ſo forward, need not any meditation to ſolicite them: Theſe by how much more hard they are to intreate, by ſo much more precious they are being obtained;

and therfore worthier our indeuour: As then we cannot goe amiſſe, ſo long as wee keepe our ſelues in the tracke of Diuinitie; while the ſoule is taken vp with the thoughts, either of the Deitie in his eſſence, and perſons (ſparingly yet in this point, and more in faith and admiration then inquiry) or of his attributes, his iuſtice, power, wiſedome, mercie, trueth; or of his works, in the creation, preſeruation, gouernement

of all things, according to the Pſalmiſt, I will meditate of the beautie of thy glorious Maieſtie, and thy wonderfull workes; ſo moſt directly in our way, and beſt fitting our exerciſe of Meditation are thoſe matters in Diuinity, which can moſt of all worke compunction in the hart, &amp; moſt ſtirre vs vp to deuotiō: Of which kind are the Meditatiōs concerning CHRIST IESVS, our Mediatour, his Incarnation, Miracles, Life, Paſſion, Burial,

Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, Interceſſiō, the benefit of our Redēption, the certaintie of our Election, the graces and proceeding of our ſanctification, our glorious eſtate in Paradiſe loſt in our firſt Parents, our preſent vilenes, our inclination to ſin, our ſeuerall actuall offences; the tētations &amp; ſleights of euill Angels, the vſe of the Sacraments, nature &amp; practiſe of faith &amp; repentance: the miſeries of our-life, with the frailty of it, the certainty

and vncertainty of our death, the glory of Gods Saints aboue, the awfulnes of iudgement, the terrors of hel, and the reſt of this qualitie: wherein both it is fit to haue variety (for that euen the ſtrongeſt ſtomacke doeth not alwayes delight in one diſh) &amp; yet ſo to chāge, that our choice may be free from wildneſſe and inconſtancie.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 13.
               
                  NOW after that we haue The order of the worke it ſelfe. thus orderly ſuited the perſon &amp; his qualities, with the due circūſtances of Time, Place, diſpoſition of body, and ſubſtance of the matter diſcuſſed; I knowe not what can remaine, beſides the maine buſines it ſelfe, and the maner and degrees of our proſecution thereof; which

aboue all other calles for an intentiue Reader, and reſolute practiſe; Wherein, that we may auoide all niceneſſe and obſcurity (ſince wee ſtriue to profit) we will giue direction for the Entrance, Proceeding, Concluſion of this Diuine worke.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 14.
               
                  A Goodly building The Entrāce into the worke. muſt ſhew ſome magnificence in the gate: and great perſonages haue ſeemely Vſhers to goe before them; who by their vncouered heads commaund reuerence and way; Euen verie Poets of old had wont, before their Ballads, to implore the aid of their Gods: And the heathen

                  Romans entred not vpō any publike ciuile buſines, without a ſolemne apprecation of good ſucceſſe: How much leſſe ſhould a Chriſtian dare to vndertake a ſpirituall 1. The cō
                     mon entrance, which is Prayer. worke of ſuch importāce, not hauing craued the aſſiſtance of his GOD? which (me thinkes) is no leſſe, than to profeſſe hee could doe well without Gods leaue. When we thinke euill, it is frō our ſelues, when good from God. As prayer is our ſpeach to God, ſo is each good

Meditation (according to Bernard) GODS ſpeach to the heart; The heart muſt ſpeake to God, that God may ſpeake to it. Prayer therefore, and Meditation are as thoſe famous twinnes in the ſtorie, or as two louing Turtles, whereof ſeparate one, the other languiſhes.
               Prayer makes way for Meditation; Meditation giues matter, ſtrength, and life to our prayers. By which, as all other things are ſanctified

to vs, ſo we are ſanctified to all holy things: This is as ſome royall Eunuch to perfume and dreſſe our ſoules, that they may be fit to conuerſe with the King of heauen.
               But the prayer that leades in Meditation would not be long, requiring rather that the extenſion and length ſhould be put into the vigor and feruencie of it; for that it is not here intended to be the principall buſineſſe, but an introductiō to another;

and no otherwiſe than as a Portall to this building of Meditation: The matter whereof ſhall be, that the courſe of our Meditation may bee guided aright and bleſſed; that all diſtractions may be auoided; our iudgements inlightened, our inuentions quickned, our willes rectified, our affections whetted to heauenly things, our harts enlarged to God-ward, our deuotion enkindled; ſo that we may finde our corruptiōs abated, our

graces thriuē, ourſoules &amp; liues euery way bettered by this exerciſe.
            
            
               
                  Chap. 15.
               
                  SVch is the cō
                  mon Particular &amp; proper entrance into the matter, which is in our choice thereof. entrance into this work: There is another yet more particular &amp; proper; wherein the mind recollecting it ſelf, maketh choice of that Theme or matter wherupon it will beſtowe it ſelfe for the preſent; ſettling it ſelfe on that

which it hath choſen: which is done by an inward inquiſition made into our heart of what we both doe, &amp; ſhould thinke vpon: reiecting what is vnexpedient &amp; vnprofitable: In both which, the ſoule, like vnto ſome noble Hauk, lets paſſe the Crowes, and Larkes, and ſuch other worthleſſe birdes that croſſe her way, and ſtoopeth vpon a foule of price, worthy of her flight: after this manner,
               
                  What wilt thou muze
                  
                  vpon, O my ſoule? thou ſeeſt how little it auailes thee to wander and roue about in vncertainties: thou findeſt how little ſauour there is in theſe earthly things, wherewith thou haſt wearied thy ſelfe; Trouble not thy ſelf any longer (with Martha) about the many &amp; needleſſe thoughts of the world: None but heauenly things can afford thee comfort: Vp then my ſoule, and mind thoſe things that are aboue, whence thy ſelfe art: Amongst all which,
                  
                  whereon ſhouldeſt thou rather meditate than of the life &amp; glory of Gods Saints. A worthier employment thou canſt neuer finde, than to thinke vpon that eſtate, thou ſhalt once poſſeſſe, and now deſireſt.
               
            
            
               
                  Chap. 16.
               
                  HItherto the Entrāce; after The proceeding of our meditation. which our Meditation muſt Proceed in due order, not troubledly, not prepoſterouſly: It

begins in the vnderſtā
                  ding, ends in the affections; It begins in the braine, deſcends to the heart; Begins on earth, aſcends to heauen; Not ſuddenly, but by certain ſtaires &amp; degrees, til we come to the higheſt.
               I haue found a ſubtill And therin a Methode allowed by ſome authors, reiected by vs. Scale of Meditation, admired by ſome profeſſors of this Arte, aboue all other humane deuiſes; and farre preferred by them to the beſt directiōs of Origen, Auſten, Bernard, Hugo, Bonauenture, Gerſon,
                  
and whoſoeuer hath been reputed of greateſt perfection in this skil: The ſeueral ſtaires whereof (leſt I ſhould ſeeme to defraud my Reader through enuie) I would willingly deſcribe, were it not that I feared to ſcarre him rather with the danger of obſcurity, from venturing further vpon this ſo worthy a buſineſſe: yet, leſt any man perhaps might complaine of an vnknowen loſſe, my Margent ſhall find roume for that, which I

hold too knotty for my Text.
               
                  
                     
                        The ſcale of Meditation of an Author, ancient, but nameleſſe.
                        * Degrees of Preparation.
                           
                              1. Queſtion.
                              
                              What I

                                    thinke.
                                    ſhould think.
                                 
                              
                              2. Excuſſion.
                              
                              A repelling of what I ſhould not thinke.
                              3. Choice, or Election.
                              
                              Of what moſt

                                    neceſſary.
                                    expedient
                                    comely.
                                 
                              
                           
                        
                        * Degrees of proceeding in the vnderſtanding.
                           
                              4. Commemoration.
                              
                              An actual thinking vpon the matter elected.
                              5 Conſeleration.
                              
                              A redoubled Commemoration of the ſame, till it be fully knowen.
                              6. Attention.
                              
                              A fixed and earneſt cōſideratiō: wherby it is faſtened in the mind.
                              7 Explanation.
                              
                              A cleering of the thing conſidered by ſimilitudes.
                              8 Tractation.
                              
                              An extending the thing conſidered to other points: where all queſtions of doubt are diſcuſſed.
                              9. Diindication.
                              
                              An eſtimation of the worth of the thing thus handled.
                              10. Conſ
                                       •
                                    tion
                              
                              A confirmation of the eſtimation thus made
                              11. Rumination.
                              
                              A ſad and ſerious Meditation of all the former, till it may worke vpon the affections.
                           
                        
                        From hence to the degrees of affection.
                     
                   In all which, (after the incredible commendations of ſome practicioners) I doubt not but an ordinary Reader will eaſily eſpie a double fault at the leaſt, Darkeneſſe and Coincidence; that they are both too obſcurely deliuered, and that diuers of them fal into other, not without ſom vain

ſuperfluity. For this part therfore which cōcerneth the vnderſtāding, I had rather to require only a deep and firme Conſideration of the thing propounded; which ſhall be done, if we followe it in our diſcourſe, through all, or the principall of thoſe places which natural reaſō doth afford vs: wherein let no man plead ignorāce,

or feare difficulty: we are all thus farre borne Logicians; Neither is there in this ſo much need of skil, as of induſtry. In which cours yet, we may not be too curious in a preciſe ſearch of euery place, &amp; argumēt without omiſſiō of any (though to be fetcht in with racking the inuētiō). For as the mind, if it go looſe and without rule, roues to no purpoſe; ſo if it be too much fettred with the giues of ſtrict regularity moueth nothing at all.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 17.
               
                  ERe I enter Premonitions concerning our proceeding in the firſt part of Meditation. therfore into any particular tractatiō, There are three things whereof I would premoniſh my Reader, concerning this firſt part which is in the vnderſtanding. Firſt, that I deſire not to binde euery man to the ſame vniforme proceeding in this part. Practiſe and cuſtome may perhaps

haue taught other courſes more familiar, and not leſſe direct: If then we can, by anie other method, worke in our hearts ſo deepe an apprehenſion of the matter meditated, as it may duely ſtirre the affections, it is that only wee require.
               Secondly, that whoſoeuer applieth himſelf to this direction, thinke him not neceſſarily tyed to the proſecution of all theſe Logicall places, which hee findes in the ſequell of our

Treatiſe, ſo as his Meditation ſhould be lame and imperfect without the whole number: for ther are ſome Themes which wil not beare all theſe; as when we meditate of God, there is no roume for Cauſes or Compariſons; &amp; others yeeld thē with ſuch difficultie, that their ſearch interrupteth the chiefe work intēded: It ſhalbe ſufficient if we take the moſt pregnant, &amp; moſt voluntary.
               Thirdly, that whē we ſticke in the diſquiſitiō
                  
of any the places following, as if meditating of Sin, I cannot readily meet with the Material &amp; Formal Cauſes, or the Appendances of it, wee rack not our minds too much with the inquiry thereof; which were to ſtriue more for Logique, than deuotion: But without too much diſturbaunce of our thoughts, quietly paſſe ouer to the next. If we breake our teeth with the ſhell, we ſhall finde ſmall pleaſure in the kernell.
               
                  
Now then, for that my onely feare is, leſt this part of my diſcourſe ſhall ſeeme ouer perplexed vnto the vnlearned Reader; I will in this whole proceſſe, ſecond my rule with his example; that ſo what might ſeeme obſcure in the one, may by the other be explaned; and the ſame ſteps he ſees me take in this, hee may accordingly treade in any other Theme.
            
            
               
               Chap. 18.
               
               
                  FIrſt therfore The practiſe of Meditation; wherin Firſt, wee begin with ſome deſcription of that we meditate of. it ſhalbe expedient to conſider ſeriouſly, what the thing is whereof wee meditate.
               What then, O my ſoule, is the life of the Saints, whereof thou ſtudieſt? who are the Saints, but thoſe which hauing been weakely holy vpon earth, are perfectly holy aboue? which euen on earth

were perfectly holy in their Sauiour, now are ſo in themſelues? Which, ouercomming on earth, are truely canonized in heauen? What is their life, but that bleſſed eſtate aboue, wherein their glorified ſoule hath a full fruition of God?
            
            
               
               Chap. 19.
               
               
                  THe nature wherof after Secondly, followes an eaſie &amp; voluntary diuiſion of the matter meditated we haue thus ſhadowed out to our ſelues by a deſcriptiō, not curious alwaies, &amp; exactly framed according to the rules of arte, but ſufficient for our own conceit; the next is (if it ſhal ſeeme needfull, or if the matter will beare, or offer it) ſome eaſie and voluntary diuiſion, whereby our thoughts

ſhall haue more roume made for them, and our proceeding ſhall bee more diſtinct.
               There is a life of nature, whē thou, my ſoule, dwelleſt in this body, and informeſt thine earthly burden: There is a life of grace, when the ſpirit of God dwels in thee; There is a life of glory, whē thy body being vnited to thee, both ſhall bee vnited to God; or when, in the meane time, being ſeparated from thy companiō, thou enioyeſt God alone: This life of thine

therefore, as the other, hath his ages, hath his ſtatures; for it enters vpon his birth, whē thou paſſeſt out of thy body, and changeſt this earthly houſe for an heauenly: It enters into his full vigor, when at the day of the common reſurrection, thou reſumeſt this thy companion, vnlike to it ſelfe, like to thee, like to thy Sauiour, immortall now, and glorious. In this life there may be degrees, there can be no imperfection: If ſome be like the skie, others like

the ſtarres, yet all ſhine; If ſome ſit at their Sauiours right hand, others at his left, all are bleſſed; If ſome veſſels hold more, all are full; none complaynes of want, none enuies at him that hath more.
            
            
               
               Chap. 20.
               
               
                  
                     WHich done it ſhalbe requiſite 
                  3. A conſideration of the cauſes therof in al kinds of them. 
                  for our perfiter vnderſtanding, and for the laying grounds of matter for our affection, to carie it through thoſe other principall places, and heads of reaſon, which nature hath taught euery man, both for knowledge &amp; amplification: The firſt whereof are the Cauſes of all ſorts.
               
               
                  
Whence is this eternal life, but from him which onely is eternall; which onely is the fountaine of life, yea, life it ſelfe? Who but the ſame God that giues our temporall life, giues alſo that eternall? The Father beſtowes it, the Sonne merits it, the holy Ghoſt ſeales and applies it: Expect it onely from him, O my ſoule, whoſe frecelectiō gaue thee the firſt title to it, to bee purchaſed by the blood of thy Sauiour. For thou ſhall not therefore be happie,

becauſe hee ſawe thou wouldeſt bee good; but therefore art thou good, becauſe he hath ordained thou ſhalt be happie: He hath ordained thee to life; he hath giuen thee a Sauiour to giue this life vnto thee; faith, whereby thou mighteſt attaine to this Sauiour; his word, by which thou might'ſt attaine to this faith; what is there in this, not 
                     •
                  is? And yet not ſo his 
                     ••
                  mply, as that it is without thee: without thy merit indeed, not without thine acte; Thou liueſt

here through his bleſſing, but by bread; thou ſhalt liue aboue through his mercy, but by thy faith belowe, apprehending the authour of thy life: And yet as he wil not ſaue thee without thy faith, ſo thou canst neuer haue faith without his gift; Looke vp to him therefore, O my ſoule, as the beginner &amp; finiſher of thy ſaluation; and while thou magnifieſt the Author, be rauiſhed with the glorie of the worke: which farre paſſeth both the tongue of

Angels, and the heart of man: It can bee no good thing that is not there; Howe can they want water that haue the ſpring? where God is enioyed in whom only all things are good, what good can bee wanting? And what perfection of bliſſe is there where all goodneſſe is mette and vnited? In thy preſence is the fulneſſe of ioye, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for evermore: O bleſſed reflection of glorie! wee 
                     ••
                  e there, as wee are

ſeene: In that wee are ſeene, it is our glorie; in that wee ſee, it is Gods glory; Therefore doth he glorifie vs, that our glory ſhould bee to his. Howe worthy art thou, ô Lord, that through vs thou ſhouldest looke at thy ſelfe!
            
            
               Chap. 21.
               
               
                  
                     THE next place 
                  4. The Conſid. of the Fruits &amp; Effects. 
                  place ſhalbe the Fruits &amp; Effectes following vpon their ſeuerall
                  
                  cauſes: which alſo affoords very feeling and copious matter to our Meditation; wherein it ſhall be euer beſt, not ſo much to ſeeke for all, as to chuſe out the chiefeſt.
               
               No maruell then if from this glory proceede nonſpeakeable ioy, and from this ioy the ſweete ſongs of praiſe &amp; thākſgiuing. The ſpirit bids vs, when wee are merrie, ſing: How much more then, when wee are merrie without all mixture of ſorrowe, beyond all

meaſure of our earthly affections, ſhall wee ſing ioyfull Hallelu-iahs, and Hoſannahs to him that dwelleth in the highest heauens? Our hearts ſhal be ſo full that we cannot chuſe but ſing, and wee cannot but ſing melodiouſly; There is no iarre in this Muſicke, no end of this ſong. Obleſſed chāge of the Saints; they doe nothing but weepe belowe, and now nothing but ſing aboue; we ſowed in teares, reape inioy; there was ſome comfort in thoſe teares, when

they were at worſt; but there is no danger of cō
                  plaint in this heauenly mirth; If we cannot ſing here with the Angels, On earth peace, yet there wee ſhall ſing with them, Glory to God on hie; and ioyning our voices to theirs, ſhall make vp that celeſtial conſort, which none can either heare or beare part in, and not be happie.
            
            
               
               Chap. 22.
               
               
                  
                     AFter which 
                  
                     5. Conſideratiō of the Subiect, wherin, or wherabout it is.
                   
                  comes to be conſidered the Subiect either wherein that is, or whereabout that is imployed, which wee meditate of: As,
               
               And indeede, what leſſe happineſſe doth the very place promiſe, wherein this glory is exhibited? which is no other than the Paradiſe of God: Here belowe wee

dwell, or rather we wander in a continued wilderneſſe; there wee ſhall reſt vs in the true Eden; I am come into my gardē, my ſiſter, my ſpouſe. Kings vſe not to dwell in Cottages of clay; but in Royal Courts ſit for their eſtate: How much more ſhall the King of heauen, who hath prepared for men ſo faire manſions on earth, make himſelfe an habitation ſutable to his Maieſtie: Euen earthly Princes haue dwelt in Cedar and Yuory: but the great Citie, Holy Ieruſalem,
                  
the palace of the hieſt hath her wall of Iaſper, her building of gold, her foundation of precious ſtones, her gates of pearle: How glorious things are ſpoken of thee, O thou Citie of GOD! Wee ſee but the pauement, and yet how goodly it is! The beleeuing Centurion thought himſelfe vnworthy that Chriſt ſhould come vnder his roofe; yet then wert thou, O Sauiour, in thine humbled eſtate, in the forme of a ſeruant: How then ſtall I thinke

my ſelfe worthy to come vnder this roof of thine, ſo ſhining and glorious? O if this clay of mine may come to this honour aboue, let it bee trampled vpon and deſpiſed on earth.
            
            
               Chap. 23.
               
               
                  
                     SIxtly, ſhall 
                  
                     6. Conſid▪ of the Appendances, and Qualities of it.
                   
                  followe the Appēdances, and Qualities, which cleaue vnto the Subiect, wherof we meditate: As,
               
               But were the place leſſe

noble and maieſticall, yet the company which it affords, hath enough to make the ſoule bleſſed: For not the place giues ornament to the gueſt, ſo much as the gueſt to the place. How loath are we to leaue this earth, onely for the ſocietie of ſome few friends in whom we delight? which yet are ſubiect euery day to mutuall diſlikes: what pleaſure ſhall wee then take in the enioying of the Saints? when there is nothing in them not amiable, nothing in vs that

may coole the feruor of our loue. There ſhalt thou my ſoule, thy ſelfe glorified, meete with thy deare Parēts and friends alike glorious, neuer to be ſeuered: There ſhalt thou ſee and conuerſe with thoſe ancient worthies of the former worlde; the bleſſed Patriarkes and Prophets, with the crowned Martyrs and Cōfeſſors; with the holy Apoſtles, and the Fathers of that Primitiue, and this preſent Church, ſhining each one according to the meaſure

of his bleſſed labours. There ſhalt thou liue familiarly in ſight of thoſe Angels, whom now thou receiueſt good from, but ſeest not. There (which is the head of all thy felicitie) thine eyes ſhall ſee him whom now thine heart longeth for (that Sauiour of thine) in the onely hope of whom now thou liuest. Alas how dimmely, and a farre off doest thou now beholde him? howe imperfectly doeſt thou enioy him? while euery tēptation bereaues thee, for the time,

of his preſence. I ſought him whom my ſoule loueth: I ſought him, but I found him not; his backe is now towards thee many times throgh thy ſins, and therfore thou hardly diſcerneſt him: Otherwhile and ofter thy back is turned to him through negligence, that when thou mighteſt obſcurelie ſee him, thou doest not: Now thou ſhalt ſee him, and thine eyes thus fixed ſhall not be remooued. Yet neither could this glory make vs happy, if being thus abſolute,

it were not perpetuall. To be happie, is not ſo ſweete a ſtate, as it is miſerable to haue beene happie. Leaſt ought therfore ſhould bee wanting beholde, this felicitie knoweth no end, feareth no intermiſſion, and is as eternall for the continuance, as hee that had no beginning. O bleſſednes, truly infinite! Our earthly ioyes doe ſcarce euer begin; but when they begin, their ende borders vpon their beginning. One houre ſees vs oft-times ioyful and miſerable:

Here alone is nothing but eternitie. If then the diuine Prophet thought one day in Gods earthly houſe, better than a thouſand other-where; what ſhall I compare to thouſands of millions of yeeres in Gods heauenly Temple? Yea, millions of yeeres are not ſo much as a minute to eternitie, and that other houſe not a cottage to this.
            
            
               
               Chap. 24.
               
               
                  
                     SEuenthly, our 
                  
                     7. Of that which is Diuers frō it, or Contrary to it.
                   
                  thoughts leauing a while the conſideratiō of the thing as it is in it ſelfe, ſhal deſcēd vnto it as reſpectiuely with others; and therefore firſt ſhall meditate of that which is Diuers from it, or Cō
                  trary vnto it.
               
               What doest thou here then, O my ſoule? What doeſt thou here groueling

vpon earth? where the best things are vanity; the reſt no better than vexation. Looke round about thee, and ſee whether thine eyes can meet with any thing but either ſinnes or miſeries. Thoſe few and ſhort pleaſures thou ſcest, end euer ſorrowfully; and in the mean time are intermingled with many grieuances. Here thou heareſt one crie out of a ſicke bodie, whereof ther is no part which affords not choice of diſeaſes; This man layes his hande vpon

his conſuming lungs, and complayneth of ſhorte winde; that other, vpon his riſing ſpleene, a third ſhaketh his painefull head; another roares out for the torment of his reines or bladder; another for the racking of his goutie ioyntes; one is diſtempered with a watery dropſie, another with a windy Colicke, a third with a fiery ague, a fourth with an earthen Melancholie; one grouels and fometh with the falling ſicknes, another lies bed ridde

halfe ſenſeleſſe with a dead Palſey: Ther are but few bodies that complaine not of ſome diſeaſe; and that thou mayſt not looke farre, it is a wonder if thy ſelf feele not alwayes one of theſe euils within thee. There, thou heareſt another lament his loſſes: either his eſtate is impayred by ſuretyſhip, or ſtealth, or ſhipwracke, or oppreſſion; or his childe is vnruly, or miſcarried; or his wife dead or diſloyall; Another tormēted with paſſions; Each one is

ſome way miſerable: But that which is yet more irkeſome; thy one eare is beatē with curſings and blaſphemies; thy other with ſcornefull, or wanton, or murdering ſpeaches; thine eyes ſee nothing but pride filthines, profaneneſſe, blood, exceſſe; and whatſoeuer elſe might vexe a righteous ſoule: and if all the world beſides were innocent, thou findeſt enough within thy ſelfe, to make thy ſelfe weary, and thy life loathſom: Thou needeſt not fetch cauſe of

complaint from others; thy corruptiōs yeeld thee too much at home; euer ſinning, euer preſuming; Sinning euen when thou haſt repented, yea, euen while thou repenteſt, ſinning. Goe to nowe, my ſoule, and ſolace thy ſelfe here belowe, and ſuffer thy ſelfe beſotted with theſe goodly cōtentmēts; worthy of no better while thou fixeſt thy ſelfe on theſe: ſee if thou cāſt find any of theſe aboue; and if thou canſt meete with any diſtemper, any loſſe, any ſinne, any complaint,

frō thy ſelfe or any other aboue, deſpiſe thine heauen as much as now thou loueſt the earth. Or if all this cannot enough commend vnto thee the ſtate of heauenly glory, caſt down thine eyes yet lower, into that deep &amp; bottomles pit, ful of horror, full of torment, where there is nothing but flames, and teares, and ſhrikes, and gnaſhing of teeth; nothing but fiends and tortures: where there is palpable darkeneſſe, and yet perpetuall fire; where the damned

are euer boyling, neuer conſumed; euer dying, neuer dead; euer complaining, neuer pitied; where the Glutton, that once would not giue a cruſt of bread, now begs for one drop of water; and yet alas, if whole riuers of water ſhould fall into his mouth, howe ſhould they quench thoſe riuers of brimſtone that feede this flame? where there is no intermiſſion of complaints, no breathing from paine, and after millions of yeeres, no poſſibility of comfort:

And if the rod wherewith thou chaſtiſeſt thy children, O Lord, euen in this life be ſo ſmart and galling, that they haue been brought downe to the brim of deſpaire; and in the bitterneſſe of their ſoule haue intreated death to releaſe them: What ſhal I think of their plagues in whoſe righteous confuſion thou inſulteſt; and ſayest, Aha, I wil auenge me of mine enemies? Euen that thou ſhalt not bee thus miſerable, O my ſoule, is ſome kind of happines;

but that thou ſhalt bee as happie, as the reprobate are miſerable, how worthy is it of more eſtimation, than thy ſelfe is capable of?
            
            
               Chap. 25.
               
               
                  AFterthis oppoſitiō 
                  8. Of cō
                     pariſons and ſimilitudes whereby it may bee moſt fitly ſet forth. the mind ſhall make cō
                  pariſon of the matter meditated with what may neereſt reſemble it; and ſhall illuſtrate it with fitteſt ſimilitudes, which giue no ſmall

light to the vnderſtanding nor leſſe force to the affection.
               Wonder then, O my ſoule, as much as thou canſt, at this glory; and in compariſon thereof, contemne this earth, which now thou treadeſt vpon; whoſe ioyes, if they were perfect, are but ſhort; and if they were long, are imperfect: One day when thou art aboue, looking downe from the height of thy glory, and ſeeing the ſons of men creeping like ſo many Ants on this molehill

of earth, thou ſhalt thinke: Alas how baſely I once liued! was yonder ſilly dungeon the place I ſo loued, and was ſo loath to leaue! Thinke ſo now before-hand; and ſince of heauē thou canſt not, yet account of the earth, as it is worthy: How hartleſſe and irkeſome are yee, O yee beſt earthly pleaſures, if ye be matched with the least of thoſe aboue? Howe vile are you, O ye ſumptuous buildings of kings, euen if all the entrailes of the earth had agreed

to enrich you, in compaſon of this frame not made with hands? It is not ſo hie aboue the earth in diſtance of place, as in worth and maieſtie: we may ſee the face of heauen from the heart of the earth; but from the neereſt part of the earth who can ſee the leaſt glory of heauen? The three diſciples on mount Tabor, ſawe but a glimpſe of this glory ſhining vpon the face of their Sauiour; and yet being rauiſhed with the ſight, cryed out, Maſter, It is good

being here; and thinking of building of three Tabernacles, for Chriſt, Moſes, Elias, could haue been content themſelues to haue lien without ſhelter, ſo they might alwaies haue enioyed that ſight: Alas, how could earthly Tabernacles haue fitted thoſe heuēly bodies? They knewe what they ſawe, what they ſaid they knew not: Lo theſe 3. diſciples were not trāsfigured; yet how deeply they were affected, euē with the glory of others? how happy ſhal wee be, when our ſelues

ſhal be changed into glorious? and ſhall haue Tabernacles not of our own making, but prepared for vs by God? and yet not Tabernacles, but eternal manſions. Moſes ſawe God but a while, and ſhined; How ſhal we ſhine that ſhal behold his face for euer? What greater honour is there than in Souereignty? what greater pleaſure than in feaſting? This life is both a kingdome and a feast. A kingdome: He that ouercomes, ſhall rule the nations, and ſhall ſit
                  
                  with me in my Throne: O bleſſed promotion, Oh large dominion, and royall ſeate! to which Salomons throne of yuory was not worthy to become a footeſtoole. A feast; Bleſſed are they that are called to the Marriage ſupper of the Lambe: Feaſtes haue more than neceſſitie of prouiſion, more than ordinary diet; but marriage-feaſts yet more than common abundance; But the marriage-feaſt of the Sonne of God to his bleſſed ſpouſe the Church,

muſt ſo farre exceed in all heauenly munificence and varietie, as the perſons are of greater State and Maieſtie: There is new wine, pure Manna, and all manner of ſpirituall dainties; and with the continuall cheare, a ſweete and aunſwerable welcome; while the bridegrome louingly cheares vs vp, Eate, O Friends, drinke &amp; make you merrie, O welbeloued: yea, There ſhalt thou be my ſoule not a gueſt, but (how vnworthy ſoeuer) the Bride her ſelfe;

whom hee hath euerlaſtingly eſpouſed to himſelfe in truth and righteouſneſſe; The contract is paſſed here belowe, the mariage is cōſummate aboue, and ſolēnized with a perpetual feaſt: So that now thou mayest ſafely ſay, My welbeloued is mine, and I am his: Wherefore hearken, O my ſoule, and conſider, and incline thine eare, forget alſo thine owne people, and thy fathers houſe, (thy ſuppoſed home of this world) ſo ſhall the King

haue pleaſure in thy beauty; for hee is thy Lord, and worſhip thou him.
            
            
               Chap. 26.
               
               
                  
                     THE verie Names, and 
                  
                     9. The Titles and Names of the thing cōſidered.
                   Titles of the matter cō
                     ſidered, yeeld no ſmall ſtore to our Meditation which, being commonly ſo impoſed that they ſecretly comprehend the nature of the thing which they repreſent,
                  
                  are not vnworthy of our diſcourſe.
               
               What neede I ſeeke theſe reſemblances, whē the very name of life implieth ſweetneſſe to men on earth; euen to them which confeſſe to liue with ſome diſcontentment? Surely the light is a pleaſant thing, and it is good to the eyes to ſee the Sunne: yet when Temporall is added to Life, I know not how this additiō detracteth ſomthing, and doth greatly abate the pleaſure of life; for thoſe which ioy

to thinke of Life grieue to thinke it but Temporall: So vexing is the ende of that whoſe continuance was delightfull; But nowe when there is an addition, aboue Time, of Eternitie, it makes life ſo much more ſweete, as it is more lasting; and laſting infinitelie, what can it giue leſſe than an infinite contentment? Oh dying and falſe life, which wee enioy here, and ſcarce a ſhadowe and counterfeit of that other: What is more

eſteemed than glory? which is ſo precious to men of ſpirit, that it makes them prodigall of their blood, proud of their wounds▪ careleſſe of themſelues: and yet alas, how pent and how fading is this glory, affected with ſuch dangers and deaths? hardly after all Trophees and monuments, either knowen to the next ſea, or ſuruiuing him that dyes for it: It is true glorie to triumph in heauen; where is neither enuie, nor forgetfulneſſe.
               
                  
What is more deare to vs than our Countrey? which the worthy and faithfull Patriotes of all times, haue reſpected aboue their parēts, their children, their liues; counting it onely happie to liue in it, and to die for it: The baniſht man pines for the want of it; the trauailer digeſts all the tediouſneſſe of his way, all the ſorrowes of an ill iourney, in the only hope of home; forgetting all his forraine miſeries, when hee feeles his owne ſmoake. Where is our

Countrey but aboue? Thence thou camest, O my ſoule; thither thou art going, in a ſhort, but weary pilorimage: O miſerable men, if wee account our ſelues at home in our pilgrimage, if in our iourney we long not for home! Doeſt thou ſee men ſo in loue with their natiue ſoyle, that euen when it is all deformed with the deſolations of warre, and turned into rude heapes, or while it is euen now flaming with the fire of ciuill broiles, they couet yet ſtil

to liue in it; preferring it to all other places of more peace and pleaſure; and ſhalt thou ſeeing nothing but peace and bleſſednes at home, nothing but trouble abroad, content thy ſelfe with a faint wiſh of thy diſſolution? If heauen were thy Iayle, thou couldest but thinke of it vncomfortably. Oh what affection can be worthy of ſuch an home?
            
            
               
               Chap. 27.
               
               
                  
                     LAſtly, if we 
                  10. Cōſid. of fit teſtimonies of Scripture, concerning our Theme. 
                  can recall any pregnāt Testimonies of Scripture concerning our Theme, thoſe ſhall fitly conclude this part of our Meditation: Of Scripture; for that in theſe matters of God, none but diuine authoritie can cōmand aſſent, and ſettle the conſcience: Witneſſes of holy men may ſerue
                  
                  for colours; but the ground muſt bee onely from God.
               
               There it is (ſaith the ſpirit of God, which cannot deceiue thee) that all teares ſhall be wip't from our eyes; there ſhall bee no more death, nor ſorrow, nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more paine: yea, there ſhall not onely be an end of ſorrowes, but an abundant recompence for the ſorrowes of our life; as hee that was rapt vp into the third heauen, and there ſaw what cannot

hee ſpoken, ſpeakes yet thus of what he ſaw: I count that the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthy of the glory which ſhall bee ſhewed to vs: It was ſhewed to him what ſhould hereafter be ſhewed to vs; and hee ſawe, that if all the world full of miſeries were layed in one balance, and the least glory of heauen in another, thoſe would bee incomparably light yea (as that diuine Father) that one dayes felicitie aboue, were worth

a thouſand yeeres torment belowe; what then can bee matched with the eternitie of ſuch ioyes? Oh how great therefore is thy goodnes, O Lord, which thou hast layd vp for them that feare thee, and done to them that truſt in thee, before the ſonnes of men!
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 28.
               
                  THE moſt Of our ſecond part of Meditation: which is, in the affections. difficult and knotty part of Meditation thus finiſhed, there remayneth that which is both more liuely, and more eaſie to a good heart; to bee wrought altogether by the affections; which if our diſcourſes reach not vnto, they prooue vain, and to no purpoſe;

That which followeth therefore, is the very ſoule of Meditation, whereto all that is paſt ſerueth but as an inſtrument. A man is a man by his vnderſtanding part: but he is a Chriſtian by his will and affections. Seeing therefore, that all our former labour of the braine, is only to affect the heart; after that the minde hath thus trauerſed the Wherin is required a Taſte and relliſh of what we haue thought vpon. point propoſed throgh all the heads of reaſon, it ſhall indeuour to find in the firſt place ſome

feeling touch, &amp; ſweete relliſh in that which it hath thus chewed; which fruit, through the bleſſing of God will voluntarily follow vpon a ſerious Meditation. Dauid ſayes, Oh taſte and ſee how ſweete the Lord is: In Meditation wee doe both ſee and taſte; but we ſee before we taſte: ſight is of the vnderſtanding; taſte, of the affection; Neither can we ſee, but we muſt 
                     •
                  aſte; we can not knowe 
                     •
                  right, but wee muſt needes bee affected:

Let the heart therefore firſt conceiue and feele in it ſelf the Sweetneſſe or bitterneſſe of the matter meditated; which is neuer done without ſome paſſion; nor expreſſed without ſome hearty exclamation.
               
                  Oh bleſſed estate of the Saints: O glorie not to bee expreſſed, euen by thoſe which are glorified! O incomprchenſible ſaluation! What ſauour hath this earth to thee? Who can regarde the worlde that
                  
                  beleeueth thee? Who can thinke of thee, and not bee rauiſhed with woonder and deſire? Who can hope for thee, and not reioyce? Who can knowe thee, and not bee ſwallowed vp with admiration at the mercie of him that beſtowes thee? O bleſſedneſſe worthy of Christs blood to purchaſe thee! worthie of the continuall ſongs of Saints and Angels to celebrate thee! Howe ſhould I magnifie thee! Howe ſhould I long for thee!
                  
                  how ſhould I hate all this world for thee?
               
            
            
               Chap. 29.
               
               
                  
                     AFter this 
                  
                     Secondly, a Cōplaint; bewailing our wants and vntowardnes.
                   Taste ſhall followe a Complaint, wherin the heart bewayleth to it ſelfe his owne pouerty, dulneſſe, and imperfection; chiding and abaſing it ſelfe in reſpect of his wants and indiſpoſition: wherein Humiliation

truly goes before glory. For the more we are caſt downe in our conceit, the higher ſhall GOD lift vs vp at the ende of this exerciſe, in ſpirituall reioicing.
               But alas, where is my loue? where is my longing? where art thou, O my ſoule? what heauineſſe hath ouertaken thee? Howe hath the worlde bewitched and poſſeſſed thee, that thou art become ſo careleſſe of thine home, ſo ſenſeleſſe of ſpiritual delights,

ſo fond vpon theſe vanities? Doest thou doubt whether there bee an heauen? or whether thou haue a God, and a Sauiour there? O farre bee frō thee this Atheiſme; farre bee from thee the leaſt thought of ſuch deſperate impiety: Wo were thee if thou beleeuedst not: But O thou of little faith; doeſt thou beleeue there is happineſſe, and happineſſe for thee, and deſireſt it not, and delightest not in it? Alas, how weake and vnbeleeuing is thy beleefe?

how cold and faint are thy deſires? Tel me, what ſuch goodly entertainemēt haſt thou met withall here on earth, that was worthy to withdraw thee frō theſe heauenly ioyes? what pleaſure in it euer gaue thee contentment? or what cauſe of diſlike findest thou aboue? Oh no, my ſoule, it is onely thy miſerable drowzineſſe, only thy ſecuritie: The world, the world hath beſotted thee, hath vndone thee with careleſneſſe. Alas if thy delight

bee ſo colde, What difference is there in thee frō an ignorant Heathē, that doubts of another life; yea, frō an Epicure that denies it? Artthou a chriſtian, or art thou none? If thou be what thou profeſſeſt, away with this dul and ſenſeleſſe worldlineſſe; away with this earthly vnchearfulneſſe; ſhake off at last this profane and godleſſe ſecuritie that hath thus long weighed thee downe frō mounting vp to thy ioies; Looke vp to thy GOD, and to thy crowne, and

ſay with confidence, O Lord I haue wayted for thy ſaluation.
            
            
               Chap. 30.
               
               
                  
                     AFter this Cō
                  plaint, Thirdly, an harty wiſh of the ſoule for what it cōplaineth to want. 
                  muſt ſucceede an harty &amp; paſſionate Wiſh of the ſoule, which ariſeth clearely from the two former degrees; For that which a man hath found ſweete, and comfortable, &amp; complaines that hee ſtill wants; hee
                  
                  cannot but wiſh to enioy.
               
               O Lord that I could waite and long for thy ſaluation; Oh that I could minde the things aboue; that as I am a ſtranger in deed, ſo I could be alſo in affectiō; Oh that mine eyes, like the eyes of thy firſt Martyr, could by the light of faith ſee but a glimpſe of heauen; Oh that my heart could bee rapt vp thither in deſire! How ſhould I trample vpō theſe poore vanities of the earth? How willingly ſhould I indure all

ſorrowes, all torments? how ſcornefully ſhould I paſſe by all pleaſures? how ſhould I be in trauel of my diſſolution? Oh when ſhall that bleſſed day come, when all this wretched worldlines remoued I ſhall ſolace my ſelfe, in my God; Behold, as the Hart brayeth for the riuers of water, ſo panteth my ſoule after thee, O GOD; My ſoule thirſteth for God, euen for the liuing God; Oh when ſhal I come and appeare before the preſence of God?
            
            
               
               Chap. 31.
               
               
                  
                     AFter this Wiſhing, 
                     4. An hū
                        ble Confeſſion of our diſability to effect what we wiſh.
                   
                  ſhall follow hū
                     ble Confeſſion, by iuſt order of nature: For hauing bemoned our want, and wiſhed ſupplie, not finding this hope in our ſelues, we muſt needes acknowledge it to him, of whom only we may both ſeek &amp; find; wherin it is to bee duely obſerued,
                  
                  how the mind is by turnes depreſſed and lifted vp: Being lifted vp with our Taſte of ioy; it is caſt downe with Complaint: lift vp with Wiſhes, it is caſt downe with Confeſſion; which order doeth beſt hold it in vre, and iuſt temper; and makes it more feeling of the cō
                     fort which followes in the Concluſion. This Confeſſion muſt derogate all from our ſelues, and aſcribe all to God.
               
               Thus I deſire, O Lord, to bee right affected towards

thee and thy glory; I deſire to come to thee: but, alas, how weakly? how heartleſly? Thou knowest that I can neither come to thee, nor deſire to come but from thee. It is Nature that holds me from thee; this treacherous Nature fauors it ſelfe, loues the world, hates to thinke of a diſſolution, and chooſes rather to dwell in this dungeon with continuall ſorrow and complaint, than to endure a parting although to liberty and ioy: Alas, Lord, it is my

miſery that I loue my paine: How long ſhall theſe vanities thus beſot me? It is thou onely that canſt turne away mine eyes frō regarding theſe follies, and my heart from affecting them: Thou onely, who as thou ſhalt one day receiue my ſoule into heauen, ſo now before-hande canſt fixe my ſoule vpon heauen and thee.
            
            
               
               Chap. 32.
               
               
                  
                     AFter Confeſſion 
                     5. An earneſt Petitiō 
                     for that which wee confeſſe to want.
                   
                  naturally followes Petition, earneſtly requeſting that at his handes, which we acknowledge our ſelues vnable, and none but GOD able to performe.
               
               Oh carie it vp therefore, thou that haſt created, and redeemed it, carie it vp to thy glorie: Oh let mee not alwayes

bee thus dull and brutiſh; Let not theſe ſcales of earthly affection alwayes dimme and blind mine eyes: Oh thou that layedst clay vpon the blind mans eyes, take away this clay from mine eyes, wherewith alas they are ſo dawbed vp, that they cannot ſee heauen: Illuminate thē from aboue, and in thy light let me ſee light. Oh thou that hast prepared a place for my ſoule; prepare my ſoule for that place; prepare it with holineſſe, prepare it with

deſire: and euen while it ſoiourneth on earth, let it dwell in heauen with thee, beholding euer the beauty of thy face, the glory of thy Saints and of it ſelfe.
            
            
               Chap. 33.
               
               
                  
                     AFter Petition, ſhall followe 
                  6. A vehement enforcement of our Petiuon. 
                  the Enforcemēt of our requeſt from argument and importunate obſecration; wherin we muſt take heede of complementing in
                  
                  tearmes with God; as knowing that hee will not be mocked by any faſhionable forme of ſute, but requires holy and feeling intreatie.
               
               How graciouſly haſt thou proclaimed to the worlde, that who-euer wants wiſedom ſhal aske it of thee, which neither deniest nor vpbraidest: O Lord, I want heauenly wiſedome, to conceiue aright of heauen; I want it and aske it of thee; giue me to aske it inſtantly, and giue me according to thy promiſe abundantly.

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
Thou ſeeſt it is no ſtrange fauour that I begge of thee; no other than that which thou hast richly bestowed vpon all thy valiant Martyrs, Confeſſors, ſeruants from the beginning: who neuer could haue ſo chearfully imbraced death and torment, if through the middest of their flames and paine they had not ſeene their crowne of glorie. The poore theefe of the Croſſe had no ſooner craued thy remembrance when thou camest to thy kingdome

than thou promiſedst to to take him with thee into heauen: Preſence was better to him than remembrance. Behold, now thou art in thy kingdome, I am on earth: remember thine vnworthy ſeruant, and let my ſoule in conceit, in affection, in conuerſation be this day &amp; for euer with thee in Paradiſe. I ſee, man walketh in a vaine ſhadow, and diſquieteth himſelf in vain; they are pitifull pleaſures hee enioyeth, while he forgets thee; I am as vaine,

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
make me more wiſe: Oh let mee ſee heauen, and I knowe I ſhall neuer ennie, nor followe them: My times are in thine hande: I am no better than my fathers, a ſtranger on earth; As I ſpeake of them, ſo the next; yea, this generation ſhall ſpeake of mee as one that was; My life is a bubble, a ſmoake, a ſhadowe, a thought: I knowe it is no abiding in this thorow-fare: Oh ſuffer me not ſo madde, as while I paſſe on the waye, I

ſhould forgette the ende; It is that other life that I must truſt to. With thee it is that I ſhall continue; Oh let mee not bee ſo fooliſh as to ſettle my ſelfe on what I must leaue, and to neglect eternitie; I haue ſeene enough of this earthe, and yet I loue it too much; Oh let mee ſee heauen another while, and loue it ſo much more than the earth, by howe much the things there are more

worthy to be loued; Oh God, looke downe on thy wretched Pilgrim; and teach mee to looke vp to thee, and to ſee thy goodneſſe in the land of the liuing. Thou that boughteſt heauen for me, guide mee thither; and for the price that it cost thee, for thy loue and mercies ſake, in ſpight of all tentations, enlighten thou my ſoule, direct it, crowne it.
            
            
               
               Chap. 34.
               
               
                  
                     AFter this Enforcement, 
                     7. A chearfull Confidence of obtaining what wee haue requeſted &amp; enforced.
                   
                  doeth followe Confidence; wherin the ſoule after many doubtfull and vnquiet bickerings, gathers vp her forces, and cheerefully rouzeth vp it ſelfe; and like one of Dauids Worthies, breaks through a whole armie of doubts, and fetches comfort from
                  
                  the Well of life; which, though in ſome later, yet in all is a ſure reward from GOD of ſincere Meditation.
               
               Yea, bee thou bolde, O my ſoule, and doe not meerely craue, but challenge this fauour of God, as that which hee owes thee: Hee owes it thee becauſe hee hath promiſed it, and by his mercie hath made his gift, his debt; Faithfull is hee that hath promiſed▪ which will alſo doe it▪
                   Hath hee not giuen thee not onely his hand in the

ſweete hopes of the Goſpell, but his ſeale alſo in the Sacraments? Yea, beſides promiſe, hand, ſeale; hath hee not giuen thee a ſure earnest of thy ſaluation, in ſome weake, but true graces? Yet more: hath hee not giuen thee beſides Earneſt, poſſeſſion? while he that is the Trueth and Life, ſaith, Hee that beleeueth hath euerlaſting life, and hath paſſed from death to life: Canst thou not then bee content to cast thy ſelfe vpon this bleſſed iſſue;

If God be faithfull, I am glorious; I haue thee already, O my life; God is faithfull, and I doe beleeue: who ſhall ſeparate mee from the loue of Christ? from my glorie with Christ, who ſhall pull mee out of my heauen? Goe to then, and returne to thy rest, O my ſoule; make vſe of that heauen wherin thou art, and be happie.
               
                  Thus we haue found, that our Meditatiō like the winde, gathers ſtrengthin proceeding;
                  
                  and as naturall bodies, the neerer they come to their places, moue with more celerity, ſo doeth the ſoule in this courſe of meditation, to the vnſpeakeable benefite of it ſelfe.
               
            
            
               
                  Chap. 35.
               
                  THe Concluſion 
                  The Concluſ. of our Meditation, in what order it muſt be. remaineth; wherin we muſt aduiſe (like as Phyſicians doe in their ſweats

and exerciſe) that wee ceaſe not ouer-ſuddenly; but leaue off by little and little. The mind may not bee ſuffered to fall headlong from this height, but muſt alſo deſcend by degrees.
               The firſt whereof, After our Confidence, ſhall be an hearty Gratulation, 
                  Firſt, with Thankeſgiuing.
                   and thankeſgiuing. For, as man naturally cannot bee miſerable, but he muſt complaine, and craue remedie; ſo the good heart cannot finde it ſelfe happie, and not be

thankefull: and this thankefulneſſe which it feeles and expreſſes, makes it yet more good, and affects it more.
               
                  What ſhall I then doe to thee for this mercie, Othou Sauiour of men? What ſhould I render to my Lord, for all his benefites? Alas, what can I giue thee which is not thine owne before? Oh that I could giue thee but all thine! Thou giueſt mee to drinke of this cuppe of ſaluation; I will therefore take the cuppe
                  
                  of ſaluation, and call vpon the name of the Lord: Praiſe thou the Lorde, o my ſoule; and all that is within mee, praiſe his holy name: And ſince here thou beginneſt thine heauen, begin here alſo that ioyfull ſong of thankeſ-giuing, which there thou ſhalt ſing more ſweetly, and neuer ende.
               
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 36.
               
                  AFter this Secondly, with Recommendation of our ſoules and wayes to God. 
                  Thankeſgiuing, ſhall followe a faithful recommendation of our ſelues to God; wherein the ſoule doth chearfully giue vp it ſelfe, and repoſe it ſelfe wholly vpon her Maker, and Redeemer; committing her ſelfe to him in all her wayes, ſubmitting

her ſelfe to him in all his wayes, reſoluing in all things to glorifie him; and to walke worthy of her high &amp; glorious calling.
               Both which later ſhal bee done (as I haue euer found) with much life and comfort, if for the full concluſion, wee ſhall lift vp our heart and voyce to God, in ſinging ſome Verſicle of Dauids diuine Pſalmes, anſwerable to our diſpoſition, and matter; whereby the heart cloſes vp it ſelfe with

much ſweeteneſſe and contentment.
               This courſe of Meditation thus heartily obſerued, let him that practiſes it, tell we whether he find not that his ſoule, which at the beginning of this exerciſe did but creepe and grouell vpon earth, doe not now in the Concluſion ſoare aloft in heauen; &amp; being before aloofe off, doe not now find it ſelfe neere to God, yea with him, and in him.
            
            
               
               
                  Chap. 37.
               
                  THus haue I endeuoured, An Epilogue. (right Worſhipfull Sir) according to my ſlender faculty, to preſcribe a Methode of Meditation: Not vpon ſo ſtrict tearmes of Neceſſitie, that whoſoeuer goeth not my way, erreth. Diuers paths leade ofttimes to the ſame end; and euery man aboundeth

in his owne ſenſe: If experience and cuſtome hath made another forme familiar to any man, I forbid it not; as that learned Father ſayde of his Tralation, Let him vſe his owne, not contemne mine. If any man bee to chuſe, and beginne, let him practiſe mine, till he meete with a better Maſter: If an other courſe may be better, I am ſure this is good. Neither is it to Reproouing the neglect, be ſuffered, that like as fantaſticall men, while they doubt what faſhion'd

ſute they ſhould we are, put on nothing; ſo, that wee Chriſtians ſhuld neglect the matter of this worthy buſineſſe, while we nicely ſtand vpon the forme thereof. Wherein giue mee leaue to complain with iuſt ſorrowe and ſhame, that if there bee any Chriſtian duetie, whoſe omiſſion is notoriouſly ſhameful, and preiudicial to the ſoules of profeſſors, it is this of Meditation: This is the very end God hath giuen vs our ſoules▪ we

miſſe-ſpend them, if we vſe them not thus. How lamentable is it, that wee ſo imploy them, as if our facultie of diſcourſe ſerued for nothing, but our earthly prouiſion? as if our reaſonable and Chriſtian mindes were appointed for the ſlaues and drudges of this bodie; onely to bee the Caters and Cookes of our appetite.
               The worlde filles vs, yea, cloyes vs: we finde our ſelues worke enough to thinke; What
                  
                  haue I yet? Howe may I gette more? What must I lay out? What ſhall I leaue for posterity? How may I preuent the wrong of mine aduerſarie, how may I returne it? What anſweres ſhall I make to ſuch allegations? What entertainement ſhall I giue to ſuch friends? What courſes ſhall I take in ſuch ſuits? In what pastimes ſhall I ſpend this day, in what the next? What aduantage ſhall I reape by this practiſe; what loſſe? What was ſayd, anſwered,
                  
                  replied, done, followed?
               
               Goodly thoughts, and fitte for Spirituall mindes! Say, there were no other worlde; how could wee ſpend our cares otherwiſe? Vnto this only neglect, let mee aſcribe the commonneſſe of that Laodicean temper of men, or (if that bee worſe) of the dead coldneſſe which hath ſtriken the hearts of many, hauing left them nothing but the bodies of men, and viſors of Chriſtians; to

this onely, They haue not meditated. It is not more impoſſible to liue Exhorting to the vſe of Meditation. without an heart, than to bee deuout without Meditation: Woulde GOD therefore my words could be in this (as the wiſe man ſayes the wordes of the wiſe are) like vnto Goades in the ſides of euery Reader, to quicken him vp out of this dull and lazy ſecurity, to a chearfull practiſe of this Diuine Meditatiō. Let him curſe mee vpon his death-bed, if looking

backe from thence to the beſtowing of his former times, hee acknowledge not theſe houres placed the moſt happily in his whole life? if he then wiſh not he had worne out more daies, in ſo profitable and heauenly a worke.
               DEO SOLI GLORIA.
            
            
            
         
      
   

