
   
      
         
            Mortalities meditation: or, A description of sinne VVith a definition and plaine setting forth of mans three chiefest and greatest enemies; to wit, the world, the flesh, and the Diuell. Written by William Hall.
            Hall, William, fl. 1624.
         
         
            
               1624
            
         
         Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02593
            STC 12720
            ESTC S106137
            99841862
            99841862
            6477
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02593)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6477)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 961:1)
         
         
            
               
                  Mortalities meditation: or, A description of sinne VVith a definition and plaine setting forth of mans three chiefest and greatest enemies; to wit, the world, the flesh, and the Diuell. Written by William Hall.
                  Hall, William, fl. 1624.
               
               [44] p.   
               
                  By Aug. Mathewes, for Beniamin Fisher, and are to be sold at his shop in Pater-noster Row, at the signe of the Talbot,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1624.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sin --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.
               Sin --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-07
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-07
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            MORTALITIES MEDITATION: OR, A DESCRIPTION OF SINNE.
            With a Definition and plaine ſetting forth of Mans three chiefeſt and greateſt Enemies; to wit, the WORLD, the FLESH, and the DIVELL.
            
               Written by WILLIAM HALL.
            
               
                  Gutta cadent lapides, non vi ſed ſaepe cadendo:
               
               
                  Sic homo fit Doctus, non vi ſed ſaepe ſtudendo.
               
            
            In Engliſh thus:
            
               
                  By often falling, not by force doe raine the ſtones make ſoft,
               
               
                  So Man's made learned not by force, but its by ſtudying oft.
               
            
            
               
                  Nemo ſine Crimine viuit.
               
            
            Imprinted at London, by Aug. Mathewes, for Beniamin Fiſher, and are to be ſold at his Shop in Pater-noſter Row, at the Signe of the Talbot. 1624
         
         
            
            
            TO THAT COVRTEOVS GENTLEMAN, AND MY much reſpected Friend M. IOHN LOVVE, Iunior, Eſquire; WILLIAM HALL humbly dedicates the Buds and Bloſſomes of theſe is firſt Fruits, wiſhing all Honour during this Life, and after Death Life eternall.
            I Haue preſum'd to Dedicate this Booke
            To you; on which if you'l vouchſafe to looke,
            And if you pleaſe kindly to accept it,
            And from all ſlanderous tongues to protect it;
            Then at your feet I proſtrate my Burden,
            If you accept it I haue my guerdon:
            In loues vnlimited and lawles Band,
            I vnto you ſo farre obliged ſtand,
            That if I ſhould the Age of Neſtor liue,Tres centos fertur vixiſſe amos.
            
            I ſatisfaction to you ſhould not giue,
            For vndeſerued kindneſſes receiuing,
            Which makes me thankful whilſt I'ue life &amp; breathing:
            For truſty friends are ſcarce to be gotten,
            Hard to be kept, but nere to be forgotten:
            
               Amities chiefe breach is Ingratitude;
            But vnto that I'le not be ſeruitude;
            And in requitall of the loue I owe,
            My weake Inuention on you Ile beſtow:
            Some litterate Pamphlet better you befits;
            Then the Inuention of my ſhallow wits.
            Yet kind Sir read them, although rude they be,
            Iudge with iudicious eyes and you ſhall ſee
            My vntun'd verſe; but yet my Muſe is free,
            And ſo vnto the end ſhe meanes to be:
            I'le not inſinuate, flatter, lie nor faine,
            My wit in Paper ca'nt your worth explaine;
            Still ſtriue with vertue for to be ſuperiour,
            Deiect and throw downe vice as your Inferiour:
            Goe on in Vertue as you haue begun;
            That godly Race vnto the end out-run,
            Then ſhall you be belou'd of all good Men;
            Here ſtayes my Muſe, and here ſhall reſt my Pen.
            
               Your Worſhips to command in what he may. WILLIAM HALL.
            
         
         
            
            To the Courteous and vncourteous Readers.
            REaders, reade iudge, and then ſay what you will,
            All's one to me whether it bee good or ill:
            If you ſpeake well, for that I am your Debtor,
            And i
                  •
                this be not well, I would 'twere better:
            But if you ſpeake ill of it, all is one,
            To cry you mercy, Ile ne're make my mone,
            For ill mens tongues they ſay no ſlanders are,
            Therefore ſay what you will and doe not ſpare.
            I muſt confeſſe my Muſe is young and tender,
            And this is all he ſcuſe that I can render,
            This is the firſt time ſhee did euer write;
            Therefore with curriſh words doe not her bite.
            Leſt in her budding you doe ſpoyle her growth,
            If that you ſhould doe ſo I ſhould be loth:
            Giue her no ill words with good words her nouriſh,
            That ſhee in time may grow, and bud, and flouriſh.
            
               
                  Yours, as you are his: WILL: HALL.
            
         
         
            
            THE AVTHOR TO HIS BOOKE.
            NOw Farewell Booke, trauell the Word ſo wide,
            Hauing no Tutor, Truths thy only guide:
            From enuious tongues Truth will ſtill defend thee,
            To good and bad mens Iudgements I commend thee.
         
      
      
         
            
            Mortalities Meditation, or a Deſcription of Sinne.
            
            
               1
               I That as yet nere taſted one poore drop,
               Of the Caſtalian Liquor; nor as yet
               Did ere mine eyes behold Pernaſſus top:
               How ſhould my vnderſtanding then beget,
               Nay, or begin and frame my Pen to write,
               Since I my ſelfe knows not how to indite.
            
            
               2
               Your helpe, Oh ſacred Muſes, I muſt craue,
               But not the blotting of Apolloes P
                     •
                  n,
               By any meanes I muſt, nor will not haue,
               But ſimply of mine owne inuention then;
               And induſtry ſome ſimple worke Ile make,
               Since I haue gone thus farre to vndertake.
            
            
               3
               
                  Cicero I want thy learned eloquence,
               And Mars thy ſtout and valiantnes of heart;
               And likewiſe Sol thy ſhining influence,
               To accommodate me and to take my part.
               Againſt enuious tongues that ſeeke to ſhame me,
               And belying me oft-times doe defame me.
            
            
               4
               My Inke congeales, vnwilling to fulfill,
               My Hand vnſteady, Palſie-like doth ſhake:
               My Memory is dull, and I want skill,
               For to ſet forth that which my Mind ſhould ſpeake:
               Obliuiouſneſſe doth ſo my Braines poſſeſſe,
               That what I ſhould, I forget to expreſſe.
            
            
               
               5
               Of Tilts and Triumphs my Muſe ſhall not ſing,
               Ne wars nor wonders wrought within the ayre
               Nor how Tamberlaine did Baiazet bring,
               Conquered by him in the Turkiſh warre:
               And carried by him in 
                     •
                  n Iron Cage,
               To bee a Spectacle vnto that Age.
            
            
               6
               Nor yet of ancient Stories will I write;
               Nor trauellers that goe beyond the Cope,
               As did Pariſmus, Huon and the like)
               Nor ſuch as ſacrifice vnto the Pope:
               Hel-hounds they are that denye their Maker,
               The Diuels friends, but the Lords forſaker.
            
            
               7
               But of a meaner Subiect will I treate,
               That which I know is true I will reueale;
               And all the Follies of my Youth repeate:
               There's nothing hidden that I will conceale:
               And rip the target of my troubled heart,
               Which long haue caus'd my wounded ſoule to ſmart.
            
            
               8
               And hauing then laid open to your ſight,
               A Mappe of all my foule enormious Crimes,
               Committed both by day and eke by night
               In all places, all ſeaſons, at all times:
               Now Ile begin my dolefull Song to ſing,
               And hope the ſame to good effect to bring.
            
            
               9
               But if I faile, I pray ſpare not to iudge,
               But paſſe your cenſures on me how you will;
               I care not though you owe to me a grudge,
               Speake what you will I care not good or ill:
               Now once againe my ſong I will begin,
               No Song of Songs: but it's a Song of Sinne.
            
            
               
               10
               For ſince the time that I was firſt conceiu'd
               Within the wombe and entrailes of my Mother;
               Before I was into the world receiu'd
               Sinne was my Father, Siſter, and my Brother:
               Being borne in ſinne, in ſinne I liued ſtill,
               And vnto pleaſure only gaue my will.
            
            
               11
               Who vrg'd and prickt me alwaies to goe forward,
               And follow ſtill the ſame I had begun;
               Saying, I was a goodly Child and toward;
               But yet this pleaſure I did ſeeke to ſhun:
               Who luld and rockt my ſenſes faſt aſleepe,
               Which ſince hath caus'd me many times to weepe:
            
            
               12
               To ſee that pleaſure ouercame me ſo,
               For I no Reaſon had it to withſtand:
               But when I ſaw it was my deadly foe,
               I would no longer liue at her Command:
               But threw her ſlauiſh yoake from off my necke,
               And then began my follies for to checke.
            
            
               13
               Which long time had b
                     •
                  reft me of my ſight,
               That I at no time any good could ſee;
               It kept me vnder in moſt ſlauiſh ſpight,
               Vntill the Lord was mercifull to me,
               Opening my eyes to me the way did ſhowe,
               That I muſt walke the Goſpell for to know.
            
            
               14
               Then I began the Engliſh tongue to learne,
               My vowels and my Letters for to ſpell;
               And in mine yeares I ſomewhat could diſcerne,
               How Latin writers Engliſh doe excell:
               Who can compare with Horace, Virgil, and
               
                  Homer, which hath all vnder his command.
            
            
               
               15
               In which mine yeares I many ſinnes committed,
               Through ignorance againſt my Soueraigne Lord,
               All thoſe I hope through Chriſt are cleane remitted,
               As alſo thoſe were done by my accord:
               As I to knowledge afterward increaſed,
               Sinning I ſinn'd, from ſinning I nere ceaſed.
            
            
               16
               But ſtill prouokt the Lord of Hoſts to ire,
               And had no care his Statutes to obey;
               The Stipend due for ſinners is hell fire,
               And thoſe that from their Maker runne aſtray,
               Let them be ſure to feele his ſcourging Rod,
               He is a iuſt, a wiſe, and louing God.
            
            
               17
               
                  Ezeck. 27.18 21.The death of Sinners he doth not deſire,
               But that they would returne and follow grace;
               It's true repentance that he doth require,
               That they may ſee his glory face to face:
               And praiſe his glorious name with one accord,
               
                  Reu. 19.3.With ſinging Halleluiah to the Lord.
            
            
               18
               My Infancie and Childhood being paſt,
               My Youth and Manhood poſting on with ſpeed,
               
                  Non videbo id Manticae quod intergo eſt.Still I my faults and ſinnes behind me caſt:
               And would not ſee them vntill vtmoſt need
               Compel'd me from this wicked kinde of life,
               Where was continuall wars and deadly ſtrife.
            
            
               19
               Betwixt my Spirit alwayes ready preſt
               For Gods Seruice contrary to euill;
               And my weake fleſh continually oppreſt,
               Hauing conflicts with the World and Diuell:
               Being thus bagirt with foes on euery ſide,
               Vnto thy mercy Seat I come to hide.
            
            
               
               20
               My ſences are inueloped in ſinne,
               The waight whereof into Hell would ſinke me,
               When on the wicked life I haue liued in,
               And Hels torments I begin to thinke me:
               Oh how I am perplext with griefe of minde,
               My troubled Conſcience can no comfort finde.
            
            
               21
               With Dauid now I am enforſt to crye,Pſal. 22.6.
               
               I am a worme of men the very ſcorne,
               My helpe on thee O Lord doth ſtill relie,
               And haue done euer ſince that I was borne:
               In time of old age off doe me not caſt;
               Nor yet when ſtrength doth faile me at the laſt.Pſal. 71.1.
               
            
            
               22
               The Sabbaths which thou vnto vs doſt giue,
               Commanding vs it holy for to keepe,Exod. 31.13.14.
               
               Giuen as a ſigne, or elſe wee ſhould not liue
               Amongſt the flocke of thy elected ſheepe:
               Who ſo defiles thy Sabbaths ſure ſhall dye,
               Wert not for mercy Lord, euen ſo ſhould I.
            
            
               23
               For I thy Sabbaths often haue prophaned,
               And ſpent them vildly to thy abuſing;
               Againſt thy holy name I haue exclaimed,
               Vnder colour of my faults excuſing:
               I went to Church Gods holy word to heare,
               But was exempt from all Paternall feare.
            
            
               24
               The ſubtile Serpent, ſubtiller then the reſt,
               Of all the beaſts which the Lord God did make,
               Hee cunningly doth creepe into my breſt,
               And the good ſowne ſeed away doth take:
               Pleaſures of Sinne alſo choake many ſeeds,
               Which nere ſprung vp puld down by vicious weeds.
            
            
               
               25
               I lookt for Sundayes to no other end,
               But take my pleaſure in paſtime and play,
               In doing ſo I was not my owne friend,
               The aged Counſell I would not obay:
               But ran at pleaſure to drinke and carouſe,
               In ſome by place, or in ſome tipling houſe.
            
            
               26
               I car'd not where if that I liquor had,
               For to content and pleaſe my fianticke Braine,
               I car'd not greatly where 'twere good or bad,
               If ſo I were in a right roring ſtraine;
               A roring ſtraine, yea thats the terme we vſed,
               Whereby Gods day and name was much abuſed,
            
            
               27
               Yet in this Sinne I neuer was alone,
               But had Copartners alwayes leſſe or more;
               For them, and I, and all, I make great mone,
               And pray that they, nor I doe ſo no more:
               Who ſo doth vſe it, let him marke me well,
               It's both the High-way and the Gate to Hell.
            
            
               28
               This ſinne is odious in Iehouahs ſight,
               He doth abhor the perſon and the Crime,
               VVith th'inſtrumentall meanes that gaue them light,
               Alſo the place, the ſeaſon and the time:
               Yet ſome doe ſeeke this ſinne for to extenuate,
               But yet it doth the vſers life abreuiate.
            
            
               29
               
                  Pro. 23.29.30.VVho hath wo, babling, ſorrow, who hath ſtrife,
               But thoſe that follow wine and drinke their fill?
               Of wine thats mixt, ohtis a drunken life,
               To ſpend their dayes ſo wicked and ſo vile:
               Let them be ſure God will ſtrike home at laſt,
               Though he forbeare his anger is not paſt.
            
            
               
               30
               With true repentance Lord I come to thee,
               And hearty ſorrowing for my former ſinne;
               In mercy Lord vouchſafe to looke on me,
               To lead a new life now I will begin:
               Grant me thy grace I beſeech thee therefore,
               My idle wayes I may hate and abhorre.
            
            
               31
               Forgiue me Lord the ſinnes I haue committed,
               Againſt thee both in word, in deed, and thought,
               Hauing done euill but the good omitted,
               VVhich in thy ſacred Scriptures thou haſt taught:
               Godly repentance worketh to ſaluation,2 Cor. 7.10.
               
               VVhereby wee ſhall be freed from condemnation.
            
            
               32
               Forgiue me Lord, for mercy now I call,
               Blot out my ſinnes, no more them thinke vpon;
               Before thy Mercy ſeat I proſtrate fall,
               And begge thee bury them in obliuion:
               Mercy good Lord, mercy, I mercy craue,
               Hoping throgh Chriſt that thou my ſoule wilt ſaue.
            
            
               33
               Farewell all ſinfull pleaſures of my youth,
               Thrice farewell to the exerciſe I haue vſed:
               VVhich long hath caus'd me to erre from the truth,
               Both God contemned and his Lawes abuſed:
               Farewell I ſay; thrice farewell and adue,
               Too long God knowes I haue been led by you.
            
            
               34
               For twenty yeares and vpward I haue led,
               A wicked life diſpleaſing vnto God;
               On worldly vanities I haue ſtill fed,
               For which I doe do ſerue Gods ſcourging Rod:
               Except his Mercy, his Iuſtice ouercome,
               I muſt expect a diſmall day of Doome.
            
            
               
               35
               My life was ſinfull Lord I doe confeſſe it,
               Spare them O Lord that doe their faults confeſſe;
               As it was ſinfull now I will redreſſe it,
               And from thoſe errors euer will I ceaſe,
               Then mercy on me take, heare my complaint,
               Of a vild Sinner make me a glorious Saint.
            
            
               36
               Being with ſinne poluted and defild,
               Which cann't be clenſed without Chriſt his bloud;
               (In whoſe ſight I a Sinner am moſt vild)
               Which was ſhed for vs all to doe vs good;
               Yea for vs all which in time doe repent.
               That we Gods future anger may preuent.
            
            
               37
               There is no bondage like to that of Sinne,
               Where neither Body nor yet minde is free,
               To ſlauiſh ſeruitude we are kept in,
               When as our Soules bereft of libertie:
               From that bondage good Lord deliuer me,
               That I may ſing continuall praiſe to thee.
            
            
               38
               My Soule from out of priſon Lord then bring,
               As Dauid prayed in like wiſe doe I,
               Thy Song in a ſtrange Land how can I ſing,
               
                  Pſal. 137.4.I would bee ſet at freedome willingly;
               Freedome each Creature gladly doth require,
               And to be free from ſinne is my deſire.
            
            
               39
               Three enemies we haue with all to fight,
               Which doe incite vs euill to commit,
               Yea they ſuggeſt vs all wayes day and night,
               That the good which we ſhould doe we omit:
               We commit nothing but that which is euill,
               Theſe three are, the World, the fleſh and Diuell.
            
            
               
               40
               The World inticeth vs to pleaſures vaine,
               That momentary things wee more reſpect,
               Then that which doe belong Heauen to gaine,
               Thoſe things wee altogether doe neglect:
               We ſpend our time, or ſtudy and our wit,
               To that which turnes not to our benefit.
            
            
               41
               Our greateſt care is how to gather wealth,The nature of moſt men.
               
               To purchaſe Land, to riſe vnto promotion;
               At no time wee take care for our Soules health,
               Nor to ſerue God with any good Deuotion:
               That which by vs ſhould chiefly be reſpected,
               Continually by vs is ſtill neglected.
            
            
               42
               Wee ſtriue for honour, follow after pleaſure,
               
                  Pauls exhortation ſeldome we obay,
               As for Decorum we keepe little meaſure,
               Our chiefe delight's in pride and going gay:
               Hauing good cloathes that we goe neat and fine,
               Wee take no care how many Bodies pine.
            
            
               43
               
                  Dauid deſcribeth how vaine man doth waſt,Homo vanitate fimales factus eſt. Pſal. 144.4.
                  
               
               And to a ſhadow hee doth him compare,
               Which is no ſooner ſeene but ſtaight its paſt,
               So fraile, ſo fickle, and ſo weake we are:
               We gather wealth which turnes to our annoy,Pſal. 39.7.
               
               But yet know not who ſhall it enioy.
            
            
               44
               The Lillies of the field,Luk. 12.27. conſider how
               They get their liuing, for they neuer ſpin;
               Nor once take paines their Bodies for to bowe,
               At no time they doe any worke begin:
               Yet Salomon being a mighty King,
               Such cloathing as this was he could not bring.
            
            
               
               45
               
                  Baruch 3.17.19.What are become of thoſe that hoord vp Gold,
               And of their gettings neuer make an end?
               Still ſcraping wealth vntill it can't be told,
               But yet they know not who the ſame ſhall ſpend:
               Vaniſht they are and gone downe to the graue,
               Others come vp their riches for to haue.
            
            
               46
               VVho will it ſpend faſter then 'twas gotten,
               VVhen as their meanes doe come into their hand;
               Thoſe friends that it gaue ſhall be forgotten,
               To purchaſe parrell they will pawne their Land:
               They'l ſell their credit all what ere they haue,
               But they will haue cloathes to goe neat and braue.
            
            
               47
               
                  Ecleſiaſt. 5.12.3.The ſonne of Syrach poynteth at the pride,
               And vaine exceſſe of parell in our dayes:
               Decking our ſelues much good time we let ſlide,
               And ſpend it all to Iehouahs diſpraiſe,
               Pride will raigne in ſome men doe what they can,
               
                  Eccleſ. 10.7.It's a ſinne hated both of God and man.
            
            
               48
               
                  Eccleſ. 11.4.To boaſt in rayment is 'gainſt God a fault,
               Knowing we are but worm▪s meat and duſt;
               Likewiſe in honour our ſelues to exalt,
               Neither in ſtrength we ought not put our truſt:
               Help vs good tord in trouble and in paine,
               
                  Pſal. 60.11.As for the helpe of man it is but vaine.
            
            
               49
               
                  1 Tim. 6.7.Th'Apoſtle wils vs for to be content,
               And not for worldly wealth to care and cracke,
               It is enough if we haue food and rayment,
               VVhat need wee then for droſsie pelfe to rake?
               Conſidering as we here this wealth did finde,
               VVee muſt depart and leaue it all behind.
            
            
               
               50
               From the mean'ſt Caitiue to the mightieſt King,
               That euer breath'd, or on the earth did raigne:
               Into this world nothing at firſt did bring,1 Tim. 6.1.
               
               And ſure ſhall carry nothing forth againe:
               Except a Coffin and a winding ſheete,
               Tied with two knots, one at the head and feete
            
            
               51
               To many errors the world doth vs leade,
               Which for to follow we are apt you ſee;
               But in the path of Vertue we nere tread,
               We run the Race when once the raine's let free,
               Of luſtfull youth wee ſwagger, lye and ſweare,
               And with blaſphemous oathes the Lord we teare.
            
            
               52
               We ought to tremble when Gods name wee heare,
               And not blaſpheme him, nor againſt him ſpue:
               Such Oathes that ſtinke before him (I doe feare,
               I write no more then what is too to true:)
               Wee ſtill blaſpheme him, and wee forget how
               At's name each knee in heauen &amp; earth ſhall bowe.Phil. 2.10.
               
            
            
               53
               For foure cauſes God beſtowes on men,
               Riches to vſe, as goods vnto them lent,
               They muſt leaue all behind but knowes not when,
               And therefore care not how their time be ſpent:
               Th'vnthrifty will ſpend all in Prodigality,
               But the old Miſer none in hoſpitality.
            
            
               54
               The firſt is for the honor of Gods name,Pro. 3.9.
               
               And propagation of Gods holy word,
               Still to continue and preſerue the ſame,
               That we may praiſe his name with one accord,
               And that the ſplendent light of this cleare Sun,
               May alwayes ſhine but yet be neuer done.
            
            
               
               55
               The ſecond vſe for which our goods were giuen,
               Is for to ſpend it for our Countries ſake;
               By our wealth others might be relieuen,
               With it a freedome or releaſment make:
               We ought to ſpend our goods, our liues, our blood,
               In any thing to doe our Countries good.
            
            
               56
               
                  The third vſe.Is for the good of thoſe by whom we liue,
               That are in need, neceſſity, and want;
               To them part of our meanes we ought to giue,
               And to relieue them if their ſtore be ſcant:
               
                  Pro 31.20.Yea to ſtrengthen with all our power,
               And to refreſh their bodies euery hower.
            
            
               57
               The laſt is for the maintenance of thoſe
               Which are our ſeruants, yea and for vs all;
               Yea for our ſelues we may thinke and ſuppoſe,
               And for all others that on him doe call:
               
                  Luk. 16.3.Opening his hand each liuing thing doth fill,
               With plenteouſneſſe according to his will.
            
            
               58
               
                  1 Ioh. 2.25.Saint John exhorts vs from this worldly loue,
               
                  Quiſquis amat mundum, amor dei non eſt in illum.And not to loue it nor the things therein,
               Yea, very plainly, he the ſame doth proue,
               That whatſoere is of the world is ſinne:
               Then of this enemy we muſt beware,
               That hee at no time doe our Soules inſnare.
            
            
               59
               How many Diues at this time haue wee,
               VVhich doe fare moſt deliciouſly each day;
               In Purple and fine Linnen wee them ſee,
               Being brauely clad in Robes and rich array:
               
                  Luk. 16.19.Theſe Silke-wormes many Lazarus will ſtarue.
               Rather then with their ſcraps they wil them ſerue.
            
            
               
               60
               The ſecond Enimie's our fleſhly Luſt,Mans ſecond enemy is himſelfe.
               
               And alwaies freſh aſſaults with him wee haue,
               Vnto our ſelues therefore we muſt not truſt,
               But flye to Chriſt, i
                     •••
                   hee our Soule muſt ſaue:
               Who conquered hath the graue, yea death, and hell,
               All our aduerſaries for to expell.
            
            
               61
               Each ſenſe and member feſtered is with ſinne,
               Yea and corrupted in Iehouas ſight:
               Such an infectious time we doe liue in,
               And this ſinne ſerpent-like doth vs ſo bite,
               Euen as a ſcurfe doth ore mans bodie ſpread,
               So ſoule and bodies with ſinn's peſtered.
            
            
               62
               Our bodies to ſinne are ſo linckt and chained,
               Euery ſenſe of Vertue is be reft.
               And Vitiouſneſſe in vs ſo long hath Raign'd,
               So little goodneſſe in vs there is left,
               Turning from God, wee are Chriſts ſinfull abiects,
               But vnto Sathan very louing ſubiects.
            
            
               63
               From top to toe we are with ſinne Cloſd faſt,
               That in vs there is no whole part nor ſound,
               Our breath infects the Ayer at each blaſt,
               Our feete vnworthy to treade on the ground:
               Sinne doth Raigne in vs and about vs Round,
               Is nought but ſinfullneſſe for to be found.
            
            
               64
               Our head is the Receptakle of ſinnes,
               And firſt receiuer of vngodly deeds,
               Yea the head Fountaine where all vice begines,
               Vpon mans bodie greedily it feeds:
               And like the horſe-leach ſtill doth cry giue, giue,
               Seldome forſaking men whilſt they doe liue.
            
            
               
               65
               Our memory with dulneſſe is poſſeſt,
               Eſpecially in hearing of thy word;
               For that wee ſeeke not which ſhould pleaſe thee beſt,
               But follow vanity with one accord:
               We quite forſake that which being vnderſtood,
               At preſent time would proue our future good.
            
            
               66
               Our eyes ſpectators on iniquity,
               The gate and entrance to the inward man;
               Delight wee take to gaze on vanity,
               But ſeldome ſatisfied doe what we can:
               Wee greedily deſire what we doe ſee,
               Longing to haue it although ill it be.
            
            
               67
               Our eyes ſhould be imployd to better vſe,
               The ſacred Scripture with them we ſhould read;
               But oft we doe neglect and ſtill refuſe,
               The way that we a godly life might lead:
               We run the way that is composd of euill,
               Following which path we walke vnto the Diuell.
            
            
               68
               Our eares are open blaſphemies to heare,
               And all reuilings 'gainſt Gods holy name,
               And gainſt his Chriſt which all our ſinnes did beare,
               To free vs from that euerlaſting paine:
               To vs belongeth both ſhame and confuſion,
               To which wee are led by Sathans illuſion.
            
            
               69
               
                  Pſal. 58.45.Like the deafe Adder wee doe ſtop our eares,
               Yea deafe and dumbe almoſt our ſelues we faine,
               The Charmers voyce we doe refuſe to heare,
               Charme whilſt he will his charming is in vaine:
               Though he charme wiſely wee don't it reſpect,
               He and his charming both wee doe neglect.
            
            
               
               70
               To talke of Riches, of wealth and glory,
               To heare of newes of merriment and ſport,
               To paſſe our time in things tranſitory,
               To this whole flocks of people will reſort:
               With great attention all will hearken to it,
               Though it be ill actors enough to doe it.
            
            
               71
               Our mouth the Chamber of vngodlines,
               Our lips the Roofe which doth that hoſe couer;
               Through which all emitable beaſtlines,
               Proceedeth forth which doth our liues diſcouer:
               And ſhewes the wicked life we haue liued in,
               Which to amend wee neuer doe begin.
            
            
               72
               Our teeth's a hedge foſ that vnruly member,
               Which do we what we can it will breake out;
               To haue a care of him we muſt remember,
               For in vaine he too faſt will run about,
               The tongue is a good member if well vſed,Lingua quid peius eadem.
               
               But it's the worſt we haue if that abuſed.
            
            
               73
               That godly Prophet holy Dauid ſayes,
               As with a bit he will his mouth keepe faſt;Pſa. 39.123.
               
               Looke to his tnngue take heed vnto his wayes,
               And ſpeake not till the wicked ones be paſt:
               Yea from good words he alſo did refraine,
               Although to him it was both griefe and paine.
            
            
               74
               Scurrility we alwayes ought to flye,
               And not with curſings once our mouthes defile;
               All beaſtly idle talke and blaſphemy,
               Wee from our mouthes ſhould vtterly exile:
               
                  Paul doth will vs lying to put away,Eph. 4.2
                        •
                     
                  
               
               And each man to his neighbour truth to ſay.
            
            
               
               75
               
                  Mat. 12.6.Its written wee a iuſt account muſt giue
               Of euery idle word that we doe ſpeake;
               But yet alas how vainly doe we liue,
               And neuer care how we Gods Statutes breake:
               
                  Mat. 12.37.For by our words wee iuſtifide ſhall be,
               Or elſe condemn'd to liue in miſerie.
            
            
               76
               
                  Pro. 10.11.A righteous mouth is like a Well of life,
               From the which many godly ſtreames doe flow;
               A wicked mouth is alwayes fild with ſtrife,
               Which nought but wrath and violence doth ſhow:
               Knowing the beſt, the ſame we ought to chooſe,
               And from the worſt refraine and it refuſe.
            
            
               77
               Euery member of vs thats within
               With wickedneſſe is ſo repleat and ſtuft;
               Wee are ſo ſoone tempted vnto each ſinne,
               And with ſecurity we be ſo puft:
               If we conſider how we are oppreſt,
               We neuer ſhould liue quiet, nor at reſt.
            
            
               78
               Sinne is a foe externall and internall,
               Eternally heereafter it will ſhame
               And bring vs into the Lake infernall,
               Which ſtill doe burne in continuall flame:
               Both ſoules and bodies ſhall be there tormented,
               If in life time our ſinnes be not repented.
            
            
               79
               
                  Pſal. 51.6.Truth thou requireſt in the inward parts,
               We ſhould performe as much as in vs lies;
               Create in vs both new and contrite hearts,
               Such ones (O Lord) which thou wilt not deſpiſe
               Grant wee may be amongſt the ſheepe elected,
               And not amongſt the Goats to be reiected.
            
            
               
               80
               Our hearts are harder then an Adamant,Zach. 7.12.
               
               Gods Law nor word we at no time will heare,
               So obdurate that we cannot recant
               Our wicked life, nor of God ſtand in feare:
               We nere obey but diſobey him ſtill,
               And doe prouoke to wrath Gods holy will.
            
            
               81
               Yet God is iuſt in all that hath beene done,
               Vnto vs ſinners euery thing is right,
               But we contemned haue God and his ſonne,
               And wickedly haue wee done in his ſight:
               Yet Lord forgiue vs our ſinnes wee thee pray,
               Thy heauy hand of Iuſtice from vs ſtay.
            
            
               82
               Our mind ſo eleuated is with pride,
               Our ſelfe-conceipt doth puffe vs vp on high,
               Our equalls and inferiours we deride,
               Againſt our betters oft-times we inueigh:
               What we affect to be good we approue,
               Though it be hurtfull, yet the ſame we loue.
            
            
               83
               Modeſty is a bridle to raine backeModeſtie and humility are two bridles for Pride.
               
               This ſwift wingd pride ſwifter then a ſwallow,
               Our appetite to it wee ſhould keepe ſlacke;
               For if we giue way ſure it will follow:
               If that we let it run his full Careere,
               Ore ſoules and bodies it will donineere.
            
            
               84
               What things we doe we muſt of it eſteeme,
               So that in it no pride at all we take;
               Better then wee are we ought not to deemeRom. 12.3.
               
               Our ſelues▪ but from all errors to awake:
               He that thinkes himſelfe wiſe in's own conceit,
               Doth like a foole fill his heart with deceit.
            
            
               
               85
               Humility a curbe to keepe vs in,
               Much like a Snaffle, nay rather a Bit,
               Which doth with-hold vs from that deadly ſinne,
               
                  Mat. 11.4.And keepe vs that we doe not it commit:
               Who humbleth himſelfe like vnto a Child.
               Of Heauens Ioyes ſhall not be beguild.
            
            
               86
               
                  Pſa. 131.13.Like weaned Children we ſhould vs behaue,
               Haue no proud lookes, nor yet no ſcornfull minde;
               If that we doe intend our ſoules to ſaue,
               Theſe miſdemeanors wee muſt caſt behind:
               Our ſmalleſt thoughts on it we muſt not ſpend,
               On Elohim ſhould all our hope depend.
            
            
               87
               The pleaſures of the fleſh are manifold,
               Yea numberleſſe they cannot be accounted;
               Which cauſeth all to ſinne both young and old,
               Our ſinnes the ſands in number haue ſurmounted:
               In number more then the haires of our head,
               Such an impious Courſe of life we haue led.
            
            
               88
               Now hauing thus deſcrib'd each ſeuerall ſence,
               Throughout mans body in which ſinne doth raigne;
               Which oft is coloured vnder good pretence,
               Of godlines from which we doe refraine:
               We take no paines nor care the Lord to ſerue,
               The leaſt of's mercies we doe not deſerue.
            
            
               89
               We neuer thanke God for what he hath done,
               Creating vs after his Image right;
               And redeeming vs with Chriſt his deere Sonne,
               To ſanctifie vs with his holy Spirit:
               By our workes we expect Iuſtification,
               And after death we hope glorification.
            
            
               
               90
               My Muſe to the laſt enemy is come,
               With much adoe the other two are paſt;
               My ſcantling glaſſe of time is almoſt runne,
               Time is ſoone gone, yet comes againe as faſt:
               Lord I beſeech thee guide my heart and hand,
               This cunning Aduerſary to withſtand.
            
            
               91
               Sathan did tempt our Parents firſt of all,Our third enemy is the Diuell. Gen. 3.4.
               
               And the forbidden fruite caus'd them to eate:
               Eating this fruit it brought's all into thrall,
               Our miſery no tongue can halfe repeate:
               Deceiuer-like hee ſaid yee ſhall not dye,
               To which they condiſcended willingly.
            
            
               92
               And eate the fruit forbidden of the Lord,
               Hee firſt vnto the woman did it giue,
               Shee to her Husband, thus with one accord
               Both ſure of death though promiſed to liue:
               By his inticements hee them both allured,
               By which he their eternall woe procured.
            
            
               93
               Againſt the feebler Sexe his Rage is ſhowne,
               The woman he did firſt of all attempt;
               Thus his deceit was at the firſt made knowne,
               Yet from ſeducing he would not exempt,
               Nor free himſelfe; but like an old deceiuer,
               Of Soule and Bodies good hee's a bereauer.
            
            
               94
               Hee's alwayes ready for to lay his baites
               To catch all ſilly Soules and to inſnare
               Them in his ſubtile and deceiuing ſlights;
               For to withſtand him then we muſt prepare,
               We cannot him reſiſt doe what we can;
               Helpe us Lord, for vaine is the helpe of Man.
            
            
               
               95
               
                  The preſumption of Sathan.Our Sauiours preſence he did not refraine,
               With proffer'd ſhew of worldly wealth and pleaſure;
               This worldly pleaſure hee did cleane diſdaine,
               Hauing Gods word farre better then all treaſure:
               
                  Mat. 4.10.Sathan did tempt, yea reattempt againe,
               And thrice deui'de before hee would refraine.
            
            
               96
               In thouſand ſhapes hee will to vs appeare,
               What wee command him he will that fulfill;
               Inuiſible, we ca'nt him ſee nor heare,
               Yet ſoone will bee obedient to our will:
               Of our deſire we ſhall not faile or miſſe,
               On the condition that wee will be his.
            
            
               97
               To any thing hee'l tempt vs that is ill,
               Each motion that is good hee'l from vs put;
               With idleneſſe allure vs he will ſtill,
               Our thoughts in ignorance he cloſe will ſhut:
               And blind vs from the loue of God the higheſt,
               
                  2 Ioh. 1.7.Hee's a Deceiuer and an Antichriſt.
            
            
               98
               Hee often will inſinuate into
               Our heads, our thoughts, our hearts for to offend;
               God, King, and Countrey, all for to vndoe,
               In whoſe defence our deare blood we ſhould ſpend:
               Againſt our ſelues he our owne ſelues will ſet,
               For to deſtroy vs if wee haue no let.
            
            
               99
               Hee will attempt vs for to hang our ſelues,
               
                  Gal. 3.13.Whereby Gods heauy wrath we doe procure;
               To die in ſuch a caſe like deſperate clues,
               A curſe denounced againſt all its ſure:
               Yea againſt all that doe this ſinne commit,
               
                  Amen.God grant we may haue grace to witſtand it.
            
            
               
               100
               Sometime he tempts vs when we are aſleepe,
               With falſe deluding and deceitfuil dreames;
               To drench our ſelues in ſome vaſt Ocean deepe,
               And loſe our liues in one of Neptunes ſtreames:
               God did it giue, it's hee that muſt it take,1 Cor. 10.20
               
               A Sathans ſacrifice we muſt not make.If wee deſtroy our bodies, wee ſacrifice them to the Diuell.
               
            
            
               101
               Of our owne bodies or of any other,
               If Sathan doe intice vs for to murther;
               Our deareſt friends, our Siſter, or our brother,
               To doe wicked deeds he will vs further:
               With hearty prayers we muſt it preuent,
               Thinke not on future time, but on th'euent.
            
            
               102
               And what will follow after ſhedding blood,
               Eſpecially of thoſe whom God doth loue:
               That we nere had beene borne it had beene good,Mat. 26.24.
               
               Then to prouoke the holy one aboue:
               And grieue his holy Spirit which did ſealeEphe. 4.30.
               
               Vs to ſaluation if wee haue true zeale.
            
            
               103
               A murtherer from the OriginallIoh. 8 44.
               
               
                  Belzebub is, the truth hee doth abhorre;
               Alſo of lies he is the principall,
               And is to be of vs abhord therefore,
               Becauſe that in the truth we ſhould reioyce,1 Cor. 13.6.
               
               And laud the Lord both with our hearts and voice.
            
            
               104
               He can transforme himſelfe to any ſhape,
               His cunning purpoſes for to obtaine;
               Vnto the likeneſſe of a Beare or Ape,
               And then that likeneſſe can againe regaine:
               And change himſelfe perchance to ſome Creature,
               Hee is of ſuch a variable nature.
            
            
               
               105
               Like a Camelion quickly he can change
               His darke and obſcure forme both cleare and bright:
               Throughout the ſpacious Orbe he ſtill doth range,
               
                  2 Cor. 11.14. Eph. 2.2.And turnes himſelfe to an Angels ſhape of light;
               Prince of the Ayer he is cald likewiſe,
               Which workes in thoſe that doe the Lord deſpiſe.
            
            
               106
               To malice, pride, and anger hee'l prouoke
               Vs vnto drunkenneſſe and letcherie;
               All Godly thoughts in vs he ſure will choake,
               And ſtirre vs vp to wrath and trechery:
               To play the Prodigall and the vnthrift,
               To win our ſoules to him is all his drift.
            
            
               107
               Each baite for vice is hidden vnder pleaſure,
               Which greedily wee follow and purſue;
               And wickedneſſe we worke beyond meaſure,
               We nere regard, nor thinke what will enſue:
               So that of pleaſure we may haue our fill,
               Wee doe not care although our ſoules it ſpill.
            
            
               108
               Vnder the honeſt ſhew of cleanlineſſe,
               Pride walketh mask't yet all men may it ſee;
               Old griping, carking raking couetouſnes,
               Is cald of euery cloth good Husbandrie,
               In the ſuperlatiue degree they ſweare,
               As if the Diuell ſhould them rent and teare.
            
            
               109
               
                  Iam. 5.12.My brethren ſaith Saint Iames ſweare not at all▪
               
               Nether by Heauen nor yet by the Earth,
               Nor any Oth that may our ſoules inthrall,
               When euer Mors doth come to ſtop our breath,
               
                  Mat. 5.37.Yea, yea, nay, nay, are the oathes wee ſhould call,
               Leaſt into condemnation we fall.
            
            
               
               110
               Thus Swearing is the Diuels inſtrument,
               On of the lowdſt alarums he can found;
               Likewiſe the Diuell Pride did firſt inuent,
               The firſt Author of any ſinne that's found:
               Hee's the firſt founder of iniquity,
               And the Originall of all antiquity.
            
            
               111
               We muſt aſſault this ſeauen headed beaſt,Reu. 12.3.
               
               Hauing ten hornes; yet not with dint of ſword,
               Ne Lance nor Speare (deceiuing hee'l nere reſt)
               Hee muſt be conquered by Gods holy word:
               A Chriſtians Armour then we muſt put on,
               And take a Chriſtians courage vs vpon.
            
            
               112
               Our Loynes with truth they muſt be girded well,Eph. 6.44.15 16.17.18.
               
               Of Righteouſnes wee muſt haue the breſt-plate,
               With preparation of the Goſpell,
               Our feet muſt be ſhod, eſchewing all hate:
               The ſhield of Faith, laying aſide all euill,
               To quench the fiery Darts of the Diuell.
            
            
               113
               Alſo the Helmet of Saluation,
               The ſpirituall ſword the Word of God;
               Still praying with Prayer and Suppplication,
               That God would turne away his ſcoerging Rod,
               And all our miſdeeds vtterly deface,
               Blot out our ſinnes they nere may come in place.
            
            
               114
               Neither in this world vs for to accuſe,
               Nor in the world to come vs to condemne;
               The death of Chriſt will all our ſinnes excuſe,
               And his Bowels burie all and ſome:
               And being then from ſeruile ſinne made free,Rom. 6.18.
               
               True ſeruants of righteouſneſſe we might be.
            
            
               
               115
               This old deceiuer will vs not yet leaue,
               So long as there is any ſparke of life;
               In our bodies he will our Soules deceiue,
               Till death doth cut it with his fatall knife:
               Ofttimes in ſickneſſe he will ſome moleſt:
               With terrors which are not to be expreſt.
            
            
               116
               This is the Dragon which would vs deuoure,
               This is the Serpent which did Eue beguile;
               This is the roring Lion which each hower,
               This he that ſeekes t'inſnare vs with his wile:
               This is the father of falſhood and lies,
               The worker of our woes and miſeries.
            
            
               117
               
                  Peter commands vs to be vigillant,
               This deadly Aduerſary to withſtand;
               Him to reſiſt with force and to bee valiant,
               Our ſoules and bodies againſt him to band:
               And reunite our forces altogether,
               Yea to defie him ſtill we muſt perſeuer.
            
            
               118
               If theſe vngodly ſinnes wee follow ſtill,
               And the inticers of them doe obay;
               And follow it: in Folio wee ſhall fill
               A Volume great compil'd againſt that day,
               In which one good deed done will profit more
               Then thouſands of Gold hoorded vp in ſtore.
            
            
               119
               And hauing ſeru'd theſe Maiſters whilſt we liue,
               Farre worſe then ſlaues by them wee are kept vnder;
               Yet vnto them by no meanes we ſhall giue,
               One inch of leaue; for they are nere aſunder:
               To worke our bodies or our ſoules annoy,
               They doe incite themſelues both to deſtroy.
            
            
               
               120
               Our worldly pleaſures little will auaile,
               Our fleſhly luſts will nothing helpe at all;
               Our hoorded wealth will naught at all preuaile,
               When we are ſummon'd by deaths fatall call:
               Who vncertaine yet certaine will meet vs,
               And with, Sir I arreſt you, it will greet vs.
            
            
               121
               Like a bold Sergeant with his Maſe in's fiſt,
               Not to be danted, for death no man feares;
               Who can reſiſt him then, not he that liſt,
               The rich mans threats, nor yet the widdowes teares:
               Hee's vnrelenting for he neuer reſpects,
               Rich, poore, faire, foule, hee all to graue deiects.
            
            
               122
               Hee's ſo impartiall that he none will ſpare,
               Both young and old, yea all death will ſurprize;
               For fatherleſſe nor Orphants he doth care,
               Weepe whilſt they will he nere regards their cryes:
               Death is the wages that is due for ſinne,Rom. 6.13.
               
               Which all our life time wee haue liued in.
            
            
               123
               Certaine death will come, we muſt expect it,
               The time and place God hath from vs conceal'd;
               Is't fit for vs therefore for to neglect it,
               Becauſe our day of death is not reueal'd:
               Wee ſhould thinke on it and premeditate,
               Before it come and our ſelues conſolate.
            
            
               124
               Againſt the time that death will vs depriue,
               Of all this worldly pleaſure wee inioy;
               It is in vaine to withſtand him or ſtriue
               Againſt him: for hee ſoone can vs deſtroy:
               And change vs as is Gods decree we muſt,
               Be turned into aſhes and to duſt.
            
            
               
               125
               Death is the depriuation of Life,
               Ordaind by God, imposd on man for ſinne;
               
                  Rom. 5.12.A puniſhment which endeth all our ſtrift,
               Due vnto vs ſince Life did firſt begin:
               And by the diſobedience of one man,
               Sinne entred firſt, and death by him began.
            
            
               126
               To ſeize on all the time of Adams Kace,
               Vpon each Creature, there's not one that's free,
               Or can eſcape, each one muſt it imbrace,
               Yea, all are ſubiect to Mortality:
               Be it Emperour, King, Potentate or Prince,
               Death ſtands not with him for to diſpence.
            
            
               127
               Two kinds of death the Scripture ſaies there are,
               The firſt whereof is called corporall;
               Of which each Mothers Sonne muſt haue a ſhare;
               The laſt and ſecond is ſpirituall.
               Ordain'd by God to be a puniſhment,
               For all hard hardned hearts that don't repent.
            
            
               128
               Of corporall death each Creature muſt taſt,
               Birds, Fiſhes, Beaſts, as well as mortall men;
               Therefore before ſpirituall death it's paſt,
               As it in order firſt proceedeth when
               Corporall death of life doth vs depriue,
               Gainſt which all humane creatures ſtill do ſtriue.
            
            
               129
               Betwixt Mans death and Beaſts the difference
               After they are of vitall life bereauen,
               The ſpirit of Man hath his perfect eſſence,
               With the immortall God that reignes in Heauen:
               And though mans body be diſſolu'd to duſt,
               At day of Iudgement riſe againe we muſt.
            
            
               
               130
               And hauing finiſhed death corporall,
               Which is the depriuation of breath;
               So that our ſoules may become immortall,
               So that wee need not feare the ſecond death:Reu. 2.11
               
               That through Chriſt who hath bruiz'd the Serpents head,
               Our ſoules may liue although our Bodies dead.
            
            
               131
               Yet dead we are not, but in Chriſt we ſleepe,
               Though in the ground our bodies buried be;
               We hope th
                     •
                  ogh Chriſt that God our ſoules doth keep
               Who hath redeem'd vs with his blood, and freed
               Vs from the bondage both of death and Hell,
               That his elected might in glory dwell.
            
            
               132
               The death of a beaſt now is otherwiſe,
               Hee being dead his body is reſolued;
               To the firſt maker his ſoule doth ariſe
               From the temperature, and is diſſolued,
               To nothing, which was nothing firſt of all,
               There is the end of breath and life finall.
            
            
               133
               Spirituall d
                     •
                  ath's the totall ſeparation,
               Of Soule and body from the loue of Chriſt;
               And from that bleſſed Congregation,
               Which doe remaine aboue with God the higheſt
               Triumphantly reioyce and ſinging praiſe,
               Lauding and bleſſe Gods holy name alwaies.
            
            
               134
               Who would not then ſpend well in this little time,
               That is beſtowed on vs, and vs lent;
               We ſhould haue a care to commit no crime,
               To ſerue the Lord our chiefe care ſhould be bent;
               In prime of youth we ought to thinke on death,
               Seeing you know not when hee'le ſtop our breath.
            
            
               
               135
               Perhaps it may be at this preſent hower,
               When leaſt of all wee thinke vpon our end;
               Man withereth (ſaith Job) as doth a flower,
               So doth Man periſh and come to an end:
               Chriſt which our ſins did beare this ſalue did giue,
               
                  Pet. 11.24.Being dead through ſinne, to righteouſneſſe to liue.
            
            
               136
               Our youthfull dayes of iollity and pleaſure,
               Thoſe dayes wee ſacrifice vnto the diuell;
               For Gods ſeruice ſeldome we find leaſure,
               Our lips is 
                     •
                  o compoſed of all euill,
               That ſin
                     •
                  e we doe commit whilſt we haue power,
               And nere deſiſt from ſinning day nor hower.
            
            
               137
               But to doe euill ſtill we doe inſue,
               
                  Eph. 4.19.All wickedneſſe we worke with greedineſſe,
               Each motion that is good we doe eſchew,
               Wee giue our minds vnto laſciuiouſneſſe,
               With wanton pleaſures we our ſelues deceiue,
               And nere leaue ſinning till ſinne doth vs leaue.
            
            
               138
               Death in his nature fearefull is and grim,
               Chriſt by his death that feare hath rane away,
               And with his powerfull death vanquiſhed him,
               That we to death triumphantly may ſay:
               
                  1 Cor. 15.55Death wheres thy ſting? and likewiſe to the graue
               No victory of vs thou now canſt haue.
            
            
               139
               
                  Pſal. 90.10.
                  Moſes deſcribes our yeares threeſcore and ten,
               But few doe liue to that, fewer to more;
               So ſhort then are the dayes of mortall men,
               Not one to twenty liues to be foure ſcore:
               That godly Moſes to the Lord ſtill prayes,
               Teach me (ſaith he) for to number my dayes.
            
            
               
               140
               That holy Dauid likewiſe doth intreatPſal. 39.4.
               
               That he the number of his dayes might know;
               Yea earneſtly theſe words he doth repeate,
               As is apparant, wherein he doth ſhow:
               To know his frailty he doth it require,
               Which was the totall ſomme of his deſire.
            
            
               141
               My dayes thou haſt made like vnto a ſpan,Pſal. 39.5.
               
               Mine age is nothing in reſpect of thee;
               We muſt returne to duſt doe what we can,
               Euery one liuing is but vanity:
               Like to a ſhadow time doth paſſe away,
               Without controulement, no man can him ſtay.
            
            
               142
               Each day our life doth haſten to an end,
               For wee are neerer vnto death this day,
               Then yeſterday, who can with time contend,
               Nor boſtingly no man ought thus to ſay,
               I certaine am to liue till to morrow,
               The ſmalleſt moment of time who can borrow.
            
            
               143
               Man is by Iob compared vnto graſſe,Iob. 14.2.
               
               Which now doe flouriſh, yet cut downe ere night:
               Or to a ſhadow which apace doth paſſe,
               Swifter then Eagles haſtning in their flight:
               Death ſtill purſues men whereſoere they goe,
               Friend to the Godly, but the wickeds foe.
            
            
               144
               Life is compar'd to things of ſhort continuance,
               To ſmoke, to flowers, which doe vaniſh ſoone;
               Vnto things which are of no perſiſtance,
               And changeth oftner then the changing Moone:
               Vnto a dreame, or likewiſe vnto ſtubble,
               Which fire doth burne, or to a water-bubble.
            
            
               
               145
               Seing mans life is ſo vncertaine then,
               We need not wiſh long liuers for to be,
               Being certaine death will come wee know not when,
               And longeſt liuers greateſt ſinners be:
               Although we liue long, yet death comes at laſt,
               And then amongſt dead men we muſt be plaſt.
            
            
               146
               
                  Pſal. 34.12.What man is he that liſteth long to liue,
               Vnto the vtmoſt as Long as may be,
               His minde to viciouſneſſe he muſt not giue,
               If that he doe intend good dayes to ſee:
               His heart vprightly he muſt keepe the while,
               His tongue and lips that they do ſpeak no guile.
            
            
               147
               Our life's compos'd of nought but miſery,
               In Youth, in Manhood, and Decrepit age;
               Nothing attends on theſe but vanity,
               Which doth the ſhortneſſe of mans life preſage,
               Which is Compar'd to glaſſe that is ſo brittle,
               And flyeth faſter then a weauers Shittle,
            
            
               148
               For in this life is nought but vexation,
               Our minds and bodies are alwayes troubled,
               Repleat with ſorrow and contemplation,
               Chriſts death theſe ſorrowes all hath comforted,
               And buried them in his deare precious blood,
               Which is the ſalue that ſhould do our ſoules good.
            
            
               149
               God grant it may, that we may raigne in heauen,
               And with Jehoua ſing continuall praiſe;
               Of care and ſorrowes wee ſhall be bere
                     •
                  aen,
               If we take care to ſerue the Lord alwayes:
               Which for to doe we muſt our ſelues indeauour,
               From doing good we neuer muſt perſeuer.
            
            
               
               150
               For of wel-doing we ſhould not be weary,
               As wee haue ſowne ſo wee ſhall reape likewiſe;Gal. 6.8.
                        •
                     .
               
               Yea in due time we ſhall reape and be merry,
               If that we faint not, nor Gods lawes deſpiſe:
               We need not feare the fatall dint of death,
               Come when it will it can but take our breath.
            
            
               151
               Our bodies for a while may be diſſolu'd,
               And turn'd to duſt and earth from whence twas tane:Gen. 18.27.
               
               Our ſoules ſhall liue w'are certainly reſolu'd,
               To raigne with Chriſt with whom they did remaine:
               When we were in our Mothers wombe conceiued,
               Before we were into the world receiued.
            
            
               152
               As our ſoule is the vnion of life,
               So is 
                     •
                  he Spirit of God the ſoule of ours,
               Which cannot be diuided with deaths knife,
               If God his Spirit into our ſoules once power:
               In the Celeſtiall heauen we ſhall raigne,
               And neuer feele the force of death againe.
            
            
               153
               The thought of death in ſome will terror breed,
               (And like Belſhazzar make them trembling ſtand;)
               At the rememberance of each thought and deed,
               When all our enemies themſelues doe band
               Againſt vs; and the diuell will imploy,
               His beſt indeauors our ſoules to deſtroy.
            
            
               154
               Death to the Godly is a welcome gueſt,
               And ſuch a one as they doe long to ſee,
               It being come their troubles ſhall haue reſt,
               And they Gods glory face to face ſhall ſee:
               Bleſſed are thoſe that in the Lord doe die,Reu. 14.
                        •
                     .
               
               From their labours they reſt eternally.
            
            
               
               155
               Certaine vncertaine death we muſt expect,
               And at all times we muſt ſtand on our Guard,
               No time nor moment we muſt once neglect,
               Vnto our ſelues we muſt haue more regard:
               That death at no time vnprouided catch vs,
               And vnexpected to the graue do ſnatch vs.
            
            
               156
               In dying well, God doth two things require,
               Of euery Chriſtian man that he ſhould ſaue;
               At theſe two things I greatly doe admire,
               To ſee that men no greater wiſedome haue:
               But to neglect a thing of greateſt: good,
               In time to come if they it vnderſtood.
            
            
               157
               The firſt is on death to premeditate,
               Come wh
                     •
                  n it will we may be ready for it;
               And not deferre it till it be too late,
               So that wee need not feare it, nor abhorre it:
               To bid death welcome we ſhould ready be,
               And think't the ioyful'ſt day we ere ſhall ſee.
            
            
               158
               The ſecond thing God doth of vs require,
               At time of death well our ſelues to behaue;
               Whereby we may eſcape Hels burning fire,
               And flye to Chriſt that he our ſoules may ſaue:
               This wee ſhould doe, deaths vigor to preuent,
               'Gainſt God doth come and call vs to iudgement.
            
            
               159
               VVhilſt we are liuing yet we may relent,
               And turne from vs Gods wrath and indignation,
               But being dead its too late to repent,
               There is no ſacrifice nor ſatisfaction:
               For after death there is no change at all,
               The tree doth lie as is at firſt his fall.
            
            
               
               160
               And as men die they muſt to indgement riſe,Qualis vitae finisita.
               
               To anſwer for thoſe ſinnes they haue committed;
               Euen as they dyed and no otherwiſe,
               They can adde nought, nor ought can be omitted:
               To think on death each man ſomtime ſhould ſpend,
               If that hee'l make a ſanctified end.
            
            
               161
               As death doth leaue them ſo God will them finde,
               And as hee finds them ſo they iudg'd ſhall be;
               If to doe well they haue themſelues inclin'd,
               From all eternall woe they ſhall be free:
               Certaine all muſt die by Gods appointment,Heb. 9.27.
               
               And after death all muſt come to iudgement.
            
            
               162
               
                  Nam ſcriptum eſt that we account muſt giue,Mat. 12.36.
               
               Of euery idle word we peake thats bad;
               In what ſtate of condition we did liue,
               A Redde rationem muſt be had:Luk. 16.2.
               
               Of all our ſinnes we muſt caſt vp the ſumme,
               When we before Gods Iudgement ſeat doe come.
            
            
               163
               The Booke laid open our offences read,Reu. 20.12.
               
               Before Gods face all muſt trembling ſtand;
               Both ſmall and great, yea all that haue been dead,
               Being ſummoned by Trumpets Command:
               Bleſſed are they thrice bleſſed in their heart.Reu. 20.6.
               
               That in the firſt Re
                     •
                  urrection had part.
            
            
               164
               Whether one talent be hid or deſtroy'd,Mat. 25.1
                        •
                     .
               
               Vnder ground, account ſhall be demanded,
               To what good vſe or bad it be imployed.
               Doing Gods Seruice as we are commanded:
               That we may goe into our Moſters ioy,
               And vtterly be freed from all annoy.
            
            
               
               165
               
                  Mat. 24.29.The Sun in that day ſhall be darkened quite,
               The Firmaments of light ſhall be bereau
                     •
                  n;
               The changing Moone ſhall not renew her light,
               The Starres likewiſe ſhall fall downe from Heauen:
               All mortalls hearts with feare muſt needs be taken
               When as the powers of Heauen ſhall be ſhaken.
            
            
               166
               The Earth ſhall be remou'd from off her place,
               The Ayre ſhall be diſſolu'd to drops with heate;
               Euery thing thus chang'd, it's a heauy caſe,
               The terror of that day who can repeate:
               It would diſſolue a heart harder then Ire,
               To behold the world in a burning fire.
            
            
               167
               
                  Zeph. 1.15.This is a day of wrath and wearineſſe,
               A day of Clouds and of thicke gloomineſſe,
               A day of deſolation and diſtreſſe,
               A day of trouble and of waſtineſſe:
               This day will put the ſtouteſt heart to feare,
               Maugre his force in it he muſt appeare.
            
            
               168
               
                  1 Cor. 5.10.Before the Iudgement ſeat of Ieſus Chriſt,
               For to receiue the guerdion for their hire;
               If it be good they ſhall raigne with the higheſt;
               If otherwiſe they are fit for Hell-fire:
               Fewell for Gods wrath to be tormented,
               Becauſe in life their ſinnes were not repented.
            
            
               169
               
                  Iud. 1.6.
                  Iude, Iames his Brother, likewiſe tels vs plaine,
               That the Angels which kept not their eſtate,
               Their firſt eſtate, but follow'd pleaſures vaine,
               Their Habitation they left deſolate,
               In euerlaſting chaines he them reſerues,
               Againſt the Iudgement day, as they deſerues.
            
            
               
               170
               In what place will the ſinner then apeare,
               No place is left for him himſelfe to hide;
               When God in Iudgement begins to draw neere,
               Before whoſe Iuſtice he cannot abide:
               With all his power he will crye and call,
               And wiſh that mountaines on him then would fall.
            
            
               171
               And hide them from the face of him that ſitteth
               Vpon the Throne, and from the angry Lambe:
               Being a Iudge, all feare to him befitteth,Ioh. 15.
                        •
                     8.
               
               To him that before Abram was, I am:
               
               Before his face all men muſt trembling ſtand,
               Like Belſhazzer ſummond by trumphs command.
            
            
               172
               The ſigne of the Sonne of Man ſhall appeare,
               In the Cloudes comming with power and glory,
               Who will aſtoniſh all mens hearts with feare,
               What will profit this life tranſitory?
               Each creature for feare ſhall be forlorne,
               And all the Tribes of the earth then ſhall mourne.
            
            
               173
               In an inſtant God will his Angels ſend,Mat. 25.39.
               
               With Trumpets ſound to gather his Elect;
               From the foure corners of the earth hee'l ſend
               Legions of Angels to call his Elect:
               This Iudgement's generall we muſt ſurmiſe,Mat. 29 
                        •
                     2.
               
               All graues muſt open, all dead muſt ariſe.
            
            
               174
               And all before the Iudge muſt be preſented,
               Rich, poore, young, old, perſons are not reſpected,
               Twice happy are thoſe that their ſinnes repented,Rom. 2.11.
               
               But treble woe to thoſe that it neglected:
               The ioyes of one ſhall nere be deceiued,
               The others torments cannot be conceiued.
            
            
               
               175
               This is a time of trouble and Vexation,
               A time of griefe of ſorrow and of paine;
               A time of anguiſh and deſolation,
               A time that former time will not regaine:
               One hower the worth of thouſands will ſurmount,
               Of howers, dayes, years, we now make no account.
            
            
               176
               A ſeparation of Goates from the ſheep,
               Sheepe on the right hand, Goates on left being placd:
               With mercy and iuſtice God will iudgement keepe,
               In no wiſe he will haue his Saints diſgrac'd:
               Each one ſhall ſhine farre brighter then the Sun,
               Being ſo decreed by God it muſt be done.
            
            
               177
               Vnto the ſheepe with ioy the Lord ſhall ſay,
               
                  Mat. 25.34.Come yee bleſſed of my Father inherit
               The Kingdome that's prepar'd for you for aye,
               Becauſe in life time you the ſame did merit:
               You cloath'd me naked, hungry you me fed,
               And if not me, poore Brethren in my ſtead.
            
            
               178
               Vnto the goates the Lord will ſay in's ire,
               
                  Mat. 25.41.Yee workers of iniquity depart;
               Goe yee curſed into erelaſting fire,
               I doe hate and abhorre you with my heart:
               I being hungry you no meate me gaue,
               And in my Kingdome you no ſhare ſhall haue.
            
            
               179
               What ioy and ſorrow will be vttered then,
               The iuſt to goe ſinging continuall praiſe;
               That they ſhall raigne with God who were but men,
               In the fellowſhip of Angels alwayes:
               Continually with prayſes there to ſing,
               Vnto the Lord both earth and heauens King.
            
            
               
               180
               Oh endleſſe Ioy that doth all Ioy containe,
               Oh happy hauen whoſe harbor is eaſe;
               Oh place of reſt for to be freed from paine,
               Oh fruitfull tree that fruit doſt neuer lack,
               Oh place delightfull which ſhall neuer ceaſe,
               Oh Bleſt hauen that nere ſuffereſt wracke.
            
            
               181
               Euen as their Ioyes be innumerable,
               So in likewiſe the wicked are in paine;
               They ſuffer torments inſupportable,
               And nere ſhall be at eaſe nor reſt againe,
               A terrible woe againſt them is denounſt,
               When as the ſentence, goe, is once pronounc'd.
            
            
               182
               Woe be to them they ſtill ſhall liue in paine,
               Woe vnto them they torments ſhall indure;
               Woe to them they ſhall nere be freed againe,
               Woe to their ſinnes for they did this procure:
               Wo be to them, and woe be to vs all,
               For ſinning thus we bring our ſoules in thral
            
            
               183
               Now that we may leaue ſinning God grant grace,
               That in the higheſt heauens we may raigne;
               There to behold Jehouahs ſhining face,
               In that celeſtiall place ſtill to remaine:
               There we ſhall praiſe his name with one accord
               With ſinging Halleluiah to the Lord.
            
            
               
                  Memento to eſſe Mortalem.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

