
   
      
         
            The remedy of prophanenesse. Or, Of the true sight and feare of the Almighty A needful tractate. In two bookes. By Ios. Exon.
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1637
            
         
         Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 138 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02586
            STC 12710
            ESTC S103753
            99839498
            99839498
            3926
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02586)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3926)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1175:17)
         
         
            
               
                  The remedy of prophanenesse. Or, Of the true sight and feare of the Almighty A needful tractate. In two bookes. By Ios. Exon.
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [14], 252, [12], 83, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Thomas Harper, for Nathanael Butter, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the pyde-Bull, at S. Austins Gate,
                  London :
                  1637.
               
               
                  Ios. Exon. = Joseph Hall.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  "A sermon preach't in the city of Excester, at the consecration of a new buriall-place, there, on Saint Bartholomews day, Aug. 24. 1637" has separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous.
                  With errata list on imprimatur leaf. Variant: without errata list; preliminaries ([24] p.) in an earlier imposition.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Fear of God --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE REMEDY OF PROPHANENESSE.
            OR, OF The true ſight and feare of the ALMIGHTY.
            A needfull Tractate.
            In two Bookes.
            BY IOS. EXON.
            
               LONDON, Printed by Thomas Harper, for Nathanael Butter, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the pyde-Bull, at S. Auſtins Gate, 1637.
         
         
            
            
            Imprimatur.
            
               SA. BAKER.
               
                  Octob. 11. 1637.
            
         
         
            
            
            The Contents.
            THe Remedy of Prophaneneſſe.
A Sermon Preach't in the City of Exceſter, at the conſecration of a new Buriall-place there, Gen. 23.19.20.
            
         
         
            
            
            
               Reader,
            
            
               I Had meant to take leave of the Preſſe, as one that repented to bee guilty of this common ſurfet. Yet once againe my zeale urges me to breake ſilence. I finde ſo little feare of God in this world which I am ſhortly leaving, that

I could not forbeare, after my tears, to beſtow ſome inke upon it. Every man can bewaile it, I have ſtudied to redreſſe it. Wee may indevour that which GOD onely can effect. I humbly leave this to the worke of no leſſe then an omnipotent grace. In the meane time it is both holy and laudable to project the remedies; and it ſhall bee the no-ſmall comfort of my death-bed, that I have

left behind me this ſeaſonable advice of better thoughts; which, when I am gone, may ſurvive to the benefit of many: Know withall that this Treatiſe entred the Preſſe under the honored name of my deare Lord, the Earle of Norwich, whoſe death preventing the publication, hath ſent it forth Patron-leſſe; Mee thought I ſhould not indure that what was once his, in my deſtination,

ſhould ever bee any others; Let this blanke be as my laſt memoriall of the honour that I juſtly beare to that incomparable friend, both alive and dead, ſerve to profeſſe unto the world, that theſe papers yeeld themſelves not unwilling Orphans upon his loſſe: But why doe I ſo miſ-name his glory? That bleſſed ſoule not ſtaying the leiſure of my preſent directions, haſted up to the free view of the

face of his God, which I could onely ſhew dimly, and aloofe. There will be more uſe of the imitation of his practice, then of the honour of his protection; Let us goe cheerefully on in the ſteps of true piety, and conſcionable obedience, untill our faith likewiſe ſhall ſhut up in an happy fruition.
         
         
            
            
            The Contents of the ſeverall Sections.
            
               BOOKE I.
               
                  Proem. THe occaſion, need and uſe of the Treatiſe enſuing.
               
                  Sect. 1. No one word can expreſſe that grace which we treat of; what it includes and intimates. Feare is no fit terme for it: Affections well imployed, turne vertues. Wherein holy feare conſiſts: What is required to the attaining of it:

                     The ſight of God.
                     The ſight of our ſelves.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 2. Of the ſight of the Inviſible: Moſes a fit patterne for it. Two waies wherein he ſaw the Inviſible. Our felicity conſiſts in the ſight of God: the degrees of our ſpirituall ſight: how ſight and inviſibility may conſiſt together.
               
                  
                  Sect. 3. How wee may not think to ſee God: Not by any fained repreſentation; Not by the worke of improved reaſon; Not in a full comprehention; Not here in his divine eſſence, or height of reſplendence. How Moſes deſired to ſee the face of God.
               
                  Sect. 4. How we muſt indeavour to ſ
                     •
                  e the Inviſible:

                     
                        1. That our eyes muſt be cleared from all hindrances of ſight.
                     
                        2. That bleſſed object muſt bee ſet before our eyes.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 5.
                  
                     
                        3. There muſt be an exaltation, and fortification of our ſight.
                     
                        4. There muſt be a trajection of the viſuall beames of the ſoule thorow all earthly occurrences.
                     
                        5. A divine irradiation of the mind muſt follow: what light wee muſt conceive.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 6.
                  
                     
                        
                           6. The eye muſt be fixed upon this bleſſed object unremoveably.
                        How this may bee effected, and how farre.
                        
                           Three waies of our apprehention of God.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 7.
                  
                     
                        7. There will follow a delight and complacency in that God whom wee ſee. Reprobates doe rather ſee Gods anger, than himſelfe.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 8. Motives to ſtirre us up to ſtrive to this happie ſight: The act is reward enough to it ſelfe:

                     
                        1. This ſight frees us from being tranſported with earthly vanities.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 9.
                  
                     
                        2. It is a prevalent meanes to reſtraine us from ſinning.
                     
                        3. It upholds us in the conſtant ſuffering of evill.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 10.
                  
                     
                        4. It enters us into our heaven. This viſion is not without a fruition: not ſo in other objects.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 11. Of the caſting downe our eyes to ſee our owne wretchedneſſe. How fraile we are; how ſinfull; in how wofull condition by our ſinne.
            
            
               
               BOOKE II.
               
                  Sect. 1. WHat the feare of God is. A double ſtamp or ſignature in this impreſſion of feare.

                     
                        1. An inward adoration of God.
                     
                        2. A filiall care of being approved to God.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 2. What inward adoration is; wherein it conſiſts, and how to be wrought. Of Gods infinite greatneſſe, ſhown in the Creation of the world, and the government thereof, in the frame of the heaven, earth, ſea, man himſelfe.
               
                  Sect. 3. Of Gods infinite mercy ſhown in the redemption of mankind.
               
                  Sect. 4. Of the holy mixture of this feare: Of the continuation and perpetuily of it.
               
                  Sect. 5. Religious adoration diffuſed through our whole outward cariage, in our reſpects.

                     
                        1. To the holy name of God. The

Iewes ſcruples; our careleſneſſe.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 6.
                  
                     
                        2. To the word of God.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 7.
                  
                     
                        3. To the ſervices of God, Prayer, Preaching, Adminiſtration of Sacraments.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 8.
                  
                     
                        4. To the houſe of God.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 9.
                  
                     
                        5. To the meſſengers of God.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 10. Of the humble ſubjection of our ſelves to the hand of God.

                     
                        1. In ſuffering from him meekely, and patiently: The good examples thereof.
                     
                        2. In all changes of eſtates.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 11. Of our child-lik care of a ſecret approving our ſelves to God, and avoyding his diſpleaſure: How wee are affected after wee have beene miſcarried. The holy jelouſy and ſuſpicion of Gods children: This feare a retentive from ſinne. Rifeneſſe of ſinne, an argument of the want of this feare. Wicked hearts muſt have terrible remedies. The miſplaced feare of prophane men.
               
                  
                  Sect. 12. Of the filiall indevour of obedience; in particular callings, ariſing from this feare. The happy effects and iſſue of this feare.
               
                  Sect. 13. Of the extreames of this feare, on both ſides.

                     
                        1. Whereof the firſt is Security: whence it ariſeth. Of the abuſe of Gods mercy, in giving and forgiving.
                     
                        2. Of the cuſtome of ſinning.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 14.
                  Of the remedies of Security.
                  Meanes to keepe the heart tender.
                  Meditations of Gods judgements, and of our owne frailties.
                  A reſolution to repell the firſt motions of ſinne.
                  Care of ſpeedy recovery after our fall.
                  Due heed not to check the conſcience.
                  A right eſtimation of worldy things.
               
               
                  
                  Sect. 15. Of Preſumption, another oppoſite to feare.

                     Preſumption of the way.
                     Preſumption of the end.
                  
                  
                     
                        1. In matter of event.
                     
                        2. In matter of ability.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 16. The remedies of Preſumption, in the ſeverall kindes of it.

                     
                        1. In reſpect of outward events; of our due valuation of them.
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 17.
                  
                     
                        
                           2. In reſpect of abilities.
                        An exact ſurvay of our graces.
                        The differences betwixt counterfeit vertues and true.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Sect. 18.
                  The remedy of our preſumption of the end, which is ſalvation.
                  Of our modeſt conſideration of the waies and counſels of God.
               
               
                  Sect. 19. The extreames on the other hand.

                     
                        1. Of the feare of horrour; how to be remdyed.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Sect. 20.
                  
                     
                        
                           2. Of the feare of diſtruſt; with the remedy thereof.
                        Concluſion.
                        A recapitulation of the whole.
                     
                  
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            OF THE SIGHT and FEARE of the ALMIGHTY. The Firſt Book.
            
               The Proem.
               
                  NOthing is more eaſie to obſerve, than that the mind of man (beeing ever prone to extremities) is no ſooner fetcht

off from Superſtition, than it is apt to fall upō Prophaneneſſe: finding no meane betwixt exceſſe of devotion, and an irreligious neglect. No wiſe Chriſtian, who hath ſo much as ſojourned in the world, can chooſe but feele, and (with griefe of heart) confeſſe this truth: We are ready to think of Gods matters, as no better than our owne: And a ſaucy kind of familiarity, this way, hath bred a palpable contempt; ſo as we walk with the great God of Heaven, as with our fellow; and think of his ſacred Ordinances, as either ſome common imployment, or faſhionable ſuperfluity. Out of

an earneſt deſire therefore to ſettle in my ſelfe, and others, right thoughts, and meet diſpoſitions of heart, towards the glorious and infinite Majeſty of our God, and his holy ſervices (wherein we are all apt to be too defective) I have put my pen upon this ſeaſonable task; beſeeching that Almighty God, (whoſe work it is) to bleſſe it both in my hand, and in the perufall of all Readers; whom I beſeech to know, that I have written this, not for their eyes, but for their hearts; and therefore charge them as they tender the good of their owne ſoules, not to reſt in the bare ſpeculation, but to work themſelves

to a ſerious, and ſenſible practice of theſe holy preſcriptions, as without which, they ſhall never have either true hold of God, or found peace, and comfort in their owne ſoules.Pſal. 34.11 
                  Come then yee children, hearken unto me, and I ſhall teach you the feare of the Lord; There cannot be a fitter leſſon for me, in the improvement of my age, to reade, nor for your ſpirituall advantage to take out: One glance of a thought, of this kind, is worth a volume of quarrelſome litigation.
            
            
               
               SECT. II.
               AS above we ſhall need no words; when we ſhall be all ſpirit, and our language ſhall be all thoughts, ſo, below, wee cannot but want words, wherein to cloath the true notions of our hearts. I never yet could find a tongue, that yeelded any one terme to notifie the awfull diſpoſition of the heart towards God; wee are wont to call it Feare; but this appellation comes farre too ſhort; for this ſignifies an affection; whereas this, which we treat of, is no other than an excellent vertue, yea a grace

rather; yea rather a precious compoſition of many divine graces, and vertues.
               
                  Gen. 42.18 Deu 6.13. Pſa. 25.12. Eccl. 12.13 Pſal. 128.1.It is no marvell therefore, if the Spirit of God have wont under this one word, to comprehend all that belongs either to the apprehenſion, or adoration of a God; For this alone includes all the humble conſtitution of an holy ſoule, and all the anſwerable demeanure of a mortified creature: neither is there any thing ſo well becomming an heart ſenſible of infiniteneſſe, as this which wee are faine to miſ-name Feare.
               
               To ſpeak properly, there is no feare but of evill, and that

wch we juſtly call ſervile: which is a doubtfull expectation of ſomething that may be hurtfull to us: and this, when it prevailes, is horror, and dreadfull confuſion; an affection (or perturbation rather) fit for the gallies, or hell it ſelfe; Love caſts it out, as that which is ever accompanied with a kind of hate; and ſo will we; we are meditating of ſuch a temper of the heart,Pſa. 103.17 128.4 Eccl. 8.11. as in the continuance of it is attended with bleſſedneſſe; as in the exerciſe of it, is fixed upon infinite greatneſſe, and infinite goodneſſe, and in the meane time is accompanied with unſpeakable peace, and contentment in

the Soule.
               And yet, who ſo had a deſire to retaine the word (if our Ethick Doctors would give him leave) might ſay, that affections well imployed upon excellent objects, turne vertues; ſo love though commonly marſhelled in thoſe lower ranks of the ſoule, yet when it is elevated to the All-glorious God, is juſtly ſtyled the higheſt of Theologicall vertues, yea, when it riſes but to the levell of our brethren, it is Chriſtian charity; ſo, griefe for ſinne, is holy penitence; and what more heavenly grace can be incident into the ſoule, than joy in the holy Ghoſt? Neither is it

otherwiſe with Feare, when it is taken up with worldly occurrents of paine, loſſe, ſhame, it is no better than a troubleſome paſſion, but when wee ſpeak of the feare of God, the caſe and ſtyle is ſo altered, that the breaſt of a Chriſtian is not capable of a more divine grace. But not to dwell in ſyllables, nor to examine curious points of morality: That which we ſpeak of, is no other than a reverentiall awe of the holy and infinite majeſty of God, conſtantly and unremovably ſetled in the ſoule; A diſpoſition ſo requiſite, that he who hath it, cannot but be a Saint, and he that hath it not, is in a ſort without

God in the world. To the producing whereof there is need of a double apprehenſion; The one of an incomprehenſible excellence, and inſeparable preſence of God; The other of a moſt miſerable vileneſſe, and, as it were, nothingneſſe of our ſelves. The former is that which the ſpirit of God calls the ſight of the Inviſible: For ſight is a ſenſe of the quickeſt, and ſureſt perception; ſo as in ſeeing of God, we apprehend him infinitely glorious in all that he is, in all that he hath, in all that he doth; and intimately preſent to us, with us, in us.
            
            
               
               SECT. II.
               LEt us then firſt ſee what that Sight is; wherein we cannot have a more meet patterne than Moſes; that expoſed infant, who in his cradle of Bulruſhes was drawne out of the flagges of Nilus, is a true embleme of a regenerate ſoule, taken up out of the mercy of a dangerous world, in whoſe waves he is naturally ſinking: Hee that was ſaved from the waters ſaw God in fire; and in an holy curioſity haſted to ſee the Buſh that burned, and conſumed not; Let our godly zeale carry us as faſt to ſee what he ſaw;

and make us eagerly ambitious of his eyes, of his Art. Surely Moſes, as St. Stephen tels us, was learned in all the wiſedome of the Egyptians; Hee was not a greater Courtier, than a Scholler: But, Moſes his Opricks were more worth than all the reſt of his skill. All Egypt, and Chaldea to boot, though they were famous of old for Mathematick Sciences, could not teach him this Art of ſeeing the Inviſible: As only the Sunne gives us light to ſee it ſelfe, ſo only the Inviſible God gives a man power to ſee himſelfe that is Inviſible.
               There is a threefold world objected to humane apprehenſion;

A ſenſible world, an intelligible, a ſpirituall or divine; and accordingly man hath three ſorts of eyes, exerciſed about them; The eye of ſenſe, for this outward and materiall world; of reaſon, for the intelligible; of faith, for the ſpirituall: Moſes had all theſe; By the eye of ſenſe he ſaw Pharaohs Court, and Iſraels ſervitude; By the eye of reaſon he ſaw the myſteries of Egyptian learning; By the eye of faith hee ſaw him that is inviſible. In the eye of ſenſe, even brute creatures partake with him, In the eye of reaſon men, In the faculty of diſcerning ſpirituall and divine things only Saints

and Angels. Doubtleſſe Moſes was herein priviledged above other men, Two wayes therefore did he ſee the Inviſible, Firſt, By viewing the viſible ſignes, and ſenſible repreſentations of Gods preſence; as in the Buſh of Horeb (the hill of viſions:) in the Fire and Cloud in the Mount of Sinai; Secondly, By his owne ſpirituall apprehenſion: That firſt was proper to Moſes, as an eminent favourite of God: This other muſt be common to us with him. That we may then attaine to the true feare and fruition of God, we muſt ſee him that is inviſible, as travellers here, as comprehenſors

hereafter; How we ſhall ſee him in his, and our glorious home, we cannot yet hope to comprehend; When we come there 
                     •
                  o ſee him, we ſhall ſee and know how, and how much we ſee him; and not till then. In the meane time it muſt bee our maine care to bleſſe our eyes with Moſes object, and even upon earth to aſpire to the ſight of the Inviſible. This is an act wherein indeed our cheife felicity conſiſts. It is a curiouſly witty diſquiſition of the Schooles, ſince all beatitude conſiſts in the fruition of God, Whether we more eſſentially, primarily, and directly injoy God in the act of underſtanding,

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
(which is by ſeeing him,) than in the act of will, which is by loving him; and the greateſt Maſters (for ought I ſee) pitch upon the underſtanding in the full ſight of God; as whoſe act is more noble, and abſolute, and the union wrought by it more perfect. If any man deſire to ſpend thoughts upon this divine curioſity,Iohan. de Neapoli. qu. 14. I referre him to the ten reaſons which the Doctor Solennis gives and reſts in, for the deciſion of this point. Surely theſe two go ſo cloſe together, in the ſeparated ſoule, that it is hard, even in thought, to diſtinguiſh them. If I may not rather ſay, that as there is no imaginable

compoſition in that ſpirituall eſſence; ſo its fruition of God is made up of one ſimple act alone, which here reſults out of two diſtinct faculties. It is enough for us to know, that if all perfection of happineſſe and full union with God conſiſt in the ſeeing of him, in his glory, then it is, and muſt be our begun happineſſe, to ſee him (as we may) here below: hee can never be other than he is; our apprehenſion of him varies: Here we can only ſee him darkly, as in a glaſſe, there cleerely, and as hee is. Even here below there are degrees, as of bodily, ſo of ſpirituall, ſight: The newly recovered

blind man ſaw men like trees, the eyes of true ſenſe ſee men like men; The illuminated eyes of Eliſha, and his ſervant, ſaw Angels, invironing them;Act. 7.56. Saint Stephens eyes ſaw heaven opened, and Ieſus ſtanding at the right hand of God: The cleere eyes of Moſes ſee the God of Angels: Saint Pauls eyes ſaw the unutterable glories of the third heaven: ſtill, the better eyes the brighter viſion.
               But what a contradiction is here, in ſeeing the Inviſible? If inviſible, how ſeene? and if ſeene, how inviſible? Surely God is a moſt purely and ſimply ſpirituall eſſence. Here is

no place for that, not ſo much hereſie, as ſtupid conceit, of Anthropomorphiſme: A bodily eie can only ſee bodies like it ſelfe; the eye muſt anſwer the object: A ſpirituall object therefore (as God is) muſt be ſeene by a ſpirituall eye: Moſes his ſoule was a ſpirit, and that ſaw the God of ſpirits: ſo he that is in himſelfe inviſible, was ſeene by an inviſible eye: and ſo muſt be. If we have no eyes but thoſe that are ſeene, we are as very beaſts as thoſe that we ſee; but if we have inviſible and ſpirituall eyes, we muſt improve them to the ſight of him that is inviſible.
            
            
               
               SECT. III.
               LEt us then, to the unſpeakable comfort of our ſoules, inquire, and learne how wee may here upon earth, ſee the inviſible God.
               And ſurely, as it was wiſely ſaid of him of old, that it is more eaſie to know what God is not, than what he is, ſo it may be juſtly ſaid alſo, of the viſion of God, it is more obvious to ſay how God is not ſeene, than how he is; Let us (if you pleaſe) begin with the negative, we may not therefore think to ſee God by any fancied repreſentation; hee

will admit of no image of himſelfe; no not in thought; All poſſibly conceiveable Ideas, and ſimilitudes, as they are infinitely too low, ſo they are cleane contrary to his ſpirituall nature, and his expreſſe charge; and the very entertainment of any of them is no other than a mentall idolatry. In the very holy of holyes, where he would moſt manifeſt his preſence, there was nothing to be ſeene but a cloud of ſmoake,Nil preter nubes. Iuv. as the Poet ſcoffingly; and as that great King profeſſed to ſee there;Alex. Mag. to teach his people that he would not be conceived any way, but in an abſolute immunity from all formes.
               
                  Secondly, we may not hope to ſee God by the working of our improved reaſon; for as intelligible things are above the apprehenſion of ſenſe, ſo divine matters are no leſſe above the capacity of underſtanding. Iuſtly is Durand exploded here, who held that a created underſtanding was of it ſelfe, ſufficient for the viſion of God, without ſupernaturall aid; for what ever our ſoule underſtands here, it doth it by the way of thoſe phantaſmes which are repreſented unto it; by which it is not poſſible there ſhould be any comprehenſion of this infinite eſſence: every power works within the compaſſe

of his owne ſphere; even from the loweſt of ſenſe, to the higheſt of faith: If the eye ſhould encroach upon the eare, in affecting to diſcerne the delicate ayre of pleaſant ſounds; and the eare ſhould uſurp upon the eye, in profeſſing to judge of a curious picture, or pleaſant proſpect; it were an abſurd ambition of both. It is all one for a beaſt to take upon him to judge of matter of diſcourſe; and for a Philoſopher to determine of matters of faith: Reaſon was not given to man for nought, even that can impart unto us ſomething concerning God, but not enough. I remember

                  Gerſon,
                  Io. Gerſ: de diſtinctione verarum viſionum à falſis. a great Maſter of Contemplation, profeſſes that he knew one, (which is, in Saint Pauls phraſe, himſelfe) who after many temptations of doubt, concerning a maine article of faith, was ſuddenly brought into ſo cleere a light of truth, and certitude; that there remained no reliques at all of dubitation; nothing but confidence, and ſerenity, which (ſaith hee) was wrought by an hearty humiliation, and captivation of the underſtanding to the obedience of faith; neither could any reaſon bee given of that quiet, and firme peace in beleeving, but his owne feeling

and experience: And ſurely, ſo it is in this great buſineſſe of ſeeing God; the leſſe wee ſearch, and the more wee beleeve, the cleerer viſion do we attain of him that is inviſible.
               Neither, thirdly, may wee hope here to aſpire to a perfect ſight, or a full comprehenſion of this bleſſed object; the beſt of all earthly eyes doth but look through a ſcarfe at this glorious Sight, and complaines of it's owne weakneſſe and obſcurity; and what hope can we have to compaſſe this infinite proſpect? The cleereſt eye cannot, at once, ſee any round body, if it be but of a ſmall bullet, or ring; And

when we ſay, wee ſee a man, we meane, that we ſee but his outſide; for ſurely, his heart, or lungs, or braine, are out of our ſight; much leſſe can we ſee his ſoule, by which he is: What ſpeak I of the poore narrow conceit of us mortals? I need not feare to ſay, that the glorified Saints and glorious Angels of Heaven, being but of a finite (though ſpirituall) nature, hold it no diſparagement to diſclaime the capacity of this infinite object; much leſſe may we think to draine this Ocean with our egge ſhell.
               Laſtly, we may not make account here to ſee the face of God in his divine eſſence, or

in the height of the reſplendence of his glory: This, even Moſes himſelfe did not; he deſired it indeed, but it might not be yeelded, (Exodus 33) and God tels him, this was no object for mortall eyes; A man muſt die to ſee it, as Auſten well. Indeed it is ſaid, Moſes ſpake to God, face to face; the word in the originall is (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) faces to faces:) but ye never read that he ſaw God face to face; he ſtill conferred with that Oracle which was ever inviſible. It is a poore conceit of Cornelius à Lapide, that Moſes longed ſo much to ſee the face of God in ſome aſſumed forme; for then that

face ſhould not have been his: And if God ſhould have been pleaſed to aſſume ſuch a forme, it had beene no leſſe eaſie for him, to have made the face aſpectable, as the back; In this ſenſe,Gen 32.30 old Jacob calls his Altar Penu-el, the face of God, and profeſſes to have ſeene God, face to face; his face ſaw that face which God had for the preſent aſſumed, without a preſent death: Doubtleſſe Moſes, having ſeene divers vayles of Gods preſence, (that is, ſenſible teſtimonies of his being there) deſires now to ſee that glorious Majeſty of God open-faced, without thoſe maskes of outward repreſentation,

(ſo hee interprets himſelfe whiles he expreſſes 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   by 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   verſ. 19.Thy face, by thy glory. Exo. 33.18) the deſire was zealouſly ambitious; too high, even for him, that had beene twice bleſſed with forty dayes cōference with the God whom he longed to ſee; much leſſe may we think of aſpiring to this Sight, who muſt know our diſtance, even from the foot of the Mount. It is abundantly enough, for us, if out of ſome ſmall loop hole of the rock, we may be allowed, in his paſſage, to ſee ſome after-glimpſes of that incomprehenſible Majeſty; to ſee him, both as we can be capable, and as he will be viſible; that is, as he

hath revealed himſelfe to us in his word, in his works, in his wonderfull attributes. In his word as a moſt glorious ſpirituall ſubſtance, in three equally glorious ſubſiſtences. In his works, as the moſt mighty Creator, and munificent Preſerver, as the moſt mercifull Redeemer of the world, as the moſt gracious Comforter, and Sanctifier of the world of his Elect. In his attributes, as the God of ſpirits, whoſe infinite power, wiſedome, mercy, juſtice, truth, goodneſſe is eſſentiall; ſo as he is all theſe abſtractedly, uncompoundedly, really, infinitely. Shortly therefore, we may not look here to

ſee him by the eye of fancy, or by the eye of reaſon, or in a full view, or in the height of his glory.
               Let us then in the next place ſee how we may and muſt ſee him.
            
            
               SECT. IIII.
               WOuld we therefore ſee him that is inviſible? In the firſt place we muſt have our eyes cleered from the naturall indiſpoſition, to which they are ſubject; we have all, in nature, many both inward, and ambient hinderances of this ſight; there is a kind of earthlineſſe in the beſt eye;

whereby it is gouled up, that it cannot ſo much as open it ſelfe, to ſee ſpirituall things; theſe are our carnall affections: There is a dimneſſe and duskineſſe in the body of the eye, when it is opened; which is our naturall ignorance of heavenly things: There is, beſides theſe, a filme, which is apt to grow over our eye, of naturall infidelity; which makes it incapable of this divine viſion; and after all theſe, (when it is at the cleareſt) the moats and duſt of worldly thoughts, are apt to trouble our ſight: Laſtly, every known ſinne, wherein a man willingly continues, is a beame in the

eye, that bars all ſight of God:
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Wiſd. 1.4. Wickedneſſe blinds the underſtanding. 
                  Jn malevolam animam, &amp;c. Wiſdome enters not into an ill-doing ſoule, and Malitia occaecat intellectum, as the wiſe man of old; There muſt bee a removall and remedy of all theſe, ere we can attaine to a comfortable viſion of the Inviſible. The goule of our eyes muſt bee waſht off; and if we cannot by our utmoſt endeavours, lift up our eye-lids, as we ought, we muſt ſue to him that can do it, (Aperioculos:) Open thou mine eyes that I may ſee the wonderfull things of thy Law. The dimneſſe and duskineſſe of our eyes muſt be cleared, by that eye-ſalve of the Spirit.

(Revel. 3.) The filme of our infidelity muſt be ſcoured off by the clenſing waters of Siloam, the fountaine of divine truth, welling out of the holy Scriptures; The moates and duſt of worldly cares muſt be wipt out, by a contemptuous, and holy reſolution; The beame of ſinne, laſtly, muſt be pulled out by a ſerious repentance. So then, if there be any of us that makes account to ſee God, whiles he is taken up with ſenſuall affections, whiles he is blinded with his naturall ignorance, and infidelity, whiles he is ſeized upon by worldly cares, and diſtractions, whiles he harbours

any knowne ſinne in his boſome, he doth but deceive his own ſoule; away with all theſe impediments, that wee may be capable of the viſion of God.
               In the ſecond place, wee muſt ſet this bleſſed object before our eyes; reſolving of the certainty of his preſence, with us; Or, rather, we muſt ſet our ſelves before him, who is ever unremovably before us, with us, in us; acknowledging him with no leſſe aſſurance of our faith, than we acknowledge the preſence of our owne bodies, by the aſſurance of ſenſe: For, how ſhall we ſuppoſe wee can ſee him that is abſent from

us? No man will ſay, he ſees the Sun, when it is out of our Hemiſphere: That infinite God therefore, who cannot but be every where, muſt bee acknowledged to be ever, in a glorious manner, preſent with us; manifeſting his preſence moſt eminently, in the high heavens, and yet filling both heaven and earth with the Majeſty of his glory: In him it is that we live, and move, and have our being: he comprehends the whole world, himſelfe being only incomprehenſible; ſecluded from no place, included in no place; neerer to us than our owne ſoules: when we die, we part from them;

from him we cannot part; with whom remoteneſſe of place can make no difference, time no change: when the heart is thus throughly aſſured, it is in a faire way to ſee the Inviſible; for now, after all the former impediments, the hinderance of diſtance is taken away; and nothing remaineth, but that the eye bee ſo affected, and imployed hereabouts, as it ought.
            
            
               SECT. V.
               TO which purpoſe, in the third place, there muſt be an exaltation, and a fortification of our ſight; An exaltation

raſing it above our wonted pitch, for our heart is ſo inured, and confined to bodily objects, that, except it bee ſomewhat raiſed above it ſelfe, it is not capable of ſpirituall things. A fortification of our ſight, ſo raiſed; for our viſive beames are (at our beſt) ſo weak, that they are not able to look upon a ſight ſo ſpiritually glorious; alas, wee cannot ſo much as look upon the Sunnebeames, but we are dazeled, and blinded, with that, which gives us opportunity of ſight: how ſhall wee be able to behold the infinite reſplendence of him that made it? St. Stephen was a true Eagle; that bleſſed

protomartyrs cleared, exalted, fortified ſight pierced the heavens, and ſaw Jeſus ſtanding at the right hand of God▪ Whence was this vigor, and perſpicacity? Hee was full of the holy Ghoſt, that Spirit of God, that was within him, gave both clearneſſe, and ſtrength (in ſuch miraculous manner) to the eyes of him, who ſhould ſtrait-way ſee, as hee was ſeene; who ſhould inſtantly by the eye of his glorified ſoule, no leſſe ſee the incomprehenſible Majeſty of God the Father, than now by his bodily eye, he ſaw the glorified body of the Son of God: It muſt bee the only work of

the ſame Spirit of God within us, that muſt enable us, both to the faculty, and exerciſe of ſeeing the Inviſible; for the performance whereof, there muſt be, in the fourth place, a trajection of the viſuall beames of the ſoule, thorow all earthly occurrences, terminating them only in God; as now, we look thorow the aire, at any object, but our ſight paſſes thorow it, and reſts not in it: whiles we are here, we cannot but ſee the world; even the holieſt eye cannot look off it; but it is to us, as the vaſt aire is betwixt us and the Starry heaven, only for paſſage; all is tranſlucid, till the ſight arrive

there; there it meetes with that ſolid object of perfect contentment, and happineſſe, wherewith it is throughly bounded. When it hath therefore attained thither, there muſt bee, in the fifth place, a certaine divine irradiation of the mind, which is now filled, and taken up with a lightſome apprehenſion of an infinite Majeſty, of a glory incomprehenſible, and boundleſſe; attended and adored by millions of heavenly Angels, and glorified Spirits; whereto way muſt be made by the conceit of a tranſcendent light; wherein God dwelleth; as far above this outward light which we ſee, as that is above darkneſſe:

For though we may not in our thoughts liken God to any created brightneſſe, (bee it never ſo glorious;) yet nothing forbids us to think of the place of his eternall habitation, as infinitely reſplendent, above the compariſon of thoſe beames which any creature can caſt forth. He is clothed (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) with light as with a garment. Lo, when wee cannot ſee a mans ſoule, yet we may ſee his body; and when we cannot ſee the body, yet wee may ſee the clothes: Even ſo, though wee may not think to ſee the eſſence of God, yet we may ſee, and conceive of this his reſplendent garment

of light. Farre be it therefore from us, when we would look up to a Deity, to have our eyeſight terminated in a gloomy opacity, and ſad darkſomneſſe, which hath no affinity with any appendance of that divine Majeſty, who hath thought good to deſcribe it ſelfe by light: Let our hearts adore ſuch an infinite ſpirit, as that the light wherein he dwels, is inacceſſible, the light which he hath, and is, is inconceiveable, and rather reſt themſelves in an humble and devout adoration of what they cannot know, than weary themſelves with a curious ſearch of what they cannot comprehend. A

ſimple and meek kind of aſtoniſhment, and admiration, beſeemes us here better, than a bold and buſie diſquiſition. But, if this outward light (which of all viſible creatures comes neereſt the nature of a ſpirit) ſhall ſeeme too materiall, to expreſſe the glory of that bleſſed habitation, of the Higheſt: Let the mind labour to apprehend an intellectuall light, which may be ſo to our underſtanding, as this bodily light is to our ſenſe, purely ſpirituall, and tranſcendently glorious; and let it deſire to wonder at that which it can never conceive; How ſhould this light be inacceſſible, if it were

ſuch as our either ſenſe, or reaſon could attaine unto?
            
            
               SECT. VI.
               WHen we have attained to this comfortable and heavenly illumination, there muſt be, in the ſixt place, a fixing of the eye upon this beatificall object, ſo, as it may be free from diſtraction, and wandring. Certainly there is nothing more apt to be miſcarried, than the eye; every new ſight winnes it away from that which laſt allured it. It is not hard, or unuſuall to have ſome ſudden ſhort glympſes of this happy viſion; which yet

the next toy fetches off, and makes us to forget: like as the laſt wave waſheth off the impreſſion of the former: what are we the better for this, than that patient, who having the filme too early raiſed from his eye, ſees the light for the preſent, but ſhall never ſee any more. Would wee ſee God to purpoſe? when we have once ſet eye upon him, we may not ſuffer our ſelves, by any means to loſe the ſight of him againe; but muſt follow it ſtill with a conſtant and eager intention: Like as the Diſciples of Chriſt, when they had fixed their eyes upon their aſcending Saviour, could not be taken off, with

the preſence of Angels; but ſent their eye-beames after him into heaven, ſo earneſtly, that the reproofe of thoſe glorious ſpirits could hardly pull them off. You are now ready to tell me, this is a fit task for us, when we are in our heaven; and to plead the difficulty of ſuch our ſettlement, in this region of change; where our eyes cannot but bee forced aſide, with the neceſſity of our worldly occaſions; and to queſtion the poſſibility of viewing two objects at once; God, and the world; not conſidering, that herein lyes the improvement of the Chriſtians skill, in theſe divine Opticks:

The carnall eye looks through God, at the world; The ſpirituall eye lookes through the world, at God; the one of thoſe he ſeeth mediately, the other terminatively; neither is it in nature hard to conceive, how we may ſee two ſuch objects, as whereof one is in the way to the other, as thorow a proſpective glaſſe, we can ſee a remote mark; or thorow a thin cloud wee can ſee heaven. Thoſe glorious Angels of heaven are never without the viſion of God, yet being miniſtring ſpirits for the good of his Elect, here below, they muſt needs take notice of theſe earthly occurrents: the variety

of theſe ſublunary objects cannot divert their thoughts from their Maker: Although alſo (to ſpeak diſtinctly) the eye thus imployed is not the ſame: nothing hinders but that whiles the bodily ſees a body, the ſpirituall eye may ſee a ſpirit: As when a load-ſtone is preſented to my view, the eye of my ſenſe ſees the body, and faſhion of the ſtone, my eye of reaſon ſees the hidden vertue which is in it; both theſe kinds of eyes may be thus fixed upon their ſeverall objects without any interſection of the viſuall lines of each other. But, that no man may think God hath ſo little reſpect to our infirmities

as to impoſe upon us impoſſible tasks, we muſt know, that ſince the ſoule of man in this ſtate of fraile mortality, is not capable of a perpetuall act of ſuch an intuition of God, here is neceſſary uſe of a juſt diſtinction: As the Schoole therefore is wont to diſtinguiſh of intentions, ſo muſt we here of the apprehenſion of God, which is either actuall, or habituall, or virtuall. Actuall, when our cogitations are taken up, and directly imployed in the meet conſideration of the bleſſed Deity, and the things thereto appertaining: Habituall, when we have a ſettled kind of holy diſpoſition,

and aptitude inclining us ever to theſe divine thoughts, ready ſtill to bring them forth into act, upon every leaſt motion: Virtuall, betwixt both theſe, being neither ſo quick and agile, as the actuall; nor yet ſo dull and flagging as the habituall, (which may be incident to a man whether ſleeping, or otherwiſe buſied) when by the power of an heavenly diſpoſition, wrought in the mind, we are ſo affected, as that divine thoughts are become the conſtant (though inſenſible) gueſts of the ſoule; whiles the vertue of that originall illumination ſticks ſtill by us, and is, in a ſort, derived

into all our ſubſequent cogitations; leaving in them perpetuall remainders of the holy effects of the deeply-wrought, and well grounded apprehenſion of God: As in a pilgrim towards the holy Land, there are not alwaies actual thoughts concerning his way, or end; yet there is ſtill, an habituall reſolution, to begin and compaſſe that journey; and a ſecret power of his continued will, to put forward his ſteps to that purpoſe; there being a certaine impreſſion remaining in the motive faculty, which ſtill inſenſibly ſtirres him towards the place deſired: Neither is it unuſuall, (even in nature) to

ſee many effects continuing, when the motion of the cauſe, by which they were wrought, ceaſeth; As when ſome deep Bell is rung to the height, the noyſe continues ſome time in the ayre, after the clapper is ſilent: Or when a ſtone is caſt into the water, the circles that are cauſed by it are enlarged, and multiplyed, after the ſtone lyes ſtill in the bottome.
               How ever therefore we cannot hope in this life (through our manifold weakneſſes, and diſtractions) to attaine unto the ſteddy continuance of the actuall view of him that is inviſible, yet, to the habituall, and virtuall power of apprehending

him, wee may, (through the goodneſſe of him, whom we ſtrive to ſee) happily aſpire.
               Neither may we be wanting to our ſelves in taking all occaſions of renewing theſe our actuall viſions of God; both ſet, and caſuall: there is nothing that wee can ſee, which doth not put us in mind of God; what creature is there, wherin we do not eſpy ſome footſteps of a Deity? every herb, flower, leafe, in our garden; every Bird, and Fly in the aire; every Ant and Worme in the ground; every Spider in our window, ſpeakes the omnipotence, and infinite wiſedome

of their Creator: None of theſe may paſſe us without ſome fruitfull monition of acknowledging a divine hand. But beſides theſe, it will be requiſite for us, every morning to ſeaſon our thoughts with a ſerious renovation of our awfull apprehenſions of God; and not to take off our hand, till wee have wrought our hearts to ſome good competency of right, and holy conceits of that glorious Majeſty; the efficacy whereof may dilate it ſelfe to the whole following day; which may be often revived by our frequent ejaculations: But above all other, when wee have to do with

God, in the ſet immediate exerciſes of his ſervices, and our heavenly devotions, we muſt endeavour (to our utmoſt) to ſharpen our eyes, to a ſpirituall perſpicacity; ſtriving to ſee him, whom we ſpeak unto, and who ſpeaks unto us, as he hath pleaſed to reveale himſelfe. But, over and beſide all theſe, even when we have no provocations from any particular occaſion, it muſt be our continual care, to labour with our God, that it would pleaſe him to work us to ſuch an holy, and heavenly diſpoſition, as that what ever our imployments may be, we may never want the comfort of a virtuall and

habituall enjoying the ſight of God; ſo as the power and efficacy of our firſt, well-taken apprehenſion may runne on, thorow all the following actions, and events both of our life, and death.
            
            
               SECT. VII.
               VPon this conſtant fixedneſſe of our thoughts, on God, there cannot but follow (in the ſeventh place) a marvellous delight, and complacency of the ſoule, in ſo bleſſed an object; neither is it eaſie to determine whether of theſe doe more juſtly challenge a precedency in the heart, whether

the eye be ſo fixed, becauſe it is well pleaſed with the ſight; or whether it be ſo pleaſed and raviſhed, with that happy ſight, becauſe it is ſo fixed: whatſoever theſe two are in the order of nature, I am ſure in time, they are inſeparable, neither is it poſſible for any man to ſee God as intereſſed in him, and not to love him, and take pleaſure in him: As a ſtranger, as an enemy, or avenger, even divels and reprobate ſoules behold him, to their regret, and torment; if I may not ſay, they rather ſee his anger, and judgement, than himſelfe; but never eye can ſee him as his God, and not be taken

with infinite delight: for that abſolute goodneſſe (out of which no man can contemplate God) can be no other, than infinitely amiable. And if in the ſeeing of God, we be (as the Schoole hath taught us to ſpeak) unitively carried into him, how can we chooſe but in this act, bee affected with joy unſpeakable and glorious? In thy preſence, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, is the fulneſſe of joy: and at thy right hand, are pleaſures for evermore. In ſumme therefore; if when our eyes being freed from all naturall indiſpoſitions, and both inward, and outward impediments; wee have ſo this bleſſed object preſented

before us, as that, there is an exaltation and fortification of our ſight; and thereupon a trajection of the viſuall beames thorow all earthly occurrents, and a divine irradiation of the underſtanding, and a ſtedfaſt fixing of the eye upon this happy object, without wandring and diſtraction; not without a wonderfull delight, and joy in the God of all comfort, whom we apprehend; we do now effectually borrow Moſes his eyes, and, as he did, ſee the Inviſible.
            
            
               
               SECT. VIII.
               BVt as all good things are difficult, and all difficulties full of diſcouragement, unleſſe they be matched with a countervaileable benefit, (in which caſes they doe rather whet, than turne the edge of our deſires) let us ſee what conſiderations of profit, ariſing from this noble act, may ſtirre up our languiſhing hearts to the endeavour, and performance thereof: There are actions, which carrying nothing but danger and trouble in the mouth of them, had need to be drawne on with the promiſe

of an externall reward; there are thoſe, which carry in them their owne recompence; ſuch is this wee have in hand: What can there bee out of it ſelfe, ſo good as it? When we take paines to put our ſelves into ſome Theater, or Court, or ſome pompous triumph, we have no other end but to ſee; and yet how poore, and unſatisfying is that ſpectacle; and ſuch, as wherein our frivolous curioſity ſhuts up in emptineſſe, and diſcontentment? how juſtly then are we ambitious of this proſpect, wherein, to but ſee, is to be bleſſed. It is no newes to ſee wantons tranſported from themſelves,

with the ſight of a beautifull face, though ſuch, perhaps, as wherein they can never hope to have any intereſt; and ſome curious eyes no leſſe taken with an exquiſite picture, which yet ſhall never be theirs: how can we be other than raviſhed with an heavenly delight, and pleaſure, in ſo ſeeing the infinite beauty of the God of Spirits, as that our ſight cannot be ſevered from fruition? the act it ſelfe is an abundant remuneration, yet doth it not want many ſweet, and beneficiall conſequences, which do juſtly quicken our deſires to attaine unto the practiſe of it. Whereof it is not the meaneſt,

that who-ever hath happily aſpired thereunto, cannot bee carryed away with earthly vanities; what poore things are theſe, in compariſon of thoſe inviſible glories? Alas, what was the pleaſure and riches of the Court of Egypt, in the eyes of Moſes, when he had once ſeene his God? It is a true word,Guſtato ſpiritu deſipit omnis caro. Gerſ. de. 4. domibus. that of the Chancellor of Paris, when a man hath taſted once of the ſpirit, all fleſh is ſavourleſſe: Surely, when once the choſen veſſell had beene rapt into the third heaven, and ſeene thoſe unutterable magnificencies of the divine Majeſty, who can wonder, if he looked, ever after,

with ſcorne, and pitty upon all the glittering poverty of this inferiour world? Goe then ye poorely-great ones of the world, and admire the piles of your treaſures, the ſtatelineſſe of your ſtructures, the ſound of your titles, the extent of your territoryes; but know, that hee who hath ſeene the leaſt glympſe of the Inviſible, knowes how to commiſerate your felicity, and wonders what yee can ſee in all theſe, worth your admiration, and purſuit: What joy and triumph was among the Iewes when they ſaw the foundation of the ſecond Temple laid? yet thoſe ancient Prieſts and

Levites, whoſe eyes had ſeene the glory of the former Temple, wept, and cryed as loud, as the reſt ſhouted: Thoſe that know no better, may rejoyce and exult in theſe worldly contentments; but thoſe, who have had but a blink of the beauty of heaven, can look upon them no otherwiſe, than with an overly contemptuouſneſſe. I wonder not if good old Simeon were content to have his eyes clozed for ever, when he had once ſeene the Sonne of God: what ever he ſhould ſee afterwards, would but abaſe thoſe eyes, that had beene bleſſed with the face of his Saviour. It was no ill conceit

of the wiſe Oratour, that he who had once knowne and conſidered the magnitude of the world, could never after admire any thing; Surely we may more juſtly ſay, that hee who hath duly taken into his thoughts the conſideration of the infinite power, wiſdome, goodneſſe, of the great God of the world, cannot think the world it ſelfe, worthy of his wonder. As ſome great Peere therefore, that hath beene uſed to ſtately ſhowes, and courtly magnificence, doth not vouchſafe ſo much as to caſt his eye towards the meane worthleſſe gewgawes of a Pedlars Stall, (which yet ſilly children behold

with great pleaſure and admiration: ſo the ſoule that hath beene inured to the ſight of the divine Majeſty, ſcornes to ſuffer it ſelfe to be tranſported with the traſh and toyes of this vaine and tranſitory world.
            
            
               SECT. IX.
               NO whit inferiour to this benefit, is the ſecond; that this ſight of the Inviſible is a notable and prevalent meanes to reſtraine us from ſinning, for how dares he ſinne, that ſees God ever before him? whom he knowes of ſo pure eyes, that he deteſts the leaſt

motion to evill; of ſo almighty power, as to revenge it everlaſtingly. It was a poore thought of him (who yet could know no better) that hee who would diſſwade himſelfe from a ſecret wickedneſſe, ſhould ſuppoſe a grave Cato, or ſome other ſuch auſtere frowning Cenſor, to be by him, looking upon his actions; as if the ſhame or feare of ſuch a witneſſe were a ſufficient coercion from evill: he that hath no eyes to ſee a God, may ſcarre himſelfe with the imagined ſight of a man, ſomewhat better than himſelfe; but he who hath the grace to ſee the Inviſible, finds a ſtronger reſtraint

in that preſence, than if hee were looked on by millions of Witneſſes, Iudges, Executioners: Yet as this ſight is mutuall, (ours of God, and Gods of us,) the good heart finds a more powerfull reſtriction in his ſeeing of God, than in Gods ſeeing of him: if there be more feare in this, there is more love in the other; for, ſince this holy viſion of God is ever joyned with ſome warmth of good affection to that prime, and infinite goodneſſe, the very apprehenſion of that unſpeakable lovelineſſe, which is in him, more effectually curbeth all evill deſires, in us, than the expectation

of any danger, that can threaten us: How can I do this great evill, and ſinne againſt God,
                  Gen. 39 9. ſaith good Ioſeph: the ſinne affrights him more than the ſuffering, and the offence of a God, more than his owne danger.
               The Spirit of God hath thought fit to ſpecifie the third benefit, upon occaſion of the mention of Moſes his viſion of God; he endured, as ſeeing him who is inviſible: As this ſight therefore hath power to withhold us from doing evill; ſo alſo to uphold us in the ſuffering of evill; What but cheerfulneſſe, and eaſe, could holy Stephen find in the ſtones of

his enraged murtherers, when, through that haile ſtorme he could ſee his Ieſus, ſtanding at the right hand of God, ready to revenge, and crowne him? What a pleaſing walk did the three children find in Nebuchadnezzars Fornace, whiles the Sonne of God made up the fourth? What Bath was ſo ſuppling, and delightfull, as the rack of Theodorus the Martyr, whiles Gods Angel wip't, and refreſhed his diſtended joynts? With what confidence and reſolution, did the Father of the faithfull break thorow all troubles, and tentations, when he heard God ſay, Feare not,
                  Gen. 15.1. Abraham, I am thy ſheild,

and thy exceeding great reward. Certainly, all feare and diſcouragement ariſes from a conceit of our owne weakneſſe, and an adverſaries power, and advantage; take away theſe two, and the mind of man remaines undanted: and both theſe vaniſh at the ſight of the Inviſible; For, what weakneſſe can we apprehend, when God is our ſtrength, or what adverſary can we feare, when the Almighty is with us? Good Ezekiah was never ſo much ſcarred with all the bravings of Rabſhakeh, as when he ſaid, Am I come up hither without the Lord? Had God taken part againſt his degenerated

people, what could the arme of fleſh have availed, for their defence? As contrarily, when hee ſtrikes in, what can the gates of hell do? Is it multitude that can give us courage? as Eliſha's ſervant ſaid; there are more with us than againſt us: It is ſtrength? behold, the weakneſſe of God is ſtronger than men; than divels: How juſtly do we contemne all viſible powers, when we ſee the Inviſible? when we ſee him, not empty handed, but ſtanding ready, with a crowne of glory,Revel. 2, 7. To him that overcomes it ſhall be given. to reward our conqueſt; Vincenti dabitur: Are we therfore perſecuted, for profeſſing the truth of the Goſpell, and

caſt into a dark, and deſolate dungeon, where no glimmering of light is allowed to look in upon us; where we are ſo farre from being ſuffered to ſee our friends, that we cannot ſee ſo much as the face of our Keeper? Lo even there, and thence, we may yet ſee the Inviſible, and (in ſpight of malice) in his light wee can ſee light. Do we lie groaning upon the painfull bed of our ſickneſſe, cloſing our curtaines about us to keep out the light, which now growes offenſive to our ſight; yea, doth death begin to ſeize upon our eyes, and to dim and thicken our ſight, ſo as now we cannot diſcerne

our deareſt friends, that ſtand ready to cloſe them for us; yet, even then may we moſt cleerly ſee the Inviſible; and that ſight is able to cheere us up, againſt all the pangs, and terrours of death, and to make us triumph even in dying.
            
            
               SECT. X.
               LAſtly, what other doth this viſion of God but enter us into our heaven? Bleſſed are the pure in heart, (ſaith our Saviour upon the Mount) for they ſhall ſee God; Lo, he that only can give bleſſedneſſe, hath promiſed it to the pure; and he that beſt knowes wherin

bleſſedneſſe conſiſts, tells us, it is in the ſeeing of God; The bleſſed Spirits above, both Angels and ſoules of the departed Saints, ſee him cleerly, without any vaile drawne over their glorified eyes; we, wretched Pilgrims here on earth, muſt ſee him as wee may; there is too much clay in our eyes, and too many, and to groſſe vapors of ignorance and infidelity betwixt us and him, for a full and perfect viſion: Yet even here, we ſee him truly, though not cleerly; and the ſtronger our faith is, the clearer is our ſight; and the clearer our ſight is, the greater is our meaſure of bleſſedneſſe:

Neither is it a meere preſence, or a bare ſimple viſion, which doth either inchoate, or perfect our happineſſe: we find there was a day, when the Sonnes of God came to preſent themſelves before the Lord,Iob 1.6. and Satan came alſo among them;Zach. 12.10 and the wickeds eyes ſhall ſee him whom they have peirced; we ſee ſo much of God, (in the way of our bliſſe) as we enjoy. I know not how the eye in theſe ſpirituall objects, (betwixt which and us there is a gracious relation) hath a certaine kind of applicatory faculty, which in theſe materiall things it wanteth: O taſte, and ſee (ſaith

the Pſalmiſt) how ſweet the Lord is; as if our ſight were more inwardly apprehenſive of heavenly pleaſures, than our moſt ſenſible guſtation: In theſe bodily objects, either there is no operation upon the ſenſe, or, to no purpoſe; The eye is never the warmer for ſeeing a fire a farre off, nor the colder for beholding yce: we are no whit the richer for ſeeing heapes of treaſure, nor the fairer for viewing anothers beauty; But ſuch a powerfull, and glorious influence there is of God into our ſpirituall ſenſes, that we cannot ſee him by the eye of our faith here, and not be the happier; we

cannot ſee him above by the eye of our ſeparated ſoules, and not be perfectly glorious; and the one of theſe doth neceſſarily make way for the other: for, what is grace here but glory begun? and what is glory above, but grace perfected? Whoſoever therfore here, hath pitcht the eye of his faith upon the Inviſible, doth but continue his proſpect, when he comes to heaven: the place is changed, the object is the ſame; the act more compleat: As then, we do ever look to have our eyes bleſſed with the perpetuall viſion of God, in the higheſt heavens; let us acquaint them before hand,

with the conſtant and continuall ſight of him, in this vale of mortality.
            
            
               SECT. XI.
               NO ſooner have our eyes beene thus lifted up above the hills, to the ſight of the Inviſible, than they muſt be inſtantly caſt downe, and turned inwards to ſee our owne wretchedneſſe; how weak and poore we are, how fraile, how vaine and momentany, how deſtitute of all good, how obnoxious to all ſinne, and miſery: Contrarieties make all things better diſcerned; And ſurely however it be cōmonly

ſeene, that the neerneſſe of the object, is an hindrance to the ſight, yet here, the more cloſely we behold our owne condition, the more cleerly we ſhall diſcerne, and the more fully ſhall we be convinced of this unpleaſing truth: It is not for us to look back (like the heires of ſome decayed houſe) at what we were; whoever was the better for a paſt happineſſe? Alas, what are we now? miſerable duſt and aſhes; earth at the beſt, at the worſt, hell; Our being is vanity, our ſubſtance corruption; our life is but a blaſt, our fleſh wormes-meat, our beginning impotent, above all creatures, (even

wormes can crawle forward, ſo ſoone as they are, ſo cannot we) our continuance ſhort, and troubleſome; our end grievous; who can aſſure himſelfe of one minute of time, of one dramme of contentment? But, woe is me, other creatures are fraile too, none but man is ſinfull; our ſoule is not more excellent, than this tainture of it, is odious, and deadly; our compoſition laies us open to mortality, but our ſinne expoſes us to the eternall wrath of God, and the iſſue of it, eternall damnation: The grave waits for us, as men; hell, as ſinners: Beaſts compare with us in our being;

in our ſinning, Devils inſult over us. And now, ſince the ſpring is foule, how can the ſtreames be cleare? Alas, what act of ours is free from this wofull pollution? who eats, or drinks, or ſleepes, or moves, or talks, or thinks, or heares, or prayes without it? Even hee that was bleſſed with the ſight of the third heaven, as tyred with this clogge, could ſay, O wretched man that J am, who ſhall deliver mee from this body of death? Bleſſed Apoſtle, if thou wert ſo ſenſible of thy in-dwelling corruptions, who knew'ſt nothing by thy ſelfe, how muſt our hearts needs rend with ſhame, and

ſorrow, who are guilty of ſo many thouſand tranſgreſſions, which our impotence can neither avoid, nor expiate? how juſtly do we feare God, ſince we have deſerved to be under ſo deep a condemnation.
            
         
         
            
            
            OF THE SIGHT and FEARE of the ALMIGHTY. The Second Book.
            
               SECT. I.
               
                  THus therefore when a man ſhall have ſtedfaſtly fixed his eyes upon the dread Majeſty of an ever-preſent God, and upon the deplored

wretchedneſſe of his own condition, hee ſhall bee in a meet capacity to receive this holy Feare, whereof we treat: Neither indeed is it poſſible for him to ſee that all-glorious preſence, and not preſently thereupon find himſelfe affected with a trembling kind of awfulneſſe. Neither can hee look upon his owne vileneſſe, without an humble and baſhfull dejection of ſoule; But when he ſhall ſee both theſe at once, and compare his owne ſhamefull eſtate, with the dreadfull, incomprehenſible Majeſty of the great God; his owne impotence, with that almighty power; his owne ſinfulneſſe,

with that infinite purity, and juſtice; his owne miſery with the glory of that immenſe mercy, how can he chooſe but be wholly poſſeſſed with a devout ſhivering, and religious aſtoniſhment. The heart then thus tempered with the high thoughts of a God, and the humble conceits of our ſelves, is fit for the impreſſion of this Feare, which is no other, than an awfull diſpoſition of the ſoule to God: wherein there is a double ſtamp, or ſignature; the one, is an inward adoration of the Majeſty ſeene and acknowledged; the other, a tender and filiall care of being ſecretly approved of God;

and of avoyding the diſpleaſure, and offence of that God whom we ſo adore. The firſt, is a continuall bowing the knees of our hearts to that great, and holy God; both inwardly bleſſing, and praiſing him in all his divine attributes; in his infinite power, wiſedome, juſtice, mercy, and truth; and humbly ſubmitting and reſigning our ſelves wholly to his divine pleaſure in all things; whether for his diſpoſing, or chaſtiſing.
            
            
               
               SECT. II.
               ALL true adoration begins from within; even the ſoule hath the ſame parts, and poſtures with the body: as therefore it hath eyes to ſee, ſo it hath a tongue to ſpeak unto, and a knee to bend unto the Majeſty of the Almighty: Shortly then; we ſhall inwardly adore the God of heaven, when our hearts are wrought to bee awfully affected to the acknowledgment, cheifly of his infinite Greatneſſe, and infinite Goodneſſe; And this ſhall be beſt done, by the conſideration of the effects of

both: Even in meaner matters, wee cannot attaine to the knowledge of things by their cauſes; but are glad to take up with this ſecondary information: how much more in the higheſt of all cauſes, in whom there is nothing but tranſcendency, and infiniteneſſe? We ſhall therefore moſt feelingly adore the infinite greatneſſe of God, upon repreſenting unto our ſelves, the wonderfull work of his creation, and his infinite goodneſſe, in the no leſſe wonderfull work of our redemption:Rom. 1.20. For (as the great Doctor of the Gentiles moſt divinely) the inviſible things of God from the creation of

the world are cleerly ſeene, being underſtood by the things that are made; even his eternall power, and Godhead. Even ſo, O God, if we cannot ſee thee, we cannot but ſee the world, that thou haſt made: and in that, wee ſee ſome glympſes of thee: When wee behold ſome goodly pile of building, or ſome admirable picture, or ſome rarely-artificiall engine, our firſt queſtion uſes to be, who made it? and we judge of, and admire the skill of the workman, by the excellent contrivance of the work; how can we do otherwiſe in this mighty and goodly frame of thy univerſe? Lord

what a world is this of thine, which wee ſee? What a vaſt, what a beautifull fabrick is this, above and about us? Lo thou, that madeſt ſuch an heaven, canſt thou be other than infinitely glorious? O the power and wiſdome of ſuch a Creator! Every Starre is a world alone, the leaſt of thoſe globes of light, are farre greater than this our whole inferiour world, of earth and waters (which we think ſcarce meaſurable,) and what a world of theſe lightſome worlds haſt thou marſhalled together in that one firmament? and yet what roome haſt thou left in that large contignation, for

more? ſo as the vacant ſpace betwixt one Starre, and another, is more in extent than that which is filled: In how exact a regularity do theſe celeſtiall bodies move, ever ſince their firſt ſetting forth, without all variation of the time or place of their riſing, or ſetting; without all change of their influences? In what point and minute Adams new created eyes ſaw them begin, and ſhut up their diurnall motions, we, his late poſterity, upon that ſame day and in the ſame Climate find them ſtill; How have they looked upon their ſpectators, in millions of changed generations, and are ſtill

where they were, looking ſtill for more? But, above the reſt, who can but be aſtoniſhed at that conſtant miracle of nature, the glorious Sunne, by whoſe beames, all the higher and lower world is illuminated; and by whoſe ſole benefit, we have uſe of our eyes? O God, what were the world without it, but a vaſt, and ſullen dungeon of confuſion, and horrour; and, with it, what a Theater of beauty and wonders? what a ſad ſeaſon is our midnight, by reaſon of his fartheſt abſence; and yet, even then, ſome glympſes of emanations, and remainders of that hidden light, diffuſe themſelves

thorow the aire, and forbid the darkneſſe to bee abſolute. Oh what an hell were utter darkneſſe; what a reviving and glorious ſpectacle it is, when the morning opens the curtaines of heaven, and ſhowes the riſing Majeſty of that great Ruler of the day, which too many eyes have ſeene with adoration; never any ſaw, without wonder, and benediction: And if thy creature be ſuch, what, oh, what art thou that haſt made it? As for that other faithfull witneſſe in heaven, what a cleare and laſting teſtimony doth it give to all beholders, of thine omnipotence? Alwayes, and

yet never changing? ſtill uniforme in her conſtant variations, ſtill regular in the multiplicity of her movings; and O God, what a traine doth that great Queene of Heaven (by thine appointment) draw after her? no leſſe than this vaſt element of waters, ſo many thouſand miles diſtant from her ſphere? She moves in heaven, the ſea followes her, in this inferiour orb, and meaſures his paces by hers: How deep, how ſpacious, how reſtleſly turbulent is that liquid body? and how tamed and confined by thine Almightineſſe? How juſtly didſt thou expoſtulate with thy people of old, by thy Prophet

                  Ieremy, Feare yee not mee,
                  Ier. 5.22. ſaith the Lord, will ye not tremble at my preſence, which have placed the ſand, for the bounds of the ſea, by a perpetuall decree, that it cannot paſſe it; and though the waves thereof toſſe themſelves, yet they cannot prevaile; though they roare, yet can they not paſſe over it? And what a ſtupendious work of omnipotence is it, that thou, O God, haſt hanged up this huge globe of water and earth, in the midſt of a yeelding aire, without any ſtay, or foundation, ſave thine owne eternall decree? How wonderfull art thou in thy mighty winds; which, whence they come, and whither

they go, thou only knoweſt; in thy dreadfull thunders, and lightnings; in thy threatning Comets, and other fiery exhalations? With what marvellous variety of creatures haſt thou peopled all theſe thy roomy elements; all of ſeverall kinds, faſhions, natures, diſpoſitions, uſes; and yet all their innumerable motions, actions, events, are predetermined and over-ruled by thine all-wiſe, and almighty providence! What man can but open his eyes, and ſee round about him theſe demonſtrations of thy divine power, and wiſedome, and not inwardly praiſe thee in thine excellent

greatneſſe? For my owne practiſe, I cannot find a better notion, wherby to work my heart to an inward adoration of God, than this; Thou that haſt made all this great world, and guideſt, and governeſt it, and filleſt and comprehendeſt it, being thy ſelfe infinite and incomprehenſible: And I am ſure there can be no higher repreſentation of the divine greatneſſe unto our ſelves. Although withall, we may find enough at home: for what man that lookes no further than himſelfe, and ſees the goodly frame of his body, erected and imployed for the harbour of a ſpirituall, and immortall

ſoule, can chooſe but ſay, I will praiſe thee, for I am fearefully, and wonderfully made.
            
            
               SECT. III.
               SVrely, could we forget all the reſt of the world, it is enough to fetch us upon our knees, and to ſtrike an holy awe into us, to think that in him we live, and move, and have our being: For, in theſe our particular obligations, there is a mixed ſenſe both of the greatneſſe, and goodneſſe of our God; which, as it manifeſtly ſhowes it ſelfe in the wondrous work of our excellent creation,

ſo moſt of all magnifies it ſelfe, in the exceedingly gratious work of our redemption: Great is thy mercy that thou mayſt be feared, ſaith the ſweet Singer of Iſrael; Lo, power doth not more command this holy feare, than mercy doth; though both here, meet together; for as there was infinite mercy mixed with power, in thus creating us; ſo alſo, there is a no leſſe mighty power mixed with infinite mercy, in our redemption: What heart can but awfully adore thy ſoveraigne mercy, O bleſſed God, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in ſending thine only, and coequall Sonne, the

Sonne of thy love, the Sonne of thine eternall eſſence, out of thy boſome, downe from the height of celeſtiall glory, into this vale of teares and death, to abaſe himſelfe, in the ſuſception of our nature, to clothe himſelfe with the ragges of our humanity, to indure temptation, ſhame, death, for us? O bleſſed Ieſu, the redeemer of mankind, what ſoule can be capable of a ſufficient adoration of thine inconceive able mercy, in thy meane and deſpicable incarnation, in thy miſerable, and toilſome life, in thy bloudy agony, in thine ignominious and tormenting paſſion, in thy wofull ſenſe

of thy fathers wrath in our ſtead, and laſtly, in thy bitter and painfull death? thou that kneweſt no ſinne, wert made ſinne for us, thou that art omnipotent, would'ſt die; and by thy death, haſt victoriouſly triumphed over death, and hell. It is enough, O Saviour, it is more than enough, to raviſh our hearts with love, and to bruiſe them with a loving feare. O bleſſed Spirit, the God of comfort, who but thou only can make our ſoules ſenſible of thy unſpeakable mercy, in applying to us the wonderfull benefit of this our deare redemption, in the great work of our inchoate regeneration,

in the mortifying of our evill and corrupt affections, in raiſing us to the life of grace, and preparing us for the life of glory? O God, if mercy be proper to attract feare, how muſt our hearts, in all theſe reſpects, needs be filled with all awfull regard unto thy divine bounty?Pſal. 31.20. Oh how great is the goodneſſe that thou haſt laid up for thoſe that feare thee, even before the ſonnes of men!
            
            
               SECT. IV.
               NOw we may not think this inward adoration of the greatneſſe, &amp; goodnes of God to be one ſimple act, but that,

which is ſweetly compounded of the improvement of many holy affections: for there cannot but be love mixed with this feare;Eccl. 25.5. 
                  The feare of the Lord is the beginning of love; and this feare muſt be mixed with joy:Pſal. 2.11. 
                  Rejoyce in him with trembling: and this feare and joy, is ſtill mixed with hope:Pro. 
                        •
                     1.2
                        •
                     . 
                  For in the feare of the Lord is ſtrong confidence; and the eye of the Lord is upon them that feare him,
                  Pſal. 33.1
                        •
                     . 
                  upon them that hope in his mercy: As therefore, we are wont to ſay that our bodies are not, neither can bee nouriſhed with any ſimple ingredient; ſo may we truly ſay of our ſoules, that they neither receive any comfort,

or eſtabliſhment, nor execute any powers of theirs, by any ſole ſingle affection; but require a gracious mixture for both. As that father ſaid of obedience, we may truly ſay of grace, that it is all copulative. Neither may wee think, that one only impreſſion of this holy feare, and inward adoration will ſerve the turne, to ſeaſon all our following diſpoſition, and carriage; but, there muſt be a virtuall continuation thereof, in all the progreſſe of our lives; Our Schooles do here ſeaſonably diſtinguiſh of perpetuity, of, whether the ſecond act, when all our ſeverall motions and

actions are ſo held on, as that there is no ceſſation, or intermiſſion of their performance: (which wee cannot here expect) Or, of the firſt act, when there is an habit of this inward adoration, ſettled upon the heart ſo conſtantly, that it is never put off, by what ever occurrences; ſo as whatſoever we do, whatſoever we indeavour, hath a ſecret relation hereunto. And this ſecond way; we muſt attaine unto, if ever we will aſpire to any comfort in the fruition of Gods preſence here, upon earth, and our meet diſpoſition towards him. I have often thought of that deep, and ſerious queſtion

of the late judicious, and honourable,Mr. Samuel Burton Archdeacon of Gloceſter.
                   Sir Fulke Grevil, Lord Brook, (a man worthy of a fairer death, and everlaſting memory) moved to a learned kinſman of mine, (much intereſſed in that Noble man) who when he was diſcourſing of an incident matter, very conſiderable, was taken off with this quick interrogation, of that wiſe and noble perſon; What is that to the Infinite? as ſecretly implying, that all our thoughts and diſcourſe muſt be reduced thither; and that they faile of their ends, if they be any other where terminated▪ It was a word well becomming the profound judgement,

and quinteſſentiall notions of that rare, memorable Peere. And certainly ſo it is, if the cogitations and affections of our hearts be not directed to the glory of that infinite God, both they are loſt, and we in them.
            
            
               SECT. V.
               REligious adoration begins in the heart, but reſts not there; diffuſing it ſelfe through the whole man, and commanding all the powers of the ſoule, and all the parts of the body to comply in a reverent devotion: ſo that, as we feare the Lord whom wee ſerve,

ſo wee ſerve the Lord with feare.
               Where the heart ſtoopes, it cannot be, but the knees muſt bend, the eyes and hands muſt be lift up; and the whole body will ſtrive to teſtifie the inward veneration; as upon all occaſions, ſo eſpecially, when wee have to deale with the ſacred affaires of God, and offer to preſent our ſelves to any of his immediate ſervices: Our feare cannot bee ſmothered in our boſomes; Every thing that pert
                     •
                  ines to that infinite Majeſty muſt carry from us due teſtifications of our awe; his Name, his Word, his Services, his Houſe, his Meſſengers: I

cannot allow the ſuperſtitious niceties of the Iewes, in the matters of God; yet I find in their practiſe, many things worthily imitable; ſuch as favour of the feare of their father Iſaac, and ſuch as juſtly ſhame our prophane careleſneſſe.
               There is no wiſe man but muſt needs miſlike their curious ſcruples, concerning that ineffable name, the letters and ſyllables wherof, they held in ſuch dreadfull reſpect, that they deemed it worthy of death, for any but ſacred lips, and that, but in ſet times and places, to expreſſe it; as if the mention of it pierced the ſide of God, together with their

owne heart;Schichard de jure regio Hebr. And, if the name of God were written upon their fleſh, that part might not bee touched either with water, or oyntment. But well may wee learne this point of wit, and grace from this firſt, (and, then, the only) people of God; not raſhly, ſleightly, regardleſly, to take the awfull name of God into our mouths, but to heare and ſpeak it (when occaſion is given) with all holineſſe, and due veneration.
               There are thoſe that ſtumble at their adoration at the bleſſed name of Ieſus, preſcribed and practiſed by our Church; as unjuſtly conceiving, that wee put a ſuperſtitious holineſſe in

the very ſound, and ſyllabicall enunciation of the word; wheras, it is the perſon of that bleſſed Saviour, to whom, upon this occaſion, our knees are bended: A geſture ſo far out of the juſt reach of blame, that if it ſeemed good to the wiſedome of the Church, to allot this reverent reſpect to all▪ whatſoever the names, wherby the Majeſty of God, in the whole ſacred Trinity, is ſignified, and expreſſed to men, it were moſt meet to be accordingly exhibited unto them: And now, ſince it hath (without inhibition of the like regard to the reſt) pitched upon that name, which intimating and

compriſing in it the whole gratious work, and immediate author of our deare redemption, hath beene expoſed to the reproach and oppoſition of the gain-ſaying world; We cannot (if we be not wanting to our filiall obedience) detrect our obſervance of ſo antient, and pious an inſtitution. Never any contempt was dared to bee caſt upon the glorious name of the Almighty, and abſolute Deity, only the ſtate of exinanition, ſubjected the Sonne of God to the ſcorne, and under-valuation of the world; Iuſtly therefore hath our holy and gracious Mother thought fit, and ordained, upon

that perſon and name, which ſeemed leſſe honourable, and lay more open to affront, to beſtow the more abundant honour: In the meane time, as ſhee is a profeſſed incourager and an indulgent lover of all true devotion, ſhee cannot but be well pleaſed, with what ſoever expreſſions of reverence, we give to the divine Majeſty, under whatſoever termes, uttered by our well adviſed, and well inſtructed tongues.
               I have knowne, and honored, as moſt worthy a conſtant imitation, ſome devout perſons, that never durſt mention the name of God, in their ordinary communication, without

uncovering of their heads, or elevation of their hands, or ſome ſuch other teſtimony of reverence.
               And certainly, if the heart be ſo throughly poſſeſſed with a ſad awe of that infinite Majeſty, as it ought; the tongue dares not preſume in a ſudden unmannerlineſſe to blurt out the dreadfull name of God; but ſhall both make way for it, by a premiſed deliberation, and attend it with a reverent elocution. I am aſhamed to think how farre we are ſurpaſſed by heatheniſh piety; The ancient Grecians and amongſt the reſt, Plato, (as Suidas well obſerves,) when they would

ſweare by their Iupiter, out of the meere dread, and reverence of his name, forbare to mention him: breaking off their oath, with a, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , as thoſe that onely dare to owe the reſt to their thoughts; And Climas the Pythagorean, out of this regard, would rather undergoe a mulct of three talents, than ſweare. Whiles the prophane mouthes of many Chriſtians, make no difference in their appellation, betweene their God, and their ſervant.
            
            
               
               SECT. VI.
               AS the name, ſo the word of our maker challengeth an awfull regard from us, as a reflection of that feare wee owe to the omnipotent author of it. What worlds of nice caution have the maſters of the Synagogue preſcribed to their diſciples, for their demeanour towards the book of the Law, of their God? No letter of it might be writ without a copy; no line of it without a rule; and the rule muſt be upon the back of the parchment; no parchment might bee imployed to this ſervice, but that which is

made of the skinne of a cleane beaſt; no word might be written in a different colour; inſomuch as when in the Pentateuch of Alexander the Great,Idem Schicardus de jure regio Heb
                        •
                     aeorum. the name of Iehovah, was (in pretence of honour) written in golden Characters, their great Rabbins cōdemned the whole volume to be obliterated, and defaced: No man might touch it, but with the right hand, and without a kiſſe of reverence: No man might ſit in the preſence of it; No man might ſo much as ſpit before it; No man might carry it behind him; but lay it next to his heart, in his travell; No man might offer to read it, but in a cleane place;

no man might ſell it, though the copy were moth-eat, and himſelfe halfe famiſhed: And is the word of the everlaſting God of leſſe worth and authority, now, than it hath beene? Or is there leſſe cauſe of our reverence of thoſe divine Oracles, than theirs? Certainly, if they were ſuperſtitiouſly ſcrupulous, it is not for us to be careleſly ſlovenly, and neglective of that ſacred Book, out of which wee ſhall once bee judged: Even that impure Alcoran of the Turkes is forbidden to bee touched by any but pure hands. It was not the leaſt praiſe of Carlo Boromeo,
                  Ogier. Apolog. Balſac
                        •
                     , &amp;c. the late Saint of Millaine, that hee

would never read the divine Scripture, but upon his knees; and if we profeſſe to beare no leſſe inward honour to that ſacred volume; why ſhould we, how can wee think it free for us to entertaine it with an unmannerly neglect?
            
            
               SECT. VII.
               AS to the name and word, ſo to the ſervices of God muſt the efficacy of our holy feare bee diffuſed; and theſe, whether private or publick: If we pray, our awe will call us, either to a ſtanding on our feet, as ſervants; or a bowing of our knees, as ſuppliants; or,

a proſtration on our faces, as dejected penitents; Neither when the heart is a Camell, can the body be an Elephant: What Prince would not ſcorne the rudeneſſe of a ſitting petitioner? It was a juſt diſtinction of Socrates of old,
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plat. Apol. that, to ſacrifice, is to give to God; to pray, is to beg of God: And who is ſo liberall, as to caſt away his almes upon a ſtout, and unreverent beggar? If we attend Gods meſſage in the mouth of his holy ſervants, whether read or preached, our feare will frame us to a reverent carriage of our bodies; ſo as our very outward deportment may really ſeeme to

ſpeak the words of the good Centurion;Acts 10.33 
                  Now we are all here preſent before God, to heare all things that are commanded thee of God; we ſhall need no law to vaile our bonnets, ſave that in our owne breaſt. It was a great word that Simeon the ſonne of Satach,
                  Talm. ſaid to the Iewiſh Prince, and Prieſt, convented before their Sanhedrin; Thou ſtandeſt not before us, but before him that ſaid, Let the world be made, and it was made: did we think ſo, how durſt wee ſit in a bold ſaucineſſe (whiles that great Embaſſie is delivered) with our hats on our heads; as if we acknowledged no preſence but

of our inferiours; yea, (that which is a ſhame to ſay) thoſe very apprentices, who dare not cover their heads at home, where their Maſter is alone; yet, in Gods houſe, where they ſee him in a throng of his betters, waiting upon the ordinances of the God of heaven, think it free for them, equally, to put on, and to bee no leſſe fellowes with their Maſter, than he is with his Maker: as if the place and ſervice gave a publick priviledge to all commers, of a prophane lawleſneſſe: Surely, the ſame ground whereon the Apoſtle built his charge for the covering of the heads of the women, ſerves

equally for the uncovering the heads of the men, Becauſe of the Angels; yea more, becauſe of the God of the Angels;1 Cor. 11.10. who by theſe viſible Angels of his Church, ſpeakes to us, and ſolicites our ſalvation. If we addreſſe our ſelves to the dreadfull myſteries of the bleſſed Sacrament of the body and bloud of our Lord Ieſus, our feare will bend our knees in a meet reverence to that great and gracious Saviour, who is there lively repreſented, offered, given, ſealed up to our ſoules; who at that heavenly Table, is, (as Saint Jerome truly) both the gueſt,Ipſe conviva &amp; convivium. Ad Hedibiam and the banquet: Neither can the heart

that is ſeaſoned with true piety, be afraid of too lowly a participation of the Lord of glory; but rather reſolves, that he is not worthy of knees, who will not here bow them; for, who ſhould command them, if not their Maker, if not their Redeemer? Away with the monſters of opinion, and practiſe, concerning this Sacrament: Chriſt Ieſus is here really tendred unto us; and who can, who dares take him but on his knees? What poſture can we uſe with our fellowes, if we ſit with our God and Saviour? At our beſt, well may we ſay with the humble Centurion; Lord we are not worthy thou ſhouldeſt

come under our roofe: but, if we prepare not both ſoules, and bodies, to receive him reverently, our ſinfull rudeneſſe ſhall make us utterly uncapable of ſo bleſſed a preſence.
            
            
               SECT. VIII.
               NEither doth our awfull regard reach onely to the actions of Gods ſervice, but extends it ſelfe even to the very houſe, which is called by his name: the place where his honour dwelleth. For, as the preſence of God gives an holineſſe to what place ſoever he is pleaſed to ſhew himſelfe in; (as the Sunne carries an inſeparable

light whereſoever it goes) ſo that holineſſe calls for a meet veneration from us: It was a fit word for that good Patriarch, who ſware by his fathers feare; which he ſpake of his Bethel;
                  Gen. 31.53 
                  How dreadfull is this place,
                  Gen. 28.17 
                  this is none other, but the houſe of God: this is the gate of Heaven. The ſeverall diſtances, and diſtinctions that were obſerved in the Temple of God, at Hieruſalem, are famouſly knowne: None might ſit within the verge thereof, but the King; all others, either ſtood, or kneeld. I have read of ſome ſects of men ſo curiouſly ſcrupulous, that their Prieſts were not allowed to

breathe in their Temple,Rugianorum ſacerdos non intra aedem Dei ſui halitum emittebatne, &amp;c. Hoſpinian de orgi. Feſtor. Mabumetan. but were commanded (whiles they went in to ſweep the floore) to hold their winde, (like thoſe that dive for ſponges at Samos) to the utmoſt length of time; and when they would vent their ſuppreſſed aire, and change it for new, to goe forth of the doores, and returne with a freſh ſupply. But,Zago Zabaes relation. we are ſure the Ethiopian Chriſtians are ſo holily mannerly, that they doe not allow any man ſo much as to ſpit in their Churches; and if ſuch a defilement happen, they cauſe it to be ſpeedily clenſed: What ſhall we then ſay of the common prophaneneſſe of thoſe

careleſſe Chriſtians, that make no diſtinction, betwixt their Church, and their barne; that care not to looke unto their foule feet, when they come under this ſacred roofe; that with equall irreverence ſtumble into Gods houſe, and their tavern; that can find no fitter place for their ambulatory, their burſe, their counting houſe; their ſepulcher? It is recorded of Saint Swithine,
                  Matth. Weſtmonaſt. 862. the (no leſſe famous than humble) Biſhop of Wincheſter, that when he died, he gave charge that his body ſhould not in any caſe be buryed, within the Church; but be layd where his grave might be wet with raine, and

open to weather &amp; paſſengers; I ſuppoſe, as conceiving that ſacred place too good for the repoſitory of the beſt carcaſſes.
               Surely, we cannot eaſily entertaine too venerable an opinion of the habitation of the Almighty: If our hearts have the honour to be the ſpirituall Temples of God, we ſhall gladly give all due honour to his materiall Temples: and doubtleſſe in all experience, we ſhall ſo reſpect the houſe, as we are affected to the owner. It was the diſcipline and practiſe of the Hetruſcians, from whom old Rome learned much of her skill in Auguries, and many myſteries of religion,

that thoſe deities whom they deſired to harbour in their owne breaſts, as Vertue, Peace, Modeſty, ſhould have Temples erected within their walls; but thoſe, which were the Preſidents of warres and combuſtions, or pleaſures, and ſenſualitie, (as Mars, Venus, Vulcan,) ſhould take up with Temples without their walls: And even ſo it is, and will be ever with us; if we have an holy regard to the God of heaven, and adore him, as inhabiting our boſomes, we cannot but give all faire and venerable reſpects to thoſe houſes, which he hath taken up for his own worſhip, and preſence.
            
            
               
               SECT. IX.
               NEither, laſtly, can Gods very Meſſengers (though partners of our owne infirmities) eſcape ſome ſenſible reflections of our feare: It was the rule of the Iewes, that the very Prince of the people,Vide Schicardum de jure regio Hebr. if hee would conſult Gods Oracle, out of reverence to that divine pectorall, muſt reverently ſtand before that Prieſt, who, at other times was bound to give lowly obedience to his Soveraigne Lord. What Great Alexander did to the Iewiſh high Prieſt, who knowes not? Neither hath the practiſes of

the godly Emperours in the Chriſtian Church, through all ſucceſſions of Ages, ſavored of leſſe regard: Even the late Caeſar Ferdinand in the ſight of our Engliſh, not long before his end, together with his Empreſſe, received an Epiſcopall benediction publickly, upon their knees. Away with that inſolent pompe of kiſſing of toes,Lipſius, electorum lib. 2. turpem &amp; ſervilem. (which Iuſtus Lipſius juſtly called once, foule and ſervile) fit for a Caligula, or Maximinus the younger, or a Diocleſian; Away with the proud horſing on ſhoulders, or treading on necks, or the lackeying of Princes; It was a moderate word of Cardinall Zabarell,
                  
concerning his great Maſter;Tract. de Schiſm: Innocentii ſeptimi &amp; Benedicti. So is he to be honoured, that he be not adored. Surely when religion was at the beſt, great Peeres thought it no ſcorne to kiſſe the venerable hands of their ſpirituall fathers;Paulin. in vita Sancti Ambroſii. and did not grudge them eminent titles of honour. It was but a ſimple port that Elijah carryed in the world, who after that aſtoniſhing wonder of fetching downe fire and water from heaven, thought it no abaſement to be Ahabs lackey from Carmel to Iezreel;1 Kings 18.46. yet Obadiah, who was high Steward to the King of Iſrael, even that day, could fall on his face to him, and ſay, Art thou that

my Lord Elijah? Not much greater was the ſtate of thoſe Chriſtian Biſhops, who began, now to breathe from the bloudy perſecutions of the heathen Emperours; yet, with what deareneſſe did that gracious Conſtantine (in whom this Iland is proud to challenge no ſmall ſhare) kiſſe thoſe ſcarres, which they had received for the name of Chriſt? with what titles did he dignifie them? as one that ſaw Chriſt in their faces; and meant in their perſons to honour his Saviour: And indeed, there is ſo cloſe, and indiſſoluble a relation betwixt Chriſt and his Meſſengers, that their mutuall

intereſt can never be ſevered. What Prince doth not hold himſelfe concerned in the honors, or affronts that are done to his Ambaſſadors? Thoſe keyes which God hath committed to our hands, lock us ſo faſt to him, that no power in earth, or hell, can ſeparate us; but ſtill that word muſt ſtand faſt, in heaven: He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me: In vaine ſhall they therefore pretend to feare God, that contemne and diſgrace their ſpirituall governours. There is a certain plant,Gerard pag. 642. which our Herbaliſts call (herbam impiam) or wicked Cudweed, whoſe younger branches ſtill yeeld flowers to over-top

the elder; Such weeds grow too rife abroad; It is an ill ſoyle that produceth them: I am ſure, that where the heart is manured, and ſeaſoned with a true feare of the Almighty, there cannot be but an awfull regard to our ſpirituall Paſtors; well are thoſe two charges conjoyned,Eccl. 7.33. 
                  Feare God, and honour his Preiſts.
               
            
            
               SECT. X.
               HItherto having conſidered that part of holy Feare, which (conſiſting in an inward adoration of God) expreſſeth it ſelfe in the awfull reſpects to his Name, Word,

Services, Houſe, Meſſengers; we deſcend to that other part, which conſiſts in our humble ſubjection, and ſelfe-reſignatito his good pleaſure, in all things; whether to order, or correct: The ſuffering part is the harder. It was a gracious reſolution of old Eli;
                  1 Sam. 3.18 
                  Jt is the Lord, let him doe whatſoever hee will; Surely, that man, though he were but an ill Father, to his worſe ſonnes, yet he was a good ſonne to his Father in heaven: for nothing but a true filiall awe could make the heart thus pliant; that repreſents our ſelves to us, as the clay, and our God to us, as the potter; and therefore ſhowes

us how unjuſtly we ſhould repine at any forme, or uſe, that is by his hand put upon us: I could envy that word which is ſaid to have falne from the mouth of Francis of Aſsiſſe, in his great extremity; I thank thee,Lib. 1. Conform
                     
                        ••
                     uct. 12. O Lord God, for all my paine; and I beſeech thee (if thou think good) to adde unto it, an hundred fold more. Neither was it much different from that, which I have read, as reported of Pope Adrian,
                  Binius, &amp;c. but I am ſure was ſpoken by a worthy divine, within my time and knowledge, of the Vniverſity of Cambridge. (whoſe labours are of much note, and uſe in the Church of God)

Maſter Perkins; who, when he lay in his laſt, and killing torment of the ſtone, hearing the by-ſtanders to pray for a mitigation of his paine, willed them, not to pray for an eaſe of his complaint, but for an increaſe of his patience; Theſe ſpeeches cannot proceed but from ſubdued, and meek, and mortified ſoules; more intentive upon the glory of their Maker, than their owne peace and relaxation: And certainly, the heart thus ſeaſoned, cannot but bee equally tempered to all conditions, as humbly acknowledging the ſame hand, both in good, &amp; evill: And therfore, even frying in Phalaris his

Bull (as the Philoſopher ſaid of a wiſe man) will be able to ſay,Hovv pleaſant? 
                  Quàm ſuave? Was it true of that heathen Martyr, Socrates, that, as in his lifetime he was not wont to change his countenance upon any alteration of events, ſo when hee ſhould come to drink his Hemlock,
                  
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plat. Apol. &amp;c. as Plato reports it, no difference could be deſcryed, either in his hand or face; no paleneſſe in his face, no trembling in his hand, but a ſtedfaſt and fearleſſe taking of that fatall cup, as if it differed not from the wine of his meals? Even this reſolution was no other, than an effect of the acknowledgment of that one

God for which he ſuffered; If ſo, I cannot leſſe magnifie that man for his temper, than the Oracle did for his wiſdome: but I can doe no leſſe than bleſſe, and admire the known courage, and patience of thoſe Chriſtian Martyrs, who out of a loving feare of him, that only can ſave, and caſt both bodies and ſoules in hell, deſpiſed ſhame, paine, death, and manfully inſulted upon their perſecutors? Bleſſed Ignatius could profeſſe to challenge and provoke the furious Lyons, to his dilaniation. Bleſſed Cyprian could pray that the Tyrant would not repent of the purpoſe of dooming him to

death; and that other holy Biſhop, when his hand was threatned to be cut off, could ſay, Seca ambas, Cut of both: It is not for me to tranſcribe volumes of Martyrologies. All that holy army of conquering Saints began their victories in an humble awe of him, whoſe they were; and cheerfully triumphed over irons, and racks, and gibbets, and wheeles, and fires, out of a meek and obedient ſubmiſſion to the will and call of their ever-bleſſed God, and moſt deare Redeemer; In ſo much as Saint Chryſoſtome profeſſes to find patterns and parallels, for himſelfe in all varieties of

tormenrs, and whatſoever ſeverall formes of execution: And the bleſſed Apoſtle hath left us a red Calender of theſe conſtant witneſſes of God; whoſe memory is ſtill on earth,Heb. 11.36, 37, 38. their Crowne in heaven.
               Neither is it thus only in the undaunted ſufferings for the cauſes of God; but our awe ſubjects us alſo to the good will of God, in all whatſoever changes of eſtate. Do I ſmart with afflictions? I will beare the indignation of the Lord,
                  Mich. 7.9. 
                  becauſe I have ſinned againſt him. I held my peace becauſe thou Lord haſt done it. Doe I abound in bleſſings? Who am I, O Lord God,
                  2 Sam. 7.18 
                  and what is my

fathers houſe, that thou haſt brought me hitherto:
                  Philip. 4.11. In both; J have learned in what condition ſoever I am, to bee there with content.
               
            
            
               SECT. XI.
               THus do we bow the knee
                     •
                   of our hearts to God, in our adoration of his Majeſty, both in duely magnifying his greatneſſe and goodneſſe; and in our humble ſubmiſſion to his holy, and gratious pleaſure▪ there remaines that other ſignature of our awfull diſpoſition, which conſiſts in a tender and child-like care, both of his ſecret approbation of us, and

of our avoydance of his diſpleaſure, and our offence towards him; theſe two part not aſunder, for, he that deſires to be approved, would be loath to diſpleaſe.
               The heart that is rightly affected to God, is ambitious, above all things, under heaven, of the ſecret allowance of the Almighty; and therefore is carefull to paſſe a continuall, and exact inquiſition upon all his thoughts, much more upon his actions, what acceptation, or cenſure they find above; like as ſome timorous child upon every ſtitch, that ſhe takes in her firſt Sampler, lookes tremblingly in the face

of her Miſtreſſe, to ſee how ſhe likes it;Error Tho. Aqui. Quodlib. art. 20. Hoſpin. in notis ad regul Benedicti. as well knowing that the Law of God was not given us (as ſome have ſaid of Benedicts rule) only to profeſſe, but to peforme; and that accordingly the conſcience ſhall find either peace or tumult. As we are wont therefore, to ſay of the Dove, that at the picking up of every graine, ſhe caſts her eyes up to heaven, ſo will our godly feare teach us to do, after all our ſpeeches and actions: For which cauſe it will be neceſſary to exerciſe our hearts with very frequent (if not continuall) ejaculations;Io. Capgrave. I remember the ſtory tells us of that famous

                  Iriſh Saint (of whom there are many monuments in theſe weſterne parts) that hee was wont to ſigne himſelfe,Patricius. no leſſe than an hundred times in an houre: Away with all ſuperſtition; although Cardinall Bellarmine tells us (not improbably) that in the practiſe of thoſe ancient Chriſtians,In one of his prefaces to his controverſie. their croſſing was no other than a ſilent kind of invocation of that Saviour, who was crucified for us; Surely I ſhould envy any man that hath the leiſure, and grace, to lift up his heart thus often, to his God; let the glance bee never ſo ſhort: neither can ſuch a one chooſe, but be full of religious

feare: I like not the faſhion of the Euchites, that were all prayer, and no practiſe, but the mixture of theſe holy elevations of the ſoule, with all out actions, with all recreations, is ſo good and laudable, tha
                     •
                   whoſoever is moſt frequent i
                     •
                   it, ſhall paſſe with me for moſ
                     •
                   devout, and moſt converſant it heaven.
               But the moſt proper an
                     •
                   pregnant proofe of this Fear
                     •
                   of God,
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plat. Euthy phr. is the feare of offending God; in which regard i
                     •
                   is perfectly filiall; The goo
                     •
                   child is afraid of diſpleaſin
                     •
                   his father, though he were ſu
                     ••
                   not to be beaten; whereas, th
                     •
                   ſlave is only afraid of ſtripes

not of diſpleaſure: Out of this deare awe to his father in heaven, the truly regenerate trembles to be but tempted; and yet reſolves not to yeild to any aſſault; whether proffers of favour, or violence of battery, all is one: The obfirmed ſoule will hold out, and ſcornes ſo much as to looke of what colour the flagge is; as having learned to bee no leſſe affraid of ſin, than of hell: and if the option were given him, whether hee would rather ſinne without puniſhment; or bee puniſhed without ſinne, the choyce would not be difficult; any torment were more eaſie than the conſcience of a divine

diſpleaſure. It was good Ioſephs juſt queſtion.Gen. 39.9. 
                  How ſhall I do this great wickedneſſe and ſinne againſt God? Lo it is the ſinne that he ſticks at, not the judgement; as one that would have feared the offence, if there had beene no hell: But, if it fall out that the renewed perſon (as it is incident to the moſt dutifull children of God) bee, through a violent tentation, and his owne infirmity, miſcarryed into a knowne ſinne, how much warme water doth it coſt him, ere hee can recover his wonted ſtate? what anxiety, what ſtrife, what torture, what ſelfe-revenge, what ejaculations and complaints,

what unrepining ſubjection to the rod? I have ſinned,
                  Iob 7.20. 
                  what ſhall I do to thee, O thou preſerver of men; So I have ſeene a good natur'd child, that even after a ſharp whipping, could not be quieted till hee had obtained the pardon, and evened the browes of a frowning parent.
               And now, (as it is with little ones, that have taken a knock with a late fall) the good man walkes hereafter with ſo much the more wary foot; and is the more fearefully jealous of his owne infirmity, and finding in himſelfe but the very inclinations towards the firſt motions of evill, he is

carefull, according to that wholſome rule of a ſtrict Votary,Benedict. reg. cap. 4. (Cogitationes malas mox ad Chriſtum allidere,) inſtantly to daſh his new borne evill thoughts againſt the rocke Chriſt. And henceforth, out of a ſuſpition of the danger of exceſſe, he dares not go to the further end of his tether, but in a wiſe and ſafe rigour, abridges himſelf of ſome part of that ſcope, which he might be allowed to take, and will ſtint himſelfe rather than laſh out; indeed, right reaſon teacheth us to keep aloofe from offending that power which wee adore:Marr. Dorza. Sab. poſt d
                        •
                     minic. 4 Quadrag The ancient Almaines holding their rivers for gods,

durſt not waſh their faces with thoſe waters, leſt they ſhould violate thoſe deities: And the Iewes were taught not to dare to come neere an Idolatrous grove, though the way were never ſo direct and commodious. No wiſe man however hee might have firme footing upon the edge of ſome high rocky promontory, will venture to walk within ſome paces of that downfall; but much more will his ſenſe and judgement teach him to refraine from caſting himſelfe headlong (like that deſperate Barbarian in Xenophon) from that ſteep precipice;Xenoph. de exped. Cyri. The feare of God therefore is a ſtrong retentive

from ſinne; neither can poſſibly conſiſt (in what-ſoever ſoule) with a reſolution to offend; As then the father of the faithfull when he came into Gerar, a Philiſtim City, could ſtrongly argue that thoſe heathens would refraine from no wickedneſſe, becauſe the feare of God was not in that place;Gen. 20.11 ſo, we may no leſſe irrefragably inferre, where we ſee a trade of prevalent wickedneſſe, there can be no feare of God: Wo is me, what ſhall I ſay of this laſt age, but the ſame that I muſt ſay of mine owne? As this decrepit body, therefore, by reaſon of the unequall temper of humors, and

the defect of radicall moyſture and heat, cannot but be a ſewer of all diſeaſes; So it is, ſo it will be with the decayed old age of this great body of the world, through want of the feare of the ever-living God;Pſal 119.136. 
                  Rivers of waters O God ſhall run downe mine eyes becauſe men keep not thy law. But what do I ſuggeſt to the obdured hearts of wilfull ſinners, the ſweet and gracious remedies of a loving feare? This preſervative is for children; ſturdy rebells muſt expect other receits: A frown is an heavy puniſhment to a dutifull ſonne, ſcourges and ſcorpions are but enough for a rebellious vaſſall. I muſt lay

before ſuch, an hell of vengeance; and ſhow them the horrible Topheth prepared of old, even that bottomleſſe pit of perdition; and tell them of rivers of brimſtone, of a worm ever gnawing, of everlaſting burnings, of weeping, wailing,2 Theſ 1.8 and gnaſhing, when the terrible Iudge of the world ſhall come in flaming fire rendring vengeance to them that know not God, and obey him not; And certainly, if the ſinner had not an Infidell in his boſome, the expectation of ſo direfull a condition, to be inflicted and continued upon him, unto all eternity, without poſſibility of any intermiſſion,

or of any remiſſion▪ were enough to make him run made with feare; only unbeleefe keeps him from a frantick deſpaire, and a ſudden leap into his hell. And if the cuſtome and deceit of ſinne have wrought an utter ſenſeleſneſſe in thoſe brawny hearts, I muſt leave them over to the wofull ſenſe of what they will not feare, yea to the too late feare of what they ſhall not bee able either to beare, or avoid. Certainly the time will come, when they ſhall be ſwallowed up with a dreadfull confuſion, and ſhall no more be able not to feare, than not to bee; Oftentimes

even in the midſt of all their ſecure jollity, God writes bitter things againſt them, ſuch as make their knees to knock together, their lips to tremble, their teeth to chatter, their hands to ſhake, their hearts to faile within them, for the anguiſh of their ſoules; Were they as inſenſate as the earth it ſelfe,Habac. 3.10. 
                  Touch the mountaines and they ſhall ſmoke, ſaith the Pſalmiſt; The mountaines ſaw thee, and they trembled, ſaith Habbacuc: But if their feare be reſpited, it is little for their eaſe; it doth but forbeare a little that it may overwhelme them at once for ever; Woe is mee for them; In how heavy and deplorable

caſe are they and feele it not? They lie under the fierce wrath of the Almighty, and complaine of nothing but eaſe. The mountains quake at him,
                  Nahum. 1.56. 
                  and the hils melt, and the earth is burnt at his preſence; Who can ſtand before his indignation? and who can abide in the fierceneſſe of his anger? his fury is poured out like fire, and the rockes are thrown downe by him, ſaith the Prophet Nahum. Yet, oh, what a griefe it is to ſee, that ſo dreadfull a power ſhould carry away no more feare from us wretched men; yea even from thoſe that are ready to feare where no feare is? Paines of body, frownes of the great, reſtraint

of liberty, loſſe of goods, who is it that feares not? But, alas, to avoid theſe, men feare not to venture upon the diſpleaſure of him whoſe anger is death, and who is able to caſt body and ſoule into hell fire: So wee have ſeene fond children, that to avoid a bugbeare have runne into fire, or water: So we have ſeen a ſtarting jade, that ſuddenly flying from a ſhadow, hath caſt himſelfe into a ditch; We can but mourne in ſecret for thoſe that have no teares to ſpend upon themſelves, and tremble for them that will needs gnaſh. If thoſe that are filthy, will be filthy ſtill; If ſecure men will

ſet up a trade of ſinning; every good heart will take up Nehemiahs reſolution:Neh. 5.15 
                  But ſo did not J, becauſe of the feare of the Lord; and the practice of holy Habacuc;
                  Hab. 3.16. 
                  I trembled in my ſelfe, that I might reſt in the day of trouble: It is wiſe Solomons good experiment, (which hee loved to repeat;Prov. 16.6. Prov. 3.7.) By the feare of the Lord men depart from evill: for they ſay one to another, (as the Tremelian verſion hath it, in Malachy) The Lord hearkeneth and heareth;Mal. 3.16. and how dare they, how can they doe amiſſe in that preſence? For as the Saints ſay, after the Song of Moſes, and the Song of the Lambe; Great

and marvellous are thy workes,
                  Revel. 15.3.4. 
                  Lord God Almighty: Iuſt and true are thy wayes, thou King of Saints; who ſhall not feare thee, and glorifie thy Name? for thou onely art holy.
               
            
            
               SECT. XII.
               SHortly then, that wee may put theſe two together, (which are not willing to be ſevered:) Whoſoever is duely affected with a true filiall feare of the Almighty, cannot by allurements be drawne to doe that which may offend ſo ſweet a mercy: cannot by any difficulties bee diſcouraged from doing that which may

bee pleaſing to ſo gracious a majeſty: The Magiſtrate that feares God, dares not, cannot be partiall to any wickedneſſe; dares not, cannot bee harſh to innocence; managing that ſword wherewith hee is intruſted, ſo as God himſelfe, if he were upon earth, would doe it, for the glory of his owne juſt mercie: The Meſſenger of God that feares him on whoſe errand hee goes, dares not, cannot either ſmother his meſſage, or exceed it: he will, he muſt lift up his voice like a trumpet, and tell Iſrael of her ſinnes, and Iudah of her tranſgreſſions; not fearing faces, not ſparing offences. The

ordinary Chriſtian that feares God, dares not cannot, but make conſcience, of all his wayes; he dares not defraud or lie for an advantage, he dares not ſweare falſely for a world, hee dares not proſtitute his body to whatſoever filthineſſe, he dares not oppreſſe his inferiours, he dares not turn away his owne face from the poore, much leſſe dares hee grind theirs; in one word, he dares rather dy than ſinne; And contrarily; what blockes ſoever nature layes in his way, (ſince his God calls him forth to this combat) he cannot but bid battell to his owne rebellious corruptions, and offer a

deadly violence to his evill and corrupt affections; and enter the liſts with all the powers of darkneſſe, reſiſting unto bloud, and willingly bleeding, that he may overcome: Who now would not be in love with this feare?Pſal. 34.9. 
                  O feare the Lord yee his Saints, hee that feares him ſhall lacke nothing;
                  Mal. 4.2. 
                  The Sunne of righteouſneſſe ſhall ariſe unto him with healing in his wings; In the meane time,Pſal. 25 
                        •
                     
                   
                  the ſecret of the Lord is with him; The Angells of the Lord are ever about him;
                  P
                        •
                     al. 
                        ••
                     
                   
                  Pſal. 2
                        •
                     .23 
                  His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe here below; and above ſalvation is neare unto him; yea,Pſal. 85.10 he is already feoffed of life and glory.Pro. 19.25
               
            
            
               
               SECT. XIII.
               NOw, as ſome carefull Pilot, that takes upon him to direct a difficult ſea-paſſage, which his long and wary obſervation hath diſcovered, doth not content himſelfe to ſteere a right courſe, in his owne veſſell, and to ſhow the eminent ſea-markes a farre off, but tells withall, what rocks, or ſhelves lie on either ſide of the channell, which, upon the leaſt deviation, may indanger the paſſengers; So muſt we do, here; Having therefore ſufficiently declared wherein this feare of God conſiſteth, what it requireth

of us, and how it is acted, and expreſſed by us; it remayneth, that we touch at thoſe extremes, which on both ſides muſt bee carefully avoyded; Theſe are, Security, and Preſumption on the one hand; on the other, Vicious feare. It was the word of the wiſe man, yea,Prov. 28.14. rather of God, by him, Happy is the man that feareth alway; but he that hardneth his heart, ſhall fall into miſchiefe; Lo an obdured ſecurity is propoſed to feare, both in the nature and iſſue of it: Feare intenerates the heart, making it fit for all gracious impreſſions; ſecurity hardens it, and renders it uncapable of good: feare ends in

happineſſe, ſecurity in an evitable miſchiefe; And theſe two (though contraries, yet) ariſe from the ſame cauſe contrarily applyed: Like as the ſame Sunne hardens the clay, and ſoftens the wax; it is heat that doth both; cauſing dryneſſe in the one, and a diſſolution in the other: Even ſo the ſame beames of divine mercy melt the good heart into an holy feare, (Great is thy mercy that thou mayſt be feared) and harden the wicked heart in a ſtate of ſecurity; For, upon the goodneſſe of God to men, both in giving and forgiving, do men grow ſecurely evill, and rebellious to their God; as being

apt to ſay; J have ſinned, and what harme hath happened unto mee?
                  Ecclus. 5.4. ſaith Siracides: Lo even forbearance obdureth,Eccleſ. 8.11. 
                  Becauſe ſentence againſt an evill work, is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the ſonnes of men is fully ſet in them to do evill: How much more do the riches of Gods goodnes which are the hotteſt beams of that Sun,Rom. 2.4. when they beat directly upon our heads?Prov. 1.32. 
                  The eaſe of the ſimple ſhall ſlay them, and the proſperity of fooles ſhall deſtroy them, ſaith Salomon; Our philoſophy tells us,Nemo poteſt amplecti Dei gratiam ſimul &amp; ſeculi. Ambroſ, lib. 4. Epiſt. 29. that an extreme heat ſhuts up thoſe pores, which a moderate openeth; It was a ſore word of Saint Ambroſe; that no man can at

once embrace Gods favour,Aegidius. lib. Conform. &amp;.c. conform. 8 and the worlde: Neither can I diſallow that obſervation of a rigorous Votary; that the Divells of conſolation (as he calls them) are more ſubtile, and more pernicious, than thoſe of tribulation; Not ſo much perhaps in their own nature, as for the party they find in our own breaſts: The wiſe man could ſay;Prov. 30.9. 
                  Leſt J bee full and deny thee, and aske, who is the Lord? Even very heathens have beene thus jealouſly conſcious of their owne diſpoſition;Tit. Livius. So as Camillus when upon ten yeeres ſiege he had taken the wealthy city Veies, could pray forſome miſhap to befall himſelfe, and

                  Rome, to temper ſo great an happineſſe. This is that which Gregory the great, upon his exaltation to that papall honour,Torpet ignava mens, &amp; circumla▪ trantibus curis temporalibus cum pene ad ſtuporem deducta &amp;c. Greg. Epiſt. l. 7.127. doth ſo much complaine of, in himſelfe: that his inward fall was no leſſe than his outward rayſing; and that his dull heart was almoſt grown ſtupid, with thoſe temporall occaſions: And ſurely, ſo it will be, if there be not a ſtrong grace within us,Trifarius rerum curſus, Abun dantiae, Indigentiae, Temperantiae; ex abundantia animoptatas &amp;c. Faſcic. temp. in An. 1404. to ſeaſon our proſperity.
               That which the Hiſtorian obſerved in the courſe of the world, that abundance begets delicacy and animoſity; that againe, quarrells and vaſtation of warre; and from thence

growes poverty; is no leſſe true in the particular ſtate of the ſoule; If we be rich and high fed, we grow wanton, and ſtomackfull, and apt to make warre with heaven, till we be taken down againe with affliction: Thereupon, it is that the wiſe and holy God, hath found it ſtill needfull to ſauce our contentments with ſome mixtures of ſorrow; and to proclaime the Iubile of our mirth and freedome, upon the ſad day of expiation: The man after Gods owne heart could ſay, In my prosperity I ſaid,
                  Pſal. 6.7. 
                  I ſhall never be moved; but the next yee heare is, Thou didſt hide thy face, and I was troubled;

and this trouble he profeſſes to have beene for his good; without theſe meet temperaments, worldly hearts runne wilde, and can ſay with the ſcornfull men, that rule in Ieruſalem;
                  Eſay. 28 15. 
                  We have made a covenant with death, and with hell are wee at agreement; when the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſſe thorow, it ſhall not come to us, for we have made lies our refuge, and under falſhood have wee hid our ſelves: yea in a ſtout inſolence, as the Prophet Ieremy expreſſes it;Ier. 5.12. 
                  They belie the Lord, and ſay, it is not he; neither ſhall evill come upon us; neither ſhall we ſee ſword, or famine. Neither yet is it only the abuſe of

Gods long ſuffering and bounty that produceth this ill habit of ſecurity, and hard-heartedneſſe; but eſpecially, a cuſtome of ſinning: Oft treading hardens the path; the hand that was at the firſt ſoft, and tender, after it hath beene inured to worke, growes brawned, and impenetrable. Wee have heard of Virgins, which at the firſt, ſeemed modeſt; bluſhing at the motions of an honeſt love; who being once corrupt, and debauched, have grown flexible to eaſie intreaties unto unchaſtity, and from thence, boldly laſcivious, ſo as to ſolicite others, ſo as to proſtitute themſelves to all commers,

yea (as our Caſuiſts complaine of ſome Spaniſh Stewes) to an unnaturall filthineſſe.Martin. Vivaldus in Candelabro. in Cap. de Confeſſi. That which our Canoniſts ſay, in an other kind, is too true here,Vivald. 4. parte in 30. Cuſtome can give a Iuriſdiction; neither is there any ſtronger law than it: The continued uſe then of any known ſinne, be it never ſo ſmall, gives (as Gerſons phraſe is) a ſtrong habituation; and, though it be a true rule,Habitus inclinant, non cogunt. that habits do only incline, not compell; yet the inclination that is wrought by them, is ſo forceable, that it differs little from violent: Surely ſo powrefull is the habit of ſinne, bred by ordinary practiſe, as that it takes away

the very ſenſe of ſinning; ſo as the offender now knowes not that he doth the very act of ſome evill; much leſſe that he ſinnes, and offends in doing it; and now the heart is all turned dead fleſh, whether too good, or ill: there is not then a more dangerous condition incident into the ſoule of man, than this of ſecurity; it bars us of the capacity of any good, that may be wroug
                     ••
                   upon us, it expoſes us to the ſucceſſe of all tentations, it drawes downe the heavieſt of Gods judgements upon our heads; it defies juſtice, it rejects mercy, it makes the heart Gods Anvile, (which the harder it is ſtruck, the more rebounds

the blow) but the devills featherbed, wherein hee ſinkes, and lyes ſoft, at free eaſe; neither would that evill ſpirit wiſh for any more pleaſing repoſe; it flatters the ſoule with an impoſſible impunity, it ſhifts off neceſſary vengeance: Laſtly, whiles other diſpoſitions do but yeild to an hell, this invites it. By how much more wofull it is, by ſo mu
                     •
                  h more carefull muſt we be to avoid it.
            
            
               
               SECT. XIV.
               IF we care for our ſouls then, we ſhall zealouſly apply our ſelves to prevent this helliſh evill; which ſhall bee done, if wee ſhall conſtantly uſe all meanes to keepe the heart tender; whereof the firſt is, Frequent meditation upon the judgements of God, attending ſinners: it is the Apoſtles owne preſcript; Let us have grace, whereby we may ſerve God acceptably,
                  Heb. 12.28, 29. 
                  with reverence and godly feare; For our God is a conſuming fire. Could wee but ſtoop downe a little, and looke into hell, wee ſhould never come

thither; the apprehenſion of thoſe torments would be ſure to keep us from ſinning, and and impenitence; It is a true obſervation of Cyrill, that the want of beleefe is guilty of all our obduredneſſe; for ſhould it be told thee,Cyr. in Lev. lib. 9 (ſaith that Father) that a ſecular Iudge intends to doome thee to bee burned alive to morrow, how buſily wouldſt thou imploy the remaining time to prevent the judgement? how eagerly wouldſt thou runne about, how ſubmiſſively and importunately wouldſt thou ſue, and beg for pardon, how readily wouldeſt thou poure out thy mony to thoſe friends, that

ſhould purchaſe it? and why wouldeſt thou do all this, but becauſe thou doubteſt not of the truth of the report? Were our hearts no leſſe convinced of the deſignation of an everlaſting burning to the rebellious and impenitent, could we leſſe beſtirre our ſelves? To this purpoſe alſo it will much conduce that we meditate often of our owne frailty and momentanyneſſe; no evill can faſten upon the ſoule of that man, that hath death ever before his eyes; That father ſaid well, he eaſily contemnes all things that thinks to die every day; The ſervant that ſaid, my maſter deferres his comming,

was he that revelled in the houſe, and beat his fellowes; he durſt not have done it, if he had ſeene his maſter at the doore: No whit leſſe prevalent a remedy of ſecurity is a firme reſolution of the ſoule to repell the firſt motions to what ſoever ſinne, whoſe nature (as experience tells us) is to gather ſtrength by continuance; commonly all onſets are weakeſt in their beginnings, and are then moſt eaſily, and ſafely reſiſted: Cuſtome can never grow where no action will be admitted to make a precedent: It is well obſerved by that learned Chancellour of Paris, that ſome filthy and blaſphemous

cogitations are better overcome by contemning them,Cogitationes fo
                        •
                     
                     dae, blaſphemae, noxiae, potiùs vincuntur contemnendo, quàm reſpondendo. Gerſ. de precept. Theolog. than by anſwering them; If either way they bee repulſed, the heart is ſafe from ſecurity: But, thirdly, if we have beene ſo farre overtaken as to give way to the perpetration of evill, our care muſt be to work our hearts to a ſpeedy renovation by repentance; If ſinne have ſeized upon the ſoule, it may not ſettle there; this is that which will elſe work a palpable indiſpoſition: Let a knife be wet with the ſtrongeſt aqua fortis, and preſently wipt dry againe, the mettall is yet ſmooth, and bewrayeth no change; but, if that moiſt fire

bee ſuffered to reſt upon it a while, it eates into the blade, and leaves behind, ſome deep notes of corroſion; It is delay in theſe caſes that breeds the utmoſt danger; Let a candle that is caſually put out, be ſpeedily rekindled at the next flame, neither is the ſcent offended, nor the wick unapt to be ſtrait-way re-inlightned; ſtay but a while, the whole roome complaines of the noyſome ſmell, and it will coſt perhaps much puffing, and dipping in aſhes, ere it can recover the loſt light. That which Salomon adviſes in matter of ſuretiſhip, we muſt do in the caſe of our ſinne; ſpeedily extricate

our ſelves,Prov. 6.4. and give no ſleep to our eyes till we bee freed from ſo dangerous an engagement. Moreover, unto theſe, it muſt bee our maine care, not to give any check to the conſcience, upon whatſoever occaſions: That power hath as a keene ſo a tender edge, and eaſie to be rebated; when that dictates to a man ſome duty, or the refraining of ſome doubtfull action, he that diſobeyes it, makes way for an induration; for when that faculty hath once received a diſcouragement, it will not be apt to controule us in evill; but growes into a careleſſe neglect of what we do, or omit; and

ſo declines to an utter ſenſeleſſeneſſe; As therefore wee muſt bee carefull to have our conſciences duly regulated by the infallible word of God, ſo muſt wee be no leſſe carefull ſtill, to follow the guidance of our conſcience, in all our wayes: And that all theſe things may be performed with effect, we muſt bee ſure that wee do conſtantly obſerve all our ſet exerciſes of piety, hearing, reading, receiving the bleſſed Sacrament, prayer, and eſpecially, ſtrict ſelfe examination, whereby wee may come to eſpy our firſt failings, and correct our very propenſions to evill: One ſaid well, that nature

doth not more abhorre vacuity than grace doth idleneſſe:Gerſ. ſer. de Domin. Evangel. Plus abhorret gratia otium, quàm natura vacuum. now all theſe, if they ſeeme harſh and tedious to corrupt nature; yet to the renewed heart (familiarly converſant in them) nothing is more pleaſing, and cordiall. The Philoſopher could ſay, and find,
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Ariſt. Eth. lib. 1. that vertuous actions are delightfull to well diſpoſed minds; in ſo much as it is defined for the ſureſt argument of a good habit fully acquired, that wee find contentment and delectation in good performances.
               Laſtly, becauſe ill uſed proſperity is apt to obdure the heart, we muſt be ſure to ſettle

in our ſelves a right eſtimation of all theſe worldly things; which indeed, are, as they are taken: I may well ſay of riches, as the Iewiſh Rabbins had wont to ſay of their Cabala; with a good heart, they are good; otherwiſe they are no better than the Mammon of iniquity: and indeed, worſe than want; but at their beſt, they are ſuch, as are utterly unable to yeeld true contentment to the ſoule; they are good for uſe, ill for fruition; they are for the hand to imploy, not for the heart to ſet up his reſt in: hereupon it is, that the holieſt men have ſtill both inclined and perſwaded to their

contempt:Bene habet quod moleſtant te omnia quae cernis, utique temporali: &amp; mortalia, &amp;c. Gerſ. epiſt. ad Card. Cameracenſ. That great maſter of meditation applauded it in his friend, the Cardinal of Cambray, as the happieſt condition; that all theſe earthly and temporall things which his eye beheld, were tedious unto him; And Saint Bernard magnifies in this name his deare acquaintance,Ep. 24. ad Gilbertum Londini. 
                  Gilbert, Biſhop of London, that even in that ſtate, he would live poore; and the ſame Father would have his Monke to take moſt joy,Ber. Specul. Monachorum. and think himſelfe then welcommeſt, when the courſeſt fare was ſet before him;Lib. Conformirat: Conform. 8. anſwerable whereunto (but beyond it was the diet of Valentine a rigorous Votary, who for

ten yeares together, would eat nothing but bread dipt in water, wherein wormwood was ſteept; And of that other his fellow, who ſteept his bread in lye, that he might eat aſhes with the Prophet.
               Not to runne into extremities, it is ſure and neceſſary counſell which the Pſalmiſt gives us to reſolve;Pſal. 62.10. 
                  If riches increaſe, not to ſet our hearts upon them; to account them no other than as good helps, and needfull impediments; and all worldly contentments ſuch, as are not worthy to take us up: It was a queſtion moved to the founder of ſome ſtrict devotioniſts, whether they might

laugh with all their heart,Si ex toto corde ridere non licet? R
                        •
                     ſp. negativè Reg. Benedic
                        •
                     i. c. 32. and it is anſwered negatively; Non licet: And the devout Governour of the votaries of Clareval, could give charge to his religious; Non debet totus manducare: and it is reported by the writer of his life, if he heard any of his Dorter ſnorting in his ſleep, he would chide that man, as ſleeping carnally, and ſecularly. Surely the world is, and ſhould be the ſame to them and us, who have no leſſe ingaged our ſelves to a profeſſed hoſtility unto all the vanities thereof; and have no more hearty ſhare in the pomps, and pleaſures of it, than the moſt recluſed Anachorets:
                  
At the beſt, this earth can be no other than our vally of teares, and region of our pilgrimage.Girald. Cambr. prefat. ad tract. de mirac. Our Giraldus Cambrenſis tells us that his Saint Brendan, upon long and weariſome travell, at laſt went ſo farre, as to come to the ſight of the earthly Paradiſe: They may, that liſt, believe it,Abrah. Ortel. In the Geograph. Ego vero paradiſum ubique fuiſſe puto, nempe ante Adami lapſum, &amp; non locum ſignificare, ſed loci naturam &amp; qualitatem. but ſure I am; Never any mortall eye (ſince the Angell brandiſhed his ſword there) could find ought worthy the name of a Paradiſe, in this inferiour world; here is Purgatory enough, and perhaps, ſome hell above ground: But if, as Ortelius of late held, that all the whole earth was, at the firſt,

                  Paradiſe, any man ſhall now think that any part of it is ſo ſtill, I ſhall pitty him; and think him worthy the pleaſure of theſe earthly torments: For us, if we would have our ſoules ſafe, wee muſt learn with the bleſſed Apoſtle, ſo to uſe the world,S. Martin. Cujus faciem non fuſca vit moeror, nec l
                        •
                     vigavit riſus. Ber. ſpec. monach. as if we uſed it not, and ſtrive to attaine to the equable temper of that holy man, whoſe face was neither darkned with ſorrow nor ſmoothed with laughter, as well knowing,Quantò in
                        •
                     erius delectamur, tan tò a ſuperno amore diſju
                        •
                     gimur. Her. de interiore domo. that what affection ſoever the world wins of us, is loſt unto God. Thus, if we ſhall keep our ſelves carefully from the trade of ſinne, and from the faſcination of the world, wee

ſhall be ſure that our hearts ſhall not thus be deaded with ſecurity.
            
            
               SECT. XV.
               THe no leſſe direct, but more active oppoſite to holy feare, is Preſumption. We preſume when, out of an unjuſt ſelfe-love, we entertaine an higher opinion of our ſpirituall eſtate, than there is cauſe; whether in reſpect of the way, or of the end; Gods favour as the way, Salvation as the end: We are apt to overweene our intereſt in Gods favour &amp; our aſſured ſafety thereby; cōmonly upon a double ground, either

matter of event, or matter of ability: For, either we miſinterpret faire events, as pledges of happineſſe, and ſafety; or, we miſtake thoſe qualities, for true graces, which are either meere appearances, or perhaps, no better than very enormities; Millions of men miſcarry both wayes; and are therfore ſo far from feare, as that they go dancing towards their hell. It was the ſtrong Bulwark which the Egyptian Iewes ſet up againſt all Ieremy's menaces,Ier. 44.17. 
                  We will burne incenſe to the Queene of Heaven, and poure out drink-offerings to her, as wee have done, we and our fathers, our Kings and our Princes, in the

Cityes of Judah, and in the ſtreets of Ieruſalem: For then, wee had plenty of victuals, and were well, and ſaw no evill. Had their belly beene their God, the argument had held well; that deity is beſt pleaſed with ſtore of cares, but the true God, many times, even with Quailes ſends leanneſſe: Carnall hearts know not how to meaſure felicity, but by the affluence of what moſt pleaſes them; and that pleaſe them moſt, which gives moſt contentment to their ſenſe, and appetite; wherin, if their deſires be anſwered, they are ſoone tranſported from themſelves; and now, can be no other than the great favourites

of heaven.2 Chron. 26.15. If 
                     Ʋzziah once feele himſelfe growne ſtrong, his heart is lifted up; why ſhould not a Cenſer fit him no leſſe than a Scepter? The great Dragon of Egypt,
                  Ezec. 29, 2. when hee hath lien at eaſe a while, in the ſwolne waters of his Nilus, can ſay, My river is my owne, and I have made it for my ſelfe: and, who is there that hath fiſhed ſucceſſefully in this ſea of the world, but is ready to ſacrifice unto his owne nets; and ſayes within himſelfe, Had I not beene ſo good, I had not ſped ſo well: Our naturaliſts truly obſerve, that the moſt poyſonous flyes are bred in the ſweeteſt fruit-trees; So are

theſe moſt dangerous preſumptions in an outward happineſſe of condition: Let an Amalekitiſh Agag be but a little made of,1 Sam. 15.3
                        •
                     . he comes in delicately and ſayes; Surely the bitterneſſe of death is overpaſt; when a King hath beene indulgent, a Prophet will not be bloudy: all is ſafe; there may be hope of my crowne; there can bee no danger of my head. Hereupon it is, that (as thoſe whoſe heads are laid upon downe pillowes, are not apt to heare noyſe) the over-proſperous have their eares precluded againſt all threats of perill, all counſells of reformation; as thinking they neither need to

wiſh themſelves better, nor to feare being worſe. And whiles they applaud themſelves (as the only darlings, they looke overly and ſcornfully upon the meaner eſtate of others, and paſſe deep cenſures upon the adverſities of their miſerable neighbours; as if they could not fare ill, if they were not ſo: Iob cannot bee afflicted if hee were not an hypocrite; Doth the Tower of Siloe, like ſome dreadfull pitfall,Luk. 13 4. overwhelme eighteene Citizens of Jeruſalem? they were more hainous ſinners than their fellowes. Doth a Viper ſeize upon Saint Pauls hand?Acts 28.4. 
                  Doubtleſſe, this man is a murtherer,

whom vengeance would not ſuffer to live: Thus the vaine hearts of ſenſuall men are carried with thoſe outward events, which God never meant for the diſtinction of either love, or hatred; Thoſe that are rich in theſe proud conceits, make their imaginary wealth their ſtrong City; which they pleaſe themſelves in thinking impregnable; and as fooliſh Micah argued a neceſſity of Gods future beneficence to him, by the good that he had done,Iudg. 17.1
                        •
                     . in procuring a Levite to his Prieſt; So theſe flatter themſelves with an aſſurance of Gods preſent favour, by the benefits which God hath

ſhowred downe upon them; wherein it falls out oft, as it did with the riflers of Semiramis his tombe; who, where they expected to find the richeſt treaſure, met with a deadly poyſon. Neither is it eaſie to know whether that other preſumption of abilities be not at leaſt equally frequent and dangerous; The proud Angell of the Church of Laodicea could ſay, I am rich and increaſed with goods, and have need of nothing; not knowing that hee was wretched, miſerable, poore, blind, naked: How many have wee heard to boaſt of thoſe graces, whereto they beene perfect ſtrangers? How

have wee knowne ſome that have pretended to no leſſe illumination than Piſanus reports of Iohn of Alverne,
                  Lib. conformit. who in a rapture was elavated above every creature, and his ſoule ſwallowed up in the abiſſe of the divinity; when it hath beene, indeed, nothing but a fanaticall illuſion: How ordinarily do wee find men challenging no meane ſhare in a lively faith, ſpirituall joy, fervent zeale, true ſanctity, when in the meane while, they have embraced nothing but the clouds of their owne fancies, inſtead of theſe heavenly graces; and, by this meanes have ſtript themſelves of the

poſſibility of thoſe holy vertues, which they falſly ſoothed in themſelves: for who can care to ſeeke for that which he thinks he hath already? Men do not ſo much covet, as arrogate ſpirituall gifts, Every Zidkijah can ſay,1 King. 22.24. 
                  which way went the spirit of God from mee to speake unto thee? and like a ſpirituall Epicure, can clap himſelfe on the breaſt, with Soule take thy eaſe, thou haſt grace enough layd up for many yeares: from this opinion of ſatiety ariſes a neceſſary careleſneſſe of better indeavors, and a contemptuous undervaluation of the poore ſtock of grace in others; It being commonly incident

into theſe preſuming ſoules, that was of old wont to be ſaid of the Tartars, that they are better invaders of other mens poſſeſſions, than keepers of their owne: thoſe cenſures then, which they ſhould ſpend upon their owne ſecret corruptions, they are ready to caſt upon the ſeeming enormities of their neighbours: And as if they would go contrary to the Apoſtles charge; Be not high minded, but feare; theſe men are high-minded and feare not.
               The way leades to the end, the preſumption of the way, to the preſumption of the end: over-weening and miſpriſion

of grace, to an over-reckoning of an undue ſalvation. Good God, with what confidence have I heard ſome, not over-conſcionable men, talke of the aſſurance of their heaven; as if the way thither were ſo ſhort, and ſo plaine, that they could not miſſe it; as if that paſſage had neither danger nor difficulty; as if it were but a remove from the Lobby to the great Chamber, wherein they can neither erre, nor fall: Here need no harſh exerciſes of mortification, here are no miſdoubts of Gods deſertions, no ſelfe-conflicts, no flaſhes of troubled conſciences, but all faire and ſmooth; Have they ſinned,

the ſcore is croſſed by their ſurety; have they forfeited their ſoules, their ranſome is payd; is juſtice offended, mercy hath ſatisfied: Shortly, they have by Aceſius his ladder climbed up into heaven, and ſtollen the ſight of the Book of life, and found their name there; and who can obliterate it? I cannot forget a bold word, which many yeeres ago, I heard fall from a man whom I conceived not to have had any extraordinary reaſon of confidence; If I ſhould heare God ſay, there ſhall but one man be ſaved, I would ſtrait ſay, That is I, Lord. Surely

the man was in good favour with himſelfe, in what termes ſoever hee ſtood with the Almighty. Not that I condemne an holy and well-grounded reſolution of our ſpirituall eſtate; I know who hath charged us, to give diligence to make our calling and election ſure: Had it not been at all feiſible, our wiſe and good God had not tasked our diligence with it; and, had it been eaſie, and obvious, it might even without diligence of ſtudy and endeavour, have beene effected: Now, as one ſaid of Evangelicall Councels, I muſt ſay of this high pitch of

Chriſtianity;Non eſt omnium vo
                        •
                     are ad alta montana conſiliorum. Gerſ. It is not for every man to mount up this ſteep hill of aſſurance; every ſoule muſt breathe, and pant towards it, as he may; even as wee would and muſt to perfection: hee is as rare as happy, that attaines it. Give mee a man that hath worne out himſelfe with a ſtrict auſterity, who by many ſecret bickerings hath maſtered his ſturdy and rebellious corruptions, who in a trembling awfulneſſe walks conſtantly with his God, keeping a ſevere watch over all his wayes, aſſiduous and fervent in his devotions; Shorly, who hath ſpent his time in

heaven before-hand: why ſhould I not beleeve that God hath ſealed up to ſuch a ſoule, an aſſecurance of his future glory? Some tranſient acts of interpoſed doubting may, and will glance into the holieſt heart; but, a formed habit of doubt falles not into ſuch an eminence of grace: This is not a leſſon for every novice to take out; whoſe maine care muſt ever bee, to work out his ſalvation with feare and trembling. As for ſpirituall ſecurity, let him labour towards it, as that which hee would moſt gladly compaſſe, but

not brag of it too ſoone, as that which he hath already compaſſed.
            
            
               
               SECT. XVI.
               AS there is no diſeaſe incident into the body, for which nature hath not provided a remedy, ſo neither is there any ſpirituall complaint incident into the ſoule, for which grace affords not a redreſſe.
               The way of the generall cure of preſumption is, to take a juſt eſtimate of our priviledges and abilities; and to work the heart to a true ſelfe-dejection, and humiliation,

under the mighty hand of God; Particularly, he can never preſume upon thoſe outward commodities, that ſeriouſly conſiders how they are valued by the owner, and giver of them: Where are the moſt curious and rich Pearles layd up, but in the mud of the ſea? And what is the earth, but marſupium Domini, (as Saint Malacby termd it of old;) Gods purſe wherein he puts his moſt precious jewells, and mettalles; And what baſer peece hath the world, than this repoſitory? And, if it pleaſe him to lay them out; how doth hee think them worthy to be beſtowed;

                  He fills the belly of the ungodly with his hidden treaſure,
                  Iob. 9.24. ſaith the Pſalmiſt; and, The earth is given into the hands of the wicked, ſaith holy Iob in his anſwer to Bildad; neither is it other that he obſerves in his reply to Zophar,
                  Iob. 12.6. 
                  The Tabernacles of the robbers prosper, and they that provoke God, are ſecure, into whoſe hands God bringeth abundantly; How then can we eſteeme thoſe things as pledges of favour, which God makes choyce to caſt upon enemies? which mere naturall men have contemned, as not worthy their affectation, or regard? with

what ſcorne did thoſe naked Brachmanni (the relation is fatherd upon Saint Ambroſe) repell the profered gold? And if at any time it hath pleaſed him, whoſe the earth is, and the fullneſſe thereof, to lade his deere ones with this thick clay, as himſelfe ſtiles it; and, to ſtore them with abundance, he doth it not without a further bleſſing of ſanctification; Some kinds of fiſhes there are that paſſe for delicate, with our great maſters of the palate, which yet, muſt have the dangerous ſtring in their backs puld out, ere they

can bee ſafely fed upon. Such is worldly wealth and proſperity; The wiſe and holy God plucks out their venome, when he will have them ſerv'd up for dainties to his childrens table; Or if he find that the deceitfulneſſe of riches will be apt to beguile good ſoules, he deales with them, as carefull gardiners are wont to do by thoſe trees from which they expect fayre fruit; abate the number of their bloſſomes, as more caring they ſhould be good, than full: Laſtly then, How can we account thoſe arguments of favour, which the

beſt have had leaſt; Even the great Lord of all the world, for whom heaven it ſelfe was too ſtrait, when he would come down and converſe with men, could ſay, The Foxes have holes, and the fowles of heaven have neſts, but the ſon of man hath not where to reſt his head; And when the tribute mony was demanded, is faine to ſend for it, to the next fiſh: Shortly, wore out his few dayes upon earth, in ſo penall a way, that his ſorrowes were read in his face; in ſo much as when he was but two and thirty yeares of age, the by-ſtanders could ſay, Thou art not yet fifty;

What proofes of divine favour then are theſe to preſume upon, which the worſt have, which the beſt want, which God oft-times gives in judgement, denyes in mercy.
            
            
               
               SECT. XVII.
               THere cannot bee a more ſure remedy for preſumtion of abilities, than to take an exact ſurvay of our graces, both of their truth, and degrees. Satan is a great impoſter, hee that was once an Angell of light, knowes how to ſeeme ſo ſtill; when hee left to bee an Angell, hee began to bee a Serpent; and his continuall experience cannot but have added to his Art, ſo

as he knowes how to counterfeit graces, both in himſelfe and his, in ſo exquiſite a faſhion, that it is not for every eye to diſcerne them from true. We ſee to what perfection Mechanicall imitation hath attayned; what precious ſtone hath Nature yeelded, which is not ſo artificially counterfeited, both in the colour and luſtre, that only the skilfull Lapidary can deſcry it; Pearles ſo reſembled, that for whiteneſſe, cleerneſſe, ſmoothneſſe, they dare contend with the true; Gold ſo cunningly multiplyed and tinctured, that neither the eye can diſtinguiſh

it, nor the touch, ſcarce the crucible: So as Art would ſeeme to bee an Havilah, whoſe Gold is good; whiles Nature is an Ophir, whoſe Gold is exceeding good: What marvell is it then, if crafty Spirits can make ſo faire repreſentations of ſpirituall excellencies, as may well deceive ordinary judgements? The Pythoneſſe's Samuel was ſo like the true, that Saul adored him for ſuch; And Iannes and Iambres made their wooden Serpent to crawle ſo nimbly, and hiſſe ſo fiercely, that till Moſes his Serpent devoured theirs, the beholders knew not whether

were more formidable; Some falſe things ſeeme more probable than many truths; there muſt be therefore much ſerious and accurate diſquiſition, ere we can paſſe a true judgement, betwixt apparent and reall graces; Neither would it aske leſſe than a volume to ſtate the differences whereby we may diſcriminate counterfeit vertues from true, in all their ſeverall ſpecialties; they are faced alike, they are clad alike; the markes are inward, and ſcarce diſcernable by any but the owners eyes. In a generality, we ſhall thus deſcry them in our owne

hearts. True grace is right-bred, of a divine originall, and comes down from above, even from the father of lights; Gods ſpirit working with, and by his own ordinances, produceth it in the ſoule, and feeds it by the ſame holy meanes it is wrought: The counterfeit is earth-bred, ariſing from mere nature, out of the grounds of ſenſualialitie. True grace drives at no other end than the glory of the giver, and ſcornes to look lower than heaven: The counterfeit aimes at nothing but vaine applauſe, or carnall advantage, not

caring to reach an inch above his own head.
               True grace is apt to croſſe the plauſibleſt inclinations of corrupt nature, and chears up the heart to a delihgtfull performance of all good duties, as the beſt paſtime. The counterfeit is a meere paraſite of fleſhly appetite, and findes no harſhneſſe, but in holy devotions. True grace is undantedly conſtant in all oppoſition; and like a well wrought vault, is ſo much the ſtronger by how much more weight it undergoes; This metall is purer for the fire, this Eagle can look upon the hotteſt

Sunne: The counterfeit ſhowes moſt gloriouſly in proſperity; but when the evill day commeth, it looks like the ſkinne of a dead Camelion, naſty and deformed. Laſtly, true grace is beſt alone: the counterfeit is all for witneſſes. In briefe, if in a holy jealouſie of our own deceitfulneſſe, wee ſhall put dayly interrogatories to our hearts, and paſſe them under ſevere examinations, we ſhall not bee in danger to preſume upon our miſtaken graces; but the more we ſearch, the more cauſe we ſhall find of our

humiliation, and of an awfull recognition of Gods mercy, and our own unworthineſſe.
            
            
               
               SECT. XVIII.
               THe way not to preſume upon ſalvation, is, in an humble modeſty to content our ſelves with the clearely revealed will of our Maker; not prying into his counſells, but attending his commands: It is a grave word wherein the vulgar tranſlation expreſſes that place of Salomon, Scrutator majeſtatis,
                  Pro. 25.27. 
                  opprimetur à gloria; hee that ſearcheth into majeſty, ſhall bee overwhelmed with glory;

Amongſt thoſe ſixteene places of the Bible, which in the Hebrew are marked with a ſpeciall note of regard; that is one,Deut 29.29. 
                  The ſecret things belong unto the Lord our God, but thoſe things which are revealed, belong unto us and to our children for ever; that wee may do all the words of this Law. Wherein our maine care muſt bee, both not to ſever, in our conceit, the end from the meanes, and withall, to take the meanes along with us, in our way to the end: It is for the heavenly Angels to climbe downe the ladder from heaven to earth: It is for us onely to climbe

up from earth to heaven: Bold men! what do we begin at Gods eternall decree of our election, and thence deſcend to the effects of it in our effectuall calling, in our lively and ſtedfaſt faith, in our ſad and ſerious repentance, in our holy and unblameable obedience, in our unfaileable perſeverance; This courſe is ſaucily prepoſterous; What have wee to do to be rifling the hidden counſells of the Higheſt; Let us look to our owne wayes: Wee have his word for this; that if wee do truly beleeve, repent, obey, perſevere, wee ſhall bee ſaved;

that if wee do heartily deſire, and effectually indeavour, in the carefull uſe of his appointed meanes, to attaine unto theſe ſaving diſpoſitions of the ſoule, wee ſhall bee ſure not to faile of the ſucceſſe: What need wee to look any further, than conſcionably and cheerefully to do what we are enjoyned; and faithfully and comfortably to expect what hee hath promiſed? Let it be our care, not to be wanting in the parts of our duty to God; we are ſure hee cannot be wanting in his gracious performances unto us: But if wee in a groundleſſe conceit of an election ſhall let

looſe the reines to our ſinfull deſires, and vicious practiſes, thereupon growing idle or unprofitable; wee make divine mercy a Pander to our uncleanneſſe, and juſtly periſh in our wicked preſumption.
            
            
               
               SECT. XIX.
               THe other extreame followes: It may ſeeme a harſh word, but it is a true one; that there may bee an evill feare of a good God; A feare of horror, and a feare of diſtruſt. That God, who is love it ſelfe, is terrible to a wicked heart; Even in the beginning, our firſt progenitor ran from the face of his late maker, and hid him in the thickets; For it is a true obſervation of Tertullian, no

wickedneſſe can bee done without feare, becauſe not without the conſcience of doing it. Neither can any man flee from himſelfe, as Bernard wittily: and this conſcience reads the terrible things that God writes againſt the ſinner; and holds the glaſſe, wherein guilty eyes may ſee the killing frownes of the Almighty: Now offenſive objects cauſe the ſpirits to retire, as Philoſophy and experience teacheth us; whereupon followes a neceſſary trepidation in the whole frame of the body: And now the wicked heart could wiſh there were no God; or (which is

all one) that this God had not power to avenge himſelfe; and, finding that after all his impotent volitions, the Almighty will bee ſtill and ever himſelfe; he is unſpeakably affrighted with the expectation of that juſt hand, which hee cannot avoid: This terror, if (through the improvement of Gods mercy) at the laſt it drive the ſinner to a true penitence, makes an happy amends for its owne anguiſh; otherwiſe, it is but the firſt flaſh of that unquenchable fire, which is prepared for damned ſoules. In this caſe men do not ſo much feare

God, as are afraid of him: and ſuch a torturing feare is never but joyned with heart-burning, and hatred: wherin ſinners demeane themſelves to God, as they ſay the Lampray doth to the fiſher, by whoſe firſt blow that fiſh is ſaid to bee dulled, and aſtoniſhed, but inraged with the next, and following: Wretched men! it is not Gods fault that hee is terribly juſt; no, it is his glory, that hee is mercifully terrible.Lib. 7. de Repub Eccleſiaſt. cap. 10. nu. 121. It is not for me to ſay as Spalatenſis cites from Cyrill, that thoſe who would not bee ſaved, are no leſſe beholden to the bounty

of the good God, than thoſe that are brought home to glory: I know and bleſſe God▪ for the difference; But certainely, God is wonderfully gracious (as hee is alſo infinitely juſt) even to thoſe that will needs incurre damnation; having tendered unto them many powerfull helps to their repentance, which hee hath, with much patience, and longanimity expected. That God therefore is juſt, it is his owne praiſe, that hee is terrible, wee may thank our ſelves; for were it not for our wickedneſſe, there were nothing in God, not infinitely

amiable: Seeſt thou then, O ſinnefull man, nothing at all in Gods face, but frownes, and fury; doth every beame of his angry eye dart vengeance into thy ſoule? ſo as thou would'ſt faine runne away from his preſence, and wooeſt the rocks and mountaines to fall upon thee and hide thee from the ſight of that dreadfull countenance; cleanſe thy hands, purge thine heart, cleare thine eyes with the teares of true contrition, and then look up, and tell me, whether thou doſt not ſee an happy change of aſpect, whether thou canſt now diſcerne ought in that

face, but a glorious lovelineſſe, fatherly indulgence, unconceivable mercy, ſuch as ſhall raviſh thy ſoule with a divine love, with a joy unſpeakable and glorious.
            
            
               
               SECT. XX.
               SEldome ever is the feare of horror ſeparated from a feare of diſtruſt; which in the height of it, is that which we call deſpaire: for when the ſoule apprehends a deep feare of Gods dereliction, it cannot but be filled with horrour. Now as the holy and well moderated feare gives glory to God, in all his attributes, ſo this extremity of it affronts and diſhonours him in them all; but eſpecially, in his mercy, and truth. In his truth, ſuggeſting that God will not make good his promiſes; in his mercy,

ſuggeſting that he either cannot, or will not, forgive and ſave; It was a true obſervation of Saint Hilary,
                  Non eſt minimum officium fidei metus. Hilar. in Pſ. 66.
                   that it is not the leaſt office and effect of faith to feare, for that it is ſaid by the Prophet Eſay, He ſhall fill them with the ſpirit of the feare of the Lord: and againe, we are charged to worke out our ſalvation with feare. But there cannot be an act more oppoſite to faith, then to feare diſtruſtfully; to deſpaire in fearing, none more injurious either to God, or our owne ſoules: For ſurely,Non ſuperat bonitatem de
                        •
                      malitia delictorum Cyril in Levit. l. 9.
                   as Cyrill well, the wickedneſſe of our offences to God, cannot exceed his goodneſſe toward us; the praiſe whereof from his

creature he affects and eſteems ſo highly, as if he cared not, in any other notion, to bee apprehended by us: proclaiming himſelfe no otherwiſe in the mount, then, The Lord,
                  Exod. 34.6.7. 
                  the Lord God, mercifull, and gracious, long ſuffering, and abundant in goodneſſe and truth; keeping mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity and tranſgreſsions, and ſinne; adding onely one word, (to prevent our too much preſumption) That will by no meanes cleare the guilty; which to doe, were a meere contradiction to his juſtice: Of all other therefore GOD hates moſt to be robbed of this part of his glory. Neither is the

wrong done to God more palpable, then that which is done herein unto our ſelves; in barring the gates of heaven upon our ſoules; in breaking open the gates of hell to take them in, and in the meane time ſtriving to make our ſelves miſerable, whether God will or no. And ſurely, as our experience tels us concerning the eſtate of our bodily indiſpoſitions, that there is more frequent ſickneſſe in ſummer, but more deadly in winter; ſo we finde it here; other ſinnes, and ſpirituall diſtempers are more common, but this diſtruſtfull feare, and deſpaire of mercy (which chils the ſoule

with a cold horror) is more mortall. For the remedy wherof, it is requiſite that the heart ſhould be throughly convinced of the ſuper-abundant and ever ready mercy of the Almighty, of the infallible and unfaileable truth of all his gracious ingagements; And in reſpect of both, be made to confeſſe, that heaven can never be but open to the penitent. It is a ſweet word and a true one of Saint Bernard,
                  Jn libro tuo ſcribuntur omnes qui quod poſſunt faciunt, et ſi quod debent non poſſunt B
                        •
                     n. Apol ad Guli
                        •
                     lm. Ab
                        ••
                     t. 
                  In thy Booke O Lord, are written all that doe what they can, though they cannot doe what they ought; Neither doth God onely admit, but he invites, but he intreates, but he importunes

men to be ſaved; what could he doe more, unleſſe he would offer violence to the Will, which were no other then to deſtroy it, and ſo to undoe the beſt piece of his owne workmanſhip? It is the way of his decree, and proceedings to diſpoſe of all things ſweetly; Neither is it more againſt our nature, then his, to force his owne ends; and when he ſees that fayre meanes will not prevayle to win us from death, he is pleaſed feelingly to bemone it, as his owne loſſe: Why will ye dye, O houſe of Iſrael? As for the ſtable truth of his promiſes, it is ſo everlaſting, that heaven and earth, in their

vaniſhing, ſhall leave it ſtanding faſt: His title is, Amen, and faithfull is he that hath promiſed, who will alſo doe it: his very eſſence can no more faile, then his word: He that feares therefore that God will be leſſe then his promiſe, let him feare that God will ceaſe to be himſelfe. It was the motto of that witty and learned Doctor Donne, the late Deane of Paules, which I have ſeene, more then once, written in Spaniſh with his owne hand, Bleſſed bee God that hee is God, divinely, like himſelfe: as the being of God is the ground of all his bleſſed adſcriptions, ſo of all our firmitude, ſafety,

conſolation: Since the veracity and truth of God (as his other holy attributes) are no other then his eternall eſſence: Feare not therefore, O thou weake ſoule, that the Almighty can bee wanting to himſelfe, in fayling thee; Hee is Iehovah, and his counſels ſhall ſtand; Feare and blame thine owne wretched infirmities, but the more weake thou art in thy ſelfe, bee ſo much the ſtr
                     •
                  nger in thy GOD; by how much more thou art tempted to diſtruſt, cling ſo much the cloſer to the Author and finiſher of thy ſalvation.
               
                  Thus if wee ſhall hold an even courſe betwixt ſecurity on the one part, and horrour and diſtruſt on the other; If the fortified and exalted eyes of our ſoules, being cleared from all inward and ambient impediments, ſhall have conſtantly fixed themſelves upon the ever-preſent Majeſty of God; not without a ſpirituall lightſomneſſe, and irradiation, and therewith, an awfull complacency of ſoule in that glorious ſight, and from thence ſhall bee caſt downe upon our owne vileneſſe, throughly apprehending how much worſe then nothing we

are, in, and of our ſelves, in the ſight of God, wee ſhall be put into a meet capacity of an holy and well mixed feare: And, if now, our hearts thus enlightened, ſhall be taken up with an inward adoration of the infinite power and greatneſſe of GOD, manifeſted in the framing and ordering of this viſible world, and of the infinite goodneſſe and mercy of GOD, ſhewed in the marvellous worke of mans redemption, and ſhall be carefull to expreſſe this inward worſhip in all due reverence, (upon all occaſions) to the Name, the Word, the Services, the Houſe, the Meſſengers

of the Almighty; withall, if our humble ſoules ſhall meekly ſubject, and reſigne themſelves over to the good pleaſure of God, in all things, being ready to receive his fatherly corrections with patience, and his gracious directions with obedience. Laſtly, if wee ſhall have ſettled in our hearts a ſerious care of being alwayes approved to God in whatſoever actions; and a child-like loathneſſe, and dread to give any offence unto ſo deare and glorious a Majeſty, wee ſhall have attained unto this bleſſed feare, which wee ſeeke for, and be happily freed from that wicked

indevotion, and prophaneneſſe, to which the world is ſo much, and ſo dangerouſly ſubject: which I beſeech the God of heaven to worke out in all readers, to his glory in their ſalvation, Amen.
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

