
   
      
         
            Certaine irrefragable propositions worthy of serious consideration. By I.H. B. of Exon
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1639
            
         
         Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02518
            STC 12646B
            ESTC S103639
            99839388
            99839388
            3802
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02518)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3802)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1069:26)
         
         
            
               
                  Certaine irrefragable propositions worthy of serious consideration. By I.H. B. of Exon
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [6], 7, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by M[iles] F[lesher] for Nath: Butter,
                  London :
                  MDCXXXIX. [1639]
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Jos: Exon, i.e. Joseph Hall.
                  Concerns oaths and covenants.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.
               Oaths --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-04
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2005-04
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Certaine IRREFRAGABLE PROPOSITIONS WORTHY OF Serious Consideration.
            By J. H. B. of Exon.
            LONDON, Printed by M.F. for NATH: BUTTER. MDCXXXIX.
         
         
            
            
            TO MY DREAD SOVERAIGN, THE KINGS MOST Excellent MAIESTIE.
            
               
                  
                     May it please your Matie,
                     
                  
                  
                     AS one, whose heart (amongst many thousands) bleeds with the sad thoughts of the wofull Divisions of our deare Fellow-Subjects; and unfainedly pitties the mis-guidance of those poore well-meaning soules amongst them, whose credulity hath heedlesly betray'd them into a zealous errour; I have let fall

these few Propositions; which I have presumed to set downe, not as in the way of a Challenger; for, most (if not all) of them are such, as be not capable of Contradiction, but rather of a faithfull Remembrancer to my dear Brethren, of those Points which they cannot but know, and yeeld: as well supposing, that nothing but meer want of consideration can be guilty of this perillous distraction, in them, who professe to love their King, and the Truth.
                  Now the good God of heaven open the eyes and hearts of us all, that we may both see, and be sensible of the invaluable blessing of our peace, and the happy freedome of his Gospel, which we doe comfortably enjoy under Your MAIESTIES sweet and religious Government, to the wonder, and

envie of all other Nations; and compose the hearts of all your Native Subjects to meet Your MAIESTIES most gracious indulgence, with all humble thankefulnesse.
                  And the same God forbid that any of us should be weary of our happiness: and be drawne to doe any act that may (before all the world) poure shame upon our holy profession; whose chiefe glory it hath alwayes hitherto beene to render us still loyall and obedient, and in this very regard, to triumph over the false religion of our opposites. Such shall be ever the prayers of
                  
                     
                        Your Maties
                         most humble, and faithfull Subject, and ancientest Chaplain, JOS: EXON.
                  
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Seaven irrefragable Propositions concerning Oaths and Covenants.
            
               1.
               
                  NO man may sweare, or induce another man to swear unlawfully.
               
            
            
               2.
               IT is no lawfull Oath that is not attended with Truth, Justice, and Judgement, Jer. 4.2. the first vvhereof requires that the thing svvorn be true: the second, that it be just: the third, that it be not undue, and unmeet

meet to be svvorn and undertaken.
            
            
               3.
               A Promissory Oath vvhich is to the certaine prejudice of another mans right, cannot be attended vvith Justice.
               
            
            
               4.
               NO prejudice of another mans right can be so dangerous and sinfull, as that prejudice vvhich is done to the right of publique and Soveraign Authority.
               
            
            
               5.
               THe right of Soveraign Authority is highly prejudiced, vvhen private subjects incroach upon it; and shall, upon suspicion of the disavowed

vovved intentions, or actions of their Princes, combine, and binde themselves to enact, establish, or alter any matters concerning Religion, vvithout (and therefore much more if against) the authority of their Lawfull Soveraign.
               
            
            
               6.
               A Man is bound in Conscience to reverse and disclaime that vvhich he vvas induced unlawfully to ingage himselfe by Oath to performe.
               
            
            
               7.
               NO oath is, or can be of force, that is made against a lawfull oath formerly taken; so as he that hath svvorne Allegeance to his Soveraign,
                  
and thereby bound himselfe to maintain the right, povver, and authority of his said Soveraign, cannot by any second oath, be tyed to doe ought that may tend to the infringement thereof: and if he have so tyed himselfe, the Obligation is, ipso facto, void and frustrate.
            
         
         
            
            COROLLARIE.
            IF therefore any sworne Subject shall by pretences and persvvasions, be dravvne to binde himselfe by Oath or Covenant, to determine, establish, or alter any act concerning matter of Religion, vvithout, or against the allowance of Soveraign Authority, the act is unlavvfull and unjust, and the party so ingaged is bound in conscience to reverse and renounce his said act: Othervvise (besides the horrible scandall vvhich hee shall dravv upon Religion) he doth manifestly incur the sinne of the breach of the third and fift Commandements.
         
         
            
            Two, as undoubted Propositions, concerning Church-government.
            
               1.
               NO man living, no History, can shevv any vvel-allovved and setled nationall Church in the vvhole Christian World, that hath beene governed othervvise then by Bishops, in a meet &amp; moderate imparity, ever since the times of Christ and his Apostles, untill this present Age.
            
            
               2.
               NO man living, no record of History can shevv any Lay-Presbyter that ever vvas in the whole Christian Church, untill this present Age.
            
         
         
            
            COROLLARIE.
            IF men would as easily learne as Christian wisdome can teach them, to distinguish betwixt callings and persons, betwixt the substance of callings, and the not-necessary appendances of them, betwixt the rules of Government, and the errors of Execution, these ill-raised quarrels vvould dye alone.
            
               Da pacem Domine,
               F.E.
            
         
      
   

