
   
      
         
            The actes of Englysh votaryes comprehendynge their vnchast practyses and examples by all ages, from the worldes begynnynge to thys present yeare, collected out of their owne legendes and chronycles by Iohan Bale. ...
            Acts of English votaries. Part 1
            Bale, John, 1495-1563.
         
         
            
               1546
            
         
         Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02573
            STC 1270
            ESTC S100591
            99836426
            99836426
            698
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02573)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 698)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 22:3)
         
         
            
               
                  The actes of Englysh votaryes comprehendynge their vnchast practyses and examples by all ages, from the worldes begynnynge to thys present yeare, collected out of their owne legendes and chronycles by Iohan Bale. ...
                  Acts of English votaries. Part 1
                  Bale, John, 1495-1563.
               
               79, [1] leaves   
               
                  By S. Mierdman],
                  [Printed at Wesel [i.e. Antwerp :
                  in the yeare of our Lorde God. 1.5.4.6]
               
               
                  Imprint from colophon.
                  The imprint is false; actual printer's name and address from STC.
                  The printing has been erroneously attributed to John Day and to Richard Jugge.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
               Catholic Church --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2006-10
            AptaraRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2008-12
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2008-12
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            The Actes of
Englysh votaryes, comprehendynge
their vnchast practyses and examples
by all ages, from the worldes
begynnynge to thys present yeare,
collected out of their owne legendes
and Chronycles
By Iohan Bale.
            ¶Lerne herin (good reader) to proue
all spretes, and to iudge false myracles,
rebukynge no Christen beleuer, but those
obstynate hypocrytes onlye, whyche yet
lyue after their popes olde rules.
Reade, but laugh not.
            O thu mayden of Chaldea, Thu shalt
no more be called tender and plesaunt.
Thy shame shall be dyscouered, aud
thy preuytees shall be seane, for
I (sayth the lorde) wyll auenge
me of the, and no man
shall let me.
            Esa▪ 47.
         
         
            
            
            
               ❧ The preface of thys boke.
            GIldas that auncyent
Brytayne, in
hys first treatyse of
the dolorouse destruccyon
of hys coutreye,
hath thys worthye sentence agaynste them
whych were the chefe
cause therof▪ And borowed yt ys of the .xxiiii.
chaptre of Salomons prouerbes.
Who so euer cōmēdeth the wycked (sayth
he) and reporteth them ryghtuouse or holye,
the same shall ones haue the curse of
the people, and the commynalte shall ab
horre hym. Plentuouse hath the Popes
clergye bene in thys poynt, specyallye in
the churche here of Englande. Not onlye
haue they commended vnto vs whoremō
               gers,
bawdes, brybers, Idolaters, hypocrytes,
trayters, and most fylthye Gomorreanes,
as Godlye men and womē,
but also they haue canonysed thē for most
holye sayntes, sett them vp gylt Images
in their temples, commāded their vygyls
to be fasted, appoynted them holye dayes
and the peoples to do them honoure with
euēsonges, howres, processyons, lyghtes,
masses, ryngynges, syngynges, sensynges,
and the deuyll and all of soche heythnysh
wares. They haue done by vs as

their olde predecessours the Idolatrouse
prestes ded by the auncyeut Romanes.
They haue set vs vp a sort of lecherouse
Goddes to be worshypped in our temples,
to be our aduocates, and to helpe vs
in our nedes.Olde goddes &amp;c. newe. In stede of Iupiter, Saturne,
Mercurye, Mars, Iuno, Proserpina,
Diana, and Venus, which ded all their
feates in whoredome, as the poetes verefyethe,
they haue geuen vs Wenefryde,
Cuthbert, Dunstane, Oswalde, Anselme,
Becket, Brigyde, Audrye, Modwē,
Edith, Osith, Ethelburge, and a great
sort more of vnpure workers out of marryage.
            Marke the lyues of their Englyshe
sayntes, almost from the begynnynge, &amp;
ye shall not fynde one of them canonysed
for preachynge Christes veryte a ryght,
neyther yet for leadynge a lyfe after the
perfyght rules of the Gospell. Not one
commende they for worshyppynge God
wythout mennys tradycyons, nor yet for
executyuge the workes of Mercye, vnles
se yt were to their aduauntage. Neuer
reckened they wedlock anye Godlye estate
of lyuyuge, though yt were an onlye
ordre inſtytuted of God in the begyunynge,
yea, for hys prestes also. Commōlye
they haue dyswaded both men and women
from yt, as from a most pernycyouse
euyll,Dyffa▪ /  or from a myschefe of all myschefes,

callynge yt folyshnesse, fylthynesse,
beastlynesse,macyōs of Marryage. a walkynge in darkenesse, a
mayntenaūce of lechery, a fulfyllyng of
fleshlye desyres, a grounde of all vyce, an
entraunce of deathe, a corruptynge of
maydenhode, a lake of myserye, a claye
pytt of vnclēnesse, a thraldome of Egipt,
a nette of Sathan, a snare of the deuyll,
&amp; a ponde of perdycyon, loke Iohan Capgraue in Catalogo sanctorum Anglie, specyallye
in the lyues or legendes of Clarus,
Eanswyde, kyneswyde, Etheldrede, we
nefrede, Mylburge, and Myldrede with
soche other lyke, aud ye shall fynde my
wordes most true. In the hystorye of
Saynt Vrsula haue they named thē Angels
of darkenesse whych hath persuaded
marryage laufull.blasphemye. Of whose nōbre was
firste God the eternall Father, and thā
Moses and the Prophetes for the olde lawe.
And afterwarde Iesus Christe hys
eternall Sonne, with Peter, Paule &amp; the
other apostles for the newe lawe. Were
not the men (thynke yow) wele ouerseane?
            So peruerse stomakes haue they borne
to women, that the more part of their
temptynge spretes they haue made she
deuyls (loke their Sayntes legendes) but
he that tempted Christ was an he deuyll,
a relygyouse deuyll, and a prestlye deuyll.
Whā they haue bene tempted with

lecherouse spretes in the lykenesse of wō
               men,The deuyls.
they haue (they saye) by the suffren
vertu of holye water, turned them into
denyls agayne. But neuer were they yet
so comiyuge with all their holy water,
as to make of theyr whores honest marryed
women. No▪ yt is not their ordre, to
do soche myracles In the lyfe of Saynt
Godrick is mencyon of a ſhe deuyll, but
in the conclusyon, he apereth with hangynge
ware of no small quantyte, hauynge hys yonge ones folowynge hym with
shauē crownes. Of a lykelyhode therfor
he was some spyrytuall he tempter, and
hys chyldren within holye orders. Soche
power had Saynt Guthlake ouer those
watchynge wormes, that he made them
to tarrye with hym, and to buylde hym
vp a monasterye at Asendyck, now called
Crowlāde, some saye. To be short in
thys matter.Sayntes vnmaryed Their sayntes in a maner
were all vnmaryed. If anye were maryed
that wolde nedes be sayntes, they were
anō compelled by othe, or by the waye
of penaunce, to leaue their makes to the
occupyenge of others, the man hys wyfe,
and the woman her husbande, as ye shall
beholde in this boke by most plentuouse
examples. For matrimonye hath euer
bene suche a blacke bugge in their synagoge
ād churche, that neuer wolde
canonysacyon serue yet, where he was

in place.
            Notwithstandinge we are throughly assertayned
by innumerable scripturs and
argumentes, that matrymonye is of
God, ād by their innumerable examples
of fylthynesse, that their vowed wyuelesse
and husbandelesse chastyte is altogyther
of the deuyll.Votaryes. Sens the gloryouse aperaunce
of the Gospell haue that Sodo
mytycall swarme or brode of Antichrist
(that ye call the spirytualte) bene oft tymes
admonyshed of their fleshlye errours
by the manyfest scripturs therof,
that they shuld ones repent their most
horryble myschefes, and graunt vnto maryage
the fredome due therunto. And
what haue they done, thynke you? Nothynge
els at all but laughed them to
scorne, reportynge them to be but fables
and lyes. The lerned allegacyons, reasons,
&amp; argumentes of Phylyp Melāchton,Christē doctors.
Luther, Lambert, Pomerane, Barnes,
and soche other, they haue hearde,
but the answere is yet to make. They
mocke and mowe at thē lyke Iack a napes,
or lyke them which went vp &amp; downe
by the crosse whan Christ was crucyfyed,
and that is ynough for them. For
they haue yt of theyr popes lawe to answere
no man, yea although they wryte
theyr abhomynacyons to the vttermost,

vnlesse they haue hym in preson. I haue
therfor thought yt best,The antour. seynge they regarde
not the sacred scrypturs, to laye
before them their abhomynable practyses
and examples of fylthynesse, by their
owne legendes, chronycles, and sayntes
Lyues, that all men maye knowe what
legerdemaynes they haue vsed, and what
lecherouse lyues they haue led here in Englande
sens the worldes begynnynge. Lete
them now be ashamed of their beastlynesse,
or els put on their mothers face altogyther.
            In the firste part of thys boke, maye
men breuelye beholde how and by whom
thys realme was first inhabyted, whiche
thynge hath bene hytherto in all Englysh
Chronycles,Chronycles. doubtfullye, vnagreablye,
yea, and vntrulye treated, vpon coniecturs,
fantasyes, and lyes onlye, by reason
of ignoraunce in the scripturs and moste
auctorysed hystoryes. They shall also perceyue,
what peoples haue here by all
ages remayned, what doctryues, hath bene
taught by their true and false prophetes,
what worshyppynges of God they
haue vsed, and what lawes in relygyon
they haue folowed. Fynallye they shall
knowe clerelye, the deceytfull workemā
               shyp
of the instrumētes of Sathan, their
byshoppes,prestes. prestes, &amp; monkes, with other
dysgysed locustes of the same generacyō.

Whose contynuall stodye, labour, and sekynge
was alwayes to blynde them by a
colour of chast lyuynge,Maryage. makynge them
to beleue, that their marryenge of wyues
was a prophane layte, a brutysh beastlynesse,
and a thynge which greatlye dyspleased
God. Their owne vowynge of
vyrgynyte was agayne (they sayd) a spirytuall
ordre,Vyrgynyte. a lyfe of Angels, and an holye
relygyon which pleased God aboue
all other, what though they neuer had yt
in their lyues. For true vyrginyte ys a
fayth vncorrupted,Faythe or a beleue gouerned
by the onlye worde of God without all
superstycyons of men. Thys was the
onlye vyrgynyte that Marye was commended
of, Luce. 1. Thys vyrgynyte perteyneth
chefelye to marryage, as testyfyethe
Saynt Paul. 2. Cor. 11.2. Cor.
                     ••
                  . And as apereth in Abraham and other iust fathers
which had faythfull wyues. No people
are lesse acquaynted with thys vprgyuyte
than sectaryes, or they that vowe vprgynyte,
for they thefelye depende vpon
mennys tradycyons and rules.
            But yf a tre maye be knowne by hys
frutes, and a man by hys dedes, as our
sauer sayth they maye, Math. 7. ye shall
easelye perceyue by their actes,Mat. 7. that these
vyrgyuall votaryes hath bene the verye
Angels of darkenesse. Marke their gostlye
conueyauuces, and their other good

workes (as they wyll haue them yet called)
lyke as they are here regestred in
course. And ye shall fynde them more fyt
for hell than for heauen. Yet must they
be canonysed sayntes, and do most wonderfull
myracles.Myracles. But those myracles are
the stronge delusyons (saynt Paule
sayth) that the lorde wyll sende vnto thē
that shall perysh for their vnbeleues sake.
2. Thessalon 2. I doubt not but thys labour
of myne, though yt be verye symple,
wyll mynystre some lyght as wele
to the lerned as vnlerned. At the least yt
shall teche thē to iudge false myracles,
that they be no more so deuylyshly deceyued.
Lete not the oft cytynge of authors
be greuouse to the readers, my occasyon
iustlye cōsidered.Autours. For therby shall the papystes
haue shame alwayes, yf they report
them fables, or els me a lyar for the
tellynge of them, beynge in their wrytynges
so manyfest. And as conceruyuge
those autours, they were their owne
dere fryndes, and wrote the best they coude
of them. If they had bene their enemyes,
and so shewed the worst of them, or
els but indyfferent wryters as they were
most parcyall wytuesses, it had bene
a farre other shewe of their mischefes
than here will apere.
            Men trusted they wolde haue seane
themselues in this clere lyght of the Gospell,

and so haue repented their former
factes of falsehede.Byshoppes But trulye they are
of a farre other kynde than so. Their
nature is not to repent, do they neuer so
manye myschefes. Rather stodye they
out newe practyses of tyrannye and cautels
of cruelte, to adde myschefe to myschefe,
tyll the great vengeaunce promysed,
lyght fullye vpon them. Who so
euer hath promoted forewarde Gods veryte
(they thanke God of yt) they haue
bene non of them as yet.Gospel If they shuld
make their boastes with Paule. 1. Corin.
15. that they haue done therin more labours
than the other discyples, men of
knowlege wolde by and by saye, that
they lyed most falselye. In dede they haue
with Menelaus, Alchinius, Ananias,
&amp; wyth Capphas gone afore all worldlye
tyrauntes in the murtheringe vp
of them which hath done yt. And for errours,Errour
they saye. But who euer erred
as they haue done, sens the worldes begynnynge?
Trulye non as yet. Neyther,
Turke, Iewe, Saracene, Pagane, nor
deuyll, as the examples herafter wyll
shewe, they shall not be able to auoyde
yt, vnlesse they dyspute with fyer ād faggottes
as they haue done hytherto. For
starke nought are they in dysputacyons,
where as they are not at hāde. For this
boke, I shall haue theyr cōmō lyuerye,

and be called a thousande tymes heretyke.
But neyther loke I for reasonable answere
of them, nor yet for amendement of
theyr knaueryes.
            In this boke of myne,Face of Antichrist. is one face of Antichrist
chefelye dysclosed (parauenture
iij. vndre one) wherwith he hath of longe
tyme paynted out his whore, the Rome
churche, that she myght to the world apere
a gloryouse madame. That face is her
vowed chastyte, wherby she hath deceytfullye
boasted herself spirituall, beynge
but whore and thefe,Marryage maketh laye. and dysdayned marryage as a vyle draffe sacke and dyrtye
dyshe cloute, callynge all them but lewde
laye persones that were vndre yt, though
they were kynges and quenes, lordes ād
ladyes. Ye noble gouerners and lerned
lawers, vnto whom God hath in thys age
delyuered the measurynge rodde of
hys worde, as he ded to Iohan. Apocal. 11.
that ye shuld measure all thynges ryghtlye.
Be not now slacke in your offyces, as
in the blynd tyme, but throwe fourth that
wretched bonde woman with her doughter,
that Rome churche with her whoryshnesse. No poynt of nobylyte were yt,Nobylyte. nor
yet of lerned worthynesse, to be as ye haue
bene of late yeares. styll seruaunt slaues
to a most fylthye whore, and to her
whoredome and whoremongers. Our
most christen Emprour of Englande, kinge

Hērye the.Kynge Henry. viî. of that name, as a most
worthye mynystre of God, hath goue before
yow in that behalfe. He hath made
open vnto ye the waye, and dryuē awaye
from your gates the great aduersarye
that shuld most haue noyed yow. Dysdayne not than yow to folowe, Take from
your true subiectes, the popes false Christ
with hys belles and bablynges,Christ. with hys
myters and mastryes, wyth hys fannoms
and fopperyes, and lete them haue frelye
the true Christ agayne that their heauenlye
father sent them from aboue fashyoned
out vnto thē in the Gospell. For moche
more bewtifull is he in the syght of
true beleuers, thā are all the corrupt chyldren
of men, with all theyr gorgyouse
aparelynges. Loke you thervnto
with ernestnesse,
for nothinge will
be at the lattre
daymore
strayghtlye requyred
of you
thā that.
            ⸫
         
      
      
         
            
            The Actes of
Englysh votaryes, comprehendynge
their vnchast practyses and examples
by all ages, from the worldes
begynnynge to thys present yeare,
collected out of their owne legendes
and Chronycles
By Iohan Bale.
            
               ¶Marryage instytuted of God.
               
                  IN paradyse our eternall
and mercyfull father
instytuted maryage,Matrymonye. inmedyatlye
after mannys first
creacyon, and left yt with
hym as an honest, comelye, wholsom, holye,
and nedefull remedye agaynst all beastlye
abusyons of the fleshe that shuld
after happē, and graunted therunto hys
eternall blessynge. Increase (sayth he)
multyplye, and fyll the earthe, Gene. 1.
And thys repeted he thryse after that▪
                  Gene. 8. ct. 9. to the intent yt myght be
groundedlye marked, and wele knowne
of men to be hys most ernest ordynaunce.the first relygyō
                  
Thys was the first ordre of Relygyō
that euer was made, and of must holynesse,
yf we dewlye respect the maker
therof with the other cyrcumstaunces besydes,
preferrynge hys wysdome to mā
                  nys

wysdome. And for that yt shuld not
be reckened a thynge vnaduysedlye done
of hym, he loked thervpon agayne amonge
all hys other workes, and coude beholde
no imperfeccyon therin, but perceyued
that yt was of excedynge goodnesse.
Yet hath there sens rysen a sort, whiche
haue agaynst Gods heauenlye wysdome,Vnmaryed prestes.
set their fleshlye folyshnesse, whiche
are non other to be reckeued than the
verye sede and of sprynge of the serpēt.
Thoughe these haue knowne that there
is a God, yet haue they not gloryfyed
hym in faythe and mekenesse, but haue
become most vayue in their ymagynacyons.
Where as he hath declared marryage
excedynglye good,Gods aduersaryes. they haue condempned
it as a thynge execrable and wicked.
And where as he hath spoken yt by hys
owne mouthe, that yt is not good for mā
to be alone, they haue improued that doctryne
and taught the cōtrarye, as a thynge
more perfyght and Godlye. 
            
            
               ¶Marryage contempned of Sathan.
               THus Sathan erected hymself agaynst
God in that wycked generacyon, whiche beganne first in
Cain,Cain. and hath euer sens contynued in
that posteryte. For thys presumpcyon
God gaue them clerelye ouer, and left
them to themselues with all their good

intentes and vowes, wherupon they haue
wrought sens that tyme fylthynesse
vnspekeable. Their chast women, vestals
Monyals,Nōnes and Mō
                     kes. Nonnes, and Begynes, changynge
the naturall vse, haue wrougth vnnaturallye.
Lyke wyse the men in their
Prelacyes, presthodes, and innumerable
kyndes of Monkerye, for want of women
hath brent in their lustes, and done
abhomynacyons without nombre, so receyuynge
in themselues the iust rewarde
of their errour. Of these most hellyshe &amp;
dyabolyck trutes, holy Saynt Paule
admonyshed the Romanes, in the firste
chaptre of hys Epystle vnto them, knowynge
afore hande that out of their corrupted
christy anyte,Sodomytes. shulde ryse soche a
fylthye flocke as shuld worke them euerye
where. But neyther of Paule nor yet
of Peter haue the fore warnynges away
led, but those brockysh boores haue gone
frely forewarde without checke tyll now
of late dayes, where in God hath geuen
vs as more pure syght to beholde their buskelynges.
            
            
               ¶Marryage of Prestes in both
lawes.
               TO make manyfest vnto thē, what
wyues the lorde appoynted by
hys seruaunt Moses,Prestes wyues. vnto the leuytycall
prestes in the sacred posteryte
of Aaron Leuit. zi. et Ezech. 44. yt were

but labour lost.Prestes wyues. Eyther to put them in
remembraunce that Christ was borne in
marryage, though hys mother were alwayes
a mayde, ād that he left vnto hys
Apostles marryage in lyberte euermore
yt were in veyne also. For all thys hath
God shewed vnto them playnelye, by
hys true prophetes in thys lattre age,
declarynge the fynall destruecyō of that
wretched kyngedome. As by Martyn
Luther,Haters of the Pope. Iohan Pomerane, Frances lambert,
Oswaldus Myconius, Philpp Melanchtō,
&amp; soche other (as ys sayd afore)
but all haue they taken for fables. That
lorde sent them one vnto their owne doores,
which effectuallye ded hys massage,
euen Robert Barnes by name,
                     
                        •
                     arnes. of whose
grounded argumentes they haue not yet
dyscharged the leaste, besydes that they
haue had from hym by good Wyllyam
Turner and George Ioye. And all thys
haue they dysdaynouslye laughed to scorne.
Consyderynge therfore that no gētyll
speche wyll amende them, nor yet sharpe
threttenynges call them to repentaunce,The autour.
he wyll now cast their owne vyle donge
in their faces, that yt shall cleaue
fast vpon them, Mala. 2. He wyll throwe
in their tethe by thys boke and soch other
the styukynge examples of their hypocrytysh
lyues, with their calkynges and
cloynynges to patche vp that dauberye

of the deuyll, their vowed wyuelesse and
husbandelesse chastyte.
            
            
               ¶Englande inhabyted afore Noe
and after.
               ANd for as moche as the tyttle of
thys present treatyse only respecteth
Englande,Englā
                     de. onlye shall yt treate
the vnchast examples of the spirytualte
therof, with serten examples of Romysh
Popes whiche than wrought their
iuggelynge mastryes there. To fetche
the matter from the first foundacyon, &amp;
so to stretche yt forewarde, I am fullye
assertayned by auncyēt writynges, that
thys lande was with people replenyshed
longe afore Noes dayes.Afore Noe. Yea, soche tyme
as men were multyplyed vpon the vnyuersall
earthe, Gene. 6. As they than had
left God appoynted Relygyō, and had
taken wayes vnto them after their owne
good intentes, soche vnspekable fylthynesse
folowed, as brought vpon them the
great dylu
                     •
                  ye or vnyuersall flod, which
left non alyue,The flood. but drowned them vp as
yt ded all other quarters. Thys wytnesseth
both Moses and Berosus, the most auncyēt
writers we reade of. After the seyd
flood, was yt agayne inhabyted by the
of sprynge of Iapheth the third sonne of
Nor.Iapheth For of thē (sayth Moses) were the
Iles of the Gentyles sorted oute into regyons,
euerye one after, knowne dyuerse

from other, by their languages, kynde
redes, &amp; nacyons, Gene. 10. And in the dayes
of Phaleg the sonne of Heber,Phaleg was
that dyuysyon of Prouynces, lyke as foloweth
in the same chapter. Samothes the
Brother of Gomer (whō the Byble calleth
Mesech) restored than agayne thys
lande in hys posteryte,Samothes gygas. the prestes therof
called Samothei, for so moch as he was the
first that fournyshed yt with lawes, as
witnesseth Ioannes Annius in commentarijs
Berosi.
               
            
            
               ¶Albion with hys Samothytes.
               AFter thys grewe yt into a name, &amp;
was called Albion.Albion gigas. Not ab albis rupibus,
as fryre Bartylmew hath
fantasyed in hys worke De proprietatibus
rerū. Nor yet ab Albiana the kynges dougter
of Syria, as Marianus the monke hath
dreamed yt. For of latyne wordes coude
yt haue no name, before the latyne yt selfe
was in vse. And the other without grounded
autoryte, apereth a playne fable,
as witnesseth both Volateranus and Badius
But rather yt shuld seme to be called Albion,
ab Albione Gygante, the sonne of Neptunus,
                  Neptunus.
whiche was afterwarde slayne of
Hercules for stoppynge hys passage at
the enteraunce of Rhodanus, as testyfyeth
Diodorus Siculus and also Pomponius
Mcla. Not onlye bycause the seyd

Albion was a gyaunt, lyke as the afore
seyd Samothes was afore hym, but also for
that hys father Neptunus was than take
for the lorde of great God of the see,
wherin yt is enclosed. What the chastyte
was of the Samothytes or prestes for
that age,Samothytes. the Poetes dothe declare at large.
Venus was than their great Goddesse,
and ruled all in that spirytuall famelye,
as she hath done euer sens.
            
            
               ¶The Samothytes and their
chastyte.
               THey had in their temples, vestals
(whom now we call Nōnes) who
se offyce was to maynteyne the fyre
for perfourmaunce of the sacryfyces,
least yt shuld at anye tyme go out.vestals. These
were chosen in before they were .xvi.
years olde, there remaynyng vnmaryed
the space of .xxx. years, and others alwayes
by that tyme succeded in their rowmes.
Some of these were presbyteresses,
as they pleased the spyrituall fathers.
And as the lyghtes went out by their neglygence,
their ponnyshmentes were to
be beaten of the Byshoppes. More ouer
yf anye of thē chaunced to fall in aduoutery,
except they ded yt in the darke with
them,chastyte their iudgement was to be buryed
in the grounde quycke. Alwayes they
went awaye vyrgynes from them (what
so euer was done in the meane season) &amp;

at the .xxx. years ende, they were in lyberte
to marrye yf they wolde. Thys testyfyeth
Hermanus Torrentinus, and Iohannes
Textor,
                  Tyrāny now. with other autours. Yet was not
thys abhomynable superstyeyon so tyrannouslye
handeled amonge them than, as
yt hath bene sens a monge their successours
the papystes, whom by their cruell
conceyons (syned they neuer so longe)
they sent at the last to hell with a conscyence
adust, were not the lorde more mercyfull.
            
            
               ¶Brute with hys Druydes.
               IN processe of tyme, gote Brutus Syluius
                  brutus syluius.
thys lande of the Albyons by
conquest, in the .xviij. yeare of Heli
the hygh prest of the Israelytes, lyke as
Aeneas ded Italye, and other great aduē
                  tourers
their regyons. And of hym was
yt called Brytayne, and the people therof
Brytaynes. After he had fournyshed yt
with newe regymentes and lawes,
there entered in a newe fashyoned sort
of prestes, all dyuerse from the other, and
they were called Druydes.Druydes. These dwelt
in the forestes lyke heremytes and procureth
both publyque and pryuate sacryfyces
to be done. To them was yt alwayes
put, to dys usse all matters of relygyon,
to appoynt therunto the ceremonyes,
to brynge vp youthe in naturall

dyscyplyne, &amp; to ende all controuersyes▪
                  Plinius, Strabo, Cornelius Tacitus, Caius Iulius,
and other approued autours, report thē
to haue their first orygynall in thys lande,
but that apereth not true. Rather
shuld they seme to come first hyther frō
Athens,Athens a most famouse cytie of the Grekes.
Iohan Hardynge reporteth in hys
Chronycle, that kynge Bladud brought
them first frome thens, allegynge there
Merlyne for hys autour.
            
            
               ¶The Druydes and their
chastyte.
               VVhat their rule was conceruynge
women, we shall not nede to
seke farder than to the .vi. chaptre
of Baruch, and the .xiiij. chaptre of
Daniel in the Byble.whores 
                  Baruch sayth there,
that their custome was to decke their
whores with the Iewels and ornamentes
of their Idolles. Daniel sayth, that
they with them deuoured vp the daylye
offerynges and sacryfyces of Bel. Yet
Hector Boethius writeth in the seconde boke
of hys Scottysh Chronycle, that there
were some amonge them,one god whiche taught
one euerlastynge God alone to be worshypped,
without Image made or other
symylytude els. Neyther allowed they
them (sayth he) that applyed vnto their
Goddes the symylytudes of beastes after

the Egyptyanes maner (as the Papystes
do yet to thys daye Saynt Marke
to a Lyon,beastes worshypped Saynt Luke to a calfe, and
Saynt Iohan to an egle, besyde Saynt
Antonyes pygge, Saynt Georges colte,
and Saynte Dunstanes deuyll) but
greatlye reproued them. Neuerthelesse
yet were they great teachers of sorcerye.
For as testyfyeth Iohan Textor in hys
offycynes, so expert were the Brytaynes
in art magyck in the dayes of plynye,
that in a maner they passed the Parthyanes,
whiche were the first masters
therof.
            
            
               ¶Prestes marryed and vnmarryed.
               NOw as concernynge the prestes
of the Hebrues or Israelytes for
all these ages (whiche were the
peculyar flocke of God) they had all
wyues that were ryghtuouse amonge
them,Prestes maryed accordynge to the Relygyon that
he first appoynted them. Not, Melchisedech,
Abraham, Moyses, Aaron, Phinees,
Samuel, Nathan, Zorobabel, Iesus,
Esdras, Mathathias, &amp; soche other,
were all marryed men and had chyldrē.
The Scripturs report that these men
were beloued with God, and that' in holynesse
non were euer founde lyke vnto
them. But neyther was that for their
vowes nor yet for their good intentes,

                  Eccli. 44. and so fourth .vi. chapters more.
If anye were chast vowers that tyme
the .ij.Votaryes. prestes that lusted after Susanna,
were of them, Daniel. 13. So were the wā
                  ton
sonnes of Heli and Samuel, 1. Reg. 2.
&amp; 1. Reg. 8. with soche other lyke. Which
were afore God verye reprobates, for
despysynge hys ordre, as wele in that as
in other thynges. Of soche chast vowers
were there some, at the verye tyme whā
Christ was borne, both relygyouse prestes
and leuytes, which were most hygh
lye taken amonge them. These thynkynge
marryage vnholye, abstayned from
the vse of women, but they spared not to
worke execrable fylthynesse amonge thē
selues,Zacharye marryed. and one to polute an other. Zacharye
a marryed prest, and father of holye
Iohan Baptyst, a man for hys marryage
founde iust afore God, reprehended
that abhomynacyon in them, &amp; was
cruellye ſlayne for yt, as testyfyeth Epiphanius
li. 1. To. 2. De heresibus. He was put
vnto deathe (sayth Philip Melanchton
vpon the .xi. chaptre of Daniel) for rebukynge
the vyces of hys college.
            
            
               ¶Christ alloweth marryage in hys.
               IEsus Christ the eternall sonne of
God, neuer contempned the firste
ordynaunce of hys euerlastynge
father, but had yt insuche reuerence, that
he wolde not be borne but vndre yt. He

found his worthy mother Mary no professed
Nonne,Marye a wyfe. as the dottynge papystes
haue dreamed, to couer their sodometrye
with a most precyouse coloure, but an honest
mannys wyfe, marryed accordynge
to the custome than vsed, Matt. 1. and Luce
1. In her so marryed without eyther vowe
or promes of virgynyte,No nonne. by the holye
Ghostes most wonderfull workynge
was he incarnated and so became man,
to redeme vs from the captyuyte of synne,
and restore vs agayne to the full fauer
of hys father. He honoured marryage
with the fyrst myracle that he outwardlye
wrought in our manhode, and called
vnto hys Apostleship, not wyuelesse
vowers, but marryed men. Ioan, 1. &amp; Mar
et. 1.
                  Peter maryed He wēt verye gentyllye vnto peters
howse, and healed hys wyues mother
which laye there syeke of a feuer, takynge
hys repast there, tarryenge with thē
all the nyght, and doynge great cures there also. And at hys departure in the mornynge,
he neyther commaunded Peter
to breake vp howsholde, nor yet to forsake
hys wyfe and make her a vowesse.
Marci. 1. Luce. 4. Math. 8. He neuer cōmaunded,No vowes cō
                     maūded
nor yet exacted the vowe of vyrgynyte
in all hys whole Gospell, but left
all men in lyberte to marrye yf they lyst,
forbyddynge al men fyrmelye, to make
anye lawe of coaccyon or of separacyon,

where God hath sett fredome in marryage.
Math. 19. Marci. 10. No forsakynge of
wyfe and chyldrē admytted he euer, but
as the vnmoueable &amp; constaunt stādynge
by hys worde requyreth yt, in them that
he hath appoynted to suffre deathe vndre
the worldes tyrannye for yt.
            
            
               The Apostles &amp; fyrst preachers marryed
               PEters wyfe went with hym in
the tyme of his preaching.Peters wyfe. 1. Cori.
9. and was put to deathe at Antioche
for confessinge Iesus Christ, as wytnesseth
Clemens Alexandrinus in .7. li. Stromatum,
and Eusebius Caesariensis li. iij. Ca. 30
Ecclesiastice historie. Paule left hys wyfe
at Philippos,Paule marryed. a cytie of the Macedoneanes,
by consent of them both. Phil 4. &amp;
1. Cor. 7. For thys onlye cause (sayth both
Clemens and Eusebius) that he myght the
more easelye therby and with the lesse cō
                  beraunce,
preache the Gospell abrode. Isi
dorus híspalēsis in hys boke De ortu &amp; obitu
sanctorum patrum, and Freculphus lexouiensis
in the seconde boke and fort chaptre of
hys Chronycles, reporteth both, that
Philip the Apostle preached in fraunce
to the verye extent of the Occeane see,Phylpp marryed. ād
was afterwarde done vnto deathe in hierepoli
a cytie of the Phrygiaues, and at
the last honorablye buryed there with his
doughters. By whose occasyon this real
me than called Brytayne was conuerted

vnto the Christen beleue For in the yeare
from Christes incarnacyō
                  Ioseph of Arimathe. An. do. 63 lxiij. was
Ioseph of Arimathe and other dyscyples
sent ouer of the seyd Philip to preache
Christ, and entered both with their wyues
and chyldren, Armagus than beynge
Kynge of the lande. This testyfyeth
Iohan Capgraue in Catologo sanctorum Anglie,
Thomas scrope de anti. carm.Scrope 
                  ca, 7. Iohā
Hardyng in hys. 47. chaptre, and Polidorus
uergilius. li. z. Anglice historie.
               
            
            
               Brytayne first conuerted by mē maryed.
               THese were surelye the orygynall
begynnynges (sayth Polidorus of
the Christē Relygyō in Brytayne.
Gildas witnessyth also, in his fyrst treatyse
De excidio Britannie. That the Brytaynes
toke the christen faythe at the verye
sprynge or fyrst goynge forth of the
Gospell,gospell. whā the churche was most perfyght,
and had most strengthe of the holye
ghost. All that tyme and a longe season
after, the mynysters helde their wyues,
accordyng to the fyrst ordre of God,
without, vowynge or yet professinge of
vyrgynyte, and so contynued to the dayes
of Lucius, which ys called in the Chronycles
the first Christē Kynge.Kynge. Though
thys Lucius were a good man,Lucius. and
began wele to inclyne to the Gospell,
yet was he worldlye mynded, and
thought that yt wanted dewe auctoryte

so lōge as yt was mynystred but of symple
and poore laye marryed men. Anon
therfor he sent vnto Rome
.ij.Rome. of those minysters
called Eluanus and Meduinus
vnto Eleutherius the Byshop (for they
had than no pope) to haue some autoryte
from thens. And thys was done in the
yeare of our Lorde. L. lxxix.Anno domini 179. Wherupon
Marcus Sabellicus sayth, Enneade. 7. li. 5.
That of all provynces Brytayne was
the fyrst that receyued the Christen fay
the with publique ordynaunce.
            
            
               ¶Christyanyte somwhat corrupted.
               THā Eleutherius sent hyther .ij. of
hys doctors, called fugacius and
Damyanus, to set here an ordre.
These fyrst baptysed lucius with a great
part of hys nobylyte and commons, ād
than with hys consent changed the Idols
temples into christen churches (as they
no we all them) the flamynes or Idoll sacryfycers,Churches.
which were than .xxviij. in nō
                  bre,
into so manye byshoppes, and the .iij.
archyflamynes into .iii. archebyshoppes,
as wytnessyth Galfridus Monemthensis
in hys seconde boke.
                  Autours 
                  De origine &amp; gestis
Britonum. cap. i. Alphredus Beuerlacensis in
hys Chronycle, Vincencius, Antoninus, Nauclerus, Bergomas, Polidorus, and a great sort
more. Thys chrystianyte endured in Brytayne,Chrystianyte
the space of .CC. and .xvi. years,
vnto the persecucyon of Dyoclesyane,

sayth Ranulphus in Polichronico. li. 4. Ca. 16,
Vpō thys toke the Rome churche first occasyon,Dyoce
                        •
                     
                     ses paryshes.
to deuyde the christen prouynces
into dyoceses and parryshes. Marke wele
these fyrst buyldynges of Antichrist,
or of Nemroth the yongar, and consydre
out of what good stuffe they ryse without
Gods worde. All this haue I writtē
hytherto, not as matters correspondynge
to the tyttle of my boke, but that their
spirytuall frutes maye apere what they
are, euen from the verye rootes.
            
            
               ¶The first sprynge of monkerye in
Brytayne.
               AS this newe chrystiantye from Rome,
had gotten here of the Paganes
both temples and possessyons,Tēples
and were wele fauerdlye satled (their
byshoppes and prestes perchaunce beynge
the same mynysters that had serued
the Idolles in them afore) anon after there
arose out of yt a serten kynde of monkerye,Mōkerye.
not in apparell, but in aperaunce
of a more sober lyfe. These within a whyle
semed better lerued than the other, ād
more depelye fell into the peoples estymacyon.
Wherupō arose sone after great
stryfe and vnquyetnesse amonge thē,Heresyeu.
and out of that stryfe most detestable he
resye
                     •…
                  . For one of them called pelagius,Pelagius.
beynge of the great monasterye of Bē
                  cornaburch
in Chestre shyre (though so

me call yt Bāgor) begā to dyspute with
them for the strēghte of mānys fre will,
and sayd that man myght be saued therby,frewyll
without the grace of God, so deuyenge
the effect of Christes blood, as hys folowers
are not ashamed to do yet to this
daye. Agaynst this heretyke pelagius,
wrote Saynt Augustyn, Saynt Hierom,
Cyrillus, Orosius, Innocencius, Gennadius, ād
at the last Thomas Braduuardin a doctour
here in Englande, with dyuerse other.
            
            
               ¶Heresye in Brytayne aryseth of
monkerye.
               YEt came there in no vowynge of
chastite all this tyme, neyther was
vyrgynyte thought anye holyar
amonge them than marryage. For one
Seuerus beynge both a monke,Seuerꝰ prest, ād
byshop, had a sonne there called leporius
a monke also and a prest,Leporiꝰ which vexed the
lande with that leruynge taught of hys
father, in the yeare of our Lord. CCCC
xxxij.432 as wytnessyth both Prosper Aquitannus,
and also Flores historiarum. Thys leporius
made hys boast, that he was able to
lyue purelye of hym selfe, and by force of
hys owne fre wyll, without the assistēce
of God, as reporteth of hym, Gennadius
Maſsiliensis,Antors Honorius Augustudunensis,
&amp; Ioannes Tritemius, in suis illustriū
uirorum Catalogis, and now last of all, Cō
                     radus
Gesnerus in uniuersali bibliotheca.. Of

the same sort was there an other called
Agricola,Agricola. a prestes sonne also, which in
the yeare of our Lorde .CCCC.xivi. trobled
the Brytaynes with the same doctrine,446.
as flores historiarum sheweth. The errours
of both these were at the same tyme
confuted by Germanus and Lupus
with other frenche doctours, which came
thydre thā for the same purpose, specyallye
of Saynt Augustine in Affrica.
            
            
               ¶A prestes sonne was Saynt Partrick.
               SAynt Partrick the great Apostle
of Irelande,Partrick was borne here in
this Brytayne aboute the yeare
of our Lorde .CCC.lxi. and had a prest
to hys father called Calphurnius,
                  361. which
was also a deacons sonne that was named
Fodunus. His mothers name hyght
Conches, and was holye Saynt Martynes
systre.Martinus. Thus testyfyeth Ranulphus
Cestrensis in Polychronico, li. 4, ca. 29. and
Iohan Capgraue in Catologo sanctorum Anglie.
If this had bene fowle playe in those
dayes, Saynt Martyne wolde neuer
so pacyentlye haue suffered yt. For we
reade that he was verye tendre vnto the
seyd Partrick,Patricius. after that his fryndes had
sent hym thydre, and taught hym manye
Godly thyngs. What rule this partrick
kepte in that behalf, I haue not redde.
Yet fynde I in hys lyfe wrytten, that

he had a ladde waytynge on hym called
Benignus,
                  Benignus. which alwayes reported hym,
to be his owne propre father, he neuer
deuynege yt. I reade also that one Moduenna
an Iryshe woman was verye famylyar
with hym, whether yt were by
the waye of marryage or no, that can I
not tell. Ex ante nominatis autoribus.
               
            
            
               ¶Sayntes were begottē in whordome.
               TO entre more depelye into the peoples
oppnyon,Chastyte. a chastyte was
pretensed anon after in that mō
                  kerye,Modwenna.
but not yet solempnelye vowed, &amp;
in manye places of the realme were monasteryes
buylded both of men and women,
But marke what folowed therof
immedyatlye after. Christ chaunced in
those dayes to haue many bretherne. For
manye virgynes had than children with
our fathers, at the least the fathers of thē
were neuer yet knowne.
               Saynt Dubrice that was after warde
the great archebyshop of Cairlegyon
and metropolytane of all the lande,Dubritius. had
a mayde to hys mother, called Eurdila,
but neuer wolde she confesse hym to haue
any father.Kētigernus. Saynt Kētigerne byshop
of glasghu) that ye now call Saynt Asses
or Asaphes (had in lyke case a fayre
mayde to hys forth bryngar, but father
wolde she graunt non to hym, for no cō
                  pulsyon.merlinꝰ
Merlyne also the great soth sayer

of wales, was an holy Nonnes sonne
in saynt Peters of Cairmardyne, no father
yet knowne to hym but a sprete of
the ayre. The first .ij. sheweth Iohan capgraue
in Catal sanc. Ang. And this lattre
wondre ys mencyoued of all famouse
writers. A great sort of the hystoryes
roude I reherse, but these are ynough at
thys tyme.
            
            
               ¶Lyke examples are amonge the
Turkes.
               SOche an other knauerye ys vsed
amonge the Turkes relygyouse
buggerers to this present
daye,Turkes and those chyldren that are begottē
amonge them, are holden for most holye
sayntes, as these were. They take it for
no maruele that Christ was borne of a
vyrgyne, for (they saye) they haue soche amonge
them at all tymes. But to turne
agayne to my purpose. The cause whye
the fathers of the afore seyd chyldren
myght not than be knowne, was thys, Iohan
capgraue sayth.A awe The lawe was that
tyme in Brytayne, that yf a yonge wenche
had be begottē with chylde in her
fathers howse, or anye where els
                     •
                  , this
was her iudgement.Iudgement. She shuld haue bene
brought vnto an hygh mountayne, ād
there throune downe headlonges, her corruptour
beynge byheaded. Yf this lawe
had styll contynued, and neuer so bene

put to the spirytuall courte without conseyence,
neuer had the vowe of their chastite
ronne so farre as yt hath done, to
manye a thousandes dempnacyon.
            
            
               ¶More Sayntes yet begotten in
whoredome
               SAynt Dauid of wales the great
archebysehop of Mentuia,Dauid.
which had so manye prophecyers
and so manye Angels sent afore to
geue warnynge of hys cōmynge .xxx. years
ere he was borne, was begotten out
of maryage in stynkyng whoredome. For
hys mother was a Nonne, ād his father
the earle of a contreye there called Cairdigam
shyre. A prynce called Dyhocus
in Kynge Arthurs tyme, inflamed at the
deuyls suggestion with the fleshlye loue
of hys owne naturall doughter, begat of
her Saynt Kynede the holye hermpte,kynedꝰ
that in Wales wrought so manye great
myracles. One Dubtacus an Iryshe mā
begate holy saynt Brigyde of hys mayd
seruaunt called brocsech,brigida. euen vnderneth
hys wyure nose to spyght her with it,
which had so manye re
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  lacyons from
heauen, and so manye popes pardōs frō
Rome. Saynt Cuthbert the great God,Cuthbert.
of the Northe, and he that was wonte to
defende vs from the Scottes, was a mysbegottē
also, for hys mother was vnmarryed.
And hys father in Irelande to haue
the good occupyēg of her, slewe both

her father and mother. These were the
spirytuall begynnynges of the Sayntes
of that age. If ye beleue not me, loke Iohan
Capgraue in Catalogo sanctorum Anglie.
                  capgraue.
and he shall tell ye moche more of the
matter. I coude shewe yow manye more
yet of soche holye sayntes byrthes, but
lete these for this tyme suffise.
            
            
               ¶Whoredome estemed most holynesse.
               MArke how abhominable whoryshnesse
in all these whorysh
frutes,whoredome is holye is auaunced of that whorysh
Rome churche, to the great blemyshynge
of Godlye marryage. The spyrytuall
Sodomytes and knaues hath not bene
ashamed to wryte yt in the lyues and
lyenge legēdes of all these, that is to saye
of Dubricius, Dauid, Kynedus, Kentigerne,
Cuthberth, and Brigyde, with soche
lyke, and solempnelye so to reade and
syng yt as Gods seruyce in their sēples,Theyr Gods seruyce
that they were sanctyfyed in their mothers
wombes. Se what aduauncementes
they haue for stynkynge whoredome,
and now lytle deuocyon to chast marryage
instituted of God. Neuer were the sō
                  nes
of Abraham, Isaac, ād Iacob, of Moyses,
Eleazar, and Phinees, so paynted
oute with myracles ād wonders, nor yet
so pranked vp with tabernacles ād lyghtes,
sensynges and massynges, as these
whores byrdes. Thus iudge they whoredome
holynesse, &amp; wholsō maryage synne,

Come out of Sodome ye whoremongers
and Hypocrytes,The Popes. chaplaynes. popysh byshoppes and
prestes, for as yet ye haue not refourmed
thys abhomynacyon, but styll vpholde
yt for your Romyshe Gods seruyce.
Come out theues and knaues come out.
            
            
               ¶Women greuouse and solacyouse.
               VVhat a do these holye sayntes of
theyrs had ād their vowers (whā
they come ones to vowes makynge)
for women ād with womē,women as to kepe
them out of their monasteryes, &amp; to make
thē beare chyldrē whā they were barrē, it
were in infynyte thyng to wryte.Dauid Saynt
Dauids mōkes were sheared away with
naked women at a broke syde in Rosidaualle.
So were Saynt Theliaes hermytes
also in an other place not farre frō
thens.dubriciꝰ Saynt Dubrices bretherne had
manye hote mouynges in their fleshe, ād
were fayne oft tymes to stande naked in
the colde ryuer.Kentigernus. Saynt Kentigernes disciplen
toke great paynes vpon them, to make
barren women frutefull. Whan saynt
Brigyde was at the verye poynt of marryage,brigida
she stole awaye preuylye with her
iij. maydes, and wayted longe after vpō
byshop Machyll, doynge manye great
cures in hys seruyce with holye water.
Saynt Modwē
                  Saynt Modwen. also after soche an other
sort, wayted vpon byshop Hiber and his

bretherne with her maydes. A woman
the same season accused byshop Broon
for begettynge her with chylde,brigida. and Brigyde
lyke a good bodye, by a charme or ij
made all safe agayne. As one of her maydes
was goynge to her lou
                     •
                  r a prestes
bed, for returnynge agayne in tyme, she
coude her moche thanke. All these holy
hystoryes shall ye fynde in Iohā capgraue.
            
            
               ¶A spirytuall example of a votarye.
               SAynt Iltute,Iltutus which had bene alwayes
a most valeaunt captayne
amonge the Brytaynes, at the
suggestyon of saynt of Cadoc an Hermpte,
put from hym hys most vertuouse and
chast wyfe, leauynge her nothynge els
to lyue vpon, but barlye breade and water,
an homelye repast for her that had
bene a ladye and tenderlye brought vp.hys wyfe.
And as she on a tyme resorted vnto hym
onlye to haue hearde the swete worde of
the Lorde, her commynge thydre so sore
discontented hys mynde, that wyth a
charme he put out both her eyes. For I
am certayne, yt come by no Godlye power,
she beynge ledde of so Godly a sprete.Not Paules lernyng
If this be saynt Paules lernynge, a
man so myserablye to leaue, hys wyfe, ād
so vngodlye to vse her for axynge good
counsell, I report me to yow. Yet must

he be styll a faynte in the Popes holye
churche, bycause he was a tyraūt to marriage,
for non other holynesse had he. So
the Sayntes recken I more fytt for hell
thā for heauē. Wale, this story hath also
Iohā Capgraue in Catalogo sāctorū Anglie
               
            
            
               ¶Vrsula with her sort, appoynted to
marrye.
               OF Vrsula and her .xi.Vrsula cum .xi millibꝰ thousande
companyons, haue the spyrytuall
hypocrytes by helpe of their spirytuall
father the deuyll, practysed innumerable
lyes, by them to make their newlye
sought out vyrgynyte to apere sumwhat
gloryouse to the worldlye dodypolles
that neuer wyll be wyse. The veryte
of the hystorye ys thys, after all iust writers.
Whan our Brytaynes had ones
gotten by theyr warre,Armorica. the lande of Armorica
(that we now call the lesser Brytayne)
and were put in perpetuall possessyon
therof by their Kynge Maximus aboute
the yeare of our Lorde .CCC. and
XC.390 they accorded amonge themselues
through the assent of Conanius their captayne,Conanus.
onlye to marrye with their, owne
nacyon, and in no wyse to haue a do with
the frenche women there, for dyuerse parels.Dionothus.
Wherupon they sent by ād by ouer
the see to Dionothus the duke of Cornewale,
which than in the kynges absence
had gouernan̄ce of all the realme, instaūtlye

desyerynge hym, to make prouysyon
for them Which immedyatlye gathered
from all partes of the lande,For mariage to the nombre
of .xi. thousande maydes ād other womē,
and so shypped them at London vpō
the Thamys with hys owne dere doughter
Vrsula, for so moche as Conanus despered
to haue her to wyfe. And as they
were abroode vpon the mayne sees, soche
contrarye wyndes and tēpestes fell
vpon thē,Drowned. as drowned some of their shyppes,
and droue the resydue of them into
the handes of their enemyes the hunnes
and the pyctes, which slewe a great nombre
of them, as they founde them
not agreable to their fleshlye purposes.
Thys sheweth Galfredus Monemuthēsis, li.
2.Autours 
                  ca, 4. Alphredus Beuerlacensis, Ranulphus
Cestrēsis, Ioānes Harding, Robertus Fabiā, Tritemius
in Cōpēdio, Volateranus, &amp; Polydorus.
               
            
            
               ¶An historye to their ghostlye purpose.
               BVt se here the cōueyaunce of these spyrytuall gentylmen, in Playsterynge
vp their vnsauerye sorcerye
                     •
                  .With lyes.
They saye, they all vowed vyrgynyte, &amp; were persuaded of saynt Michaell
the Archāgell &amp; of saynt Iohā the Euā
                  gelist,
neuer to marrye (as though they
were dyswaders of maryage for their lecherouse
vowes) &amp; so wēt frō thēs relygyously
to Rome on pylgrymage,Pylgrimage with great
deuocyō .ij. and .ij. togyther, &amp; were

honorablye receyued there of the Pope
and hys clergye. If this be not good ware,
tell me. I thynke there wanted no spyrytuall
occupyenge, for the tyme they
were there, yf the storye were true. For
Daniel sayth, that the lust of that proude
kyngedome, shuld be vpon women. Daniel.
11.Dan. 11 In all fleshlye desyres (sayth Hieremye)
they are become lyke ranke stoned
horse, neyenge at euerye mannys wyfe.
Hieremi. 5.Hiere. 5. And in dede fome wryters haue
vttered yt, that they were neuer good
sens their beynge there. Now marke the
sequeſe. In their returne homewarde agayne
towardes Coleynt, they had in
their cumpanye (saye theyr wryters) pope
Ciriacus
                  Names teyned. (yf there euer were anye
soche) Poncius, Petrus, Vincencius, Calixtus,
kilianus, Florencius, Ambrosius, Iustinus, and
Christianus, all cardinalles. Cesarius, Clemens,
Columbanus, Yuuanus, Lotharius, Pantalus,
Mauricius, Maurilius, Foillanus, Sulpicius,
Iacobus, Guilhelmus, Michael, Eleutherius, Bonifacius,
and vij more of the Popes howsholde,
all Byshoppes, besydes a great
nombre of Prestes and Chaplaynes.Hystoryames Diuerslye is
this holye legende handeled of
Iacobus Bergomas in Li. De claris mulieribus,
of Sigebertus, Vincencius, Antoninus, Hartmā
                     nus,
Carsulanus, Vorago, Vuernerus, Nauclerus,
Mantuanus, Vuicelius, Caxton, Capgraue,
Hector Boethius, Maior, and a great

sort more, scarselye one agreynge with
an other.
            
            
               ¶Fyne workemanshyp to be marked,
               HE that wolde take the payne,Proue the spretes. to
conferre their Chronycles and
writynges, but cōcernynge this
onlye matter, obseruynge dylygentlye
their diuerse bestowynge of tymes, places,
and names, with other thynges perteynynge
to the cyrcumstaunce of hystorye,
shuld anon perceyue their subtyle cō
                  ue
yaunce in manye other matters. The
solempne feast of these .xi. thousande she
pylgrymes, for their goynge to Rome,
ys yet no small matter in their Idolatrouse
churche, and yet they poore sowles neuer
came there, as the moste auctentyue
writers doth proue.Onlye to marrye. Their goynge out
of Brytanie was to become honest Christen
mennys wyues, and not to go on
pylgrymage to Rome, and so become byshoppes
bonylasses, or prestes playefers
Se what our auncyēt Englyshe writers
hath sayd in thys matter, which more experimentlye
knewe yt, and lete the forē
lyars go, whiche beynge farre of cared
the lesse to lye. In dede thys ys a verye
straunge procurynge of Sayntes, yf ye
marke yt wele, but that the monkes and
prebendes of Coleyne thought to do sumwhat
for the pleasure of their Nonnes

there,Nōnes of Coleyne. whiche had gathered togyther an
heape of dead mennys bones. For their
bones coude they not haue, beynge drowned
in the great Occeane see, as Galfredus
and the other autours veryfyeth afore.
But both Christ and Paule ones tolde
vs, that we shuld be subtyllye cyrcumuented
of that wylye generacyan, whan
they shuld worke their deceytfull wonders.
Math. 24. and. 2. Thes. 2.
            
            
               ¶Vowynges ded not yet constrayne.
               ALl thys tyme were there no constraynynge
vowes but all was fre
to leaue or to holde. For Constans
                  Cōstās
the eldeste sonne of kynge Constantyne
the seconde, beynge a mōke of Sayt Amphibalus
abbeye in Cairguent, that ye
now call Saynt Swythunes in wynchestre,
was taken out of yt without dyspensacyon,
about the yeare of our lorde.
CCCC.xliij.443. ād crowned kynge of Brytayne,
beynge in full lyberte of marryage.
Galfredus, Ranulphus, Hardyng, Capgraue,
Caxton, and Fabyan. In lyke case Maglocunus
                  Maglocunus.
(as Gildas reporteth) was first a
monke, and afterwarde constytute kynge
in the yeare of our lorde .CCCCC.lij.
contynuynge styll by the space of more
than .xxxiiij.552. years, and had for the tyme
.ij. wyues besydes hys concubynes.
Thys Maglocunus was rekened the most
comelye persone of all hys regyon, and a

man to whom God had than geuen great
vyctoryes agaynst the Saxons, Norweyes,
and Danes. Yet was he in hys
age as was longe afore hym, Mempricius
                  Mempricius.
hys predecessour, geuen to most abhomynable
sodometrye, whiche he had serued
in hys youthe of the consecrate chastyte
of the holye clergye. Galfredus, Ranulphus,
Hardynge, Fabian, and Flores Historiarum.
Verye vehement was Gildas beynge thā
a monke of Bencornaburch not farre frō
Chestre,Gildas prophecyeth. in hys dayly preachynges, both
agaynst the clergye and layte, concernynge
that vyce and soche other, and prophecyed
afore hande of the subuersyon of
thys realme by the Saxons for yt, lyke
as yt sone after folowed in effect. Loke
in both hys bokes, De excidio Britannie, et
in scriptis Polidori, Galfredi, et Ranulphi,
with the preface of Wyllyam Tyndals
obedyence.
            
            
               ¶The Saxons entre with newe
Christyanyte.
               ANon after the Saxons had gottē
of the Brytaynes the full cōquest
of thys lāde,Saxōs. the name therof was
changed, and hath euer sens bene called
Englāde of Engist which was thā their
chefe captayne,Englād as wytneseth Iohan Hardyng,
Iohā Maior,
                  Christyanyte. 
                  Hector Boethius, Caxtō, Fabyā. Thā came there in a newe fashyoned
Christyanyte yet ones a gayne frō Rome

with manye more heythnysh yokes than
afore. And that was vpon thys occasyō,
as all writers agre. Gregorye the first
of that name (now called Saynt Gregorye)
behelde in the open market at Rome,Gregorye.
Englysh boyes to sell. Marke thys
ghostlye mysterye, for the prelates had
than no wyues. And womē in those dayes
myght sore haue dystayned their newlye
rysyn opynyō of holynesse, yf they
had chaunced to haue bene with chylde
by them, and therfor other spirytuall remedyes
were sought out for thē by their
good prouyders and proctours, ye maye
(yf ye wyll) call thē apple squyres.In stede of marryage. And
as thys Gregorye behelde them fayre
skynned and bewtyfullye faced, with heare
vpon their heades most comelye, anō
he axed, of what regyon they were. And
answere was made hym, that they were
of an yle called Englande. Wele maye
they be called Angli
                  Angli. (sayth he) for they
haue verye Angelyck vysages. Se how
curyouse these fathers were, in the wele

                     •
                  yenge of their wares.Wares Here was no cyrcumstaunce
vnloked to, perteynynge to
the sale. Yet haue thys Byshopp bent of
all writers reckened the best sens hys tyme.
Thys storye mencyoneth Iacobus de
Voragine, Vincencius, Antoninus, Ioannes Capgraue,
Maior, Polydorus, &amp; an hondred Autours
more.
            
            
               
               ¶More Englysh boyes solde at
Rome.
               AN other example lyke vnto thys,
telleth the seyde Iohan Capgraue in
hys Cataloge. That as one Macutus
                  Macutus.
an Englysh Brytayne, and Byſhop
of Ale
                     •
                  h in Irelande, beynge at Rome
about the yeare of our lorde .CCCCC.
                     
                        •
                     00.
perceyued serten Englysh boyes to be
lolde there openlye. He gaue the pryce of
them, and sent them home agayne. Of a
lyke lyhode he smelled the spirytuall occupyenge
there, and pysyed the most dāpnable
castynge awaye of those poore innocentes,
whome Christ had so derelye
redemed with hys blood. Soche an other
acte of christē pitye wrought kynge Eteluuolphus
                  Ethelwolphꝰ
there (after dyuerse writers)
whan he in the yeare of our lorde. DCCC.
xlvij.847. made sute to Pope leo the
fort, to be clerelye dyspensed with for the
ordre of subdeacon, whiche he had in hys
yowthe receyued (wholsome ware I warande
yow) of Helmestane thā Byshop
of wynchestre. For by that tyme they
had crepte into the seate of the Serpent,
Apoca. 13.Apo. 13. and obtayned full autoryte to
dyspense with all pactes, professyons,
promyses, vowes, 
                     •
                  thes, oblygacyons,
and sealynges to the Beastes holye seruyce.
Marke alwayes the tymes.Tymes Thys
storye hath Vuylyam of Malmesburye, li. 2.

De regibus, Ranulphe, Hardyng, Fabyan and
Polydorus with other. And that the one
wanteth, the other alwayes habundauntlye
supplyeth. Possessyon was taken of
that seate of the Beast vndre phocas the
emproure in the yeare of our lorde. DC
and .vij.607. whan the papacye first begōne.
            
            
               ¶Augustyne entreth with hys Mōkes
               NOw to returne agayne vnto
Gregorye. He sent vpon the aforesayd
occasyon, into Englande
in the yeare from Christes in carnacyō
.CCCCC. xcvi.596. a Romy she mōke called
Augustyne,Augustinus. not of the ordre of Christ as
was peter, but of the superstycyouse seete
of Benet, there to sprede abrode the Romyshe
faythe and relygyon, for Christes
faythe was there lōge afore. With hym
entered Melitus, Iustus, Laurencius, Ioannes,
Petrus, Rufinianus, Paulinus, and a great sort
more to the nombre of .xl. all monkes
                  Mōkes &amp;
Italyanes. Wele armed were they with
Aristotles artylerye, as with logyck,
Phylosophye, and other craftye scyēces,craftye scyence.
but of the sacred scripturs, they knewe
lyttle or nothynge. If ye beleue not me,
reade in Iohan Capgraues Cataloge, Inu
ita Augustini, hys interrogacyōs, Ad Gregorium
per laurenciū et Petrum, and ye shall
fynde thē voyde of all christen lernynge,
eyther of lawe or Gospell. yea, moste incypyent
&amp; folyshe. Yet was the seyd Augustyne

the best lerned amōge thē.Ignoraunt apostles. These
toke with thē a great nombre of frenche
interpretours, bycause they were all ignoraunte
of the languages there. Here
was a noble christyanyte towardes, whā
the preachers knewe neyther the scripturs
nor yet the speache of the people.
Well, yet they ded myracles.Myracles. Yea, so sayd
Christ they shuld do, whā he bad vs in anye
wyse to be ware of thē. Mat. 24. For
thys storye, marke specyallye Iohan Capgraue
in Catalogo sanctorum Anglie, Sigebertus, Vincē
                     
                        •
                     ius, Antoninus, Tritemius, Christianus
Masseus, and the churche legendarye.
Dyuersly were they of womē intreated
               ANd as cōcernynge womē,Womē
                   greuousslye
were they vexed with them cō
                  mynge
hytherwarde, specyallye at
a vyllage called Saye,Saye. within the coūtye
of Angeu in fraunce. In the which was
buylded immedyatlye after, a churche
(they saye) in the honour of the seyd Augustyne,
where as no women come, but
are plaged with most sodayne deathe, for
the dyspleasure there shewed them than,angrye sayntes
yet ded thy but laugh vpō thē. Thys sheweth
Alexādre the prior of Esseby in hys
Annuall of Sayntes by these verses.
               
                  Cetus aput Saye uexauit eos mulierum,
                  Quas peccasse probat, lux noua fōs
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      nouus.
                  Plebs parat ecclesiā, mulieribus haud reserādā,
                  Introitum tentat una, sed inde perit.
               
               
                  
Thys storye hath also Iohan Capgraue,
and the olde Englysh Festyuall
                  Festyuall. of Sayntes,
which was sōtyme the onlye taught
Gospell of Englande. Notwithstandynge
thys dyspleasure of women abrode,
yet founde they womē fauorable within
England. For Bertha the quene of Kent,
than beynge a frenche woman, caused
Kynge Ethelbert to admyt thē with all
their tyr
                     •
                  erye trashe.Ethelbert. Yet for the small
trust he had vnto them at their first metynge,
he wolde in no wyse commē with
thē within anye howse (the storye sayth)
least they shuld after any sorcerouse sort
by wytche hym. The first poynt of Relygyō
they shewed, was thys. They spred
fourth a banner with a paynted crucifixe
and a syluer crosse thervpon, and so come
to the kynge in processyon,Processyon. syngynge
the letanye. Wele myght thys be called
a newe christyanyte, for neyther was yt
knowne of Christ nor of hys Apostles,
nor yet euer seane in Englande afore. It
came altogyther from the dust heape of
their monkerye.
            
            
               ¶Their first spirytuall prouysyons
here.
               AS the kynge admytted their enteraunce,
he couenaunted thus
with them, and verye wyselye.
That hys people shulde alwayes be at
lyberte,lyberte. and no man constrayned to their

newe founde Relygyon, sacryfyces▪ and
worshyppynges. But alac that fredome
con
                     •
                  yaued not longe with them, as ye
shall wele perceyue here after. Than ded
Augustyne get hym into Fraunce agayne,
and caused one Etherius than Archebyshop
of Arelas,Etheriꝰ to consecrate hym the
great byshop of all Englande, without
eleccyon or consent of the people that we
reade of. And in the yeare of our Lorde
euen .DC.600 ded Gregorye sende vnto
hym from Rome,Iustrumētes. hys prymates pall,
with superaltares, ch
                     •
                  lyces, copes, candelstyckes,
vestymentes, surplyces, alter
clothes, syngynge bokes, relly
                     •
                  kes, and
the blessynges of Peter and Paule. And
so admytted hym for the fyrst metropolitane
of all the whole realme, appoyntynge
hys seate from thens fourth at Canterburye,
than called Doroberna,
                  Doroberna▪
                   the worthye
cytie of london euer after depryued
of her former tytle, and so made an vnderlynge.
But the spyrituall fathers knewe
wele ynough what they ded, beholdynge
afore hande manye hydden mysteryes.
They perceyued that Caunterbury
was wele out of the waye,Caūterburye. and moche nygher
the see than was London, and so
moche the fytter for their craftye conueyaunces,
ād flyghtes to their holye father
yf nede shuld requyre yt, with manye
other commoditees els. Marke alwayes

these nombers of Syxes and their mysteryes,Nombers.
for the age of Man and the Beast,
Apoca, 13.
            
            
               ¶Their preparacyons for Antichrist,
               THe first stodye of these fathers after
they were ones satled,primitie was all
aboute masse offerynges, ceremonyes,
byshoppes seates, consecracyons,
churche hallowynges, orders geuynge,
tythes, personages, puryfycacyous of
women, and soche lyke. Wherupon a
Syunode was called,Synodus. and there comman̄
dementes were geuen that all thinges
shuld be here obserued accordynge in the
customes of Rome. In Englande was
there afore their commynge a christyanyte,Christyanyte.
but it was all without masses, and
in a maner without choyce of ey
                     •
                  her dayes
or meates. The Brytaynes in those
dayes had non other Gods seruyce but
the Gospell.Brytaynes, Seldome admytted they
any dyfference of tymes with the Iewes,
eyther anye Idoll sacry
                     •
                  yces with the
Gentyles, but folowed the playne rules
of the ſcripturs. If anye superstycyons
were amonge their Monkes, they had
nought to do ther with, but were euermore.
at lyberte. For Prynces at that tyme
were not yet becomen the Beastes Images,Princes
to speake out of theyr spretes, or to
make lawes accordynge to theyr lustes.
The labour of Augustyne with his mō
                  kes,

from the forseyd yeare of our Lorde
DC.600 was to prepare Antichrist a seate
here in Englande, agaynst the full tyme
of hys perfyghtage, of. 666.666 For though
he were first conceyued in the wycked
churche of Cain, yet coude he not shewe
hymself in hys owne lykenesse, that is to
saye, Christes opē aduersary, tyll Christ
came in the fleshe. And than he apered
at all one tyme with hym, in the malygnaunt
churche of the Iewes or spyrytualte
of Herode,Antichrist which than first began to
persecute hym and to seke hys death.
            
            
               ¶The prouynge of Augustynes
Apostleship.
               IN the yeare of our Lorde .DC.602 ād
ij helde Augustyne an other counsell
in the west part and countye
of worcestre,Synodus in a place that is yet called
Augustynes oke, wherunto he called by
cōmaundemēt, the vij. byshoppes of the
Brytayne churche with their principall
doctours. And as they were takynge
their iournaye thydreward, they counselled
with a serten solytarye man, which
was knowne to be of amost perfight chri
sten lyfe,Solytarye mā. what was to be done cōcernynge
the afore seyd Augustyne. Anon
he made them this christen answere:
If he be a man of God (sayth he) in anye
wyse folowe hys counsell. If he be
not, vtterlye refuse it. How shall

we know that?Christē counsell saye they. Ye shall wele
perceyue yt by his gentyll sprete, sayth
he agayne. For Christ bad hys scolers,
lerne of him to be meke harted. If he be of
that sort, he ys lyke to brynge ye non other
than Christes moste easye yoke. But
yf ye fynde hym proude, be ware of the
importable burdenes of the hygh mynded
Pharysees.A proude monke. And as they were commen
thydre, they founde hym syttynge a
loft in a throue of hygh honoure, shewynge
vnto them no countenaunce of gentylnesse.
Wherfor they regarded hym not,
but vtterlye withstode all hys enforcemē
                  tes.
            
            
               ¶The Englysh churche begynneth
with tyrannye.
               AFter longe dysputacyons and other
weywarde wrangelynges, he
layed vnto their charges, that they
were in many thynges, contrarye to the
vnyuersall Christen churche, Notwithstā
                  dynge,Thre poyntes
yf they wolde consent vnto hym
in these .iij. poyntes. That ys to saye, to
baptyse after the Romysh maner, to celebrate
the feast of Eastre as they do there,
and preache to the Englysh Saxons
as he shuld appoynt them, he wolde wele
beare with them in all other causes. In
no case wolde they graunte vnto hym,
nor yet accept him for their archebyshop▪
but sayd playnelye, they wolde styll holde

theyr auncyent tradycyōs, which they
perfyghtlye knewe to be agreable to the
holy Apostles doctryne.A tyraunt Than sayd Augustyne
furyouslye vnto them, that yf
they wolde not peceably graunte to hys
requestes, they shuld be enforced therunto by most cruell battayle. And so in the
yeare next folowynge, were slayne of
their preachers by Augustynes procurement,A murtherer.
to the nombre of a thousande and
ij. hondred, with their great mastre Dionothus. Loke Flores Historiarum, Amandus Zierixensis,
Galfrede, Ranulph, Capgraue, Caxton,
Fabianc, their churche legendarye, and
other.A carnall Synagoge. Thus ded that carnall Synagoge
(than called the Englysh churche) which
came from Rome with Augustine, most
cruellye persecute, at her first commynge
in, the Christē churche of the Brytaynes
in these holye martyrs. Theyr synefull
Syon buylded they than in blood,Bloody Syon.
for that theyr wycked instytutes were
Godlye dysobeyed. But he they sure, yt
shall be plowed vp in thys lattre age, ād
lye wast lyke a uoyde felde, accordynge
to Mycheas prophecye. Mich. 3
            
            
               ¶What the Brytayne churche was
afore.
               TRue is the faythfull saynge of Iohan
Leylande in assertione Arturij.
                  Iohan Leylād.
                  fo. 35. That the Romysh Byshop
sought all meanes possyble to vpholde

the Englysh Saxōs in a kyngedome falselye gotten, the Brytaynes hatynge hym
for yt, and he agayne of myschefe prouokynge
those Saxons fearcelye to invade
them. Marke yt hardelye, for yt ys worthye
to be noted. Marke also the agrement
of the Brytayne churche with the
vij.Brytayne churche. churches of Asia in Saynt Iohans tyme.
Not onlye for the iust nōbre of theyr
byshoppes, but also for their obseruacyon
of Eastre afore thys Augustynes cō
                  mynge.
For in their argumentacyons aboute
that matter, they layde alwayes
for themselues the vsages of that churche
receyued first of Iohan the Euangelist, Philip the Apostle, Policarpus, Traseas,
Sagaris, Papirius, and Meliton, allegynge
the saynges of Policrates, and Eusebius, in
that behalfe. The churche that Augustyne
than planted in Englande,Englyshe churche was more
gouerned by byshoppes polycyes for
their aduauntage, than by the expresse
worde of God to hys honour, as it hath
beue euer sens. And therfor yt was and
is yet in outwarde obseruacyons, rather
a polytyque churche than a Christē
churche, the Iewyshe and Heythnishe superstycyons
not reckened. God graunt
yt ones a shappe after his prescripte lawes
and ordynaunces. Amen.
            
            
               ¶Antichrist approched fast to hys
full age.
               
                  
IN the yeare of our Lorde (as I
sayd afore).607 DC. and .vij. Antitechrist
fast approchynge to the fulnesse
of hys age,full age grewe into a vnyuersall
fatherhode. For than first beganne
the papacye at Rome vndre the false Emproure
phocas, as wytnesseth Abbas Vrspergensis,
Hermannus Contractus, Sigebertus,
Ranulphus, Matheus Palmarius, Christianus
Masseus, Archilles Pirminius, Ioannes Carion,
et Martinus Lutherus in Mundi supputacione.
Than obtayned Bonifacius the
thirde of that name,The papacye. of the seyd Phocas
for moneye, in the myddes of all seysme,
stryfe, myschefe, and murther, to be Sathans
great stewarde here, &amp; the deuyls
leftenaūt. For in hys power yt was not,
to make hym Christes vycar, nor yet
saynt Peters successour. Thus gaue the
Dragon, then hys autoryte and power
to the Beast with .vij. heades, that arose
out of the see, or from the superstycyouse
wauerynge multytude, Apoco. 13.Apo. 13. Than
wanted he nothynge els, but to sytt in
the place of God, which ys the conscyence
of Man,2. thes. 2 that he myght there exalte
hymselfe aboue all that is called God. 2
Thessa. 2. To brynge that to passe, the
Monkes and the prestes sturred quycklye
about them, and left no cautels vnsought
out to brynge all Christen realmes
vndre hys deuylysh domynyon.
For than had the Monkes autoryte

to preache,Mon
                     
                        ••
                     s autoryte. baptyse, and assoyle from synne,
which they neuer had afore. How and
what th
                     •
                  y wrought here in Englande,
ys euydent by that hath bene shewed af
                     •
                  
                  re,
and wyll be yet more playne in that
which herafter foloweth. Marke yt
therfor in the name of God, for now ys
the tyme, wherin he must he reueled, that
the Lorde Iesus maye consume hym
with the breathe of hys mouth. Esa, 11.Esa. 11 and
2. Thes, 2.
            
            
               ¶The chastyte of hys masmongers.
               NOw conceruynge the contynencye
of thys new broched broode
or newlye fashyoned clergye.
For so moche as they were Monkes ād
came from Rome, they had professed a
false chastyte,A false chastyte to apere more holye than
the prestes, and therby in processe of tyme
to robbe them of their benefyces or
appoynted lyuynges.Gregory. Though Gregory
in hys tyme made these constytucyons,
that nō shuld be admytted a prest which
had marryed ij wijues, nor yet they be accepted
that in presthode, kepte concubynes,
as testyfyeth Sabellicus, yet durst he
not vtterlye condempne prestes marryage,Example
by reason of a most terryble example
of innumerable chyldrens heades seane
drowned in a ponde. But marke the spyrytuall
occupyēge of these hote fathers,
for greuouslye were they than vexed

with nyght pollucyōs. Wherupō Augustyne
sēt vnto Gregory,Mōkes chastyte to knowe yf they
myght wele saye masse hauyng them the
nyght afore. Vnto whom after manye
wordes, he maketh in effect thys answere.
That lyke as they chaunce vnto men
iiij. ways, that ys to saye, by superfluyte
of nature,iij. by glottenouse eatynge &amp; drynkynge,wayes.
by intyrmyte of the fleshe, and by
fylthye cogytacyons of the mynde, so
ought they to haue .iiij. consyderacyons.
For the first .iij. a prest ought not (he
sayth) to abstayne from hys masse saynge.Coloured Sodomye.
The fort he describeth by suggestyō,
dylectacyon, &amp; consent, leauynge yt without
anye conclusyon. If thys be not good
wholsome dyuynyte of your holye Romysh
dayntes, tell me. Thys hath Iohan
Capgraue in Catalogo sanctorum Anglie.
               
            
            
               ¶Contempt of marryage, with
tayles.
               I thynke a man myght fynde as honest
stuffe as thys,stewes dyuynyte. in the scooles of
my lorde of wynchestres rentes at
the banke syde at London, yf he had nede
of yt. Ye maye se by thys, the vertuouse
stodye of these holye chast fathers, &amp; the
clarkelye conueyaunce of their fleshlye
mouynges. Great pytie had yt bene, but
yt had had place in their holy sayntes legendes
to the ghostlye infourmacyon of
other, but that we shuld not els wele haue

knowne their bawdye hypocresye. If
their vnuirginall vowes had not bene,Vota
                     
                        •
                     yes lernynge.
lyttle shuld the worlde haue neded thys
lecherouse lernynge. Honest marryage
hath no knowlege therof, and yet ys yt
a pleasyuge seruyce vnto God. Is not
that (thynke yow) a straunge kynde of
chastyte, that ys thus euerye weke poluted?
Yet maye they after thys leruynge,
euerye daye saye Masse, their vowe neuer
hyndered, but in marryage they maye
not so vndre payne of deathe. Now
forsoth yt ys wholsom ware, &amp; yt shulde
come euen unto frome the deuyls blacke
bowgett. Thys ys the reuerence these poluted
wretches haue to matrymonye, beynge
Gods clere instytucyon,Marryage contēpned. that they
preferre all their fleshlye knaueryes vnto
yt. For yt onlye, haue they named men
laye &amp; women lewde,Laye, with tayles appoyntynge their
chyldren tayles here in Englande in dyſdayne
ād scorne. For nought was yt not
that Saynt Paule called their lernynge
Hypocresye, and the detestable doctryne
of deuyls. 1. Timoth 4. Iohan Capgraue and
Alexandre of Esseby sayth, that forcastynge
of fyshe t
                     •
                  yles at thys Augustyne,
Dorsett shyre men had tayles euer after.
But Polydorus applyeth yt vnto kentysh
men at Stroude by Rochestre,Dorset &amp; Stroude. for cuttynge
of thomas Beckettes horses tayle.
Thus hath Englande in all other landes

a perpetuall dyffamye of tayles by their
wryttē legēdes of lyes, yet can they not
wele tell, where to bestowe them trulye.
            
            
               ¶Stryfe aboute the Eastre celebracyon.
               NExt after thys Augustyne was
Laurencius archebyshop of Caunterburye.
And after hym Melitus.
Than Iustus,
                  Laurencius cū alijs. than Honorius, than Theodatus,
and Theodorus, all blacke monkes and
Italyanes borne to the nombre of .vij.
Thys Laurence helde a great Synode
with hys other prelates in the Ile of Mā
                  ne,
dysputynge there with the Scottyshe
and Iryshe Byshoppes,Synodus. for the feast of
Eastre, what daye yt shuld be yearlye celebrated,
writynge from thens vnto their
other prelates a treatyse of the same.
More thā an hondred years space, were
the Papystes thā in controuersye for the
daye of that Eastre celebracyon, ere they
coude be quyeted.the feast of Eastre. Great paynes the relygyouse
fathers toke in those dayes to
strayne out a gnatt, that their lecherouse
posteryte after them, myght the better
swallowe in a myghtye camell. Math. 23.
In thynges of small value they were thā
verye scrupulose, but the wayghtyer causes
they coude lete slyppe wele ynough.
What so euer thys Laurence was to
women by hys lyfe,Womē
                   he was (they saye)

verye cruell vnto them after hys deathe.
For in a se
                     •
                  tē towne called fordune, was
a church buylded in hys name, where no
women myght entre with offerynge nor
without offerynge, but they had euer more
sore bellyes of yt.Sore bellyes. I praye God they
went not manye tymes thens with chylde,
for there were manye fatte Canons
and prebendes. Thys superstyeyouse fable
borowe they of the paganes, whose
opynyon was that no woman myght entre
into the temple of Venus their great
Goddesse in the mounte of Olympus,Venus
with out a great vyllanye. Iacobus Zieglerus
in sua Syria.
               
            
            
               ¶Great busynesse for their other
tradycyons.
               HEre passe I ouer the clowtynge
in of their canonycall houres,
                     Ceremonyes &amp; rytes. of
their absolucyōs for synnes, their
temples, their aulters, their bel ryngynges,
their lētes, their dyuersyte of orders
and dyuysyons of paryshes, least I shuld
be therin to tedyouse vnto the readers.
Aidanus,
                  Good men. 
                  Finnanus, and Colmānus, beynge all
iij. byshoppes of lyndyſfarne in Northunberlande one after an other, &amp; Scottysh
men borne, coude not wele awaye with
the pryde and wanton toyes which they
behelde in their Romyshe rytes, but perseuered
styll in the symple ordre of the
prymatyue churche, not contented to chā
                  ge

yt. For the which in those dayes, they
had moche a do with these hygh stomaked
Romanes. Hilda in lyke case, that was thā
abbasse of Streneshalt (that we now call
Whytby) a womā lerned,Hilda et Colmā
                     nus. wyse, and vertuouse,
dysputed with them in their generall
counsell vpon Colmannus syde,
in the yeare of our lorde .DC. and lxiiij.
concernynge the daye of their eastre celebracyon,664.
their head shauynge, and other
vnsauerye ceremonyes, and wrote afterwarde
an ernest treatyse agaynst Agilbertus
a frenche man and at that tyme
byshop of Wynchestre.Agilbertus. All thys myght
not helpe than, but in processe of tyme
they had their whole myndes, magry all
their hartes. Bedas Giruuinus li. 3. Ca. 25. De
gestis Anglorum, Guilhelmus Malmesburye li.
3. De Pontificibus Ranulphus. li. 5. Ca. 17. Ioann
es Capgraue and other.
            
            
               ¶Relygyouse examples dysuadynge
marryage.
               AFter Laurencius folowed Melitus
                  melitus
in the Archebyshoppes seate of
Caunterburye, in the yeare of our
lorde .DC. and .xix. whiche (they saye)
both alyue &amp; dead,619. dysuaded yonge men
from christen marryage. As Saynt Columbanus
a Scott,Columbanus. about the same tyme,
came to the sell of an holye Nonne for
ghostlye counsell. She bad hym, awaye,
least wanton youthe wolde brynge them

togyther wylde they nylde they. Saynt
Edwyne kynge of Northumberlande gaue
vnto saynt Paulinus the archebyshop
of yorke,Paulinus. hys yonge doughter Eanfleda,
so sone as she was baptysed in the yeare
of our lorde. DC. and. xxvi. that he shuld
make her an vnholye Nonne. And the
daye after the sayd Edwyne was slayne,
he toke with hym both the doughter and
mother, and so fled with them vnto Rochestre
in kent be water, neuer returnynge
thydre agayne.fiacrius Saynt fiacre a Scottysh
hermyte had so greate malyce vnto
women, that he plaged so manye of thē
with the fowle euyll, as came within the
precynct of hys monasterye, bycause one
woman had ones complayned to the bysh
                     •
                  p
of hys prodygyouse charmynges.
Hector Boethius.
                  Foillanus. Saynt Foillanus an Iryshe
Byshop with hys bretherne was verye
famy
                     •
                  yar and seruysable vnto Saynte
Ger
                     •
                  ruyde and her nonnes at Nigella, &amp;
made dyuerse barren women full gracyouslye
to conceyue. Saynt keynwirye a Keyna.
virgyne of wales, contēmpnynge marryage,
fled from thēs to Saynt Myhels
of the mounte, to kepe her vowed virgynyte
amonge the holye fathers there, as
vower with vowers. All these storyes
hath Iohan Capgraue.
               
            
            
               ¶Other relygyouse examples of
that age.
               
                  
SEbba kynge of the East Saxōs,Sebba ys monked.
was so bywytched of the Byshop
of London and hys caskynge
collygeners there for hys substaunce,
that he had made hymselfe a monke, leauynge
vnto them both hys wyfe and possessyons,
yf she had bene no wyser than
he.
               Yet was she by their incantacyous at
the last deceyued, they hauynge of hym
an innumerable summe of moneye, and
he nothynge of them agayne but a mangye
monkes cowle and hys buryall in
Paules.Egbinus Whan Saynt Egbynes father
was ones departed in wales, his mother
resorted with hym to the abbeye of
Saynt Sampson,Sāpson and there receyued of
hym the habyte of a Nonne, bestowynge
the rest of her lyfe amonge the good bretherne
there.Eanswida. Saynt Eanswyde abbesse
of folkstane in kent, inspyred of the deuyll,
dyffyned christen marryage to be
barren of all vertues, to haue but transytoryouse
frutes, and to be a fylthye corrupcyō
of virgynyte. Yet ware Marye,
Iohan Baptyst, and Iesus Christ swete
frutes, therof,Frutes of marryage. the iust fathers of the olde
lawe not reckened. Saynt Paule sayth
also, that by vertue of marryage, the vnfaythfull
man ys sanctyfyed by the woman
that ys faythfull. 1. Cor. 7. Neyther
ded he at anye tyme teache marryage

to be eyther a corrupcyon or yet an impedymēt
of christen virgynite, whan he
coupled the Corintheanes (which 
                     〈7 letters〉
                  ed
styll marryed) a chaste vyrgyne to
Christ. 2. Cor.
                  Eanswida. 11. But thys gentylwoman
Eanswyde was moche better acquaynted
with the monkes lernynge than with
Christes, and with a chastyte rather to
their behoue than to hys. Yet droue she
out all the gyantes there, yf their churche
legende be true. These storyes sheweth
Iohan Capgraue.
               
            
            
               ¶The wanton toyes of the holye
fathers.
               ABout thys same tyme sent Pope
Bonyface the fift, a shyrte with a
golden collor,babyshe ioyes. and a fyne petycote
of straunge makynge, vnto kynge Edwyne
with the blessynges of Peter and
Paule. And vnto hys wyfe Ethelburge
a syluer glasse and a combe of yvoriye
with the same, to vpholde them in thys
newe christyanyte. Se these wanton fathers
what toyes they vse, to set vp their
kyngedome here. Neuer shall ye reade
that Christes dysciples had anye soche
wyttye polycyes. Saynt Petrock an hermyte of Cornewale,Petronus. was fayne euerye
nyght from the crowe of the cocke to the
sprynge of the mornynge, to stande naked
in a pyt, to abate the hote mouynges
of hys fleshe. And neuer coude he haue

remedye of that dysease, tyll he went on
pylgrymage to Rome &amp; Hierusalē. Here
was a newe sought out salue for that sore.Piranus
Saynt Pyrane a Byshop also in Cornewale,
had a fayre dammesell in the monasterye
of hys mother wingell, called
Brunett, whom the Lorde of the soyle toke vp for hys occupyēge. At the last he a
greed with hym no lōgar to haue her, thā
the bernacle or butture shuld breake hym
of hys slepe, which chaunced sone after, &amp;
than he sent her home agayne. If these be
not good honest legendes to be redd in
the popes holye churche,legēdes tell me. Plentuouse
shall ye fynde Iohan Capgraue in the
rehersall of them and soche other.
            
            
               The ghostly bestowynge of their vowes
               A Nonne belōgynge to saynt Cota,Chastyte of 
                        •••
                     ar
                        •
                     es.
and a monke perteyninge to saynt
Pyrane, aboute the same tyme strake
vp a couenaunt of loue. And as they
mett in a wode for perfourmaunce of the
same, a yonge pygeon fell betwixt thē ād
made them both ashamed, &amp; so they went
home agayne▪ i
                     •
                   lyke matter. Soche an
other pagent was played at yorke, but
it was longe after.Vowes obserued. The monkes of saynt
Marye abbeye, and the nonnes of Clement
thorpe mett togyther there at haye
makynge, the abbottes fole beynge with
them. And as the abbot enquyred of hym
at supper for pastyme, where he had done

all that daye. He fell in a great laughynge
and declared before all hys gestes,
that a sore battayle had bene foughten
that after none betwixt hys monkes
and the monkes of clemēt thorpe. But he
thanked God that hys monkes had the
best, for they laye euer aloft. Bycause
that one of Saynt modwēs maydes,Modwenna. had
layed her best beloues shoes at her beddes
head, the spretes of heauen that were
wonte to vysyte her, wolde not come there
that nyght. After she had bene at Rome,
and was comen home agayne, she
dwelt at Scalesclyf,Heremite. where as an holye
hermyte ded oft tymes vysyte her, and
moche refreshe her with a legende boke
of sayntes lyues. But no tydynges was
there amonge them, of Christes holy gospell.
Loke Iohan Capgraue.
               
            
            
               ¶Erkenwalde and Osith, with their
Nondryes.
               SAynt Erkenwalde the sonne of
Vffa the first Kynge of the east ā
                  gles,Erkenwaldus
abbot of Cherteseye ād Byshop
of London, buylded a Nondrye at
Berkynge. And bycause there were at
that tyme in Englāde no Nonnes to hys
mynde (for Hilda his kynswoman was
to great a scripture woman in those dayes)
he sēt ouer the see for an old acquayntaunce
of his called Hildelitha, lerned in

arte, but not in Christes dyuynyte, Her
made he there abbasse, commyttynge vnto
her gouernaunce, hys systre Ethelburge
and a great sort more of yonge maydes,Ethelburga
to be taught and made nōnes there.
Soche rule was kepte amonge thē within
a short space after, that God sent vpon
them a plage of pestylēce, which toke awaye
all their chaplaynes, the cruell Da
                  
                     ••…
                  s
folowynge and burnynge vp that
was left, monasterye, nonnes and all.
Saynt Osith was marryed to Sigher
Kynge of the East Saxons.Ositha. But bycause
she loued the spirytualte moche better
thā hym, whyls he was on a tyme in
huntynge, she sent by a preuye lettre for
Accas, and Bedeuuinus,
                  Spirituall knauerye. Byshoppes of the
East Angles, contaynynge Northfolke
and Sothfolke, causynge thē to put vpō
her a nonnes aparell. So made she him
to beleue in his returne, that she had professed
the vowe of chastyte, and gaue him
therby a most wretched occasyon to lyue
all the dayes of his lyfe after, in most
synnefull aduoutrie. But a iust plage folowed.
For in the yeare of our Lorde .DC.liii.653 was she slayne of the Danes, and
her whore howse (nondrye I shuld saye)
vtterlye destroyed. Yet was she in the
Popes churche allowed for a stynkynge
martyr, for contempnynge marryage. Iohan
Capgraue.
               
            
            
               
               ¶The perfyght age of the Beast.
               THeodorus a Greke,Theodo
                     
                        ••
                     s was of pope
vptelianus constytute the sixt archebyshop
of Caunterburye, frō
Augustyne or sens the Papacye began,
to make all sure here to Antichristes behoue,
in the sixtye and sixe yeare of hys
age, and in the yeare from Christes incarnacyon six hondred, syxtie, and sixe,
which is in saynt Iohans Apocalyps the
full age of the Beast,Apoc▪ 13. &amp; the full nombre of
man. Marke yt good reader. For now of
a Beast,The fullye complete age. becometh he a kynge, ye, as Daniel
calleth hym, the vnshame fast Kynge
of faces. Daniel. 8. Presumynge to sitt aboue
God in euerye mannys conscyence
2. Thessa. 2. Named yt is there, the nombre
of man, and the nombre of the Beast,Nōbre of the beast for
so moche as yt was the tyme, wherin mā
                  nys
lernynge most stronglye withstode
the lernynge of God, to the prankynge
vp of that odyouse aduersarye, the verye
man of synne, and sonne of perdycyon,
all blasphemyes therupon folowynge.
Euydent is yt, by all the Englysh Chronycles,
that than this Theodorus came hyther with the seale of that execrable Beast,
to marke vp all to that most blasphemouse
kyngdō. For neuer afore wrought
the sprete of Antichrist, the mystery of iniquite
so strongelye as at that tyme. For

hyther than brought he all vayne &amp; craftye
scyences,Crafty scyēces. of countinge, calkynge, measurynge,
syngynge, rymynge, reasonynge,
arguynge, dyffynynge, shauinge, oylynge,
exorcysynge, incantynge, &amp; coniurynge.
Loke Iohan Capgraue, in uitis Adriani,
et Theodori Besydes that Bedas wryteth
li. 4. Capit, 2. and Ranulphus li. 5. Ca▪
                   18.
            
            
               ¶For the varyaunce had in supputaciōs
               TO auoyde cōtrouersyes in the supputacyō
of years, for so moche as
some writeth hym to haue comē hyther
in the yeare afore rehersed, &amp; some .ij
years after. Ye shall vnderstāde that Theodatus which was his predecessour,Theodatus departed
in the yeare of our Lorde .DC.lxv.
as witnesseth Hermānus Cōtractus in Chronico
de ſexetatibus mundi. In the yeare folowynge
was this Theodorus admytted
of V
                     ••
                  elianꝰ,Theodorus &amp; receyued his full autoryte
of byndynge and losynge (sayth Platina)
to holde the Englyshe nacyon styll in
that faythe. Marke yt. But by reason of
serten delayes, yt was more than a yeare
after ere he entered into Englāde. One
cause of hys tarryaunce (Iohan Capgraue
sayth) was the growynge of hys heare
concernynge his crowne,Shauynge which was
shauē afore after a farre other sort, he beynge
a Greke. Hys abydynge there for
that only cause, was more thā .iiij. Monthes,
besydes other nedye matters. So

that yt was the yeare of our Lorde .DClxviij.668. the xxvi. daye of Maye, and the
seconde yeare of hys consecracyon ere he
came into Kēt, as wytnesseth both Bedas
and Ranulphus With hym sent Vitelianꝰ
a monke borne in Aphrica, called Adriā,Adrianus.
to loke to hys doctryne, least he taught
anye thynge in the Englyshe churche
that were not agreable to the Romyshe
faythe (as the marriage of prestes, and
the howselynge with leuened breade) for
he ded not in all poyntes trust hym, bycause
he was a Greke borne.A scole. Anon after
he sett vp a Greak scole at Caunterburye
of all maner ſcyences, as Rhetoryck, Logyck,
philosophie, Mathesye, Astrologie
Geometrye, Arithmetyck, and Musyck,
and taught them there openly both in latyue
ād Greke,Straunge sciences besydes the art Magyck
Sortilege, Physuomye, Palmestrye, Alcumye,
Necromancye, Chyromācye, Geomancye,
ād witcherye, that was taught
there also. Bedas, Ranulphus, and Iohan. Cap
               
            
            
               ¶Sealynges to the Beastes obedyence
               THan constytute he the seyd Adriane
both abbot and generall reader
there,Adrianus whyls he cōpased aboute all the whole regyon for the Eastre celebracyon
&amp; other Romyshe rytes. This
is the first archebyshop (sayth Iohan Capgraue)
that all the Englyshe churche was
sworne to.Character. Marke here the Seale of the

Beast. Apo. 13. In the yeare of our Lorde.
DC.lxxij.672 he helde a Synode at Thetforde in Northfolke,Synodus where as he enquyred
of euerye mannys faythe towardes
the Churche of Rome. Than constytute
he byshoppes for euerye quarter, ād deposed
all them that were not confirmed by
the popes auctoryte, of whose nombre
Ceddas the byshop of yorke was one.Ceddas
More ouer he publyshed there a boke of
the churches ordynaunces,Ordinaūces made by the
forsayd Vitelianus, with permyssion of
organes to make them myrye, commaundynge
yt onlye to be obserued, Christes
ordre sett a part. If this were not the departynge
that Paule prophecyed to come
.2. The .2. where shall we loke for any.
A sayinge hath Ioannes de Molinis,
                  Ioānes de Molinis 
                  in speculo
carmel. Ca. 6. which (though he were a
papyst) I fynde here most true. From
the dayes of Heraclius the Emprour
(sayth he) vnto our tymes, the daye drawynge
towardes nyght, the churche sufferinge
a sore eclippes, is come to a downe
goynge. Yea, she is almost at the case
of a full departynge, et c. I thynke a
truer sentence coude not than be vttered
all circumstaunces therupon cōsydered.
Great pytye was yt, that the churches
posteryte than perceyued not so manyfest
a defeccyon.
            
            
               ¶More sealynges yet to Antichristes

kingedome.
               IN the yeare of our Lorde DC.680 and
lxxx.Synodus. helde this Theodorus an other
coūsell at hatefelde in the west
partyes. Where as he demaunded a reckenynge
of the byshoppes and other curates,
what faythe ād fauer their peoples
had than to the churche of Rome, as pope
Agathon had commaunded hym to do
by hys wrytynges,Agathō
                   which wrote than vnto
hym, to do all thynges wyselye. Ye
knowe what that meaneth▪ I thynke. Here
was non enquirye made, what beleue
they had than there in the Gospell of our
Lorde Iesus Christ. No, yt was an other
maner of matter,No Gospell. that they sought. Oh,
wonderfull was the workynge of that
Serpentes generacyon. Polidorus sayth,
li. 4. Anglice historie, that false relygyon &amp;
counterfett presthode, was than throughlye
satled and placed there, the Actes of
the, iiij generall counsels receyued in stede
of the .iiij. Euāgelies.Synodus generalis. In the next yeare
folowinge, was a generall Synode
kepte at Constātynople in Grece, where
as marryage was for euer permytted
vnto the Greke prestes, and vtterly forbidden
the latynes, or all other besydes
thē,Masse. the latyne masse receyuynge there
hys first confirmacyon. But Theodorꝰ
&amp; hys monkes were at a good indyfferēt
poynt for that, which had veyled within

one mounsterye in the Ile of Thanete
lxx.Mildreda. Nonnes, makynge fayre Myldrede
their abbasse. Loke Iohā Capgraue Ranulphe
and other Englyshe autors. In spyght
of the former Acte,Vitiza. ded Vitiza the kynge
of Spayne, permytt hys prestes by a lawe
newlye made, to kepe so manye concubynes
as they wolde. Michael Ricius de
regibus Hispanie, et Paulus Constantinus Phrigio
in Chronicis regnorum.
               
            
            
               ¶Chastyte, Monkes, Monasteryes,
and Penaunce.
               
                  VVernerus Cartusiensis sayth, in Fasciculo
temporum,
                  Chastyte fre. that vowynge of chastyte
was fre without constraynt,
in the tyme of Saynt Gregorye &amp; sumwhat
after. Bedas reporteth li. 3. Ca. 6. De
gestis Anglorum, et Ioannes Maior in gestis
Scotorum li 2 Ca. 11. That a monkes cowle,
after they had ones vowed chaſtyte,
was holden in soche reuerēce, that no mā
wolde in a maner than iourneye, vnlesse
he had their blessynges Into a most wonderfull
madnesse were the people than
brought,Hypocresye worketh by their hypocrytycall wytcherye,
the verye elect persones scant fre
from that dampnable errour. Matth. 24.
Marci. 13. For the vnthankefulnesse of
men (sayth Iob) in settynge hys veryte
lyght, doth God permytt the Hypocrytes
to reigne ouer them in all power of
deceytfull wonders. Iob. 34. 2. Thessal. 2.

They ded than spedelye set vp monasteryes
without nōbre,Monasteryes. all the realme ouer.
Iohan Hardynge sayth in hys Chronycle,
that kynge Oswye buylded within Nor
thumberlande.oswius. xij. in one years space. In
the yeare of our lorde. DC. and .lxxxiiij.684.
helde Theodorus yet an other counsell
in the North partyes at Twyforde,Synodus. where
as he publyshed a serten boke of hys
owne makynge, called A penytencyall
summe, commaundynge hys clergye to
put yt euerye where in practyse. Therin
were contayned all maner of synnes and
excesses, with aggrauacyons,Sūma peniten
                     
                        •
                     ialis. reseruacyons,
penaltees, sorowes, penuaunces, and
ponnyshmentes. And thys was to terryfye,
captyue, and snare the wretched cō
                  scyences
of men, euen to vttre desperacy
on. And where coude haue bene sought
out a practyse of more deuylyshnesses Sigebertus,
Sabellicus, Tritemius, et Scriptores
ferme omnes.
               
            
            
               ¶The foundacyon of their Purgatorye.
               AT the same verye tyme, was there
one Drithelmus in Northumberlande,
whiche leauynge both wyfe
and chyldrē in the yeare of our lorde
.DC. and .lxxi.Drithelmꝰ 671. made hymselfe a monke
at Mailros, Saynt Cuthbert thā beynge
abbot there. The sayd Drithelmus
fayned hymselfe on a tyme to be dead

there was knauerye vpon knauerye)
and reported in hys returne,Foūdacyon of purgatorye. that he had
seane by an Angels demōstracyon, both
purgatorye ād paradyse, hell and heauē.
After that he had subtylly declared this
vnto kynge Alphrede and other great
men of the contreye there, at the request
of the monkes, moche people resorted
vnto hym for counsell for their sowles
from all quarters of Englande. So redye
are the foles of thys worlde to heare
lyes and illusyons,Illusyons. whiche neuer had
loue to the veryte. Thys knaue euermore
commended vnto them confessyon ād
penaunce,Confessyon. fastynge, prayer, and almes
dedes, specyallye and aboue all other,
masse saynges,Masses ād monasteryes buyldynge.
Was not thys thynke yow, a vertuouse
christyanyte of these chast fathers,
to begynne their holye churche with?
Were yt not pytie but they were canonysed
sayntes, and their feastfull dayes
solempnysed twyse in the yeare,Canonysed deuyls? with
ryngynges, syngynges, sensynges, and
massynges, as thys Cuthbertes were
and are yet to thys daye? I thynke the
Turkes churche had neuer more knaues
to their Sayntes thā these. For thys
Drithelmus ys one of their sayntes also.
Iohan Capgraue post uitam Adriani,
Sigebertus, Vincencius, Antoninus, with
dyuerse other,
            
            
               
               ¶Chastyte of Cuthbert and doctryne
of Colfride.
               SO cruell was thys Cuthberte
vnto women,Cuthbertus. after he became a
Saynt of theirs, that nō myght
come within hys sayntuaryes (they say)
at Doilwein, Coruen, and Mailros in
Scotlande, nor yet at Durham, Tynmouth,
and Lyndefarne here in Englande,
vndre payne of sodē deathe, their chā
                  bers
and selles exempted alwayes. Yet
was the seyd Cuthbert verye famylyar
in hys tyme with Ebba,Nōnes. Elsteda, &amp; Verca
.iii. holye abbasses, ād buylded for hys
pleasure, a solempne nondrye at Carliell.
Fynallye for the specyall good loue he
had vnto Verca aboue all other,Verca. he commaunded
in hys testament, that hys bodye
after hys departynge, shuld be wrapped
in the fyne lynnen clothe that she had
geuen hym. Ye maye se by thys, that these
chast fathers had their louers, and set
sumwhat by their owne precyouse bodyes.
Saynt Colfryde abbot of Girwin in
Northumberlande,Colfridus. wrote vnto Athō kynge
of the Pyctes, that yt was as necessarye
for the vowe of a monke or degre of
a prest (prestes were than no vowers) to
haue a shauen crowne for restraynt of
their lustes,Shauē crownes. as for anye christen man to
blesse hym agaynst spretes whan they come
vpō hym. What wyse lernynge thys

ys, I report me vnto yow. Yet ys yt regettred
of Bedas in hys .v. boke, De gestis
Anglorum,
                  Waldē
                   and also of Thomas Vualden in
hys volume, De sacramētalibus. ti. 9. Ca 80
to stoppe heretypkes mouthes with, besydes
that Iohan Capgraue hath sayd in yt.
            
            
               ¶The fallen starre, and .ij. Hornes of
the Beast.
               ABout thys tyme were manye wō
                  derfull
thynges seane in dyuerse
quarters of the worlde, specyallye
a great Comete or blasynge starre,A comete. which
semed with flamynges of fyre to fall into
the see, great morren folowynge both
of beast and man. Not all vnlyke was
thys to that ys described, Apoca. 8. And
betokened than (in my opynyon) both the
vttre fall of the pryncelye gouernaunce
and also the christen presthode,Regnū et sacerdotium. or of both
vndre one, as powers of one God. For
both they heynge as starres in the firmament
or powers from about. Romano. 13.
most wretchedlye than declyued frō the
true obedyence and faythfull ad ynystracyon
of Gods eternall veryte, vnto
the beastlye subieccyon and tradycyons
of that execrable Pope. Sens that tyme
haue they comen from the see. They haue
taken their autoryte of that Beast
whyche rose out of the see. Apocal. 13.Apo. 13. (tyll
now of late dayes) the .ij. hornes of the
other Beast, that is to saye, of hypocresye,

pryckynge them than forewarde.
Those.ijhornes .ij. hornes of that earthlye Beast
were here in Englande, the .ij. monkysh
sectes that in those dayes firste entered.
The first of them were the blacke monkes
of Saynt Benet, which entered first
of all with the afore named Augustyne
in the yeare of our lorde .CCCCC.Augustinus. and
xcvi.696. to peruerte the South Saxons and
kentysh men. The other were the blacke
Chanons of the other Saynt Augustyne
(both blacke) which came in with Berinus
the archebyshopp of Dorcestre in
the yeare of our lorde .DC.xxxvi.Berinꝰ from
Pope Honorius the firste,636. to deceyue the
west Saxons. For yche Pope and byshopp
preferred euermore the secte he
was of.ij. sectes These .ij. wrought so their wycked
feates in those dayes, with lyenge
sygnes in hypocresye, that they caused
the afore named starres, Regnum et Sacerdocium,
Regalyte and presthode, to fall
clerelye from heauen. Iohan Capgraue, Ranulphus,
et Polydorus.
               
            
            
               ¶The fall of kyngedoms, and rayse
of the Papacye.
               MArke in the Chronycles, and ye
shall fynde thys most true.Papacye.
That lyke as the Papacye had
hys firste rayse in and of the fall of the

Empyre, so had those kyngdomes which
firste obeyed yt, their orygynall begynnynges
of the ouerthrowe of the inferyour
kyngedomes. As Englande vndre
kyng Inas by the fall of the Brytaynes,Kyngedomes popysh
                        •
                     
                  
and Fraunce vnder kynge Pypyne by
the puttynge a syde of the Merouyngeanes.
Sens these lecherouse locustes crepte
first into Englande, neuer throue that
kyngedome of the auncyent Brytaynes
(whose spirytuall head was God alone)
but euerye daye more and more decayed,Brytaynes.
tyll yt was fullye ended. Marke yt hardelye
from the first commynge hyther of
the seyd Augustyne,cadwal tyll the yeare of our
lorde .DC.lxxxix.lader. 689. wherin Cadwallader
their last kynge dyed a most desolate pylgryme
at Rome, offerynge hymselfe vp
there most myserablye to the Pope.
               Euer sens hath yt bene to hym obedyent
in all blasphemouse errours and doe

                     •
                  ryues of Deuylles, by the space of
.DCCC. and .xliiij. years,Marke yt. 1533. tyll the yeare
of our lorde .M.D. and .xxxiij. wherin
at our noble kynges moste wholsome
request, we vtterlye by othe renounced
that odyouse monstre. Now ys yt Gods
owne fre kyngedome agayne, and our
kynge hys inmedyate mynystre. That
Lorde graunte of hys infynyte mercye,englāde
that lyke as we haue put a syde hys
name, we maye euen frome the harte

also cast ouer hys Idolatrouse yokes▪ folowynge
from henceforth the vncorrupt
rules of the Gospell. Amen. A lyke conparyson
hath Paulus Orosius, li. 2. Ca. 4. Historiarum
mundi,
                  Roma et Babilon. of Babylon and Rome.
Verye lyke begynnynges (sayth he) had
Babylon and Rome, lyke powers, lyke
prydes, lyke contynuaunces, lyke fortunes,
and lyke ruynes, sauynge onlye that
Rome arose of the fall of Babylon, and
so fourth.
            
            
               ¶An olde prophecye of Merlyne
dysclosed.
               AS I was in wrytynge thys matter
an olde prophecye of Merlyne came
vnto my remembraunce.Merlyne. That
after the manyfolde irrupcyons of straungers,
the kynges of thys realme shuld
be ones agayne crowned with the Dyademe
of Brute,Brute. and beare hys auncyent
name, the newe name of straungers so
vanyshynge awaye. He that applyeth
vnto thys a ryght vnderstandynge, ſhall
fynde yt verye true. The dyademe of
Brute ys the pryncelye power of thys
whole regyō,of God inmedyatlye geuē of God
without anye other meane mastrye worker
to Antichristes behoue. F
                     •
                  re was that
power f
                     •
                  m the great whores domynyon
(which ys the Rome churche) tyll the
vyolēt conquest of the Englysh Saxōs▪
                  Saxōs.
whiche they had of the Brytaynes for

their iniquitees sake▪ And now (prayse
be vnto that Lorde) yt is in good waye to
that fredō agayne, &amp; wold fully attayne
therunto, were her heythnysh yokes in
relygyō ones throwne a syde, as I doubt
yt not but they will be within short space.
As wele maye ye geue credēce to this
Merlyne whan he vttered the veryte,Merlyne. as
vnto olde Balaam the sothsayer,Balaā
                     ▪
                   which
at a tyme prophecyed the commynge of
Christ. Numeri 24. And as concernynge
the returne of the name, marke in this age
the wrytinges of lerned men, and ye
shall wele perceyue the change, for now
cōmonlye do they write vs for Englysh
men, Brytaynes.
            
            
               ¶The whores fleshe eaten of the x.
hornes.
               THe .x. hornes of the first Beast
(which were kyngedomes maynteynynge
that whore (now ioyned
all into one,The .x. hornes of the Beast▪
                   doth mortallye hate her at
this present instaunt▪ &amp; ys makynge her
desolate and naked in Englande. In the
ende they shall eate her fleshe, and clerelye
cōſume her with the fyre appoynted.
Englande was sumtyme into .vij. kyngedomes
deuyded, by the consent of all writers,
and wales into .ij. called Cambria &amp;
Demecia or north wales &amp; South wales;
Irelande makynge vp the tenth. Or yf

ye holde wales but for one, lete Scotlande supplye that rowme, which oweth
vnto Englande perpetuall homage. As
all these are now in one most worthye &amp;
vyctoryouse Kynge but one, so wyll
God put into all their hartes one consēt
to fulfyll hys will, and to geue her kyngedome
vnto the Beast, or to sende yt agayne
to the Deuyll from whens yt first
came. Apoca.
                  Apo. 17 17 Consydre with your selues
the late ouerthrowe of the monasteryes,
couentes, collegys, and chaunteryes,
alleages of vncleane spretes, and holdes
of most hatefull byrdes by the manyfest
worde of God. And thynke not but
the fylthye habytacyons of the great mastre
deuyls wyll folowe sone after. Apoc.
18.Apo. 18 Lete the gogle eyed Gardyner of wyncestre
gyrde at yt tyll hys rybbes ake, ād
an hondred dyggynge deuyls vpon hys
syde,Wynker of wyles yet shall not one Iote of the Lordes
promes be vnfulfylled at the tyme appoynted
for that blasphemouse whores
ouerthrowe, hys most holye mother.
Praye in the meane season (good christen
readers) praye, praye, praye, that hys heauenlye wyll be done in earthe and not
mannys, and fashyon your lyues to the
fourme of hys most dere sonne Iesus
Christes doctryne. Amen.
            
            
               ¶Actes of vowed virgynyte for that
age.
               
                  
NOw to returne agayne to their
spirytuall actes of chastyte for
that age.Sedia. Whā one Sedia the father
of saynt Aidꝰ, perceyued that he by
no meanes coude haue a chyld by hys wyfe,
he brought her to these cōtynēt fathers
for remedy of her barrennesse, &amp; she was
spedde the next nyght after by a myracle,
for all were myracles they ded. Ioā Cap,
                  Guenhera
Guenhera a Cornysh woman (whom some wryters call fayre Elyne) that made
Kynge Arthure a cuckolde, was after
hys death deuoutelye receyued into Ambesburye
nondrye, as a penitent to their
spirytuall vse.Oswaldus. 
                  Guilhelmus Malmesburye.
Saynt Oswalde layed hys wyfe Bebla
in bed with a relygyouse hermyte.Bebla And
whan the great heate came vpō hym (as
the spirytuall fathers are haſtye 
                     •
                  he founde
the meanes that he was cast in colde
water to abate hys hote corage. This
is one of the holy actes whervpō the pope
hath made the seyd Oswalde a saynt.
Iohan Hardyng.
                  Ebba. Saynt Ebba which was
in those dayes the mother of all nonnes,
was generate of an whore, as were all
her fathers chyldren besydes her ij. of thē
onlye excepted. This Ebba had in the
monasterye of Coldyngham not farre
from Barwyck, both men &amp; womē dwel
lynge togyther sell by sell) as the maner
was than of all Nondryes in Englande)
which exercysed the battayles of chastyte

so longe, that in their nyght metynges
they went to bed togyther by couples,
their relygyouse loue was than so great,
tyll God sent a wylde fyre vpon them
for that contempt of marryage. Ionnes
Maior. libro secundo. Capittulo. 12. &amp; Ioannes
Capgraue.
               
            
            
               ¶A spirytuall conueyaunce to be
marked.
               ETheldred (whom ye call Saynt Audrye
of helye) marryed .ij.Etheldreda great
prynces, Tombert of the South
Girwyes, and Egfride the Kynge of Northumberlande,
mockynge them both by
the space of more than .xiij. years, in not
geuynge them due beneuolence accordinge
to the holye doctryne of saynt Paule
1. Cor. 7. And in occasyonynge them to aduouterouse
lyuynge. The lattre of them
knowynge that she mynded wilfryde thā
Byshop of yorke moche more than hym
(for the storye sayth that she loued that
monke aboue all the men lyuynge) requyred
hym in Gods behalfe to admonysh
her of her dewtye,Wilfridus. that he myght accordynge
to hys lawes haue increase of successyon
by her. And he lyke a false traytour
knaue, not withstandynge hys promes
to the contrarye,Knauerye. persuaded her to
perseuer in her obstynacye and vtterlye
to resyst hym, allegynge her vowe and

requyrynge a diuorcement from hym.
Wherupon he was than compelled to
marrye an other wyfe, called Ermenburgis,
and Eteldrede was professed a Nonne
in Coldynghā with Ebba, by the seyd
wilfryde. This Kynge after that perceyuynge
hys knauerye,Theodorus by assent of Theodorus
the archebyshop of Caunterburye,
bannyshed hym out of hys lande. Than
folowed she after a pace, and whyls he
was byshop of Eastsexe,A waytynge hounde. she bycame abbasse
of hely, not farre from hys elboue,
Marke this conueyaunce for your seruynge.
If this were not knauerye, where
shall we fynde knauerye: Yet was this
gētylmii cōueyer admytted for a saynte,
bycause he buylded a college at Rippon,
where my selfe was ones bayted of his
Basan bulles,The autour. for maynteynynge the
Kynges prerogatyue agaynst theyr Pope,
as good mastre Iohā Hercye can full
wele tell. Ioannes Capgraue in uitis Etheldre
de, &amp;. Vuilfridi.
               
            
            
               ¶Kynges became pylgrymes, and
their wyues Nonnes.
               A Verye proper cast the womē had
in those dayes, by the ghostly
counsell of the prelates.Pylgrimes. They sēt
theyr husbandes to Rome on pylgrymage
by heapes, whyls they kept them spyrituall

cōpanye at home. Ethelburge made
great hast and left no callynge on, tyll
her husbande Kynge Inas was thydrewardes,Inas
with scrippe hatte and staffe, she
lokynge for hys nomore comynge home
in the abbeye of Berkynge, This Inas
became a monke there, and was the first
that clogged the west Saxons with payment
of the Rome shott, or Peter Pens
to the Pope. Volateranus, and Fabiane. After
hym folowed Ethelrede Kynge of
Mercia in lyke fashyon of Pylgrymage,Ethelredus.
and became afterwarde abbot of Bardeneye.
Iohan Capgraue.
                  Cōredꝰ Conredus also
Kynge of the same prouynce, dyed a solys
he monke at Rome. So ded Kynge Offa
of the East Saxons,Offa the selfe same yeare
of our Lorde .DCC. and .ix.709 besydes Kē
                  redus,Kenredus
Ethelwolphus, and a great sort
more. Hermannus Contractus, Platina &amp; Polidorus.
Colwolphus Kynge of Northūberlande,Colwolphus
returned agayne to Gyrwyn, and
there dyed a monke. Robert Fabiane, Great
layser wolde yt requyre, to shewe here
how manye of soche Kynges, the ghostlye
fathers sent at dyuerse seasons vnto
Rome, that they for the tyme myght haue
the spirytuall occupyenge of their wyues,
and how manye of their owne bastardes
they made Kynges for them.Bastardes.
And therfor at this tyme I passe them
ouer. Innumerable knaueryes wrought

they in those dayes, and all vndre the coloure
of vowed chastyte.
            
            
               ¶Great experymentes of virgynyte.
               AS Saynt Aldelmus,Adelmus. the byshop of
Sherborne (that ye now call Salysburye)
chaunced to be at Rome, the
people there made a fowle exclamacyon
vpon Pope Sergius the first, for begettynge
a wenche with chylde, which he
(they saye) by a lytle straunge workynge
pacyfyed.Synodus In whose returne, a Synode
was holden in Englande agaynst the
Brytaynes or welche men, for not cōformynge
their churches to the Romysh obseruacyons,
he there requyred to inueye
agaynst them. Vpon the which mocyon,
he wrote than two bokes,ij. bokes one for the Eastre
celebracyon, and an other in the prayse
of virgynes, to blemyshe the marriage
of their prestes there, and also to aduaunce
their newlye professed chastyte. For
that he had also in commaundement of
Sergius,Sergius. not withstandynge hys owne
knowne lecherye. This Aldelmus neuer
refused women, but wolde haue them cō
                  mōlye
both at borde and at bedde, to mocke
the deuyll with. In the tyme he was
abbot of Malmesbury, he appoynted oft
tymes to hys fleshe this martyrdō. As he
felte any sore mouynges therof, he layed
by him naked, the fairest mayde he coude

lōge tyme as an whole Dauids pſalter
was in saynge. And whan hys heate
was past, he sent her home agayne as
good a mayde as he left her. Is not thys
(thynke you) a stronge argument to proue
that all prestes maye lyue chast? This
telleth Bedas, Ranulphus, Iohan Capgraue, ād
manye other Englishe Autours more.
            
            
               ¶Images admytted, with chast
examples.
               ABout the same tyme,Egwinus saynt Egwine
abbot of Euesham, and byshop
of Worcestre (than called wyckes)
hearynge tell that labour was made to
the pope, to haue the christen temples replenyshed
with Images,Images to promote that
markett forewarde, he hyed hym apace
to Rome. And there he declared to the
holye father, the secrete reuelacyons and
commaundementes of our ladye that he
had, to sett vp an Image of her to be worshypped
at Worcestre,Ladye of worcestre. delyuerynge hym
a boke which he had wrytten of the same
apparycyons, besydes the lyfe of Aldelme.
The pope than called Constantyne
the first, hearynge this newe wondre
sent hym home agayne with his bulles
of autoryte,Brithwaldus cōmaundinge Brithwalde
than Archebyshop of Caunterburye
(wythe all hast) to call a generall

Synode of all the clergye for confirmacyon
of the same,sinodꝰ the kynges requyred
not to be absent that daye. And thy
                     •
                  
was done in the yeare of our lorde. Dcc
and .ix.709. Thys Brithwalde beynge also a
monke, was the first Englysh man that
was Archebyshopp of Caunterburye.
Marke yt. Saynt Guthlake an hermyte
of Rependon,Guthlacus. tolde a serten abbot the same
tyme, that goynge homewarde, he
shuld fynde in a wydowes howse .ij. of
hys holye monkes whych had lyen with
her the nyght afore for easement of their
chastyte.Bartellinus. Saynt Bartellyne hermyte of
Stalforde, stale out of Irelande the kynges
doughter there. And as she was afterwarde
trauelynge of chylde in a forest,
whyls he was sekynge the mydwyfe,
a wolfe came and deuoured both her
and her chylde. These storyes hath at large
Iohan Capgraue in Catalogo sanctorum Anglie,
Guilhelmus Malmesburye et Ranulphus.
               
            
            
               ¶Englysh monkes become Antichristes
Apostles.
               IN those dayes the mōkes of Englande
were becomen so myghtye
in superstycyouse lernynge,Mōkes Dyſpersed. that
they were able to peruert all other christen
regyons, as they ded than in dede.
Some of them went into Germanye, some
into Fraunce, some into Italye and
Spayne, and became the Popes instrumentes

of all falshed, falshyonynge hym
vp there a newe kyngedome of all deuylyshnesse
to withstande the manyfest glorye
of God, and subduynge therunto all
pryncelye Powers. Yow that are exercysed
in Chronycles and Sayntes Lyues,
marke for that age what ys written of
Columbanus, Colomannus, Totimannus, Vuenefridus,
Vuilibrordus,
                  The popes apostles. 
                  Vuilibaldus, Vuenebaldus,
Burghardus, kilianus, Vuigbertus, Egbertus,
Heuualdus the whyght and the blacke,
Etto, Bertuuinus, Eloquius, Lullius, Lebuinus,
Liuinus, Ioānes, Embertus, Gallus, Gaudus, Ga
                     
                        •
                     abaldus,
Gregorius, Megingolus, Sturmio,
and a great sort more with their women,
and ye shall se in them practyses wonderfull.
I wyll geue ye out one here breuelye
for an example, for to moche yt were
to write of them all.Wenefridus. Wenefridus was
admytted of Pope Gregorye the seconde,
for the Archebyshop of Magunce &amp;
great Apostle of all Germanye, and for
hys bolde countenaunce was of hym named
Bonifacius.
                  Bonifacius. In London was he first
borne, and professed a blacke Monke at
Cissancestre (now called Chichestre)
vndre abbot wolfharde. After the great
Synode holden at London by the afore
named Brithwalde,Synodus. about the yeare
of our Lorde .DCC. and .x.710. where as
prestes Marryage was iudged fornycacyon,
and the honourynge of Images

accepted for a christen relygyon.Daniel Daniel
than Byshopp of Wynchestre, sent thys
wenefride to Rome with hys letters of
commendacyon for hys manfulnesse there
shewed. Iohannes Capgraue. et Georgius
Vuicelius in Hagiologo de sanctis
ecclesie.
               
            
            
               ¶The great Apostle
of all Germanye.
               THe Pope after certen conmunycacyons,
perceyuynge hym in all
poyntes fytt for hys purpose,apostle of Germanye.
sent hym anon into Germanye with
hys fulle autoryte (as afore ys specyfyed)
to do hys false feates there, and
to brynge that styffe necked people vndre
hys wycked obedyence, whom they
call the holye Christen beleue. I thynke
sens Christes incarnacyon was there
neuer non that more lyuelye wrought
the Propertees of the other Beaste in
Saynt Iohans Apocalyps,Alia Bestia Apo. 13. whyche ryse
out of the earthe hauynge .ij. hornes
lyke the lambe, yf ye marke yf wele.
Apocal. in the .13. chapter. For he was
next in autoryte to the Pope, by the Popes
owne witnesse, soche tyme as he came
with the hyghe legacye from hys
owne ryght syde, into all the quarters
and Prouynces of the seyd Germanye.

                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
hym concernynge vowed chastyte, rellyques,
Images, the Popes prymacye,
Kynges deposycyons, othes breakynge,
and soche lyke errours.errours Loke the workes
of Nauclerus, Vuicelius, Bernardus Lutzenburg,
and Alphonsus de castro.
               
            
            
               ¶Doctryne of Bonyface, with sale
of whores.
               MOst dampnable was the doctryne
of thys Bonyface,Doctryne. concernynge
the Pope. In a sertē Epystle
of hys we fynde thys most execrable
sentence. That in case the seyd Pope were
of most fylthye lynynge, and so forgetfull
of hym self and of the whole christente,
that he ledde with hym to hell innumerable
sowles, yet ought no man to
rebuke hys yll doynge. For he (he sayth)
hath power to iudge all men, and ought
of no man to be iudged agayne. Thys
haue the Canonystes regestred in the popes
decrees for a perpetuall lawe,Canonystes. and
for a necessarye artycle of Christen beleue.
Dist. xl Ca. Si Papa. Yet wrote he at another
tyme to Pope Zacharye, to se the
manyfest abusyons of Rome reformed,Rome.
specyallye their maskynges in the nyght
after the paganes maner,Opē sale of whores. and their open
sellynge of whores in the markett there.
For they were (he sayd) sore impedymentes
to hys preachynges. For they that
had seane those reuelynges there, mystrusted

moche that faythe. He wrote also vnto
kynge Ethelbalde and other great mē
in Englande,Ethelbaldus. requyrynge them to leaue
the aduouterouse occupyenge of nōnes,
least soche a plage fell on thē, as chaūced
vpō kynge Colfrede and kynge Ofrede
for lyke doynges.
                  Colfredus. Osredus. And though thys Bonyface
allowed not christē matrymonye
in prestes but hated yt, yet after that one
Geraldus a marryed byshop was slayne
in Thuringia in tyme of the warres there,geraldꝰ
he permytted hys sonne Geilepus to
succede hym in that offyce.geilepꝰ 
                  Helinādus monachus,
Vincēcius, Antoninus, Capgraue. &amp;c.
               
            
            
               ¶The monasteryes of fulda &amp; floryake.
               HE buylded the great monastery
of Fulda in Germanye,Fulda. in the
yeare frō Christes incarnacyon
.DCC. &amp; .xliiij.744. Into the which no womē
myght entre, but onlye Lieba &amp; Tecla .ij
Englysh nonnes hys best beloues.Lieba. The
bodye of the seyd Lieba, he commaunded
by hys lyfe, of most tēdre loue, to be buryed
in one graue with hys owne precyouse
body.Monasterium fuldēse. So rytche was that monasterye
within fewe years after, that yt was
able to fynde the ēprour in hys warres
.lx. thousāde mē. For the which the abbot
had alwayes thys pryuylege, to syt vpō
the ryght hande of the seyd emproure at
the hygh feastes. An other abbeye was
buylden afore that at floriake in fraunce,Floriacus.
                  
and not farre from orlyaunce, in the yeare
of our lorde .DC.li.651. These .ij. monasteryes
floriake and fulda with their olde
inhabytauntes, wolde I counsell all Chronycle
readers to marke, as they fall in
their waye, for wonders whiche hath comen
from thens, as wyll apere after. A
custome the holye fathers had in those
dayes,To ease their vowes. to leade nonnes aboute with thē
in straunge lādes where they went. As
we reade of walburga, Hadeloga, Lieba
and soche other. I thynke yt was to helpe
thē to beare their chastyte, whose carryage
was sumtyme verye comberouse
vnto them, and they founde not than in
all contreyes soche plentye of Nondryes
as hath bene sens. Sigebertus, Capgraue, Tritemius,
Nauclerus, Vuicelius.
               
            
            
               ¶Oxforde shurned. And Aleuinus
monkes.
               AShamed are not these prestygyouse Papystes, to vtter yt in their
storyes and reade yt in their Sayntes
legendes, in contempt of their christē
gouernours, that no kynge maye entre
the towne of oxforde without a myschefe,Oxforde
bycause one Algar a Prynce aboute
thys age wolde haue had Saynt frideswyde
to wyfe.Frideswyde. As though to be a kynge
were a farre vyler or vnworthyer offyce,
than to be a pylde shytten Nonne.
O blynde bludderynge Balaamytes,

without all iudgementes godlye. Of
God only ys the worthy office of a Kyng.A Kynge.
                  Prouer. 8. where as your fystynge Nōnes,
were of Antichrist ād the deuyll. Capgraue,
Fabiane, Polidorus. Aboute the same tyme,
was Alcuinus a doctour of Englande,
made abbot of Turonia in Fraunce
by the gyft of Charles the great,Alcuinus. which
on a nyght founde all his monkes dead
in the dorter, by the soden stroke of God
for their Sodometrye, one only excepted.
Odo cluniacensis, Guilhelmus Malmesburye
Vincencius, Antoninus, Ranulphus, &amp; Capgraue
post uitam Ythamari.
                  Autours. A great matter had
yt bene in the popes bokes, yf these men
had had wyues. For thā he coud not haue
sent them to the deuyll so fast, accordynge
to generall commyssyō, which he had
of Sathan hys great mastre; in that vycarshypp
of hys.
            
            
               ¶Englyshe men ponnyshed at Rome.
               AFter Kynge Ethelwolphe beynge
subdeacon,Ethelwolphꝰ through wanton occupyenge
had had a bastarde, by the
popes dyspensacyō he marryed Osburga
hys butlers doughter, and had by her
iiij. sonnes, which all succeded Kynges after
hym. Guilhelmus Malmesburye, &amp; Ioannes
Harding. As this Kynge on a tyme
chaunced to be at Rome, he se manye Englysh
men there wearynge fetters and gyues

                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
delyuered of chylde without mydwyfe
and so dyed. Wherin God declared manyfestlye
to the worlde, that their glytie
rynge churche was altogyther an whore,An whore.
to make good that was written in the
reuelacyon of Saynt Iohan. Apo. 17. Oh
he that had seane the coūtenaunce of the
prelates than, shuld haue beholden a great
change.
            
            
               ¶Popes chosen from thens fourth
by their. N.
               SEns that tyme hath popes alwayes
bene chosen,Popes chosen by their stones as stoned horse
are in a colte feyer, by their
dontye dymyceryes, that they can nomore
be deceyued that waye. For at the solempne
stallynge of them, the last deacon
Cardynall doth grope them brechelesse,
at an hole made in the seate for that ghostlye
purpose, and than cryeth yt out before
all the multytude, that he hath ware
suffycyent to proue hym no woman. More
ouer the strete where she was delyuered,
hath euer sens bene shurned in all generall
processyons, for feare of yll happes.An exā
                     ple.
As ys of women a sexten brydge in
a Scottyshe Ile called Leuissa, where as
yf but one woman shuld passe ouer (they
saye) there are no salmons seane in that
ryuer, all the yeare after. Hector Boethius
in Scotici regni descriptione. For the hystorye
afore reherced of this woman Pope,

was yt partlye my desyre that ye shuld
marke that monasterye of fulda.Fulda For she
was one chast frute of our Englyshe clergye,
yssuynge from thens, ye maye chaū
                  ce
after this yet to heare of more. Soche
an enemye to prestes marryage was not
in hys tyme, as was that Boniface,
which was therof the first buylder. For
euerye where ded he, in all his generall
Synodes,Matrimonye cōdempned. condempne yf for aduouterye
by the popes canon lawes, For the scripturs
wolde not serue hym. The lyfe of
this female pope sheweth more at large,
Iacobus Bergomas in li. De claris mulieribus,
Platina, Sabellicus, Martinus Carsulanus, Volateranus,
Nauclerus, Mantuanus, Iohannes Stella,
Ioannes textor, &amp; Robertus Barnes in uitis
Romanorum Pontificum.
               
            
            
               ¶Holye water, with a boke agaynst
marryage.
               IN the yeare of our Lord .DCCC.
LVIII.858 as a serten daydeuyll at
the forsayd Maguncia was hunted
of the prestes with processyon and holye
water,A prest. for dyuerslye vexynge the cytie,
he hyd hym selfe for feare (they saye) vndre
one of the prestes copes▪ saynge. He
myght wele be bolde there, consyderynge
he had by hym the fleshlye occupyenge
of the generall proctours doughter
there. This relygyouse example of holye
churche sheweth Sigebertus, Vincencius, Antoninus,

                        〈2 pages missing〉
                     
                     
Capgraue in uita Etheldrede. Ethelstanus a
monke,Ethelstanꝰ a monke maryed at one tyme takynge presthode
with Dunstane and Ethelwolde, within
a whyle after left all hys orders and
toke hym to a wyfe. Wherfor they prophecyed
of hym that hys ende shulde be
myserable. And bycause they wolde apere
no false Prophetes, they inchaunted
hym, charmed hym, and changed hym in
to an ele,A myracle. and so he lyued in the water
euer after with a great sort more of hys
companye. Wherupon (they saye) that
monasterye and towne hath euer sens bene
called Elye.Elye. 
                  Guilhelmus Malmesburye et
Ioannes Capgraue. A yonge infante called
Brithgina,Brithgina. beynge nomore than one daye
olde, professed Elphegus into the monasterye
of wylton aboute the same tyme.
So ded he also an other called Wilfhilda,
into the nondrye of Wynchestre,
so sone as she was weaned from sucke.
Whom afterwarde kynge Edgare claymed
in marryage,Wilfhilda. but she was to famylyer
with Ethelwolde a monke and a
bysshop, to graunt therunto. Whan he
came to the howse where she was afterwarde
abbasse, there was no small fyllynge
in of cuppes, Ioannes Capgraue.
               
            
            
               ¶Miracles and wonders
wrought.
               
                  
VVhan Odo the Byshopp of Salysburye

                     •
                  as elected Archebyshopp
of Caunterburye in the
yeare of our lorde .DCCCC. and .xlvi.Odo.
he wolde in no case be consecrated,946. tyll
he was by the abbot of Floriake professed
a monke.Floriacus. Partlye bycause all hys predecessours
in that seate to the nombre of
.xxi. had bene monkes, and partlye for
that the prestes in those dayes were in
hate of the people for their marryage at
the monkes suggestyons. And after he
had receyued hys palle with Antichristes
autoryte from Rome,the kynges concubines he wexed so
frantyck vpon the kynges concubynes,
that some of them he sealed in the faces
with hote burnynge Irons most shamefullye,
and some of them he bannyshed
into Irelande for euer, but vnto hys owne
store he was gentyll ynough. For
most haynouse heresye helde he than the
christen marryage of prestes, and made
synodall constytucyons agaynst yt, to
enryche the mōkes through that craftye
colour with their great possessyons.Constytucyōs. Hys
neuye Oswalde founde he to scole at
floryake the welsprynge of Necromancye,Oswalde.
to lerne there all craftye seyences.Floriacus.
In hys tyme was a stryfe amonge
the clergye at Caunterburye, for
Christes fleshe and bloode in the Sacramente,
the prestes most ernestly affyrmynge

yt to remayne styll breade 
                     〈◊〉
                  
an onlye fygure of Christes bodye,The sacramēt. and
the monkes to be Christes essencyall bodye,
yea Christ hymselfe. But whā scripturs
fayled ones vpon the monkes syde▪
they were dryuen to false myracles o
                     •
                  
playne experymentes of sorcerye. For
Odo by a cast of legerdemayne, shewed
vnto the people a broken host bledynge,Myracles.
as a popishe prest called sir Nicolas Gerues
ded a. ij. years a go in Surreye, by
pryckynge hys fyngar with a pynnne.
            
            
               ¶Monkerye augmented by Dunstane.
               SAynt Dunstane here in Englā
                  de
beynge taught of Iryshe mō
                  kes
at Glastenburye,Dunstanus magnꝰ. was founde
verye connynge in wāton musyck,
in sorcerye, and in Image makynge out
of all maner metals, stone, and kyndes
of wode. By these and soche lyke occupyenges,
he founde the meanes to augmēt
and enryche the monasteryes of mōkes
and nonnes euerye where whithin Englande,
not withstandynge he had oft tymes
moche a do with deuyls and with
women. Yet had he at length these pryuyleges
than aboue all other spirytuall
doers. He wanne by hys musyck and fayre
speche,musyck the good fauer of dyuerse women,
yea, of some whiche had bene the
kynges cōcubynes, as Alfgyne, wilfrith

and soche other, though he afore had put
them to paynes. By hys sorceryes,sorcerye he
alwayes made the kynges fytt for hys
ghostlye purpose, as wyll apere herafter,
specyallye by kynge Edmonde that
was Ethelſtanes brother, whom by hys
necromancye he brought to the poynte,
inuysysyblye to haue bene torne in peces.
What he gote by hys Image makynge,Caruynge.
the scripture sheweth playne, whiche
curseth both the hande and the instrument
of the Image maker. Sapi. 14. and
Deutro. 27. Thys storye declareth more
at large Osbertus monachus in uita Dunstani,
Vincencius. li. 24. Ca. 74. Antoninus par. 2.autours
                  
                     
                        •
                     i. 16. Ca. 6. Martanus Scotus, Guilhelmus Malmesburiensis, Ranulphus Cestrensis li. 6. Cap.
10. Volateranus, Bergomas, Nauclerus, Iohan
Capgraue, Iohan hardynge Vuyllyam Caxton,
Iohan 1. yd gate, and Robert Fabyane.
               
            
            
               The relygyouse Occupyenge of
Dunstane.
               AS Dunstane in the howse of a wydowe
was fashyonynge a prestes
stoole, hys harpe hangynge vpon
the wall without towchynge sownded
the note of Gaudent in celis.
                  A caste or feate. Wherupon
the wenches astoyned, went out of the
howse with the wydowe &amp; all her howsholde,
proclamynge yt a brode, that he
had moche more lernynge thā was good.
For thys &amp; soche lyke feates, ſerten men tolde

                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
I thynke thys playe sumwhat passed course
legerdemayne. After that was Dū
                  stane
the hygh stewarde of hys howse, &amp;
had ouer all the realme a iurysdycyon.
Of Glastenburye was he put in perpetuall
possessyon,Glastē
                     burye. to make therof what he
wolde. And so bycame yt first of all
Saynt Benettes patrymonye. Antedicti
Autores. Lete all the Popes armye stande
vp here, and allowe thys styll for a myracle,
as they haue done hytherto in hys
legende, yet do not I doubt to proue yt
agaynst them all, abhomynable knauerye
by the scripturs.
            
            
               ¶He vexeth kynge Edwyne, retaynynge
hys concubyne.
               AS kynge Edwyne vpon the daye
of hys coronacyon occupyed Alfgina
hys concubyne, hauynge thā
non other wyfe,Edwinus. alfgina Dunstane beynge at
that tyme but a mōke and abbot of Glastenburye,
plucked them both vyolentlye
from the bedde, and brought their before
the Archebyshopp Odo,Odo cā
                     tuariensis. threttenynge
the woman suspensyon, ye maye call
yt hangynge yf ye wyll. For the whyche
the kynge after that exyled the seyd Dū
                  stane
into Flanders, &amp; wrought the monkes
manye other dyspleasurs, tyll they
founde the meanes to depose hym, by the
vertu of eare confessyon.Confession. 
                  Voleteranus. li. 3
Geographic, Osbertus, Vincencius, Antoninus,

Guilhelmus Ranulphus &amp; Ioannes Capgraue.
Yet in the conclusyon (they saye) he
delyuered Kynge Edwynes sowle, after
he was dead, from hell (I praye God
he kylled hym not afore) and vanquyshed
all the deuyls there by vertu of a Requiem
masse,Masse of requiem. so bryngynge hym into
their purgatorye. This was (I trowe)
no badde ware. As a serten noble womā
called Alfgina (the Kynges former concubine
I feare me) possessynge great substaunce,alfgina loueth.
had ones commoned with Dunstane,
she so delyghted in hys fayre wordes
(for hys aduauntage) that she wolde
neuer after from hym, but dwell with
hym styll for terme of lyfe.Strōge loue. She left her
owne howse and buylded her an habytacyon
by the churche, louynglye intertaynynge
men of holye orders. In conclusyon
whan she departed the worlde, she
left her great coffers and treasure bagges
with Dūstane to dyspose for her soule
(she had hearde of Kynge Edwyne)
with the which he after that buylded fyne
monasteryes. Ioan. Cap. in Cat. sāc. An.
               
            
            
               ¶Dunstane kepeth the Kynges of
Englande vndre.
               DVnstane was excedyngly beloued
with Cadina Kynge Eldredes
mother (these are the playne
wordes,Cadina loueth. of the hystory) &amp; he loued her excedynglye
agayne. And whā he ones became

                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
lyke vnto the tyrannye of these spirituall
Antichristes, thus cruellye handelynge,
a man that ys dead. This sheweth more
at large, Liuthprandus Ticinensis▪ li. 2. Capi.
13.autours 
                  ac li. 3 Cap, 12. rerum Europicarum. Blondus
Flauius, Baptista Platina, Ioannes Stella, Abbas
Vrspergensis, Ptolomeus Lucensis, Vincencius,
Antoninus, Bergomas &amp; alij.
               
            
            
               ¶The chastyte of holye churche there.
               THeodora a most execrable whore,Theora cum filiabus
and aduonterouse mother to the
forsayd Marozia ād theodora the
yongar (both vnshamefast whores also)
so burned in concupiscens of the bewtye
of one Iohan Rauennas a prest,Ioānes Rauennas, than sēt
in massage to the pope by Peter the Archebyshop
of Rauenna, that she not only
moued hym, but also compelled hym to
lye with her, ād so become her peramoure
dere. This whore for hys lecherouse
occupyenge of her, made him
first Byshop of Bononye, than Archebyshop
of hys owne natyue cytye Rauē
                  na,
and fynallye Saynt Peters vycar in
Rome, called Iohan the .x.Ioan the .x pope of that
name, that she myght at all tymes haue
hys companye nygher home. This was
done in the yeare of our Lorde. DCCCC.
and. xv.915 and he gouerned the papacye
there .xiij. years and more. Liuthprandus
Ticinensis li. 2. Dap. 13. rerum per Europam
gestarum. It is easye to se by this open experiment,

that she and her .ij. doughters
myght do moche in the holye college of
cardynalles.whores rule all. He that iudgeth not that
churche to be whoryshe, which was so depelye
vndre the rule of whores, that they
at their pleasure myght appoynt thervnto
what head rulers they wolde, hath lytle
good iudgement in hym, I thynke.
            
            
               ¶A popes bastarde ys made pope
               GVido the marques of Thuscia,Guido &amp; Mazozia. at
the lattre marryed Pope Sergius
whore Marozia. Which wyllynge
to preferre vnto Saynt Peters seate,
the bastarde whom she had by the
seyd Pope, caused hym to enpryson her
mothers dere peramoure Iohan the .x.
and to stoppe vp hys breathe with a pyllowe.
Immedyatlye after, which was the
yeare of our Lorde .DCCCC. ād xxix.929
was he constytute pope, and called Iohā
the xi.Ioā. xi but the same self yeare he was deposed
agayne. Wherupon she clerly left
all spirytuall occupyenge, and in displeasure
of the prelates, marryed her self loue
after her husbandes deathe to one hugh
the Kynge of Italye,Hugo rex Italie. which was her other
husbandes brother by the mothers
syde, and made hym the monarke of Rome
to recouer agayne this lost dignyte
for her bastarde. Thus shewed she her
self to be a playne Herodias, besydes her
other vnshamefast whoredomes in the spity
                  
                     •••…
                  
                  
                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
Thys holye successour of Peter and vȳ
                  car
of Christ (as they call popes) was accused
of hys Cardynalles and Byshoppes
vnto the Emprour Otho in the generall
Synode at Rome, that he wolde
saye no seruyce,Synodus Rome. he massed without consecracyon,
he gaue holye orders in hys stable,
he made boyes Byshoppes for moneye,
he wolde neuer blesse hymself, he
forced not to be periured, and made the
holye palace of Laternense a verye stewes.
For he kepte therin Raynerathe wyfe
of hym that was knyght for hys owne
bodye,rainera and gaue her great possessyons,
with benefyces, goldē chalyces, and crosses.
He helde also Stephana and her systre,Stephana
(which had bene hys fathers concubyne)
and had by her a bastarde not longe
afore. He occupyed at hys pleasure Anna
a freshe wydowe,Anna her doughter also
and doughters doughter. He spared neyther
hygh nor lowe, olde nor yonge, poore
nor rytche, fayre nor foule (they sayd)
so that no women durst come vnto Rome
on pylgrymage in hys tyme.Rome sacryfyce. Neyther
reuerenced he anye place, but wolde do
yt euerye where, yea, vpon their verye
aulters. He wolde hawke, hunte, daunce,,
leape, dyce, sweare, fyght, ryot,
roune, straye abrode in the nyght
breakynge vppe dores and wyndowes,
and burne manye mennys howses,

One of hys Cardynalles he gelded,He myght be chast he
put out an others eyes whyche had bene
hys godfather. Of some he borowed an
hande, of some a tunge, a fynger, a nose,
an eare. In hys dyce playnge wolde he
call vpon yll spretes, and drynke to the
deuyll for loue. Thus was he in the ende
deposed,Their spirytuall father. tyll hys dere dyamōdes sett hā
                  des
vnto yt (for they ruled all) ād caused
the Romaynes to sett hym in agayne.
            
            
               ¶Dunstanes autoryte agaynst marryed
prestes.
               THe papacye helde thys Iohā the
.xij.Ioā. xij. for the space of .ix. years .iij.
monthes, and .v. dayes, and was
s
                     ••…
                  kē of the deuyll (they saye) as he was
lyenge in bedde with a mannys wyfe, &amp;
so dyed within .viij. dayes after without
howsell or shrift, they saye. All thys writeth
of hym the foreseyd Liuthprandus
                  Liuthprādus. 
                  li.
6. Ca. 6. and so fourth .v. chapters more to
the ende almoste of hys boke, whiche at
the same selfe tyme dwelt at Ticina in Italye.
Thys ys he of whome the byworde
ryse, As myrye as Pope Iohan.By worde. 
                  Ʋnto
thys holye vycar of Sathan &amp; successour
of Symon Magus, went Dunstane out
of Englande in the yeare of our lorde.
DCCCC. and .lx.960. to be cōfyrmed archebyshop
of Caunterburye.Dunstanus. And there receyued
therwith for a great summe of
moneye, autoryte &amp; power of the Beast,

                  Apoca. 13. vtterlye to dyssolue prestes maryage,
that hys monkes by that meanes,
myght possesse the cathedrall churches of
Englande, as within a whyle after they
ded. Thys Dunstane (as witnesseth Iohā
Capgraue) was the first that in thys realme
compelled men and women to vowe
chastyte and to kepe claustrale obedyence,the first compulsyon.
agaynste the fre doctryne of Saynte
Paule. 1 Cor. 7. et Gala. 5. Forbyddynge
marryage instytuted of God, whiche ys
the verye doctryne of deuils.Foundacyon of chastyte 1. Timoth. 4
Thys ys the worthye orygynall and first
foundacyon of monkes and prestes professed
chastyte in Englande. marke yt
with the sequele, and tell me herafter,
whether yt be of the deuyll or naye.
            
            
               ¶Dunstane executeth hys deuylyshe
commyssyon.
               THys craftye merchaunde Dūstane,The deuyls cō
                     myssyoner.
as he was returned agayne
into Englāde, by autoryte of this
most execrable monstre and wycked Antichrist,
gaue a strayght commaundemēt
that prestes out of hāde shuld put awaye
their lawfull wyues (whō that brēt consepenced
hypocryte called the vessels of
fornycacyon) els wolde he (he sayd) accordynge
to hys commyssyon,A thefe put them
both from benefyce and lyuynge. And
where as he perceyued the benefyces
most welthye, there was he most gredye

vpon them, and shewed most vyolence &amp;
tyrannye. For whan the hygh deanes of
cathedrall churches,A tyraunt. masters of colleges,
prebendes, persones, and vycars wolde
not at so beastly a commaundement, leaue
their wyues and chyldren so desolate
without all naturall ordre, he gote vnto
hym the great power of kynge Edgare,Kynge Edgare
to assyst that creull commyssyon of hys,
procured for moneye of the former Antichrist
of Rome, and by force therof in
manye places most tyrannouslye expelled
them. Ioānes Capgraue in Catalogo sanctorum
Anglie. Reade all the Byble and
Chronycles ouer, of Nemroth, Pharao,
Antiochus, Nero, Decius, Traianus,
with other lyke,Tyrannye spirytuall. and I thynke, ye shall
not fynde a more tyrannouse example.
No, not in cruell Herode hys selfe. For
though he slewe the innocent babes, yet
demynyshed he not the lyuynge of the
fathers and mothers, but thys tyraunt
toke all with hym. If he had sought a
Godlye reformacyon where marryage
was abused, yt had bene sumwhat commendable.
But hys huntynge was to
destroye yt all togyther,Maryage condēpned. as an horryble
vyce in prestes, and in place therof to
sett up Sodome and Gomor by a sort
of Hypocryte monkes, so changynge all
godlye ordre.
            
            
               
               ¶Kynge Edgare ys brought vndre
therby.
               THus bycame the face, first of the
Brytonysh and than of the Englysh
churche sore changed,Facies ecclesiarum. blemyshed,
and by whorysh commyssyons
frō the whorysh byshoppes of the whorysh
Synagoge of Rome, was made all
togyther whoryshe. Proue me herin a lyer
and an heretyke yf ye can, for I wyll,
by the helpe of God, stāde by that I write
here to the ende of my lyfe. If ye can
not (I speake onlye to yow papystycall
byshoppes and prestes) graunt your selues
to be the most theues, heretykes,Heretykes and theues. and
seducers of the people, that euer yet reigned
vpon the earthe, for maynteynynge
for holynesse so deuylysh a knauerye. Immedyatlye
after thys be fell a sore chaunce,
as God walde. Kynge Edgare which
was euer a great whore mastre and a tyraunte
(as the Chronycles report hym)
had a do with a yonge mayde called wilfrith,wilfrith
brought vp in the nondrye of wylton
(parauenture to their vse) wherupon
by force of the former commyssyon, he
was condempned of Dunstane to .vij.
years penaunce, and myght in no wyse
be dyspensed with,Penaū
                     ce. tyll he had buylded
for their commodyte the great nondrye
of Shaftesburye with .xij. other monasteryes
besydes. Specyallye tyll he had

fullye graunted to the vtter condempnacyon
of prestes maryage through out all
hys realme, and fyrmelye promysed to
put the monkes in their rowmes in the
great cathedrall churches,An apyshe liaue writynge to
the pope for the same. For as witnesseth
both Vuyllyam of Malmesburye, Ranulph of
Chestre, Guido de columna, and Robert sabyane,
he was not crowned tyll the .xij. yeare
of hys reigne.
            
            
               ¶Dunstane fashyoneth the kynge
to hys purpose.
               IN the ende, thys aduoutrye of
the kynge made greatlye for their
purpose. For whan yt was ones
openlye knowne, Dunstane with hys
Bulle went by and by vnto hym, and by
force therof denounced hym accursed.The beastes autoryte.
The kynge of gentylnesse, as he was cō
                  mynge
towardes hym, arose out of hys
regall seate to take hym by the hande ād
geue hym place. The hystorye sayth, that
he than dysdayned to geue hym hys hande.
And lokynge vpon hym with bende
browes and most spyghtfull countenaunte,
he sayd thus vnto hym. Thu that hast
not feared to corrupte a vyrgyne made
handefast to Christ,A proude knaue presumest to towche
(a knaue) the consecrate handes of a byshopp?
Thu hast defyled the spowse of
thy maker (a monkes wanton) and thynkest
by flatterynge seruyce, to pacyfye (a

                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
But what matter maketh yt whiche of
them yt was, whan all they are allowed
now for canonysed Sayntes in the popes
whoryshe churche.All sayntes Yea, the whoremonger,
the whore, the whoryshe bastarde
and all, to sett whoryshnesse forewarde
and make yt apere holye, where marryage
ys thought vnholye. And as for
the mother of Edwarde,The mother. 
                  Iohan Hardynge
nameth her Elflede, Polydorus Elfrede,
Wyllyam of Malmesburye, Ranulphe, &amp;
Fabyane calleth her whyght Egelflede, &amp;
Caxton dare geue her no name, and therfore
the matter ys doubtfull.Dunstane. As Dunstane
was on a tyme hallowynge of a
churche in the honoure of Saynt deuyll,
saynt Deuys I shuld saye, he behelde the
ryght thombe of the foreseyd Edithe,Editha. thā
beynge abbesse of wylton, as she was
crossynge ād blessynge her forhead. And
moche delyghtynge therin, he toke yt in
hys hande, and sayd. Neuer myght thys
thombe peryshe. Immedyatlye after he
beynge at Masse and dolouroussye wepynge,
sayd vnto the deacon that serued
hym. Alas thys floryshynge floure will
fade,Great loue shewed. thys redolēt rose wyll be gone, this
dayntye Dyamonde wyll peryshe, thys
swete byrde wyll awaye for euer. And
after her deathe he founde all her bodye
resolued into ashes, except that thombe
and the secrete part vndre her bellye, for

those .ij. partes of her, he had blessed afore.
In dede he was verye homelye to serche
so farre.A narrowe sercher. But the cause of thys (they
saye) she afterwarde declared vnto hym
in a secrete vysyon. Thys storye sheweth
Vuillyā of Malmesburye. li. 2. de pontificibus.
Ranulphus in polychronico, li. 6. Ca. 9. Vincencius,
li. 25. Ca. 33. Antoninus. par. 2. ti. 16. Ca. 8
Iohannes Capgraue in uita Edithe.
               
            
            
               ¶Kynges become th Beastes
Images.
               
                  Ʋ
                  Ʋhan Kynge Edgare had ones
perfourmed hys .vij.Edgare years penaūce
for hys aduowterye with
fayre Wilfrith (whom Dūstane parauē
                  ture
prepared for hys owne store) he became
altogyther the dumme Image of
the Beast,Imago Bestie. and myght not vtter frō thens
fourth, but as they gaue hym sprete. Apo. i
                        •
                     .
Than caused they hym to call a generall
counsell (at London some saye) in the
yeare of our lordeSynodus. .DCCCC. and .lxix.969
by the vngracyouse autoryte of the aforeseyd
pope Iohan. And there was yt fullye
enacted, and establyshed for a lawe
euer to endure, that all canons of cathedrall
churches, collygeners, persons, curates,
vycars, prestes, deacons,An Acte for sodome. and subdeacons
shuld eyther lyue chast, that ys
to saye, become Sodomytes (for that hath
bene their chastyte euer sens) or els be
suspended from all spirytuall iurysdyccyon.

Thys more than Pharaonycall constytucyō,Tyrannye.
was the kynge sworne to ayde,
maynteyne, and defende with the materyall
swerde, by the popes antoryte. Thā
were there chosen oute .ij. pryncypall vysytours,
Ethelwolde the Byshopp of
Wynchestre (that nest ys euer vngracyouse)
&amp; Oswalde the Byshopp of Worcestre,
both monkes, to se thys throughe
out the whole realme executed.
                     Ʋysytours. 
                  Vincencius
li. 24. Cap. 83. Antoninus par. 2. li. 16. Cap. 6.,
Guilhelmus Malmesburye, Ranulphus, Guido
de columna, Ioan Capgraue. et opus nouum De
utra
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      potestate. fo. 57.
            
            
               ¶Dunstane ys accused of yll rule.
               IN thys counsel were some wyse
men (as all these writers wytnesse,
though yt be sumwhat fayntly)
which layed for their marryage the scripturs,For maryage.
and substancyallye proued themselues
the maynteyners of vertu therin, ād
not of aduouterye as they were there vncharytablye
noted. But that wolde not
serue thē. The holye Ghost myght in no
wyse preuayle,Bulles the popes bawdye bulles
beynge in place, but they must nedes haue
the preferment, no remedye. An other
sort were there which accused Dunstane
of yll rule in the darke.Dunstane accused For Petrus Equilinus
sayth in Catalogo Sanctorum li. 8. Ca. 49.
that he was put to hys purgacyon of manye
thyngs there layed agaynst hym. Of

a lyekelyhode therfore they had smelled oute
sumwhat that was not all to hys spirytuall
honestye. Neyther wolde these accusacyons
helpe, the popes Power ones
so largelye publyshed. The kynge durst
vtter nothynge that was agaynst hym,Edgare
for feare of newe penaunce, and for as
moche as yt was wele knowne that in
the tyme of hys olde penaunce he had occupyed
one mynyon at Wynchestre, an
other at Andouer,alfreda. besydes alfrede whō
he at the lattre gote to wyfe by the craftye
mourther of her husbāde Ethelwolde
an earle.
            
            
               ¶The kynge defendeth Dunstane &amp;
destroyeth wolues.
               BƲt to pacyfye and please thys
Dunstane,Oratio ad clerū
                   kynge Edgare in hys
oracyon there to the clergye, rebuked
the prestes verye sore, for banketynge
with their wyues, for slacknesse of
their masse saynges, for pretermyttynge
their canonycall houres, for their crownes
ſhauynges with their vnprestlye aparellynges,
and soche other lyke. More
ouer he alleged vnto thē in the seyd oracyon
the lamentable complayntes (good
knauerye I warāde yow) of hys fathers
sowle aperynge to Dunstane,Knauerye. and reprouynge
the wantō behauer of the prestes
with their wyues. He also tolde them, in
repressynge their former accusementes, that

                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
by hys peramoure Stephana) of hys breames
and vysyons for the tyme of hys
progresse,Stephana desyeryng hys power agaynst
the prestes also, with manye other wonders.
Iohānes Capgraue in Catal. Guilhelmus
Malmesburye, Vincencius, Antoninus, Ranulphus,
Guido de columna▪ et Polydorus.
               
            
            
               ¶Oswalde with hys Beastlye
autoryte.
               ON the other syde went Oswalde
with hys autoryte frō that wycked
counsell,Oswaldus magus. which had stodyed
necromancye with other vnpure scyēces
at floryake besydes Orleaunce in frāce,
where he was first made monke, and afterwarde
in Englande bycame byshopp
of Worcestre.Floria
                     
                        •
                     us. Thys fellawe so wele armed
with deceytes as euer were Pharaoes
sorcerers, was thought a man mete
to deceyue with lyenge sygnes the commō
sort. So trudged he fourth with hys
craftye ca
                     •
                  kynges, and first expelled the
Canons of the cathedrall churche of worcestre
with their carefull wyues and chyldren,Prestes expelled
and out of .vij. other churches more
within that hys dyoces, and there placed
for them the laysye leane locustes, which
not longe afore had leaped out of the bottomlesse
pytt. Apoca. 9.Apoc. 9 the monkes which
at that tyme were bare and nedye. Thā
went he farther abrode, and wrought there
lyke masteryes, wherof Englāde hathdepelye

felt euer sens. Hys suggestyons
were lyke the other,
                     a colour
                   as that the prestes
lyued wantonlye, and wolde not masse
in due forme. For hys trauayle in thys,
was he made archebyshop of Yorke by
the laboure of Dunstane. To tell hys other
feates yt wolde axe to moche tyme,
and therfor I passe yt ouer.iij. false knaues. These .ij. promoted
the seyd Dūstane aboue all other,
as men hauynge most wylye craftes, to
assyst hym in hys busynesse. These .iij.
Monkes brought the Kynges so vndre,
that they had than all the realme at their
pleasures. Ioannes Capgraue, Malmesburye,
Vincencius, Antoninus, Ranulphus, Guido de
Columna, et Polydorus.
               
            
            
               ¶Dunstane maketh a Kynge at hys
pleasure.
               AFter the decease of Kynge Edgare,
in the yeare of our lorde. DCCCC.
and .lxxv.975. was a wonderfull
varyete and scysme through out the
whole realme,Scisma partlye for hym that next
shuld succede Kynge, and partlye for the
great iniurye done to the marryed prestes.Alpherus.
The quene Alfrede with Alpherus
the duke of Mercia and other great lordes
fauorynge her quarell worlde nedes
haue Ethelrede Kynge whiche was her
sonne by Edgare,Ethelredus. on the one syde. Dunstane
and hys mōkyshe byshoppes with
the earle and Eastsexe and serten other lordes

                     〈2 pages missing〉
                  
                  
part both of the nobles and commons,
iudged the prestes to haue great wronge,
and sought euerye where by all meanes
possyble,Ba
                        •
                     kare, sir monke. to brynge them agayne to their
olde possessyōs and dygnytees. Yea, sum
where with good ernest blowes and buffettes.
Robertus Fabyane cum antedictis Autoribus.
               
            
            
               ¶Dunstane maketh an Idoll to
speake.
               THys caused Dunstane in the yeare
of our lorde .DCCCC. and
lxxv.975. to call an other solempne
counsell.Synodus. But that was where they
thought themselues most stronge, and
myght best do their feates, at Wynchestre.
Where after great wordes had betwen
the duke of Marche and the earle
of Eastsexe (which were than appoynted
as arbyters) Dunstane perceyuynge all
to go with the prestes, broughte fourthe
hys former commyssyō,Cōmyssyon. thynkynge therby
to stoppe their mouthes. And whan
that wolde not serue, they sought out a
practyse of the olde Idolatrouse prestes,
which were wont to make their Idolles
to speake, by the art of Necromancye,
wherin the monkes were in those dayes
expert. A roode there was vpon the frayter
wall in the monasterye where the counsel
was holdē,Aroode &amp; (as Ʋyncēt &amp; Antoninus
testyfyeth) Dunstane required thē
                  
all to praye therunto, which was not thā
ignoraunte of that spirytuall prouysyon.Knauerye.
In the myddes of their prayer, the roode
spake these wordes, or els a knaue mōke
behynde hym in a truncke through the
wall, as Bonyface ded after for the papacye
of Celestyne. God forbyd (sayth he)
ye shulde chāge thys ordre takē.The roode speaketh. Ye shuld
not do wele, now to alter yt. Take Dunstanes
wayes vnto ye, for they are the
best. At thys worke of the deuyll all they
were astoyned, that knewe not therof the
craftye cōueyaunce. If thys were not cleane
legerdemayne, tell me. Oh, that there
was not a Iohā Boanerges at that tyme,
to proue the spretes of that workemā
                  shyp.
1. Ioan. 4.1. Ioā. 4 If there had bene but one
Thomas Cromwell,Thomas crō
                     well. they had not so clerelye
escaped with that knauerye. Polydorus
Vergilius, which alloweth thē in manye
other lewde poyntes, smelled out
their bouerye in thys, and reporteth dyuerse
other to do the same at the daye.
            
            
               ¶That Idoll ys crowned Kynge of
Englande.
               IN remēbraunce of thys knauerye
(myracle, they saye) were afterwarde
writtē vpō the wall vndre that
roodes fete,
                     Ʋerses these verses folowynge.
               
                  Humano more, crux presens edidit ore,
                  Coelitus affata, que perspicis hic subarata,
                  Absit ut hoc fiat, et cetera tunc memorata.
               
               
                  
Wyth lye and all.Capgraue. Whom Iohan Capgraue
reporteth that he se there more thā
CCCC. years after, the roode translated
from thens into the churche for hys
myracles sake. Aboute the yeare of our
lorde a. M. and .xxxvi.1036. as kynge Canutus
beynge at Southampton was boasted
of one of hys knyghtes to be the great
lorde of the see,Canutꝰ he thought to proue yt
by a commaundemēt of obedyence. And
as he wele perceyued that yt wolde obeye
hym in no poynt,The crowne. he toke the crowne
from hys owne head, acknowlegynge
that there was a lord moche hygher &amp; of
more power thā hymself was. And therfor
he promysed neuer more to weare yt,
but to rendre yt vp vnto hym for euer.
With that,Egelnothus. Egelnothus than archebyshopp
of Caunterburye, infourmed hym
of thys roode whiche had dysolued prestes
matrymonye ād done manye other
great myracles. Whiche prouoked hym
anon after to go to Wynchestre, and to
resigne vnto hym hys regall crowne, cō
                  stytutynge
hym than kynge of thys real
me.An Idol made kynge. Was not thys (thynke yow) good
wholsom counsell of thys Idolouse byshopp.
Zacha. 11. yf a man had nede of yt?
A playne token ys yt that they were thā
the Images of the Beast.Image of the Beast. 
                  Apoca. 13. &amp; no
godlye gouernours, yea, verye Idolles 
                     〈◊〉
                  
no kynges, that were vndre soche ghostly

fathers. Henricus Huntyngtonensis Archidia
conus. li. 6. Ranulphus li. 6. Ca. 20. Fabianus.
li. 1. Ca. 206. et Polydorus li. 7. with other
autours more.
            
            
               ¶An example of Claustrall
virgynyte.
               MArianus Scotus &amp; serten other
writers besydes, do testyfye in
their Chronycles, that whan
thys Canutus coude haue no frute by
hys wyfe Elgyne of hampton,Canutꝰ Elgius. and was
not througlye contented therwith. She
fearynge that he shuld eyther caste her
vp, or els resort to some other, gote her amonge
relygyouse chast women, to knowe
what good chere was amonge them.
And anon she founde one to her mynde,Clanstrall chastyte
whiche was bygge with chylde by a mō
                  ke,
not withstandynge the great chastyte
that was boasted afort. But Marianus
sayth, she was a presbyteresse or a prestes

                     •
                  e
                     ••…
                  an, to saue the honoure of that ordre,
bycause he was a monke hys selfe. Algyne
bad thys nonne be of good chere, and
yf she wolde agre vnto her, yt shuld be
to her great honoure.A monkes bastarde. But yt must (she
sayd) be kept wonderfully close. Immedyatlye
after the quene fayned herselfe
to be great with chylde, and by the conueyaunce
of a mother. B. goynge betwixt
them both, as the tyme appoynted
of labourynge, she was delyuered of the

nonnes chylde, makynge the kynge to be
leue yt was hys, to no small reioyce of
them both.Sweno This chylde was called Sweno,
and the yeare afore Canutus dyed,
was constytute kynge of Norweye. Some
writers haue thought that Heraldus
the first (whiche after succeded kynge of
Englande) to come fourth also the same
waye,Heraldus. ād hys owne brother harde Canutus
reporte yt not farre otherwyse. Ranulphus
li 6. Ca. 20. cum ceteris autoribus.
               
            
            
               ¶Dunstane dysputeth with sorcerye
and murther.
               NOw let vs returne vnto Dūstane
agayne.Dunstanus. Though the aforesayd
controuersye betwen the
prestes &amp; the mōnkes ceased for a tyme, by
reason of their legerdemayne in the roode,Knauerye.
yet was yt not all fynyshed. For some
men of wysdome there were in those dayes,
which smelled somwhat (as Polydorus
reporteth) iudgynge yt to be as yt was
in dede, verye subtyle knauerye. And
playnelye Ranulphus sayth, that the spech
came frō the wall. Marke yt bardelye.
Wherupon Alpherus the duke of Marche
with hys companye,Alpherus. in the yeare folowynge
(whiche was from Christes incarnacyon .DCCCC.
and .lxxvi.)976. sent
into Scotlande for a certen lerned Byshop,a lerned byshop.
which was knowne both eloquent

&amp; wytty, to dys
                     •••…
                  te the matter with thē.
Than was the place appoynted in a ſtrete
or vyllage of the Kynges, called Calua,
for they trusted no more close howses
in the monasteryes. And whan the Byshopp
had layed for the marryed prestes
soche invyncyble scripturs,Dunstane an asse. reasone, and
argumentes as Dunstane and hys dodypoll monkes were not albe to auoyde,
the blynde asse had non other shyft but
to laye these faynte excuses for hymself.
As that he was an aged man, sore brokē
in the labours of holye churche, and that
he had at that tyme geuen ouer all stodye,A blynde beast
and onelye addycted hymself vnto
prayer. But for as moche (he sayd) as
they wolde not leaue the dysquyetynge
of hym, but styll vexe hym with olde
quarellynges, they myght wele seme
to haue the vyctorye, yet shuld they not
haue their myndes. And with that he
arose in a great furye, for a coloure commyttynge
hys cause vnto Christ,A lymme of the deuyll. but he
sett the Deuyll by hys necromancye to
worke. For so sone as he was gone,
with soche as yt pleased hys pontyfycall
pleasure to call with hym, sodenly (sayth
Fabyane, Antonyne, Vyncent, and Iohan Capgraue)
the ioystes of the loft fayled, and
they that were vndre yt, peryshed
there.
            
            
               
               ¶Dunstanes prouysyon in Englande
for Sathan.
               THus haue thys most cruell and
wycked generacyon contynuallye
buylded their synnefull Syon
in blood. Michee. 3.Mich. 3 and are not yet ashamed
of these their manyfest knaueryes.
For these belly founders, theues, and
mourtherers of theirs yet aduaunce they
for their princypall Sayntes.sayntes And whā
their feastfull dayes come, they are yet
in the papystych churches of Englande
with no small solēpnyte, mattensed, 
                     •…
                  assed,
candeled, lyghted, processyoned, sense
                     •
                  ,
smoked, perfumed, and worshypped,
the people brought in beleue, that the latyne
readynge of their wretched actes
there in their legendes, ys Gods dyuyne
seruyce,Gods seruyce. beyng without fayle the most
dampnable seruyce of the deuyll. Lyke
as holye Iohan Baptyst by preachynge
repentaunce, prepared a playne pathwaye,
to Christ and hys kyngedome, Luce. 3.
So ded thys vnholye Dunstane by sowynge
of all superstycyons,Precursor Antichristi. make redye
the waye to Sathā and hys fylthye kyngedome
agaynst hys commynge fourth
from the bottomlesse pytt, after the full
thousande of years from Christes incarnacyon.
Apoca. 20.Apo. 20 Myracles. which ys the sprete of
Antichrist, He raysed vp in Englāde the
pestylent ordre of monkes, he buylded

them monasteryes, he procured them substaunce
innumerable, fynally he brought
into their handes the cathedrall churches
with the free eleccyon of byshoppes, that
nothyng shuld there be done within that
realme, but after their lust and pleasure.
Thā was Chrystes kyngedome clerelye
put a syde, and hys immaculate spouse,
or churche vpon hys worde onlye dependynge,The churche Apo. 12.
compelled to flee into the desart.
Apoca. 12. Men and womē that ryghtlye
beleued, durst not than confesse their faythe,
but kept all close within them. For
than was Sathan abrode,Sathan these monkes
euerye where assystynge hym in the fournyshynge
out of that proude paynted
churche of Antichrist. Superstycyon, hypocresye,
and vayne glorye, were afore
that tyme soche vyces as men were glad
to hyde,Vyces. but now in their gaudyshe ceremonyes,
they were taken for Gods dyuyne
seruyce.
            
            
               ¶Sygnes and plages folowynge
these myschefes.
               BƲt now se what folowed of these
afore rehersed myscheues. In the
yeare of our lorde .DCCCC. &amp;
lxxxviij.988 (which was the .xij. yeare before
that full thousande) departed thys Dunstane,
a swarme of deuyls frequētynge
hys tumbe,Deuyls. as I shall in the next boke she
we more playnelye. Within the same

yeare appered a bloodye cloude in the
skye,A bloodye cloude. which couered all Englāde, as witnesseth
Iohā Hardinge with dyuerse other
Chronyclers, and yt rayned blood ouer
all the lande.Danes. After that entered the Danes
so fast (sayth Ranulphe) at euerye
porte, that no where was the Englyshe
nacyon able to withstande them. And
the monkes to helpe the matter wele forewarde,
by counsell of their Archebyshop
Siricius,Siricius. gaue them .x. thousand pounde
to begynne with, that they myght
lyue in rest and not be hyndered. For lytle
cared they what became of the reest,
so their precyouse bodyes were safe. After
thys by dyuerse compulsyons they
augmented that summe, from .x. to .xvi.
to .xx. to .xxiiij. to .xxx. and so fourth tyll
they came to the sharpe payment of .xl.
thousande pounde,Mōkes were Englandes destruccyon. and tyll they had nomore
moneye to geue.The Danes stregthned. For the more the
Danes had, the more couetouse and cruell
they were euermore. Thus ded they
to the lande innumerable harme, in sekynge
their owne pryuate commodyte, and
so brought their owne natyue people in
most myserable thraldome. For by that
meanes were the Danes made stronge,
and the Englyshe nacyon bycame feble
and weake, yea, so wretched at the last,
that they were fayne to call euerye vyle
slaue amonge the seyde Danes,Lorde Dane. their

good lorde. But now marke the ende cō
                  cernynge
these monkes. In the yeare of
our lorde a thousande &amp; .xij whiche was
the .xxiiij.1012. yeare from Dunstanes departynge.
and the .xij. from the deuyls goynge
fourth, the Danes after manye great
vyctoryes within the realme,Caōterburye. fyered
the cytie of Caunterburye and enprisoned
the Archebyshopp than Elphegus.Elphegus.
And as he and hys monkes were able
to geue no more moneye, they tythed thē
after thys sort. They slewe alwayes .ix.
and reserued the tenth to perpetuall sorowe
and seruytude, tyll they had mourthered
of them to the nōbre of more thā
ix.Tythynges. hondred, there and in other quarters abrode.
And the moste part of them they
hynge vp by the members,A iust Plage. which was a
playne sygnyfycacyon, that plage to come
than vpon them for their Sodometrye
and most vyolent contempt
of christen marryage.
Ranulphus Cestrensis li. 6.
Ca. 13. et. 15. Fabianus
Par. 1. Cap. 199.
            
         
         
            
            ¶The Conclusyon
of thys fyrst boke.
            HEre haue I paynted oute
before your eyes (most derelye
beloued contreye mē)
the chast,Extent of thys boke holye, consecrate,
and spirituall actes of your
Englyshe votaryes, prestes, Monkes, &amp;
Byshoppes, frō the worldes begynnynge,
to a full complete thousande years
ſens Christes incarnacyon. Not all haue
I here rehersed, for that were a laboure
without ende, they beynge so innumerable,
but a serten of them for euerye age,
that ye maye by them perceyue what the
rest hath bene.The other boke. In the next part or boke,
which shall begynne at Sathans goynge
fourthe at large, after hys thousande
years tyenge vp. Apoca. 20. and so contynue
to thys yeare of our Lorde a .MD.
and .xlvi.1546. that ye maye knowe what chere
hath bene amonge them, what occupyenge
they haue had, what masteryes
they haue played, ād what myracles they
haue done, for that tyme ād space also. I
thynke yt wyll apere an other maner of
thynge, than that which hath gone afore.Sathan at large
For so moche as Sathan their ghostlye
gouernoure hath for that tyme wrought

most strongelye. Nomore wyll I be ashamed
to reherse their fylthye factes (lete
them trust vpon yt) than they haue bene
to do them in effect, and to sett them fourthe for holye, spirytuall, cōsecrate, chast,
honorable,Good workes and ghostlye good workes, beynge
abhomynable and most stynkynge
knaueryes.
            The worlde shall wele knowe what
Sodomytes and Deuyls they are,Sodomites. that
haue all thys tyme contempned christen
marryage instytuted of God, and do not
yet repent their most dampnable doynges
in that behalf, but contynue styll the
saint, leadynge their lyues in vnspekeable
fleshlye fylthynesse. Christ promysed
ones to all soche as they are, that all their
hydden myscheues shuld come to lyght,
yf they wolde not at the call of hys most
holye Gospell, repent. Nothynge (sayth
he) ys so closelye hydden amonge those
spirytual murtherers, but wyl be clerely
opened, neyther yet so secretlye couered,
but shall apere manyfest and be knowne
to the worlde. Math. 10.Mat. 10 
               Marci. 4.Mar. 4. 
               Luce. 12.
Christ suffered verye longe the Pharysees
and Byshoppes,Luc. 12▪
                the lewde predecessours
of our proude spirytualte. But
whan he ones perceyued non other in thē
but contempt of hys veryte with wylfull
resystaunce of the holye Ghost,Christ rebuketh. he went
fearcelye vpon them with wo vpon wo,

callynge them all that nought was. As
hypocrytes, dyssemblers, dodypolles,
fooles, blynde beastes, bellygoddes, scorners,
false prophetes, periures, vypers,
serpentes, deuourers, rauenours, brybers,
theues, tyrauntes, murtherers, and
fyre brandes of hell.
            Loke the .xxiij. chapter of Mathew,Mat. 23
&amp; ye shall fynde that he poured all thys
vpon them, and doubled yt in the captyuyte
of Hierusalem, whan the great vengeaunce
of all innocent blood lyght greuouslye
vpon them. For in the syege of
that cytie were slayne by vespasianus &amp;
Titus,
                  Ʋespasianus et Titus to the nombre of .x. hondred thousandes
of Iues. Not onlye of the inhabytauntes
of that regyon there, but from
all quarters of the worlde aboute, which
at that tyme came thydre to their Eastre
celebracyon. Besydes there, were there
ledde fourth from thens captyue .xcvij.
thousande,Captyues. of whome some were solde
to the Romanes to become their contynuall
seruauntes and slaues, and the resydue
geuen vnto the Lyons and wylde
beastes, that they shuld daylye deuoure
them and be fed with their fleshe. All
thys witnesseth Egesippus Iudeus, li. 5. Ca.
49. De Hierosolimorum excidio.
               Exāple And now
after hys most manyfest example, Christ
wylleth vs also extremelye to rebuke

these cruell corrupters of the christyanyte,
for their most spyghtfull contempt
of hys wholsom warnynges, the Christen
magistrates hereafter,Magystrates. or els some
other enemye of theirs, folowynge with
double vengeaunce vpon the heades of
them. Apoca. 18. Thys plage, whan yt
shall fall, as yt ys not farre of, wyll be
the most ryghtouse hande of God, vpon
the malygnaunte generacyon.
            Great wondre wyll yt be vnto manye
(I know yt wele) to beholde their
chefe Englyshe sayntes thus rebuked.englysh Sayntes.
And parauēture they wyll thynke, that
I myght as wele speake agaynst Peter
and Iohan, Paule and Iames, with the
other Sayntes, Apostles and Martyrs
of the prymatyue churche, as agaynste
these vngodlye hypocrytes of theirs.
But I tell those men afore hande,The Autour. that
they are wretchedlye blynde, for want of
lyuelye knowlege in the sacred scripturs.
They haue no true iudgement in
them to dyscerne the fallen starre,starres. from
the starre so fyermelye fixed in the fyrmamēt
as neuer coude be yet from thēs
remoued. Neuer shall he that declyueth
to mennys inuencyons, be all one with
hym whyche onlye folowethe the pure
woorde of God.
            But vndoubtedly of no small tyme,

                  〈2 pages missing〉
               
               
great honoure wyll yt now be to yow
(yea, rather moche greatter) to flee the sede
of the Serpent by the worde of God,
as euer yt was to Saynt George that
noble captayne,Saynt George to slee the great hydre or
Dragon at Silena, as Baptista Mantuanus
specyfyeth. I speake not thys for
that I wolde ye to fall vpon that sorte
with materyall weapon, but with the
myghtye stronge worde of the Lorde.
For as Esaye, Daniel, and Paule reporteth,
they shall be destroyed without hā
               des.
Esa. 11. Dani. 8. et. 2. Thes. 2. Onlye ys
yt Gods true knowlege,What maketh noble. that nobleth
yow before hym, be therfor no longar neglygent.
An vnrecurable dyshonoure
were yt vnto yow, from hens fourth to
be led blynde felde of these bushardes in
the darke. The most of yow are all redye
verye plentuouslye entered (that
lorde be praysed) thynke hym only blessed
which perseuereth to the ende. Hauynge
the gouernaunce of Christes dere
herytage,Lawes. drawe not your lawes out of
Antichristes rules now that ye knowe
Christes wholsom doctryne.Doctryne. Neyther
yet fatche the breade that ye shall feade
your commons with, oute of hys bawdye
beggerlye bowgettes, but lete them
haue the pure purueaunce of God out
of the vndefyled scripturs. Be ones so
mercyfull to that christen flocke, that ye

clerelye delyuer them from that vyle generacyon,
Lete them no longer worshyp
deuyls as they haue done, in these
dead monkes and theues,deuyls. but
lete thē loke frelye towardes
their eternall &amp; lyuynge
God, both to
their sowles helthe
and yours.
Amen.
            ¶Thus endeth the first parte of thys
worke, called. The Actes of
Englyshe votaryes. Collected
by Iohan Bale.
Anno. 1546.
         
         
            
            ¶The Autours
names both Englyshe
and other, out of whom thys
present Boke ys collected.
            
               Abbas Vrspergensis.
               Achilles Pyrminius.
               Alphonsus de Castro.
               Alphredusbeu
                     •
                  rlacēsis
               Amandus Zierixensis.
               Antoninus Florētinus.
               Baptista Platina.
               Baptista Mantuanus.
               Bartholomeus Anglus.
               Bedas Girnuinus.
               Bernardus Lutzēburg
               Berosus Chaldeus.
               Biblia Sacra.
               Blondus Flauius.
               Caius Iulius.
               Christianus Masseus.
               Clemēs Alexandrinus.
               Colfridus Abbas.
               Conradus Gesnerus.
               Cornelius Tacitus.
               De utra
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Potestate.
               Diodorus Siculus.
               Edgari Oratio.
               Egesippus Iudeus.
               Epiphanius Cyprius.
               Eusebius Cesariensis.
               Festiuale Sacerdotum.
               Flores Historiarum.
               Franciscus Lābertus.
               Freculphus lexouiēsis.
               Galfredus Monemutensis.
               Gēnadius Massiliēsis.
               Georgius Ioye.
               Gorgius Vuicelius.
               Gildas Britannus.
               Giraldus Cambrensis.
               Guido de Columna.
               Guilhelmus Malmesburiensis.
               Guilhelmus Caxton.
               Guilhelmus Tyndale.
               Guilhelmus Turner.
               Hartmannus Shedel.
               Hector Boethius.
               Helinādus Monachus.
               Henricus Huntyngtonensis.
               Hemānus Contractus.
               Hermānus Torrētinus
               
                  
Honorius Augustudunensis.
               Iacobus Vorago.
               Iacobus Bergomas.
               Iacobus Zieglerus.
               Iodocus Badius.
               Ioannes Capgraue.
               Ioannes Hardyng.
               Ioannes Stella.
               Ioannes de Molinis.
               Ioannes Annius.
               Ioannes Nauclerus.
               Ioannes Lydgate.
               Ioannes Textor.
               Ioannes Tritemius.
               Ioannes Pomeranus.
               Ioannes Carion.
               Ioannes Maior.
               Ioannes Lelandus.
               Isidorus hispalensis.
               Legendariū Ecclesie.
               Liuthprandus Ticinē
                  sis.
               Marcus Sabellicus.
               Marianus Scotus.
               Martinus Carsulanus.
               Martinus Lutherus.
               Matheus Palmarius.
               Merlinus Ambrosius.
               Michael Ricius.
               Nauclerus, Ioannes.
               Nennius Britannus.
               Odo Cluniacensis.
               Osbertus Cātuariēsis.
               Osuualdus Myconius.
               Otto Phrisingensis.
               Paulus Orosius.
               Paulus Aemilius.
               Paulus Constantinus.
               Petrus Equilinus.
               Philippus Melāchton.
               Plinius Secundus.
               Polycrates Ephesius.
               Polydorus Vergilius.
               Pomponius Mela.
               Prosper Aquitannus.
               Ptolomeus Lucensis.
               Ranulphus Cestrensis.
               Raphael Volateranus
               Robertus Fabyane.
               Robertus Barnes.
               Sigebertus Gēblacēsis.
               Strabo Cretensis.
               Thomas Braduuardin
               Thomas Vualden.
               Thomas Scrop.
               Vincēcius Beluacēsis.
               Vtra
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   potestas.
               VVernerus Cartusiensis.
               VVilibaldus Anglus.
            
            Finis.
         
         
            
            
               The holye Gost shall rebuke the worlde
of synne, and of ryghtousnesse, and of
iudgement. 
               Ioan. 16.
            
            
               Into the newe Hierusalem shall entre
no vncleane thynge, neyther that
which worketh abhomynacyon, nor yet
what maketh lyes. But they only which
are written in the lambes boke of lyfe.
               Apoca. 21.
            
            
               The man of synne shall be opened,
before the Lordes commynge, euen the
sonne of perdycyon, whiche is an aduersarye,
and ys exalted aboue all that ys
called God, whom he shall consume with
the sprete of hys mouthe. 
               2. Thes. 2.
            
         
      
      
         
            
               ❧ Printed at Wesel In the Yeare
Of our Lorde God.
1. 5. 4. 6.
            
         
      
   

