
   
      
         
            A sermon preached at the happily-restored and reedified chappell of the Right Honorable the Earle of Exceter in his house, of S. Iohns On Saint Stephens day. 1623 By Ios. Hall, Deane of Worcester.
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1624
            
         
         Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02590
            STC 12714
            ESTC S115163
            99850382
            99850382
            15579
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02590)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15579)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1274:3)
         
         
            
               
                  A sermon preached at the happily-restored and reedified chappell of the Right Honorable the Earle of Exceter in his house, of S. Iohns On Saint Stephens day. 1623 By Ios. Hall, Deane of Worcester.
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [8], 47, [3] p.   
               
                  Printed by F. Kyngston, for George Winder, and are to be sold at his shop in S. Dunstons Churchyard,
                  London :
                  1624.
               
               
                  The first leaf and last leaf are blank.
                  Identified as 12714b on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-02
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2006-02
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
               
                  A SERMON Preached at the happily-reſtored and reedified Chappell of the Right Honorable the Earle of Exceter in his Houſe, of S. Iohns.
                  On Saint Stephens day.
                  1623.
                  By IOS. HALL, Deane of Worceſter.
                  LONDON, Printed by F. Kyngſton, for George Winder, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S. Dunſtons Churchyard. 1624.
               
            
            
         
         
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, MY SINGVLAR good Lady, the Lady Elizabeth, Counteſſe of Exceter.
            
               RIght Honourable: this poore Sermon both preached and penned at your motion (that is to mee your command) now preſents itſelfe to your hand, and craueth a place (though vnworthy) in your Cabinet, yea, in your heart. That holy zeale

which deſired it, will alſo improue it. The God, whom your Ld. hath thus honoured in the care and coſt of his houſe, will not faile to honor you in yours.
            For me, your Honour may iuſtly challenge mee on both ſides; both by the Druries, in the right of the firſt Petronage; and by the Cecils, in the right of my ſucceeding deuotions. In either, and both, that little I haue, or am, is ſincerely at your Ladiſh. ſeruice, as whō you haue merited to be
            
               Your Honours in all true obſeruance and duty, IOS. HALL.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE WORSHIPFVLL AND REVEREND, Mr. Dr. HALL, Deane of Worceſter, my worthy and much reſpected Friend, all happineſſe, with my loue in Chriſt Ieſus.
            
               REuerend Sir; this Sermon, I know, is at the Preſſe before you expected: But I thought (as this glorious Chappell occaſioned it,) ſo it might miniſter occaſion of perpetuall remembrance of the Chappell, by remaining its firſt Monument. And altho both theſe were confined to the priuate; the Chappell for the Family of my Right Honourable Lord, the Earle of Exceter, who hath giuen the materiall thereof ſufficient luſter: and the Copie of the Sermon to the Cabinet of my truly Noble, and vertuous Lady, his Counteſſe; yet both theſe are much and oft required to the publike; the Sermon to be an inſtruction, and ſo it is; the Chappell, to bee

an example, and ſo it may be. The Sermon to teach all, to be all glorious in their ſoules. The Chappell to teach ſome, who build houſes for their owne habitation, to ſet vp another for Gods Religion. The Sermon was craued at the hands of my Honourable Lady, that it might come to the Preſſe; who, of her owne pious diſpoſition, gaue forth the Copie; and for her Noble eſteeme of your ſelfe, and of the worth of your Sermon, was willing and deſirous to giue it way to the Printer. And this I thought good to impart vnto you, and to the courteous Reader, that you may be ſatisfied of the meanes how, and the cauſe why it comes in publike. And ſo praying for you, and deſiring your prayers for me, I remaine
            
               Your truly louing Friend, H. Baguley.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A SERMON PREACHED AT THE reedified Chappell of the Right Honorable, the Earle of Exceter, in his Houſe of Saint Iohns.
            
               HAGGAI 2. 9.
               The glory of the latter Houſe, ſhall bee greater then of the former, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and in this place will I giue peace, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.
            
            
               AS we haue houſes of our owne, ſo God hath his; yea, as great men haue more houſes then one, ſo hath the Great God of Heauen much more; more, both

in ſucceſſion (as here, the latter houſe, and the firſt) and in varietie: He hath an houſe of fleſh (Ye are the Temples of the liuing God;) An houſe of ſtone; (Salomon ſhal build me an houſe;) An houſe immateriall in the Heauens, 2. Cor. 5. 1. Wherefore then hath God an houſe? Wherefore haue we ours; but to dwell in? But doth not he himſelfe tell Dauid, and ſo doth Stephen the Protomartyr (vpon whoſe day we are falne) tell the Iewes, that He dwells not in Temples made with hands? True; Hee dwells not in his Houſe, as we in ours, by way of comprehenſion; he dwells in it by teſtification of preſence. So doe we dwell in our houſes, that our houſes containe vs, that we are only within them,

and they without vs. So doth he dwell in his, that yet hee is elſewhere, yea, euerywhere, that his houſe is within him. Shortly, God dwells where he witneſſes his gracious preſence, that, becauſe hee doth both in the Empyreall heauen, amongſt his Angels and Saints, and in his Church vpon Earth; therefore his dwelling is both in the higheſt Heauen in perfect glory; &amp; on Earth, in the hearts and aſſemblie of his children. As of the former, our Sauiour ſaith; Jn domo Patris mei, Jn my Fathers houſe are many Manſions. So alſo may wee ſay of the latter, There is much varietie and choice in it; There was the Church of the Iewes, the Church of the Gentiles; There is a materiall,

and a ſpirituall houſe. In the one, Salomons, Zorobabels, ſuch piles as this: In the other; ſo much multiplicitie, as there are Nations, yea, Congregations that profeſſe the name of Chriſt. One of theſe was a figure of the other, the Materiall, vnder the Law; of the Spirituall, vnder the Goſpell. Yee ſee now the firſt houſe, and the latter, the ſubject of our Text and diſcourſe. The latter, commended to vs comparatiuely, poſitiuely. Comparatiuely with the former, Maior gloria. Poſitiuely, in it ſelfe, Jn this place will J giue peace. Both, ſet out by the ſtile of the promiſer, and avower; ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. All which challenge your Chriſtian attention.
            
               
As the firſt houſe (which was materiall) was a figure of the ſecond, which is ſpirituall: ſo the glorie of that materiall, was a figure of the glorie of this ſpirituall. Now becauſe all the life and glorie of the ſpirituall, ſtands in Chriſt the Meſſias, the Prophet lookes through the type of the material, at him which ſhal beautifie, yea, glorifie the ſpirituall, of whoſe exihibition the Prophet ſpeakes, Adhuc modicum, Yet a little while, and J will ſhake the Heauens. This Modicum was but ſome 500. and odde yeeres; much to men, but a modicum to the Ancient of dayes, with whom 1000. yeeres are but one day. It is in and by him, that this latter houſe vnder the Goſpell, ſhall in glorie

ſurpaſſe that firſt vnder the Law. The Prophets had ſpoken gloriouſly of the Temple that ſhould be; and now, leſt when the people ſhould ſee the homely and cottagelike reedification of Zerubbabel, they ſhould be diſ-hartned and offended, the Prophet deſires to draw their eyes from the ſtone and timber, to the ſpirituall inſide of the Euangelicall Church, ſhewing the glorie of this latter Houſe, to exceed the former.
            Some groſſe Interpreters haue lookt with Iewiſh eyes vpon the outward fabrick, which was threefold: Salomons, Zorobabels, Herods. Salomons, ſumptuous and magnificent; Zorobabels, meane and homely; Herods, rich and maieſticall,

               immodico ſumptu, incredibili ſplendore, as one ſayes. Salomons was before defaced. Now becauſe Zorobabels was ſo farre from making this Word good, that the people wept, when they ſaw the difference (which Caluin well obſerues, was not without a ſpeciall prouidence of the allwiſe God; elſe the Iewes would ſo haue fixed their eyes vpon the outward ſplendor, that they would neuer haue looked for the ſpirituall and inward Grace of the Houſe of God:) therefore they haue taken it of Herods temple; the walls and lining whereof were indeed anſwerable to this Propheſie, more glorious. But this conceit, as it is too carnal, ſo is quite diſſonant from the

context, both in regard of the precedents, and ſubſequents. Of the precedents: For, how did the deſire of all Nations come to that Pile of Herods? Of the ſubſequents: For, what peace was vnder the Herodian Temple? Firſt, the builder of it, was the chiefe oppreſſor of the Iewiſh libertie: and then ſecondly, it gaue occaſion to the perpetuall miſerie of that people. Pilate would expilate the Treaſures of it for aquae ductae; which denied, coſt the Iewes much blood. Vnder Claudius, twenty thouſand ſlaine in a Feaſt of vnleauened bread. Jonathas the Prieſt ſlaine by theeues ſuborned by Foelix, in the very Temple; and euer after, it was the harbour and ſpoyle of Villaines.

What hills of Carcaſſes? What ſtreames of blood was in't at the laſt vaſtation? Enough to amaze any Reader: ſo as in that 79. yeeres wherein it ſtood (longer it did not,) it was no better then a ſtage of Tragedies, a ſhambles of crueltie. Of that therefore God could not ſay, Dabo pacem; it was Templum adulterinum, as one calls it iuſtly, and had neither command nor promiſe: It was the Spirituall Temple, the Euangelicall Church, whoſe glory ſhal be greater then the Iewiſh, which ſhall be bleſſed with the deſire of the Nations, with the aſſurance of Peace. But why then doth the holy Ghoſt ſpeake of Gold and Siluer, the coſtly materials of an outward

ſtructure? Euen theſe very Metals are figuratiue: not that God cares ſo much for them, but becauſe wee doe; becauſe our eyes vſe to bee dazled with this beſt parcell of Earth; therefore when hee would deſcribe a glorious Church, he borrowes the reſemblance of Gold, Siluer, precious Stones, Eſay 60. and euen by theſe doth he ſet forth his New and Heauenly Ieruſalem, Reuel. 21. Wherein then is the glory of Gods Euangelicall Houſe greater, then of the Legall? Yea, wherein is it not greater? Whether yee looke to the efficient, the matter, the duration, the extent, the ſeruice. The efficient, that was built by man, tho directed by God: In this, God himſelfe is the

Architect, not onely giuing the modell, but the frame. The matter, whether of ſtructure, or ornament. The ſtructure of the one was of ſtone and wood: of the other, is of liuing ſtones. The ornament of the one was Gold and Siluer: of the other, diuine Graces of Faith, Charitie, Hope, Sanctitie, Truth, Pietie, and all other vertues, to which, Gold itſelfe were but traſh.
            The duration of the one (euen that longſt-liued Temple of Salomon, though called (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) domus ſeculi) was but 430. yeeres. Of the other, beyond time, to eternitie. The extent of the one to be meaſured by a few Poles, yea (though yee take in the Courts, and all) by a few Acres: Of the other, vniuerſall,

ſo farre as the King of Heauen hath any Land. The ſeruice in the one performed by a few men, mortal, ſinful, the blood of beaſts ſhed vpon the Altar: In the other, performed by our eternall High-Prieſt, after that higher order of Melchiſedech; offring vp his owne moſt precious blood for our redemption. In that, Chriſt Ieſus was obſcurely figured: In this, really exhibited, borne, liuing, dying, riſing, aſcending, preached, beleeued, liued, Euery way therfore both in efficient, matter, duration, extent, ſeruice, Maiorgloria.
            
            Let no man tell mee now of that iuſt wonder of the world, the Iewiſh Temple; white Marble without, lined with Gold

within, Brazen pillars, Golden veſſels, coſtly vayles, an High-Prieſthood ſet forth with precious Stones, rich Robes, exquiſite Perfumes, curious Muſick, and what-euer that ancient goodly inſtitution had rare and admirable, I ſay the clay of the Goſpell, is more worth then the Marble of the Law; Euangelicall Braſſe, more worth then legall Gold; the ragges of the Euangelicall Prieſthood, more excellent then the robes of the Leuiticall. In ſhort; the beſt of the Law is not comparable to the baſeſt of the Goſpell.
            
               Iohn Baptiſt was the Ianus of both Teſtaments; he was to the Churches, as Noah was to the Worlds; he ſaw both the firſt, and

the latter. It is a great word that our Sauiour ſaith of him, that amongſt thoſe which were borne, or rather (as ours reade it better) begotten of women, there did not a greater then he ariſe: but it is a greater word that he ſpeakes of the Children of the new Teſtament, that the leaſt in the Kingdome of Heauen is greater then he. I ſtand not vpon examining the compariſon, whether it bee ratione ſanctitatis, or officii; it makes either way for my purpoſe, therfore was John ſo great,The leaſt of the greateſt is more, then the greateſt of the leaſt. becauſe he was the laſt of the law, and the firſt of the Goſpell: and the old rule is minimum maximi maius eſt maximo minimi; therfore is the leaſt in this Kingdome of Grace greater then he, becauſe

hee is all, what John was halfe; wholly vnder that Euangelium
               Goſpell of the Kingdome. 
               Regni, which is able to aduance him to a greater perfection, then that Harbinger of Chriſt. What a fauour then is it (Right Honourable and beloued) that God hath reſerued vs to theſe better dayes of his Goſpell, wherein the helpes of ſaluation are more cleare, obuious, effectuall; wherein, as the glory of the latter Houſe exceeded the former; ſo the meanes of that incomprehenſible glorie of the Houſe not made with hands, eternall in the Heauens, lye more open vnto vs? What ſhould we doe, but both vti, and frui, gladly vſe, and ſweetly inioy this vnſpeakable bleſſing, which God hath kept in ſtore for vs, and

walke worthy of ſo incomparable a mercy. The old Iewes liued in the dawning of the day, wherein they had but a glimmering of that Sunne, which would riſe. Wee liue after the highnoone of that happie day. If we walke not anſwerable to ſo great a light, what can we looke for, but vtter darkeneſſe?
            Yee ſhall now giue me leaue (Right Honourable) to carrie theſe words in a meet analogie to the preſent occaſion. The Temples vnder the Law, were both a figure, and a patterne of the Churches vnder the Goſpell. Within this roofe, vnder which we now ſtand here, was both the former, and the latter houſe; and euen in theſe walls doth God

make his Word good, That the glorie of this latter Houſe ſhall bee greater, then of the former. The firſt foundation of it was, no doubt, both pious and rich. I ſhall not need to fetch the Pedigrees of it from Saint Iohn Baptiſt inConſecrated by Heraclius, Patriarch of Ieruſalem. Ieruſalem, nor to diſcourſe of either the deuotion, or wealth of that religiouſly-military Order, for whom theſe ſtones were firſt layde. Imagine the Altar neuer ſo gay, the Imagerie neuer ſo curious; the Veſtments neuer ſo rich; the Pillars, Walls, Windowes, Pauement, neuer ſo exquiſite; yet I dare boldly ſay, this preſent glory of this Houſe in this comely whiteneſſe, and wellcontriued coarctation, is greater then the former. What care I?

nay, What doth God care for the worke of a Lapidary, or Painter, or Maſon? One zealous Prayer, one Orthodoxe Sermō is a more glorious furniture, then all the precious rarities of mechanique excellencies. I doe moſt willingly (as what good hart doth not?) honour the vertuous actions, and godly intentions of our worthie fore-fathers, which (no doubt) it hath pleaſed God in mercy to accept and crowne, but withall it muſt be yeelded, that they liued vnder the tyrannous iniurie and vſurpation of thoſe Phariſes, who kept the keyes of knowledge at their owne girdles, and would neither draw for them, nor ſuffer them to draw for themſelues. Bleſſed be God for better

conditions; the Well of life lyes open to vs, neither are wee onely allowed, but inuited to thoſe heauenly liquors, Jnebriamini O chariſſimi, Drinke, yea, drinke abundantly, O beloued, Cant. 5. 1. This happie liberty of the ſauing Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, daily and ſincerely preached to vs (Noble and beloued Chriſtians) is worthy to bee more worth vnto vs, then all the treaſures, ornaments, priuiledges, of this tranſitory World; &amp; this, ſince through the ineſtimable goodneſſe of God, ye doe, and may find in this latter Houſe. Well hath God verified this Word in your eies and eares; The glorie of the latter Houſe ſhall be greater, then of the former.
            
            Hitherto the comparatiue

prayſe of the latter Houſe; the poſitiue followes in the promiſe of a gracious effect; In this place will I giue peace: wherein I know not whether the bleſſing doth more grace the place, or the place the bleſſing; both grace each other, and both bleſſe Gods people; In this place will I giue peace. If yee looke at the bleſsing it ſelfe, it is incomparable, Peace; that whereby the Hebrews had wont to expreſſe all welfare in their ſalutations, and wel-wiſhes; the Apoſtolicall benediction dichotomizes all good things into Grace and Peace; wherein, at the narroweſt, by Grace, all ſpirituall fauours were ſignified; temporall, by Peace. The ſweet Singer of Iſrael could not wiſh better to

Gods Church, then, Peace be within her walls: and behold, this is it which God will giue, Dabo pacem:
               I wil giue peace. yea, our eyes ſhould ſtoope too low, if they ſhould fixe here. The ſweete Quiriſters of Heauen, when they ſung that diuine Caroll, to the honour of the firſt Chriſtmas, next to Gloria in excelſis
               Glory to God in the higheſt heauens; in earth, Peace, &amp;c. 
               Deo, ſaid, In terris pax: Yet higher; the great Sauiour of the World, when he would leaue the moſt precious Legacie to his deare ones on earth, that they were capeable of, he ſayes, My peace I giue you. And what he there giues, he here promiſes, Dabo pacem, I will giue it. But where? Whence? In this place. Not any where; not euery where; but in his own houſe, in his latter houſe,

his Euangelicall Houſe; as if this bleſsing were confined to his holy walls, he ſaith, In this place will I giue peace. This flower is not for euerie ſyle; it growes not wilde, but is onely to be found in the Garden of Sion. It is very pregnāt which the Pſalmiſt hath, Pſal. 128. 5. and 134. 3. The Lord that made Heauen and Earth, bleſſe thee out of Sion. He doth not ſay, The Lord that made the Earth, bleſſe thee out of Heauen; nor, The Lord that made Heauen, bleſſe thee out of Heauen; but, bleſſe thee out of Sion. As if hee would teach vs, that all bleſsings come, as immediately and primarily frō heauen, ſo immediatly and ſecondarily frō Sion, where this Temple ſtood. Some Philoſophers haue

held the Moone to be the receptacle of al the influēces of the heauenly bodies, and the conueyances of thē to this inferior World, ſo as all the vertue of the vpper Orbes and Starres are deriued by her, to this elementary Sphere. Such doth both Dauid and Haggai repute the houſe of God; whither, as to Ioſephs Storehouſe, doth God conuey the bleſsings of peace, that they may be thence tranſmitted to the ſonnes of men. How, and why then doth God giue peace in this his Houſe? Becauſe here (as Bernard well) Deus &amp; audit, &amp; auditur, God heares, and is heard here; audit orantes, erudit audientes; hee heares his ſuppliants, and teacheth his hearers. As this place hath two vſes,

it is both Oratorium, and auditorium: ſo in reſpect of both, doth it bleſſe vs with peace: our mouth procures it in the one, our care in the other; God workes in our hearts by both. In the firſt, God ſayes, as our Sauiour cites it, Domus me a domus orationis; My Houſe ſhall be called, The Houſe of Prayer. And what bleſsing is it, euen the beſt of Peace, that our prayers cannot infeoffe vs in? Salomon, when hee would conſecrate the Church hee had built, ſolemnely ſues to God, that he would inueſt it with this priuiledge of an vniuerſally-gracious audience; and nūbring the occaſions of diſtreſſed Suppliants, makes it euer the foot of his requeſt; (Then hearken to the prayer that thy ſeruant ſhall
               
               make towards this place; Heare thou in beauen, thy dwelling place; and when thou heareſt, haue mercy.) If euer therefore wee would haue peace outward, inward, priuate, publike, ſecular, ſpirituall: If wee would haue peace in our eſtate, peace in our Land, peace in our Church, peace in our ſoules, pray for it. And if euer we will pray for it, pray here, in Gods houſe, for in this place will I giue peace. In vaine ſhall wee looke for it elſewhere, if we aske it not here. It is true, we are bidden euery where to lift vp pure hands to God: but they cannot bee pure, that are profane; and they cannot be but profane, that contemne the holy ordinances of God. He ſaid well, In templo vis orare, in te ara; for

               (Know you not, that your bodies are the Temples of the liuing God?) but let me as truly returne it; In te vis or are, in templo ora? Wouldſt thou pray with effect at home? Pray at Church; elſe thy deuotion is but the ſacrifice of fooles; for hee hath ſaid it, who hath good reaſon to appoint the circumſtances of his owne beneficence, Jn this place will J giue peace.
            
            Will yee then ſee the reaſon why there is ſo much emptie Caske in the Celler of God? Therfore are men void of grace, becauſe they are voyd of deuotion. They ſeeke not God where he may bee found; and therefore it is iuſt with God not to be found of them, where they pretend to ſeeke him: for, Jn hoc loco;
               
               Jn this place will I giue peace.
            
            
               Gerſon diſtinguiſhes well in his Sermon de Angelis, that there is Duplex Coelum, A double Heauen; Gloriae, &amp; Eccleſiae; of Glory aboue, of the Church below; the Church is the Heauen on earth; where God is ſeene, heard, ſpoken vnto. Where are his Saints (whoſe Aſſemblies are here;) where are his Angels: (Let the woman haue power on her head, becauſe of the Angels, 1. Cor. 11.) As the Iewes then, whileſt the Church of God was Nationall, were wont (according to command) to looke towards the Temple, if they could not come to it, in their deuotions: So now that the Church is Catholike, or vniuerſall, and euery of our Churches is equally Gods

houſe (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ;) we ſhal gladly with Peter and John, goe vp to this Temple to pray; How can wee looke for a better incouragement, then God giues vs here, In this place will I giue peace?
            
            In the latter, as it is Auditoriū, ſo I create the fruit of the lips to be peace (ſaith God.) Naturally we are all (euen thoſe that applaud themſelues in the beſt opinion of their harmeles, and faire diſpoſition) enemies to God: Enemies both actiuely &amp; paſſiuely. Actiuely, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                God-haters, Rom. 1. Paſſiuely, Filii irae, The ſons of diſpleaſure. Wee fell out in Adam, through our own wilfull Apoſtaſie and diſobedience; and we ſtill ſtand out in the maintenance of our inward corruption. There is

no way to peace, but by reconciliation; there is no way to recōciliation; but by the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, which is Euangelium pacis;
               The Goſpell of peace. there is no proper element for the Goſpell of God, but the houſe of God; Locus iste, Jn this place will J giue peace. It is not (I know) for euery hart to apprehend, either the want of this peace, or the miſerie of this want. This is one of thoſe happineſſes which is moſt brag'd of, where it is leaſt had. The ſenſual Securitan pleaſes himſelf in the conceit of his owne peace. All is well at home; he quarrels not with himſelfe, for hee denies himſelfe nothing, God quarrels not with him; here are no checks of a chiding conſcience; no frownes of an angrie Iudge; nothing

               The beauty of peace. but Pulchritudo pacis (as the Prophet ſpeakes.) Alas, my beloued, call not this peace, call it ſtupiditie; euen Hell it ſelfe is not a Kingdome diuided in it ſelfe. There is no bleſsing, whichI will giue true peace. is not alſo counterfeited, Pacem veram dabo, is the ſtile of the Prophets, Ier. 14. 13. This were a needleſſe Epithet, if there were not a falſe peace; ſuch is this of carnall hearts. That Word of eternall Truth muſt ſtand: There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked. Haue you ſeene a ſore ſuddenly fild vp with vnſound fleſh, and fairely skinned ouer, without all offence to the eie, which ere long will breake out againe, and bewray a ſecret, and ſo much-morehardly-cured corruptiō? Such is

a wicked mans peace. Haue you ſeene a ſlaue ſit quietly in the Gally, not ſtruggling with his chaine, not repining at his Oare (neceſſitas fortiter, conſuetudo facile?)
               Neceſſitie hath taught him to beare it ſtrongly, cuſtome eaſily. Haue you heard a dying man profeſſe, that hee felt no paine? Such is a wicked mans peace, of which he ſhall once ſay, though now all ſeeme ſmooth, and plauſible; Jn pace amaritudo mea amariſſima; Jn peace J had great bitterneſſe, Eſay 38. 17. Neither is the want of this peace leſſe perceiued, then the miſery of this want. Men ſee no difference in the face of Heauen, whatſoeuer they doe; their blaſphemies and prayers find the ſame intertainement: therefore the careleſſe man reſolues, I ſhall haue peace,

though I follow the wayes of mine owne heart. Oh the miſerable ſottiſhneſſe of wilfull ſinners! Sinne lyes (like a ſleeping Bandog) at the doore of their heart; they looke vpon him, as if hee would neuer wake; or, as if though he ſhould, yet he were ſo clogged, and chained, and muzled, that there can be no danger of his hurt. Let God but rowze him vp a little, he ſhall bay them to deſpaire; hee ſhall flie vpon them, and pull out their throats: Then ſhall their troubled heart proiect terrible things, and they ſhall feele what it is to liue in the anger of a God. They ſhall ſee the Almightie putting himſelfe into the fearefull formes of vengeance; Who can ſtand before

his indignation? And who can abide in the fierceneſſe of his anger? His furie is powred out like fire, and the rocks are throwne downe before him, Nahum. 1. 6. And if his very loue haue drawne blood of his deare ones: (Terrores Domini militant contra me, ſaith holy Iob: The terrors of the Lord are ſet in aray againſt mee, Iob 6. 4:) and hee that bore the chaſtiſements of our peace, the Sonne of his loue, could lay (My God, my God, why haſt thou for ſaken me?) Oh, what ſhall be the Iudgements of his wrath? If this be the rod of children, Oh, what ſhall be the Scorpions for his enemies? They ſhall ſee that gulfe of fire ready to receiue them into euerlaſting burnings. They ſhall ſee

the Deuils their inceſſant tormentors, ready to ſeize vpon their guilty ſoules. Then, O then, ſhall they know, too late, what an happineſſe it is, that God here promiſes, Dabo pacem. Would we then auoyde the vnſpeakeable horror of this wofull condition? Would wee find the bed of our ſickneſſe and death, comforted with the ſweete teſtimony of an heauenly peace betwixt God and our ſoules? See whence we muſt fetch it; Jn this place will J giue peace. If euer we haue it, wee muſt haue it from the bleſſed ordinances of God, his Word and Sacraments, which this place can affoord vs. In vaine ſhall yee ſeeke for this (deare Chriſtians) in a licentious Tauerne, in a rich

Counting-houſe, in Chambers of dalliance, in full Tables, in Pompous Courts; no, not in thrones of earthly Maieſtie. Alas, many of theſe are the make-bates betwixt Heauen and vs, moſt of them can marre, none of them can make our peace. It is onely the deſpiſed Miniſtery of the Goſpell; the Word of reconciliation, (as it is called, 2. Cor. 5. 19.) which ſounds in Gods Houſe, that can doe it. As yee loue your ſoules therefore, as you would find peace at the laſt, and would looke with a comfortable aſſurance in the face of death and iudgement; as yee would ſee a gracious Mercy-ſeate in the dreadfull Tribunall of God, at the day of our laſt appearance,

frequent the Houſe of God; attend reuerently and conſcionably vpon the ſacred Inſtitutions of God; yeeld your ſelues ouer to be wrought vpon by the powerfull Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt. Oh, be not you wanting vnto God, he will not bee wanting vnto you, but will make good this promiſe of his vnfaileable grace, Jn this place will I giue peace.
            
            It is a great word that is heere ſpoken, Dabo pacem; and therfore it is vndertakē by an omnipotent Agent, I will giue peace. If all the Angels of Heauen ſhould haue ſaid ſo, we ſhould ſoone haue replied, as Korah and his company did to Moſes and Aaron; Yee took too much vpon you, Numbers 16. 3. This worke is not for

any finite power; the ſtile of peace, is the peace of God; the ſtile of God, the Mediator betwixt God and man, is, The Prince of Peace. He is the true Salomon, the other was but typicall. It is he onely, that when the Diſciples were toſſed with contrary winds and threatning billowes, could command the winds and waues to a calme. It is hee onely, that when his Church is toſſed with the winds and waues of raging and impetuous enmitie, can giue outward peace. It is he only, that when the diſtreſſed ſoule is toſſed with the winds and waues of ſtrong temptation, of weake diffidence, can giue inward peace Iuſtly therefore doth hee challenge this act as his owne, J will
               
               giue peace. We vſe to ſay, It is beſt treating of peace with a Sword in our hand. Thoſe who hauc the aduantage of the warre, may command peace: vnderlings muſt ſtoope to ſuch conditions, as the victor will yeeld. To ſhew vs therefore how eaſily he can giue peace, God ſtiles himſelfe the God of Hoſts; a title wherein he takes no ſmall delight, referring not to the being of the creature, but to their marſhalling; not to their naturall eſtate, but their militarie; neither would God bee lookt at in it, as a Creator, but as a Generall. In but two of the Prophets, Eſay and Ieremy, no leſſe then an hundred and thirtie times hath hee this ſtile giuen him. Euery thing, as it hath an

exiſtence from the Maker, ſo an order from the Gouernor; and that order is no other then warlike, wherein it doth (militare Deo) ſerue vnder the colours of the Almightie. All creatures are both muſtred and trained, and placed in Garriſon, and brought forth into the field, in the ſeruice of their Creator; they are all excercitus pugnatorum. If yee looke into Heauen, there is a company of heauenly Souldiers, Luke 2. Neither was there only the conſtruction of Idolaters, vniuerſa militia coeli, to which theſe burnt Incenſe; but of Moſes himſelfe; Thus the Heauen and the Earth were finiſhed, and all the Hoſt of them, Gen. 2. 1. If yee looke to the Earth, not men onely, whom reaſon

hath fitted for ſuch deſignes, but euen the bruite, yea, the baſeſt and indocibleſt of the brute creatures are ranged into arayes: euen the very Locuſts, though they haue no Leader, yet Egrediuntur per turmas, They goe forth by bands, Prou. 30. 27. And if ye looke into Egypt (where for the time was Sedes belli,) you ſhal find a Band of Frogs, that were appointed to march into the very Bed-chamber, the Bed, the Ouens, the Diſhes of Pharaoh; you ſhal find an hoſt of Lice, of Flies, of Caterpillers, ſent againſt thoſe Egyptian Tyrants. Elſe-where, yee ſhall find troopes of Palmerwormes, of Locuſts, of Cankerwormes, of Caterpillers to ſet vpon Iſrael, Ioel 1. 4. Shortly, where

he meanes to preſerue, the fierie Charrets and Horſemen of Heauen ſhall compaſſe Dothan. Where he meanes to deſtroy, the moſt deſpicable of his creatures ſhal be armed, to the ruine of the proudeſt. Doth Goliab ſtalke forth to the defiance of the God of Iſrael? A Pebble out of the Brooke ſhall ſtraw him on the ground. Doth an Herod heare his flatterers gladly ſay, Nec vox hominom ſonat? Stay but a while, God ſets his vermine vpon him; all the Kings Guard cannot maſter thoſe Lice. He hath Hornets for the Hiuites and Canaanites, Exod. 23. Mice for the Philiſtims, Iudg. 6▪ Rats for the couerous Prelate: A Flye for Pope Adryan: A world of creatures for either

defenſiue or offenſiue ſeruices. Quare fremuerunt gentes? Why doe the Heathen rage, and the people imagine a vaine thing? The Kings of the Earth ſet themſelues, and the Rulers take councell together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anointed. Preſumptuous duſt and aſhes, that dare riſe vp againſt the God of hoſts! If a ſilly Ant out of a Mole-hill ſhould march forth, and proffer to wreſtle a fall with a Gyant, there were ſome proportion in this challenge, there is none of a finite power to an infinite. Should all the powers of Hell band themſelues with thoſeWho hath reſiſted his will? on earth, Quis reſtitit? What power haue they of being, of motion, but from him whom they oppoſe? How eaſily can he

blow vpon their enterprizes? How eaſily can hee command theſe to their Duſt, thoſe to their Chaines? Be confounded therefore, O vaine men, whoſe breath is in your Noſthrils (and that not your owne neither) when yee thinke of the power and Maieſtie of the God of Hoſts.
            And why are we diſmayd with the rumors, or feares of the ſtrongeſt oppoſitions? Gebal and Ammon, and Amalec, the Philiſtims, with them that dwell at Tyre? Aſhur alſo is ioyned to the inceſtuous children of Lot: (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) O thou of little faith, why feareſt thou? The Lord of hoſts is with vs, the God of Iacob is our refuge, Pſal. 46. Come, all yee Bands of wickedneſſe, and conſpire

againſt the Scepter of the Kingdome (that is, the Goſpell) of Ieſus Chriſt. He hath his Armageddon, He hath a Feaſt for the fowles of the Aire, and the beaſts of the field, whom he hath inuited to the fleſh of Captaines, and the fleſh of Kings, Reuel. 19. 8. I will not bee afraid of ten thouſands of people that haue ſet themſelues againſt mee round about; Dominus ſuſcepit; The Lord hath ſuſtained me, and he is the Lord of Hoſts.
            Yea, why are we apalled, when we ſee the meaſures of the ſonnes of Anak; the ſpirituall wickedneſſes in heauenly places? If wee looke at their number, they are Legions. If to their ſtrength, they are Principalities and Powers.

If to their nature, they are ſpirits that rule in the ayre. Wee are men, fleſh and blood, ſingle, weake, ſinfull. What euer we are, our God is in Heauen, and doth whatſoeuer hee will; hee is the Lord of Hoſts; though Cowards in our ſelues, yet in him wee are more then Conquerors; hee who is more then All power, then All truth, hath ſaid it; The Gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt his Church. Thanks be to God, which giueth vs victory, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.
            Laſtly, he is the Lord of Hoſts; his vndertakings are infallible: Hath hee ſaid, that the glory of the Euangelicall Church ſhall exceede the Legall? Hath hee ſaid, that, In this place he will giue
               
               peace? How can the Church faile of glory, or the ſoule of peace? His Word can be no more defectiue, then himſelfe impotent. Truſt God with his owne cauſes; truſt him with thy ſelfe; doe that he bids; expect what he promiſes; haunt this Houſe of his, wait on his ordinances. The Lord of Hoſts ſhall giue thee that peace, which paſſeth all vnderſtanding; and with peace, glorie, in that vpper Houſe of his not made with hands, eternall in the Heauens.
            To the poſſeſſion whereof, that God, who hath ordained vs, in his good time mercifully bring vs.
            And now, O Lord God of hoſts, make good thy promiſes to this

Houſe of thine. Whenſoeuer any Suppliant ſhall in this place offer vp his praiers vnto thee, heare thou in Heauen, thy dwelling place; and when thou heareſt, haue mercy. What Word ſoeuer of thine ſhall ſound out of this place, let it bee the ſauour of life vnto life to euery hearer. What Sacrament ſoeuer of thine ſhall bee in this place adminiſtred, let it be effectuall to the ſaluation of euery receiuer.
            Thou that art the God of glory, and peace, giue peace and glorie to thy Seruants, for thy mercies ſake, for thy Sonnes ſake, euen the Sonne of thy loue, Jeſus Chriſt the Juſt. To whom with thee, and the holy Ghoſt, one infinite God, be giuen all praiſe, honour, and thanks giuing, now and for euer.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

