
   
      
         
            Holy obseruations. Lib. 1. Also some fewe of Dauids Psalmes metaphrased, for a taste of the rest. By Ios. Hall
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1607
            
         
         Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02545
            STC 12671
            ESTC S103654
            99839403
            99839403
            3819
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02545)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3819)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1274:01)
         
         
            
               
                  Holy obseruations. Lib. 1. Also some fewe of Dauids Psalmes metaphrased, for a taste of the rest. By Ios. Hall
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [8], 129, [55] p.   
               
                  Printed by H. L[ownes] for Samuel Macham: and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Bull-head,
                  At London :
                  1607.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  "Some fewe of Dauids Psalms metaphrased, for a taste of the rest", unpaginated, has separate dated title page; register is continuous.
                  The last leaf is blank except for marginal rules.
                  Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Christian life --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            HOLY Obſeruations.
            LIB. I.
            ALSO Some fewe of DAVIDS Pſalmes Metaphraſed, for a taſte of the rest.
            By IOS. HALL.
            
            AT LONDON Printed by H. L. for Samuel Macham: and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Churchyard, at the ſigne of the Bull-head. 1607.
         
         
            
            To the right Honorable, EDWARD Lord Denny, Baron of Waltham, my moſt boū
               tifull Patron, Grace &amp; PEACE.
            
               Right Honorable:
            
            
               THis aduantage a ſcholler hath aboue others, that hee cannot be idle, and that hee can worke without inſtruments▪ For, the mind inured to contemplation

will ſet it ſelfe on work, when other occaſions faile: and hath no more power not to ſtudy then the eye which is open hath, not to ſee ſomthing; in which buſineſſe it carries about his owne Library, neither can complain to want books while it enioyeth it ſelfe.
            I coulde not then neglect the cōmodity of this plentifull leaſure in my ſo eaſie attendance heere; but (though beſides my courſe, and without the help of others writinges) muſt needs buſie my ſelfe

in ſuch thoughts as I haue heere giuen account of, to your Lordſhip: ſuch, as I hope will not bee vnprofitable nor vnwelcome to their Patron, to their Readers. I ſende them forth from hence, vnder your honorable name; to ſhewe you that no abſence, no imployment can make mee forget my due reſpect to your Lordſhip: to whom (next vnder my gracious Maiſter) I haue deſeruedly bequeathed my ſelfe and my indeuours. Your goodneſſe hath not wont to magnifie

it ſelfe more in giuing thē in receiuing ſuch like holy preſents: the knowledge whereof hath intitled you to more labours of this nature (if I haue numbred aright) then any of your Peeres. I miſdoubt not either your acceptation, or their vſe. That GOD, who hath aboue all his other fauours giuen your Lordſhip euen in theſe careleſs times, an heart truly religious, giue you an happy increaſe of all his heauenly graces by my vnworthie ſeruice. To his gracious care I daily

commende your Lordſhip with my Honorable Lady; wiſhing you both, all that litle ioy earth can afford you, and fulneſſe of glory aboue.
            
               Non-ſuch.

                     Iuly 3.
               
               Your Lo: Moſt humbly deuoted for euer, In all duty and obſeruance, Ioſ. Hall.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  HOLY Obſeruations.
                  
                     AS there is nothing ſooner dry then a teare; ſo there is nothing ſooner out of ſeaſon thē worldly ſorrowe: which if it be freſh and ſtill bleeding, findes ſome to comfort and pitty it; If ſtale and skinned ouer with time, is rather intertained with ſmiles then commiſeration:

But the ſorrowe of repētance comes neuer out of time. Al times are alike vnto that eternitie, whereto we make our ſpirituall moanes: That which is paſt, that which is future, are both preſent with him. It is neither weake nor vncomely, for an old man to weepe for the ſinnes of his youth. Thoſe teares can neuer be ſhed either too ſoon, or too late.
                  
                     2
                     Some men liue to be

their own executors for their good name; which they ſee (not honeſtly) buried, before thēſelues dy. Some other of great place, and ill deſert, part with their good name &amp; breath, at once. There is ſcarce a vicious man whoſe name is not rottē before his carcaſſe. Cō
                        trarily, the good mans name is oft times yt heyr to his life; eyther borne after the death of the parent, for that enuy wold not ſuffer it to come forth before: or perhaps ſo well growen vp in

his life time, that the hope therof is the ſtaffe of his age, and ioy of his death. A wicked mans name may be feared awhile; ſoone after, it is eyther forgotten or curſed: The good mans eyther ſleepeth with his bodie in peace, or waketh (as his ſoule) in glorie.
                  
                  
                     3
                     Oft times thoſe which ſhow much valor while there is equall poſſibility of life, when they ſee a preſēt neceſſity of death,

are found moſt ſhamefully timorous. Their courage was before grounded vpon hope: that, cut off, leaues them at once deſperate and cowardly: wheras men of feebler ſpirits meete more cheerefully with death; becauſe though their courage bee leſſe, yet their expectatiō was more.
                  
                  
                     4
                     I haue ſeldome ſeene the ſon of an excellent and famous man, excellent: But, that an ill bird

hath an ill egge, is not rare; children poſſeſſing as the bodily diſeaſes, ſo the vices of their Parēts. Vertue is not propagated: Vice is; euē in them which haue it not raigning in themſelues: The grain is ſowen pure, but comes vp with chaffe &amp; husk. Haſt thou a good ſon? Hee is Gods, not thine. Is he euill? Nothing but his ſinne is thine: Help by thy praiers and indeuors to take away that which thou haſt giuen him, and to obtaine from God that

which thou haſt, &amp; canſt not giue: Els thou maiſt name him a poſſeſſion; but thou ſhalt finde him a loſſe.
                  
                  
                     5
                     Theſe things be comly &amp; pleaſāt to ſee; &amp; worthy of honor frō the beholder: A young Saint, an old Martyr, a religious ſouldier, a cōſcionable Stateſ-man, a great man curteous▪ a learned man hūble, a ſilent woman, a child vnderſtanding the ey of his Parēt, a mery cōpaniō without

vanitie, a friende not changed with honour, a ſick man cheerefull, a ſoule departing with cō
                        fort and aſſurance.
                  
                  
                     6
                     I haue oft obſerued in mery meetings ſolemnly made, that ſomewhat hath fallen out croſſe, eyther in the time, or immediately vpon it; to ſeaſon (as I thinke) our immoderation in deſiring or inioying our friends: and againe, euentes ſuſpected haue proued euer beſt; God

herein bleſſing our awfull ſubmiſſion with good ſucceſſe. In all theſe humane things, indifferency is ſafe. Let thy doubtes bee euer equall to thy deſires: ſo thy diſappointmēt ſhall not bee grieuous, becauſe thy expectation was not peremptory.
                  
                  
                     7
                     You ſhall rarely finde a man eminent in ſundry faculties of mind, or ſundry manuarie trades. If his memory be excellent, his fantaſie is but

dull: if his fancie be buſie and quick, his iudgement is but ſhallow: If his iudgement be deep, his vttrance is harſhe: which alſo holds no leſſe in the actiuities of the hand. And, if it happen that one man be quallifyed with skill of diuers trades, and practice this variety, you ſhal ſeldom finde ſuch one thriuing in his eſtate: with ſpirituall giftes it is otherwiſe; which are ſo chayned together, that who excels in one hath ſome eminencie in more, yea

in all. Look vpon faith: ſhee is attended with a Beuie of Graces: Hee that beleeues, cānot but haue hope: if hope, patience. He that belieues and hopes muſt needes finde ioy in God: if ioy, loue of God; hee that loues God, cannot but love his brother: his love to God breedes piety &amp; care to pleaſe, ſorrow for offending, feare to offend. His loue to men, fidelity &amp; Chriſtian beneficēce: vices are ſeldō ſingle; but vertues go euer in troups: they go ſo

thicke, that ſometimes ſome are hid in ye croud; which yet are, but appear not: They may be ſhut out from ſight; they cannot be ſeuered.
                  
                  
                     8
                     The Heauen euer mooues, and yet is the place of our reſt: Earth euer reſts, and yet is the place of our trouble: Outwarde motion can be no enemy to inward reſt; as outwarde reſt may well ſtand with inwarde vnquietneſſe.
                  
                  
                     
                     9
                     None liue ſo ill, but they contēt themſelues in ſomewhat: Euen the begger likes the ſmell of his diſh. It is a rare euill that hath not ſomething to ſweeten it, either in ſenſe or in hope: Otherwiſe men woulde growe deſperate, mutinous, enuious of others, wearie of themſelues. The better that thing is wherein wee place our comfort, the happier we liue: and the more wee loue good things,

the better they are to vs. The Worldlinges comfort, though it bee good to him becauſe he loves it; yet becauſe it is not abſolutely and eternall good, it failes him: wherein the Chriſtian hath iuſt aduantage of him, while hee hath all the ſame cauſes of ioy refined and exalted; beſides more and hyer, which the other knows not of: The worldling laughes more, but the Chriſtiā is more delighted. Theſe two are eaſily ſeuered: Thou ſeeſt a

goodly picture, or an heap of thy gold: thou laugheſt not, yet thy delight is more then in a ieſt that ſhaketh thy ſplene: As grief, ſo ioy is not leſſe whē it is leaſt expreſſed.
                  
                  
                     10
                     I haue ſeene the worſt natures, &amp; moſt depraued minds not affecting all ſinnes: but ſtill ſome they haue condemned in others, and abhorred in themſelues: One exclaimes on couetouſneſſe, yet he can too wel

abide riotous good fellowſhip: Another inueighes againſt drunkenneſſe and exceſſe, not caring how cruel he be in vſury and oppreſſion. One cannot indure a rough and quarrellous diſpoſition, yet giues himſelfe ouer to vnclean &amp; laſciuious courſes: Another hates all wrongs, ſaue wrong to God. One is a ciuill Atheiſt, another a religious Vſurer, a third an honeſt Drunkarde, a fourth an vnchaſte Iuſticer, a fift a chaſte Quarreller.

I know not whether euery diuel excel in all ſins: I am ſure ſome of them haue denomination from ſome ſinnes more ſpeciall. Let no man applaude himſelfe for thoſe ſinnes he wanteth, but condemn himſelf rather for that ſin he hath. Thou cenſureſt another mans ſinne, hee thine; GOD curſeth both.
                  
                  
                     11
                     Golde is the heauieſt of all metalles: It is no wonder that the rich

man is vſually carryed downward to his place. It is hard for the ſoule, clogged with manie weights, to aſcēd to heauen: It muſt be a ſtrong and nimble ſoule that can carry vp it ſelfe, and ſuch a lode; yet Adam and Noah flewe vp thither with the double Monarchy of the worlds the Patriarkes with much wealth, maoie holy Kings with maſſie Crowns and Scepters. The burden of couetous deſires is more heauy to an empty ſoule

then much treaſure to the full. Our affections giue poiſe or lightneſſe to earthly things. Either abate of thy lode if thou finde it too preſſing, whether by hauing leſſe, or louing leſſe: or adde to thy ſtrength &amp; activitie, that thou mayſt yet aſcend. It is more commendable, by how much more harde, to climbe into heauen with a burden.
                  
                  
                     12
                     A Chriſtian in all his wayes muſt haue three

guides: Truth, Charity, Wiſedome: Truth to go before him; Charity &amp; Wiſdome on eyther hand. If any of the three be abſent, he walks amiſſe. I haue ſeen ſome doe hurt by following a truth vncharitably: And others while they would ſalve vp an errour with loue, haue fayled in their wiſedome, and offended againſt iuſtice. A charitable vntruth, and an vncharitable truth, and an vnwiſe menaging of truth or loue, are all to be carefullie

auoyded of him that woulde goe with a right foot in the narrow way.
                  
                  
                     13
                     GOD brought man forth at firſt, not into a Wilderneſſe, but a Garden; yet then he expected beſt ſeruice of him. I neuer finde that hee delights in the miſery, but in the proſperity of his ſeruants. Cheerfulnes pleaſes him better then a deiected and dull heauineſſe of heart. If wee can bee good with pleaſure

hee grudgeth not our ioy: If not, it is beſt to ſtint our ſelues; not for that theſe comforts are not good, but becauſe our harts are euil: falting not their nature but our vſe and corruption.
                  
                  
                     14
                     The homelieſt ſeruice that we doe in an honeſt calling, tho it be but to plow, or dig, if done in obedience, &amp; cōſcience of Gods cōmandement, is crowned with an ample reward; whereas the

beſt works for their kind (preaching, praying, offering euangelical ſacrifices) if without reſpect of Gods iniunction and glory, are loded with curſes: God loueth aduerbs; &amp; cares not how good, but how well.
                  
                  
                     15
                     The goldē infancy of ſome hath proceeded to a brazen youth, and ended in a leaden age: All humane maturities have their period: Onely grace hath none. I durſt neuer laie too muche

hope on the forwarde beginnings of witt and memorie, which haue been applauded in children. I knew they could but attaine their vigor; and that if ſooner, no whit the better: for the earlier is their perfection of wiſedome, the lō
                        ger ſhal be their witleſs age. Seaſonableneſſe is beſt in all theſe things which haue their ripeneſſe and decay: Wee can neuer hope too much of the timely bloſſomes of grace, whoſe ſpring is perpetuall,

and whoſe harueſt begins with our end.
                  
                  
                     16
                     A man muſt giue thankes for ſome-what which he may not pray for. It hath been ſayde of Courtiers, that they muſt receiue iniuries &amp; giue thanks. God cannot wrong his, but hee will croſſe them▪ thoſe croſſes are beneficiall; all benefites challenge thanks: Yet I haue read that Gods children have with condition prayed againſt them, neuer for

them. In good things we pray both for them, and their good vſe: in euill, for their good vſe, not themſelues: Yet, wee muſt giue thankes for both. For, there is no evill of paine which God dooth not; nothing that God doth, is not good; no good thing but is worthy of thankes.
                  
                  
                     17
                     One half of the world knowes not how the other liues: and therefore the better ſort pitty not the diſtreſſed; and the

miſerable enuy not thoſe which fare better, becauſe they knowe it not. Each man iudges of others condition, by his owne. The worſt ſort would be too much diſcontented, if they ſawe how farr more pleaſant the life of others is: And if ye better ſort (ſuch we cal thoſe which are greater) could look down to the infinit miſeries of inferiours, it would make them either miſerable in compaſſion, or proude in conceite. It is good, ſome-times, for the

delicate riche man to look into the poor mans cupboard: and ſeeing God in mercy gives him not to knowe their ſorrowe by experience, to knowe it yet in ſpeculation: This ſhall teache him more thankes to God, more mercy to men, more contentment in himſelfe.
                  
                  
                     18
                     Such as a mans prayer is for another, it ſhall be in time of his extreamity for himſelfe: For, though he loue himſelfe

more then others, yet his apprehenſiō of God is alike for both. Such as his praier is in a former extreamity, it ſhalbe alſo in death: this way, we may haue experience euen of a thing future: If God haue been far off frō thee in a fit of thine ordinary ſickneſſe, feare leaſt he will not be neerer thee in thy laſt: what differs that from this, but in time? Correct thy dulneſſe vpon former proofs: or els at laſt thy deuotion ſhall want life before thy body.
                  
                  
                     
                     19
                     Thoſe that come to their meat as to a medicine (as Auguſtine reports of himſelf) liue in an auſtere &amp; Chriſtian tēper, &amp; ſhalbe ſure not to ioy too much in the creature, nor to abuſe themſelues: Thoſe, that come to their medicine as to meate, ſhall be ſure to liue miſerablie and dye ſoone: To come to meate as meate, if without a gluttonous appetite &amp; palate, is allowed to Chriſtians:

To come to meat as to a ſacrifice vnto ye belly, is a moſt baſe &amp; brutiſh idolatry.
                  
                  
                     20
                     The worſt that euer were, euen Caine and Iudas haue had ſome 
                           •
                        autors that haue honoured them for Saints: And the Serpent that beguyled our firſt Parents hath in that name had diuine honour and thankes. Neuer anie man trod ſo perilous and deepe ſteppes, but ſome haue followed,

and admired him. Each maſter of hereſie hath found ſome clients; euen hee, that taught all mens opinions were true: Againe, no man hath been ſo exquiſite, but ſome haue detracted from him, euen in thoſe qualityes which haue ſeemed moſt worthy of wonder to others. A man ſhall bee ſure to be backed by ſome, eyther in good or euil, and by ſome ſhouldred in both. It is good for a man not to ſtand vpon his Abbetters, but his

quarrell; and not to depend vpon others, but himſelfe.
                  
                  
                     21
                     We ſee thouſands of Creatures dye for our vſe, and neuer doe ſo much as pitty them: why do we think much to dye once for God? They are not ours ſo much as wee are his; nor our pleaſure ſo much to vs as his glory to him: their liues are loſt to vs, ours but chā
                        ged to him.
                  
                  
                     
                     22
                     Much ornament is no good ſigne: Paynting of the face argues an ill complexion of bodie, a worſe minde. Truth, hath a face both honeſt and comely, and lookes beſt in her owne colours: but, aboue all, diuine truth is moſt faire, and moſt ſcorneth to borrowe beautie of mans witt or tongue: ſhe loveth to come forth in her natiue grace like a Princely Matrone; and counts it the greateſt

indignity, to be dallyed with as a wanton Strumpet: She lookes to command reuerēce, not pleaſure: ſhe would be kneeled to, not laughed at; To pranke her vp in vaine dreſſes and faſhions, or to ſport with her in a light and youthful maner, is moſt abhorring from her nature: they know her not, that giue her ſuch entertainment; and ſhall firſt knowe her angry, when they do know her. Againe ſhee would bee playne, but not baſe,

not ſluttiſh: She would be clad not gariſhly, but not in ragges: Shee likes as little to bee ſet out by a baſe foyle, as to ſeeme credited with gaye colours. It is no ſmall wiſdome to know her iuſt guiſe, but more to followe it; and ſo to keepe the meane, that while we pleaſe her, wee diſcontent not the beholders.
                  
                  
                     23
                     In worldly carryage ſo much is a man made of, as he takes vpō himſelfe:

but ſuch is Gods bleſſing vppon true humility, that it ſtill procureth reuerence. I neuer ſawe Chriſtian leſſe honored for a wiſe neglect of himſelfe: If our deiection proceed from the conſcience of our want, it is poſſible wee ſhould be as little eſteemed of others, as of our ſelues: But if wee haue true graces, and prize them not at the higheſt; others ſhall value both them in vs, and vs for them, and with vſurie giue vs that honour wee

with held modeſtly frō our ſelues.
                  
                  
                     24
                     He, that takes his full liberty in what he may, ſhall repent him: how much more in what he ſhoulde not? I neuer read of Chriſtian that repented him of too little worldlie delight. The ſureſt courſe I have ſtill found in all earthlie pleaſures, To riſe with an appetite, and to bee ſatisfied with a little.
                  
                  
                     
                     25
                     There is a time when Kings goe not forth to warfare: Our ſpirituall warre admitts no intermiſſion: it knowes no night, no winter, abides no peace, no truce. This cals vs not into a gariſō, where we may have eaſe and reſpite, but into pitched fields cōtinually: we ſee our enemies in the face alwaies, and are alwayes ſeene and aſſalted: euer reſiſting, euer defēding, receiuing and returning blowes.

If eyther wee be negligent or weary, wee dy: what other hope is ther while one fights, &amp; the other ſtands ſtill? We can neuer haue ſafet
                           ••
                         &amp; peace, but in victory. There muſt our reſiſtance be couragious and conſtant, whe
                           ••
                         both yielding is death, and all treatyes of peace mortall.
                  
                  
                     26
                     Neutrality in things good or euil is both odious, and preiudicial; but in matters of an indifferent

nature is ſafe and commendable: Herein taking of parts, maketh ſides, and breaketh vnitie. In an vniuſt cauſe of ſeparation, hee that fauoureth both partes, may perhaps haue leaſt loue of either ſide; but hath moſt charitie in himſelfe.
                  
                  
                     27
                     Nothing is more abſurd then that Epicurean reſolution, Let vs eat and drinke, to morrow wee ſhall dy: As if wee were made onely for

the paunch, &amp; liued that we might liue: yet ther was neuer any naturall man found ſauor in that meat which hee knewe ſhould be his laſt: wheras they ſhould ſay; Let vs faſt and pray, to morrow we ſhall die: For, to what purpoſe is the body ſtrengthened that it may periſh? whoſe greater ſtrength makes our death more violent. No man beſtowes a coſtly roofe on a ruinous tenement: That mans end is eaſie &amp; happy whom death finds with a weak

bodie, and a ſtrong ſoule.
                  
                  
                     28
                     Somtimes, euen things in themſelues naturally good, are to bee refuſed for thoſe, which (being euil) may be an occaſion to a greater good. Life is in it ſelf good, and death-euill: Els Dauid, Elias and many excellent Martyrs would not have fled, to hold life, and auoid death; Nor Ezekiah haue prayed for it, nor our Sauiour haue bidden vs to flee for it,

nor God promiſed it to his for a reward; yet if in ſome caſes wee hate not life, wee loue not God, nor our ſoules. Heerein, as much as in any thing, the peruerſneſſe of our nature appeares, that wee wiſhe death, or loue life vpon wrong cauſes: we would liue for pleaſure, or wee woulde die for payne; Iob for his ſores, Elias for his perſecution, Ionas for his gourd would preſently dye, and will needs outface God that it is better for him to

die, then to liue: wherin wee are like to garriſon ſouldiers, that while they liue within ſafe wals, and ſhowe themſelues once a day rather for ceremony &amp; pomp, then neede or daunger, like warrefare well enough; but if once called foorth to the field, they wiſh thēſelues at home.
                  
                  
                     29
                     Not onely the leaſt but the worſt is ever in the bottome: what ſhoulde God doe with the dregges of our age?

when ſinne will admitt thee his Clyent no longer, then God ſhall be beholdē to thee for thy ſeruice: Thus is God dealt-with in all other offrings; The worſt &amp; leaſt ſheafe muſt bee Gods Tenth: The deformedſt or ſimpleſt of our Children muſt bee Gods Miniſters: The vncleanlyeſt and moſt careleſſe houſe muſt be Gods Temple; the idleſt and ſleepyeſt houres of the day muſt bee reſerued for our praiers; The worſt part of our age

for Deuotion. Wee woulde haue God giue vs ſtil of the beſt, and are ready to murmure at euerie little euill he ſends vs: yet, nothing is bad enough for him, of whō we receiue all. Nature condemnes this inequality: and tells vs, that he which is the author of good, ſhould haue the beſt; and hee which giues al ſhould haue his choice.
                  
                  
                     30
                     When we go about an euill buſineſſe, it is ſtrange how readie the

diuell is to ſet vs forward; how carefull that we ſhould want no furtherances: So that if a man would bee lewdly witty, hee ſhalbe ſure to be furniſhed with ſtore of profane ieſts, wherein a looſe heart hath double aduātage of the conſcionable. If hee would bee voluptuous, hee ſhall want neither obiects nor opportunities. The currant paſſage of ill enterpriſes is ſo far from giuing cauſe of incouragement, that it ſhoulde iuſtly fright a

man to look back to the author; and to conſider that hee therefore goes faſt, becauſe the Diuell driues him.
                  
                  
                     31
                     In the choice of cō
                        panions for our conuerſation, it is good dealing with men of good natures: for, tho grace exerciſeth her power in bridling nature, yet (ſith wee are ſtill men, at the beſt) ſome ſwinge ſhe will haue in the moſt mortyfied. Auſteritie, ſullenneſſe, or ſtrangeneſſe

of diſpoſition, and what-ſoeuer qualityes may make a man vnſociable, cleaue faſter to our nature, then thoſe which are morally euill. True Chriſtian loue maie bee ſeparated from acquaintance, and acquaintance from intireneſſe: Theſe are not qualities to hinder our loue, but our familiaritie.
                  
                  
                     32
                     Ignorāce as it makes bold, intruding men careleſly into vnknow'n

dangers; ſo alſo it makes men oft-times cauſeleſly fearefull. Herod feared Chriſts comming, becauſe he miſtooke it: If that Tyrant had knowen the manner of his ſpirituall regiment, hee had ſpared both his own fright and the blood of others. And hence it is, that wee feare Death, becauſe wee are not acquainted with the vertue of it. Nothing but innocēce &amp; knowledge can giue ſound confidence to the heart.
                  
                  
                     
                     33
                     Where are diuers opinions, they may be all falſe; ther can be but one true: and that one Truth oft-times muſt be fetcht by peece-meale out of diuers branches of contrary opinions. For, it falles out not ſeldome, that Truth is through ignorance or raſh vehemency ſcattred into ſundry parts; and, like to a little ſiluer melted amongſt the ruines of a burnt houſe, muſt be tried out from heapes of

much ſuperfluous aſhes. Ther is much paines in the ſearch of it; much skill in finding it: the value of it once founde requytes the coſte of both.
                  
                  
                     34
                     Affectation of ſuperfluitie, is in all thinges a ſigne of weakneſſe: As, in words hee that vſeth circumlocutions to expreſſe himſelfe, ſhowes want of memory, and want of proper ſpeach: And much talk argues a braine feeble &amp; diſtempered:

what good can any earthly thing yield vs beſide his vſe? and what is it but vanitie to affect that which dooth vs no good? and what vſe is in that which is ſuperfluous? It is a great skill to know what is enough, and great wiſedome to care for no more.
                  
                  
                     35
                     Good things, which in abſence were deſired, now offring themſelues to our preſence are ſcarce intertained; or at leaſt not with our purpoſed

cheerefulneſſe. Chriſts comming to vs and our going to him are in our profeſſion wel eſteemed, much wiſhed: But when hee ſingleth vs out by a direct meſſage of death, or by ſome fearefull ſigne giueth likelihood of a preſent returne, wee are as much affected with feare, as before with deſire. All changes, although to the better, are troubleſome for the time, vntill our ſettling: Ther is no remedy herof but inward preuention:

Our minde muſt change, before our eſtate be changed.
                  
                  
                     36
                     Thoſe are greateſt enemies to religion, that are not moſt irreligious. Atheiſtes, tho in themſelues they be the worſt, yet are ſeldome found hot Perſecuters of others: wheras thoſe which in ſome one fundamentall point be hereticall, are commonly moſt violent in oppoſitions. One hurts by ſecret infection, the other

by open reſiſtance: One is careleſſe of all truth, the other vehement for ſome vntruth. An Atheiſt is worthy of more hatred, an Hereticke of more feare; both, of auoidance.
                  
                  
                     37
                     Wayes if neuer vſed cannot but bee faire; if much vſed are made cō
                        modiouſly paſſable; if before oft vſed, and now ſeldome, they become deep and dangerous. If the hart be not at al inured to meditation, it findeth

no fault with it ſelf; not for that it is innocent, but ſecure; If often, it findeth comfortable paſſage for his thoughts; If rarely, and with intermiſſion, tedious and troubleſome. In things of this nature, wee onely eſcape complaint, if wee vſe them eyther alwayes or neuer.
                  
                  
                     38
                     Our ſenſual hand holds faſt whatſoeuer delight it apprehēdeth: our ſpirituall hand eaſily remitteth;

becauſe appetite is ſtronger in vs thē grace: whence it is that wee ſo hardly deliuer our ſelues of earthlie pleaſures, which wee haue once entertayned; and with ſuch difficulty draw our ſelues to a conſtant courſe of faith, hope, and ſpirituall ioy, or to the renued acts of thē once intermitted. Age is naturally weak, and youth vigorous; but in vs the olde man is ſtrong, the newe faint and feeble: the fault is not in grace, but in vs: Faith dooth

not want ſtrength, but we want faith.
                  
                  
                     39
                     It is not good in worldly eſtates for a man to make himſelfe neceſſary. For, herupon he is both more toyled, and more ſuſpected: but in the ſacred Common-wealth of the Church, a man cannot bee ingaged too deepely by his ſeruice: The ambition of ſpirituall well-doing, breedes no danger. He that doth beſt, and may worſt be ſpared, is happieſt.
                  
                  
                     
                     40
                     It was a fit compariſon of worldly cares, to thornes: For, as they choak the word, ſo they prick our ſoules: Neyther the word can grow vp amongſt them, nor the heart can reſt vpon them: Neyther bodie nor ſoule can finde eaſe while they are within, or cloſe to vs: Spirituall cares are as ſharpe; but more profitable; they payne vs, but leaue the ſoule better. They break our ſleepe, but for a

ſweeter reſt: we are not wel but either while we haue them, or after wee haue had them. It is as impoſſible to haue ſpirituall health without theſe, as to haue bodily ſtrength with the other.
                  
                  
                     41
                     In temporall good things, it is beſt to live in doubt; not making full account of that, which we hold in ſo weak a tenure. In ſpirituall, with confidence; not fearing that which is warranted

to vs by an infallible promiſe &amp; ſure earneſt. He lives moſt contētedly, that is moſt ſecure for this world, moſt reſolute for the other.
                  
                  
                     42
                     God hath in nature giuen euery man inclinatiōs to ſome one particular calling; which if he follow, he excells; if hee croſſe, he proues a non-proficiēt, &amp; changeable: But all mens natures are equally indiſpoſed to grace, and to the common vocation

of Chriſtianity: we are all borne heathens. To do well; nature muſt in the firſt be obſerued and followed, in the other croſſed and ouercome.
                  
                  
                     43
                     Good-man, is a title given to ye loweſt; wheras all Titles of Greatneſſe, Worſhip, Honor, are obſerued and attributed with choice. The ſpeech of the World bewrayes their minde &amp; ſhowes the common eſtimation of goodnes compared with other

qualities. The World therfore is an il Herald, and vnskilful in the true ſtiles: It were happie that goodneſſe were ſo common; and pity that it eyther ſhoulde not ſtand with greatneſſe, or not bee preferred to it.
                  
                  
                     44
                     Amongſt all actions Satan is euer buſieſt in the beſt, and moſt in the beſt part of the beſt; as in the ende of Prayer when the heart ſhould cloſe vp it ſelfe with

moſt comfort. Hee neuer feares vs, but when wee are well imployed: and the more likelyhood he ſees of our profit, the more is his enuie, and labour to diſtract vs. Wee ſhoulde loue our ſelues, as much as he hates vs; and therfore ſtriue ſo muche the more towardes our good, as his malice ſtriueth to interrupt it. We doe nothing, if we contende not, when wee are reſiſted. The good ſoule is ever in contradiction; denying what

is graunted, and contending for that which is denyed; ſuſpecting when it is gayne-ſaide, and fearing libertie.
                  
                  
                     45
                     God forewarnes ere he try, becauſe he would be preuented: Sathan ſteales vpon vs ſuddenly by temptations, becauſe he would ſoile vs. If we relent not vppon Gods premonition, and meet not the lingring paſe of his puniſhmēts to foreſtall them, he puniſheth

more by how much his warning was more euident and more large; Gods tryals muſt be met when they come: Satans muſt bee ſeene before they come; and if we be not armed ere wee bee aſſaulted, wee ſhall be foyled ere wee can bee armed.
                  
                  
                     46
                     It is not good to bee continuall in denunciation of iudgement: The noyſe, to which wee are accuſtomed (tho loud) wakes vs not; whereas

a leſſe if vnuſuall ſtirreth vs: The next waie to make threatnings contemned, is to make them common. It is a profitable rodde that ſtrikes ſparingly, and frightes ſomwhat oftener then it ſmiteth.
                  
                  
                     47
                     Want of vſe cauſeth diſabilitie, and cuſtome perfection. Thoſe that haue not vſed to praie in their cloſet, cannot pray in publique, but coldely and in forme. Hee that diſcontinues

meditation ſhal be long in recouering; whereas the man inured to theſe exerciſes (who is not dreſſed till he haue praied, nor hath ſupped till hee haue meditated) dooth both theſe well, and with eaſe. He, that intermittes good duties, incurres a double loſſe: of the bleſſing that followeth good; of the facultie of dooing it.
                  
                  
                     48
                     Chriſtianitie is both an eaſie yoke, and an

hard; hard to take vp, eaſie to beare when once taken. The heart requires much labour, ere it can bee induced to ſtoope vnder it; and findes as much contentment when it hath ſtooped. The Worldling thinkes Religion ſeruilitie: but, the Chriſtian knowes whoſe ſlaue hee was, till hee entred into this ſeruice; and that no bondage can be ſo ill, as freedome from theſe bondes.
                  
                  
                     
                     49
                     It is a wonder how full of ſhiftes nature is; Ready to turne ouer all good purpoſes. If wee thinke of death, ſhe ſuggeſts ſecretly, Tuſh it ſhall not come yet: If of iudgement for ſinne, this concernes not thee; it ſhall not come at all: If of heauen and our labour to reach it; Trouble not thy ſelfe, it will come ſoone enough alone: Addreſſe thy ſelf to pray; it is yet vnſeaſonable, ſtay for a better

opportunitie: To giue almes; thou knoweſt not thy owne future wāts: To reproue; what neeedeſt thou thruſt thy ſelfe into wilfull hatred? Euery good action hath his lett: He can neuer be good, that is not reſolute.
                  
                  
                     50
                     All Artes are Maides to Diuinitie; therefore they both vayle to her, and do her ſeruice: and ſhe like a graue miſtreſſe controlls them at pleaſure: Naturall philoſophie

teacheth, that of nothing can be nothing made; and, that from the privation to the habite is no returne: Diuinitie takes her vp, for theſe; and, vpon ſupernaturall principles, teaches her a Creation, a Reſurrection. Philoſophy teaches vs to follow ſenſe, as an infallible guide; Diuinity tels hir, that faith is of things not ſeen. Logick teaches vs firſt to diſcourſe, then to reſolue: Diuinity, to aſſent without arguing. Ciuil law teacheth, that

long cuſtome preſcribeth: Diuinity that old things are paſſed; Morall Philoſophie that tallying of iniuries is iuſtice: Divinitie, that good muſt be returned for ill; Policie, that better is a miſchiefe then an inconuenience: Diuinitie, that wee maie not doe euill that good maie enſue. The Schoole is well ordered, while Diuinitie keepes the chaire: but, if anie other skill vſurpe it, and checke their miſtreſſe, there can followe

nothing but confuſion and Atheiſme.
                  
                  
                     51
                     Much difference is to bee made betwixt a reuolter, and a man trayned vp in error. A Iew and an Arryan both deny Chriſts deity: yet this opinion is not in both puniſhed with bodily death. Yea, a reuolt to a leſſe error is more puniſhable then education in a capitall hereſie. Errors of iudgement, tho leſſe regarded then errors of practice, yet are

more pernicious: but none ſo deadly as theirs that once were in the truth. If truth be not ſued to, it is dangerous; but if forſaken, deſperate.
                  
                  
                     52
                     It is an ill argument of a good action not well done, when we are glad that it is done. To bee affected with the comfort of the conſcience of wel performing it, is good: but meerly to reioyce that the act is ouer, is carnall. He

neuer can begin cheerfully, that is glad he hath ended.
                  
                  
                     53
                     Hee that dooth not ſecret ſeruice to GOD with ſome delight, doth but counterfaite in publique. The truth of anie acte or paſſion is then beſt tryed, when it is without witneſſe. Openlie, manie ſiniſter reſpects may draw from vs a forme of religious duties: ſecretly, nothing but the power of a good conſcience. It is to bee

feared, God hath more true &amp; deuout ſeruice, in cloſets, thē in churches.
                  
                  
                     54
                     Words and diſeaſes grow vpō vs with years. In age wee talke much, becauſe wee haue ſeene much, and ſoone after ſhal ceaſe talking for euer: Wee are moſt diſeaſed, becauſe nature is weakeſt, and death which is neere, muſt have harbingers: ſuch is the old age of the World. No maruell, if this laſt time bee full of

writing, and weake diſcourſe; full of ſectes and hereſies, which are the ſickneſſes of this great and decaied body.
                  
                  
                     55
                     The beſt ground vntilled ſooneſt runs out into ranke weeds. Such are Gods Children; Ouer-growne with ſecuritie ere they are aware, vnleſſe they bee wel exerciſed both with Gods plow of affliction, and their owne induſtry in meditation. A man of knowledge that is eyther

negligent, or vncorrected, cannot but growe wilde and godleſſe.
                  
                  
                     56
                     With vs vileſt things are moſt common; But with GOD the beſt thinges are moſt frequently giuen. Grace which is the nobleſt of all Gods fauours, is vnpartially b
                           ••••
                        wed vpon all willing 
                           •
                        eceiuers; whereas Nobilitie of blood and height of place, bleſſings of an inferiour nature, are reſerued

for fewe. Heerein the Chriſtian followes his Father; his prayers which are his richeſt portion hee communicates to al; his ſubſtance according to his ability, to fewe.
                  
                  
                     57
                     God therfore giues, becauſe hee hath giuen; making his former fauours, 
                           ••••
                        ments for more: Man therefore ſhuts his hand, becauſe he hath opened it. Ther is no ſuch way to procure more from God,

as to vrge him with what he hath done. All Gods bleſſings are profitable and excellent; not ſo much in themſelues, as that they are inducements to greater.
                  
                  
                     58
                     Gods immediate actions are beſt, at firſt. The frame of his creation how exquiſite was it vnder his hand! afterwardes, blemiſhed by our ſin: mans indeuours are weake in their beginnings, and perfitter by degrees. No ſcience,

no deuiſe hath euer bin perfite in his cradle; or at once hath ſeene his birth and maturitie: of the ſame nature are thoſe actions which God worketh mediately by vs according to our meaſure of receit. The cauſe of both is, on the one ſide the infiniteneſſe of his wiſedome and power which cannot bee corrected by any ſecond aſſayes: On the other, our weakenes helping it ſelfe by former grounds and tryals. Hee is an happie man

that detractes nothing from Gods workes, and addes moſt to his owne.
                  
                  
                     59
                     The olde ſaying is more cōmon then true; that thoſe which are in hell know no other heauen: for this makes the damned perfitly miſerable, that out of their own torment, they ſee the felicitie of the ſaints; togither with their impoſſibility of attayning it. Sight without hope of fruition is a torment alone: Thoſe that heere

might ſee God and will not, or doe ſee him obſcurely and love him not, ſhall once ſee him with anguiſh of ſoule &amp; not enioie him.
                  
                  
                     60
                     Somtimes euill ſpeeches come from good men, in their vnaduiſedneſſe▪ and, ſomtimes, euen the good ſpeeches of men may proceede from an ill ſpirit. No confeſſion coulde bee better then Satan gaue of Chriſt: It is not enough

to conſider what is ſpoken, or by whom; but whence, &amp; for what. The ſpirit is oft-times tryed by the ſpeech: but other-times the ſpeech muſt bee examined by the ſpirit; and the ſpirit, by the rule of an higher word.
                  
                  
                     61
                     Greatneſſe puts hie thoughts, &amp; big words, into a man; whereas the deiected minde takes, careleſly, what offers it ſelfe. Euerie worldling is baſe-minded;

&amp; therfore his thoughts creep ſtil lowe vpon the earth. The Chriſtian both is &amp; knowes himſelfe truely great; and thereupon mindeth and ſpeaketh of ſpirituall, immortall, glorious, heauenly thinges. So much as the ſoule ſtoopeth to earthly thoughts; ſo much is it vnregenerate.
                  
                  
                     62
                     Long acquaintance as it maketh thoſe things which are euill, to ſeem leſſe euill; ſo it makes

good thinges which at firſt were vnpleaſant, delightfull. There is no euill of payne, nor no morall good action, which is not harſh at the firſt. Continuance of euill, which might ſeem to weary vs, is the remedie and abatement of wearineſſe: &amp; the practice of good, as it profiteth, ſo it pleaſeth. He that is a ſtrāger to good and euill, findes both of them troubleſome. GOD therefore dooth well for vs, while he exerciſeth vs with long afflictions:

and wee doe well to our ſelues while wee continually buſie our ſelues in good exerciſes.
                  
                  
                     63
                     Sometimes it is well taken by men, that wee humble our ſelues lower then there is cauſe. Thy ſeruant IACOB, ſayth that good Patriarch; to his brother, to his inferiour. And no leſſe well doth God take theſe ſubmiſſe extenuations of our ſelues; I am a worme &amp; no man:

Surely I am more fooliſh then a man, &amp; haue not the vnderſtanding of a man in mee. But I neuer finde, that anie man bragged to GOD although in a matter of Truth, and within the compaſſe of his deſert, and was accepted. A man may be too lowly in his dealing with men, euen vnto contempt: with God hee cannot; but the lower hee falleth, the higher is his exaltation.
                  
                  
                     
                     64
                     The ſoule is fed as the bodie, ſtarued with hunger as the body, requires proportionable diet and neceſſarie varietie, as the bodie. All ages and ſtatures of the ſoule beare not the ſame nouriſhment. There is milk for ſpiritual infants, ſtrong meate for the growen Chriſtian. The ſpoone is fit for one, the knife for the other. The beſt Chriſtian is not ſo growen that hee neede

to ſcorne the ſpoone: but the weake Chriſtian may finde a ſtrong feede dangerous. How manie haue beene caſt away with ſpirituall ſurfets; becauſe being but newe-borne they haue ſwallowed down bigge morſelles of the higheſt myſteries of godlineſſe, which they neuer could digeſt; but together with them haue caſt vp their proper noriſhment. A man muſt firſt know the power of his ſtomach, ere hee knowe how with ſafetie

and profit to frequent Gods Ordinary.
                  
                  
                     65
                     It is verie hard for the beſt man, in a ſuddayne extreamitie of death, to ſatisfie himſelf in apprehending his ſtaie, and repoſing his heart vppon it: for the ſoule is ſo oppreſſed with ſuddaine terrour, that it cannot wel commaund it ſelfe, till it haue digeſted an euill. It were miſerable for the beſt Chriſtian, if all his former prayers and

meditations did not ſerue to ayde him in his laſt ſtraites, and meete together in the center of his extreamitie: yielding though not ſenſible reliefe, yet ſecret benefit to the ſoule; wheras the worldly man in this caſe, hauing not laid vp for this houre, hath no comfort from God, or from others, or from himſelfe.
                  
                  
                     66
                     All externall good or euill is meaſured by

ſenſe: neither can we account that eyther good or ill, which doth neither actually auaile, nor hurt vs: ſpiritually this rule holds not. All our beſt good is inſenſible. For, al our future (which is the greateſt) good, we hold onlie in hope; and the preſent fauour of God wee haue many times, and feel not. The ſtomach findes the beſt digeſtion euen in ſleepe when we leaſt perceiue it; and whiles wee are moſt awake, this power worketh in vs eyther to

further ſtrength or diſeaſe, without our knowledge of what is done within: And on the other ſide, that man is moſt dangerouſly ſick, in whome nature decayes without his feeling, without his complaint. To knowe our ſelues happie, is good: but wo were to vs Chriſtians, if wee could not bee happie, and knowe it not.
                  
                  
                     67
                     There are none that euer did ſo much miſchief

to the Church, as thoſe that haue beene excellent in wit &amp; learning. Others may bee ſpightfull enough, but want power to accompliſh their malice. An enemy that hath both ſtrength &amp; craft is worthy bee feared. None can ſinne againſt the Holy-Ghoſt, but thoſe which haue had former illumination. Tell not mee what partes a man hath, but what grace: honeſt ſottiſhnes is better then profane eminence.
                  
                  
                     
                     68
                     The intertainement of all ſpiritualll euents muſt bee with feare or hope; but, of all earthly extreamities, muſt bee with cōtempt or deriſiō. For, what is terrible, is worthy of a Chriſtians contempt; what is pleaſant, to bee turned ouer with a ſcorne. The meane requires a mean affection betwixt loue &amp; hatred. We may not loue them, becauſe of their vanitie: wee may not hate them, becauſe

of their neceſſarie vſe. It is an hard thing to bee a wiſe hoſt; and to fit our entertainment to all comers: which if it be not done, the ſoule is ſoone waſted, eyther for want of cuſtomers, or for the miſ-rule of ill gueſts.
                  
                  
                     69
                     God and man build in a contrary order. Man layes the foundatiō firſt, then addes the walls, the roofe laſt. God began the roofe firſt, ſpreading out this vault of heauen,

ere he layd ye baſe of the earth. Our thoughtes muſt followe the order of his worke-manſhip. Heavē muſt be minded firſt; earth afterwarde: and ſo much more, as it is ſeene more. Our meditation muſt herein follow our ſenſe: A fewe miles giue boundes to our view of earth; wheras wee may neere ſee half the heaven at once. Hee that thinkes moſt both of that which is moſt ſeene, and of that which is not ſeene at all, is happieſt.
                  
                  
                     
                     70
                     I haue euer noted it a true ſigne of a falſe heart, To be ſcrupulous and nice in ſmall matters, negligent in the mayne: whereas the good ſoule is ſtill curious in ſubſtātiall points, and not careleſſe in things of an inferiour nature; accounting no dutie ſo ſmall as to bee neglected, and no care great enough for principall duties: not ſo tithing mint and cummin, that he ſhould forget

iuſtice and iudgement; nor yet ſo regarding iudgement and iuſtice, that he ſhould contemne mint &amp; cummin. Hee that thus miſplaces his conſcience, will bee found either hypocriticall or ſuperſtitious.
                  
                  
                     71
                     It argues the world full of Atheiſtes, that thoſe offences which may impeach humane ſocietie, are entertained with an anſwerable hatred and rigor: Thoſe which do immediately

wrong the ſupreme maieſtie of God, are turned ouer with ſcarce ſo much as diſlike. If wee conuerſed with God as we doe with men, his right would bee at leaſt as precious to vs as our owne. All that conuerſe not with God are without God: not only thoſe that are againſt God, but thoſe that are without God are Atheiſts. Wee may be too charitable: I feare not to ſay, that theſe our laſt times abound with honeſt Atheiſts.
                  
                  
                     
                     72
                     The beſt thing corrupted, is worſt: An ill man is the worſt of all creatures, an ill Chriſtian the worſt of all men, an ill profeſſor the worſt of all Chriſtians.
                  
                  
                     73
                     Naturally life is before death, and death is only a priuation of life: Spiritually it is contrary: As PAVL ſayth of the grayne, ſo may wee of man in the buſineſſe of his Regeneration. Hee

muſt die before hee can liue; yet this death preſuppoſes a life that was once, and ſhould bee. God chooſes to haue the difficulteſt, firſt: we muſt bee content with the payne of dying, ere we feele the comfort of life. As wee dy to nature, ere we liue in glory: So, wee muſt die to ſinne, ere we can live to Grace.
                  
                  
                     74
                     Death did not firſt ſtrike Adam the firſt ſinfull man: nor Cain the

firſt hypocrite; but Abel the innocent and righteous. The firſt ſoule that met with death, overcame death: the firſt ſoule that parted from earth, went to Heaven. Death argues not diſpleaſure: becauſe he whō God loved beſt, dyes firſt; and the murtherer is puniſhed with living.
                  
                  
                     75
                     The lives of moſt are miſ-ſpent, only for want of a certayne ende of their actions. Wherin,

they doe as vnwiſe Archers, ſhoot away their arrows they know not at what mark: They liue only out of the preſent, not directing thēſelues and their proceedings to one vniuerſall ſcope: whence they alter vpon all change of occaſions, and neuer reache anie perfection; neither can doe other but continue in vncertaintie, and end in diſcomfort. Others ayme at one certaine marke, but a wrong one. Some (tho fewer) leuell at the right end,

but amiſſe. To liue without one maine and common ende, is idleneſſe and folly. To liue to a falſe ende is deceit and loſſe: True Chriſtian wiſdom both ſhows the end, and findes the way. And as cunning Politickes have many plots to compaſſe one and the ſame deſigne by a determined ſucceſſion: ſo the wiſe Chriſtian, fayling in the meanes, yet ſtill fetcheth about to his ſteadie ende with a conſtant change of indeuours: Such one onely

lives to purpoſe, and at laſt repents not that hee hath lived.
                  
                  
                     76
                     The ſhip-wrack of a good conſcience is the caſting awaie of all other excellencies. It is no rare thing to note the ſoule of a wilfull ſinner ſtripped of all her graces, and by degrees expoſed to ſhame: ſo thoſe, whom wee have knowen admired, have fall'n to bee levell with their fellows; and from thence beneath them, to

a mediocrity; and afterwards to ſottiſhnes and contempt, belowe the vulgar. Since they haue caſt awaie the beſt, it is iuſt with God to take away the worſt; and to caſt off them in leſſer regardes, which haue reiected him in greater.
                  
                  
                     77
                     It hath euer bin counted more noble and ſuccesfull, to ſet vpon an open enemie in his owne home, then to expect till hee ſet vppon vs, whiles wee make onely

a defenſiue warre. This rule ſerues vs for our laſt enemy Death: whence that olde demand of Epicure is eaſily anſwered; whether it bee better Death ſhould come to vs, or that we ſhould meete him in the waie: meet him in our minds, ere hee ſeize vpon our bodies. Our cowardlineſſe, our vnpreparation is his aduantage: wheras true boldeneſſe, in confronting him, diſmayes and weakens his forces. Happie is that ſoule that can ſende out

the ſcoutes of his thoughts before-hand, to diſcouer the power of Death afarre off; and then can reſolutely incounter him at vnwares vpon aduantage: ſuch one lives with ſecuritie, dies with comfort.
                  
                  
                     78
                     Manie a man ſends others to heauen, and yet goes to hell himſelfe: and not fewe hauing drawn others to hell, yet themſelues returne by a late repentance, to life. In a good actiō it is not

good action, it is not good to ſearche too deeply into the intentiō of the agent, but in ſilēce to make our beſt benefit of the worke: In an euil, it is not ſafe to regard the qualitie of the perſon, or his ſucceſſe, but to conſider the action abſtracted from all circumſtances, in his owne kind. So we ſhall neither neglecte good deedes becauſe they ſpeede not well in ſome hands, nor affecta proſperous euill.
                  
                  
                     
                     78
                     God doth ſome ſingular actions, wherein we cannot imitate him; ſome wherein wee may not; moſt wherin he may and would fain be followed. He fetcheth good out of euill; ſo may wee turn our owne &amp; others ſinnes to priuate or publique good: we may not doe euill for a good vſe; but wee muſt vſe our euil once done, to good. I hope I ſhall not offende, to ſay, that the

good vſe which is made of ſinnes is as gainefull to God, as that which ariſes from good actions. Happie is that man, that can vſe eyther his good, well, or his euill.
                  
                  
                     79
                     There is no difference betwixt anger and madneſſe, but continuance: for, raging▪ anger is a ſhort madneſſe. What elſe argues the ſhaking of the hands and lippes, paleneſſe or redneſſe,

or ſwelling of the face, glaring of the eies, ſtammering of the tongue, ſtamping with the feet, vnſteadie motions of the whole bodie, raſhe actions which wee remember not to haue done, diſtracted and wilde ſpeeches? and madneſſe againe is nothing but a continued rage, yea ſome madneſſe rageth not: ſuch a mild madneſſe is more tolerable then frequent and furious anger.
                  
                  
                     
                     80
                     Thoſe that woulde keepe ſtate, muſt keepe aloofe off; eſpecially if their qualities bee not anſwerable in height to their place. For, many great perſons are like a well-wrought picture vpon a courſe cloath; which afarre off ſhewes faire, but neer hand the roundneſſe of the thred marres the good workemanſhip. Concealement of gifts, after ſome one commended acte, is

the beſt way to admiration, and ſecret honor: but hee that would profit, muſt vent himſelfe oft and liberally, and ſhowe what he is, without all priuate regarde. As therefore, manie times, honour followes modeſtie, vnlookt for; ſo, contrarily, a man may ſhewe no leſſe pride in ſilence and obſcuritie, then others which ſpeake and write for glorie. And that other pride is ſo much more the worſe, as it is more vnprofitable:

for, wheras thoſe which put forth their gifts, benefit others while they ſeeke themſelues; theſe are ſo wholly deuoted to themſelues, that their ſecrecy dooth no good to others.
                  
                  
                     81
                     Such as a mans delightes and cares are in health, ſuch are both his thoughtes and ſpeeches commonly on his death-bed: The proud man talkes of his faire ſutes, the glutton of

his diſhes, the wanton of his beaſtlineſſe, the religious man of heauēly things. The tongue will hardly leaue that, to which the heart is inured. If we would haue good motions to viſit vs while wee are ſicke, wee muſt ſend for them familiarly in our health.
                  
                  
                     82
                     Hee is a rare man that hath not ſome kind of madneſſe reigning in him: One a dull madneſſe of melancholy, another

a cōceited madneſſe of pride, another a ſuperſtitious madneſſe of falſe deuotion, a fourth of ambition, or couetouſneſſe, a fift the furious madneſſe of anger; a ſixt the laughing madneſſe of extreame mirth, a ſeauenth a drunken madneſſe, an eightth of outragious luſt, a ninth the learned madneſſe of curioſitie, a tenth the worſt madneſſe of profaneneſſe and Atheiſme. It is as hard to reckon vp all kindes of madneſſes,

as of diſpoſitions. Some are more noted and puniſhed then others; for that the mad in one kinde dooth as much condemne another, as the ſober man condemnes him. Onlie that man is both good, and wiſe and happie, that is free from all kindes of phrē
                        ſie.
                  
                  
                     75
                     There bee ſome honeſt errors, wherewith I neuer found that God was offended; That

an husband ſhould think his owne wife comely, although ill-fauoured in the eyes of others; that a man ſhoulde thinke more meanely of his owne good partes then of weaker in others; to giue charitable (though miſtaken) conſtructions of doubtfull actions and perſons (which are the effectes of naturall affection, humilitie, loue) were neuer cenſured by God: Herein alone wee erre, if wee erre not.
                  
                  
                     
                     84
                     No maruell if the worldling eſcape earthly afflictions. God correctes him not; becauſe hee loues him not. He is baſe-borne and begot: God will not doe him the fauour to whip him. The world afflicts him not; becauſe it loues him. For each one is indulgent to his owne. God vſes not the rodde where he meanes to vſe the ſword; The pillory or ſcourge is for thoſe

malefactors which ſhall eſcape execution.
                  
                  
                     85
                     VVeake ſtomackes which can not digeſt large meales, feede oft and little: For our ſoules, that which we want in meaſure, we muſt ſupply in frequence. Wee can neuer fully enough cō
                        prehēd in our thoughts the ioyes of heauen, the meritorious ſufferings of Chriſt, the terrours of the ſecōd death: therfore wee muſt meditate of them often.
                  
                  
                     
                     86
                     The ſame thoughtes doe commonly meet vs in the ſame places; as if wee had left them there till our returne. For that the minde doth ſecretly frame to it ſelf me moratiue heads, wherby it recalls eaſily the ſame conceits: It is beſt to employ our mind there, where it is moſt fixed. Our deuotion is ſo dull, it cannot haue too many aduantages.
                  
                  
                     
                     87
                     I finde but one example, in all ſcripture, of anie bodily cure which our Sauiour wrought by degrees: Onely the blind man, whoſe weake faith craued helpe by others, not by himſelf, ſaw men firſt like trees, then in their true ſhape. All other miraculous cures of Chriſt were done at once, and perfect at firſt. Contrarily, I finde but one example of a ſoule ſully

healed (that is) ſanctified and glorified, both in a day; all other by degrees and leaſure. The ſteps of grace are ſoft &amp; ſhort. Thoſe external miracles hee wrought immediately by himſelfe; and therefore no maruell if they were abſolute like their Author. The miraculous worke of our regeneration he works together with vs; He giueth it efficacie: wee giue it imperfection.
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  SOME fewe of Dauids Pſalms Metaphraſed, for a taſte of the rest.
                  By J. H.
                  
                  AT LONDON, Printed by H. L. for Samuel Macham. 1607.
               
               
                  
                  
                  TO MY LOVING and learned Coſen, Mr SAMVEL BVRTON, Archdeacon of Gloceſter.
                  
                     INdeede, my Poetrie was long ſithence out of date, &amp; yielded hir place to grauer

ſtudies: but whoſe vaine would it not reuiue to looke into theſe heauenly ſongs? I were not woorthy to be a Diuine, if it ſhould repent me to be a Poet with DAVID, after I ſhall haue aged in the Pulpit: This worke is holy and ſtrict, &amp; abides not anie youthful or heatheniſh libertie; but requires hands

free from profaneneſſe, looſeneſſe, affectation. It is a ſeruice to God and the Church by ſo much more carefully to bee regarded, as it is more common. For, who is there that will not challenge a parte in this labour? and that ſhall not find himſelf much more affected with holy meaſures rightly compoſed▪
                     
Wherfore I haue oft wondered, howe it coulde be offenſiue to our aduerſaries, that theſe diuine ditties which the ſpirit of GOD wrote in verſe, ſhoulde bee ſung in verſe; and that an Hebrue Poeme ſhould be made Engliſh. For, if this kinde of compoſition had beene vnfit, God woulde neuer haue made choice of

numbers, wherin to expreſſe himſelfe▪ Yea, who knows not, that ſome other Scriptures, which the ſpirit hath indited in proſe, haue yet been happily &amp; with good allowance put into ſtrict numbers? If hiſtories tell vs of a wanton Poet of old, which loſt his eyes while he went about to turne MOSES into verſe; yet euerie

ſtudent knowes with what good ſucceſſe and commendatiō NONNVS hath turned IOHNS goſpell into Greek Heroicks; And APOLLINARIVS that learned Syrian, matched with BAZIL and GREGORY (who lived in his time) in the tearms of this equality, that BAZILS ſpeech was 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , but APOLLINARIES

                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , wrote, as SVIDAS reports, all the Hebrue ſcripture in heroicks, as Sozomen (ſomewhat more reſtrainedly) all the Archaiology of the Iewes, till SAVLS gouernment, in 24. parts; or as SOCRATES yet more particularly, all MOSES in Heroicks, and all the other hiſtories in diuerſe meeters: but

how euer his other labours lie hid, his Metaphraſe of the Pſalmes is ſtill in our hands with the applauſe of all the learned: beſides the labours of their owne FLAMINIVS &amp; ARIAS MONTANVS (to ſeeke for no more) which haue worthily beſtowed themſelues in this ſubiect. Neither doe I ſee how it

can bee offenſiue to our friends, that wee ſhoulde deſire our engliſh Metaphraſe bettered. I ſay nothing to the diſgrace of that wee haue: I know how glad our aduerſaries are of all ſuch aduantages; which they are ready enough to finde out without mee, euer reproachefully vpbrayding vs with theſe defectes. But

ſince our whol Tralation is now vniuerſally reuiſed; what inconuenience or ſhowe of innouation can it beare, that the verſe ſhould accompanie the proſe? eſpecially ſince it is well knowne howe rude &amp; homely our Engliſh Poëſy was in thoſe times, compared with the preſent; wherin, if euer, it ſeeth her full perfection.

I haue been ſolicited by ſom reuered friends to vndertake this taske; as that which ſeemed vvell to accord with the former exerciſes of my youth, and my preſent profeſſion. The difficulties I founde manie, the worke long &amp; great; yet not more painefull then beneficiall to Gods Church. Whereto as I dare

not profeſſe anie ſufficiencie; ſo will I not denie my readineſſe, and vtmoſt indeuour, if I ſhall bee imployed by Authoritie: wherfore, in this part, I doe humbly ſubmit my ſelfe to the graue cenſures of them, whoſe wiſedome menageth theſe cōmon affaires of the Church: and

am readie eyther to ſtand ſtil or proceed, as I ſhall ſee their Cloude or Fire goe before or behinde me. Onely (howſoeuer) I ſhall for my true affection to the Church, wiſhe it done by better workemen. Wherin as you approoue, ſo further my bolde but not vnprofitable motiō,

and commend it vnto greater cares: as I doe you to the greateſt.
                  
                     Non-ſuch

                           Iuly, 3.
                     
                     Your louing Kinſ-man, IOS. HALL.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Pſal. 1. In the tune of 148. Pſalmes; Giue laud vnto the Lord.
                  
                     
                        1 WHo hath not walkt aſtray,
                     In wicked mens adviſe,
                     Nor ſtood in ſinners way;
                     Nor in their companyes
                     That ſcorners are,
                     As their fit mate,
                     In ſcoffing chayre,
                     Hath euer ſate;
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        2 But in thy lawes diuine,
                     O Lord ſets his delight,
                     And in thoſe lawes of thine
                     Studies all day and night;
                     Oh, how that man
                     Thriſe bleſſed is!
                     And ſure ſhall gaine
                     Eternall bliſſe.
                  
                  
                     
                        3 He ſhall be like the tree,
                     Set by the water-ſprings,
                     Which when his ſeaſons be
                     Most pleaſant fruite forth-brings:
                     Whoſe boughes ſo greene
                     Shall neuer fade,
                     But couered bene
                     With comely ſhade.
                  
                  
                     
                     So, to this happy wight,
                     All his deſignes ſhall thriue:
                     
                        4 Whereas the man vnright,
                     As chaff which winds do driue,
                     With euery blaſt
                     Is tost on hy,
                     Nor can at laſt
                     In ſafety lie.
                  
                  
                     
                        5 Wherefore, in that ſad doome,
                     They dare not riſe from dust:
                     Nor ſhall no Sinner come
                     To glory of the iuſt.
                     For, God will grace
                     The Iuſt-mans way;
                     While ſinners race
                     Runs to decay.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 2. In the tune of the 125. Pſalme; Thoſe that do put their conf.
                  
                     WHy do the Gentils tumults make,
                     And nations all conſpire in vain,
                     And earthly Princes counſell take
                     Againſt their God; againſt the raigne
                     Of his deere Chriſt? let vs, they ſaine,
                     Break al their bonds: &amp; from vs ſhake
                     Their thraldoms yoke, &amp; ſeruile chain.
                     VVhiles thus alas they fondly ſpake,
                  
                  
                     
                     He that aloft rides on the skies,
                     Laughs all their leud deuiſe to ſco
                           •
                        
                     
                     
                        5 And when his wrathfull rage ſhal 
                           〈◊〉
                        ,
                     With plagues ſhal make the al forlorne,
                     And in his fury thus replyes;
                     
                        6 But I, my King with ſacred horne
                     Anointing, ſhall in princely guiſe
                     His head with royall crowne adorne.
                  
                  
                     
                        Ʋpon my Syons holy mount
                     His Empires glorious ſeat ſhall be.
                     And I thus raiſ'd ſhall farre recount
                     The tenour of his true decree:
                     
                        7 My Son thou art, ſaid God, I thee
                     Begat this daie by due account:
                     Thy ſcepter, do but ask of mee,
                     All earthly kingdomes ſhall ſurmount.
                  
                  
                     
                     All nations, to thy rightfull ſway,
                     will ſubiect; from furthest end
                     
                        9 Of all the world: and thou ſhalt bray
                     Thoſe ſtubborn foes that wil not bend,
                     With iron mace (like potters clay)
                     
                        10 In pieces ſmall: Ye Kings attend;
                     And ye, whom others wont obay,
                     Learne wiſedome, and at laſt amend.
                  
                  
                     
                        11 See, ye ſerue God, with greater dread
                     Then others you: and in your feare
                     Reioice the while; and (lowely ſpred)
                     
                        12 Do homage to his ſonne ſo deare:
                     Leaſt he be wroth, and do you dead
                     
                        13 Amids your way. If kindeled
                     His wrath ſhalbe; O bleſſed thoſe,
                     That do on him their trust repoſe.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 3. As the 113. Pſalme; Ye Children which, &amp;c.
                  
                     
                        1 AH Lord! how many be my foes!
                     How many are againſt me roſe,
                     
                        2 That to my grieued ſoule haue ſed,
                     Tuſh: God ſhall him no ſuccour yield;
                     
                        3 whiles thou Lord art my praiſe, my ſhield
                     And doſt aduance my carefull head.
                  
                  
                     
                        4 Loud with my voice to God I cri'd:
                     His grace vnto my ſute reply'd,
                     From out his Sions holy hill.
                     
                        
                        5 I layd me downe, ſlept, roſe againe.
                     For thou O Lord doſt me ſuſtaine,
                     And ſav'ſt my ſoule from feared ill.
                  
                  
                     
                        6 Not if ten thouſand armed foes
                     My naked ſide ſhould round encloſe,
                     Would I be thereof ought a-dred.
                     
                        Ʋp Lord and ſhield me from diſgrace:
                     
                        7 For thou haſt broke my foe-mens face,
                     And all the wickeds teeth haſt ſhed.
                  
                  
                     
                        8 From thee O God is ſafe defence;
                     Do thou thy free beneficence
                     Vpon thy people largely ſpred.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 4. As the x. Commandements; Attend my People.
                  
                     
                        1 THou witneſſe of my truth ſincere,
                     My God vnto my poore requeſt
                     
                        Ʋouch-ſaue to lend thy gracious eare:
                     Thou hast my ſoule from thral releast.
                  
                  
                     
                        2 Fauour me still, and daigne to heare
                     Mine humble ſute. O wretched wights,
                     
                        3 How long will yee mine honour deare
                     Turn into ſhame through your deſpites?
                  
                  
                     
                     Still will ye loue what thing is vaine,
                     
                        4 And ſeek falſe hopes? know thē at laſt,
                     That God hath choſe &amp; will maintain
                     His fauorite, whom ye diſgrac't.
                  
                  
                     God will regard mine inſtant mone.
                     
                        5 Oh! tremble then, and ceaſe offending;
                     And, on your ſilent bed alone,
                     Talk with your harts, your waies amending.
                  
                  
                     
                        6 Offer the trueſt ſacrifice
                     Of broken hearts; on God beſetting
                     
                        7 Your only truſt. The moſt deuiſe
                     The waies of worldly treaſure getting:
                  
                  
                     But thou, O Lord, lift vp to mee
                     The light of that ſweet lookes of thine;
                     
                        
                        8 So ſhall my ſoule more gladſome be,
                     Then theirs with al their corn &amp; wine.
                  
                  
                     
                        9 So I in peace ſhall lay me down,
                     And on my bed take quiet ſleep;
                     Whiles thou, O Lord, ſhalt me alone
                     From dangers all ſecurely keep.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 5. In the tune of 124. Pſalme; Now Iſrael may ſay, &amp;c.
                  
                     
                        1 BOw downe thine eare
                     Lord to theſe words of mine,
                     And well regarde
                     the ſecret plaints I make.
                     
                        2 My King, my God,
                     to thee I do betake
                     My ſad eſtate
                     oh do thine eare incline
                     To theſe loud cryes
                     that to thee powred bin.
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        3 At early morne
                     thou ſhalt my voyce attend:
                     For, at day breake,
                     I will my ſelfe addreſſe
                     Thee to implore,
                     and waite for due redreſſe.
                     
                        4 Thou doſt not Lord
                     delight in wickedneſſe;
                     Nor to bad men
                     wilt thy protection lend.
                  
                  
                     
                        5 The boaſters proud
                     cannot before thee ſtay:
                     Thou hat'ſt all thoſe
                     that are to ſinne deuoted:
                     
                        6 The lying lippes,
                     &amp; who with bloud are ſpotted,
                     Thou dooſt abhorre,
                     and wilt for euer ſlaie:
                     
                        
                        7 But I vnto
                     thine houſe ſhall take the way,
                  
                  
                     And through thy grace
                     aboundant ſhall adore,
                     With humble feare
                     within thine holy place.
                     
                        8 Oh! lead me Lord
                     within thy righteous trace:
                     Euen for their ſakes
                     that malice me ſo ſore,
                     Make ſmooth thy paths
                     my dimmer eyes before.
                  
                  
                     
                        9 Within their mouth
                     no truth is euer found:
                     Pure miſchiefe is
                     their heart: a gaping toome
                     
                        
                        10 Is their wide throate;
                     &amp; yet their tongues ſtil ſound
                     
                        11 With ſmoothing words.
                     O Lord giue them their doom,
                     And let them fall,
                     in thoſe their plots profound.
                  
                  
                     In their exceſſe
                     of miſchiefe them deſtroy
                     
                        12 That rebells are;
                     ſo thoſe that to thee flie
                     Shall all reioice
                     and ſing eternally:
                     
                        13 And whom thou doſt
                     protect, and who loue thee,
                     And thy deare name,
                     in thee ſhall euer ioy.
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        
                           •
                         Since thou with bliſſe
                     the righteous doſt reward,
                     And with thy grace
                     as with a ſhield him guard.
                  
               
               
                  Pſal. 6. As the 50. Pſalme; The mighty God, &amp;c.
                  
                     LEt mee not Lord
                     be in thy wrath reproued:
                     Oh! ſcourge mee not·
                     when thy fierce rage is moued.
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        2 Pity mee, Lord,
                     that do with languor pine:
                     Heale mee whoſe bones
                     with paine diſſolued bin;
                     
                        3 Whoſe weary ſoule
                     is vexed aboue meaſure.
                     Oh Lord how long
                     ſhall I'bide thy diſpleaſure!
                  
                  
                     
                        4 Turne thee O Lord,
                     reſcue my ſoule diſtreſt;
                     
                        5 And ſaue me, of thy grace.
                     Mongst thoſe that reſt,
                     In ſilent death
                     can none remember thee:
                     And in the graue
                     how ſhouldſt thou praiſed be?
                     
                        6 Weary with ſighs,
                     all night I cauſ'd my bed
                     
                        To ſwim: with teares
                     my couch I watered.
                  
                  
                     
                        7 Deepe ſorrow hath
                     conſum'd my dimmed eyne,
                     Sunk in with griefe
                     at theſe leud foes of mine:
                     
                        8 But now hence, hence,
                     vaine plotters of mine ill:
                     The Lord hath heard
                     my lamentations ſhrill;
                     
                        9 God heard my ſuit
                     and ſtill attends the ſame:
                     
                        10 Bluſh now, my foes,
                     and fly with ſudden ſhame.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 7. As the 112. Pſalme; The man is bleſt that God doth feare.
                  
                     
                        1 ON thee, O Lord my God, relyes
                     Mine only truſt: frō bloody ſpight
                     Of all my raging enemies
                     Oh! let thy mercy me acquite;
                     
                        2 Leaſt they like greedy Lyons rend
                     My ſoule, whiles none ſhal it defend▪
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        3 Oh Lord! if I this thing haue wrought,
                     If in my hands be found ſuch ill:
                     
                        
                        4 If I with miſchief euer ſought
                     To pay good turnes; or did not ſtill
                     Doe good vnto my cauſeleſſe foe,
                     That thirſted for my ouerthrowe;
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                         Then let my foe, in eager chace,
                     Ore take my ſoule, and proudly tread
                     My life belowe; and with diſ-grace
                     In duſt lay downe mine honor dead.
                     
                        6 Riſe vp in rage, O Lord, eft-ſoone
                     Aduance thine arm againſt my fo'ne:
                  
                  
                     And wake for me till thou fulfil
                     My promis'd right; ſo ſhal glad throngs
                     Of people flock vnto thine hill.
                     For their ſakes then reuenge my wrōgs,
                     And rouſe thy ſelf. Thy iudgements be
                     O're al the world: Lord iudge thou me;
                  
                  
                     
                     As truth and honest innocence
                     Thou find'ſt in me, Lord iudge thou 
                           〈◊〉
                        
                     
                     
                        9 Settle the iuſt with ſure defence:
                     Let me the wicked's malice ſee
                     
                        10 Brought to an end. For thy iuſt eye
                     Doth hearts and inward reyns deſcry
                  
                  
                     
                        11 My ſafety ſtands in God; who ſhields
                     The ſound in hart: whoſe doom each day
                     
                        12 To iust men and contemners yields
                     
                        13 Their due. Except he change his waie
                     His ſword is whet, to bloud intended,
                     His murdring bowe is ready bended.
                  
                  
                     
                        14 Weapons of death he hath addreſt
                     And arrowes keene to pearce my foe,
                     
                        15 Who late bred miſchiefe in his breſt;
                     But when he doth on trauell goe,
                     
                        
                        
                           
                              •
                           6 Brings forth a ly. Deep pits he delues,
                     And falls into his pits himſelue.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           7 Back to his own head ſhall rebound
                     His plotted miſchiefe; and his wrongs
                     
                        
                           
                              •
                           8 His crown ſhal craze: But I ſhal ſound
                     
                        Iehouah's praiſe with thankful ſongs,
                     And will his glorious name expreſſe,
                     And tell of all his righteouſneſſe.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 8. As the 113. Pſalme; Ye Children, &amp;c.
                  
                     
                        1 HOw noble is thy mighty name,
                     O Lord o're all the worlds wid
                           •
                         frame
                     Whoſe glory is aduanc't on hye
                     Aboue the rouling heauens rack!
                     
                        2 How for the graceleſſe ſcorners ſake,
                     To ſtill th'auenging enemy,
                     Haſt thou by tender infants tongue,
                     The praiſe of thy great name made ſtrōg,
                     While they hang ſucking on the breſt▪
                     
                     
                        3 But when I ſee thine heauens bright,
                     The Moon &amp; glittering ſtars of night▪
                     
                     By thine almighty hand addreſt;
                  
                  
                     
                     Oh! what is man, poore ſilly man,
                     That thou ſo mind'ſt him, &amp; doſt daine
                     To look at his vnworthy ſeed!
                     Thou haſt him ſet not much beneath
                     Thine Angels bright; &amp; with a wreath
                     Of glory haſt adorn'd his head.
                     Thou haſt him made hy ſouerayne
                     Of al thy works; &amp; ſtretcht his raigne
                     
                        Ʋnto the heards, and beaſts vntame,
                     To foules, and to the ſcaly traine,
                     That glideth through the watery main.
                     How noble each-where is thy name!
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 9.
                  To the tune of that knowen ſong, 
beginning; Preſerue vs Lord.
                  
                     
                        1 THee &amp; thy wondrous deeds, O God
                     With all my ſoule I ſound abroad
                     
                        2 My ioy, my triumph is in thee,
                     Of thy drad name my ſong ſhal be,
                  
                  
                     
                        3 O higheſt God: ſince put to flight,
                     And fall'n and vaniſht at thy ſight,
                     
                        4 Are all my foes; for thou haſt paſt
                     Iust ſentence on my cauſe at laſt:
                  
                  
                     
                     And ſitting on thy throne aboue,
                     A rightful Iudge thy ſelfe do'ſt proue:
                     The troupes profane thy checkes haue ſtroid
                     And made their name for euer void.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                         Where's now, my foes, your threatned wrack?
                     So well you did our citties ſack,
                     And bring to duſt; whiles that ye ſay,
                     Their name ſhall dy as well as they.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                         Lo, in eternall ſtate God ſits,
                     And his by throne to iuſtice fits:
                     Whoſe righteous hand the world ſhall weeld
                     And to al folk iust doom ſhal yeeld.
                  
                  
                     The poore from hy find his reliefe,
                     The poore in needfull times of griefe:
                     
                        
                        10 Who knowes thee Lord, to thee ſhall cleaue,
                     That neuer do'ſt thy cliēts leaue.
                  
                  
                     
                        11 Oh! ſing the God that doth abide,
                     On Sion mount; and blazon wide
                     
                        12 His worthy deeds. For, he purſues
                     The guiltleſſe bloud with vengeance due:
                  
                  
                     He minds their caſe; nor can paſſe o're
                     Sad clamours of the wronged poore.
                     
                        13 Oh! mercy Lord; thou that do'ſt ſaue
                     My ſoule from gates of death &amp; graue:
                  
                  
                     Oh! ſee the wrong my foes haue done;
                     
                        14 That I thy praiſe, to all that gone,
                     Through daughter Sions beautious gate
                     With thankfull ſongs may loud relate▪
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     And may reioice in thy ſafe ayd.
                     Behold: the Gentiles, whiles they made
                     A deadly pit my ſoule to drowne,
                     Into their pit are ſunken downe;
                  
                  
                     In that cloſe ſnare they hid for mee,
                     Lo their owne feet entangled bee.
                     
                        16 By this iuſt doom the Lord is known,
                     That th'ill are puniſht with their own.
                  
                  
                     
                        17 Down ſhall the wicked backward fall
                     To deepeſt hell, and nations all
                     
                        18 That God forget; nor ſhall the poore
                     Forgotten be for euermore.
                  
                  
                     The conſtant hope of ſoules oppreſt
                     
                        19 Shall not ay dy. Riſe from thy rest,
                     
                        Oh Lord, let not men baſe and rude
                     Preuaile: iudge thou the multitude
                  
                  
                     
                        20 Of Laweleſſe pagans: ſtrike pale fear
                     Into thoſe breaſts late ſtubborn were:
                     And let the Gentiles feele and find,
                     They been but men of mortall kind.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Pſal. 9. As the 51. Pſalme; O Lord conſider
                  
                     
                        1 WHy ſtād'ſt thou Lord aloof ſo lōg
                     &amp; hid'ſt thee in due times of need
                     
                        2 Whiles leud men proudly offer wrong
                     Vnto the poore? In their owne deed,
                     And their deuiſe let them be caught.
                     
                        3 For lo, the wicked braues and boaſts
                     In his vile and outragious thought,
                     And bleſſeth him that rauins moſt.
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        4 On God he dares inſult: his pride
                     Scornes to inquire of powers aboue,
                     But his ſtout thoughts haue ſtil deni'd
                     
                        5 Ther is a God; His waies yet proue
                     Aye proſperous: thy iudgements hye
                     Doe farre ſurmount his dimmer ſight.
                     
                        6 Therfore doth he all foes defie:
                     His heart ſaith; I ſhal ſtand in ſpight,
                  
                  
                     Nor euer moue; nor danger 'bide.
                     
                        7 His mouth is fill'd with curſes foule,
                     And with cloſe fraud: His tongue doth hide
                     
                        8 Miſchief &amp; il: he ſeeks the ſoule
                     Of harmleſſe men in ſecret wait,
                     And in the corners of the ſtreet,
                     Doth ſhed their blood; with ſcorne and hate
                     His eyes vpon the poore are ſet.
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        9 As ſome fell Lyon in his den,
                     He cloſely lurkes the poore to ſpoile,
                     He ſpoiles the poore and helpleſſe men,
                     When once he ſnares them in his toile.
                     
                        10 He croucheth lowe in cunning wile,
                     And bows his breſt; wheron whol thrōgs
                     Of poor, whom his fair ſhowes beguile,
                     Fall to be ſubiect to his wrongs.
                  
                  
                     
                        11 God hath forgot, (in ſoule he ſayes)
                     He hides his face to neuer ſee.
                     
                        12 Lord God ariſe; thine hand vp-raiſe:
                     Let not thy poore forgotten be.
                     
                        13 Shal theſe inſulting wretches ſcorne
                     Their God; and ſay thou wilt not care?
                     
                        14 Thou ſee'ſt, (for all thou haſt forborn)
                     Thou ſee'ſt what al their miſchiefs are;
                  
                  
                     
                     That to thine hand of vengeance iuſt
                     Thou maiſt thē take: the poor diſtreſſed
                     Rely on thee with conſtant trust,
                     The help of Orphans and oppreſſed.
                     
                        15 Oh! break the wickeds arme of might,
                     And ſearch out al their curſed trains,
                     And let them vaniſh out of ſight.
                     
                        16 The Lord as King for euer raignes.
                  
                  
                     From forth his coaſts, the heathen ſect
                     
                        17 Are rooted quite: thou Lord attēdeſt
                     To poore mens ſuites; thou doo'ſt direct
                     Their harts: to thē thine eare thou bēdeſt;
                     
                        18 That thou maiſt reſcue, frō deſpight,
                     The wofull fatherleſſe, and poore:
                     That, ſo, the vaine and earthen wight
                     On vs may tyrannize no more.
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

