
   
      
         
            Quo vadis? A iust censure of travell as it is commonly vndertaken by the gentlemen of our nation. By Ios. Hall D. of Diuinitie.
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1617
            
         
         Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02578
            STC 12705
            ESTC S119019
            99854226
            99854226
            19635
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02578)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19635)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1070:02)
         
         
            
               
                  Quo vadis? A iust censure of travell as it is commonly vndertaken by the gentlemen of our nation. By Ios. Hall D. of Diuinitie.
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [10], 100 p.   
               
                  Printed by Edward Griffin for Nathaniel Butter,
                  London :
                  1617.
               
               
                  In this edition there are 100 numbered pages.
                  A variant of STC 12705a, an edition with H. Fetherstone's name in the imprint.
                  Imperfect; tightly bound affecting text.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Travel --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Quo vadis?
            A IVST CENSVRE of TRAVELL as it is commonly vndertaken by the GENTLEMEN of our Nation.
            By IOS. HALL D. of Diuinitie.
            LONDON, Printed by EDWARD GRIFFIN for Nathaniel Butter. 1617.
         
         
            
            
            
               TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, my ſingular good Lord, EDWARD Lord DENNY, Baron of WALTHAM.
            
            Right Honorable,
            
               I Feuer any men had reaſon to bee in loue with the face of a forraine entertainment, thoſe are they, which

were admitted to the attendance of the truly Generous and Honorable, Lord HAY, your moſt noble ſonne, in his late embaſſage to France; in which number my vnworthineſſe was allowed to make o
                  •
               e; who ca
                  •
                therefore well witneſſe, that no man could either recei
                  •
               e more honour from a ſtrange Countrey, or doe more honour to his owne. What wanted there that might make men confeſſe themſelues more welcome then ſtrangers? Neither doubt I but that after many ages, France it ſelfe will wonder at the bountifull expreſs
                  •
               
               ons of her own
                  •
                fauours. But whiles others were 
                  •
               nioying the noble courteſies of the Time, my

thoughts entertained themſelues with ſearching into the proofe of that ordinary Trauell, wherewith I ſaw men comm
                  •
               nly affected; which, I muſt needs confeſſe, the more I ſaw, the leſſe I liked. Neither is it in the power of any forraine munificence, to make mee thinke ours any where ſo well
                  •
                as at home. Earthly commodities are no part of my thought: I looked (as I ought) at the ſoule; which I 
                  •
               ell ſaw, vſes not only to gather 
                  〈◊〉
                moſſe in this rolling, but ſuffers the beſt graces it bath, 
                  •
               o molder away inſenſibly in ſuch vnneceſſary agitation. I haue now beene twiſe abroad: both times (as thinking my ſelfe worthy of nothing

but neglect) I bent my eyes vpon others, to ſee what they did, what they got: my inquirie found our ſpirituall loſſe ſo palpable, that now at laſt my heart could not chuſe but breake forth at my hand, and tell my Countrymen of the dangerous iſſue of their curioſitie. I meddle not with the common iourneyes to the miner all waters of the Spa; to which many ſicke ſoules are beholden for a good excuſe: who whiles they pretend the medicinall vſe of that ſpring, can freely quaffe of the puddle of popiſh ſuperſtition; poiſoning the better part, in ſtead of helping the worſe. Theſe I leaue to the best Phyſician, Authoritie; which if it

may pleaſe to vndertake the cure, may perhaps ſaue as many Engliſh ſoules from infection, as that water cures bodies of diſeaſes. I deale only with thoſe, that profeſſe to ſeeke the glory of a perfect breeding, and the perfection of that, which we call Ciuilitie, in Trauell: of which ſort I haue (not without indignation) ſeene too many loſe their hopes, and themſelues in the way; returning as empty of grace, and other vertues, as full of words, vanitie, miſ-diſpoſitions. I dedicate this poore diſcourſe to your Lo: as (beſides my daily renued obligations) congratulating to you the ſweet libertie and happy vſe of your home; who like a fixed ſtarre

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
may well ouer-looke theſe planets, and by your conſtant ſettledneſſe, giue that aime to inferiour eies, which ſhall be in vaine expected from a wandring light. The God of beauen, to whoſe glorie I haue intended this weake labour, giue it fauor in the 
                  •
               ight of his Church, and returne it backe; but with this good newes that any one of the ſon
                  •
                of Iaphet, is hereby perſwaded to dwell euer in the tents of Sem: Vnto that diuine protection, I humbly betake your Lo: Iuſtly vowing my ſelfe
            
               Your Lo: humbly deuoted in a
                     •
                  l faithfull and Chriſtian obſeruance,
IOS. HALL.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            QVO VADIS?
            
               
                  Sect. 1.
               
                  IT is an ouer-rigorous conſtruction of the workes of God, that in moting our ILAND with the Ocean he ment to ſhut vs vp from other regions; For God himſelfe that made the Sea, was the Author of Nauigation, and hath therein taught vs to ſet vp a wooden bridge, that may reach to the very Antipodes themſelues: This were to ſeeke diſcontentment in the bounty of God, who hath placed vs apart, for the ſingularity of our

happineſſe, not for reſtraint.
               There are two occaſions wherein Trauell may paſſe, Matter of trafique, and Matter of State. Some commodities GOD hath confined to ſome countries, vpon others hee hath with a full hand powred thoſe benefits, which hee hath but ſprinkled vpon ſome. His wiſe prouidence hath made one Countrey the Granary, another the Celler, another the Orchard, another the Arſenall of their neighbours, yea of the remoteſt parts. The earth is the Lords which he meant not to keepe in his hands, but to giue; and hee which hath giuen no man his faculties and graces for himſelfe, nor put light into the Sun, Moone, Stars for their owne vſe, hath ſtored no parcell of earth with a purpoſe of priuate reſeruation. Salomon would neuer haue ſent his nauie

for Apes and Peacockes, but yet held gold and timber for the building of Gods houſe, and his own, worthy of a whole three yeares voyage: The ſea and earth are the great Cofers of God; the diſcoueries of Nauigation are the keyes, which whoſoeuer hath receiued, may know that he is freely allowed to vnlocke theſe cheſts of nature, without any neede to picke the wards: Wiſe Salomons compariſon is reciprocall. A ſhip of Merchants that fetches her wares from farre is the good Huſ-wife of the Common-wealth, and if ſhe were ſo in thoſe blind voyages of antiquity, which neuer ſaw needle nor card, how much more thrifty muſt ſhee needes be in ſo many helpes both of nature and Art? Either Indies may be ſearched for thoſe treaſures, which God hath laid vp in them for their fardiſtant

owners; Onely let our Merchants take heed, leaſt they go ſo farre, that they leaue God behinde them; that whiles they buy all other things good cheape, they make not an ill match for their ſoules, leaſt they end their proſperous aduentures in the ſhipwracke of a good conſcience.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 2.
               And for matter of policy, nothing can be more plaine then that our correſpondence with other nations cannot poſſibly be held vp, without intelligence of their eſtate, of their proceedings; The neglect whereof were no other then to proſtrate our ſelues to the mercie of an hollow friendſhip, and to ſtand ſtill, and willingly lie open whiles wee are plaide vpon by the wit of vntruſty neighbourhood. Th
                     •
                  ſe eyes and eares of State are neceſſarie to the well-being of the head; In which number I doe not

include thoſe priuate Inter-lopers of intelligence, that lie abroad only to feed ſome vaine Cameleons at home with the aire of Newes, for no other purpoſe, ſaue idle diſcourſe; but only thoſe profitable agents, whoſe induſtrie either fitteth them abroad for publike imployment, or imployeth them after due maturitie, in the fit ſeruices of the Common-wealth: Neither my cenſure nor my direction reaches to either of theſe occaſions. It is the Trauell of curioſity wherwith my quarrell ſhall bee maintained; the inconueniences whereof my owne Senſes haue ſo ſufficiently witneſſed, that if the wiſe parents of our Gentry could haue borrowed mine eyes for the time, they wou
                     •
                  d euer learne to keepe their ſonnes at home, and not wil
                  
                     •
                  ully beate themſelues with the 
                     •
                  taffe of their age: vpon them let

my pen turne a little, as thoſe that are more then acceſſaries to this both priuate and publike miſchiefe.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 3.
               It is the affectation of too-early ripeneſſe that makes them prodgall of their childrens ſafety an
                     •
                   hopes; for, that they may be wi
                     ••
                   betimes, they ſend them foo
                     ••
                   to the world in the minority bo
                     •
                   of age and iudgement, like as fon
                     •
                   Mothers vſe to ſend forth the
                     •
                   daughters on froſting, early in col
                     •
                   mornings (though into the mi
                     •
                   of a vaporous and foggy ayre) an
                     •
                   whiles they ſtriue for a colo
                     •
                   looſe their health; If they were n
                     •
                   blinded with ouer-weening a
                     •
                   deſire, they could not but ſee 
                     〈◊〉
                   their vnſetledneſſe carries in it manifeſt perill of mi
                     •
                  -carriag
                     •
                   grant that no danger were thre
                     •
                  
                  ned by the place, experience gi
                     •
                   vs, that a weake-limde childe if 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  
be ſuffered to vſe his legges too ſoone, too mu
                     •
                  h, lames himſelfe for euer; bu
                     •
                   if hee wa
                     •
                  ke in vneuen ground, he is no le
                     •
                  ſe ſubiect to maimes, then crookedneſſe. Do they not ſee how eaſily a young twig is bowed any way
                     •
                   Do they not ſee that the Mid-wi
                     ••
                   and the Nurſe are wont to frame the griſtly head of the Infant to any fa
                  
                     •
                  hion? May not any thing be written vpon a blanke? And if they make choice of this age, becauſe it is moſt docible, and for that they would take the day before them, why doe they not conſider that it 
                     •
                  s therefore more docible of e
                     •
                  ill; 
                     •
                  ince wickedneſſe is both more 
                     〈◊〉
                   and more plauſible then 
                     •
                  ertue, eſpecially when it meetes with an vntutored iudge; and 
                     •
                  inc
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  here is ſo much inequality of 
                     •
                  he 
                     •
                  umber of both, that it is not 
                     •
                  ore hard to finde vertue, then to

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
miſſe vice. Heare this then, yee careleſſe Oſtriches, that leaue your egges in the open ſand for the Sun to hatch, without the feare of any hoo
                     •
                  e that may cruſh them in peec
                     •
                  s, haue your ſtomackes reſolued to digeſt the hard newes of the ruine of your children? Doe ye profeſſe anmity to your owne loynes? then turne them (as ye doe) looſe to theſe dangers, ere they c
                     •
                  n reſiſt, ere they can diſcerne; but if ye had rather they ſhould liue and grow, beſtow vpon them the kindly heat of your be
                     •
                  t plumes, and ſhelter them with your owne breſt and wings, till nature haue opened a ſeaſonable way to their owne abilities.
            
            
               
                  Se
                        ••
                     . 4.
               Yea let it be my iuſt complaint in this place, that in the very tranſplantation of our ſonnes to the ſa
                     •
                  er ſoile of our owne Vniuerſities, and Innes of Court, nothing

is more preiudiciall then ſpeede. Perfection is the childe of Time; neither was there euer any thing excellent, that required not meet leiſure: but beſides, how commonly is it ſeene, that thoſe which had wont to ſwimme onely with bladders, ſinke when they come firſt to truſt their owne armes? Theſe Lap-wings that goe from vnder the wing of their damme with their ſhell on their heads, run wilde. If Tutors be neuer ſo carefull of their early charge, much muſt be left to their owne diſpoſition; which if it leade them not to good, not only the hopes of their youth, but the proofe of their age lies bleeding. It is true, that as the French Lawyers ſay merily of the Normans, which by a ſpeciall priuiledge are reputed of full age at 21. yeeres, whereas the other French ſtay for their fiue and

twentieth, that Malitia ſupplet aetatem; ſo may I ſay of the younglings of our time, that Precocitie of vnderſtanding ſupplieth age and ſtature: but as it is commonly ſeene, that thoſe bloſſomes which ouer-runne the ſpring, and will be looking forth vpon a FebruarySunne, are nipped ſoone after with an Aprill-froſt, when they ſhould come to the knitting: ſo is it no leſſe ordinary that theſe rathe-ripe wits preuent their owne perfection, and after a vaine wonder of their haſte, end either in ſhame, or obſcuritie. And as it thus falles out euen in our Vniuerſities (the moſt abſolute and famous Seminaries of the world) where the Tutors eye ſupplies the parents; ſo muſt it needs much more, in th
                     •
                  ſe free and honourable Innes (as they are called, for their libertie, Colledges for their vſe) of our

Engliſh Gentry, wherein each one is his owne maſter in reſpect of his priuate ſtudie and gouernment: where there are many pots boiling, there cannot but bee much ſcumme. The concourſe of a populous citie affords many brokers of villanie, which liue vpon the ſpoiles of young hopes, whoſe very acquaintance is deſtruction. How can theſe nouices, that are turned looſe into the maine, ere they know either coaſt, or compaſſe, auoid theſe rockes and ſhelues, vpon which both their eſtates and ſoules are miſerably wracked? How commonly doe they learne to roare in ſtead of pleading, and in ſtead of knowing the lawes, learne how to conternne them? We ſee, and rue this miſchiefe, and yet I know not how careleſſe we are in preuenting it.
               How much more deſperate

muſt it then needs be to ſend forth our children into thoſe places which are profeſſedly infectious, whoſe very goodneſſe is either impietie, or ſuperſtition? If wee deſired to haue ſonnes poiſoned with miſ-be
                     •
                  eefe, what could wee doe otherwiſe? Or what elſe doe thoſe parents, which haue bequeathed their children to Antichriſtianiſme? Our late iourney into France informed me of ſome ordinary factors of Rome, whoſe trade is the tranſporting and placing of our popiſh nouices beyond the ſeas; one whereof (whoſe name I noted) hath beene obſerued to carry ouer ſixe ſeuerall charges in one ye
                     •
                  re. Are wee ſo fooliſh to goe their way, whiles wee intend a contrary period? Doe wee ſend our ſonnes to learne to be chaſte in the midſt of Sodome? The world is wide and open; but our ordinary

trauell is ſouthward, into the iawes of danger: for ſo farre hath Satans policie preuailed, that thoſe parts which are only thought worth our viewing, are moſt contagious; and will not part with either pleaſure, or information, without ſome tang of wickedneſſe. What can wee pleade for our confidence, but that there is an houſhold of righteous Lot in the midſt of that impure citie; that there are houſes in this lericho, which haue ſcarlet threeds ſhining in their windowes; that in the moſt corrupted aire of Poperie, ſome well reformed Chriſtians draw their breath, and ſweeten it with their reſpiration. Bleſſed bee God, that hath reared vp the towers of his Sion, in the midſt of Babylon. Wee muſt acknowledge, not without much gratulation to the Goſpell of Chriſt, that in the very hotteſt climates of oppoſition,

it findes many clients, but more friends; and in thoſe places, where author
                     •
                  tie hath plea
                     •
                  ed to giue more aire to the truth, would haue had many more, if the Retormed part had happily continued that correſpond
                     •
                  nce in ſome circumſtances wi
                     •
                  h the Romane Church, which the Church of Englan
                        •
                     
                   hath hitherto maintained. God is my record how 
                     •
                  r
                     •
                  e my heart is both from pa
                     •••
                  alitic, and pr
                     •
                  iudi
                     •
                  e. Mine eyes and eares can witneſſe with wha
                     •
                   approo
                     •
                  e and applauſe diuer
                     •
                   of the Catholiques Royall (as they are termed) entertained the new-tran
                     •
                  lated Liturgie o
                     •
                   our Church, as maruelling to ſee ſuch order and regular deuotion in them, whom they were taught to condemne for hereticall. Whoſe allowances I w
                     •
                  ll ſaw, might with a little helpe, haue beene raiſed higher, from the practiſe

of our Church, to ſome points of our iudgement. But if true religion were in thoſe parts yet better attended, and our young Traueller could finde mo
                     •
                  e abettors, and examples of pie
                     •
                  ie, on whom wee might relie, yet how ſafe can it bee to truſt young eyes with the view and cenſure of truth or 
                     •
                  alſhood in religion? eſpecially when truth brings nothing to this barre, but extreme ſimplicitie, and contrarily, 
                     •
                  alſhood, a gaw dy magnificence, and proud maieſtie of pompous ceremonies, wherewith the hearts of children and fooles are eaſily taken. That Curtizan of Rome (according to the mann
                     •
                  r of that profeſſion) ſets out her ſelfe to ſale in the moſt tempting faſhion; here want no colours, no per
                  
                     •
                  umes, no wanton dre
                     •
                  ſes; whereas the poore Spouſe of Chriſt can on
                     •
                  y ſay of her ſelfe, I am blacke,
                  
                  but comely. When on the one ſide they ſhall ſee ſuch rich ſhrines, gariſh Altars, ſtately Proceſſions, when they ſhall ſee a Pope adored of Emperours, Cardinals preferd to Kings, confeſſors made Saints, little children made Angels, in a word nothing not outwardly glorious: on the other ſide, a ſeruice without welt or guard, whoſe maieſtie is all in the heart, none in the face, how eaſily may they incline to the conceit of that Pariſian dame, who ſeeing the proceſſion of S. Genoueifue goe by the ſtreets, could ſay, (O que belle, &amp;c.) How fine a religion is ours in compariſon of the Hugenots? Whereto muſt bee added, that (ſuppoſing they doe not carry with them, but rather goe to fetch the language of the place) ſome long time needs be ſpent, ere they can receiue any helpe to their deuotion; whiles in

the meane ſeaſon, their vnthriuing intermi
                     ••
                  ion is aſſailed with a thouſand ſuggeſtions: And who ſees not that this lucrum ceſſans (as the Ciuil
                     •
                  ans terme it) offers an open aduantage to a bu
                     ••
                  e aduerſarie?
            
            
               
                  Sect. 6.
               In a word, it hath beene the old praiſe of early riſing, that it makes a man healthfull, holy, and rich; whereof the firſt reſpects the body, the ſecond the ſoule, the third the eſtate: all fals out contrary in an early trauell. For health: The wiſe prouidence of God hath ſo contriued his earth, and vs, that he ha
                     •
                  h fitted our bodies to our clime, and the natiue ſuſtenance of the place vnto our bodies. The apparant difference of diet (and of drinkes eſpecially) falling into ſo tender age, muſt needs cauſe a iarre in the conſtitution; which cannot in all likelihood, but ſend forth diſtemper into the whole

courſe of the enſuing life. The ſtreame runnes like the fountaine, and ſpeeds well, if at laſt, by many changes of ſoile it can leaue an ill qualitie behinde it: beſides that the miſ-gouernance of diet, whereto their libertie layes them open in the weakneſſe of their pupillage, cannot but bee extremely preiudiciall. In this point let experience be conſulted with; her vnpartiall ſentence ſhall eaſily tell vs, how few young trauellers haue brought home, ſound and ſtrong, and (in a word) Engliſh bodies. As for holineſſe, we loſe our labour, if this diſcourſe proue not that it hath none ſo great enemie as timely trauell; at once doe wee hazard to abandon God and our home: ſet an empty pitcher to the fire, it crackes preſently, whereas the full will abide boiling. It was the younger ſonne in the Goſpell, who

therefore turnes vnthrift, becauſe he got his portion too ſoone into his hands, and wandred into a farre countrey. The eye of the parent, and the ferule of the maſter, is all too little to bring our ſonnes to good. Where then there is neither reſtraint of euill, nor helps to grace, how ſhould their condition bee other than hopeleſſe? The ſoile doth much in many plants: the Perſian Hyoſ
                        •
                     yamus if it be tranſlated to Egypt, proues deadly; if to Ieruſalem, ſafe and wholeſome: neither is it otherwiſe with ſome diſpoſitions, which may iuſtly curſe the place, as acceſſory to their vndoing. Laſtly, for riches, not of the purſe, (which is not here thought of) but of the mind, what can bee expected from that age, which is not capable of obſeruation, carele
                     ••
                  e of repoſition? whereof the one gets, the other keepes

the treaſure of our vnderſtanding. What is this age fit to looke after but Butterflies, or birds neſts, or perhaps the gay coat of a Courtier? And if remarkable conſiderations be put into it by others, they are as ſome looſe pearles, which for want of filing vpon a ſtring, ſhake out of our pockets; ſo as all the wealth of a young Traueller is only in his tongue, wherein he exceeds his mothers Parrat at home, both for that hee can ſpeake more, and knowes that he ſpeaketh.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 7.
               And in truth, it is not onely in trauell, wherein wee may iuſtly complaine of the inconuenience of haſte, but (that wee may looke
                     •
                   a little aſide) in all the important buſineſſes of our life; eſpecially in marriages and profeſſions; The ordinary haſte in the one (before the face can deſcry the ſex) fils the world full of beggerie and impotence;

and no leſſe haſte in the other, fils it as full of ignorance and imperfection. For on the one ſide, where the vigour of nature wants, what can be propagated but infirmity, or how can hee skill to liue that wants experience? On the other, what plenty of water can there be, where the leade of the ciſterne is put all into the pipes? Where thoſe that ſhould be gathering knowledge for themſelues, ſpend it (like vnthrifty heires) vpon others, as faſt as they get it. I am deceiued, if I haue not touched one of the maine grounds of that vniuerſall decay of Arts and Men, wherewith the world is commonly checked: They muſt bee mightier and wiſer, that know to redreſſe it.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 8.
               But let vs giue our Traueller (that which Parents ſeldome care to giue) maturity of age; let him be as ripe as time can make him;

what is the beſt aduantage which his abſence can promiſe vs: Let vs lay the benefits of Trauell in the one ſca
                     •
                  e, the inconueniences on the other, whetherſoeuer ouerwaighes, ſhall ſway downe the beame of our iudgement. The priuate contentment of a mans owne heart in the view o
                     •
                   forraine things, is but a better name of an humorous curio
                     •
                  ity. If a man yeelde to runne after his appetite and his eye, he ſhall neuer know where to re
                     •
                  t, and after many idle excurſions, 
                     •
                  hal lie downe weary, but vnſa
                     •
                  is
                     •
                  ied. For, giue me a man that hath ſeene 
                     
                        •
                     udaſſes Lanterne at S. Denniſes, the Ephe
                     •
                  ian 
                     
                        •
                     iana in the Louure, the great veſſell at Heydelberg, the Amphitheater at 
                     
                        •
                     iſmes, the ruines and halfe-lettred monuments of the ſeuen hilles, and a thouſand ſuch rarities; what peace hath his heart aboue thoſe, that ſit at home,

and contemne theſe toyes? And what if that mans fancie ſhall call him to the ſtables of the great Mogol, or to the ſolemnities of Mecha, or to the Librarie of the Moun
                  
                     •
                  aine of the Moone, will hee be ſo farre the drudge or Lacquay of his owne imagination, as to vndertake 
                     •
                  his pilgrimage? Or where will he ſtay at laſt, vpon his returne? If he haue ſmelt the ill-ſented Cities of France, or haue ſeene faire Florence, rich Venice, proud Genua, Luca the induſtrious: if then his thoughts ſhall tempt him to ſee the rich gluttons houſe in Ieruſalem, or inuite him to Aſmere, or Bengala, muſt he goe? And if hee can denie and chide his owne vnprofitable deſires at the laſt, why began hee no ſooner? That could not be forborne too early, which at laſt we
                     •
                   repent to haue done: he therefore that trauels onely to pleaſe his fantaſie,

is like ſome woman with childe, that longs for that peece which ſhe ſees vpon anothers trencher, and ſwounds if ſhe miſſ
                     •
                   it; or ſome ſquire of Dames, tha
                     •
                   doats vpon euery beautie, and is euery day loue-ſicke anew: Theſe humours are fitter for controlment, than obſeruation.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 9.
               It is an higher facultie that Trauell profeſſeth to aduance, the ſupreme power of our vnderſtanding, which if from hence it may be manifeſtly improued, he ſhould not bee worthy to tread vpon the earth, that would not emulate Drake, and Candiſh, in compaſſing it: but (ſet aſide the ſtudie of Ciuill Law, which indeed findes bett
                     •
                  r helpes abroad) all ſciences (the word may ſeeme proud, but is true) may be both more fitly wooed, and more ſurely wonne within our foure ſeas: for what learning

is that, which the Seas, or Alpes, or Pyrenees haue ingroſſed from vs? what profeſſion either liberall, or manuary, wherein the greateſt maſters haue not beene at leaſt equalled by our hom
                     •
                  -bred Ilanders? what hath this, or the former age knowne more eminent for learning, then ſome of ours, whi
                     •
                  h haue neuer trod on any but th
                     •
                  ir owne earth? And (as good market-men by one handfull iudge of
                     •
                   all the whole ſacke) why may we
                     •
                   not finde cauſe to thinke ſo of the reſt, if they would not be wanting to themſelues? I am ſure the Vni uerſities of our Iland know no matches in all the world; vnto whoſe per
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  tion (that as they exceed others, ſo they may no leſſe exceed themſelues) nothing wanteth, but ſeuere execution of the wiſe and carefull lawes of our Anceſtors, and reſtraint o
                     •
                   that libertie,

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
which is the common diſeaſe of the time. And why ſhould not the childe thriue as well with the mothers milke, as with a ſtrangers? Whether it be the enuie, or the puſillanimitie of vs Engliſh, wee are ſtill ready to vnder-value our owne, and admire forrainers; whiles other nations haue applauded no profeſſors more then thoſe which they haue borrowed from vs; neither haue wee beene ſo vnwiſe, as to lend forth our beſt: our neighbours (which ſhould be our corriuals in this praiſe) ſhall be our Iudges, if thoſe f
                     •
                  w of our writers, which could be drawne forth into the publike light, haue not ſet copies to the reſt of the world, not without iuſt admiration. And how many ſtarres haue wee of no leſſe magnitude, that will not be ſeene? Bleſſed be God (who hath made this word as true, as it is great) no

nation vnder heauen ſo aboundeth with all varietie of learning, as this Iland. From the head of Gods anointed doth this ſweet perfume diſtill to the vtmoſt skirts of this our region. Knowledge did neuer ſit crowned in the throne of maieſtie, and wanted either reſpect, or attendance. The double praiſe which was of old giuen to two great nations, That Italie could not be put down for armes, nor Greece for learning, is happily met in one Iland. Thoſe therefore that croſſe the ſeas to fill their braine, doe but trauell Northward for heat, and ſeeke that candle which they carry in their hand.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 10.
               Yea ſo farre is our ordinary Trauell from perfecting the intellectiue powers of our Gentry, that it rather robs them of the very deſire of perfection. For what diſcouragements ſhall they finde

from the loue of ſtudies, in thoſe parts which are moſt ſough
                     •
                   to for ciuilitie? Who k
                     •
                  ow
                     ••
                   not that they are growne to that height of debauch
                     •
                  ment, as to hold learning a ſhame to Nobilitie; eſteeming it as a fit gard for the l
                     •
                  ng robe only, too baſe for their Tiſſ
                     •
                  es? An opinion ſo ſauouring of proud ignorance, and ignorant looſeneſſ
                     •
                  , tha
                     •
                   I cannot honour it with a confutation. Who would thinke that the reaſonable ſoule of men, not profeſſedly barbarous, ſhould bee capable of ſuch a monſter? What is learning, but reaſon improued? And can reaſon ſo farre degenerate, as to hate and contemne it ſelfe? Were theſe men made onely for a ſword, or a dogge, or an horſe? Onely for ſport, or execution? I know not wherein Lewi
                        •
                     
                   the eleuenth ſhewed himſelfe vnwitty, but in the charge which hee

gaue to his ſonne, to learne no more Latine, but, Qui neſcit diſsimulare, neſcit viuere: and would this alone teach him to rule well? Doth the Art of Arts (ſuch is the gouernment of men) require no grounds but diſſimulation, or ignorance? Euen to the feeding of hogges, or ſheepe, there is more and better skill neceſſary. How v
                     •
                  like is this to a ſucceſſor of Charles the great, whoſe word it had wont to be, that he had rather abound in knowledge, then wealth? In the Court of our King Henry the eight, a certaine great Peere (of this diet) could ſay, it was enough for Noblemens ſonnes to winde their horne, and carry their Hauke faire; that ſtudie was for the children of a meaner ranke: To whom Pace iuſtly replied, that then Noblemen muſt bee content that their children many winde

their hornes, and carry their Haukes, while meaner mens ſons doe weild the affaires of State. Certainly it is a blinde and lame gouernment that lackes learning; whoſe ſubiects, what are they elſe, but as limmes of a body whoſe head wanteth ſenſes, which muſt needs therefore faile of either motion, or ſafetie? From hence it is, that ſo few of the forraine Nobleſſe are ſtudious, in compariſon of ours; (in which regard I am not aſhamed to recant that which my vnexperience hath (out of heareſay) written in praiſe of the Frenc
                     •
                   education) and thoſe few that haue ſtolne the turning ouer of bookes, hide their skill, left they ſhould be made to bluſh at their vertue. What braue Trophees and rich monuments hath the pen of our gracious Soueraigne raiſed of himſelfe vnto all poſterities? When

ignorance and malice haue ſhot their bolt, the glory of his great wiſdome, and knowledge, ſhall more fill the mouthes and affect the hearts of all ſucceeding ages, then of his greatneſſe. Paul the fift, and his greateſt Chaplaines, Bellarmine and Perron, haue felt the weight of his hand; whereas the great King that ſtiles himſelfe Catholike, when he comes to paſſe his cenſorious edict vpon Cardinall Baronius (who in the eleuenth Tome of his Hiſtorie ſeemed too buſie in faſtening the title of theEdicto del 
                        •
                     ey D
                        •
                     n Phelipped
                        •
                      Eſpana co
                        •
                     tra el Tr
                        •
                     ct ad
                        •
                      della Mon
                        •
                     r
                        ••
                     ia d
                        •
                      S
                        •
                     cil
                        •
                     a e
                        •
                     xerid
                        •
                      por Ceſar Baronio Cardenal, on el T
                        •
                     mo vndecim
                        •
                      de 
                        〈◊〉
                      Annales Eccl
                        •
                     ſi
                        •
                     ſtic
                        •
                     s. Kingdome of Sicilie vpon the Pope) profeſſeth to ground his intelligence of this wrong only vpon others eyes; as if a booke (though of a Cardinall) were too meane an obiect for the view of Maieſty: and as all ſubordinate greatnes flowes from the head, ſo doe commonly alſo the diſpoſitions. Neither haue

the Doctours of the Romiſh Church (vpon whom the implicit faith of the Laitie is ſuſpended) found it any ill policie, to cheriſh this diſlike of bookiſhneſſe in the great; for, whiles the candle is out, it is ſafe for them to play their trickes in the darke: and if the Aſſyrians be once blinded, how eaſily may they bee led into the midſt of any Samar
                        •
                     a? If the light of knowledge might freely 
                     •
                  hine to the world, Poperie would ſoone bee aſhamed of it ſelfe, and vaniſh amongſt the workes of darkneſſe. Now how well theſe examples, and this conuerſation, ſhall whet the appetite vnto good ſtudies, it cannot be hard to iudge.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 11.
               But perhaps it is not the learning of the ſchoole, but of the State, wherein our Traueller hopes for perfection: The ſite and forme of cities, the faſhions of gouernment,

the manners of people, the raiſing and rate of forraine reuenues, the deportment of Courts, the menaging both of warre and peace, is that wherein his owne eye ſhall be his beſt intelligencer; The knowledge whereo
                     •
                   ſhall w
                     •
                  ll requite his labour, whether for diſcourſe or for vſe. What if I ſay, that (ſaue the ſoothing vp of our fancy in all this) theſe leſſons may bee as well taken out at home: I haue knowen ſome that haue trauelled no further then their owne cloſet, which could both teach and correct the greateſt Traueller, after all his tedious and coſtly pererrations, what doe wee but loſe the benefit of ſo many iournals, maps, hyſtoricall deſcriptions, relations, if we cannot with theſe helps, trauell by our owne fire-ſide? Hee that trauels into forraine countries, talkes perhaps with a Peaſant, or a

Pilgrim, or a Citizen, or a Courtier; and muſt needs take ſuch information as partiall rumour, or weake coniecture can giue him; but hee that trauels into learned and credible Authors, talkes with them who haue ſpent themſelues in bolting out the truth of all paſſages; and who hauing made their labours publike, would haue beene like to heare of it, if they had miſ-reported: The ordinary Traueller propounds ſome prime Cities to himſelfe, and thither hee walkes right forward, if he meet with ought that is memorable in the way, hee takes it vp; but how many thouſand matters of note fall beſide him, on either hand; of the knowledge whereof he is not guilty; Whereas 
                     •
                  ome graue and painefull Author hath collected into one view, whatſoeuer his country affords worthy of marke; hauing meaſured many

a fowle ſtep for that, which we may ſee dry-ſhod; and worne out many yeeres in the ſearch of that, which one houre ſhall make no leſſe ours, then it was his owne. To which muſt be added, that our vnperfit acquaintance may not hope to finde ſo perfect information on the ſudden, as a naturall inhabitant may get, by the diſquiſition of his whole life: Let an Italian or French paſſenger walk through this our Iland, what can his Tablebookes carry home, in compariſon of the learned Britaine of our Camden, or the accurate Tables of Speed? Or if one of ours ſhould (as too many doe) paſſe the Alpes, what pittances can his wilde iourney obſerue, in compariſon of the Itenerary of Fr. Schottus and Capugnanus: Or he that would diſcourſe of the Royalties of the French Lillies, how can hee bee ſo furniſhed

by flying report, as by the elaborate gatherings of Caſſaneus, or of Degraſſalius; What ſhould I bee infinite? This age is ſo full of light, that there is no one country of the habitable world, whoſe beames are not croſſed and interchanged with other; Knowledge of all affaires, is like muſicke in the ſtreets, whereof thoſe may partake, which pay nothing; Wee doe not lie more open to one common ſnnne, then to the eyes and pens of our neighbours; Euen China itſelfe, and Iaponia, and thoſe other remoteſt Iſles, &amp; continents (which haue taken the ſtricteſt order for cloſeneſſe) haue receiued ſuch diſcoueries, as would rather ſatisfie a Reader, then prouoke him to amend them. A good booke is at once the beſt companion, and guide, and way, and end of our iourney; Neceſſity droue our forefathers

out of doores, which elſe in thoſe miſty times had ſeene no light, we may with more eaſe, and no leſſe profit ſit ſtill, and inherit, and enioy the labours of them, &amp; our elder brethen, who haue purchaſed our knowledge with much hazard, time, toile, expence; and haue beene liberall of their bloud (ſome of them) to leaue vs rich.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 12.
               As for that verball diſcourſe, wherein I ſee ſome place the felicity of their trauell (thinking it the onely grace, to tell wonders to a ring of admiring ignorants) it is eaſie to anſwer; that table-talk is the leaſt care of a wiſe man; who like a deepe ſtreame deſires rather to runne ſilent; and as himſelfe is ſeldome tranſported with wonder, ſo doth he not affect it in others; reducing all to vſe, rather then admiration, and more deſiring to benefit, then aſtoniſh the hearer;

withall, that the ſame means which enable vs to know, d
                     •
                   at o
                     •
                  ce furniſh vs with matter of diſ
                     •
                  ourſe, &amp; for the forme of our expreſſion, if it proceede not from that naturall dexterity which we carry with vs, in vaine ſhall wee hope to bring it home; the change of language is rather an hinderance to our former readineſſe; and if ſome haue fetcht new noſes, and lips, and eares from Italy (by the helpe of Tagliacotius, &amp; his ſchollers) neuer any brought a new tongue from thence. 
                     •
                  o conclude, if a man would giue himſelfe leaue to bee thus vaine and free, like a mill without a ſcluſe, let him but trauell through the world of bookes, &amp; he ſhall eaſily be able to out-talke that tongue, whoſe feet haue walkt the furtheſt; what 
                     •
                  ath any eye ſeene, or imagination deuiſed, which the pen hath not dared to write? Out of our bookes

can we tell the ſtories of the Monocelli, who lying vpon their backes, ſhelter themſelues from the ſunne with the ſhadow of their one only foot. We can tell of thoſe cheapedieted men, that liue about the head of Ganges, without mea
                     •
                  , without mouthes, feeding onely vpon aire at their noſthrils. Or of thoſe headleſſe Eaſterne people, that haue their eyes in their breaſts (a miſ-conceit ariſing from their faſhion of attire, which I haue ſometimes ſeene): Or of thoſe Coromand
                        •
                     e, of whom Pliny ſpeaks, that couer their whole body with their eares: Or of the perſecutors of S. Thoma
                        •
                     
                   of Canterbury, whoſe poſteritie (if wee beleeue the con
                  
                     •
                  ident writings of Degra
                        ••
                     alius) are borne with long and hairie tailes, ſouping after them; which (I imagine) gaue occaſion to that prouerbiall ieſt, wherewith our mirth

vſes to vpbraid the Kentiſh: Or of Am
                        •
                     zons, or Pygme
                        •
                     s, or Satyres, or the Samarcaudean Lambe, which growing out of the earth by the nauell, grazeth ſo 
                     •
                  ar
                     •
                  e as that natural
                     •
                   
                  
                     ••
                  ther will reach: Or of the bird Ruc, or ten thouſand ſuch miracles, whether of nature, or euent
                     •
                   Little neede wee to ſtirre our feet to lea
                     ••
                  e to tell either loud lies, or large 
                     •
                  ruth
                     •
                  . Wee haue heard a bird in a cage 
                     •
                  ing more change of 
                     •
                  otes, then others haue done i
                     •
                   the wilde libertie of the wood
                     •
                   And as for the preſent occurrences of 
                     •
                  he time, the world about vs is ſo full of Preſſes, that it may, and 
                     •
                  s grow
                     •
                  e ſo good a fellow, that it will, impart what it knowes to all the neighbours: whoſe relations, if ſometimes o
                     •
                  ey ſwarue from truth, we may well conſider, what varietie of report euery accident will y
                     ••
                  ld; and 
                     •
                  hat therefore

our eares abroad are no whit more credible, then our eyes at home. Yea rather, as Tully could ſay, that at Antium he could heare the newes of Rome, better then at Rome; ſo may wee oft-times better heare and ſee the newes of France, or Spaine, vpon our Exchange, then in their Paris, or Madrill: Since (what libertie ſoeuer tongues may take to themſelues) a diſcreet man will be aſhamed to ſubſcribe his name to that, whereof hee may bee afterwards conuinced.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 13.
               Since therefore Trauell cannot out-bid vs in theſe higheſt commodities, which concerne the wealth of the minde; all the aduantage it can afford vs, muſt bee in thoſe mixt abilities, wherein our bodies are the greateſt partners, as dancing, 
                     •
                  encing, muſicke, vaulting, horſemanſhip; the only profeſſions

of the miſ-named Academies of other nations. Who can denie that ſuch like exerciſes are fit for young Gentlemen, not onely for their preſent recreation, but much more for the preparing of them to more ſerious action? Yet muſt theſe learne to know their places: what are they elſe but the varniſh of that picture of Gentry, whoſe ſubſtance conſiſts in the lines and colours of true vertue? but the lace or facing of a rich garment? but the hang-byes of that royall court which the ſoule keeps in a generous heart? He that holds Gentilitie accompliſhed with theſe (though laudable) qualities, partakes more of his horſe, then his horſe can poſſibly of him. This skill then is worthy of our purchaſe, yet may not bee bought too deare; and perhaps need not bee fetch't ſo farre. Neither my profeſſion,

nor my experience will allow mee to
                     •
                   hold compariſons in this kinde; but I haue beene heartened by no meane maſters of theſe Arts, to ſay that our Nation hath yeelded ſome in all theſe faculties, which need not ſtoope vnto the proudeſt 
                     •
                  orrainer: ours haue no fault but one, that they are our owne; and what h
                     ••
                  h their Countrey offended, if their Art offend not? It is an humorous giddineſſe to meaſure the goodn
                     •••
                  e of any thing by the diſtance of miles, and where there is equalitie of worth, to neglect the neereſt. I ſlander our Nation if it bee not ſicke of this diſeaſe, in the courſe of all ſciences. And if neereneſſe and preſence bee the cauſe of our diſlike, why doe wee not hate our ſelues, which are euer in our owne boſomes? Why doe we not hate this faſtidious curioſitie, which is

too cloſe to vs? Perhaps perfection in theſe qualities is thinner ſowne amongſt vs, then ſome other-where; ſo as our Iland for want of worke, and incouragement, affords not ſuch multitude of maſters: but how can wee complaine of rareneſſe, ſince if our age yeeld vs but one excellent in each kinde, it is more then wee are willing to vſe? and if the fault were not in our ſelues, one candle may light a thouſand. To inſtance in the beſt: The horſe is a noble cr
                     •
                  ature, which as it is the ſtr
                     •
                  ngth and pride of France, ſo wins the hearts and heeles of that Nation: The generalitie of their skill is nothing to a ſtranger; each pri
                     •
                  ate mans cunning reſts in himſelfe; it is only the Teacher, whoſe abilitie may concerne vs. And whereas there is a double kinde of menage (as I haue heard) one for ſeruice, the other

for pleaſure; in the firſt our maſters thinke they cannot yeeld vnto the beſt; in the latter, if they grant themſelues exceeded, how many men haue taught their dogge the ſame trickes, with no leſſe contentment? In both, we haue the written directions of their greateſt Artiſts; who (for the perpetuitie of their owne honour) failed not to ſay their beſt. And if theſe dead maſters ſuffice not, wee haue had, wee may haue the beſt of their liuing: The conſcience of a mans excellencie will abide no limits, but ſpurres him forth to winne admiration abroad; and if therewithall he can finde aduancement of profit, how willingly doth hee change his home? Wee haue had experience of this in higher profeſſions, much more in theſe vnder foot. One obſcure towne of Holland in our memory, had by this

meanes drawne together at once the greateſt lights of EVROPE, and made it ſelfe then no leſſe renowned for Profeſſors, then it is now infamous for Schiſme. Feare of enuy forbids me to name thoſe amongſt vs, which haue honoured this Iland in the choice of their abode. Where Art is encouraged, it will ſoone riſe high, and go farre, and not ſuffer a channell of the ſea to ſtay it from the preſence of a more bountifull patronage.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 14.
               But let vs grant theſe faculties ſo fixed vpon any nation, that all our water muſt neceſſarily bee fetcht at their Well; and adde vnto theſe a few wa
                     •
                  te complements, and mimicall courteſies, which muſt needs bee put into the match of our ordinary trauell: and now let vs ſit downe, and ſee what wee paid for this ſtocke, and count our winnings: What muſt our com
                     •
                  pleat

Traueller ſtake downe for this goodly furniture o
                     •
                   his Gentry? If not loſſe, danger; danger of the beſt part, if not all; a double danger; of corruption of religion, and deprauation of manners; both capitall: And can we thinke theſe endowments ſo precious, that they ſhould bee worth fetching vpon ſuch an hazard? Will any man (not deſperate) runne into an infected houſe, to rifle for a rich ſuit? Will any man put his finger into a fiery crucible, to pull out gold? It is wittily taken of Chryſoſtome, when our Sauiour ſaid, Ne exeat is in eremum; that he ſayes not, Goe forth into the deſert and ſee, but beleeue not; but giues an abſolute prohibition of going forth at al
                     •
                  , that they might be out of the danger of misbeleefe. Tuſh, idle and melancholicke feares, ſay ſome of our Gallants; wherefore ſerues

diſcretion, but to ſeuer good from ill? How 
                     •
                  aſily may a wiſe man pull a roſe, and not pricke his hand? How freely may he dip in this ſtreame, and not be drowned? Little doe theſe peremptory re
                     •
                  oluers know, either the in
                     •
                  inuatiue power of euill, or the treachery of their owne heart in receiuing it, or the importunitie of deceiuers in obtruding it: They are the worſe for their trauell, and perceiue it not. An egge couered with ſalt, as our Ph
                     •
                  loſophers teach vs, hath the m
                     •
                  at of it conſumed, whiles the ſhell is whole: many a one receiues poiſon, and knowes not when hee tooke it. No ma
                     •
                   proues extremely euill on the ſudden. Through many inſenſible declinations doe wee 
                     •
                  all from vertue; and at the firſt are ſo gently ſeazed by vice, that wee cannot beleeue our accuſers. It is miſchiefe enough, if they can bee

drawne to a leſſe diſlike of ill; which now by long acquaintance is growne ſo 
                     •
                  amiliar to their eyes, that they cannot thinke it ſo loathſome, as at the firſt view. The ſocietie of wilfull Idolaters will now downe with them, not without eaſe; and good meanings beginne to bee allowed for the clokes of groſſe ſuperſtition. From thence they grow to a fauourable conſtruction of the miſ-opinions of the aduerſe part, and can complaine of the wrongfull aggrauations of ſome contentious ſpirits: and from thence (yet lower) to an indifferent conceit of ſome more politike poſitions, and practiſes o
                     •
                   the Romaniſts. Neither is ther
                     •
                   their reſt. Hereupon enſues an allowance of ſome of their do
                     •
                  trines, that are more plauſible, and leſſe important, and withall a cenſure of vs that are gone too farre from Rome.
                  
Now the mariage of Eccleſiaſticall perſons begins to miſlike them: the daily and frequent conſignation with the croſſe is not to no purpoſe: The retired life of the religious (abandoning the world forſooth) ſauours of much mortification; and confeſſion giues no ſmall eaſe and contentment to the ſoule. And now by degrees, Poperie beginnes to be no ill religion: If there cannot be a falſe fire of miſ-deuotion kindled in them, it is enough, if they can be cooled in their loue of truth; which how commonly it fals out amongſt vs, I had rather experience ſhould ſpeake, then my ſelfe. Some there are that by a ſpirituall Antiperiſtaſis haue growne hotter in their zeale, by being encompaſſed with the outward cold of irreligion, and errour, who as they owe not this grace to themſelues, ſo they are more for wonder

then imitation. If Daniel found a guard in the Lions denne, ſhall another put himſelfe thither for 
                     •
                  helter? And if Peter walkt vpon the pauement of the water, did the reſt of the Diſciples ſtep forth and follow him? That valiant champion of Chriſt (ſince wee are fallen vpon his name) who durſt draw his ſword vpon a whole troupe, after all the proteſtations of his inſeparableneſſe from his maſter, was yet infected with the aire of the High-Prieſts Hall: and whiles hee but warmed himſelfe at that fire, cooled in his reſpect to his Sauiour. Although perhaps this contagion working (as it commonly doth) remiſſely, cauſeth not any ſudden alteration in our Traueller, but (as wee ſay of Comets and Eclipſes) hath his effect when the cauſe is forgotten. Neither is there any one more apparant ground of

that luke-warme indifferencie, which is fallen vpon our times, then the ill vſe of our wandrings: for our Trauellers being the middle-ranke of men, and therefore either followers of the great, or commanders of the meaner ſort, cannot want conuenience of diffuſing this temper of eaſe, vnto both.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 15.
               All this miſchiefe is yet hid with a formall profeſſion, ſo as euery eye cannot finde it: in others it dares boldly breake 
                     •
                  orth to an open reuolt. How many in our memory, whiles with Dina
                        •
                     
                   they haue gone fo
                     •
                  th to gaze, haue lo
                     ••
                   their 
                     •
                  pirituall chaſtitie, and therewith both the Church, and themſelues? How many (like vnto the brooke 
                     
                        ••
                     dron) run from 
                     
                        •
                     ieruſ
                        •
                     
                     lem through the vale of 
                     
                        ••
                     hoſ
                        •
                     p
                        ••
                     t,
                  
                     
                        
                           ••
                        bert P
                           •
                        int
                           •
                        
                      in his pre
                        •
                     ace to the t
                        •
                     ſtimonies for the r
                        •
                     
                     all preſence. and end their courſe in the dead Sea? A popiſh writer of our Nation

(as himſelfe thought) not vnlearned, complaining of the obſtinacie of vs heretickes, deſpaires of preuailing, becauſe hee findes it to be long agoe fore-prophecied of vs in the booke of the Chronicles, At illi Proteſtantes audire noluerunt.
                  2 Chron. 24. It is well that Proteſtants were yet heard of in the old Teſtament, as well as I
                     •
                  ſuites; whoſe name, one of their owne by good hap hath
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     n I
                        •
                     ſ
                        •
                     am, l. 
                        
                           •
                        . c. 
                        〈◊〉
                      q. 19. Gret
                        •
                     er. contra Le
                        •••
                     eum, c. 
                        
                           •
                        . &amp; 2. V r
                        •
                      ai
                        •
                      quida
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      Ieſu
                        •
                     ta
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     n ſ
                        •
                     cris l
                        •••
                     ris 
                        ••
                     p
                        •
                     riri. found, Numb
                        •
                     
                   26. 24. Like as Eraſmus found Friers in S. Pauls time, inter falſos Fratres. But it were better, if this mans word were as true, as it is idle. Some of ours haue heard to their coſt, whoſe loſſe ioyned with the griefe of the Church, and diſhonour of the Goſpell, wee haue ſufficiently lamented. How many haue wee knowne ſtrucken with theſe Aſps, which haue died ſle
                     •
                  ping? And in truth, whoſoeuer ſhall conſider

this open freedome of the meanes of ſeducement, muſt needs wonder that wee haue loſt no more; eſpecially if he be acquainted with thoſe two maine helpes of our aduerſaries, importunitie and plauſibilitie. Neuer any Phariſee was ſo eager to make a Proſelyte, as our late factors of Rome: and if they bee ſo hot ſet vpon this ſeruice, as to compaſſe ſea and land to winne one of vs, ſhall wee be ſo madde as to paſſe both their ſea and land, to caſt our ſelues into the mouth of danger? No man ſetteth foot vpon their coaſt, which may not preſently ſing with the Pſalmiſt, They come about mee like Bees. It fares with them as with thoſe which are infected with the peſtilence, who (they ſay) are carried with an itching deſire of tainting others. When they haue all done, this they haue gained, that if

Satan were not more buſie and vehement then they, they could gaine nothing. But in the meane time there is nothing wherein I wi
                     •
                  h we would emulate them, but in this heat of diligence, and viol
                     •
                  nt ambition of winning. Pyr
                        ••
                     us did not more en
                     •
                  ie the valour of thoſe old Roman ſouldiers, which hee read in their wounds, and dead faces, then we doe the buſ
                     •
                  e audacitie of theſe new. The world could not ſtand before vs, if our Truth might bee but as hotly followed, as their falſhood. Oh that our God, whoſe cauſe wee maintaine, would enkindle our hearts with the fire of holy zeale, but ſo much as Satan hath inflamed theirs with the fire of 
                     •
                  urie and faction. Oh that hee would ſhake vs out of this dull 
                     •
                  aſe, and quicken our ſlacke ſpirits vnto his owne worke. Ariſe, O North, and come, O

South, and blow vpon our garden, that the ſpices thereof may flow forth. Theſe ſuters will take no deniall, but are ready (as the faſhion was to doe with rich matches) to carry away mens ſoules whether they will or no. Wee ſee the proofe of their importunitie at home: No bulwarkes of lawes, no barres of iuſtice (though made of three trees) can keepe our rebaniſhed fugitiues from returning from intermedling. How haue their actions ſaid in the hearing of the world, that ſince heauen will not heare them, they will tr
                     •
                  e what hell can doe? And if they dare bee ſo buſie in our owne homes, where they would ſeeme ſomewhat awed with the danger of iuſtice; what (thinke wee) will they not dare to doe in their owne territories, where they haue not free ſcope only, but aſſiſtance, but incouragement?

Neuer generation was ſo forward as the Ieſuiticall, for captation of willes amongſt their owne, or of ſoules amongſt ſtrangers. What ſtate is not haunted with theſe ill ſpirits? yea what houſe? yea what ſoule? Not a Princes CounſellTable, not a Ladies chamber can be free from their ſhameleſſe inſinuations. It was not for nothing, that their great Patron Philip the ſecond King of Spaine, called them Clerigos negotiadores; and that Marcus Antonius Columna Generall of the Nauie to Pius quintus, in the battell of Lepanto, and Viceroy of Sicilie, could ſay to Father Don Alonſo, a famous 
                     •
                  eſuite, affecting to be of the counſell of his conſcience, Voi altri padri di 
                        •
                     h
                        •
                     ſu 
                        •
                     auete la mente al cielo, le mani al mondo, l' anima al diauolo.
               
            
            
               
                  Sect. 16.
               Yet were there the leſſe perill of their vehemence, if it were onely

rude and boiſterous (as in ſome other ſects) that ſo (as it is in Canon
                     •
                  ſhot) it might be more eaſily ſhun'd, then re
                     ••
                  ſted: but here, the skill of doing miſ
                     •
                  hiefe contends with the power; their miſ-zealous paſſions hide themſelues in a pleaſing ſweetneſſe, and they are more beholden to policie, then ſtrength. What Gentleman of any note can croſſe our Seas, whoſe name is not landed in their bookes before hand, in preuention of his perſon, whom now arriued, if they finde vntractable through too much preiudice, they labour 
                     •
                  irſt to temper with the plauſible con
                     ••
                  rſation of ſome ſmooth Catholike of his owne nation: the name of his Country is warrant enough for his in
                     •
                  inuation. Not a word yet may be ſpoken of religion; as if that were no part of the errand. So haue wee ſeene an Ha
                     •
                  ke caſt off at an

Heron Shaw, to looke and flie a quite other way, and after many careleſſe and ouerly fetches, to towre vp vnto the pr
                     •
                  y intended. There is nothing wherein this faire companion ſhall not apply himſelfe to his welcome Countriman. At laſt, when hee hath poſſeſt himſelfe of the heart of his new acquaintance, and got himſelfe the reputation of a ſweet ingenuitie, and delightfull ſociableneſſe; hee findes opportunities to beſtow ſome wittie ſcoffes vpon thoſe parts of our religion, which lie moſt open to aduantage. And now it is time to inuite him (after other rarities) to ſee the Monaſterie of our Engliſh Benedictines, or (if elſewhere) thoſe Engliſh Colledges, which the deuout beneficence of our well-meaning neighbours (with no other intention then ſome couetous farmers lay faltca
                     •
                  s

in their doue-cotes) haue bountifully erected. There, it is a wonder if our Traueller meet not with ſome one, that ſhall claime kindred or Country of him in a more intire faſhion. The ſocietie welcomes him with more then ordinary courteſie: neither can hee refuſe (except hee will be vnciuill) to be their gueſt. He cannot miſlike the loue of his Countrimen, hee cannot fault their carriage. And now that they haue mollified the ſtiffeneſſe of his preiudice, and with much tempering fitted him for their mold, he is a taske meet for one of their beſt workmen; who willingly vndertaking it, hath learned to handle him ſo ſweetly, as if he would haue him thinke it a pleaſure to bee ſeduced. Doe yee thinke this Doctor will begin firſt with the infallibilitie of their great Maſter, and perſwade him that a

Necromancer, an Hereticke, an Atheiſt, cannot erre in Peters Chaire? or tell him that hee may buy off his ſinnes as familiarly as he may buy wares in the market? or teach him that a man may and muſt both make and eat his God to his breakfaſt? This hard meat is for ſtronger mawes. Hee knowes how firſt to begin with the ſpoone, and to offer nothing to a weake ſtomacke, but diſcourſe of eaſie digeſtion: As firſt, that a Ca
                     •
                  holike ſo l
                     •
                  uing and dying (by our confeſſion) may be ſaued: That there is but one Church, as but one Chriſt; and that out of this Arke, there is no way but drowning: That this one Church is more likely to bee found in all the world, then in a corner; in all ages, then in the laſt Century of yeeres; in vnitie, then in diuiſion. And now comes in the glorious bragge of

the Roman Vniuerſalitie, their inviolate Antiquitie, their recorded ſucceſſions, their harmonious vnitie, their confeſſed magnificence: That theirs is the mother Church, as to the reſt of Chriſtendome, ſo eſpecially to the Engliſh: How well a Monarchie (the beſt forme of gouernment) beſeemes the Church: How vnlikely it is that Chriſt would leaue his Spouſe in the confuſion of many heads, or of none. And now, what are wee but a ragge torne from their cote? and where was our religion before Luther lay with Bora? And what miſerable ſubdiuiſions are there in our Proteſtancie? and what a gleaning are we to the harueſt of Chriſtendome? w
                     •
                  th infinite ſuggeſtions of this nature; able (as they are plauſibly vrg
                     •
                  d) to ſhake an vngrounded iudgement: which i
                     •
                   they haue ſo farre preuailed, as that

the hearer will abide himſelfe hood-winkt with this vaile of the Church, how eaſily ſhall time lead him into thoſe hatefuller abſardities?
            
            
               
                  Sect. 17.
               In all which proceedings, theſe impoſtors haue a double aduantage: Firſt, that they deliuer the opinion of their Church with ſuch mitigation and fauour, as thoſe that care to pleaſe, not to enforme: forming the voyce of the Church to the liking of the hearer, not the iudg
                     •
                  ment of the hearer to the voyce of the Church: wherein it is not hard to obſerue, that Popery ſpoken and written are two things; In diſcourſe, nothing is more ordinary then to diſclaime ſome of their receiued poſitions, to blanch others. It is the malice of an aduerſary that miſ-reports them; they doe not hold that images ſhould bee adored; that the

wood of the croſſe ſhould be worſhipped with the very ſame deuotion that is due to Chriſt himſelfe; that the Church is the Iudge of Gods writings; that Panl the fift cannot erre; that a man may merit of his maker, much leſſe ſupererogate; that a mouſe may runne away with that which either is, or was God Almighty; That it is lawfull to kill an hereticall King, and all other thoſe monſters of opinion, which their moſt claſſicke Authors haue both hatched and ſhameleſly thruſt into the light of the world. They defie thoſe ridiculous Legends which we father vpon their Church; and how much doe they ſcorne S. Francis his Bird, or his Wolfe, or his Wounds, or his Apoſtles of Aſſiſe. Pope Ioane was but a fancy: Neuer Pope was an hereticke. If now wee cry out of impudence, and call their allowed

writers to witneſſe. Lo, euen they alſo are forged by vs, &amp; are taught to play booty on our ſide. Thus reſolued to out-face all euidence, they make faire weather of their fowleſt opinions, and inueigh againſt nothing ſo much as the ſpightfulneſſe of our ſlanders. It is not poſſible that any wiſe ſtranger ſhould be in loue with the face of their Church, if he might ſee her in her owne likeneſſe, and therfore they haue cunningly masked one part of it, and painted another, ſo as thoſe features of hers which are vgly and offenſiue, ſhall not appeare to any but her owne eyes. And becauſe bookes are dangerous blabs, and will be telling the generations to come, how ſtrangely that face is altered with Age and Art, therefore their tongues are clipped alſo, and made to ſpeake none but her owne words. Out of

this licence, and hope to winne, they can fit their diſhes to eueryExemplar. Epiſt. Scriptae ad D
                        •
                     
                     minum Paulinum quondam datarium ſub Ciementis 8
                           •
                        
                      beat
                        •
                      m
                        •
                     mori
                        •
                      Ponti
                        ••
                     cat
                        •
                     . palate, and are ſo ſawcy, as to make the Church belye it ſelfe. Hence it was that a Spaniſh Father could teach, that it is not of the neceſſity of faith, to beleeue that the preſent Pope is the Vicar of Chriſt, and the Succeſſor of Peter. That Hostius the 
                     •
                  eſuite could ſay, that the Pope abuſed his keyes, and the authorityIbid. of the Church, in receiuing Henry the fourth. That another of his fellowes in a diſcourſe with a French Biſhop, could diſparage the deciſion of his Holines in compariſon of a generall Counſel. That Men
                        •
                     s the reader of diuinity at Valledolid followingIbid. 
                  Salas the Ieſuite, could affirme the lawfulnes of the mariage of religious perſons vpon a doubtful reuelation. That more then one of that order, haue dared to broach confeſſion by letters, againſt the

of Clement Bull the 8. And if theſe men be no ſparing of their contradictions to that Vice-god of theirs, whoſe vaſſals they are by peculiar profeſſion, how much more boldly will they ſwim againſt the ſtreame of any common opinion, that may concerne the body of that head?
            
            
               
                  Sect. 18.
               Their ſecond aduantage is, that they regard not with what vntruths they make good th
                     •
                  ir owne aſſertions; It is all one with what morter or rubbiſh they build vp a ſide. From hence flow the confifident reports, both of their miracles to conuince vs, and their ſlanders to diſgrace vs. Father Hayndius, a Ieſuite of 33. yeeres ſtanding, amongſt fifty two complaints, which (out of an honeſt remorſe) he put vp againſt his owne ſociety, to their Generall Aquauiua, findes this not the leaſt, that his fellowes ſ
                     •
                  amed not to ſeeke the honour

of their order, by cogging of miracles. What packets flie about daily of their Indian wonders? Euen Card. Bellarmine can abide to come in as an auoucher of theſe couzenages; who dares auerre that his fellow Xauier had not only healed the deafe, dumb and blinde, but raiſed the dead; Whiles his brother Acoſta after many yeeres ſpent in thoſe parts can pull him by the ſleeue, and tell him in his eare, ſo lowd that all the world may heare him, Prodigia nulla producimus,
                  Lib. 4. de ſalut. Ind. c. 12. &amp;c. 
                  ne
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      verò eſt opus. Of the ſame ſtamp are the daily-renued miracles, reuelations, vi
                     •
                  ions, wherewith any mans eares muſt needes bee beaten amongſt them: Africke was at the beſt but barren of nouelties, in compariſon of Rome; and yet the world is incredulous, if it will not ſuffer it ſelfe gulled with theſe holy frauds. And

no fewer are thoſe lewd calumniations (the ſtuffe of all their inuectiues) whereby they labour to make vs loathſome to the world: our perſons, our doctrines are loaded with reproaches; neither matters it how iuſt they are, but how ſpightfull; What other meaſure can be expected of vs, when their beſt friends haue thus (vpon ſome priuate diſlikes) ſmarted from them. Their owne holy Fathers, Clement the eight, and Sixtus quintus, and with them (the honour of the Ieſuiticall order) Cardinall Tollet, can all ſhew bloudy wales in their backes, from their laſhes. Their late Patron of famous memory, whoſe heart they well-merited, and keep it (as their deere relique) enſhrined in their La-Fleſche, was after his death in their pulpits proclaimed Tyran and worſe: noExamplar. 
                        •
                     pi
                        •
                     t. ſupr. cit. maruell then if after the virulent

declamations of our Gifford (their Gabriel) and the malicious ſuggeſtions of others of that viperous brood, we haue much adoe to perſwade our neighbors, that we haue any Churc
                     ••
                  s, Baptiſme, Liturgy, Religion. I appeale then to all eyes and eares, how eaſie it is for a man that will take leaue to himſelfe, of making what truth he liſts, and defending them by what vutruths he pleaſeth, to lead a credulous hea
                     •
                  t whither he pleaſeth.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 19.
               But if the power of falſified reaſon preuaile not, theſe deſperate factors of Rome (as I haue beene informed) haue learned out of their acquaintance in the Court of the Prince of darkneſſe, to imploy ſtronger aid. On ſome of their hands, I feare, Magicall deluſions and deuilliſh incantations ſhall not want, rather then they will want a client. Neither can this feeme

ſtrange to any, that knowes how familiarly the Roman Church profeſſes the ſolemne practiſe of coniuration; in ſuch a faſhion, as it doth more then trouble the beſt Caſuiſts, to ſet downe a perfect difference betwixt their ſacred Magicke, &amp; the Diabolicall. From hence perhaps haue proceeded thoſe miraculous apparitions (if at leaſt they were any other but fancie, or fraud) wherewith ſome of our death-ſicke Gentlemen amongſt them, haue beene frighted into Catholikes. A famous Diuine of France, ſecond to none for learning, or fidelitie, told me this one
                     •
                   amongſt other inſtances, of his owne experience, which hee yet liues to iuſtifie: A Gentleman of the religion, whoſe wife was popiſhly deuoted, lying vpon the bed of his ſickneſſe, in expectation of death, ſends for this Diuine, his

Paſtor; the ſicke mans wife ſends for a Ieſuite; both meet at the beds ſide; each perſwades him to his owne part; both pleade for their religion at this barre, before theſe Iudges: after two houres diſputation, not only the Gentleman was cheerefully confirmed in that iudgement which hee had embraced, but his wife alſo, out of the euidence of truth, began to incline to him, and it: The Ieſuite departed diſcontent; yet within ſome few houres after, returning (when the coaſt was clearer) intreats ſome priuate conference with the Gentlewoman; with whom walking in her garden, hee did vehemently expoſtulate, mixing therewithall his ſtrongeſt perſwa
                     ••
                  ons; at laſt to ſhut vp his diſcourſe, he importun'd her with many obſecrations, that ſhe would vou
                     •
                  hſafe to receiue from his hands a little boxe

which he there offred her, and for his ſake weare it about her continually: ſhee condeſcended. No ſooner had ſhee taken it, then ſhee fell to ſo great a deteſtation of her husband, that ſhee could by no meanes bee drawne into his preſence, and within two dayes a
                     •
                  ter, in this eſtate ſhee died. An act more worthy the ſword of iuſtice, then the penne of an aduerſarie. Theſe courſes are as ſecret as wicked: not daring therefore peremptorily to accuſe, I had rather leaue theſe practiſes to further inquirie. Sure I am that by their tongues Satan labours to inchant the world, and hath ſtrongly deluded too many ſoules. And are wee weary of ours, that wee dare tempt God, and offer our ſelues as challengers to this ſpirituall danger? The Ieſuites, amongſt much change of houſes, haue two famous

for the accordance of their names; one called The Bow, at Nola; the other The Arrow, (La Fleſche) in France: though this latter were more worthy of the name of a whole Quiuer, containing not fewer then eight hundred ſhafts of all ſizes. Their Apoſtate Ferrier (if I ſhall not honour him too much) plaid vpon them in this diſtich:
               
                  Arcum Nola dedit, dedit ill is alma Sagittam
                  Gallia; quis funem, quem meruere, dabit?
                  Nola the Bow, and France the ſhaft did bring:
                  But who ſhall helpe them to an hempen ſtring?
               
               This prouiſion is for the care of Chriſtian Prouinces: but in the meane time, what madneſſe is it in vs, not only to giue aime to theſe rouing flights, but to offer our ſelues to bee their ſtanding Butt,

that they may take their full aime and hit vs leuell at pleaſure. Doe wee not heare ſome of their owneAt etiam nu
                        ••
                      non animaduertimus quod Lati
                        ••
                      ſermonis ob
                     
                        ••
                     n
                        ••
                      impuriſſimè Gallici inuentutis mores ingenuos foedant, bonarum literarum praete
                        •
                     t 
                        •
                     peſſimas edocent artes, dum ingenia excolunt, animas perdunt, &amp;c. Oratio ad Curiam Parlamenti ſuper Henrici magni parricidali n
                        •
                     ce. fellow-Catholikes in the midſt of their awfulleſt Senate, the Parliament of Paris, pleading vehemently againſt theſe factious ſpirits, and crying out paſſionately of that danger (which will follow vpon their admiſſion) hoth of lewd manners, and falſe doctrine, and doe we in greater oppoſition feare neither? and eſpecially from Engliſh Ieſuites? Some Countries yeeld more venomous vipers then others; ours the worſt. I would it were not too eaſie to obſerue, that as our Engliſh Papiſts are commonly more Ieſuitiſh, ſo our Engliſh Ieſuites are more furious, then their fellowes. Euen thoſe of the hotteſt climates cannot match them in fiery diſpoſitions. And doe we put our ſelues out of our

comfortable ſunne-ſhine, into the midſt of the flame of theſe noted incendiaries? Doe wee take pleaſure to make th
                     •
                  m rich with the ſpoile of our ſoules, and becauſe they will not come faſt enough to fetch theſe boo
                     •
                  ies, doe we g
                     •
                  e to carry them vnto their pillage?
            
            
               
                  Sect. 20.
               The danger is in the men more then in their cauſe; and if this great Curtizan of the world had not ſo cunning Pandars, I ſhould wonder how ſhee ſhould get any but fooliſh cuſtomers. Th
                     •
                   ſearcher of all hearts (before whoſe Tribunall I ſhal once come to giue an account of this Cenſure) knowes I ſpeake it not maliciouſly; Him I call to witneſſe that I could not find any true life of Religion amongſt thoſe that would bee Catholikes. I meddle not with the errours of Speculations, or Schole-points; wherein their iudgement palpably offendeth,

I ſpeake of the liuely practiſe of Piety; What haue they amongſt them but a very out-ſide of Chriſtianity, a meere formality of deuotion; Looke into their Churches; there their poore ignorant Laity hope to preſent their beſt ſeruices to God; and yet alas they ſay they know not what, they heare they know not what, they doe they they know not what; returning empty of all hearty edification, and onely full of confuſed intentions; and are taught to thinke this ſacrifice of fooles meritorious. Looke vpon their Chemarim the ſacred actors in this religious ſcene, what ſhall you ſee but idle apiſhneſſe in their ſolemneſt worke, and either mockery, or ſlubbering? Looke into their religious houſes; what ſhall you ſee but a trade of careles and lazie holineſſe; houres obſerued
                     •
                  , becauſe they muſt, not becauſe

they would. What doe they but lull piety a ſleepe with their heartleſſe and ſleepy Veſpers? Look into the priuate cloſets of their deuout Ignorants, what difference ſhall you ſee betwixt the Image and the Suppliant? If they can heare their beades knacke vpon each other, they are not bid to care for hearing their prayers reflect vpon heauen: Shortly in all that belongs to God, the worke done ſufficeth, yea meriteth; and what neede the heart bee wrought vpon for a taske of the hand? Looke into the melancholike cels of ſome auſtere Recluſes; there you may finde perhaps an hairecloth, or a a whip, or an heardle; but ſhew me true mortification, the power of ſpirituall renouation of the ſoule? How ſhould that bee found there when as that ſauing faith (which is the onely purger of the heart) is

barred out as preſumptuous: and no gueſt of that kinde allowed, but the ſame which is common to Diuels. What Papiſt in all Chiſtendome hath euer beene heard to pray daily with his family; or to ſing, but a Pſalme at home? Looke into the vniuerſall courſe of the Catholike life; there ſhall you find t
                     •
                  e Decalogue profeſſedly broken, Beſides the ordinary practiſe of Idolatry; and frequence of oathes; Who euer ſaw Gods day duely kept in any city, village, houſhold vnder the iuriſdiction of Rom
                        •
                     ? Euery obſcure Holy-day takes the wall of it, and thruſts it into the channell. Who ſees not obedience to authority ſo ſleighted, that it ſtands onely to the mercy of humane diſpenſation; and in the reſt of Gods Lawes, who ſees not how fowle ſinnes paſſe for veniall? and how eaſily veniall ſinnes paſſe their

ſatisfaction: for which, a croſſe, or a drop of holy-water is ſufficient amends. Who ſees not how no place can bee left for truth, where there is full roome giuen to equiuocation. All this, though it bee harſh to the conſcionable man, yet is no leſſe pleaſing to the carnall. The way of outward faſhionableneſſe in religion, and inward libertie of heart cannot but ſeeme faire to nature; and eſpecially when it hath ſo powerfull angariation. It is a wonder if but one halfe of Chriſtendome bee thus won to walke in it. Thoſe which are either vngrounded in the principles of Religion, or the vnconſcionable in the practiſe, are fit to trauell into the
                     •
                  e miſerable errours, But though Iſrael play the harlot, yet let not Iudah ſinne. Come yee not to Gilgal; neither goe yee vp to Bethauen.
               
            
            
               
                  Sect. 21.
               From the danger of corruption


iudgement. Let vs turne our eyes to the deprauation of manners; which not ſeldome goes before: Apples therefore fall from the tree becauſe they are worme-eaten, they are not worme-eaten becauſe they fall; and, as vſually followes, Satan like the rauen firſt ſeizes vpon the eye of vnderſtanding, and then preyes freely vpon the other carcaſe. Wee may be bad enough at home, certainly wee are the worſe for our neighbours. Old Rome was not more iealous of the Grecian and African manners, then wee haue reaſon to be of the Roman. It were well if wee knew our owne faſhions, better if wee could keepe them. What miſchiefe haue wee amongſt vs that we haue not borrowed? To begin
                     ••
                   at our skinne; who knowes not whence wee had the varietie of our vaine diſguiſes? As if wee had not wit

enough to bee fooliſh, vnleſſe wee were taught it. Theſe dreſſes being conſtant in their mutabilitie, ſhew vs our maſters. What is it that wee haue not learned of our neighbours, ſaue only to be proud good cheape? Whom would it not vexe to ſee how that other ſexe hath learned to make Antiks and monſters of themſelues? Whence came their hips to the ſhoulders, and their breaſts to the nauell; but the one from ſome ill-ſhap't Dames of France, the other from the worſe minded Curtizans of Italie? Whence elſe learned they to daube theſe mudde-walles with Apothecaries morter; and thoſe high waſhes, which are ſo cunningly lickt on, that the wet napkin of Phryne ſhould be deceiued? Whence the friſled and poudred buſhes of their borrowed excrements? as if they were aſhamed of

the head of Gods making, and proud of the Tire-womans? Where learned wee that deuilliſh Art and practiſe of duell, wherein men ſeeke honour in bloud, and are taught the ambition of being glorious butchers of men? Where had we that luxurious delicacie in our feaſts, in which the noſe is no leſſe pleaſed, then the palate; and the eye no leſſe then either? wherein the piles of diſhes make barricades againſt the appetite, and with a pleaſing encombrance trouble an hungry gueſt? Where thoſe formes of ceremonious quaffing, in which men haue learned to make Gods of others, and beaſts of themſelues; and loſe their reaſon whiles they pretend to doe reaſon? Where the lawleſneſſe (miſ-called freedome) of a wilde tongue, that runs, with reynes in the necke, through the

bed-chambers of Princes, their cloſets, their Counſell-Tables, and ſpares not the very cabinet of their breaſts, much leſſe can bee barr'd out of the moſt retired ſecrecie of inferiour greatneſſe? Where the change of noble attendance, and hoſpitalitie, into foure wheeles, and ſome few butterflies? Where the Art of diſhoneſtie in practicall Machiaueliſme, in falſe equiuocations? Where the ſlight account of that filthineſſe, which is but condemned as veniall, and tolerated as not vnneceſſary? Where the skill of ciuill and honorable hypocriſie, in thoſe formall complements, which doe neither expect beleefe from others, nor carry any from our ſelues? Where that vnnaturall villanie, which though it were burnt with fire and brimſtone from heauen, and the aſhes of it drowned in the dead

ſea, yet hath made ſhift to reuine, and cals for new vengeance vpon the actors? Where that cloſe Atheiſme, which ſecretly laughes God in the face, and thinkes it weakneſſe to beleeue, wiſdome to profeſſe any religion? Where the bloudy and tragicall ſcience of King-killing; the new diuinitie of diſobedience and rebellion; with too many other euils, wherewith forraine conuerſation hath indangered the infection of our peace. Loe here, deare Countrimen, the fruit of your idle gaddings: Better perhaps might bee had; but hee was neuer acquainted at home, that knowes not our nature to bee like vnto fire, which if there bee any infection in the roome, drawes it ſtraight to it ſelfe: Or like vnto 
                     •
                  et, which omitting all precious obiects, gathers vp ſtrawes and duſt. Ilanders haue beene euer in

an ill name. Wherefore? ſaue only for the confluence of forrainers, which neuer come without the fraight of their nationall wickedneſſe. The experience whereof, hath moued ſome witty nations, both ancient and preſent, to ſhut themſelues vp within their owne bounds, and to barre the entercourſe of ſtrangers, as thoſe that thought beſt to content themſelues with their owne faults. A corrupt diſpoſition, out of a naturall fertilitie, can both beget and conceiue euill alone; but if it bee ſeconded by examples, by precepts, by incouragements, the Ocean it ſelfe hath not ſo much ſpawne, as it: In all which regards, he hath eſcaped well, that returnes but what hee carried; but hee is worthy of memorie, that returnes either more good, or leſſe euill. Some haue come home perhaps


more ſparing, others more ſuttle, others more outwardly courteous, others more capricious, ſome more tongue-free, few euer better. And if themſelues bee not ſenſible of their alterations, yet their Country and the Church of God feeles and rues them.
            
            
               Sect. 22.
               Let mee theref
                     •
                  re haue leaue to cloſe this diſcourſe with a double ſute, one to our Gentry; the other to ſupream authority; both which ſhall come from the bottome of an heart vnfainedly ſacrificed to the common good; neither ſpeak I words, but my very ſoule vnto both. To the former my ſuit is, that they would bee happy at home: God hath giuen vs a world of our owne, wherein there is nothing wanting to earthly contentment. Whither goe yee then, worthy Country-men, or what feeke yee? Heere growes that

wealth, which yee go but to ſpend abroad; Heere is that ſweet peace which the reſt of the world admires and enuies: Heere is that gracious and well-tempered gouernment, which no nation vnder heauen may dare once offer to parallell: Here all liberall Arts raigne and triumph: And for pleaſure, either our earth, or our ſea yeelds vs all thoſe dainties, which their natiue Regions enioy but ſingle. Laſtly, heere Heauen ſtands open, which to many other parts is barred on the out-ſide with ignorance or miſ-beleefe. And ſhall our wantonnes contemn all this bounty of God, &amp; carry vs to ſeek that, which we ſhall find no where but behind vs, but within vs? Shall the affectation of ſome friuolous toyes draw vs away from the fruition of thoſe ſolid comforts, which are offred vs within our owne doores? How

many of ours, whom their iuſt offence hath caſt out of the boſome of their country, compare their exile with death, and can ſcarce abide to bid that breath welcome, which they are forced to draw in a forraine aire; and though freedome of conſcience entertaine them neuer ſo liberally abroad, yet reſolue either to liue or die at home; and doe wee ſuffer our folly to baniſh vs from thoſe contentments, which they are glad to redeeme with the hazard of their blood? Are we ſo little in our owne books that wee can bee content to purchaſe out-landiſh ſuperſ
                     •
                  uities with the mis-carriage of our ſoules, with the danger of miſ-carriage, with the likely-hood of danger? Are we ſo fooliſh, that whiles we may ſweetely enjoy the ſettled eſtate of our Primogeniture, wee will needes bring vpon our ſelues

the curſe of Reuben, to run abroad like water; whoſe quality it is, not ea
                     •
                  ily to be kept within the proper bounds? yea the curſe of Cain, to put our ſelues from the 
                     •
                  ide of Eden into the Land of Nod, that is, of demigration? None of the leaſt imprecations, which Dauid makes againſt Gods enemies, is, Make them vnto like a wheele, o Lord: Motion is euer accompanied with vnquietneſſe; and both argues, and cauſes imperfection, whereas the happy eſtate of heauen is deſcribed by reſt; whoſe glorious ſpheres in the meane time, doe ſo perpe
                     •
                  ually moue, that they are neuer remoued from their places. It is not the leaſt part either of wiſdome, or happineſſe, to know when wee are well. Shall we
                     •
                   not be ſhameleſly vnthankfull, if we cannot ſing the note of that great Choriſter of God, My lot is fallen to mee in a good
                  
                  ground? Hath not the munificence of God made this Iland as it were an abridgement of his whole earth, in which he hath contriued (though in a leſſer letter) all the maine and materiall commodities of the greater world, and doe wee make a priſon where God meant a Paradiſe? Enioy therefore (happy Countrimen) enioy freely God and your ſelues; enrich your ſelues with your owne min
                     •
                  s, improue thoſe bleſſed opportunities which God hath giuen you, to your mutuall aduantage; and care not to be like any but your ſelues.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 23.
               And if at any time theſe vnworthy papers may fall betwixt the hands of my Soueraigne Maſter, or any of his graue and honorable miniſters of State, let the meaneneſſe of ſo weake and obſcure ſolicitors preſume to commend this matter to their deepeſt conſideration;

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
and out of an honeſt zeale of the common ſafetie, ſue to them for a more ſtrict reſtraint of that dangerous libertie, whereof too many are bold to carue themſelues. Who can bee ignorant of thoſe wiſe and wholeſome lawes, which are enacted already to this purpoſe? or of thoſe carefull and iuſt cautions, wherewith the licences of Trauell are euer limited? But what are wee the better for Gods owne lawes, without execution? Or what are limits vnto the lawleſſe? Good lawes are the hedges of the Common-wealth: iuſt diſpenſations are as gates, or ſtiles in the hedge. If euery ſtragler may at pleaſure caſt open a gap in this fence of the State, what are we the better for this quickſet, then if wee lay open to the common? Who ſees not how familiarly our young Recuſants, immediately

vpon their diſcloſing, are ſent ouer for their full hatching and making? Italie, Spaine, Artois, and now of late France it ſelfe, prouides neſts, and perches, and mewes for theſe birds, with the ſame confidence, wherewith wee breede our owne at home; which, when they are once well acquainted with the Roman lure, are ſent backe againe, fit for the prey. And as for thoſe of our owne feather: whereas the libertie of their Trauell is bounded chiefly with this double charge; one, that they haue no conuerſation or conference with Ieſuites, or other dangerous perſons; the other, that they paſſe not into the dominions of the Kings enemies; both theſe are ſo 
                     •
                  ommonly neglected, as if they were intended only for a verball formalitie, yea as if the prohibition meant to teach men what they ſhould doe.

Euery of our nouices hath learned to make no difference of men; and dare breathe in the poiſonous aire of Italie it ſelfe, and touch the very pommell of the chaire of peſtilence. It is this licentious freedome (which wee miſ-call open-hearted ingenuitie) that vndoes vs. Doe wee not ſee the wary cloſeneſſe of our Aduerſaries, which will not ſo much as abide one of our books (a mute ſolicitor) to harbour in any of their coaſts? How many of the Italian or Spaniſh Nobleſſe haue wee knowne allowed to venture their education in our Courts or Vniuerſities? Doe they lie thus at the locke, and doe wee open our breaſt, and diſplay our armes, and bid an enemie ſtrike vs where hee liſt? Since then wee haue no more wit, or care, then 
                     •
                  o bee willingly guiltie of our owne ſhame, oh that the hands of ſupreme authoritie

would be pleaſed to locke vs within our owne doores, and to keepe the keyes at their owne girdle. And (to ſpeake truth) to what purpoſe are thoſe ſtrait and capitall inhibitions of the returne of our factious fugitiues into th
                     •
                  s Kingdome, if whiles the wicket is ſhut vpon them, that they ſhould not come to vs, the poſterne be open to vs, that we may goe to them? As all intercourſe is perillous, ſo that is moſt, which is by our owne prouocation. Here yet they dare but lurke in ſecret, and take only ſome ſudden ſnatches at a weake prey, like vnto euening-wolues, that neuer walke forth but vnder the cloake of the night; but in their owne territories, they can ſhew the ſunne their ſpoiles, and thinke this act worthy of garlands and trophees. Here we haue maſtiues to ſecure our flockes: there the

prey goes ſtragling alone to the mouth of their dennes, without protection, without aſſiſtance, and offers to be deuoured. Ye whom the choice of God hath made the great Shepheards of his people, whoſe charge it is to feed them by gouernment, ſuffer not their ſimplicitie to betray their liues vnto the fangs of theſe cruell beaſts; but chaſe them home rather, from the wilfull ſearch of their owne perdition, and ſhut them vp together in your ſtrong and ſpacious folds, that they may be at once ſafe, and yee glorious.
            
            
               
                  Sect. 24.
               Laſtly, for thoſe, whom neceſſary occaſions draw forth of their owne coaſts (that wee may haue done with thoſe, which like fooliſh Papiſts goe on pilgrimage to ſee another blocke better dreſſed then that at home) let mee ſay to them, as Simeon that propheticall

Monke ſaid to the pillers which hee whipped before the Earth-quake, Stand faſt, for yee ſhall be ſhaken. And therefore, as the Crane, when ſhee is to flie againſt an high winde, doth ballace her ſelfe with ſtones in her bill, that ſhee may cut the aire with more ſteddineſſe; ſo let them carefully fore-inſtruct, and poiſe themſelues with the ſound knowledge of the principles of religion, that they may not bee carried about with euery winde of doctrine. Whereto if they adde but thoſe leſſons, which they are taught by the State, in their letters of paſſage, there may be hope, they ſhall bring backe the ſame ſoules they carried. It was at leaſt an inclination to a fall, that Eue tooke boldneſſe to hold chat with the Serpent. And as ſubtill Lawyers deſire no more aduantage in the

quarrell, which they would picke at conueyances, then many words, ſo neither doe our Aduerſaries. Whiles our eares are open, and our tongues free, they will hope well of our very denials. Errour is cra
                     •
                  tie, and out of the power of his Rhetoricall inſinuations, ofttimes carries away probabilitie from truth. I remember in that famous Embaſſie of the three Philoſophers, which Athens ſent to Rome, Critolaus, Diogenes, and Carneades, there falling out many occaſions of diſcourſe, wiſe Cato perſwaded the Senate to a ſpeedie diſmiſſion of thoſe (otherwiſe welcome) gueſts; becauſe (ſaid hee) whiles Carneades diſputes, ſcarce any man can di
                     •
                  cerne which is the truth. There is more danger of theſe ſpirituall Sophiſters, by how much the buſineſſe is more important, and their ſubtiltie greater. Let

our paſſenger therefore (as that wiſe Grecian ſerued his fellowes) ſtop vp his eares with waxe againſt theſe Syrens. Our Sauiour would not giue Satan audience euen whiles hee ſpake true; becauſe hee knew that truth was but to countenance errour. There is euer true corne ſtrowed vnder a pit-fall: thoſe cares are full and weightie, which wee dreſſe with lime to deceiue the poore birds in a ſnow. No fiſher lets downe an emptie hooke, but clothed with a proper and pleaſing bait. Theſe impoſtors haue no other errand, but deceit. If he loue himſelfe, let him bee afraid of their fauours, and thinke their frownes ſafer then their ſmiles. And if at any time (as no flie is more importunate) they thruſt themſelues into his conuerſation, let him (as thoſe which muſt neceſſarily paſſe by a carrion

in the way) hold his breath, and haſten to be out of their aire. And if they yet follow him in his flight, let him turne backe to them with the Angels farewell, Increpet te Dominus.
               
               FINIS.
            
            
         
      
   

