
   
      
         
            King Iames his encomium· Or A poeme, in memorie and commendation of the high and mightie monarch Iames; King of great Britaine. France, and Ireland &amp;c. our late soveraigne, who deceased at Theobalds. vpon Sunday the 27. of March. 1625. By Francis Hamiltoun, of Silvertown-hill
            Hamilton, Francis, of Silvertown-hill.
         
         
            
               1626
            
         
         Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02597
            STC 12726
            ESTC S105969
            99841694
            99841694
            6292
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02597)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6292)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 961:02)
         
         
            
               
                  King Iames his encomium· Or A poeme, in memorie and commendation of the high and mightie monarch Iames; King of great Britaine. France, and Ireland &amp;c. our late soveraigne, who deceased at Theobalds. vpon Sunday the 27. of March. 1625. By Francis Hamiltoun, of Silvertown-hill
                  Hamilton, Francis, of Silvertown-hill.
               
               [8], 16, [8] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Wreittoun,
                  Edinburgh :
                  1626.
               
               
                  In verse; with other works.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Poetry.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-07
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-07
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            KING IAMES his Encomium OR A Poeme, in memorie and commendation of the High and mightie Monarch IAMES; King of great Britaine. France, and Ireland &amp;c. our late Soveraigne, who deceaſed at Theobalds. vpon Sunday the 27. of March. 1625.
            By Francis Hamiltoun, of Silvertown-hill.
            
               
                  Rev. Chap. 14. verſe 13.
               
               Then I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying vnto mee, Write, Bleſſed are the dead, which die in the Lord from hence-foorth: Yea, ſayeth the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works doe follow them.
            
            
               EDINBVRGH, Printed by Iohn Wreittoun. 1626.
         
         
            
            TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.
            
               
                  SON.
               
               VVHether thy chance, or choiſe makes thee to looke,
               (Right reverend Reader) on this Poeme penn'd:
               Accept my firſt eſſay; this litle booke
               Deſpiſe it not: nor ſpare it to amend:
               So ſhall thou thanks receive, and gaine a friend,
               And for thy paines have praiſe, the juſt reward
               Of ſuch as vertue favour, and befriend
               The juſt and good intent. Nor miſregard
               One litle Talent (being rightly vſed
               To vertues praiſe) which ſhall not bring diſgrace
               To the poſſeſſour. Talents ten abuſed
               Makes the abuſer looſe them, and his place.
               One litle Talent with right vſe I crave,
               Rather then Talents ten hid vp to have.
            
            
               SEVEN CROWNE
               SON 
                     •
                  
               
               THE Heathen Poets wh
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               (Blinded with baſtard 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Sung praiſe in Poems, in th
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               To ſuch as they alledg'd ma
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Againſt their foes in field: o
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Proſperitie and peace: falſly 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               To Idols vaine, and Fortun
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Welfare and honour, and th
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               As honey Bees, let Chriſtia
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               The wholeſome honey from 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Nor waſp-like ſucke poyſon the
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Benumde with ſloath, learne their 
                     〈…〉
                  , or Creeds,
               One God wee muſt adore, in perſo
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  ree
               Diſtinguiſh'd: who divided cannot bee.
            
            
               
               SON. 2.
               ONE God wee muſt adore, in perſons three,
               Diſtinguiſh'd: who can never bee divid'd:
               And only he through Chriſt ador'd muſt bee,
               Who Heaven and Earth, and all therein doth guide.
               Litle availes his gifts, where wants his grace,
               His ſaving grace in Chriſt our Soules delyte:
               And thats our ioy, that wee ſhall ſee his face,
               When hee ſhall all his foes with Scepter ſmyte,
               They ſhall all prove as potters ſhards, when hee
               Shall with his Word, the ſword of iuſtice kill,
               And with his powers rodde ſhall cruſhed bee,
               And fry'd in fierie flames for ever ſtill.
               VVho would enjoy Chriſts face muſt fight the field
               'Gainſt ſinne and Satan, and muſt never yeeld.
            
            
               SON. 3.
               WHo would enjoye Chriſts face muſt fight the field
               'Gainſt Sinne and Satan, till their life ſhall end.
               Its horrible Apoſtaſie to yeeld,
               Great glorie through Chriſt Ieſus to contend
               Againſt his foes, the foes of our Salvation;
               And perſecuting Dragon, who was caſt
               From out of Heaven (as Iohn by revelation
               Made knowne to Chriſtians, many yeeres ſince paſt.)
               And beaten backe by Gods moſt mightie word
               In Wilderneſſe, Church pinnacle and mountaine:
               Where Chriſt with his transſcindent two edgd ſword
               Beate Satan backe, of all our ſinnes the fountaine.
               And in the end for ever did confute him:
               And by his death triumphantly refute him.
            
            
               
               SON. 4.
               CHriſt in the end for ever did confute him
               By his owne death: and did in triumph riſe
               Aſcending to the Heaven, with Saints about him
               For to prepare a place for his, and priſe.
               Avoyde thou ſubtle Satan, ſince o'recome?
               But doeſt thou ſtill aſſault vntill the end:
               Although thou knoweſt that Chriſt defrayed the ſumme
               Of Gods Decalogue, and doth his Saints defend:
               Which though hee knowes, yet ſtrives hee to moleſt.
               Chriſts litle ones, the apple of his eye:
               And ſtill doth tempt, illude, delude, ſuggeſt
               Sinne vpon ſinne, yet would ſeeme friend to bee.
               Behold our Captane Chriſt ſhall him confound
               So much the more in paines of Hell profound.
            
            
               SON. 5.
               BEhold our Captaine Chriſt ſhall him confound,
               So much the more as he himſelf advanceth
               Gainſt him, and His: for at the trumpets ſound
               (Whilſt Chriſt in Heaven his holy Saints inhaunceth)
               Hee ſhall repaye his ſpightfull plotted treaſon
               To the leaſt farthing: and the wicked ſhall
               (Whom hee ſeduced hath againſt all reaſon)
               Grye hilles and mountaines, come, vpon vs fall:
               Then with that meaſure, which the damn'd hath mette
               To Chriſts deare Saints, they ſhall receive the dowble:
               Then ſhall Hells pitt bee ſhut, and Hells darke nette
               Shall hold for ay ſuch as Chriſts Saints did trouble.
               Then yowling, mourning, woe and lamentation,
               Shall ſeaſe on Satan, and the Damned nation.
            
            
               
               SON. 6.
               THen yowling, mourning, woe and lamentation,
               Shall ſeaſe on Satan in full ſtrength and meaſure;
               And on the falling Angells, and that Nation
               Of damned Div'liſh reprobates: whoſe treaſure,
               Shall bee the fire of Hell, which goeth not out,
               And gnawing worme of Conſcience never dying,
               Of Gods great wrath, the mightie thunder-bolt
               Shall pierce them through and through; from which no flying.
               Go howle and weepe, the day doth now approach,
               Wherein the coales of fire, which you did heape
               On your owne heads, theſe ſinnes which you did broach,
               Shall make you gnaſh your teeth, lament and weepe.
               Then ſhall they ſay, are thoſe Chriſts holy Saintes,
               Whom wee ſo oft haue vexed with our vaunts.
            
            
               SON. 7.
               THen ſhall they ſay, are thoſe Chriſts ſaved Saints?
               Whom we eſteem'd the off ſcowrings of Earth:
               'Gainſt whom ſo oft wee gloried of our tants;
               Eſteeming them not worthy mortall breath.
               Take pittie on your ſelves, yee wicked men,
               And ſtrive yet if yee can to enter in
               In the right way to Heaven, leaſt yee as then
               Debarred bee for your omiſſions ſinne.
               Let elect Saints in trembling, love, and feare,
               In faith and true repentance watch and pray:
               Praiſe God in zeale, in wiſedome perſevere
               Vntill the end, attending on that Day;
               That Day wherein God ſhall make even our ods,
               And Heathen Poets damne with fained Gods.
            
         
         
            
            THE EPISTLE DEDICATORIE.
            To all true Chriſtians, to my Countrey of Great Britaine, my native Soyle of Scotland, and to that famous, and woorthie Towne of EDINBVRGH.
            
            And eſpecially to the two magnanimous, and worthie Lords, IAMES Marqueſſe of Hamiltoun, &amp;c.
            And GEORGE Lord Chancelour of SCOTLAND.
            
            MAgnanimous Lords with duetifull respects
            This Pilgrims Poëme, FRANCK to you directs,
            Wiſhing your Lordſhips daigne to patronize it,
            What FRANCK affoords, let favour infranchize it.
            My loyall love (though I bee much deſtreſſed)
            From praiſing Vertue ſhould not bee ſuppreſſed,
            And how much more in Kings its eminent,
            So much the more to praiſe it ſhould bee bent,
            Each generous genius. Since (conjectures paſt)
            True tacticke practicke teacheth vs at laſt,
            That IAMES the Iuſt hath both begunne and ended,
            In mercie, peace, and grace now much commended,
            And ſince ſo oft inſtalled on a Throne,
            His happie Head was honoured with a Crowne,
            
               Till that nor Crownes, nor Kingdomes to him given
            Could keepe his Soule on Earth now crownd in Heaven,
            Who having left of his owne royall race
            A royall, loyall Prince to fill his place.
            (And having him in Chriſtian Schooles vptrained,
            Till hee true vertue, and Religion gained,
            So that in tender age hee did ſurmount
            All Chriſtian Princes in the beſt account)
            In Peace and true Religion hath layd downe,
            Three Swords, three Scepters, and a triple Crowne.
            Shall hee ſo much was praiſed whilſt hee lived
            For vertue loved; and who ſo much was grieved
            At vyces of this age, now beeing gone,
            Bequeath his vertues to oblivion?
            No; ſince both rich and poore ſo well were pleaſed,
            His memorie must needs bee eternized.
            My Muſe muſt praiſe ſuch vertues as did dwell
            Within his Soule, (which made him ſo excell)
            Which wee muſt imitate, and alwayes ſtrive
            Wiſely to vſe our Talents (whilſt wee live)
            By his example, who defunct, doth reſt
            In Heaven with him, in whom he put his truſt.
            The vertues of the living, men ſhould praiſe,
            That more and more wee may true vertue raiſe:
            Till like the graine of muſtard-ſeed it grow,
            And all the World aboundantly ore-flow:
            True vertues praiſe I heartlie doe intend,
            Till that my breath, and mortall life ſhall end:
            And ſo much more to praiſe it ſhall bee bent,
            As I doe finde it true and eminent.
            
               
                  Your L. loving Friend to bee commanded in all Chriſtian dueties Fr. Hamiltoun.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the right magnanimous and worthie Lord, IAMES, Marqueſſe of Hamiltoun, &amp;c,
            
            
               SON.
               HEroicke Hamlton, FRANCK to thee affoordeth,
               With heartlie Love the praiſe of IAMES his worth
               Our King defunct, and ſince my ſoule concordeth
               With CHARLES his vertuous valoure, I ſend forth
               My hearts deſire in prayer to my God,
               That hee our Soveraigne CHARLES may ſtill defend
               In Chriſts Religion: ſo that his abode,
               May in beginning, in the midſt, and end
               Bee alwayes, and for ever with our Lord,
               And Saviour ioynd, by holy inſpiration
               Of Gods good ſpirit, ſo that hee not debord,
               From the right way, which hath to Heaven relation:
               But that in him his grace aboundantlie,
               With the right vſe, and increſſe hee ſupplie.
            
            
               
                  Your L. loving friend and kinſman to honour and ſerve your L. Fr. Hamiltoun.
            
         
         
            To the right magnanimous and worthie Lord, Sir George Hay, of Kilfawnes Knight, Lord Chancelour of Scotland.
            HEroicke HAY, I know nothing ſo ſtrong,
            As bands of Loue which vertue hath conbind:
            And if I ſhould not vertue praiſe, I wrong
            My ſelfe more than I wrong true vertues friend:
            That I may neither wrong I doe intend
            To praiſe and love the vertuous: dead, or living,
            King IAMES and CHARLES our King, I muſt commend:
            King IAMES in Heaven: King CHARLES for it ſtriving.
            Magnanimous Lord even you, and I, and all
            Muſt ſtrive for Heaven, and whilſt wee breath, muſt fight
            Gainſt ſinne and Satan: leaſt wee catch a fall
            From Heaven to Hell, and ſo may loſe our right.
            Chriſts coloures now are flying in the field,
            And woe to ſuch as ſhall to Satan yeeld.
            
               
                  Your L. loving friend to honour and ſerve your L. Fr. Hamiltoun.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            KING IAMES his Encomium,
            
               
                  FRom Earth to Heauen, our Soveraigne Iames departs.
               Raviſh'd to Ioy, who raviſhed the hearts
               Of mortall men, by vertue, and is gone
               From death, to life, that ſuch may follow on
               By his example, to our Soveraigne Lord,
               Of Heauen, and Earth: who mercie doeth afford,
               To Penitents: who of their ſinnes thinke ſhame:
               Baptiſed, and belieuing in the Name
               Of God the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt,
               Of whom, not one, for ever, ſhall be loſt.
               Should not our heauenly Soveraigne Saviour,
               Who ſent vs ſuch a King, in bleſſed houre:
               As Lanterne light, to lead vs, and to leaue,
               His Sonne a burning Lampe, by him to giue
               All Chriſtians cauſe of Courage which are true,
               'gainſt Atheſts, Papiſts, Machiavellian crue?
               Should he not praiſed be, aye more and more,
               Calling our King to his Eternall ſtore
               Of heauenly glorie, perfect Ioy and Love,
               Making him raigne for aye with him above:
               Hath left vs yet a Lawfull Loyall King,
               Such one, as from his Royall Loines did ſpring.
               Whill as we doe reduce to meditation,
               How none was like King Iames in any Nation
               In all his time, nor any knowne to bee
               So learn'd, Religious, wiſe a King as hee.
               
                  Whoſe Grace was graue, whoſe words were wiſe, and few,
               Whoſe lookes were louelie, mercifull, and true:
               Whoſe viſage ſage, heart humble, meeke of mind:
               Bountie, and vertues beautie, there combin'd.
               Whoſe body Chaſte, with cheerfull Countenance,
               Whoſe bleſſed breaſt wiſe counſells did diſpence:
               By truſty tongue of honoured head, inditing,
               What well became a Royall pen in writing.
               Whoſe potent Poems, (wing'd with puiſſant ſpeed)
               From a coeleſtiall temper did proceed.
               Writing of warres, or of a civill Storie.
               Affected truth, deſpiſed mortall glorie.
               Parent of Peace, of potent Poets Prince,
               Religious, Royall, and Renown'd defence
               Of faithfull Chriſtians, gainſt the Romiſh Whoore,
               In thought, word, deed, like Campe, or Caſtle ſure.
               Could all the world ſuch Phoenix King affoord?
               Such Royall, Loyall, Learn'd, Religious Lord?
               No: Nor ſhould I degener from my kind,
               And ſo refraine to praiſe a vertuous mind.
               Heroicke Hampton prais'd a forraine King,
               For loue of Vertue which in him did ſpring:
               Miſ-conſtrued: and rewarded with a cuffe,
               Was made to change his ſoyle for's counter-buffe.
               And worthy Wallas was content to part,
               For loue of King and Countrey, from his heart.
               Shall I deduce my pedegree from ſuch,
               And not befriend true vertue even as much
               In the defunct, or living? however it goe,
               By grace of God it was, is, ſhall be ſo:
               That I true vertue praiſe, extoll, and loue,
               (In thought, word, deed) which comes from heaven aboue,
               
                  According to my power, and skill, till death:
               My will ſhall be as fervent whilſt I breath.
               And what's nor to my power, nor skill permit,
               My God (of mercie) will diſpenſe with it:
               And by his grace (of loue) he giveth me,
               In and through Chriſt, my will he'ill rectifie:
               Which ſinfull nature alwayes would pervert,
               Wer't not my God, by grace, reformes mine heart.
               I paſſe not what ſome perverſe people ſay;
               Nor mumbling Momus ſhall my pen affray:
               Nor who ſo luſt to jeaſt, to mock or ſcorne me,
               Or ſeeke by fraud, or falſhood to forlorne me,
               By poyſon, or by powder-plotted-treaſon,
               Or fairded faire pretences, bent gainſt reaſon.
               I tell them all, That Chriſt my Lord and Maſter,
               Can well avenge his little ones diſaſtre.
               And that it better were for them to bee
               Bound to a Mill-ſtone, and caſt in the ſea.
               Then to injure, or doe malicious-wrong
               Vnto the leaſt which doe to Chriſt belong.
               Except they doe repent, amend and find
               Faith, true repentance, loue, and zealous mind.
               O if Chriſts litle ones were knowne to bee
               By worldlings, as the aple of his eye.
               Durſt they injure, moleſt, wrong, or offend
               The leaſt of thoſe that on the Lord depend.
               All is not gold that gliſters, nor all good
               Which masked is with goods Similitude.
               Behold the end, ſo may you learne to know
               How good it is to walke in God his law.
               Could any King (ſince yet the world began)
               Haue ſayd as bleſſed IAMES, who in Britaine Rang
               
                  In true Religion, fiftie yeeres and eight
               A crowned King, a Magazine well fraught:
               Sent from the Heauen to propagate true peace,
               All where through his Dominions, but releaſe.
               The holie Spirit his Comforter did ſtand,
               Guarding his Soule, with his almightie hand,
               And now when Sinne and Satan made aſſault:
               The ſhield of Faith in Chriſt, fred his default.
               And quench'd thoſe fierie darts with ſacred blood,
               Which Chriſt for Iames had ſhed vpon the Rood.
               His counting booke of Conſcience did occurre,
               For to controule his Faith, and barre the doore
               (Or gates of Heauen) for his ſinfull tranſgreſſion,
               But hee, by true repentance, and confeſſion,
               (Through faith in Chriſt) to God: by's mercies looke
               Had all his ſinnes ſcrapt out of Conſcience booke.
               Vpon his head, the helmet of Salvation,
               Vpon his breaſt (to ſave him from damnation)
               The breaſtplate of true righteouſneſſe, through faith
               In Chriſt his Saviour, who him ſav'de from wrath,
               And did the joyes of Heaven for him procure,
               Giving him Faiths true ſhield: to make him ſure,
               His loynes hee girt with Trueth: his feete hee ſhod
               With Peace-preparing Goſpell of our God,
               Watching and praying, in his Spirit, aſſuring
               His Soule by perſeverance, and enduring
               Till his laſt breath: Who thus and thus could ſay,
               Death can diſſolve this Manſion houſe of clay,
               But gainſt my Faith, my love, my hope, my zeale,
               To kill my Soule: there can no death prevaile.
               I know my ſinnes are great, and that they might
               Iuſtlie bring on an everlaſting Night
               
                  Vpon my Soule: but my Redeemer liveth:
               My God, my Lord, who all my ſinnes forgiveth,
               And mee releives from all ſuch helliſh paine,
               As would my Soule and bodie aye haue ſlaine.
               Chriſt was my comfort, now is, and ſhall bee
               My All in All, in his Aeternitie:
               My faith is firme, and in Religion right,
               My hope in him, through his owne mercies might.
               Who hath directed, and protected mee,
               In the right way of true fidelitie.
               So calling for the bleſſed Bread and Wine,
               (Externall ſignes of myſteries divine,
               The Sacramentall ſeales of his Salvation,
               And tokens given of true juſtification:
               Making true mention of our Saviours death,
               And how hee hath his Saints redeemde from wrath)
               Hee them receives, vpon the ſelfe-ſame day,
               Wherein hee firſt did Englands Scepter ſway,
               The third day after that hee had received
               The Sacrament, which hee ſincerely craved,
               The twentie ſixt of March, beeing Saturday,
               Yet the Iewes Sabbath, who did Chriſt betray:
               A day for reſt ordaind at the Creation,
               That therein God ſhould haue by everie Nation
               Adored beene, according to the rites
               Contained in the ancient holie writes:
               And kept till Chriſt did from the dead ariſe,
               To gaine to all his Saints heavens glorious Priſe:
               Which day the Iewes (while as from Chriſt they ſwerve)
               Doe keepe as holy, for they ſo deſerve,
               For crucifying of the Lord of glorie,
               Renouncing Ieſus Chriſt, and's ſacred ſtorie.
               
                  Of ſaving grace) who doth Salvation giue
               To all baptiſed who in him belieue.
               The noon-tide of this Iewiſh Sabbath paſt,
               About two houres, King Iames loſt ſpeech at laſt.
               After that hee his Princely ſonne reſolued
               And often kiſſ'd, longing to be diſſolved.
               And though approching Death did him aſſaile.
               So that his ſpeech had now begun to faile.
               Yet whilſt they read, or pray (as Chriſt commands)
               He lifting up his eyes, his armes, his hands,
               Gaue cleare conſent: and what hee could not ſpeake,
               His ſighing Soule did from Chriſt Ieſus ſeeke.
               The twenty ſixt of March (Saturday) gone,
               The Iewiſh Sabbath chang'd for this reaſon,
               Our Saviour roſe, having made ſatisfaction
               To God his juſtice for all ſinfull action
               Of all his Elect, in thought, vvord, and deed:
               And for all ſinne originall did proceed
               From our preceeding parents whoſoever,
               From Adam, Eue, and from them all together,
               Triumphing over Satan, Sinne, Death, Hell.
               That hee and his in heaven might ever dwell.
               On the firſt day, as then was, of the weeke,
               Before that Mary Magdalen did ſeeke
               The Tombe of Chriſt, wherein hee was interred,
               Calling him for the Gardner, (having erred)
               Which day all Chriſtians doe our Lords day call,
               Religiouſly obſerving it, withall
               Sinceritie, mov'd by the good example
               Of the Apoſtles, preaching in the temple:
               And by the warrant of Gods word, in writ,
               Saint Iohn being raviſh'd in his ſpirit on it.
               
                  Heard a great voyce, as of a trumpet ſound,
               Which Alpha and Omega did reſound:
               Commanding him to write within a booke
               What he did ſee, (that they thereon might looke)
               And ſend it to the Churches ſeven, which were
               In Aſia: Epheſſe, Smyrne, Pergame, Thyatire:
                  
                     Rev. 1.10.11.
               
               To Sardis, Philadelphia, Laodicea,
               
               Where now the Turke reignes, cruelties Idea.
               
               Even on that day Chriſt Ieſus did ariſe
               From death, to gaine heavens glory for a priſe,
               To him, and all his Elect, through his merit,
               On that Lords day, King IAMES did heaven inherit.
               The Holy One in perſons three diſtinguiſh'd,
               One God, and indiviſible extinguiſh'd
               His mortall life, and life immortall gaue him,
               And did in new Ieruſalem receiue him.
               The three times nint, or nine times third of March,
               The twenty ſeventh, King Iames his ſoule did marche
               Amongſt thoſe Angels, and thoſe Saints of God,
               Which haue with our Redeemer their abode.
               The thouſand yeare, ſix hundred twenty fiue,
               Since our ſole Saviour tooke on mortall life,
               Immortall life prevailing over breath,
               Made him triumph over ſinne, ſhame, hell and death.
               O is hee gone? and ſhall we not bedew
               His Tombe with teares, did peace and loue renew,
               So oft? Shall he for ſuch rare vertues ſake
               As rang in him (which many Chriſtians lacke)
               Forgotten be? No, till this world ſhall end,
               Our pennes and poems ſhall King Iames commend.
               And were it not that heavens did ſo decree,
               Our prayers yet had ſtayd Deaths deſtinie.
               
                  But that his maker would ſuch Soule embrace,
               As lov'd and long'd to ſee his Sauiours face.
               To render thankes, and euerlaſting praiſe,
               Alwayes to him who did through Chriſt him raiſe,
               Vnto ſuch Glory as he ſhall adore,
               And never ceaſe to praiſe the Lord therefore.
            
            
               We waile not KING IAMES Nor need we him lament,
               Whoſe Soule in Heauen, before his oyle was ſpent,
               Whoſe Lampe, gaue Light, and Lanterne like did lead,
               By his example, rightly to proceed:
               Both Kings, and Kaeſars, Monarches of the Earth,
               Princes, and Peares, as well in life as death.
               We waile not KING IAMES who for the heauenly Ioyes,
               Hath left to dally with all earthly Toyes.
               We wail not KING IAMES whoſe Ioye ſurmounteth more
               Now in one houre, then all his dayes before.
               We wail not KING IAMES Great Britains Iewell faire,
               Thriſe Crowned King, 'mongſt Kings a Phoenix rare.
               We wail not KING IAMES who rendered to his race,
               Three Kingdomes Crownes, t'enjoy in heauen his place.
               We wail not KING IAMES whoſe potent pen refuted
               The Foes of Chriſt, and hath them much rebuted.
               We wail not KING IAMES who writ thoſe thornie cares,
               Which Crownes and Scepters, in their compaſſe beares.
               We wail not KING IAMES who Myſteries vnfolded,
               Which Iohn in Pathmos Ile, in trance beholded.
               We wail not KING IAMES whoſe Daemoniacke ſtorie,
               Diſcovered many vices, and vaine Glorie.
               We wail not KING IAMES nor need we to deplore one,
               Who did afford ſuch a Baſilike Doron.
               
               
                  Wee waile not KING IAMES, who learn'dly did rehearſe,
               King Davids Pſalmes in his owne royall verſe
               We wail not KING IAMES, whoſe Name, whoſe Fame, whoſe worth,
               Is more and more by learned men ſet foorth,
               Ev'n Vorſtius, and the Cardinalls record,
               King IAMES a Learned, and Religious Lord.
               Wee waile our want of ſuch a worthie King,
               Yet more wee joye, ſince hee in Heaven doth reigne.
               Whoſe Corps though now interred in the duſt,
               Shall riſe with Iacobs, and with Iobs the juſt.
               Nor neede wee curſe ſuch mountaines as Gilboah,
               
               Nor waile ſuch waters, as our Father Noah.
               
               Nor neede wee waile private or publicke crime
               Wrought in our native Soyle at any time.
               Nor valleyes vaunting monſtruous-marching might,
               Of forraine foes, or homebred houſhold ſpight:
               Nor thundring Cannons, nor the Trumpets ſound,
               Nor Turkiſh ſpyte, which elſe where doth abound.
               Nor Papiſts plots, with Powder-plotted treaſon,
               Prepared 'gainſt him, and his, againſt all reaſon.
               Nor Spaniſh-Papiſt policies diſguiſed,
               Deliberat, and long before adviſed,
               Which masked with the ſhew of friendly love,
               Like craftie Serpent, cunninglie to move:
               And ſo to lurke amidſt brave Britaines bowres,
               Croſſing our Gardens, tripping in our Towres:
               Into our pleaſant Palaces approching,
               And on our lives, Lands, Liberties enchroching,
               Accuſing and accrochjng, and ſeducing,
               Our Nobles, and our commountie abuſing
               With Gundomerian-Gunnes to make vs g
                     •
                  ne,
               And loſe our lives, before wee ſee our want,
               
                  Our God, and Saviour, did ſuch things prevent,
               And to ſuch Parent of our peace hath ſent,
               In peace a Meſſenger to take Iames breath,
               His Generall-muſter-maſter mortall Death:
               Bounding Deaths limits, that hee no more could,
               But bring to duſt (of duſt) his earthly mould.
               Maugre the Hells: no ſecond Death, nor terrour
               Durſt ſeaſe on him, nor no affrighting horrour,
               Durſt ſo attempt his breaſt, as for to Iudge
               In his heroicke Heart one faithleſſe grudge.
               Firme was his Faith, and franck his forttiude,
               Through and in Chriſt, who for him ſhed his blood.
               For Adams and for Eva's curious luſt,
               By Gods decree; duſt muſt returne to duſt,
               Firſt Adam through his fall damnation brought,
               
                  Chriſt ſecond Adam our Salvation wrought,
               Spoyler of Death, more than Methuſalem,
               
               No Babell Builder, but Ieruſalem,
               
               
                  Ieruſalem the New, prepar'd of God,
               Where Saints amongſt his Angells haue abode,
               Through Ieſus Chriſt: By whom Iames juſtified,
               Heere a crown'd King: hence a King glorified.
               Whilſt heere hee range, hee juſtice did affect,
               Truth, Love, and Peace: hee much more did reſpect
               Religion, right and reaſon, Chaſtitie:
               Than any King on Earth, with clemencie:
               Nor Glorie vaine, nor greed, nor golde, nor gaine
               Gould make him from the hope of heaven refraine:
               Nor truſt in treaſure, which Earth could afford:
               For why his truſt was in the living Lord.
               King Iames, thy blames are buried and forgot:
               Thy Faith, Fame, Name, claime Crowne without a ſpot.
               
                  Now bleſſed Iacob, reſt in Heaven, and ſing,
               The everlaſting praiſe of Chriſt thy King:
               The King of Kings, thy God, the Lord of Hoſtes,
               Was, is, and ſhall bee: to whom the Worlds coaſtes
               Subjected are? Didſt thou the Scriptures quote
               To praiſe thy God? didſt thou thy pen devote:
               Loe many pens of vertuous men expreſſe
               Thy worthie parts; thy praiſe for to increſſe?
               Waſt thou of modeſt mind, of bodie chaſte,
               Religious, learn'd: thou joy'ſt the intereſt.
               Thy Clemencie, thy bountie and thy Love:
               And ſuch true vertues, ſent thee from above:
               Returne to thee much more aboundantly
               Good Name, good Fame, ſince vertue can not dye.
               Thy pleaſant Poems, learned, and profound,
               Shall till the World have end, thy worth reſounds
               And counter-check ſuch ignorant prophaine,
               As Cuckooe-glorious mocke the inſpyred vaine
               Of Chriſtian Poets: who in ſacred verſe,
               The praiſe of Chriſt, and of his Church rehearſe.
               Thoſe learned workes, which from thee did proceede,
               Such ignorants vaineglorie ſhall deride:
               As jeaſt at learning, and eſteeme it folly
               To bee train'd vp in Chriſtian Schooles moſt holy:
               And ſhall move others alſo to deplore
               This vitious Age: And praiſe God evermore:
               Who as hee gave the Kingdomes, Scepters, Crownes,
               So gave hee wiſdome, which thee now renownes.
               Thoſe earthly things too litle for thy minde:
               Hee gave, then tooke, when hee had thee refinde,
               And in exchange a Crowne of glorie gave thee,
               And did in Heaven for evermore receive thee,
               
                  That thou to him mightſt ſing that ſacred Song,
               Which doth Gods Angells, and Chriſts Saints belong
               Right faithfull Stewart, Kings may learne by thee,
               To ſerve their God, while as they Stewarts bee
               Heere of alitle: with the Virgins wiſe,
               Attending on their Maſter, and their priſe:
               With burning Lamps, till that they heare the call
               Of their Bride-groome, and with him enter all
               In Heaven, that they may Crownes receive, makes ſure
               In joye and glorie, ever to endure.
            
            
               O Potent Patron, of all vertues true,
               Who didſt for thine, Sinne, Hell and Death ſubdue,
               Lord Ieſus Chriſt, God-Man: my Saviour ſweet,
               Inſpire mee with the wiſedome of thy Spirit:
               That I with Faith and zeale, may thinke, ſpeake, write,
               With wiſedome worke, and with diſcretion dite
               Thy praiſe and glorie, for thy gifts ſo good,
               Which thou to thine haſt giv'n, through thine owne Blood.
               And for? (ſince it hath pleaſed thee to call,
               King Iames to Heaven) thou Charles makeſt to all
               True Chriſtian ſubjects, a true Patron bee,
               A Father, and a friend to pietie,
               To vertues valour, and to right and reaſon,
               A friend to peace of conſcience: foe to treaſon
               Committed againſt Chriſt, and's ſacred Saints,
               By men, which of their ſinnes and vices vaunts.
               O wee vnwoorthie juſtly did deſerve,
               That thou hadſt ſent a King, to make vs ſwerve
               From true Religion! but thou didſt prevent,
               Our miſcrie with mercie, and haſt ſent
               
                  A Royall, Loyall, Learn'd, Religious Prince,
               Magnanimous, and mightie for defence
               Of all true Chriſtians: Whom good God decore
               With wiſedome, that in zeale he thee adore,
               In Loue, Faith, Feare, Obedience to thy will,
               Aye more and more, till he thy will fulfill.
               Wee did deſerve, and did by ſinne procure,
               That thou ſhouldſt not haue ſuffred to endure:
               That Royall race of faithfull Stewarts line,
               For that wee did ſo oft 'gainſt thee repine.
               If for our ſinnes thou hadſt cut with the ſtocke,
               The ſeede and ſiplings and madeſt vs a mocke
               To all the World; Yet wee much more deſerved,
               Who by our ſinfull luſts, ſo oft haue ſwerved,
               From the obedience of thy Law, and will,
               Our fleſhly ſinfull pleaſures to fulfill.
               And but thy mercie is ſo eminent,
               All perills of thy people to prevent,
               Wee had beene made a prey to everie Nation,
               For our contempt, and for our provocation.
               For our contempt of thy moſt ſacred Word,
               Provoking thee to wrath, long-ſuffering Lord.
               Infinite thou; not willing to contend
               'Gainſt fleſh infirme: didſt grace and mercie ſend
               Through Ieſus Chriſt, in whom wee are well eaſed,
               Through whom, with vs thou canſt not bee diſpleaſed.
               Aeternall trueth, who gaveſt to Iames to bee,
               Royall on Earth, Religious towards thee,
               Extend thy bleſſings vnto his ſucceſſion,
               Doe not repell our earneſt interceſſion
               O Lord our God: That ſo wee may ſing praiſe,
               Aye more and more to thee, who did him raiſe.
               
                  Now neede we pray no more for Iames, ſince gone:
               Exempt from prayer; and exempt from mone.
               Direct our hearts therefore to praiſe thee for him,
               And pray that in King Charles thou doe reſtore him.
               Reſtore him in ſuch vertues, and ſuch grace,
               
                  Eliſha-like in good Eliah's place,
               With double portion of thy holy Spirit,
               Confirming Faith, conferring grace to vnite
               His whole affection, both of ſoule and heart
               Rightly to thee, ſo that they never part.
               Make the good motions of thy Spirite him guide,
               Supreame Eſſence; who can not bee divide.
               Thy wings bee his protection, grace, and power,
               In the aſſalt of all temptations houre.
               And if his ſinnes (which God forbid) become
               Notorious blacke, or thicke, or darke, or dimme,
               Or like ſuch clowdes, as doth the Sunne obſcure,
               Diſſolve them Lord, and let not them endure.
               King of all Kings; ſo make thy mercies ſhine,
               In, through, and by Chriſt, that he knowe hee is thine:
               So that hee doe repent, returne, amend,
               In wiſedome, love, faith, zeale till life ſhall end.
               New gifts, new graces daylie to him grant,
               In ſuch aboundance, ſo that hee nought want.
               Increſſe in him what's good; and take away
               All ſinne which may his ſoule ſeduce, or ſlay.
               Moſt mighty Lord from throne of mercies grace,
               Exempt him not; ſo that thou hyde thy Face.
               Stand by him Lord, and ſave him from ſuch errour
               Of mind, as may procure his conſcience terrour.
               From damn'd defection, and from all diſgrace,
               Good Lord deliver Charles, in each caſe.
               
                  Remember not his ſinnes: but pardon give,
               Exalt him by thy grace, and him relieve
               From danger of all foes 'gainſt him repine,
               Who would him trap in traines which they propine.
               Bee his defence againſt all ſtormes, and charmes:
               Remember Lord to keepe him in thine armes,
               From all aſſalts bee thou his ſtrong refuge,
               Save him from all temptations, and from grudge.
               Grant Lord he cauſe amend what is amiſſe
               In all his Kingdomes; ſo that thou doe bleſſe
               Both him, and them; and all to him belong.
               Maintaine vs: and avenge vs of foes wrong,
               Except they doe repent, amend, returne;
               And ſo leave off to make thy Saints to mourne.
               The royall reigne of Charles wee recommend
               To thee O Lord of Hoſtes: O Lord defend,
               In right Religion; his royall Realmes all,
               His ſubject Princes, Nobles great and ſmall.
               His forraine Friends, and favorits reward,
               And vnto all pertaine him, bee a guard.
               His generous Gentles, bleſſe thou whoſoever,
               His loyall ſubjects, that they not ſwerve, nor ſever.
               Prevent him, and all his from Heaven above,
               With ſaving grace, with mercie peace and love.
               In all temptations houre muſt come to try
               (Thy Saints on Earth, who doe on thee rely.)
               O let not foes prevaile gainſt thee, nor Atheiſts,
               Nor none of their owne merite-vaunting Papiſts,
               Robbing the Lord of Love, and life his glorie:
               With Soule-ficke-fairded fictions making ſorie,
               Praying, and cauſing others for to pray,
               In tongues vnknowne not knowing what they ſay:
               
                  Suffer not foes, ſinne, Satan, ſo t'aſſalt,
               That thine from thee or ſlide, or fall, or halt:
               From feare or force of forraine foes or plots,
               Preſerve King Charles and his from all their ſhots.
               And from their craftie carriage, which is knowne,
               Now to bee like to bladders, which are blowne.
               Conſpyring 'gainſt our King, and Countries good,
               Exulting when by errours they illude.
               Abuſing ſacred Name, calde Ieſuites,
               
               Who rather ought to bee calde Gibeonites.
               
               Deluding men with worſe than rotten bread,
               In ſtead of ſuch as Soules, and bodies feed.
               Reſpecting the proud Pope, and his curſt traine,
               More than Chriſts glorie: which they doe reſtraine,
               Whilſt craftelie they derogate from Chriſt,
               And arrogate vnto their perverſe Prieſt.
            
            
               Diſtich.
               King Charles takes vp, what did King Iames lay downe,
               Three Swords, three Scepters, and a triple Crowne.
            
            
               
                  
                     On King Iames the defunct dead to ſinne and living for ever to righteouſneſſe.
                  
                  
                     On the liuing King Charles, dying to ſinne, living and to live
                  
                  
                     for ever to righteouſneſſe.
                  
                  
                     On the perverſe Pope living to ſinne, dying and to dye for ever
                  
                  
                     to righteouſneſſe, except he repent and convert to the Trueth.
                  
               
            
            Francis Hamiltoun his firſt Eſſay. Feb. 7. 1626.
            ⁂
         
         
            
            
               A Poeticall Ecphraſe and Paraphraſe on the 13 verſe of the 14 chapter of S. Iohns Revelation
               SAying to me from Heaven a voice hear I,
               Write, Bleſt are they, which in the Lord doe die
               From hence foorth: yea, the Sprit ſayes, for they reſt
               Them from their labours, and their workes (whilſt bleſt)
               Doe follow them: * — (even their reward is ſuch
               According to their workes, litle or much.)
               Not for their workes, for they doe much debord
               From the commands, and will of Christ our Lord:
               Although good workes from his good Sprit proceed,
               And as from him are perfect workes indeed:
               Yet in all mortall men by ſinfull nature,
               Are more or leſſe infect'd with ſinnes foule feature:
               And as in ſinfull man they cannot merite,
               That man the ioyes of Heaven for aye inherite.
               Through faith in Chriſt, our Saviour God and Man
               Heavens ioyes we gaine, which Chriſt vnto vs wan.
               Yet must we have good workes, as fruit which ſhow,
               The goodneſſe of the tree whereon they grow,
               Leaſt wee bee lyke to fruitleſſe trees; which cut
               Are caſt in fyre: For to each tree its roote
               The axe is layd, and if they bring not foorth
               Good fruit, they are cut downe as nothing woorth.
               But to be caſt in hell amongſt the Divels,
               The Authors; and ſuggeſters of our evils.
            
            
               The triumph of every true Chriſtian defunct.
               O death where is thy ſting,
               O grave where is thy victorie, now ſhaw:
               O all your ſtrength through ſinne was in Gods Law,
               Which Chriſt fulfil'd: (My King.)
               Through faith which Chriſt inſpired by his Sprit,
               I now with him doe reſt,
               And ſhall aye praiſe my God and Saviour ſweet,
               No more with ſinne oppreſt.
            
            
               
               Song to the comfort of every true Chriſtian.
               BLyth may he be, though his death doe arreſt him,
               Hath his ſinnes daſh'd out of the bookes of accounting.
               Blyth may he be, though his friends haue oppreſt him,
               Finds by true faith, true ſpirituall ioyes ſurmounting.
               Earthly things, though prompt in pomp, like to flowres are fading,
               When the Arch-Angell ſoundeth his Trumpe, no time for diſſuading.
               Death when paſt, brings at laſt, either ioy or ſorrow,
               Then reſpect, doth neglect, one moment to morrow.
            
            
               Time then is gone, and no more can returne,
               Time can no more as then deiect nor advaunce thee.
               Heaven or in Hell, man muſt dwell, ioy or mourne,
               Even as a tree cut downe to dye, ſhall thy death inhaunce thee.
               Chaunce and Fortune haue no place: God for all provideth,
               Sinfull life, or mercies grace, makes what man betideth.
               Life or death, after breath, from which is no returning,
               God doth guide, and provide, mirth for thoſe are mourning.
            
            
               If thou to day, heare his voyce who doth ſays,
               Better now thou weepe for ſinne, nor to laugh for pleaſure:
               Baniſh therefore away, all ſhifts of delay,
               Turne, repent thee with teares, to be kept in his treaſure:
               Mind'ſt thou to haue, knock, ſeeke, and craue, for the time is ſliding,
               Knock, he wil open: ſeek, thou ſhalt find; aske whiles thy Lord is biding
               He will grant, thou nought want, who ſo deare hath bought thee,
               He will redreſſe, thy diſtreſſe, who ſo much hath ſought thee.
            
            
               Goe then and count, though thy ſinnes doe amount
               The ſand of the ſea, like red crimfie, thou repenting,
               Thy faith ſhall ſurmount, or them thou recount,
               If thy abode bee with God, who likes not thy tormenting:
               Whiter then the whiteſt ſnow he ſhall make thy being,
               Who obedience to his law craues, but not thy dying.
               As he liveth, ſo he ſweareth, he hath no delight in
               Sinners death, if from wrath, they returne or ſmiten.
            
            
               
               Loe as a Hen calls her Birds to defend,
               He calling cries, more then twice or thrice, for repentance,
               Harden not thy heart, leaſt he depart in end,
               And ſometime thou heare, in thine eare, this fearefull ſentence.
               Goe yee curſed into hell, where damned Divels are dying,
               And from heaven he you repell (for your ſinnes and lying)
               Kiſſe his ſonne, our Saviour ſweet: Brace him by returning,
               Reſt at your redeemers feet, till he end your mourning.
            
            
               What though a day, or a month, or a yeare,
               Croſſe thy deſires with imagin'd diſcontentings,
               Can not the change of an houre from all feare,
               Crowne thy delights with ten thouſand true contentings.
               Worldly honour, beautie, wealth, like vnto flowres are fading,
               Painted pleaſures poſting pelfe: from true ioyes diſſwading.
               But when grace, guides there place, then in ſeemly ſorting:
               Loue, faith, truth, zeale and ruth, makes them all comforting.
            
            
               What if at morne, at noone-tide, or evening,
               Thy God ſhall recall thee: art thou not content than,
               Time to regard when he is befreanding,
               Think not that hee'l ſaue thee, without thy conſent man.
               Turne he from thee, looke for wrath: for he is all-ſeeing,
               No repentance after death: but aye life or dying.
               Heav'n or in Hell, man muſt dwell: thence is no returning,
               Glore or griefe, without reliefe, alwayes ioy or mourning.
            
            
               Make thy abode in this world with thy God,
               By faith, feare, loue, zeale, prayer, praiſe, and repenting
               Thy ſinnes, which blinds thy ſoule with ſuch loade,
               As ſeeme gainſt heav'n, with the Divels, or their evils, indenting.
               Wouldſt thou ring with thy King, in heav'n at his appearance,
               Heere thou muſt fight, as a Chriſtian knight, by faith &amp; perſeverance.
               Triumphs ioyes, fred from noyes, there we will finde aye byding,
               Crownes of glore, evermore, which are never ſlyding.
            
            
               
               Then new heaven, and new earth, when gone's all breath
               Create ſhall be by infinitie, both former not remembred,
               In the towne, of renowne, where is no death,
               Saints ſhall dwell, fred from hell, and be no more diſmembred.
               Saint Iohn ſaw that towne, out of heaven coming downe, new Ieruſalem,
               
               From God prepared (in this compared, to Methuſalem,
               
               The ſpoyler of death, where is no wrath) as a bride for her husband,
               Full of glory and ioy, Loue freeing from noy, many thouſand.
            
            
               There Saints ſhall remaine where is nothing filthy,
               The Citie pure gold, like glaſſe (free from mould) tranſparant,
               The foundation of the walles of the Citie,
               Were garniſh'd with all ſorts of precious ſtones (apparant)
               1 Iaſper, 2 Saphyr, 3 Chalcedone, 4 Emeraude, 5 Sardonixe, 6 Sardius one,
               7 Chryſolite, 8 Beril, 9 Topas one: 10 Chryſophras, 11 Iacinth, 12 Amethiſt ſtone.
               Twelue gates, twelue pearles, each gate of one pearle was (apparant)
               And the ſtreets of the Citie pure gold, as glaſſe, tranſparant.
            
            
               God and the Lambe are the Temple therein,
               There no need of the Sunne, nor ſhining moone, where Tri-unitie,
               For the glorie of God did it lighten,
               And the Lambe is the light thereof (moſt bright Infinitie,)
               And the people ſav'd, ſhall there be receav'd, &amp; ſhall walk in its light,
               &amp; the kings of the earth, ſhal bring (after death) to it their glory &amp; might
               &amp; the gates of it ſhal by day not be ſhut, for there ſhal be no night there,
               And the honor &amp; glore of the gentils evermore, vnto it ſhal be brought there.
            
            
               There ſhall enter in it nothing vncleane,
               Nor that doth work lies (falſhood to lurke) or abhomination,
               But onely thoſe who are written (and ſeene)
               In the Lambs book of life (where is no ſtrife) there reſts al contentation:
               In him who belieue, was dead and doth liue for aye, &amp; in his purcheſſe,
               Who hath an eare let him heare what the ſpirit ſayth vnto the Churchs,
               To him that overcommeth:
               To him will I giue for ever to liue, and with me to haue abode,
               And to eate of the tree, of life we ſhal ſee, in the midſt of the paradice of God.
            
            
               
               
                  Exhortation to all true Chriſtians for the praiſing of our Saviour.
               KIng CHARLES our King come now and ſing,
               Exult for ioy before thy King,
               The King of Kings, thy God and Lord,
               And let thy ſoule and heart accord
               To magnifie and to extoll
               Thy King, who doth his foes controll.
               Mine heart reioyceth whiles I heare,
               How Chriſtian like thou doeſt thee beare:
               Obedience offering to Chriſts will,
               By life and converſation ſtill:
               The ſacrifice of Thankeſgiving,
               With prayers offring to thy King,
               Through Ieſus Chriſt thy Saviour ſweete,
               Who thee protecteth with his Sprite.
               When God King David had advaunced,
               Before Gods Arke good David daunced
               With all his might, for he reioſed
               In God, in whom he ſtill repoſed.
               Great Britaine with the Ocean ſea
               Inviron'd, come now, and with me,
               Sing praiſe and glore to Chriſt our Lord,
               Who grace, peace, mercie doth affoord.
               Come learned, and come Laickes all;
               Come Nobles, Gentles, great and ſmall,
               Come rich, come poore, come every creature,
               Conformed in true Chriſtian feature.
               Now let vs ſing in ſongs the praiſe,
               Of God, who Charles our King doth raiſe,
               And doth devouring peſts repell,
               Captiving Satan, Sinne, Death, Hell,
               The World, (and whatſoe're gaine-ſtood
               His glorie) through his precious blood
               Who by the power of his Sprite,
               Doth his owne Saints to him vnite.
               
                  Come Scotland, and exult for ioy,
               Praiſe Chriſt who doth prevent thy noy:
               And Charles thy Soveraigne Lord hath ſent,
               Apparent perils to prevent.
               Come Edinburgh renown'd for worth:
               The towne wherein I had my birth:
               Thou Citie ſituate on a mountaine,
               (Wherein doth flow the liuely fountaine
               Of Chriſts Evangell) for whom Chriſt,
               Is Sacrifice, and King, and Prieſt.
               Come, come, all Chriſtians true, reſound
               The praiſe, and glorie ſo profound,
               Of God our Lord, of Chriſt our King,
               Who moff triumphantly doth raigne.
               Let men and Angels all agree
               To praiſe his glorious Maieſtie:
               Extoll the name of Chriſt our Lord,
               And from his will doe not debord.
               O Chriſtians true, O Saints of God,
               Whiles heere on earth you haue abode,
               Suffer for Chriſt, and for his ſake,
               If need require, all things forſake
               Which doth to mortall life pertaine,
               For he doth all in all containe.
               Who every moment doth thee view,
               For loue of Chriſt, O Chriſtian true
               If need require, if iuſt occaſion,
               Affoord thy liues ſincere oblation.
               O Chriſtian rather then thou ſlide
               From Ieſus Chriſt (who from his ſide
               His royall precious blood made fall
               To ſaue the faithfull great or ſmall,
               Who doe beleeue in him through grace,
               Sent by his Sprit, for to deface
               Satan, ſinne, ſhame, the world, death, hell,
               That ſuch with him may alwayes dwell.)
               Forſake thy father and thy mother,
               Forſake thy ſiſter and thy brother
               
                  Forſake thy children, health, wealth, wife,
               Thy credite, and thy mortall life,
               Or whatſoever's to thee deere,
               Loe he ſhall recompence thee heere,
               And hence give million millions more,
               Which he in heav'n hath layd in ſtore
               For thee (true Chriſtian) and for thine
               An Oceant of true ioyes; propine
               Surpaſſing thought of mortall man.
               For let man thinke all that he can,
               And ſpeeke and write, it to define,
               Man in this life can not attaine
               Vnto the thouſand millions part
               Which he ſhall haue in ſoule and heart
               When the Arch-Angell ſhall with ſound
               Of Trumpet, raiſe the dead from ground,
               And Chriſt with his eternall ſentence
               Shall doome pronounce, when as repentance
               Shall after that no time receaue,
               Though damn'd could giue what Chriſt did craue,
               Then after that there's be no time,
               For time ſhall then run out of time,
               As doth that Angell teſtifie
                     Rev. 10.5.6.
               
               To Iohn, whom Iohn in traunce did ſee,
               Which ſware by him (who life vs giveth)
               For ever and for ever liveth:
               Who Heav'n, earth, ſea, and all therein
               Created. (Who ſubdued ſinne,
               Through Ieſus Chriſt, and his great ſtore
               Of grace) That time ſhall be no more.
               Come all true Chriſtians now whiles time,
               Doth pardon to your ſinnes proclaime.
               Returne againe to Chriſt our Lord,
               And from his will no more debord.
               Come, come, and ioyfully reſound
               The praiſe of Chriſt, who doth abound
               In loue, in mercie, peace and grace,
               And ſhall make vs to ſee his face
               
                  In ioy and glory, who contend
               'Gainſt ſinne and Satan, till hee end
               This mortall life, and to vs giue
               For evermore with him to liue.
               
                  Michael the Dragon caſt from Heav'n,
               And Babels whoore ſhall als bee driven,
               And daſhed ſtrongly downe to duſt,
               The Antichriſt whom God hath curſt:
               O ſhe is fallen in Gods ſight,
               And daily falling through his might.
               The glorie of her pompe and pride,
               Muſt yeeld to Chriſt, and to his Bride.
               Gods Iſrael. O Chriſtians true,
               Come ſhoute for ioy, and ſtill renue
               A battery to proud Babels wall,
               Till that preſumptuous Harlot fall.
               Would God mine eyes might ſee her daſh'd
               And dung to duſt, who long hath faſh'd
               The Bride of Chriſt. O Lord of might,
               Grant we may ſhortly ſee that ſight.
               O mightie Lord, delay not long,
               Behold thy little ones in throng,
               And front of battell, fighting ſtill,
               Attending thy command and will.
               How long, how long, remember Lord,
               Thy Saints (with whom we doe accord)
               Vnder thy throne, who call and cry,
               How long, how long, doeſt thou delay
               For to avenge vs of our wrongs?
               But thou Lord know'ſt what beſt belongs
               Vnto thy glorie; which fulfill,
               According to thine holy will.
            
            
         
      
   

