
   
      
         
            One of the sermons preach't to the Lords of the High Court of Parliament, in their solemne fast held on Ashwednesday, Feb. 18 And by their appointment published: by Ios: Exon.
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1629
            
         
         Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02566
            STC 12693
            ESTC S103758
            99839503
            99839503
            3931
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02566)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3931)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:03)
         
         
            
               
                  One of the sermons preach't to the Lords of the High Court of Parliament, in their solemne fast held on Ashwednesday, Feb. 18 And by their appointment published: by Ios: Exon.
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [4], 67, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by M. Flesher, for Nath. Butter,
                  London :
                  1629.
               
               
                  Ios: Exon. = Joseph Hall.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ONE OF THE SERMONS Preach't to the Lords of the High Court of Parliament, in their ſolemne Faſt held on Aſhwedneſday, Feb. 18.
            And by their appointment publiſhed:
            
               By Ios: Exon.
            LONDON, Printed by M. Fleſher, for Nath. Butter.
            
            1629.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               Acts 2. 37, 38, 40.
               
                  37, Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid to Peter, and the reſt of the Apoſtles, Men and brethren what ſhall we doe?
                  38, Then ſaid Peter vnto them, Repent and be baptized, &amp;c. &amp;c.
                  40. And with many other words did he teſtifie, and exhort them, ſaying, Saue your ſelues from this vntoward generation.
               
            
            WHo knowes not that Simon Peter was a Fiſher? that was his trade both by Sea and Land, if we may not rather ſay, that as Simon, he was a Fiſherman, but, as

               Peter, he was a fiſher of men; He that call'd him ſo, made him ſo; And ſurely his firſt draught of fiſhes, which, as Simon, he made at our Sauiours comand, might well be a true type of the firſt draught of men, which, as Peter, hee made in this place; for, as then, the nets were ready to cracke, and the ſhip to ſinke, with ſtore; ſo here, when he threw forth his firſt drag net of heauenly doctrine, &amp; reproofe, three thouſand ſoules were drawne vp at once. This text was as the ſacred cord, that drew the net together; and pull'd vp this wondrous ſhole of conuerts to God; It is the ſumme of Saint Peters Sermon, if not at a Faſt, yet at a generall humiliation, which is more and better; (for wherefore

faſt we but to be humbled? and if wee could bee duely humbled, without faſting, it would pleaſe God a thouſand times better, then to faſt formally, without true humiliation; Indeed, for the time, this was a feaſt, the feaſt of Pentecoſt; but for the eſtate of theſe Iewes, it was dies cinerum, a day of contrition; a day of deepe hunger, and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, Men and brethren, what ſhall we doe? Neither doubt I to ſay, that the feſtiuity of the ſeaſon added not a little to their humiliation; like as wee are neuer ſo apt to take cold, as vpon a ſweat: and that winde is euer the keeneſt, wch blowes cold out of a warm coaſt; No day could be more afflictiue then an Aſhwedneſday,

that ſhould light vpon a ſolemne Pentecoſt; ſo it was here: Euery thing anſwered well; The Spirit came downe vpon thē in a mighty winde; and behold, it hath ratled their harts together; the houſe ſhooke in the deſcent, and behold here, the foundations of the ſoule were moued; Fiery tongues appeared, &amp; here their breſts were inflamed; Clouen tongues; and here their hearts were cut in ſunder. The words were miraculous, becauſe in a ſupernaturall, and ſudden variety of language; the matter diuine, laying before them both the truth of the Meſſiah, and their bloody meaſure offered to that Lord of life, and now Compuncti cordibus, they were pricked in their hearts. Wiſe Salomon ſayes,

               The words of the wiſe are like goads, and nayles; here they were ſo; Goades, for they were, compuncti, pricked; yea, but the goad could not goe ſo deepe, that paſſeth but the skin; they were nayles, driuen into the very heart of the auditors, vp to the head; the great Maſter of the Aſſembly, the diuine Apoſtle had ſet them home, they were pricked in their hearts. Neuer were words better beſtowed. It is an happy blood-letting that ſaues the life, this did ſo here: wee looke to the ſigne commonly in phlebotomy, it is a ſigne of our idle and ignorant ſuperſtition, Saint Peter here ſaw the ſigne to be in the heart, and he ſtrikes happily, Compuncti cordibus, they were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid,
               
               Men and brethren, what ſhall we doe?
            
            Oh, what ſweet Muſick was this to the Apoſtles eare? I dare ſay, none but heauen could afford better; what a pleaſing ſpectacle was this anguiſh of their wounded ſoules? To ſee men come in their zealous deuotions, and lay downe their moneyes (the price of their alienated poſſeſſions) at thoſe Apoſtolike feet, was nothing to this; that they came in a bleeding contrition, &amp; proſtrated their penitent and humbled ſoules at the beautifull feet of the meſſengers of peace; with Men and brethren what ſhall we doe? Oh when, when ſhall our eyes be bleſſed with ſo happy a proſpect? How long ſhall wee thunder out Gods fearfull iudgements

againſt wilfull ſinners; how long ſhall wee threaten the flames of hell to thoſe impious wretches, who crucifie againe to thēſelues, the Lord of life, ere we can wring a ſigh, or a teare from the rocks of their hearts or eyes? Woe is me that wee may ſay too truely, as this Peter did of his other fiſhing; Maſter, we haue trauailed all the night and caught nothing. Surely, it may well goe for night with vs, whiles wee labour and preuaile not. Nothing? not a ſoule caught? Lord what is becomne of the ſucceſſe of thy Goſpel? Who hath beleeued our report, or to whom is the arm
                     •
                   of the Lord reuealed? Oh God, thou art euer thy ſelfe, thy truth is eternall, hell is where it was; if we be leſſe

worthy then thy firſt meſſengers; yet what excuſe is this to the beſotted world, that through obduredneſſe and infidelity it will needs periſh? no man will ſo much as ſay with the Iewes, What haue I done, or with Saint Peters auditors, what ſhall I doe? Oh fooliſh ſinners, ſhall yee liue here alwayes; care ye not for your ſoules; is there not an hell that gapes for your ſtubborne impenitence? Goe on, if there bee no remedy, goe on, and dye for euer; we are guiltleſſe, God is righteous, your damnation is iuſt; But, if your life bee fickle, death vnaauoydable, if an euerlaſting vengrance be the neceſſary reward of your momentany wickednes, Oh turne, turne frō your euill waies;

and in an holy diſtraction of your remorſed ſoules ſay, with theſe Iewes, Men and brethren what ſhall we doe? This from the generall view of the occaſion; wee deſcend to a little more particularitie.
            
               Luke, the beloued Phyſitian, deſcribes Saint Peters proceeding here, much after his owne trade; as of a true ſpirituall phyſitian; who finding his Countrymen the Iewes in a deſperate, and deadly condition, gaſping for life, ſtruggling with death, enters into a ſpeedy and zealous courſe of their cure; And firſt hee begins with the Chyrurgicall part; and finding them rancke of blood, and that foule, and putrified, hee lets it out (compuncti cordibus)
               
where wee might ſhow you the inciſion, the veine, the lancet, the orifice, the anguiſh of the ſtroke: The inciſion, compuncti, they were pricked; The veine in their hearts; Smile not now, ye Phyſitians, if any heare me this day, as if I had paſſed a ſolaeciſme, in telling you theſe men were pricked in the veine of the heart, talke you of your Cephalica, and the reſt, and tel vs of another ciſtern from whēce theſe tubuli ſanguinis are deriued; I tell you againe (with an addition of more incongruities ſtill) that God and his diuine Phyſitians doe ſtill let blood in the median veine of the hart; The lancet is the keene and cutting reproofe of their late barbarous crucifixion of their holy and moſt innocent

and benigne Sauiour; The orifice, is the eare, (when they heard this:) what euer the locall diſtance bee of theſe parts; ſpiritually, the eare is the very ſurface of the heart; and whoſoeuer would giue a medicinall ſtroke to the heart muſt paſſe it through the eare, the ſenſe of diſcipline and correction: The anguiſh bewrayes it ſelfe in their paſſionate exclamation; Men and brethren what ſhall we doe?
            
            There is none of theſe, which my ſpeech might not well take vp, if not as an houſe to dwell in, yet as an Inne to reſt and lodge in; but I will not ſo much as bayt here; onely wee make this a thorow fare tothoſe other ſacred preſcriptions of ſauing remedies:

which are three in number. The firſt is, euacuation of ſinnes by a ſpeedy repentance 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ; The ſecond, the ſoueraigne bath or lauer of regeneration, Baptiſme. The third, diet
                  •
               ticall and prophylacticall receipts of wholeſome caution: which I meane (with a determinate praeterition of the reſt) to ſpend my houre vpon, Saue your ſelues from this vntoward generation. But, ere I pitch vpon this moſt vſefull and ſeaſonable particularity, let mee offer to your thoughts the ſpeedy application of theſe gracious remedies; The bleſſed Apoſtle doth not let his patients languiſh vnder his hand in the heats and colds of hopes and feares; but ſo ſoon as euer the word is out of their mouthes,

               Men and brethren, what ſhall we doe? hee preſently adminiſtreth theſe ſoueraigne receipts, Repent, be baptized, ſaue your ſelues. In acute diſeaſes wiſe phyſitians will leeſe no time; onely delay makes ſome diſtempers deadly. It is not for vs to let good motiōs freeze vnder our fingers; How many gleeds haue dyed in their aſhes, which if they had beene ſpeedily blowne, had riſen into comfortable flames? The care of our zeale for God muſt be ſure to take all opportunities of good; This is the Apoſtles (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) ſeruing the time; that is, obſeruing it; not for conformity to it when it is naught, (fye on that baſeneſſe, no let the declining time come to vs, vpon true and conſtant grounds, let not

vs ſtoope to it, in the termes of the ſeruile yeeldance of Optatus his Donatiſts, Omnia pro tempore, nibil pro veritate) not, I ſay, for conformity to it, but for aduantage of it; The embleme teaches vs to take occaſion by the forelocke, elſe we catch too late. The Iſraelites muſt goe forth and gather their Manna, ſo ſoone as it is faln; if they ſtay but till the Sunne haue raught his noone-point, in vaine ſhall they ſeeke for that food of Angels. Saint Peter had learnt this of his Maſter; when the ſhoale was ready, Chriſt ſayes, Laxate retia, Luk. 5. 14. what ſhould the net doe now in the ſhip? When the fiſh was caught, Chriſt ſayes, Draw vp againe, what ſhould the net doe now in the Sea? What

ſhould I aduiſe you Reuerend Fathers and brethren (the Princes of our Iſrael, as the Doctors are called, Iudges 5. 9.) to ſpeake a word in ſeaſon; what ſhould I preſume to put into your hands, theſe apples of gold, with pictures of ſiluer? What ſhould I perſwade you (to theſe 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) to wing your words with ſpeed, when the neceſſity of endangered ſoules calls for them? Oh let vs rowe hard whiles the tyde of grace ſerues; when we ſee a large doore, and effectuall opened vnto vs, let vs throng in, with a peaceable and zealous importunity to be ſure; Oh let vs preach the word 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               In ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon; and carefully watch for the beſt aduantages of preuailing, and

when the yron of mens hearts is ſoftned by the fire of Gods Spirit, and made flexible by a meet humiliation, delay not to ſtrike, and make a gracious impreſſion, as Saint Peter did here Repent, bee baptized; Saue your ſelues from this vntoward generation.
            
            Now to the maine, and all-ſufficient Recipe for theſe feeling diſtempers; ſaue your ſelues. This is the very extracted quinteſſence of Saint Peters long Sermon; in wch alone is included and vnited the ſoueraigne vertue of Repentance, of Baptiſme, of whatſoeuer helpe to a conuerting ſoule; ſo as I ſhall not need to ſpeake explicitely of them, whiles I enlarge my ſelfe to the treating of this vniuerſall remedy, Saue your ſelues
               
               from this vntoward generation.
            
            Would you thinke that Saint Luke hath giuen mee the diuiſion of this, whether Text, or, ſermon of Saint Peter? ye ſhall not find the like otherwhere; here it is clearly ſo: 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . He teſtifies, he exhorts; he teſtifies what he thinkes of the times; he exhorts or beſeeches, (as the Syriacke turnes it) to auoyd their danger; both of them, as St. Auſten well, referre to this one diuine ſentence: The parts whereof then, are in Saint Lukes diuiſion; Peters reprehenſory atteſtation, and his obteſtation; His reprehenſory atteſtation to the common wickedneſſe, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ; His obteſtation of their freedome and indemnity, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ; Saue
               
               your ſelues.
            
            To beginne with the former; what is a generation? what is an vntoward generation? Either word hath ſome little miſt about it; The very word, generation, hath begot multiplicity of ſenſes: without all perplexedneſſe of ſearch, wee will ſingle out the properly intended for this place; As times, ſo, wee in them, are in continuall paſſage; euery thing is in motion; the Heauens do not more moue aboue our heads, in a circular reuolution, then we here on earth doe by a perpetuall alteration; now all that are contained in one liſt of time, whether fixed, or vncertaine, are a generation of men; Fixed; ſo Suidas vnder-reckons it by ſeuen yeares; but the

ordinary rate is an hundred; It is a cleare text, Gen. 15. 16. But in the fourth generation, they ſhall come hither againe; when is that? (to the ſhame of Galatinus, who cloudes it with the fancy of the foure kinds, or manners of mans exiſtence:) Moſes himſelfe interprets it, of foure hundred yeares, verſ. 13. Vncertaine; ſo Salomon; One generation paſſeth, another commeth; The very terme implyes tranſitorineſſe: It is with men, as with Raſpices; one ſtalk is growing, another growne vp, a third withered, &amp; all vpō one root; Or, as with floures, &amp; ſome kinds of flyes, they grow vp, and ſeed, and dye; Yee ſee your condition, oh ye great men of the earth, It is no ſtaying here; Orimur, morimur; after

the acting of a ſhort part vpon this ſtage, ye muſt withdraw for euer; make no other account, but, with Abraham, to ſerue your generation, and away; ye can neuer more fitly heare of your mortality then now, that yee are vnder that roofe which couers the monuments of your dead, and forgotten Progenitors.
            What is an vntoward generation? 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                It is promiſcuouſly turned froward, peruerſe, crooked; The oppoſitiō to 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                is, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                All is as one, what euer ſwarues from the right is crooked; The Law is a right line, and what crookedneſſe is in nature, frowardneſſe, and vntowardneſſe is in moralitie. Shortly, there is a double crookedneſſe and vntowardnes;

One negatiue, the other, poſitiue; The firſt, is a failing of that right we ſhould either haue, or be; The ſecond, a contrary habit of vicious qualities; and both theſe, are, either in credendis, or agendis; In matter of faith, or matter of fact. The firſt, when wee doe not beleeue, or doe what we ought; the ſecond, when we miſ-beleeue, or miſ-liue.
            The firſt is an vntowardneſſe of omiſſion; the ſecond of commiſſion. The omiſſi
                  •
               e vntowardneſſe ſhall lead the way; and that, firſt, in matter of beleefe. This is it whereof our Sauiour ſpake to the two Diſciples in their warme walke to Emaus, O fooles, and ſlow of heart to beleeue; whereof the proto-martyr Stephen to his

auditors, (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ;) The ſtiffe necke, the vncircumciſed eare, the fat heart, the blinded eye, the obdurate ſoule (quae nec mouetur precibus, nec cedit minis, as Bernard) are wont to be the expreſſions of this vntowardneſſe.
            If theſe Iewes, then, after ſo cleare predictions of the Prophets, after ſo miraculous demonſtrations of the diuine power of Chriſt; after ſo many graues ranſackt, dead rayſed, deuils eiected, limmes and eyes new-created; after ſuch teſtimonies of the ſtarre, Sages, Angels, God himſelfe; after ſuch triumphes ouer death and hell, doe yet detrect to beleeue in him, and to receiue him for their Meſſias, moſt iuſtly are they, in this firſt kinde, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                a froward

generation; And ſo is any Nation vnder heauen, that followes them in the ſteps of their peeuiſh incredulity, more or leſſe; ſhutting their eyes vpon the glorious light of ſauing Truth; like that ſullen Tree, in the Indies, which, they ſay, cloſes it ſelfe againſt the beames of the riſing Sunne, and opens onely to the dampiſh ſhades of the night; where wee muſt take this rule with vs; a rule of moſt iuſt proportion; that the meanes of light to any Nation aggrauate the haynouſneſſe, and damnableneſſe of their vnbeleefe: The time of that ignorance God regarded not, but now: ſaith Saint Paul to the Athenians, Acts 17. If I had not comne, and ſpoken to them,

they ſhould haue had no ſinne; ſaith our Sauiour, Ioh. 15. 22. Thoſe that walke in Cimmerian, in Egyptian darkeneſſe, it is neither ſhame, nor wonder, if they either erre, or ſtumble; but, for a man to ſtumble the Sunne in the face, or to grope by the walles at noone in the midſt of Goſhen, is ſo much more hatefull, as the occecation is more willing.
            The later, which is the negatiue vntowardneſſe in action, is, when any Nation failes palpably in thoſe holy duties of Piety, Iuſtice, Charity, which the royall Law of their God requireth. Of this kinde are thoſe vſuall complaints; The feare of God is not before their eies. God looked to ſee if there were any that looked

after God, and behold there was none; The righteous is periſhed from the children of men; Behold the teares of the oppreſſed, and none comforted them. The Prophets are full of theſe querulous notes; there is not a page of them free; yea hardly ſhall yee meet with one line of theirs, which doth not brand their Iſrael with this defect of holineſſe.
            From the negatiue, caſt your eyes vpon the poſitiue crookedneſſe, or vntowardneſſe; That is, in matter of faith, the maintenance of impiety, miſ-beleefe, hereſie, ſuperſtition, atheiſme, and what euer other intellectuall wickedneſſe. In matter of fact, Idolatries, profane cariage, violation of Gods dayes and ordinances;

diſobediences, murders, adulteries, thefts, drunkenneſſe, lyes, detractions, or any other actuall rebellion againſt God. Behold, I haue drawne forth before you an helliſh rabble of ſinnes, enow to marre a world; what euer Nation now or ſucceſſion of men abounds either in theſe ſinfull omiſſions, or theſe haynous commiſſions; whether in matter of iudgement, or manners, is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                an vntoward generation; That which makes a man crooked, or vntoward, makes a generation ſo; for what is a generation, but a reſultance of men? their number doth not vary their condition. But let not our zeale (as it oft doth) make vs vncharitable; when a whole generation

is taxed for vntowardneſſe, think not that none are free, No, not one, ſaith the Pſalmiſt; by way of ſeruent aggrauation; All ſeeke their owne, ſaith the Apoſtle; all, in compariſon: but, neuer times were ſo ouer growne with iniquity, as that God hath not left himſelfe ſome gracious remainders; when the theeuiſh Chaldeans and Sabeans haue done their worſt, there ſhall be a meſſenger, to ſay I am eſcaped; Neuer was harueſt or vintage ſo curiouſly inned, that ſome gleanings were not left in the field; ſome cluſters among the leaues: But theſe few, if they may giue a bleſſing to the times, yet they cannot giue a ſtyle; the denomination ſtill followes the greater (though the worſe)

part; let theſe bee neuer ſo good; the generation, is, and is noted for euill. Let me therefore here commend to your better thoughts theſe three emergent conſiderations: 1. The irreparable wrong, and reproach that lewd men bring vpon the very ages and nations where they liue. 2. The difference of times, and ages, in reſpect of the degrees of euill. 3. The warrant of the free cenſure of ill-deſeruing times, or Nations.
            It were happy if the iniury of a wicked man could bee confiued to his owne boſome, that he only ſhould fare the worſe for his ſins; 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                &amp;c. as the Greeke rule runnes; If it were but ſelfe-do, ſelfe-haue, as the old word is;

But as his lewdneſs is (like ſome odious ſent) diffuſed through the whole roome where he is; ſo it reacheth to earth and heauen; yea to the very times and generations, vpon which he is vnhappily falne. Doubtleſſe there were many worthy Saints in theſe very times of Saint Peter; there was the bleſſed mother of Chriſt, the paragon of ſanctity; there was a beauye of thoſe deuout, and holy dames that attended the doctrine, bewayled the death, and would haue embalmed the corps of our bleſſed Sauiour; there were the twelue Apoſtles; the ſeventie Diſciples; the hundred and twenty names that were met in one roome at Ieruſalem, Acts 1. 25. The 
                  •
               iue hundred brethren that

ſaw Chriſt after his glorious and victorious reſurrection; beſides thoſe many thouſands, that beleeued, through their word, in all the parts of Iudea, and Galslee, yet, for all that, the Apoſtle brands this with 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , an vntoward generation.
            
            It is not in the vertue of a few to drowne the wickedneſſe of the more; If we come into a field that hath ſome good plenty of corne, and ſome ſtore of weeds, though it be red with poppy, or yellow with ca
                  •
               locke, or blew with wild bottles or ſcabious, we ſtill call it a corne field; but, if we come into a barne-floore, and ſee ſome few graines ſcattered amongſt an heape of chaffe, we do not call it a corne-heape, the quantity

of the offall deuoures the mention of thoſe inſenſible graines: Thus it is with times, and nations; A little good is not ſeene amongſt much ill; A righteous Lot cannot make his City to be no Sodom; wickedneſſe as it helps to corrupt, ſo to ſhame a very age. The Orator Tertullus, when hee would plead againſt Paul, ſayes, We haue 
                  •
               ound this man (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) a peſtilence
                  •
                
               Act. 24. 5. Fooliſh Tertullus, 
               
                  •
               hat miſtooke the Antidote for the poyſon, the remedy for the diſeaſe▪ but had S. Paul beene ſuch 
                  •
               s thy meſ-priſon ſuppoſed 
                  〈◊〉
                he had beene ſuch as thy vniuſt 
                  〈◊〉
                now makes thy ſel
                  •
               e, (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) the plague of thy people▪ A 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  〈1 line〉
               
               
he infects the world with ſinne, the very age with infamy; Malus vir malum publicum, is not a more old, then true word; Are there then in any nation vnder heauen lewd miſcreants, whoſe hearts are Atheiſts, whoſe tongues are blaſphemers, whoſe bodies are 
                  •
                ſtewes; whoſe lips are nothing but a factory of cloſe villany; let them pleaſe themſelues, and let others (if ye will) applaud them for their beneficiall contributions to the publike affaires, in the ſtyle of bonu
                     •
                   ciui
                     •
                  
                a good patriot; as men whoſe parts may be vſefull to the w
                  ••
               le-publike; but, I ſay, ſuch men are no better then the bane of their Country, the ſtayne of their age; Turpis eſt pars quae ſuo toti 
                     •
                  on 
                     ••
                  n
                     •
                  e
                     •
                  it as G
                     •
                  rſon well;

It is an ill member, for which all the body fares the worſe: Heare this then, ye glorious ſinners, that bragge of your good affections, and faithful ſervices to your deare Country; your hearts, your heads, your purſes, your hands (yee ſay) are preſt for the publike good; yea, but are your hearts godleſſe? are your liues filthy? let me tell you, your ſinnes doe more diſſeruice to your nation, then your ſelues are worth: All your valor, wiſedome, ſubſidiary helps cannot counterpoiſe one dramme of your wickedneſſe; Talke what yee will; ſinne is a ſhame to any people, ſaith wiſe Salomon; yee bring both a curſe, and a diſhonor vpon your Nation; It may thank you for the hateful ſtyle of

(
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) a froward generation: This, for our firſt obſeruation.
            Neuer generation was ſo ſtraight, as not to be diſtorted with ſo me powerfull ſinnes, but there are differences; and degrees in this diſtortion; euen in the very firſt world were Giants, as Moſes tells vs Gen. 6. 4. which, as our Mythologiſts adde, did (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) bid battle to heauen.
            In the next, there were mighty hunters; proud Babel-builders; after them followed beaſtly Sodomites; It were eaſie to draw downe the pedegree of euills through all times, till wee come to theſe laſt, which the holy Ghoſt markes out for perillous; yet ſome generation is more eminently ſinfull then other; as the

Sea is in perpetuall agitation, yet the Spring tydes riſe higher then their fellowes; hence Saint Peter notes this his generation with an emphaſis of miſchiefe (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) here is a tranſcendency of euill; what age may compare with that, which hath embrued their cruell hands in the blood of the Sonne of God? That roaring Lyon is neuer ſtill, but there are times, wherein he rageth more, as he did and doth in the firſt, in the laſt dayes of the Goſpel. The firſt, that he might blocke vp the way of ſauing truth; The laſt, for that hee knowes his time is ſhort. There are times that are poyſoned with more contagious hereſies, with more remarkeable villanies, It is not my meaning to ſpēd

time in abridging the ſacred Chronologies of the Church, and to deduce along the curſed ſucceſſions of damnable errours from their helliſh originall; onely let me touch at the notable difference betwixt the firſt, and the laſt world; In the firſt (as Epiphanius obſerves) 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , there was neither diuerſity of opinion, nor mention of hereſie, nor act of idolatry, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : onely piety, and impiety diuided the world; wheras now, in the laſt (which is the wrangling and techy dotage of the decrepit world) here is nothing but vnquiet claſhings of opinion, nothing but foule hereſie, either maintained by the guilty, or imputed to the innocent, nothing

but groſſe idolatry in paganiſme, in miſ-beleeuing Chriſtianity; and (woe is me that I muſt ſay it) a coloured impiety ſhares too much of the reſt; My ſpeech is glided, ere I was aware, into the third head of our diſcourſe; and is ſuddenly falne vpon the practiſe of that, which S. Peters example here warrants, the cenſure of ill deſeruing times: which I muſt craue leaue of your honorable &amp; Chriſtian patience, with an holy and iuſt freedome, to proſecute.
            It is the peeuiſh humour of a factious eloquence to aggrauate the euills of the times; which, were they better then they are, would be therefore cryed down in the ordinary language of malecontented

ſpirits, becauſe preſent; But, it is the warrantable, and neceſſary duty of S. Peter, and all his true Euangelicall ſucceſſours, when they meet with a froward generation, to call it ſo.
            How commonly doe we cry out of thoſe querulous Michaiahs, that are ſtill propheſying euill to vs, and not good? No theme but ſinnes, no ſawce but vineger: Might not one of theſe galled Iewes of S. Peters auditory haue ſtarted vp; and haue thus challenged him for this tartneſſe; what meanes this hard cenſure? why doe you ſlander the time? Salomon was a wiſe man, and he ſayes, Say not thou, what is the cauſe that the former dayes were better then theſe? for thou doſt

not enquire wiſely concerning this: this is but a needleſſe rigor; this is but an enuious calumny: The generation were not vntoward; if your tongue were not vncharitable. The Apoſtle feares none of theſe curriſh oblatrations; but contemning all impotent miſ-acceptions, calls them what he findes them, A froward generation: And well might hee doe ſo; his great Maſter did it before him, an euill and adulterous generation; and the harbinger of that great Maſter fore-ranne him in that cenſure, O generation of Vipers, Mat. 3. 7. and the Prophets led the ſame way to him in euerie page. And why doenot we follow Peter in the ſame ſteppes wherein Peter followed Chriſt,

and Chriſt his fore-runner, and his fore-runner the Prophets? Who ſhould tell the times of their ſinnes, if wee be ſilent? Pardon me, I beſeech you, moſt noble, reuerend, and beloued hearers; neceſſity is layd vpon me; in this day of our publique mourning, I may not be as a man in whoſe mouth is no reproofes. Oh let vs bee thankfull for our bleſſings, wherein, through the mercy of God, we outſtrip all the nations vnder heauen; but withall, let vs bewaile our ſinnes, which are ſo much more grieuous, becauſe ours. Would to God it were no leſſe vniuſt, then vnpleaſing to complaine of this as an vntoward generation; There be 
                  •
               oure things that are wont both to make vp

and euince the prauity of any generation; (woe is mee that they are too apparently met in this) multitude of ſinnes, magnitude of ſinnes, boldneſſe of ſinne, impunity of ſinning; Take a ſhort view of them all: you ſhall ſee that the multitude is ſuch, as that it hath couered the earth; the magnitude ſuch, as hath reacht to heauen; the boldneſſe ſuch as out-faceth the Goſpel, the impunity ſuch as fruſtrates the wholſome lawes vnder which we liue.
            For the multitude, where is the man that makes true conſcience of any the Lawes of his God? and if euery man violate all the lawes of God, what do all put together? our forefathers ſinnes were but as drops, ours are as torrents. Inſtance

in ſome few; Cannot we our ſelues remember, ſince a debaucht Drunkard was an Owle among birds, a beaſt of men, a monſter of beaſts; abhorred of men, ſhouted at by children? Is this ſight now any newes to vs? Is not euery Tauern a ſtye of ſuch ſwine? Is not euery ſtreet indented with their ſhamefull ſtaggerings? Is there not now as much ſpent in wanton ſmoake, as our honeſt forefathers ſpent in ſubſtantiall hoſpitality?
            Cannot we remember, ſince oathes were ſo geaſon, and vncouth, that their ſound ſtartled the hearer, as amazed at the ſtrange language of treaſon againſt the God of heauen▪ now they fill euery mouth, and beat euery ea
                  •
               e in a

neglected familiarity? What ſhold I tell you of the ouergrowne frequence of oppreſſions, extortions, iniurious and fraudulent tranſactions, malitious ſuites; the neighbour walls of this famous adioyning Pallace can too amply witneſſe this truth, whoſe roofe if (as they ſay) it will admit of no Spiders, I am ſure, the floore of it yeelds venome enough▪ to poyſon a Kingdome: What ſhould I tell you of the ſenſible declination to our once loathed ſuperſtitions; of the common trade of contemptuous diſ-obediences to lawfull authority, the ſcornefull vnderualuing of Gods meſſengers; the ordinary neglect of his ſacred ordinances; what ſpeake I of theſe and thouſands more?

There are Arithmeticians that haue taken vpon them to count how many cornes of ſand would make vp the bulke of heauen and earth; but no Art can reckon vp the multitude of our prouoking ſinnes.
            Neither doe they more exceed in number, then magnitude; Can there be a greater ſinne then Idolatry? Is not this (beſides all the reſt) the ſinne of the preſent Romiſh generation? One of their owne confeſſes (as he well may) that were not the bread tranſubſtantiate, their Idolatry were more groſſe, then the heatheniſh; loe, nothing excuſes them but an impoſſible figment▪ Know, O yee poore, ignorant ſeduced ſoules, that the bread can bee no more

turned into God; then God can be turned into bread, into nothing; the very omnipotent power of God barres theſe impious contradictions. My heart trembles therfore and bleeds to thinke of your higheſt, your holieſt devotions. Can there be a greater ſinne then robbing of God? This is done by our ſacrilegious Patrons: Can there bee a greater ſinne then tearing God out of heauen with our bloody and blaſphemous oathes; then the affamiſhing of ſoules by a wilfull, or lazie ſilence; then rending in peeces the bowels of our deare Mother the Church, by our headſtrong, and friuolous diſſentions; then furious murders; then affronts of authority? Theſe, theſe are thoſe huge mountaines

which our Gyantlike preſumption roles vpon each other, to war againſt heauen.
            Neither are the ſinnes of men more great, then audacious; yea it is their impudency that makes them hainous; baſhfull offences riſe not to extremity of euill; The ſinnes of exceſſe as they are opera tenebrarum, ſo they had wont to bee night-workes, They that are drunken are drunke in the night, ſaith the Apoſtle; now, they dare, with Abſaloms beaſtlineſſe, call the Sun to record: Saint Bernard tells vs of a Daemon meridianus, a nooneDeuill, out of the vulgar miſ-tranſlation of the 90. Pſalme; Surely, that ill ſpirit walkes about buſily, and haunts the licentious conuerſation of inordinate men.
            
               
Vniuſt exactions of griping Officers had wont to c
                  •
               eepe in vnder the modeſt cloke of voluntary curteſie, or faire conſiderations of a befriended expedition, now they come like Elies ſonnes, Nay but, Thou ſhalt giue it me now, and, if not, I will take it by force, 1 Sam. 2. 16.
            The legall thefts of profeſſed vſurers, and the crafty compacts of ſlie oppreſſors, dare throw downe the gantlet to iuſtice; and inſolent diſobediences doe ſo to authority; And when wee denounce the fearfull iudgements of God againſt all theſe abhominable wickedneſſes; the obdured ſinner dares ieere vs in the face, and▪ in a worſe ſenſe aske the diſciples queſtion, Domine quando fient
               
               haec; Maſter when ſhall theſe things be? yea their ſelfe-flattering incredulity dare ſay to their ſoule, as Peter did to his Maſter, Fauor thy ſelfe, for theſe things ſhal not happen to thee.
            
            Neither, laſtly, would ſinne dare to be ſo impudent, if it were not for impunity; it cannot bee but cowardly, where it ſees cauſe of feare; Euery hand is not to be layd vpon euill; If an error ſhould ariſe in the Church; it is not for euery vnlearned tradeſman to caſt away his yard-wand, and take vp his pen; Wherefore ſerue Vniuerſities, if euery blew apron may at his pleaſure turne Licenciate of Diuinity, and talke of Theologicall queſtions which hee vnderſtands not, as if they were to bee meaſured by the elle. O times! Lord whither will this preſumption

grow? Deus, omen, &amp;c. If folly, if villanie bee committed in our Iſrael, it is not for euery man to be an Officer; Who made thee a Iudge? was a good queſtion, though ill asked. But I would to God wee had more cauſe to complaine of the preſumption of them who meddle with what they ſhould not, then the neglect of thē who meddle not with what they ſhould; Woe is me the floodgates of euill are (as it were) lift open, and the full ſtreame guſheth vpon vs; Not that I would caſt any aſperſion vpon ſacred ſoueraignty; No, bleſſed bee God for his deare anointed; of whom we may truly, and ioyfully ſay, that in imitation of him whom he repreſents, hee loues iuſtice, and hates

iniquity; It is the partiality or ſlackneſſe of the ſubordinate inferiour executions that is guilty of this preualence of ſinne; what can the head do where the hands are wanting? to what vſe is the water deriued from the ceſterne, into the pipes, if the cocke be not turned? What auailes it that children are brought to the birth, if there want a midwifry to deliuer them? Can there poſſibly be better Lawes, then have in our times beene enacted, againſt drunkenneſſe? where, or when are they executed? Can there bee a better Law made for the reſtraint of too too common oathes? who vrges, who payes that iuſt mulct? Can there be better lawes againſt wilfull Recuſancy, againſt Symony,

againſt Sacriledge? how are they eluded by fraudulent euaſions? Againſt neglect of Diuine Seruice; yet how are they ſleighted? againſt the lawleſſe wandring of lazie vagabonds; yet, how full are our ſtreets, how empty our Correction-houſes? Laſtly, (for it were eaſie to be endleſſe) can there bee better lawes then are made 
                  •
               or the puniſhment of fornications, adulteries, and all other fleſhly inordinateneſſes? how doth bribery &amp; corruption ſmother theſe offences, as if the ſinnes of men ſerued onely to enrich couetous Officers? Now, put all theſe together, the multitude, the magnitude, the boldneſſe, the impunity of ſinne, and tell me whether all theſe doe not make this of

ours, generationem prauam, a froward generation; So as wee may too wel take vp Eſayes complaint, Ah ſinfull nation, a people laden with iniquity, a ſeed of euill doers, children that are corrupters. Eſa. 1. 4. Honorable &amp; beloued, how ſhould we be humbled vnder the hand of our God, in the ſenſe of our many, great, bold and lawleſſe ſinnes? What ſackcloth, what aſhes can be enough for vs? Oh that our faces could bee couered with confuſion; that wee could rend our hearts, and not our garments; Be afflicted, and mourne, and weepe, and thus Saue your ſelues from this froward generation.
            
            And ſo from St. Peters atteſtation to their wickedneſſe, wee deſcend to his obteſtation of their

redreſſe, Saue your ſelues. We muſt be ſo much ſhorter in the remedie, as we haue beene longer in the diſeaſe. The remedy is but of a ſhort ſound, but of a long extent, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . I vrge not the paſſiueneſſe of this aduiſe; that it is not, Saue your ſelues, but, Be ye ſaued: God is iealous of aſcribing to vs any power vnto good; we haue ability, we haue will enough to vndoe our ſelues; ſcope enough to hell-ward; neither motion nor will to good; that muſt bee put into vs by him that giues both poſſe, &amp; velle, &amp; poſſe velle; power to will, and will to do. This (Sauing) compriſes in it three great duties, Repentance for our ſinne; Auoidance of ſinners; Reluctation to ſin and ſinners.
            
               
Repentance. Perhaps, as St. Chryſoſtome, and Cyril think, ſome of theſe were the perſonall executioners of Chriſt; If ſo, they were the worſt of this generation; and yet they may, they muſt ſaue themſelues from this generation, by their vnfained repentance: Howſoeuer, they made vp no ſmall peece of the euill times, and had need to bee ſaued from themſelues, by their hearty contrition; Surely thoſe ſinnes are not ours, whereof we haue truly repented; The skin that is once waſhed is as cleane from ſoile, as if it had neuer beene foule; Thoſe legall waſhings, and rinſings ſhewed them what they muſt do to their ſoules, to their liues; This remedie, as it is vniuerſall, ſo it is perpetuall;

the warme waters of our teares, are the ſtreames of Iordan to cure our Leproſie, the Siloam to cure our blindneſſe, the poole of Betheſda to cure all our lameneſſe, and defects of obedience; Alas, there is none of vs but haue our ſhare in the common ſinnes; The beſt of vs hath helpt to make vp the frowardneſſe of our generation; Oh that we could vn-ſin our ſelues by our ſeaſonable repentance; Cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, and purge your hearts yee double minded.
            
            Auoydance is the next; Auoidance of all vnlawfull participation; There is a participation naturall, as to liue in the ſame ayre, to dwell in the ſame earth, to eat of the ſame meat; this we cannot

auoid, vnleſſe wee would goe out of the world, as St. Paul tells his Corinthes. There is a ciuill participation, in matter of commerce, and humane neceſſary conuerſation; This we need not auoid with lewes, Turkes, Infidels, Heretickes. There is a ſpirituall participation in morall things, whether good, or euill: In theſe lyes this 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ; and yet, not vniuerſally neither; wee are not tied to auoid the ſeruices of God, and holy duties for the commixture of leud men, as the fooliſh Separatiſts haue fancied; it is participation in euill that wee are here charged to auoid; although alſo intireneſſe, euen in ciuill conuerſation, is not allowed vs with notoriouſly wicked

and infectious perſons; The Iſraelites muſt hye them from the Tents of Corah; and, Come out of her my people. Chiefly, they are the ſins from which wee muſt ſaue our ſelues, not the men; if, not rather, from the men for the ſinnes; Haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, ſaith St. Paul, Epheſ. 5. 12. commenting vpon this 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                of St. Peter.
            
            There is nothing more ordinarie with our Caſuiſts, then the nine wayes of participation, which Aquinas, and the Schooles following him haue ſhut vp in two homely verſes, Iuſsio, conſilium, &amp;c. The ſumme is, that we doe not ſaue our ſelues from euill, if either we command it, or

counſell it, or conſent to it, or ſooth it, or further it, or ſhare in it, or diſſwade it not, or reſiſt it not, or reueale it not; Here would be worke enough (you ſee) to hold our preaching vnto St. Pauls houre, midnight; but I ſpare you, and would be loath to haue any Eutychus: Shortly, if we would ſaue our ſelues from the ſin of the time, wee may not command it, as Iezebel did to the Elders of Ieſreel; we may not aduiſe it, as Ionadab did to Amnon; wee may not conſent to it, as Bathſheba did to Dauid; wee may not ſooth it, as Zidkijah did to Ahab; wee may not further it, as Ioab did to Dauid; we may not ſhare in it, as Achitophel did to Abſalom; we may not forbeare to diſſwade it, as Hira
                     •
                  
               
               
the Adullamite to Iudah; to reſiſt it, as partiall Magiſtrates; to reueale it, as trecherous confeſſaries.
            But, of all theſe, (that we may ſingle out our laſt and vtmoſt remedy) here muſt bee a zealous reluctation to euill; All thoſe other negatiue cariages of not commanding, not counſelling, not conſenting, not ſoothing, not abetting, not ſharing, are nothing without a reall oppugnation of ſinne. Would we then thoroughly quit our ſelues of our froward generation? wee muſt ſet our faces againſt it to diſcountenance it; wee muſt ſet our tongues againſt it, to controule it; wee muſt ſet our hands againſt it, to oppoſe it; It goes 
                  •
               arr
                  •
                that of the Apoſtle, Yee haue not yet reſiſted vnto blood
               
               ſtriuing againſt ſinne, Heb. 12. 4. Loe here is a truely heroicall exerciſe for you great Ones; to ſtriue againſt ſinne, not ad ſudorem only, as Phyſicians preſcribe, but ad ſanguinem; Ye cannot better beſtow your ſelues then (in a loyall aſſiſtance of ſacred authority) vpon the debellation of the outragious wickedneſſe of the times. Theſe are the Dragons, and Gyants, and Monſters, the vanquiſhing wherof hath moralized the Hiſtories of your famous Progenitors. Oh do yee conſecrate your hands, and your hearts to God in beating down the headſtrong powers of euill; and as by repentance, and auoydance, ſo, by reluctation, S
                     •
                  ue your ſelues from this vntoward generation.
            
            
               
Now, what need I waſte the time in dehorting your Noble and Chriſtian ingenuity from participation of the Epidemicall ſinnes of a froward generation? It is enough motiue to you, that ſinne is a baſe, ſordid, diſhonourable thing; but, withall, let me adde only one diſſuaſiue from the danger, implyed in the very word Saue; for how are wee ſaued but from a danger? The danger both of corruption, and confuſion.
            Corruption; ye ſee before your eies that one yawning mouth makes many; This pitch will defile vs; One rotten kernell of the Pomegranate infects the fellowes; Saint Paul made that verſe of the heathen Poet, Canonicall, Euill conuerſation corrupts good manners;

What wofull experience haue we, euerie day, of thoſe, who by this meanes from a vigorous heat of zeale, haue declined to a temper of lukewarme indifferencie and then, 
                  •
               rom a careleſſe mediocrity, to all extremity of debauchedneſſe; and of hopfull beginners, haue ended in incarna
                  •
               e deuills? Oh the dangerous, and inſenſible inſinuations of ſinne; If that crafty tempter can hereby worke vs but to one dram of leſſe deteſtation to a familiarly inured euill, hee promiſeth himſelfe the victorie; It is well noted by Saint Ambroſe, of that chaſt Patriarch Ioſeph, that, ſo ſoone as euer his wanton Miſtreſſe had laid her impure hand vpon his cloake, he leaues it behinde him, that he might

bee ſure to auoyd the danger of her contagious touch; If the Spouſe of Chriſt bee a Lilly among thornes; (by the mighty protection of her omnipotent husband) yet take thou heed, how thou walkeſt amōgſt thoſe thornes, for that Lilly: Shortly▪ wouldeſt thou not bee tainted with wickedneſſe, abhorre the peſtilent ſocietie of leud men; and by a ſeaſonable ſubduction, thus, Saue thy ſelfe from a froward generation.
            
            The laſt and vtmoſt of all dangers is confuſion; That charge of God by Moſes is but iuſt, Numb. 16. 18. Depart, I pray you, from the tents of theſe men, and touch nothing of theirs, leſt ye periſh in all their ſinnes; Lo, the very ſtation,

the very touch is mortall. Indeed, what reaſon is there to hope or to plead for an immunity; If wee ſhare in the worke, why ſhould wee not take part of the wages? The wages of ſinne is death; If the ſtorke be taken damage faiſant with the Cranes, ſhee is inwrapped in the ſame net, and can not complaine to bee ſurprized. Qui cum lupis eſt, cum lupis vlulet, as he ſaid; Hee that is with wolues, let him howle with wolues: If we bee fratres in malo, brethen in euill, we muſt looke to bee inuolued in the ſame curſe; bee not deceiued; honorable and beloued, here is no exemption of greatneſs; nay, contrarily, eminence of place aggrauates both the ſinne, and the iudgement; when Ezra heard that

the hand of the Princes and Rulers had beene chiefe in that great offence, then he rent his cloathes, and tore his haire, Ezra 9. 3.
            Certainly this caſe is dangerous and fearfull, wherſoeuer it lights; Hardly are thoſe ſinnes redreſſed that are taken vp by the great; Eaſily are thoſe ſins diffuſed, that are warranted by great examples: The great lights of heauen, the moſt conſpicuous Planets, if they be eclipſed, all the Almanacks of all Nations write of it; whereas the ſmall Starres of the Galaxy are not heeded; All the Country runs to a Beacon on fire, no body regards to ſee a ſhrub flaming in a valley; Know then, that your ſins are ſo much greater, as your ſelues are; and, all the comfort

that I can giue you with out your true repentance, is, That mighty men ſhall bee mightily tormented; Of all other men therefore be ye moſt carefull to keepe your ſelues vntainted with the common ſins; and to renew your couenant with God; No man cares for a ſpot vpon a plaine, ruſſet, riding ſuit; but we are curious of a rich robe, euery mote there is an eye-ſore; Oh, bee yee carefull to preſerue your honour from all the foule blemiſhes of corruption; as thoſe that know vertue hath a greater ſhare in nobilitie, then blood; Imitate in this, the great frame of the Creation, which ſtill, the more it is remoued from the dregs of this earth, the purer it is; Oh ſaue yee your

ſelues from this vntoward generation, ſo ſhall yee helpe to ſaue your nation from the imminent iudgements of our iuſt God▪ ſo ſhall ye ſaue your ſoules in the day of the appearance of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; to whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, one infinite God, be all honour, and glory aſcribed, now, and for euer.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

