
   
      
         
            The olde religion a treatise, wherin is laid downe the true state of the difference betwixt the reformed, and Romane Church; and the blame of this schisme is cast vpon the true authors. Seruing for the vindication of our innocence, for the setling of wauering minds for a preseruatiue against Popish insinuations. By Ios. Hall, B. of Exon.
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1628
            
         
         Approx. 252 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02563
            STC 12690
            ESTC S117610
            99852822
            99852822
            18173
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02563)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18173)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 839:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The olde religion a treatise, wherin is laid downe the true state of the difference betwixt the reformed, and Romane Church; and the blame of this schisme is cast vpon the true authors. Seruing for the vindication of our innocence, for the setling of wauering minds for a preseruatiue against Popish insinuations. By Ios. Hall, B. of Exon.
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [46, 199, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by W[illiam] S[tansby] for Nathaniell Butter and Richard Hawkings,
                  London :
                  1628.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Running title reads: The old religion.
                  A8r is partially reset with 'Errata committed by the Printer, which will bee verie vnpleasing to the Reuerend Authour ..'( a variant has 'Errata, which will better instruct you in the true vnderstanding of the Authors meaning'); O4r headline has plain 'R' (a variant has swashed 'R').
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE OLDE RELIGION: A Treatiſe, Wherin is laid downe the true ſtate of the difference betwixt the Reformed, and Romane Church; and the blame of this ſchiſme is caſt vpon the true AVTHORS.
            SERVING For the vindication of our innocence, for the ſetl
                  •
               ng of wauering minds for a preſeruatiue againſt Popiſh inſinuations.
            By IOS. HALL, B. of Exon.
            LONDON, Printed by W. S. for Nathaniell Butter and Richard Hawkings. 1628.
         
         
            
            
            TO MY NEWE, AND DEARELY Affected charge, the Dioceſſe of EXCETER, All Grace and benediction.
            
               THe truth of my heart giues mee boldnes to profeſſe, before him, who onely knowes it, that the ſame God, who hath

cald me to the ouer-ſight of your Soules, hath wrought in me a zealous deſire of your ſaluation. This deſire cannot but incite mee to a carefull preuention of thoſe dangers, which might threaten the diſappointment of ſo happie an end: Thoſe dangers are either ſinnes of practice, or errours of of Doctrine: Againſt both theſe I haue faithfully vowed my vtmoſt indeuours. I ſhal labour againſt the firſt, by Preaching,

Example, Cenſures; Wherein it ſhall bee your choyce to expect either the rod, or the Spirit of meekeneſſe. Againſt the latter, my Pen hath riſen vp in this early aſſault. It hath beene aſſured mee, that in this time of late Vacancie, falſe Teachers, catching the Fore-locke of occaſion, haue beene buſie in ſcattering the tares of errours amongſt you: I eaſily beleeue it; ſince I know it is not in the power

of the greateſt vigilancie to hinder their attempts of euill. Euen a full See is no ſufficient barre to craftie ſeducers; Their ſuggeſtions wee cannot preuent, their ſucceſſe wee may: This I haue here aſſay'd to doe; bending my ſtile againſt Popiſh Doctrine, with ſuch Chriſtian moderation, as may argue zeale without malice, deſire to winne Soules, no will to gall them. And ſince the commoneſt of all the

grounds of Romiſh deceit is the pretence of their Age, and our Noueltie; and nothing doth more dazle the eyes of the ſimple, then the name of our forefathers, and the challenge of a particular recital of our profeſſors before Luthers reuolt, I haue (I hope) fully cleared this coaſt, ſo as out of the right apprehenſion of theſe differences, my reader ſhal euidently ſee the vanitie of this cauill, and find cauſe to bleſſe God

for the ſafetie of his ſtation in ſo pregnant, and vndeceiueable a truth.
            For me, I ſhame not to profeſſe, that I haue paſſed my moſt, and beſt houres in quiet Meditation; wherein I needed not bend mine edge againſt any Aduerſarie, but Satan, and mine own corruptions: Theſe controuerſorie points I haue rather croſt in my way, then taken along with me; Neither am I ignorant what incomparably

cleare beames (in this kind) ſome of the worthy lights of our Church haue caſt abroad into all eyes, to the admiration of preſent, and future times; no corner of truth hath lyen vnſearcht, no plea vnargued: the wit of man can not make any eſſentiall additions either to our proofes, or anſweres; But, as in the moſt perfect diſcouerie, where Lands and Riuers are ſpecially deſcried, there may bee ſome ſmall obſcure

in-lets reſerued for the notice of following experience; So is it in the buſineſſe of theſe ſacred quarrels; That braine is very vnhappie which meets not with ſome trauers of Diſcourſe more then it hath borrowed from anothers Pen; Beſides which, hauing fallen vpon a methode, and manner of Tractation, which might be of vſe to plain vnderſtandings, the familiaritie whereof promiſed to contribute, not

a little, to the information and ſetling of weaker ſoules, I might not hide it from you, to whoſe common good I haue gladly reſolu'd to ſacrifice my ſelfe: Let it bee taken with the ſame conſtruction of loue, wherewith it is tendred, and, that you may improoue this, and all other my following labours to a ſenſible aduantage, giue mee leaue to impart my ſelfe to you a litle in this ſhort, and free preamble.
            
               It is a large body, I know, and full of ordinate varietie, to which I now direct my words; Let mee awhile, in theſe lines, ſeuer them, whom I would neuer abide really diſ-ioyned.
            Yee my deare fellow-labourers (as my immediate charge) may well challenge the firſt place. It is no ſmall ioy to mee to expect ſo able hands, vpon whom I may comfortably vnloade the weight of this my ſpirituall

care: If fame doe not ouer-ſpeake you, there are not many ſoyles that yeeld either ſo frequent Flockes, or better fed; Goe on happily in theſe high ſteps of true bleſſedneſſe, &amp; ſaue your ſelues, and others; To which purpoſe; Let mee commend to you (according to the ſweete experience of a greater Shepheard) two maine helpes of our ſacred trade, firſt, the tender Paſtures, and ſecond the ſtill Waters; By the

one, I meane an inuring of our People to the principles of wholeſome Doctrine; By the other, an immunitie from all faction, and diſturbance of the publike peace.
            It was the obſeruation of the learnedſt King that euer ſate hitherto in the Engliſh Throne▪ that the cauſe of the miſ-carriage of our People into Poperie, and other errours, was, their vngroūdednes in the points of Catechiſme; How

ſhould thoſe ſoules bee but carried about with euerie wind of Doctrine, that are not wel Ballaſted with ſolid informations: Whence it was that his ſaid late Maieſtie (of happie memorie) gaue publike order for beſtowing the later part of Gods day in familiar Catechiſing; then which, nothing could bee deuiſed more neceſſarie, and behouefull to the Soules of men; It was the Ignorance, and Ill-diſpoſedneſſe

of ſome cauillers, that taxed this courſe, as preiudicial to Preachings Since, in truth, the moſt vſe-full of all Preaching is Catecheticall. This layes the grounds, the other raiſeth the wals, and roofe; this informes the iudgement, that, ſtirres vp the affections: What good vſe is there of thoſe affections that runne before the iudgement? Or of thoſe wals that want a foundation? For my part, I haue ſpent the

greater halfe of my life in this ſtation of our holy ſeruice: I thanke God, not vnpainefully, not vnprofitably; But, there is no one thing, whereof I repent ſo much, as not to haue beſtowed more houres in this publike Exerciſe of Catechiſme; In regard whereof, I could quarrell my very Sermons, and wiſh that a great part of them had beene exchanged for this Preaching conference: Thoſe other Diuine diſcourſes

enrich the braine &amp; the tong; this ſettles the heart; thoſe other are but the deſcants to this plain-ſong; Contemne it not, my Brethren, for the eaſie &amp; noted homelineſſe; The moſt excellent and beneficiall thinges are moſt familiar; What can bee more obuious then Light, Ayre, Fire, Water; Let him that can liue without theſe, deſpiſe their commonneſſe: Rather, as we make ſo much more vſe of the Diuine

bountie in theſe ordinarie benefits, ſo let vs the more gladly improoue theſe ready &amp; facil helps to the ſaluation of many ſoules; the neglect whereof breedes inſtabilitie of iudgment, meſpriſion of neceſſarie truths, faſhionableneſſe of profeſsion, frothineſſe of diſcourſe, obnoxiouſneſſe to all errour and ſeduction. And if any of our people loath this Manna, becauſe they may gather it from vnder their Feete, let not

their palates be humourd ic this wanton nauſeation: They are worthy to faſt, that are wearie of the Bread of Angels: And if herein we bee curious to ſatisfie their rouing appetite, our fauour ſhall be no better then Iniurious: So wee haue ſeene an vndiſcreete Schoole-maſter, whiles he affects the thankes of an ouerweening Parent, marre the progreſſe of a forward Child, by rayſing him to an higher forme, and

Author, ere he haue wel learned his firſt rules; whence followes an emptie oſtentation, and a late diſappointment: Our fidelitie and care of profit muſt teach vs to driue at the moſt ſure, and vniuerſall good, which ſhall vndoubtedly bee beſt attained by theſe ſafe and needfull ground-workes.
            From theſe tender paſtures let mee leade you, (and you, others) to the ſtill Waters; Zeale in the Soule is as naturall

heat in the body; there is no life of Religion without it; but as the kindlieſt heat, if it bee not tempered with a due equalitie of moyſture, waſts it ſelfe and the body; So doth zeale, if it be not moderated with diſcretion, and charitable care of the common good; It is hard to bee too vehement in contending for maine and euident truthes; but litigious and immateriall verities may ſoone be ouer-ſtriuen for; in the

proſecution whereof, I haue oft lamented to ſee how heedleſſe too many haue beene of the publike welfare; Whiles, in ſeeking for one ſcruple of truth, they haue not cared to ſpend a whole pound-weight of precious Peace.
            The Church of England, in whoſe motherhood wee haue all iuſt cauſe to pride our ſelues, hath, in much wiſdome, and pietie, deliuered her iudgment concerning all neceſſary points of religiō
               
in ſo compleat a body of Diuinitie, as all hearts may reſt in; Theſe wee read, theſe we write vnder, as profeſsing not their truth onely, but their ſufficiencie alſo. The voice of God our Father, in his Scriptures, and (out of theſe) the voyce of the Church our Mother in her Articles, is that, which muſt both guide and ſettle our reſolutiōs: Whatſoeuer is beſides theſe, is but either priuate, or vnneceſſarie and vncertain:

Oh that whiles we ſweat and bleed for the maintenance of theſe oracular truthes, we could be perſwaded to remit of our Heat in the purſuit of opinions: Theſe, theſe are they that diſtract the Church, violate our peace, ſcandalize the weake, aduantage our enemies. Fire vpon the Hearth warmes the body, but if it be miſ-placed, burnes the houſe: My brethren, let vs bee zealous for our God; Euery

heartie Chriſtian will powre Oyle, and not Water vpon this holy flame: But, let vs take heed leaſt a blind ſelfe▪ loue, ſtiffe preiudice, and factious partialitie impoſe vpon vs, in ſtead of the cauſes of God; Let vs be ſuſpicious of all New verities, and careleſſe of all vnprofitable; And let vs hate to thinke our ſelues either wiſer then the Church, or better then our ſuperiors: And if any man thinke that he

ſees further then his fellowes, in theſe Theologicall proſpects, let his tongue keepe the counſel of his eyes; Leaſt, whiles he affects the fame of deeper learning, he embroyle the Church, and rayſe his glory vpon the publike ruines.
            And ye worthy Chriſtians whoſe ſoules God hath entruſted with our ſpirituall Guardianſhip, be ye alike minded with your teachers; The motion of their tongues lyes

much in your eares; your modeſt deſires of receiuing needfull, and wholſome truthes, ſhal auoide their labour after friuolous, and quarrelſome curioſities. God hath bleſſed you with the reputation of a wiſe, and knowing people; In theſe diuine matters, let a meeke ſobrietie ſet boūds to your inquiries. Take vp your time, and hearts with Chriſt and Him crucified; with thoſe eſſentiall truthes which are neceſſarie

to ſaluation; Leaue al curious diſquiſitions to the Schooles, and ſay of thoſe problemes, as the Philoſopher did of the Athenian ſhops: How many things are here that we haue no need of. Take the neereſt cut yee can, yee ſhall finde it a ſide way to heauen, yee need not lengthen it with vndue circuitions. I am deceiued if (as the times are) yee ſhall not find worke enough to beare vp againſt the oppoſitions

of profeſſed hoſtility, it is not for vs to ſqander our thoughts and houres vpon vſe-leſſe janglings; Wherewith if we ſuffer our ſelues to be ſtill taken vp, Satan ſhal deale with vs like ſome craftie cheater, who whiles he holds vs at gaze with trickes of iugling, pickes our pockets.
            Deare brethren, what euer become of theſe worthleſſe driblets, bee ſure to looke well to the free-hold of your ſaluation.

Errour is not more buſie then ſubtile, Superſtition neuer wanted ſweet inſinuations: make ſure worke againſt theſe plauſible dangers, Suffer not your ſelues to bee drawne into the net by the common ſtale of the Church; Know that outward viſibilitie may too well ſtand with an vtter excluſion from ſaluation. Saluation conſiſts not in a formalitie of profeſsion, but in a ſoundneſſe of beliefe. A true

body may be ful of mortall diſeaſes: So is the Romane Church of this day; whom we haue long pitied, and laboured to cure in vaine; If ſhe will not bee healed by vs, let not vs be infected by her; Let vs bee no leſſe ielous of her Contagion, then ſhe is of our Remedies. Hold faſt that precious Truth, which hath been long taught you by faithfull Paſtors, confirmed by cleare euidences of Scriptures, euinced by

ſound reaſons, ſealed vp by the bloud of our bleſſed Martyrs; So whiles no man takes away the Crowne of your conſtancie, yee ſhall be our Crowne and reioycing in the day of the Lord Ieſus; To whoſe all-ſufficient grace I commend you al; and vow my ſelfe
            
               Your common Seruant in him whom we all reioyce to ſerue. IOS. EXON.
               
            
         
         
            
               
               
               The Contents.
               
                  CHAP. I.
                  THe extent of the differences betwixt the Churches. Fol. 1.
               
               
                  CHAP. II.
The Originall of the differences. Fol. 7.
               
               
                  
                  CHAP. III.
The Reformed vniuſtly charged with noueltie, hereſie, ſchiſme. 14.
               
               
                  CHAP. IV.
The Roman Church guiltie of this ſchiſme. 22
               
               
                  CHAP. V.
The newneſſe of the Article of Iuſtification by inherent righteouſneſſe. 27
                  
                     
                     
                        SECT. II
This doctrine proued to be againſt Scripture. 36
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 42
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. VI.
The newneſſe of the doctrine of merit 45
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 48.
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 50
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  CHAP. VII.
The newneſſe of the doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation. 53
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 62
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 67
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. VIII.
The newneſſe of the Halfe-Communion. 71
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 75
                     
                     
                        
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 77
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. IX.
The newneſſe of the Miſſall Sacrifice. 79
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture, 81
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 84
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. X.
The newneſſe of Image-worſhip. 87
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 94
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 98
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  CHAP. XI.
The newneſſe of Jndulgences and Purgatorie. 100
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 108
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Agai
                           •
                        ſt reaſon. 112
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. XII.
The newneſſe of Diuine Seruice in an vnknowne tongue. 114
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 120
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 122
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  CHAP. XIII.
The newneſſe of a full, forced Sacramentall Confeſsion. 124
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Not warranted by Scripture. 129
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 132
                     
                     
                        SECT. IV.
The noueltie of abſolution before ſatisfaction. 134
                     
                  
               
               
                  CAAP. XIV.
The newneſſe of the Romiſh Inuocation of Saints. 136
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 140
                     
                     
                        
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 146
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. XV.
The newneſſe of ſeuen Sacraments. 148
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Beſides Scripture. 152
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
Against reaſon. 154
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. XVI.
The newneſſe of the Romiſh Doctrine of Traditions. 156
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
Againſt Scripture. 162
                     
                     
                        
                        SECT. III.
Againſt reaſon. 66
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. XVII.
The newneſſe of the vniuerſall Headſhip of the Biſhop of Rome. 169
                  
                     
                        SECT. II
The newneſſe of challenged Infallibilitie. 177
                     
                     
                        SECT. III.
The newneſſe of the Popes ſuperioritie to Councels. 179
                     
                     
                        SECT. IV.
The new preſumption of Papall Diſpenſations. 182
                     
                     
                        
                        SECT. V.
The new challenge of Popes domineering ouer Kings and Emperours. 185
                     
                  
               
               
                  CHAP. XVIII.
The Epilogue both of Exhortation, and Apologie. 190
               
            
         
         
            
            An Aduertiſement.
            COurteous Reader; I ſhall entreat you where you finde ſome few, either 
                  •
               iterall, or verball faults, to haue recourſe to this following Errata committed by the Printer, which will bee verie vnpleaſing to the Reuerend Authour (who is many miles diſtant from the Preſſe) which errors if you ſhall vouchſafe to pardon in this Impreſſion, they ſhall be more carefully amended in the next.
            
               N. B.
            
         
         
            
            Errata.
            PAg. 5. in margine, for Probant, read Prolaeus pag. 9. in marg. for Pierius, read Prierius. p. 10. l. 8. for angry part, read angry to part. pag. 11. lin. 7. for profeſſe, read profeſſeth. p. 15. in marg. for Haereſia, read Hereſes. p. ibid. in marg. for Bellidanus, read Bellidauus. p. 22. in marg. for Puſhius read Pighius. p. ibid. for Turrectſm read Turrecremat. p. 24. l. 6. for cenſures, read cenſurers. p. 4
                  •
               . l. 23. for by And, read by faith. And
               ▪ p. 43. l. 22. for muddle, read muddie
               ▪ p. 48. l. 3. for habita, read habitatio. p. 48. l. 3. for them yeelding. read them; yeelding. p. 62. l· 5. for Barengarius, read Bereng
                     •
                  rius. p. 118. dele that. p. 124. l. vlt. dele not. p. 140. l. 14. for practices, read practicers. p. 148. l. 5. read mirrour. p. 150. l 14. for vnneceſſarie, read neceſſarie. p. 163. l. 18. for Salonons, read Salomons.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE OLD RELIGION.
            
               CHAP. I. The extent of the differences betwixt the Churches.
               
                  THe firſt bleſſing that I dayly begge of my God, for his Church, is,Ioh. 14.27. our Sauiours Legacie, Peace: that ſweete Peace; which in the verie name of it comprehends all happineſſe both of eſtate and diſpoſition.Adrichoni deſcr. Hiero fol. fig. 19
                           •
                        .
                   As that mountaine whereon Chriſt aſcended, though it abounded with Palmes, and Pines, and Mirtles, yet it caried onely the name of Oliues, which haue beene an ancient Embleme of Peace: Other graces are

for the beautie of the Church; this for the health and life of it; For how ſo euer,Faciunt fau
                        •
                     ; &amp; v
                        •
                     ſ
                        •
                     e faciunt Eccleſias &amp; Marcionitae. Ter tull. aduer. Marcion. l. 4. c 5.
                   euen Waſpes haue their Combes, and heretickes their aſſemblies (as Tertullian,) ſo as all are not of the Church that haue Peace; yet ſo eſſentiall is it to the Church, in Saint Chryſoſtomes opinion,Eccleſiae nomen conſenſus, concordiae
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      eſt Chryſoſt. com. in Ep. ad Gal. that the very name of the Church implyes a conſent, and concord; No maruel then if the Church labouring here below, make it her dayly ſuite to her glorious Bride-grome in heauen, Da pacem, giue Peace in our time, O Lord: The meanes of which happineſſe are ſoone ſeene, not ſo ſoone attained; euen that which Hierome hath to his Ruffinus,
                  Sit inter nes vna fides &amp; illico pax ſequetur Hier. aduerſ. Ruff. 
                  Vna fides; Let our beleefe be but one, and our hearts will be one.
               But ſince, as Eraſmus hath too truely obſerued,Eraſm. Epiſt. l. 20. Paulo Decimario. there is nothing ſo happie in theſe humane things, wherein there is not ſome intermixtures of diſtemper;1. Cor. 11. and S. Paul hath told vs, there muſt be hereſies, and

the Spouſe, in Salomons Song,Cantic. 2. vlt. compares her bleſſed husband to a yong Hart vpon the mountaine of Bether; that is, Diuiſion; Yea, rather,Victor. Perſer. Afric. l. 5.
                   as vnder Genſericus, and his Vandals, the Chriſtian Temples flamed higher then the Townes; ſo for the ſpace of theſe laſt hundred yeeres, there hath beene more combuſtion in the Church, then in the ciuill ſtate; My next wiſh is, that if differences in Religion cannot bee avoided, yet that they might bee rightly iudged off, and be but taken as they are. Neither can I but mourne, and bleede, to ſee how miſerably the World is abuſed on all hands with preiudice in this kinde: whiles the aduerſe part brands vs with vniuſt cenſures, and with loude clamours cries vs downe for heretickes: On the other ſide, ſome of ours, doe ſo ſleight the errours of the Romane Church, as if they were not worth our contention;Spalat. de hiſt. Eccleſ. tom. vlt. lib. 7.
                   as if our Martyrs had beene raſh, and our quarrels trifling; Others

againe doe ſo aggrauate them, as if we could neuer bee at enough defiance with their opinions, nor at enough diſtance from their communion. All theſe three are dangerous extremities; The two former whereof ſhall (if my hopes faile me not) in this whole diſcourſe be ſufficiently conuinced; wherein as wee ſhal fully cleare our ſelues from that hateful ſlander of hereſie, or ſchiſme, So we ſhall leaue vpon the Church of Rome, an vnauoydable imputation of many no leſſe foule, and enormious, then nouell errours; to the ſtopping of the mouthes of thoſe Adiaphoriſts,Melanct. Poſtill. de Baptiſmo Chri. whereof Melancthon ſeemes to haue long agoe propheſied; Metuendum eſt, &amp;c. It is to be feared (ſaith he) that in the laſt age of the world this errour will raigne amongſt men, that either Religions are nothing, or differ onely in words.
               
                  Diog Laert.The third comes now in our way; That which Laertius ſpeakes of Menedemus that in Diſputing his

very eyes would ſparkle, is true of many of ours, whoſe zeale tranſports them to ſuch a deteſtation of the Romane Church,Hooker. Eccleſ. Pol. l 4. §. 3. Comment. in Euang. ſaepe. Patres noſtri &amp; ſaluberrimam conſuetudinem tenuerunt vt quicquid diuinum ac legitimum, &amp;c. Aug-Ne
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      propter paleam relinquimus aream Domini, ne
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      propter piſees malos rumpimus retia domini Aug, Epiſt. 48 Sic Anabaptiſtae accuſant Paedobaptiſmum. Papiſmi Cliſton, contr. Smith. Sic Neariani Trinitatem arguunt &amp; articulum Papae. Probant· Faſcic· c. 1.
                   as if it were all errour, no Church; affecting nothing more, then an vtter oppoſition to their doctrine and ceremonie, becauſe theirs; Like as Maldonate profeſſeth to miſlike and auoide many faire interpretations, not as falſe, but as Caluins: Theſe men haue not learned this in Saint Auſtens Schoole, who tels vs, that it was the rule of the Fathers well before Cyprian and Agrippinus, as ſince, that whatſoeuer they found in any ſchime or hereſie, warrantable and holy, that they allowed for its owne worth, and did not refuſe it for the abettors; Neither for the chaffe doe we leaue the floore of God, neither for the bad fiſhes doe we breake his nets. Rather, as the Prieſts of Mercurie had wont to ſay, when they eate their Figs and Honie, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c. All truth is ſweet; it is indeed Gods, not ours, whereſoeuer it is found,

the Kings coyne is currant, though it be found in any impure channell.
               
                  Nos fatemur ſub papatu plurimum eſſe boni Chriſtiani, imo omne bonum Chriſtianum; dico inſuper &amp; imo vero verum nucleum Chriſtianitatis. Luther. in Epiſt. ad 2. pleb. de Anabapt. cit
                        •
                     a Cromero de falſa relig. Lutheran.For this particular; they haue not well heeded that charitable profeſſion of zealous Luther (Nos fatemur, &amp;c) We profeſſe (ſaith hee) that vnder the Papacy there is much Chriſtian good, yea all; &amp;c. I ſay moreouer, that vnder the Papacie is true Chriſtianitie, yea the very kernell of Chriſtianitie, &amp;c. No man I truſt will feare that feruent ſpirits too much exceſſe of indulgence; vnder the Papacie may bee as much good, as it ſelfe is euill; Neither doe we cenſure that Church for what it hath not;Aliud eſt credere quod Papa credit, aliud credere quod eſt Papae. Prolaeus. ibid. vbi ſupr. but for what it hath: Fundamentall truth is like that Maronaean wine, which if it bee mixed with twentie times ſo much water holds his ſtrength: The Sepulchre of Chriſt was ouer-whelmed by the Pagans with earth and rubbiſh;Euſeb. de vita Conſtantini. l. 3. c. 25.
                   and and more then ſo; ouer it, they built a Temple to their impure Venus; yet ſtill, in ſpight of malice, there was the Sepulchre of Chriſt; and it

is a ruled caſe of Papinian,
                  Iuſtin. Tit. 1. §. 4. Annot. in leg. 12. Tan. that a ſacred place looſeth not the holineſſe, with the demoliſhed walles; No more doth the Romane, looſe the claime of a true viſible Church, by her manifold and deplorable corruptions; her vnſoundneſſe is not leſſe apparent, then her being; If ſhee were once the ſpouſe of Chriſt, and her adulteries are knowne, yet the diuorce is not ſued out.
            
            
               CHAP. II. The Originall of the differences.
               
                  IT is too true that thoſe two maine Elements of euill (as Timon called them) Ambition and Couetouſneſſe,Magiſtris vtentes Ambitione &amp; Auaritiá Bern, ad Henric Senonenſem. which Bernard profeſſes were the great Maſters of that Clergie in his times, hauing palpably corrupted the Chriſtian World,

both in doctrine and manners, gaue iuſt cauſe of ſcandall, and complaint to godly minds;Quae fuerant vitia, mores fiunt. Ger
                        •
                     . de negligentia prae
                     
                        •
                     atorum. Ex Seuet. Grauam. Germ. Which (though long ſmothered) at laſt brake forth into publike conteſtation; augmented by the fury of thoſe guiltie defendants, which loued their reputation more then peace: But yet ſo, as the complainants euer profeſſed a ioynt allowance of thoſe fundamentall truths, which diſcried themſelues, by their bright luſtre, in the worſt of that confuſion; as not willing that God ſhould leeſe any thing by the wrongs of men, or that men ſhould leeſe any thing by the enuie of that euill ſpirit,Matth. 13.25. which had taken the aduantage of the publike ſleepe for his tares: Shortly then, according to the Prayers and predictions of manie holy Chriſtians, God would haue his Church reformed; How ſhall it be done?Per diſciplinam &amp; 
                        •
                     e
                        •
                     um, nun 
                        •
                     u imſponia. 
                        •
                     en. Licentious courſes (as Seneca wiſely) haue ſometimes beene amended by correction, and feare, neuer of themſelues; As therefore their owne preſident was ſtirred

vp in the Councell of Trent,Corrigenda &amp; 
                        •
                     eformanda eſt Eccleſiaſtica diſciplina quae iam diu deprauata at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      corrup. &amp;c. Orat. praeſid. conc. Trid ſeſ. 11 Prim or dia cuncta Pauida ſunt. Caſſiod. Luther offered 95. Concluſ. to be Diſputed at Wittenb. Io. Tecelius. offers the contrarie Propoſ. at Francfort. Vid. hiſt. Conc. Trid. lib. 1. Lutherus, &amp;c. Ita venio beatiſſime Pater, &amp;c. Et adhuc proſtratus rogo, &amp;c. Epi. ad Leonem▪ 
                     10 Ibid. Lut. 1 Eckius &amp; Silueſter Pieríus write ag. Luth. vid. hiſtor. Conc Trid. Saepe ſolutiſue repeſtifera. Ser Iames Hogo ſtrata Dominican Inquiſitor ſtirs vp Pope Leo to capitall puniſhments of Luther and his followers. Ibid hiſt. Concil. to crie out of their corruption of diſcipline; So was the ſpirit of Luther, ſomewhat before that, ſtirred vp to taxe their corruption of Doctrine; but, as all beginnings are timerous, how calmely did he enter, and with what ſubmiſſe Supplications did hee ſue for redreſſe? I come to you (ſaith he) moſt holy Father, and humbly proſtrate before you, beſeech you, that, if it be poſſible, you would be pleaſed to ſet your helping hand to the worke, Intreaties preuaile nothing; The whiles, the importune inſolence of Eckius, and the vndiſcreete carriage of Caietan (as Luther there profeſſes) forced him to a publike oppoſition. At laſt (as ſometimes euen poyſons turne medicinall) the furious proſecution of abuſed Authoritie increaſed the zeale of truth; Like as the repercuſſion of the flame intends it more; And as zeale grew in the plaintiue, ſo did

rage in the defendant;A primordio iuſtitiam vim patitur ſtatim vt coli Deus coepit inuidiam religio ſortita eſt. Tert. Scorpiac. aduerſ. Gnoſtic. c. 8.
                   So as now that was verified of Tertullian (A primordio, &amp;c. From the beginning righteouſneſſe ſuffers violence, and, no ſooner did God begin to be worſhipped, but Religion was attended with enuie. The maſters of the Pythoniſſe are angrie part with a gainefull (though euill) gueſt: Am I become your enemie becauſe I tolde you the truth? ſaith Saint Paul, yet that truth is not more vnwelcome, then ſucceſſefull;Bapt. Porta. For, as the breath of a man that hath chewed Saffron diſcolours a Painted face, ſo this blunt ſinceritie ſhamed the glorious falſhood of ſuperſtition.
               
                  Leonis Bulla. Anno 1518.
                  The proud offenders, impatient of reproofe, trie what fire and faggot can doe for them; and now according to the old word,Punitis ingenijs gliſcit authoritas. ſuppreſſed ſpirits gather more authoritie; as the Egyptian violence rather addeth to Gods Iſrael. In ſo much as Eraſmus could tell the Rector of Louan,
                  Eraſm. Godeſch. Roſemund. that by burning Luthers bookes they might rid him from the Li
                  
                     •
                  raries

of men, not from their hearts.
               The ventilation of theſe points dif
                  
                     •
                  uſed them to the knowledge of the world; and now, vpon ſerious ſcanning,Non defuiſſe magnos Theologos qui non verebantur affirmare nihil eſſe in Luthero quin per probatos Authores defendi poſsit. Eraſ. lib. Epiſt. 15. Godeſchalco Roſemund, &amp;c. Theod. Bez▪ contr. Andreā, &amp;c. vid. hiſtor, conc. Trid. l. 1.
                   it came to this (as that honor of Rotterdam profeſſe (Non defuiſſe) 
                     •
                  hat there wanted not great Di
                  
                     •
                  ines, which durſt confidently affirme, that there was nothing in Luther, which might not be defended by good and allowed Authors.
               Nothing doth ſo whet the edge of wit as contradiction; Now, hee, who at firſt, like the blind man in 
                     •
                  he Goſpell (it is Bezaes compariſon) ſaw men like trees, vpon more cleare light, ſees and wonders at 
                     •
                  hoſe groſſe ſuperſtitions, and tyrannies, wherewith the Church of God had beene long abuſed: And 
                     •
                  ow, as the firſt Hue and Crie rayſeth a whole Countrie, the world was awakned with the noyſe, and ſtartling vp, ſaw, and ſtood amazed to ſee its owne ſlauerie and beſot
                  
                     •
                  edneſſe: Meane while; That God,

who cannot bee wanting to himſelfe,Hulr. Zu
                        •
                     ng
                        ••
                     us in Eccl. Zurich. opon
                        ••
                      ſe Tratij Sampſoni Mediolan. Franciſ. Hugo Conſtantienſ. Epiſco
                        •
                     us opponit ſe Zuin glio. ibid. Bullaſecunda Leonis Papae. An. 1520.
                   rayſeth vp abettors to his truth; The contention growes, Bookes flie abroad on both parts. Straight Buls bellow from Rome nothing but death, and damnation to the oppoſites; Excommunications are thundred out, from their Capitoline powers, againſt all the partakers of this (ſo called) hereſie; the flaſhes of publike Anathemaes ſtrike them downe to hell.
               The condemned reprouers ſtand vpon their owne integritie, call heauen and earth to record, how iuſtly they haue complained, how vniuſtly they are cenſured; in large Volumes defending their innocence; and, challenging an vndeniable part in the true viſible Church of God, from which they are pretended to bee eiected;Anna. 1518. Vid. Histor. Concil. Trid. l. 1.
                   appeale, (next to the Tribunall of Heauen) to the ſentence of a free generall Councell, for their right.
               Profer is made at laſt of a Synode at Trent; but neither free, nor

generall; nor ſuch,Tres ſalui-conductus conceſsi Proteſtantibus, ſed quam fruſtra. vid. Iunij animaduerſiones in Bellar. as would afford (after all ſemblances) either ſafetie of acceſſe, or poſſibilitie of indifferencie; That partiall meeting (as it was Vid Epiſt. Epi. Q
                        •
                     in
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Eccleſ. in hiſtor. Concil Trid. Iudicandi poteſtas apud accuſatores erat. Ruffin. hiſt. l 1. cap. 17. 
                     
                        •
                     . q. Mu
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     , &amp;c. 3. q. 7. Nullus debet. Sententia non praeſentibus partibus dicta nullius moment
                        •
                      eſt Caſſiod. de Amicit. c 5. Nullus ante rectam cognitionem cauſae debet priuari ſuo iure. Rodriguez. Caſ. conſ. c. 241.
                   prompted to ſpeake) condems vs vnheard; right ſo as Ruffinus reports it in that caſe of Athanaſius; Iudicandi poteſtas, &amp;c. The power of iudging was in the accuſers; contrarie to the rule of their owne Lawe; Non debet, &amp;c. The ſame partie may not bee the Iudge, accuſer witneſſe; contrarie to that iuſt rule of Theodericus, reported by Caſsiodore (Sententia, &amp;c.) The ſentence that is giuen in the abſence of the parties is of no moment. We are ſtill where we were, oppoſing, ſuffering. In theſe termes wee ſtand, what ſhall wee ſay then, if men would either not haue deſerued, or haue patiently indured reproofe, this breach had neuer beene. Woe bee to the men by whom this offence commeth; For vs, that rule of Saint Bernard ſhall clearely acquit vs, before

God,Cum carpuntur vitia &amp; inde ſcandalum orituripſo ſibi ſcandali cauſa eſt qui fecit quod argui debet, non ille qui arguit. Bernard. ad Hug. de Sancto Vict▪ Epiſt. 78.
                   and his Angels (Cum carpuntur vitia, &amp;c.) When faults are taxed, and ſcandall growes, hee is the cauſe of the ſcandall, who did that which was worthie to bee reproued not he that reproued the ill doer.
            
            
               CHAP. III. The reformed vniuſtly charged with noueltie, hereſie, ſchiſme.
               
                  Nos vetera in ſtauramus, noua non prodimus Eraſ. Godeſchalco, &amp;c.
                  BE it therefore knowne to all the World, that our Church is onely Reformed, or Repaired, not made new: There is not one ſtone of a new foundation laide by vs; Yea, the old wals ſtand ſtill; Onely the ouer-caſting of thoſe ancient ſtones which the vntempered morter of new inuentions,
                     Ʋide. Fregeu
                        •
                     llij Politi
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Reforme. An. 1588.
                   diſpleaſeth vs. Plainely, ſet aſide the corruptions,

and the Church is the ſame: And what are theſe corruptions, but vnſound adiections to the ancient ſtructure of Religion; Theſe we cannot but oppoſe; and are therefore vniuſtly, and imperiouſly eiected; Hence it is that ours is by the oppoſite ſtiled an Ablatiue,Haereſia non tam docent credere, noua, quam vetera non credere: magis enim hereſis in non credendo. Ioan. Lenſaeus Bellidanus de Chriſtiana libert l. 12. c. 7.
                   or negatiue Religion; for ſo much as wee ioyne with all true Chriſtians in all affirmatiue poſitions of ancient faith, onely ſtanding vpon the deniall of ſome late and vndue additaments to the Chriſtian beleefe; Or if thoſe additions bee reckoned for ruines:Durand. Ration. lib. 1; It is a ſure rule which Durandus giues concerning materiall Churches, applyable to the ſpirituall; that if the Wall be decayed, not at once but ſucceſſiuely, it is iudged ſtill the ſame Church, and (vpon reparation) not to bee reconſecrated, but onely reconciled. Well therefore may thoſe mouthes ſtop themſelues, which loudly call for the names of the Profeſſors of our faith,Fiſher. contr. D. White, &amp; D. Featly. in all ſucceſſions of times, till Luther
                  
look't forth into the World. Had wee gone about to broach any new poſitiue Truths, vnſeene, vnheard of former times, well and iuſtly might they challenge vs for a deduction of this line of doctrine, from a pedigree of Predeceſſours; Now, that we only diſclayme their ſuperfluous, and nouell opinions, and practices, which haue beene by degrees thruſt vpon the Church of God, retayning inuiolably all former Articles of Chriſtian faith, how idle is this plea, how worthy of hiſſing out? Who ſees not now that all we need to doe, is, but to ſhow that all thoſe points which wee cry downe in the Romane Church, are ſuch, as carrie in them a manifeſt brand of newneſſe, and abſurditie. This proofe will cleerely iuſtifie our refuſall; Let them ſee how they ſhall once, before the awfull Tribunall of our laſt Iudge,Accuatio non debet admitti quae non procedit ex charitate 4. qu. 5.
                   iuſtifie their vncharitableneſſe, who ceaſe not vpon this our refuſall to eiect, &amp; condemne vs.
               
                  The Church of Rome is ſicke;Nec inficior Rom. Eccleſiam à priſco ſuo decore &amp; splendore non parum diuerſam, multiſque morbis, &amp; vitijs deformatam. Caſſde Offic. boni vir, &amp;c. Vtilia vero &amp; nolenti ingerenda. Bern. de vita Solit. Lutherus porrexit orbi pharmacum violentum &amp; amarum; Id quale, quale ſit optarim vt aliquid bonae ſanitatis, &amp;c. Eraſ. Georgio Saxon. Duci. l. 21. Nouis morbis nouis obuiandum medicamentis. Bern. ep. 161.
                   Ingenuous Caſſander confeſſeth ſo; (nec inficior, &amp;c.) I deny not (ſaith he) that the Romane Church is not a little changed from her ancient beautie, and brightneſſe, and that ſhee is deformed with many diſeaſes, and vicious diſtempers; Bernard tels vs how it muſt bee dieted; profitable, though vnpleaſing, medicines muſt bee poured into the mouth of it; Luther, and his aſſociates did this office (as Eraſmus acknowledgeth; (Lutherus porrexit) Luther, ſaith hee, gaue the World a potion violent, and bitter; what euer it were, I wiſh it may breed ſome good health in the bodie of Chriſtian people, ſo miſerably foule with all kinds of euils. Neuer did Luther meane to take away the life of that Church, but the ſickneſſe;Dulcior eſt religioſa caſtigatio, quam blanda remiſſio. Ambr. in obit. Theodoſſer. 6.
                   Wherein (as Socrates anſwered to his Iudges) ſurely, he deſerued recompence, in ſteed of rage; For as Saint Ambroſe worthily; (Dulcior eſt) ſweeter is a

religious chaſtiſement, then a ſmoothing remiſſion.
               This that was meant to the Churches health, proues the Phyſitians diſeaſe; ſo did the bitterneſſe of our wholſome draughts offend, that we are beaten out of doores;Non fu
                        •
                     us ſed 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 
                        •
                     auſ
                        ••
                     b. ad Per
                        •
                     n. Qui ab Eccleſia &amp; communio 
                        ••
                     , &amp;c. Cyrill, orat. de exitis Animae. Opertebat quidem nihil non ferre ne Eccleſiam Deiſcinderes. Di
                        •••
                     . ad Nouat Euſeb. l. S. c. 44. &amp;c. Neither did wee runne from that Church, but are driuen away, as our late Soueraigne profeſſeth by Caſaubons hand; Wee know that of Cyrill is a true word; Thoſe which ſeuer themſelues from the Church, and communion, are the enemies of God, and friends of Deuils; and that which Dionyſius ſaid to Nouatus; Any thing muſt rather be borne, then that we ſhould rend the Church of God: Farre, far was it from our thoughts, to teare the ſeameleſſe coate; or, with this precious Oyle of Truth to breake the Churches head;
               
                  Qui ſtatum conturbat Eccleſiae ab eius liminibus arceatur. 2. Epiſt. Alexand. Pap.We found iuſt faults; elſe, let vs bee guiltie of this diſturbance. If now, choler vniuſtly exaſperated with an wholſome reprehenſion,

haue broken forth into a furious perſecution of the gaineſayers, the ſinne is not ours; If we haue defended our innocence with blowes, the ſinne is not ours. Let vs neuer proſper in our good cauſe, if all the water of Tyber can waſh off the bloud of many thouſand Chriſtian ſoules that hath beene ſhed in this quarrell, from the hands of the Romiſh Prelacie. Surely, as it was obſerued of olde, that none of the Tribe of Leui, were the profeſſed followers of our Sauiour, ſo it is too eaſie to obſerue, that, of late times,Ingenia generoſa doceri capiunt, cogi non ferunt; cogere tyrannorum eſt, cogi tantum aſinorum. Eraſ. Roſumdauo. vbi ſupra. Cauendum eſt ne cum r
                        •
                     m dubiam emendare volumus maiora vulnera faciamus. Alip. Aug. Epiſt, 239.
                   this Tribe hath exerciſed the bittereſt enmitie vpon the followers of Chriſt. Suppoſe wee had offended in the vndiſcreet managing of a iuſt reproofe; it is a true rule of Eraſmus, that generous ſpirits would bee reclaymed by teaching, not by compulſion; and as Alipius wiſely to his Auguſtine; Heed muſt bee taken, leaſt whiles wee labour to redreſſe a doubtfull complaint, wee make greater wounds then we find.

Oh how happy had it beene for Gods Church, if this care had found any place in the hearts of her Gouernours; who regarding more the entire preſeruation of their own honour, then Truth, and Peace, Were all in the harſh language of warre (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) ſmite, kill, burne, perſecute: Had they beene but halfe ſo charitable to their moderne reprouers, as they profeſſe they are to the fore-going, how had the Church flouriſhed in an vnterrupted vnitie?Index Expurgat. Belg. iuſſu Phil. 2. Antwerp. Offic. Plaut. In Catholicis veteribus alios plurimos, &amp;c. In the old Catholike Writers (ſay they) wee beare with many errours, wee extenuate, and excuſe them, wee find ſhifts to put them off; and deuiſe ſome commodious ſenſes for them; Guiltineſſe, which is the ground of this fauour, workes the quite contrarie courſes againſt vs: Alas, how are our Writings racked, and wreſted to enuious ſenſes, how miſconſtrued, how peruerted, and made to ſpeake odiouſly on purpoſe to worke diſtaſte, to enlarge quarrell,

to draw on the deepeſt cenſures.
               Woe is mee, this cruell vncharitableneſſe is it, that hath brought this miſerable calamitie vpon diſtracted Chriſtendome; Surely,Magdeb, Cent. 2.
                   as the aſhes of the burning Mountaine Veſuuius being diſperſed farre and wide, bred a grieuous Peſtilence in the Regions round about; ſo the aſhes that flie from theſe vnkindly flames of diſcord haue bred a wofull infection, and death of ſoules through the whole Chriſtian World.
            
            
               
               CHAP. IIII. The Church of Rome guiltie of this Schiſme.
               
                  Quae 
                        〈◊〉
                      deprauata at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      corr
                        •
                     sp
                        •
                     a, 
                        •
                     arum 
                        〈…〉
                      haere
                     
                        •••
                     m magna ex pa
                        ••
                      cauſa origo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      
                     
                        •
                     x
                        •
                     iti
                        •
                     . Ore
                        •
                     , praeſ, Cone. Trid. ſeſſ. 11. Pe
                        ••
                     us Oxon. ſum. concil. ſub ſixto 4. Si authoritas quaer. tur. orbis 
                        〈◊〉
                      eſt vr
                        ••
                     e 
                        〈…〉
                      fuerit 
                        〈…〉
                      Romae, ſiue Eu
                     
                        •••
                     lij Hic 
                        〈…〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     gria. 
                        〈◊〉
                      d
                        •
                     ctr. fid. Tem. 1 
                     
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                      P
                        •
                     ſ
                        •
                     us. Hierar. Eccl. l. 6.3. Turrect
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , &amp; alij Vid. Mart. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . lib. 4. c. 2. §. 6.
                  
                  IT is confeſſed by the Preſident of the Tridentine Councell, that the deprauation of diſcipline and manners of the Romane Church, was the chiefe cauſe and originall of theſe diſſenſions. Let vs caſt our eyes vpon the doctrine, and wee ſhall no leſſe find the guilt of this fearefull Schiſme to fall heauily vpon the ſame heads.
               For firſt; (to lay a ſure ground;) Nothing can be more plaine then that the Romane is a particular Church, as the Fathers of Baſil well diſtinguiſh it, not the vniuerſall; though we take in the Churches of her ſubordination or correſpondence: This truth we might make good by authoritie, if our very ſenſes did not ſaue vs the labour,
               
                  Secondly,
                     Anſwer of the Biſhop of S. Dauids Chapl. to Fiſher. Nec Papa, nec Epiſcopus proprie poteſt propoſitionem alihaereticare, No particular Church (to ſay nothing of the vniuerſall ſince the Apoſtolike times) can haue power to make a fundamental point of faith; It may explane or declare, it cannot create Articles.
               Thirdly, Only an errour againſt a point of faith is Hereſie.
               Fourthly, Thoſe points wherein wee differ from the Romaniſts are they, which only the Church of Rome hath made fundamentall, and of Faith.
               Fiftly, The reformed, therefore,Gerſ. An liceat in cauſis fidei, &amp;c. being by that Church illegally condemned for thoſe points are not heretickes.
               Hee is properly an Hereticke,Nil. Theſſal. Orat. de diſſenſ. Is proprie haereticus dicitur qui ſuo ipſius iudicio condemnatus ſ
                        ••
                      ſponte ſeipſum eijcit ab Eccleſia. Hoſius de legitimis Iudicibus rerum, Eccleſiaſ
                        •
                     icarum. l. 2.
                   (ſaith Hoſius), who being conuicted in his owne iudgement, doth of his owne accord caſt himſelfe out of the Church; For vs, we are neither conuicted in our owne iudgement; nor in the lawfull iudgement of others; We haue not willingly caſt our ſelues out of the Church, but howeuer wee are ſaid to be violently

eiected, by the vndue ſentence of malice, hold our ſelues cloſe to the boſome of the true Spouſe of Chriſt, neuer to bee remoued; As farre therefore from Hereſie as Charitie is from our Cenſures. Only wee ſtand conuicted by the doome of good Pope Subeſſe Romano, &amp;c. Extr. de maior. &amp; obe
                        •
                     . vnam, &amp;c. 
                  Boniface; or S
                        •
                     lu. Prier. Epitom. resp. ad Luther. l. 2. c. 7.
                   
                  Sylueſter Prierius. Quicunque non, &amp;c. Whoſoeuer doth not relie himſelfe vpon the Doctrine of the Romane Church, and of the Biſhop of Rome as the infallible rule of faith, from which euen the Scripture it ſelfe receiues her force, he is an Hereticke. Whence followes that the Church of Rome condemning and eiecting thoſe for Heretickes which are not, is the authour of this wofull breach in the Church of God.
               I ſhall therefore, I hope, abundantly ſatisfie all wiſe and indifferent Readers, if I ſhall ſhow that thoſe points which wee refuſe, and oppoſe, are no other then ſuch, as by the confeſſions of ingenuous authors

of the Romane part,Nilus imputat diuiſiones orbis Chriſtiani praeſumptioni Romanae Eccleſiae, quae ſuſceperit in ſe abſque Graecis definire de rebus fidei, &amp; contra ſentientes anathema te ferire. Orat. de diſſenſ. Eccleſ. haue beene (beſides their inward falſity) manifeſt vpſtarts; lately obtruded vpon the Church) ſuch as our ancient Progenitours in many hundreds of ſucceſſions, either knew not, or receiued not into their beliefe, and yet both liued and dyed worthy Chriſtians. Surely it was but a iuſt ſpeech of Saint Bernard, and that which might become the mouth of any Pope, or Councell; (Ego ſi peregrinum, &amp;c.
                  Ego ſi peregrinum dogma induxero ipſe peccaui, Bern. in Cant. ſer. 30. Cit. Demoſth. Annotat. in leg. 12. Tab.) If I ſhall offer to bring in any ſtrange opinion; it is my ſinne: It was the wiſe Ordinance of the Thurians, as Diodorus Siculus reports, that he who would bring in any new Law amongſt them to the preiudice of the old, ſhould come with an halter about his necke into the aſſembly, and there, either make good his proiect, or die. For, howeuer in humane Conſtitutions (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ,
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Modeſt. Annot. ibid. &amp;c.) the later orders are ſtronger then the former; yet, in Diuinity, Primum verum; The firſt is true, as

                  Tertullians rule is; The old way is the good way, according to the Prophet; Heere wee hold vs; and becauſe we dare not make more Articles then our Creedes, nor more ſinnes then our Ten Commandements, we are indignely caſt out.
               Let vs therefore addreſſe our ſelues roundly to our promiſed taske; and make good the noueltie, and vnreaſonableneſſe of thoſe points we haue reiected; Out of too many Controuerſies diſputed betwixt vs, we ſelect only ſome principall; and out of infinite varieties of euidence, ſome few irrefragable teſtimonies.
            
            
               
               CHAP. V. The newneſſe of the Article of Iuſtification by inherent righteouſneſſe.
               
                  TO begin with Iuſtification.Card. de Monte praeſ. Concil. Orat. ſua. ſeſſ. 11. profeſſes what they meant to haue diſpatcht in 15. dayes; coſt ſeuen moneths worke. Vnica formalis cauſa eſt iu
                        •
                     titia Dei non qua ipſa iuſtus eſt, ſed qua nos iuſtos facit, &amp;c. Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 6.
                   The Tridentine Fathers, in their ſeauen moneths debating of this point, haue ſo cunningly ſet their words, that the errour which they would eſtabliſh, might ſeeme to be either hid, or ſhifted; Yet, at the laſt, they ſo far declare themſelues, as to determine, that the only formall cauſe of our Iuſtification is Gods Iuſtice, not by which he himſelfe is Iuſt, but by which he makes vs iuſt; wherewith being endowed by him wee are renewed in the ſpirit of our mindes, and are not only reputed, but are made truly iuſt, receiuing euery man his owne meaſure of Iuſtice, which the Holy Ghoſt diuides to him, according to each

mans prediſpoſition of himſelfe,Secundum propriam cuiuſque diſpoſitionem &amp; cooperationem. ibid. Si quis dixerit, &amp;c. per eam ipſam for maliter iuſtos eſſe. Vel ſola imputatione iuſtitiae Chriſti, vel ſola remiſſione peccatorum &amp;c. anathema ſit. Can. 10.11.
                   and cooperation; And withall, they denounce a flat Anathema to all thoſe, who ſhall dare to ſay that wee are formally iuſtified by Chriſts righteouſneſſe, or by the ſole imputation of that righteouſneſſe; or, by the ſole remiſſion of our ſinnes, and not by our inherent Grace diffuſed in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt; Which termes they haue ſo craftily laid together, as if they would caſt an aſperſion vpon their aduerſaries, of ſeparating the neceſſitie of ſanctification from the pretended Iuſtification by faith; wherein all our words and writings will abundantly cleare vs, before God and men; That there is an inherent iuſtice in vs, is no leſſe certaine, then that it is wrought in vs by the Holy Ghoſt. For God doth not iuſtifie the wicked man as ſuch;Nunquam remittetur culpa quin fimul inſundatur iuſtitia. Bell. l. 2. de Iuſtificat. c. 13.
                   but of wicked makes him good; not by meere acceptation, but by a reall change; whiles hee iuſtifies him whom hee ſanctifies; Theſe two acts of Mercie

are inſeparable;Perfecta ſunt opera Dei ex Deuter. 32. Bellarm. l. 2. de Iuſtif. c. 14. Iuſtitiam in nobis recipientes vnuſquiſque ſuam ſecundum menſuram quam Spiritus Sanctus partitur ſingulis prout vult, &amp; ſecundum propriam cuiuſque dispoſitionem. Conc. Trid. vbi ſupra. But this Iuſtice being wrought in vs by the holy Spirit, according to the modell of our weake receit, and not according to the full power of the infinite agent, is not ſo perfect, as that it can beare vs out before the Tribunall of God.
               It muſt bee onely vnder the garment of our elder Brother, that wee dare come in for a bleſſing; His righteouſneſſe made ours by faith, is that whereby wee are iuſtified in the ſight of God; This doctrine is that which is blaſted with a Tridentine curſe.
               Heare now the hiſtorie of this doctrine of Iuſtification, related by their Andrew Vega (de Iuſtif. l. 7. c. 24.) Magna fuit, &amp;c. Some ages ſince (ſaith hee) there was a great concertation amongſt Diuines, what ſhould bee the formall cauſe of our Iuſtification: ſome thought it to be no created iuſtice, infuſed into man, but only the fauour and mercifull acceptation of God. In which opinion

the Maſter of Sentences is thought by ſome to haue beene: Others whoſe opinion is more common, and probable, held it to bee ſome created qualitie informing the ſoules of the iuſt; This opinion was allowed in the Councell of Vienna: And, the Schoole-doctors after the Maſter of Sentences deliuered this not as probable only, but as certaine: Afterwards, when ſome defended the oppoſite part to be more probable, it ſeemed good to the holy Synode of Trent, thus to determine it. So as, till the late Councell of Trent (by the confeſſion of Vega himſelfe) this opinion was maintayned, as probable only; not as of faith:Forenſe vocab. Iuſtif. verbum Iuſtificandi in alia ſignificatione vfurpant patres. Chemnit. exam de Iuſtif. Cauſa formalis propter quam homo dicitur iustus coram Deo, Bell. l. 2. de Iuſtif. c. 1.
                   Yea, I adde, by his leaue, the contrary was till then moſt currant.
               It is not the Logick of this point, we ſtriue for; It is not the Grammer; it is the Diuinitie: What is that whereby wee ſtand acquitted before the righteous Iudge, whether our inherent Iuſtice, or Chriſts

imputed Iuſtice apprehended by faith;
                     Yet in the next Chapter he corrects this propter in Chemnitius; and expreſſes it by per. l. 2. c. 2. Chryſoſt. in Gen. hom. 2. O miſerecordiae magnitudinem, &amp;c. repente
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      iuſtus apparet. Chryſ. in Galat. c. 3. Crux ſuſtulit execrationem fides inuexit iuſtitiam iuſtitiam iuſtitia vero gratiam ſpiritus allexit. Ambroſ. de Iacob. &amp; vita beata. Non operibus iuſtificamur ſed fide, quoniam carnalis infirmitas, &amp;c. Ibid. c. 6. Non gloriabor quia mens, &amp;c. Similiter de Cain &amp; Abel. l. 1. c. 9. de fuga, ſec. c. 3 &amp; 7.
                   The Diuines of Trent are for the former, all Antiquity with vs for the latter. A iuſt Volume would ſcarce contayne the pregnant Teſtimonies of the Fathers to this purpoſe.
               Saint Chryſostome tels vs it is the wonder of Gods mercie, that hee who hath ſinned, confeſſeth, is pardo
                     •
                   ſecured, and ſuddenly app
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  ſt; Iuſt, but how? The 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  ooke away the Curſe (ſaith be
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  oſt ſweetly. Faith brought in Righteouſneſſe, and Righteouſneſſe drew on the Grace of the Spirit.
               Saint Ambroſe tels vs that our carnall infirmitie blemiſheth our workes, but that the vprightneſſe of our faith couers ours errours, and obtaines our pardon; And profeſſeth that hee will glory, not for that he is righteous, but for that hee is redeemed, not for that he is void of ſinnes, but for that his ſinnes are forgiuen him.
               
                  
                  Hieron. aduerſ. Pelag. l. 1. Tunc iuſti ſumus imperfectos nos, &amp;c.Saint Ierome tels vs then wee are iuſt when we confeſſe our ſelues ſinners, and that our righteouſneſſe ſtands not in any merit of ours, but in the meere mercie of God; and, that the acknowledgement of our imperfection, is the imperfect perfection of the Iuſt.
               
                  Gregor. in Ezech. hom. 7. ad finem iuſtus igitur aduocatus noſter, &amp;c.Saint Gregorie tels vs that our Iuſt Aduocate ſhall defend vs righteous in his iudgement, becauſe we know and accuſe our ſelues vnrighteous, and that our confidence muſt not be in our acts, but in our Aduocate.
               But the ſweete and paſſionate ſpeeches of Saint Auſten, and Saint Bernard would fill a Booke alone; neither can any reformed Diuine either more diſparage our inherent Righteouſneſſe,Ergo fratres, omnes de plenitudine eius accepimus, de pl
                        •
                     
                     nitudine miſerecordiae, &amp;c. Quid? Remiſſionem peccatorum vt iuſtificaremur ex fide, Auguſt. Tract. 3. in Ioannem· or more magnifie and challenge the imputed; It ſhall ſuffice vs to giue a taſte of both:
               We haue all therefore, Brethren, receiued of his fulneſſe; Of the fulneſſe of his mercie, of the abundance of his goodneſſe haue we receiued; What? Remiſſion of ſinnes

that we might be iuſtified by faith; And what more, Grace for Grace; that is, for this Grace wherein we liue by faith, we ſhall receiue another; ſaith that diuineſt of the Fathers; And ſoone after;Omnes qui ex Adam cum peccato, peccatores omnes qui per Chriſtum iuſtificati, iuſti non in ſe, ſed in illo. Nam in ſe ſi interroges Adam ſunt &amp;c. Ibid. August. All that are from ſinfull Adam, are ſinners, all that are iuſtified by Chriſt, are iuſt, not in themſelues; but in him; for in themſelues, if ye aske after them, they are Adam; in him, they are Chriſts. And elſewhere; Reioyce in the Lord, and bee glad, O yee righteous: O wicked, O proud men that reioyce in your ſelues;Laetamini &amp;c. O qui laetamini in vobis, O impij, O ſuperbi qui laetamini in vobis; iam credentes in eum qui iuſtificat impium, &amp;c. Aug. 2. Enarrat in Pſal. 31. Quis accuſauit, &amp;c. Sufficit mihi ad omnem iuſtitiam ſolum habere propitiū cui ſoli peccaui. now beleeuing in him who iuſtifieth the wicked, your faith is imputed to you for righteouſneſſe.
               Reioyce in the Lord; Why? Becauſe now yee are iuſt; and whence are yee iuſt? Not by your owne Merits, but by his Grace; Whence are yee iuſt? becauſe yee are iuſtified.
               Who ſhall lay any thing to the 
                     •
                  harge of Gods Elect? It ſufficeth 
                     ••
                  ee for all righteouſneſſe, that I

haue that God propitious to mee, againſt whom only I haue ſinned; All that he hath decreed not to impute vnto mee, is as if it had not beene;Omne quod &amp;c. Non peccare Dei iuſtitia eſt: hominis iuſtitia indulgentia Dei, Bern. in Cantic. ſer. 23. Et ſi miſerecordia Domini, &amp;c. Nunquid iuſtitias meas. Domine memorabor iuſtitae 
                        •
                     ue ſoli
                        •
                     es, &amp;c. Not to ſinne is Gods Iuſtice, mans iuſtice is Gods indulgence, ſaith Deuout Bernard.
               
               How pregnant is that famous profeſſion of his. And if the mercies of the Lord be from euerlaſting, and to euerlaſting; I will alſo ſing the mercies of the Lord euerlaſtingly; What, ſhall I ſing of my owne righteouſneſſe? No Lord, I will remember thy righteouſneſſe, alone; for that is mine too; Thou art made vnto me, of God, righteouſneſſe;Non eſt pallium breue, &amp;c. ſhould I feare that it will not ſerue vs both? It is no ſhort Cloake, that it ſhould not couer twaine;Et te pariter &amp; me operiet largiter larga &amp; aeterna iuſtitia, &amp;c. Bern. ſup. Cant. ſerm. 61.
                   Thy righteouſneſſe is a righteouſneſſe for euer; and what is longer then eternitie? Behold thy large and euerlaſting mercie will largely couer both thee, and mee, at once; In mee it couers a multitude of ſinnes, in thee, Lord,

what can it couer but the treaſures of pittie, the riches of bountie: Thus he.
               What ſhould I need to draw downe this Truth through the times of Anſelme, Lombard, Bonauenture, Gerſon.
               
               The Manuell of Chriſtian Re
                  
                     •
                  igion ſet forth in the Prouinciall Councell of Coleyne,
                  Bellarm. de Iuſtif. l 2. c. 1. &amp; l. 3. c. 3.
                   ſhall ſerue for 
                     •
                  ll; Bellarmine himſelfe grants them 
                     •
                  erein ours; and they are worth 
                     •
                  ur entertayning;Qui liber ab omnibus eruditoribus Theologis etiam per Italiam &amp; Galliam ſummope
                        •
                     e commendatus fui
                        •
                     , &amp;c. Caſſ. Conſult. Art. 4.
                   That Booke is 
                     •
                  ommended by Caſſander, as mar
                  
                     •
                  ellouſly approued by all the lear
                  
                     •
                  ed Diuines of Italy, and France, 
                     •
                  s that, which notably ſets forth the 
                     •
                  umme of the iudgement of the Ancients concerning this, and o
                  
                     •
                  her points of Chriſtian Religion; 
                     •
                  
                  Nos dicimus, &amp;c.
                  Nos dicimus hominem per fidem donum iuſtificationis tum demum accipere, &amp;c. Enchirid. Colon.) Wee ſay that a 
                     •
                  an doth then receiue the gift of 
                     •
                  uſtification by faith, when being 
                     ••
                  rrified, and humbled by repen
                  
                     ••
                  nce, hee is againe rayſed vp by 
                     ••
                  ith; beleeuing that his ſinnes are 
                     ••
                  rgiuen him for the Merits of

Chriſt; who hath promiſed remiſſion of ſinnes to thoſe that beleeue in him; and when he feeles in himſelfe new deſires; ſo as deteſting euill, and reſiſting the infirmitie of his fleſh, he is inwardly inkindled to an indeauour of good; although this deſire of his be not yet perfect. Thus they, in the voyce of all Antiquitie; and the-then-preſent Church. Only the late Councell of Trent hath created this opinion of Iuſtification a point of faith.
               
                  SECT. II. The errour hereof againſt Scripture.
                  YEt if age were all the quarrel
                        •
                      it were but light, For, thoug
                        •
                      newneſſe in diuine Truths is a iu
                        •
                      cauſe of ſuſpition, yet wee doe no
                        •
                      ſo ſhut the hand of our munifice
                        •
                     
                     
God, that he cannot beſtow vpon 
                        •
                     is Church new illuminations in 
                        •
                     ome parcels of formerly-hidden 
                        •
                     erities; It is the charge both of 
                        •
                     heir Canus, and Caietan,
                     Can. loc. com. l. 7. c. 3. reſ. haec de Caiet. that no 
                        •
                     an ſhould deteſt a new ſenſe of Scripture for this, that it differs 
                        •
                     rom the ancient Doctors; for God 
                        •
                     ath not (ſay they) tyed expoſition 
                        •
                     f Scripture to their ſenſes.
                  Yea,Quò iuniores, cò perspicaciores. Salmer. in Rom. 5. Diſput. 51.
                      if we may beleeue Salme
                        
                           •
                        on, the later Diuines are ſo much 
                        •
                     ore quick-ſighted; they, like the Dwarfe ſitting on the Gyants 
                        •
                     houlder, ouer-looke him that is 
                        •
                     arre taller then themſelues.Haereſes non tam nouitas quam veritas reuincit. Tertull. de Veland. Virgin. This 
                        •
                     oſition of the Romane Church is 
                        •
                     ot more new, then faultie: Not 
                        ••
                      much noueltie, as Truth con
                     
                        •
                     inceth Hereſies, as Tertullian; We 
                        •
                     ad beene ſilent, if wee had not 
                        •
                     und this point (beſides the late
                     
                        •
                     eſſe) erroneous: Erroneous; both 
                        •
                     gainſt Scripture, and Reaſon. A
                     
                        ••
                     inſt Scripture, which euery where 
                        •
                     acheth, as, on the one ſide the 
                        ••
                     perfection of our inherent righteouſneſſe,

ſo, on the other, our perfect Iuſtification by the imputed righteouſneſſe of our Sauiour, brought home to vs by faith.
                  
                     Iob 9.2, 3.The former Iob ſaw from his dung-hill; How ſhould a man bee iuſtified before God? If hee will contend with him, hee cannot anſwere one of a thouſand; Whence it is,Prou. 20.9. that wiſe Salomon askes, Who can ſay, My heart is cleane; I am pure from ſinne: And himſelfe anſwers; There is not a iuſt man vpon earth,Eccleſ. 7.20. which doth good, and ſinneth not. A truth which (beſides his experience) hee had learned of his Father Dauid,
                     Pſal. 141.2. who could ſay▪ 
                     Enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant (though a man after Gods owne heart) for in thy ſight ſhal
                           •
                         no man liuing bee iustified. And i
                           •
                         thou,
                     Pſal, 130.3. 
                     Lord, ſhouldſt marke iniquities▪ O Lord, who ſhall ſtand?
                  
                  
                     Eſa. 64.6.For wee are all as an vncleane thing (we ſaith the Prophet Eſay, including euen himſelfe) and all our righteouſneſſe are as filthy ragges▪
                     
                     
And was it any better with the beſt Saints vnder the Goſpell? I ſee (ſaith the choſen Veſſell) in my members,
                     Rom. 7.23. 
                     another law warring againſt the law of my minde, and leading mee captiue to the law of ſinne, which is in my members.
                  
                  
                     So as in many things wee ſinne all:
                     Iam. 3.2. 
                     And if we ſay that we haue no ſinne,
                     1 Ioh. 1, 8. 
                     we doe but deceiue our ſelues, and there is no truth in vs.
                  
                  The latter, is the ſumme of Saint Pauls Sermon at Antioch;Acts 13.39. Bee it 
                        •
                     nowne vnto you, Men and brethren, that through this man is prea
                        
                           •
                        hed to you forgiueneſſe of ſinnes; and 
                           •
                        y him all that beleeue are iustified: They are iuſtified, but how? Freely,
                     Rom. 3.24. 
                     
                        
                           •
                        y his Grace: What Grace? Inherent in vs, and working by vs? No; 
                        
                           •
                        y Grace are yee ſaued through faith;
                     Epheſ. 2.8, 9. 
                     
                        
                           •
                        nd that, not of your ſelues; it is the 
                           •
                        ift of God. Not of workes, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt. Workes are ours, 
                        
                           •
                        ut this is righteouſneſſe of God,
                     Rom 3.22. 
                     which 
                           〈◊〉
                         by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, to all 
                           •
                        hem that beleeue. And how doth

this become ours? By his gracious imputation:Rom. 4.5. 
                     Not to him that worketh, but beleeueth in him who iuſtifieth the wicked, is his faith imputed for righteouſneſſe.
                  
                  Loe; it is not the act, not the habit of faith that Iuſtifieth, it is he that iuſtifies the wicked, whom our faith makes ours, and our ſinne his; He was made ſinne for vs, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him.
                     2 Cor. 5.21. Loe, ſo were wee made his righteouſneſſe, as he was made our ſinne. Imputation doth both; It is that which enfeoffes our ſinnes vpon Chriſt, and vs in his righteouſneſſe; which both couers and redreſſes the imperfection of ours. That diſtinction is cleere, and full;Philip. 3.9. 
                     That I may be found in him, not hauing mine owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith. Saint Paul was a great Saint; he had a righteouſneſſe of his owne (not as a Phariſee only, but as an

Apoſtle) but that which hee dares not truſt to, but forſakes; and cleaues to Gods: not, that eſſentiall righteouſneſſe, which is in God, without all relation to vs, nor that habit of iuſtice which was remayning in him; but that righteouſneſſe, which is of God,Rom. 5 1. by faith made ours. Thus being iuſtified by faith, we haue peace with God through our Lord Ieſus Christ. For what can breake that peace but our ſinnes?Rom. 8 33. 2 Cor. 5.19. 2 Cor. 5.21. Rom. 3.28. Rom. 4 6. Ad haec vide. Gen. 15.6. Eſa. 45.25. Eſa. 50.8. Eſa. 53.11. Rom. 3.20. &amp; 3.26. Rom. 3.30. Rom 4 2, 3. Rom. 4.9. &amp; 16. Rom. 5.9.18.19 Rom 8 1. Rom. 10.5, 10. 1 Cor. 4 4. Gal. 2.16. Gal. 3.6. Gal. 3.11.22.24. and thoſe are remitted; For, who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect, it is God that iuſtifies: And in that remiſſion is grounded our reconciliation; For God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelfe, not imputing their ſinnes vnto them; but contrarily, imputing to them his owne righteouſneſſe, and their faith for righteouſneſſe. Wee conclude then, that a man is iuſtified by And bleſſed is hee to whom the Lord imputes righteouſneſſe without works: Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiuen, and whoſe ſinnes are couered
                  
                  
                     Let the vaine ſophiſtry of carnall minds deceiue it ſelfe with idle ſubtilties, and ſeeke to elude the plaine truth of God, with ſhifts of wit; we bleſſe God for ſo cleere a light; and dare caſt our ſoules vpon this ſure euidence of God; attended with the perpetuall atteſtation of his ancient Church.
               
               
                  SECT. III. Againſt Reaſon.
                  
                     Non maius eſt creare coelum &amp; terram quàm peccatores iuſtificare. Gerſ. Tract. ſup. Magnificat. 10.
                     LAſtly, Reaſon it ſelfe fights againſt them. Nothing can formally make vs iuſt but that which is perfect in it ſelfe; How ſhould it giue what it hath not? Now our inherent righteouſneſſe, at the beſt, is in this life,Bern. de verbis Eſai. ſer. 5.
                      defectiue (Noſtra ſiqua est humilis, &amp;c.) Our poore Iuſtice (ſaith Bernard) if we haue any, it is true, but it is not pure: For how

ſhould it be pure, where we cannot but be faultie? Thus hee. The challenge is vnanſwerable.
                  To thoſe that ſay they can keepe Gods Law, let mee giue Saint Hieromes anſwere to his Cteſiphon;
                     Hieron. ad Cteſiphontem. 
                     Profer quis impleuerit; Show mee the man that hath done it: For, as that Father elſe-where,Hieron. de filio prodigo. 
                     In thy ſight ſhall none liuing be iustified; Hee ſaid not, no man, but, none liuing; not Euangeliſts, not Angels, not Thrones, not Dominions; If thou ſhalt marke the iniquities euen of thine Elect,Bern. in Cantic. ſer. 73. Iuſtitia actualis imperfecta &amp;c. non deſinit tamen eſſe vera iuſtitia, &amp; ſuo quodam modo perfecta. Bell. de Iuſtif. l. 2. c. 14.
                      ſaith Saint Bernard, Who ſhall abide it? To ſay now that our actuall iuſtice, which is imperfect through the admixtion of veniall ſinnes, ceaſeth not to bee both true and (in a ſort) perfect iuſtice, is, to ſay, there may be an vniuſt iuſtice, or a iuſt iniuſtice; that euen muddie water is cleare, or a leprous face beautifull.
                  Beſides, all experience euinceth our wants: For as it is Saint Anſtens true obſeruation; Hee that is renued from day to day, is not all

renued, and ſo much as he is not renued, ſo much he muſt needs bee in his olde corruption;Aug. ad Hieron. ep. 29.
                      And, as hee ſpeakes to his Hierome, of the degrees of Charitie; there is in ſome more, in ſome leſſe, in ſome none at all; but the fulleſt meaſure which can receiue no increaſe is not to bee found in any man, whiles hee liues here; and ſo long as it may bee increaſed, ſurely that which is leſſe then it ought, is faulty; from which faultineſſe it muſt needs follow, that there is no iuſt man vpon earth which doth good, and ſinneth not; and thence in Gods ſight ſhall none liuing be iuſtified. Thus he. To the very laſt houre our Prayer muſt be, Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes; Our very daily indeuour therefore of increaſing our renouation conuinceth vs ſufficiently of imperfection; and the imperfection of our Regeneration conuinceth the impoſſibilitie of Iuſtification by ſuch inherent righteouſneſſe.
                  In ſhort therefore ſince this doctrine

of the Roman Church is both new and erroneous; Againſt Scripture and reaſon; we haue iuſtly refuſed to receiue it into our beliefe; and for ſuch refuſall are vniuſtly eiected▪
                  
               
            
            
               CHAP. VI. The newneſſe of the doctrine of Merit.
               
                  MErit is next;Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 6. c. 16. can. 32. ſi quis &amp;c. augmentum gratiae, vitam aeternam, &amp; ipſius vitae aeternae conſecutionem Anathema ſit, &amp;c. wherein the Councell of Trent is no leſſe peremptory. If any man ſhall ſay that the good workes of a man iuſtified doe not truly merit eternall life, let him bee Anathema.
               
               It is eaſie for errour to ſhroud it ſelfe vnder the ambiguitie of words; The word Merit hath been of large vſe with the Ancient, who would haue abhorred the preſent ſenſe;

with them it ſounded no other then Obtayning,O foelix culpa quae talem meruit habere ſaluatorem, Eccleſia cauit in benedictione Cerei. Salm. in 1 Tim. 1. Apostoli à ſuis ciuibus occidi meruerunt, Aug. in Pſal. 35. Maiorest mea iniquitas quàm vt veniam merear. Gen. 3. Vulg. Tral. vid. Mort. Appell. or Impetration; not, as now, earning in the way of condigne wages, as if there were an equalitie of due proportion betwixt our Workes, and Heauen; without all reſpects of pact, promiſe, fauour; according to the bold Comment of Sotus, Tollet, Pererius, Costerus, Weſton and the reſt of that ſtraine.
               Farre, farre was the gracious humilitie of the Ancient Saints from this ſo high a preſumption; Let Saint Baſil ſpeake for his fellowes;Manet ſempiterna requies, &amp;c. Baſil. in Pſal. 114. 
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , &amp;c. Ʋeteres omnes ſummo conſenſu tradunt, &amp;c. caſſand. Conſult. de bonis quaeſt. Eternall reſt remaynes for thoſe who in this life haue lawfully ſtriuen, (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c.) not for the Merits of their deedes, but of the grace of that moſt munificent God in which they haue truſted: Why did I name one; when they all with full conſent (as Caſſander witneſſeth) profeſſe to repoſe themſelues wholly vpon the meere mercie of God, and merit of Chriſt, with an humble renunciation of all worthineſſe in their owne workes.

Yea that vnpartiall Author deriues this Doctrine euen through the lower Ages of the Schoolemen,Neque ab hac &amp;c. Scholaſtici ſcriptores &amp; recentiores Eccleſiaſtici, &amp;c. and later Writers; Thomas of Aquine, Durand, Adrian de Traiecto (afterwards Pope) Clictoueus, and deliuers it for the voyce of the then preſent Church; And, before him,Tho. Wald. tom. 6. ſacr. Tit. 1. c. 7. Thomas Wald. praeclarus Wicklifiſtarum impugnator. Andr. Vega. l. 7. de Cauſis Iuſtif. c. 24.
                   
                  Thomas Waldenſis the great Champion of Pope Martine, againſt the miſcalled Hereticks of his owne name, profeſſes him the ſounder Diuine, and truer Catholique, which ſimply denies any ſuch Merit, and aſcribes all to the meere grace of God, and the will of the giuer. What ſhould I need to darken the ayre with a cloud of witneſſes, their Gregorie Ariminenſis, their Brugenſis, Marſilius, Pighius, Eckius, Ferus, Stella, Faber Stapulenſis; Let their famous Preacher Royard ſhut vp all (Quid 
                        •
                     gitur is qui Merita praetendit, &amp;c.
                  Royard. tom. 5. Dominic. 11. poſt Pentecoſt.) Whoſoeuer he be that pretends his Merits, what doth hee elſe but deſerue Hell by his Workes?
               Let Bellarmines Tutiſsimum eſt, &amp;c.
                  
ground it ſelfe vpon Saint Bernards experimentall reſolution, Periculoſa habita est, Perilous is their dwelling place who truſt in their owne Merits, perillous, becauſe ruinous; All theſe and many more teach this, not as their owne doctrine, but as the Churches; Either they and the Church whoſe voyce they are, are Hereticks with vs, or we orthodoxe with them; and they and wee with the Ancients.
               The noueltie of this Romane Doctrine is accompanied with Errour; Againſt Scripture, againſt Reaſon.
               
                  SECT. II. Againſt Scripture.
                  THat God doth graciouſly accept, and munificently recompence our good workes, euen with

incomprehenſible glory, we doubt not, we denie not; but this, either out of the riches of his mercy, or the iuſtice of his promiſe; but that we can earne this at his hands, out of the intrinſecal worthines of our acts, is a challenge too high for fleſh and bloud, yea, for the Angels of Heauen.
                  How direct is our Sauiours inſtance of the ſeruant comne out of the field, and commanded by his Maſter to attendance.Luc. 17.9, 10. 
                     Doth hee thanke that ſeruant becauſe hee did the things that were commanded him? I trow not; ſo likewiſe yee, When yee ſhall haue done all things which are commanded you, ſay, we are vnprofitable ſeruants; Vnprofitable perhaps (you will ſay) in reſpect of meriting thankes; not vnprofitable in reſpect of meriting wages;Rom. 4.4. For to him that worketh is the reward, not reckoned of grace, but of debt: True; therefore herein our caſe differeth from ſeruants, that wee may not looke for Gods reward as of debt, but as of Grace; By grace are

yee ſaued through faith;Epheſ. 2.8. neither is it our earning, but Gods gift. Both, it cannot be; For if by grace, then it is no more of workes (euen of the moſt renued) otherwiſe grace is no more grace;Rom. 11.6. but if it be of workes, then it is no more grace, otherwiſe worke ſhould bee no more worke; Now,
                     Tit. 3.5. 
                     not by workes of righteouſneſſe which we haue done (at our beſt) but according to his mercie he ſaueth vs; Were our ſaluation of workes, then ſhould eternall life be our wages, but now;Rom. 5.23. 
                     The wages of ſinne is death, but the gift of God is eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.
                  
               
               
                  SECT. III. Against Reaſon.
                  IN very reaſon, where all is of meere dutie, there can bee no merit; for how can wee deſerue reward

by doing that which if we did not, we ſhould offend? It is enough for him that is obliged to his taske, that his worke is well taken: Now, all that wee can poſſibly doe, and more, is moſt iuſtly due vnto God by the bond of our Creation, of our Redemption; by the charge of his royall Law; and that ſweet Law of his Goſpell: Nay, alas, wee are farre from beeing able to compaſſe ſo much as our dutie; In many things we ſinne all. It is enough that in our glory we cannot ſinne;Alex. Peſaut. m. 1.2ae. qu. 4. Artic. 4. disp. 4.
                      though their Faber Stapulenſis would not yeeld ſo much, and taxeth Thomas for ſaying ſo; with the ſame preſumption that Origen held the very good Angels might offend;Gloria eſt gratia conſummata. P. Ferius Specim. Schol. Orth. c. 13.
                      Then is our grace conſummate; Till then our beſt abilities are full of imperfection; 
                        •
                     herefore the conceit of merit is not more arrogant, then abſurd.
                  We cannot merit of him whom we gratifie not: We cannot gratifie 
                        •
                      man with his owne; All our good 
                        •
                     s Gods alreadie; his gift, his proprietie:

                     What haue wee that we haue not receiued?
                     1 Cor. 4.7. Not our Talent only, but the improouement alſo is his meere bountie; There can be therefore no place for Merit.
                  In all iuſt Merit there muſt needs be a due proportion betwixt the act, and the recompence. It is of fauour if the gift exceed the worth of the ſeruice.
                  Now, what proportion can bee betwixt a finite, weake, imperfect obedience (ſuch is ours at the beſt) and an infinite, full and moſt perfect glory;Peſaut. in. 3. Th. q. 1. art. 2. Valor phyſicus &amp; entitatiu
                           ••
                        s operum Chriſti, &amp;c. The bold Schooles dare ſay that the naturall and entitatiue value of the workes of Chriſt himſelfe was finite, though the moral
                        •
                      value was infinite. What then ſhall bee ſaid of our workes, which are like our ſelues,Abſit vt iuſti vitam aeternam expectent ſicut pauper eleemoſynam. Ruard. Tap. ex Artic. Colon. Aug. de verb. Apoſt. ſer. 2.
                      meere imperfection; We are not ſo proud that we ſhould ſcorne (with Ruard. Tapperus) to expect Heauen as a poore man doth an Almes; rather, (according to Saint Auſtens charge (Non ſit cap
                           ••
                        turgidum, &amp;c.) (Let not the hea
                        •
                     
                     
bee proud, that it may receiue a Crowne.) We doe with all humilitie, and ſelfe-deiection looke vp to the bountifull hands of that God, who crowneth vs in mercie and compaſſion.
                  This Doctrine then of Merit being both new and erroneous, hath iuſtly merited our reproofe and deteſtation; and we are vniuſtly cenſured for our cenſure thereof.
               
            
            
               CHAP. VII. The newneſſe of the Doctrine of Tranſſubſtantiation.
               
                  THe point of Tranſſubſtantion is iuſtly ranked amongſt our higheſt differences.Fons Idolomaniarum Tranſſubſtan. Melanct. Ad amicum, 1544. Boxhorn. Iſag. ad concord. l. 3.
                   Vpon this quar
                  
                     •
                  ll, in the very laſt age, how many 
                     •
                  ules were ſent vp to Heauen, in 
                     •
                  he midſt of their flames; as if the

Sacrament of the Altar had beene ſufficient ground of theſe bloudie Sacrifices.
                     Fox Acts and Mon. paſſim.
                  
               
               The definition of the Tridentine Councell is herein beyond the wont) cleare,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     , &amp;c Concil. T
                        ••
                     d. de Tranſſub. c. 4. Ca
                        •
                     . 2.
                   and expreſſe. If any man ſhall ſay that in the Sacrament of the ſacred Euchariſt, there remaynes ſtill the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine, together with the Body and Bloud of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; and ſhall denie that maruellous and ſingular conuerſion of the whole ſubſtance of Bread into the Bodie, and the whole ſubſtance of Wine into Bloud, the (Species) ſemblances or ſhewes only of Bread, and Wine remaining;In Syraxi ſ
                        •
                     ro 
                        •
                     ran ſubſia
                        •
                     tiationem de fi
                        •••
                     it Eccleſia. Diu ſatis erat credere, ſiue ſub pa
                        •
                     e conſecra
                        •
                     o, ſi
                        •
                     e qu
                        •
                     cunque modo adeſſe verum corpus Chriſti, Eraſ. Annot. in 1 Cor. 7.
                   (which ſaid Conuerſion the Catholike Church doth moſt fitly call Tranſſubſtantiation) let him be accurſed. Thus they.
               Now let vs inquire how old this piece of faith is; In ſynaxi ſero, &amp;c. It was late ere the Church defined Tranſſubſtantiation (ſaith Eraſmus:) For, of ſo long it was (ſaith hee) held ſufficient to beleeue that

the true Bodie of Chriſt was there, whether vnder the conſecrated Bread, or howſoeuer. And how late was this? Scotus ſhall tell vs; (Ante Concilium Lateranenſe) Before the Councell of Lateran, Tranſſubſtantiation was no point of faith;Bellar. de Euchar. l. 3. c. 23.
                   as Cardinall Bellarmine himſelfe confeſſes his opinion, with a (
                        •
                     minime probandum.) And this Councell was in the yeere of our Lord one thouſand two hundred and fifteene; Let who liſt,Ibid. Bellar. beleeue that this ſubtile Doctour had neuer heard of the Roman Councell vnder Gregory the ſeuenth, which was in the yeere one thouſand ſeuentie nine; or that other, vnder Nicholas the ſecond, which was in the yeare one thouſand and threeſcore, or that he had not read thoſe Fathers, which the Cardinall had good hap to meet with; Certainly, his acuteneſſe eaſily found out other ſenſes of thoſe Conuerſions which Antiquitie mentions;Conſitente etiam Suarez. and therefore dares confidently ſay (wherein Gabriel

Biel ſeconds him) (non admodum antiquam) that this doctrine of Tranſſubſtantiation is not very ancient. Surely, if wee yeeld the vtmoſt time, wherein Bellarmine can plead the determination of this point,Saltem ab annis 
                        ••••
                     ngentis dog
                     
                        •
                     a 
                        •
                     ranſſub. 
                        〈◊〉
                      anathemate 
                        ••
                     b
                        ••
                     tum. Bell. de Euch. l. 3. c. 21.
                   wee ſhall ariſe but to (ſaltem ab annis quingentis, &amp;c.) Fiue hundred yeares agoe; ſo long, ſaith he, at leaſt was this opinion of Tranſſubſtantiation vpon paine of a curſe eſtabliſhed in the Church: The Church, but what Church? The Roman, ywis, not the Greeke. That word of Peter Martyr is true, That the Greeks euer abhorred from this opinion of Tranſſubſtantiation; In ſo much as at the ſhutting vp of the Florentine Councell, which was but in the yeare 1539. when there was a kind of agreement betwixt the Greekes and Latines about the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt,Concil. Florent. 
                        ••
                     ſſ. vlt. the Pope earneſtly moued the Grecians that amongſt other differences they would alſo accord, (de diuinâ panis Tranſmutatione,) concerning the

diuine Tranſmutation of the Bread; wherein notwithſtanding they departed as formerly, diſſenting; How palpably doth the Cardinall ſhuffle in this buſineſſe, whiles hee would perſwade vs, that the Greekes did not at all differ from the Romans in the mayne head of Tranſſubſtantiation; but only concerning the particularitie of thoſe wordes, whereby that vnſpeakeable change is wrought; when as it is moſt cleere by the Acts of that Councell, related euen by their Binius himſelfe,Se firmiter credere verbis illis Dominicis ſacramentum fieri, Ibid. ſeſſ. vlt. that after the Greekes had giuen in their anſwere, that they doe firmely beleeue that in thoſe words of Chriſt the Sacrament is made vp, (which had beene ſufficient ſatisfaction if that only had beene the queſtion) the Pope vrges them earneſtly ſtill, (vt de diuinâ panis tranſmutatione, &amp;c.) that in the Synod there might bee treatie had of the diuine tranſmutation of the Bread; and when they yet ſtif
                     •
                  ly denied, he could haue beene content to haue had the other

three Queſtions of vnleauened Bread, Purgatorie, and the Popes Power diſcuſſed, wauing that other of Tranſſubſtantiation, which hee found would not abide agitation. Since which time their Patriarch Ieremias of Conſtantinople, hath expreſſed the iudgement of the Greeke Church,Act. Theol. Wittenberg. Ann. 1584.
                   (Et enim verè) For the Bodie and Bloud of Chriſt are truely Myſteries; not that theſe are turned into mans bodie, but that (the better preuayling) wee are turned into them yeelding a change, but Myſticall not Subſtantiall.
               As for the Ancients of either the Greeke or Latine Church, they are ſo farre from countenancing this opinion,Whitak. contr. 
                        •
                     ur. l. 
                        •
                     . fol. 220.
                   that our learned Whitakers durſt challenge his Duraeus; Si vel vnum, &amp;c. If you can bring me but one teſtimonie of ſincere antiquitie, whereby it may appeare that the bread is tranſubſtantiate into the fleſh of Chriſt, I will yeeld my cauſe. It is true that there are faire flouriſhes made of a large Iurie of fathers,

giuing their verdict this way;Ignat. ad Smyr. Iren. l. 5. cont. haereſ. Tertull. de reſur. Orig. hom. 5. in diuer. loc. Cyprian. de Coena Dom. Baſil. in reg. breu. q. 172. Greg. Nyſſen. in Ca
                        •
                     echet. Cyrill Hieroſol. Cat. myſt. 4. Hilar. l. 8. de Trinit. Ambr. de ſacr. l. 4. c. 4. &amp; 5 Greg. Naz. in Epit. Gorgon. Epiph. in Anch. Chryſ. hom 24. in 1 Cor. Cyril Alex. Epiſt▪ ad Caeleſyrium. Aug. in Pſal. 33. 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      ad Hedib. Theodor. dial 3. I. eoſer. 6. de Ieiunio. Damaſ. l. 4 de fid. orth. Theophylact. in Luc 22. Et quidem mutatur; Eſt enim alia elementi natura, Sacramentialia. Elienſ. cont. Bell. Bellar. de Euchar. l. 2. c. 4.
                   whoſe verie names can hardly finde roome in a margine. Scarce any of that ſacred ranke are miſſing; But it is as true, that their witneſſes are groſſely abuſed to a ſenſe that was neuer intended; they onely deſiring in an holy exceſſe of ſpeech, to expreſſe the Sacramentall change that is made of the elements, in reſpect of vſe, not in reſpect of ſubſtance; and paſſionately to deſcribe vnto vs the benefit of that Sacrament in our bleſſed Communion with Chriſt; and our liuely incorporation into him.
               In ſo much as Cardinall Bellarmine himſelfe is faine to confeſſe a verie high hyperbole in their ſpeeches (Non eſt nouum) It is no vnuſuall thing (ſaith he) with the Ancients, and eſpecially Irenaeus, Hilarie, Nyſſen, Cyrill, and others, to ſay that our bodies are nouriſhed by the holy Euchariſt.
               Neither doe they vſe leſſe height of ſpeech (as our learned Biſhop

hath particularly obſerued) in expreſſing our participation of Chriſt in Baptiſme,Biſh. Mortons Appell. wherein yet neuer any man pleaded a Tranſſubſtantiation.
               Neither haue their beene wanting ſome of the Claſſicall leaders of their ſchooles, which haue confeſſed more probabilitie of ancient euidence for Conſubſtantiation, then for this change. Certainely, neither of them both entred euer into the thoughts of thoſe holy men, how euer the ſound of their words haue vndergone a preiudiciall miſtaking. Whereas the ſentences of thoſe Ancients againſt this miſ-opinion are direct, punctuall, abſolute, conuictiue, and vncapable of any other reaſonable ſenſe. What can bee more choaking then that of their Pope Gelaſius aboue a thouſand yeares ſince (Et tamen,
                  Gel
                        •
                     ſ. Pap. de duabus Chriſt. nat. Biblioth. Patr. Tom. 4.
                   
                  &amp;c.) yet there ceaſeth not to be the very ſubſtance of Bread and Wine? What can bee more plaine then that of Saint Auguſtine. It is not this Bodie which you ſee,Auguſt. in Pſal. 98.
                   that you ſhall eat,

neither is it this Bloud which my Crucifiers ſhall ſpill,Non hoc ipſum corpus quod videtis &amp;c. neque hunc ipſum ſanguinem, &amp;c. ſacramentum vobis aliquod com. &amp;c. Vbi ſlagitiam, &amp;c. Aug. de doctrin. Chriſt. l. 3. c. 16.
                   that you ſhall drinke; It is a Sacrament that I commend vnto you; which being ſpiritually vnderſtood, ſhall quicken you. Or, that other; where a flagitious act ſeemes to bee commanded, there the ſpeech is figuratiue; as, when he ſaith, Except yee eat the fleſh of the Sonne of man, &amp;c. it were an horrible wickedneſſe to eat the very fleſh of Chriſt; therefore here muſt needs bee a figure vnderſtood.Tertull. contr. Marcionem. l. 4. Theoder Dial 2. &amp; 3 
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , &amp;c. Carnale eſt dubitare quo modo de coelo deſcendit, &amp;c. &amp; quomodo poſſit carnem ſuam dare ad mandecandum; Haec inquam omnia carnalia, quae myſtica &amp; ſ
                        •
                     iritaliter intelligenda ſunt. Chryſ. in cap. 6. Ioan. hom 46.
                   What ſhould I vrge that of Tertullian (whoſe ſpeech Rhenanus confeſſeth to haue been condemned after in Berengarius) My Bodie, that is, the figure of my Bodie; That of Theodoret; The myſticall ſignes, after conſecration, loſe not their owne nature. That of Saint Chryſoſtome, It is a carnall thing to doubt how Chriſt can giue vs his fleſh to eate; when as this is myſtically and ſpiritually to bee vnderſtood: And ſoone after, inquiring what it is to vnderſtand carnally; he thus explicates

it; It is to take things ſimply as they are ſpoken, and not to conceiue of any other thing meant by them.Simpliciter vt res dicuntur neque aliud quippiam excogitare, &amp;c. ibid. In iliud ſi quis dixerit contra filium h
                        •
                     m▪
                   This wherein we are is a beaten path, trod with the feet of our holy Martyrs, and traced with their bloud; What ſhould I need to produce their familiar and ancient Aduocates, who haue often wearied and worne this bar
                     •
                  . Athanaſius, 
                  Contr. Tryphon. 
                  Iustine, 
                  Hom. 7. in Leuit. 
                  Origen, 
                  De Coena Dom. 
                  Cyprion, 
                  In Epitaph. Caeſarij, &amp; ad ciues Nazaian. 
                  Nazianzen, 
                  L. de Baptiſ. 
                  Baſil, 
                  In Eſa. 66.
                   
                  Hierome, 
                  Lib. 8. de Trin. 
                  Hillary, 
                  In Ioan. l. 3. c. 34.
                   
                  Cyril, 
                  Hom. 27.
                   
                  Macarius, 
                  Lib. de Corp. &amp; Sang. &amp;c. Albin. in Ioa 
                        •
                     . c. 6.
                   
                  Bertram, beſides thoſe whom I formerly cited. Of all others (which I haue not found preſſed by former Authors) that of our Albinus or Alcuinus, Bedaes learned Scholler (who liued in the time of Charles the Great) ſeemes to mee moſt full and pregnant. Hoc eſt ergo, this is therefore to eate that fleſh, and to drinke that bloud to remayne in Chriſt and to haue Chriſt remayning in vs; ſo as he that remaynes not in Chriſt, and in whom Chriſt remayneth not, without doubt doth not ſpiritually

eat his fleſh, although carnally and viſibly hee chew the Sacrament of his Bodie and Bloud with his teeth:Dentibus premat, &amp;c. but rather he eates and drinkes the Sacrament of ſo great a thing, vnto his owne iudgement, becauſe hee preſumed to come vncleane vnto thoſe Sacraments of Chriſt, which none can take worthily but the cleane; Thus he.
               Neither is this his ſingle teſtimonie,Sicu
                        •
                      etiam a
                        •
                     
                     te nos intellexerunt homines Dei. Ibid. but ſuch as hee openly profeſſeth the common voyce of all his Predeceſſours: And a little after, vpon thoſe words The fleſh profiteth nothing; hee addeth; The fleſh profiteth nothing, if yee vnderſtand the fleſh ſo to bee eaten as other meate, as that fleſh which is bought in the Shambles. This is the ordinary language of Antiquitie, whereof wee may truely ſay as the Diſciples did of Chriſt,Ioh. 16.29. 
                  Behold now thou ſpeakeſt plainly, and ſpeakeſt no Parable. At laſt, ignorance and miſunderſtanding brought forth this Monſter of opinion, which ſuperſtition

nurſed vp, but fearefully and obſcurely, and not without much ſcope of contrary iudgements; till after Pope Nicholas had made way for it in his proceedings againſt Barengarius (by ſo groſſe an expreſſion as the Gloſſe is faine to put a caueat vpon) Anno 1060. the Laterane Councell authorized it for a matter of faith,
                     Anno 1215. 
                  Anno 1215.
               Thus young is Tranſſubſtantiation; Let Scripture and Reaſon ſhow how erroneous.
               
               
                  Tranſſubstantiation. SECT. II. Againſt Scripture.
                  WEre it not that men doe wilfully hoodwinke themſelues with their own preiudice, the Scripture is plaine enough; For the

mouth that ſaid of bread,Iohn 6.55. 
                     This is my Bodie, ſaid alſo of the ſame bodie, My fleſh is meate indeed, long before there can be any plea of Tranſſubſtantiation;Iohn 6.51. And I am the bread that came downe from Heauen; ſo was he Manna to the Iewes as he is bread to vs; And, Saint Paul ſayes of his Corinths,1. Cor. 12.27. 
                     Yee are the body of Chriſt; yet not meaning any tranſmutation of ſubſtance.
                  And in thoſe words wherein this powerfull conuerſion is placed, hee ſayes only, This is, not,Mat. 26.26. this is tranſſubſtantiate; and if whiles he ſayes, This is,
                     Marke 14.21. hee ſhould haue meant a Tranſſubſtantiation, then it muſt needs follow, that his Bodie was tranſſubſtantiate before hee ſpake; for This is, implyes it alreadie done. He addes, This is my Bodie; His true naturall humane Bodie was there with them, tooke the Bread, brake it, gaue it, eat it; if the Bread were now the Bodie of Chriſt, either hee muſt haue two bodies there, or elſe the ſame bodie is by the ſame bodie

taken, broken, eaten, and is (the while) neither taken, nor broken, nor eaten;Luc. 22.19. Yet hee addes, which is giuen for you; This was the bodie which was giuen for them, betrayed, crucified, humbled to the death; not the glorious bodie of Chriſt, which ſhould bee capeable of ten thouſand placcs at once, both in Heauen, and Earth; inuiſible, incircumſcriptible: Laſtly, he addes, Doe this in remembrance of mee; Remembrance implyes an abſence; neither can wee more bee ſaid to remember that which is in our preſent ſenſe, then to ſee that which is abſent.
                  Beſides, that the great Doctour of the Gentiles tels vs that after conſecration,1. Cor. 11.26. 
                     it is bread which is broken and eaten; neither is it leſſe then fiue times ſo called after the pretended change.
                  Shortly; Chriſt as man was in all things like to vs except ſinne;Heb. 2.17. and our humane bodie ſhall be once like to his glorious bodie. The glorie

which is put vpon it ſhall not ſtrip it of the true eſſence of a bodie; and if it retaine the true nature of a bodie, it cannot be at the ſame inſtant both aboue the Heauens, and below on Earth, in a thouſand diſtant places. He is locally aboue,Acts 3.21. 
                     For the heauens muſt receiue him till the times of the reſtitution of all things; He is not at once in many diſtant places of the earth, for the Angell euen after his Reſurrection, ſayes, He is not here,
                     Mat. 28.6. 
                     for he is riſen.
                  
               
               
                  SECT. III. Tranſſubſtantiation againſt Reaſon.
                  NEuer did, or can reaſon triumph ſo much ouer any prodigious Paradoxe, as it doth ouer this. In ſo much as the Patrones of it are faine

to diſclaime the ſophiſtry of reaſon, and to ſtand vpon the ſuffrages of faith, and the plea of Miracles. We are not they,Aug. de vtil. cred. c. 14.
                      who with the Manichees, refuſe to beleeue Chriſt vnleſſe hee bring reaſon; Wee are not they, who thinke to lade the Sea with an egge-ſhell; to fadome the deepe Myſteries of Religion with the ſhort reach of naturall apprehenſion;
                  Wee know there are wonders in Diuinitie fit for our adoration, not fit for our comprehending; But withal we know, that if ſome Theologicall truths bee aboue right reaſon, yet neuer any againſt it; for all veritie complyes with it ſelfe, as ſpringing from one and the ſame Fountaine;
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        .
                  
                  This opinion, therefore, wee receiue not;Quod cum affi
                           •
                        matur negatur impoſſibile &amp; 
                           •
                        t implicat contradictio
                        
                           •••
                         Ca
                           •••
                        n in 
                           ••
                        p
                           ••
                        c. contra
                        
                           •••
                        . not becauſe it tranſcends our conceit, but becauſe we know it croſſeth both true Reaſon and faith; It implyes manifeſt contradiction, in that it referres the ſame thing to it ſelfe in oppoſite relations; ſo as it

may be at once preſent and abſent' neere and far off, below and aboue. It deſtroyes the truth of Chriſts humane bodie,Spatia locorum tolle corpuribus Aug. Ep. 57.
                      in that it aſcribes quantitie to it, without extenſion, without localitie; turning the fleſh into ſpirit; and bereauing it of all the properties of a true bodie; thoſe properties which (as Nicetas truly) cannot ſo much as in thought be ſeparated from the eſſence of the bodie;Nicetas. In Nazianz. Orat. de Pontec. quidam ne cogitatione 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        , &amp;c. Sic &amp; Aug. Tolle ipſa corpora qualitatibus, &amp;c. Nam ſiverè ſectionem &amp; partitionem diuina natura reciperet, &amp;c. Cyrill. Alex. Tom 2. dialog. de Trin. lib▪ 
                        2.
                      In ſo much as Cyril can ſay if the Deitie it ſelfe were capeable of partition, it muſt bee a bodie, and if it were a bodie it muſt needs bee in a place, and haue quantitie and magnitude; and thereupon ſhould not auoid circumſcription.
                  It giues a falſe bodie to the Sonne of God making that, euery day, of bread, by the power of wordes, which was made once of the ſubſtance of the Virgin, by the Holy Ghoſt.
                  It ſo ſeparates accidents from their ſubiects, that they not only can ſubſiſt without them, but can

produce the full effects of ſubſtances; ſo as bare accidents are capeable of accidents; ſo as of them ſubſtances may be either made, or nouriſhed.
                  
                     Reſp. ad Epiſt. viri docti.It vtterly ouerthrowes (which learned Cameron makes the ſtrongeſt of all reaſons) the nature of a Sacrament; in that it takes away, at once, the ſigne, and the Analogie betwixt the ſigne, and the thing ſignified; The ſigne, in that it is no more bread, but accidents; the Analogie, in that it makes the ſigne to be the thing ſignified;
                  Laſtly, it puts into the hands of euery Prieſt, power to doe, euery day, a greater Miracle, then God did in the Creation of the World, for in that, the Creatour made the Creature; but in this, the Creature daily makes the Creatour.
                  Since then this opinion is both new, and conuinced to bee groſſely erroneous by Scripture, and reaſon, iuſtly haue we profeſſed our deteſtation of it; and, for that, are vniuſtly eiected.
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. VIII. The newneſſe of the Halfe-Communion.
               
                  THe noueltie of the Halfe-Sacrament, or dry Communion, deliuered to the Laitie, is ſo palpable, as that the Patrones of it, in the preſumptuous Councell of Conſtance,
                  Conſtant. Synod. ſeſſ. 13.
                   profeſſe no leſſe. Licet Christus, &amp;c. Although Chriſt (ſay they) after his Supper, inſtituted, and adminiſtred this venerable Sacrament vnder both kinds of Bread, and Wine, &amp;c. (Licet in primitiua, &amp;c.) Although in the Primitiue Church, this Sacrament were receiued by the faithfull vnder both kindes; (Non obstante, &amp;c.) Yet,Inter alia, propter periculum effuſionis. Io. de burgo. 4. partis cap. 8.
                   this cuſtome for the auoiding of ſome dangers, and ſcandalls, was vpon iuſt reaſon brought in, that Laickes ſhould receiue only vnder one kind; And thoſe that ſtubbornely oppoſe

themſelues againſt it, ſhalbe eiected, and puniſhed as Heretickes. Now this Councell was but in the yeare of our Lord God, one thouſand, foure hundred fiftie three. Yea, but theſe Fathers of Conſtance, how euer they are bold to controule Chriſts Law by Cuſtome,Ibid. yet they ſay it was (conſuetudo diutiſsimè obſeruata) a cuſtome very long obſerued;
               True; but the full age of this (Diutiſsimè) is openly and freely calculated by their Caſſander.
                  Caſſand. conſult. de vtra
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ſpec. ſacr. &amp;c. 
                  (Satis constat) It is apparent enough that the Weſterne, or Romane Church, for a thouſand yeares after Chriſt, in the ſolemne and ordinary Diſpenſation of this Sacrament, gaue both kinds of Bread, and Wine to all the members of the Church. A point, which is manifeſt by innumerable ancient Teſtimonies, both of Greekes, and Latines; and this they were induced to doe, by the example of Chriſts inſtitution. Quare non temerè, &amp;c. It is not

therefore (ſaith hee) without cauſe, that moſt of the beſt Catholickes, and moſt conuerſant in the reading of Eccleſiaſticall Writers, are inflamed with an earneſt deſire of obtayning the Cup of the Lord; that the Sacrament may bee reduced to that ancient cuſtome and vſe, which hath beene for many Ages perpetuated in the vniuerſall Church. Thus he; Wee need no other Aduocate.
               Yea, their Vaſquez drawes it yet lower, Negare non, &amp;c. We cannot deny that in the Latin Church there was the vſe of both kinds, and that it ſo continued vntill the dayes of Saint Thomas, which was about the yeare of God 1260.
               Thus it was in the Romane Church; but as for the Greeke; the World knowes it did neuer but communicate vnder both kindes. Theſe open Confeſſions, ſpare vs the labour of quoting the ſeuerall teſtimonies of all Ages; Elſe it had beene eaſie to ſhow how in the Lyturgy

of Saint Baſil and Chryſoſtome, the Prieſt was wont to pray,Liturg. Baſil. &amp; Chryſost. Vouchſafe, O Lord, to giue vs thy bodie, and thy bloud, and by vs to thy people.Vid. Caſſand. conſult. vbi ſupra. How in the Order of Rome the Archdeacon taking the Chalice from the Biſhops hand confirmeth all the receiuers with the bloud of our Lord.In Epiſt. ad Philadelph. And from Ignatius his (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) One cup diſtributed to all; to haue deſcended along, through the cleere records of S. Cyprian, Hierome, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Leo, Gelaſius, Paſchaſius and others to the verie time of Hugo and Lombard, and our Halenſis; And to ſhow, how S.
                  Lib. 1 Ep. 2.
                   
                  Cyprian would not deny the bloud of Chriſt to thoſe, that ſhould ſhed their bloud for Chriſt: How S.
                  Lib. de Coena dom. 
                  Austen (with him) makes a compariſon betwixt the bloud of the legall ſacrifices, which might not bee eaten, and this bloud of our Sauiours ſacrifice,Quaeſt. in Leuit. 57. Grat. decret. de Conſecrat. dist. 2. c. 12. comperimus. which all muſt drinke.
               But, what need allegations to proue a yeelded truth? ſo as this haluing of the Sacrament is a meere

noueltie of Rome, and ſuch a one,Diuiſio vnius eiuſdem myſterij non ſine grandi ſacrilegio poteſt peruenire. as their owne Pope Gelaſius ſtickes not to accuſe of no leſſe then ſacriledge;
               
                  SECT. II. Halfe Communion againſt Scripture.
                  NEither ſhall wee need to vrge Scripture; when it is plainely confeſſed by the late Councels of Lateran and Trent, that this practice varies from Chriſts inſtitution;Etſi. Chriſtus Dominus, &amp;c. non tamen illa inſtitutio &amp; traditio eo tendunt vt omnes Chriſti fideles ſtatuto domini ad vtram
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         ſpeciem accipiendam aſtringantur, &amp;c. Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 5. ſub Pio Anno 1562 cap. 1.
                      Yet the Tridentine Fathers haue left themſelues this euaſion, that, howeuer our Sauiour ordained it in both kindes, and ſo deliuered it to his Apoſtles, notwithſtanding hee hath not by any command enioyned it to be ſo receiued of the Laitie; Not conſidering that the charge of our Sauiour is equally vniuerſall in

both; To whom he ſayd, Take and eat, to the ſame alſo he ſayd, Drinke ye all of this; So as by the ſame reaſon, our Sauiour hath giuen no command at all vnto the Laitie to eat, or drinke; and ſo this bleſſed Sacrament ſhould bee to all Gods people (the Prieſts onely excepted) arbitrarie and vnneceſſarie: But the great Doctor of the Gentiles is the beſt Commenter vpon his maſter, who writing to the Church of God at Corinth,1. Cor. 1.2. to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus, with all that in euerie place call vpon the name of Ieſus Chriſt;Nihil differt ſacerdos à ſubdito quando fruendum eſt myſterijs, Chryſoſt. ſo deliuers the inſtitution of Chriſt, as that in the vſe of the Cup hee makes no difference; Six times conioyning the mention of drinking with eating; and fetching it in with an (
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     ) equalitie of the manner, and neceſſitie of both, charges all Chriſtians indifferently (Probet ſeipſum) Let euerie man examine himſelfe,
                     1. Cor. 11.28. 
                     &amp;c. and ſo let him eat of that bread, and drinke of that cup.
                  
               
               
                  
                  SECT. III. Halfe Communion againſt reaſon.
                  IN this practice, reaſon is no leſſe their enemie; Though it bee but a mans teſtament, yet if it be confirmed,
                     Gal. 3.15. 
                     no man diſanulleth it, (ſaith S. Paul.) How much leſſe ſhall fleſh and bloud preſume to alter the laſt will of the Sonne of God; and that in ſo materiall a point, as vtterly deſtroyes the inſtitution. For as our learned Biſhop of Carlile argues truly; Halfe a man is no man,Doct. White cont. Fiſherum. Halfe a Sacrament is no Sacrament.
                  And as well might they take away the bread, as the cup; both depend vpon the ſame ordination: It is only the command of Chriſt that makes the bread neceſſarie: the ſame command of Chriſt equally enioynes the cup; both doe either ſtand, or fall vpon the ſame ground.
                  The pretence of concomitancie

is ſo poore a ſhift, that it hurts them rather, for if by vertue thereof the body of Chriſt is no leſſe in the wine, then the bloud is in the bread, it will neceſſarily follow, that they might as well hold backe the bread, and giue the cup; as hold backe the cup, and giue the bread:
                  And could this myſterie bee hid from the eyes of the bleſſed Author of this Sacrament? Will theſe men bee wiſer then the wiſdome of his Father? If hee knew this, and ſaw the wine yet vſefull, who dares abrogate it, and if hee had not ſeene it vſefull, why did hee not then ſpare the labour and coſt of ſo needleſſe an element?
                  Laſtly, the bloud that is here offered vnto vs, is that which was ſhed for vs; that which was ſhed from the body, is not in the body, in vaine therefore is concomitancie pleaded for a ſeparated bloud.
                  Shortly then, this mutilation of the Sacrament being both confeſſedly late, and extremely iniurious

to God and his people; and contrarie to Scripture and reaſon, is iuſtly abandoned by vs; and wee for abandoning it vniuſtly cenſured.
               
            
            
               CHAP. IX. The newneſſe of the Miſſall Sacrifice.
               
                  IT ſounds not more prodigiouſly, that a Prieſt ſhould euerie day make his God, then that hee ſhould ſacrifice him. Antiquitie would haue as much abhorred the ſenſe, as it hath allowed the word. Nothing is more ordinarie with the Fathers, then to call Gods Table an Altar, the holy Elements an Oblation,Macarium in altare inſult aſſe, menſam domini euertiſſe, Socrat. l. 1. c. 10· Chryſ. in Pſ. 95.
                   the act of Celebration an Immolation, the Actor a Prieſt. S. Chryſoſtome reckons ten kindes of Sacrifice, and at laſt (as hauing forgotten

it) addes the eleuenth; All which we well allow;Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 6. c. 2. can. 1. Verum, proprium propitiatorium, &amp;c. and indeed many Sacrifices are offered to God in this one; but a true, proper, propitiatorie Sacrifice for quicke and dead, (which the Tridentine Fathers would force vpon our beleefe) would haue ſeemed no leſſe ſtrange a Soloeciſme to the eares of the Ancient, then it doth to ours. Saint Augustine calls it a Deſignation of Chriſts offering vpon the Croſſe.In lib. ſent. Prosp. Hom. 17. ad Hebr. Saint Chryſoſtome (and Theophylact after him) a Remembrance of his Sacrifice: Emiſſenus a daily celebration in myſterie of that which was once offered in payment;Prece myſtica conſecratur nobis in memoria dominicae paſſionis. Lomb. ſent. l. 4. d. 12.
                   and Lombard himſelfe, a memoriall and repreſentation of the true Sacrifice vpon the Croſſe: That which Caſſander cites from Saint Ambroſe or Chryſoſtome,
                  Caſſand. conſult. de ſacrificio. Et Ibidem, hoc autem ſacrificium exemplar eſt illius. Chryſ. vbi ſupra. may be in ſtead of all. In Chriſt is the Sacrifice once offered able to giue ſaluation; What doe we therefore? Doe we not offer euerie day? Surely, if we offer daily, it is done for a recorbation of his

death: This is the language and meaning of Antiquitie,Si qu
                        •
                     s dixerit Miſſae Sacrificium antum eſſe laudis &amp; tiarum actionis, &amp;c. Seſſ. 6. cap. 9.
                   the verie ſame which the Tridentine Synod condemneth in vs. If any man ſhall ſay, that the Sacrifice of the Maſſe is onely a Sacrifice of praiſe and thankſgiuing, or a bare commemoration of the Sacrifice offered vpon the Croſſe, let him be accurſed·
               
                  SECT. II. Sacrifice of the Maſſe against Scripture.
                  HOw plaine is the Scripture; whiles it tells vs that our High Prieſt needeth not daily, as thoſe High Prieſts (vnder the Law) to offer vp ſacrifice, firſt for his own ſins, then, for the peoples;Heb. 7.27. For this hee did once, when hee offered vp himſelfe. The contradiction of the Trent-Fathers is here verie remarkable:

Chriſt (ſay they) who on the altar of the Croſſe offered himſelfe in a bloudie Sacrifice,Co
                           •
                         Tri
                           •
                        . ſeſſ. 6 cap. 2.
                      is now this true Propitiatorie Sacrifice in the Maſſe made by himſelfe: Hee is one and the ſame Sacrifice, and one and the ſame offerer of that Sacrifice, by the Miniſterie of his Prieſts, who then offered himſelfe on the Croſſe; So then, they ſay, that Chriſt offered vp that Sacrifice then, and this now: Saint Paul ſayes he offered vp that Sacrifice and no more. Saint Paul ſaies our High Prieſt needs not to offer daily Sacrifice. They ſay theſe daily Sacrifices muſt bee offered by him; Saint Paul ſayes that he offered himſelfe but once, for the ſins of the people. They ſay hee offers himſelfe daily for the ſins of quicke and dead: And if the Apoſtle in the ſpirit of propheſie foreſaw this errour, and would purpoſely fore-ſtall it, he could not ſpeake more directly,Heb. 10.10. then when he ſaith, We are ſanctified through the offering of the bodie of Ieſus Christ, once for all. And euerie

High Priest ſtandeth daily miniſtring and offering oftentimes the ſame ſacrifices which can neuer take away ſinnes;
                     Verſe 11, 12. 
                     But this man after hee had offered one ſacrifice for ſinnes,
                     Verſe 13, 14. 
                     for euer ſate downe on the right hand of God; from henceforth expecting till his enemies be made his footſtoole: For by one offering hee hath perfected for euer them that are ſanctified.
                  
                  Now let the vaine heads of men ſeeke ſubtill euaſions in the different manner of this offering,Sola offerendi ratione diuerſa. Ibid. Concil. Trid bloudie then, vnbloudie now; The Holy Ghoſt ſpeakes punctually of the verie ſubſtance of the act; and tells vs abſolutely, there is but one Sacrifice once offered by him in any kinde; Elſe the oppoſition that is there made betwixt the Legall Prieſthood and his, ſhould not hold, if, as they, ſo he had often properly and truly ſacrificed.
                  That I may not ſay they build herein what they deſtroy; for an vnbloudie Sacrifice, in this ſenſe, can bee no other then figuratiue, and

commemoratiue. Is it really propitiatorie?Heb. 9.12. Without ſhedding of bloud there is no remiſſion. If therfore ſins be remitted by this Sacrifice, it muſt bee in relation to that bloud, which was ſhed in his true perſonall Sacrifice vpon the Croſſe; and what relation can bee betwixt this and that, but of repreſentation and remembrance;Caſſand. Conſult. de ſacrif. in which their moderate Caſſander fully reſteth?
               
               
                  SECT. III. Miſſall Sacrifice againſt reaſon.
                  IN reaſon, there muſt be in euerie Sacrifice (as Cardinall Bellarmine grants) a deſtruction of the thing offered; and ſhall we ſay that they make their Sauiour to crucifie him againe?Bell. l. 1. de Miſſa, cap. 2.
                      No, but to eat him; For (Conſumptio ſeu manducatio quae ſit à

ſacerdote) The conſumption or manducation which is done of the Prieſt is an eſſentiall part of this Sacrifice; (ſaith the ſame Author;) For in the whole action of the Maſſe, there is (ſaith hee) no other reall deſtruction but this:
                  Suppoſe we then the true humane fleſh, bloud, and bone of Chriſt, God and man, really and corporally made ſuch by this Tranſſubſtantiation, Whether is more horrible to crucifie, or to eat it?
                  By this rule it is the Prieſts teeth, and not his tongue, that makes Chriſts bodie a ſacrifice:
                  By this rule it ſhall be (hoſtia) an hoſt, when it is not a Sacrifice; and a reſerued hoſt is no Sacrifice, howſoeuer conſecrated. And what if a mouſe, or other vermin,Io▪ de Burg 4. partis c. 8. de Miniſtratione Euch. Salmer. Tom. 8. Tract. 29. An Euchar. ſit proprie ſacrificium ſhould eat the Hoſt (it is a caſe put by themſelues) who then ſacrificeth? To ſtop all mouthes; Laicks eat as well as the Prieſt, there is no difference in their manducation, but Laicks ſacrifice not; And (as Salmeron vrges)

the Scripture diſtinguiſheth betwixt the Sacrifice and the participation of it;1. Cor. 10.8. Are not they which eat of the Sacrifices, partakers of the Altar? And in the verie Canon of the Maſſe, Vt quot quot, &amp;c. the prayer is, that all wee which in the participation of the Altar haue taken the ſacred bodie and bloud of thy Son, &amp;c. Wherein it is plaine, ſaith hee, that there is a diſtinction betwixt the Hoſt, and the eating of the Hoſt.
                  Laſtly, ſacrificing is an act done to God; if then eating bee ſacrificing, The Prieſt eats his God to his God; Quorum Deus venter. Whiles they in vaine ſtudie to reconcile this new-made Sacrifice of Chriſt already in heauen, with (Iube haec perferri) Command theſe to be carried by the hands of thine holy Angels to thine high Altar in Heauen, in the ſight of thy diuine Maieſtie: Wee conclude, That this proper and propitiatorie Sacrifice of the Maſſe, as a new, vnholy, vnreaſonable ſacrifice

is iuſtly abhorred by vs, and wee for abhorring it vniuſtly eiected.
               
            
            
               CHAP. X. Newneſſe of Image-worſhip.
               
                  AS for the ſetting vp, and worſhipping of Images, wee ſhall not neede to climbe ſo high, as Arnobius, or Origen, or the Councell of Eliberis, Anno 305. Or to that fact and hiſtorie of Epiphanius,
                  Epiſt. Epiphan. Inter opera Hierom. &amp;c. (whoſe famous Epiſtle is honoured by the Tranſlation of Hierome) of the picture found by him in the Church of the village of Anablatha, though out of his owne Dioceſſe; how he tore it in an holy zeale; and wrote to the Biſhop of the place,Quae contra religionem noſtram veniunt, &amp;c. beſeeching him that no ſuch pictures may be hanged vp, contrarie to our religion; Though (by the way) who

can but bluſh at Maſter Fiſhers euaſion, that it was ſure the picture of ſome profane Pagan, When as Epiphanius himſelfe there ſayes it had (Imaginem quaſi Chriſti, vel ſancti cuiuſdam;) the Image, as it were of Chriſt, or ſome Saint: Surely therfore the Image went for Chriſts, or for ſome noted Saints; neither doth he find fault with the irreſemblance, but with the Image; as ſuch:
               
                  Biblioth. Patr. 
                        •
                     om. 9.That of Agobardus is ſufficient for vs; (Nullus antiquorum Catholicorum) None of the ancient Catholiques euer thought, that Images were to be worſhipped, or adored; They had them indeed, but for hiſtorie-ſake; To remember the Saints by, not to worſhip them.
               
                  Greg Epi
                        •
                     t. l. 9. Epiſt. 9. Indict. 4
                  The deciſion of Gregory the Great (ſome ſix hundred yeeres after Chriſt) which he gaue to Serenus Biſhop of Maſſilia, is famous in euerie mans mouth, and pen: (Et quidem quia eas adorari vetuiſſes, &amp;c.) Wee commend you (ſaith hee) that you forbade thoſe Images to bee worſhipped;

but we reproue your breaking of them; adding the reaſon of both; For that they were onely retained for hiſtorie and inſtruction, not for adoration; which ingenuous Caſſander ſo comments vpon,Caſſand. Conſult. 2
                           •
                        . Artic. de cultu Imag. as that he ſhowes this to be a ſufficient declaration of the iudgement of the Roman Church in thoſe times. (Videlicet ideo haberi picturas, &amp;c.) That Images are kept not to bee adored and worſhipped, but that the ignorant by beholding thoſe pictures might, as by written records, be put in minde of what hath beene formerly done, and bee thereupon ſtirred vp to pietie; And the ſame Author tells vs, that (Sanioribus ſcholaſticis diſplicet &amp;c.) the ſounder Schoole-men diſliked that opinion of Thomas Aquine, who held that the Image is to be worſhipped with the ſame adoration, which is due to the thing repreſented by it; reckoning vp Durand, Holcot, Biel. Not to ſpend many words in a cleere caſe. What the iudgement and practice

of our Anceſtors in this Iland was, concerning this point, appeares ſufficiently by the relation of Roger Houeden our Hiſtorian;Rog. Houeden. Part. Annal 1. Anno 792. fol. 3
                   Who tells vs that in the yeere 792. Charles the King of France ſent into this Iſle, a Synodall Booke directed vnto him from Conſtantinople, wherein there were diuers offenſiue paſſages; but eſpecially this one, that by the vnanimous conſent of all the Doctors of the Eaſt, and no fewer then 300. Biſhops, it was decreed, that Images ſhould be worſhipped (quod Eccleſia Deiexecratur) (ſaith he) which the Church of God abhorres. Againſt which errour, Albinus (ſaith he) wrote an Epiſtle maruellouſly confirmed by authoritie of diuine Scriptures; and in the perſon of our Biſhops and Princes exhibited it together with the ſayd Booke vnto the French King; This was the ſetled reſolution of our Predeceſſours; And if ſince that time preuailing ſuperſtition haue incroached vpon the enſuing ſucceſſion of

the Church, (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) Let the old rules ſtand, as thoſe Fathers determined: Away with nouelties.
               But, good Lord, how apt men are to raiſe or beleeue lies for their owne aduantages? Vſpergenſis,
                  
                     Ʋid. Binium in vita Conſtantini P. and other friends of Idolatrie, tell vs of a Councell held at London, in the dayes of Pope Conſtantine, Anno 714. wherein the worſhip of Images was publiquely decreed; the occaſion whereof was this: Egwin the Monke, (after made Biſhop) had a viſion from God, wherein hee was admoniſhed to ſet vp the Image of the Mother of God, in his Church. The matter was debated; and brought before the Pope in his See Apoſtolike; There, Egwin was ſworne to the truth of his viſion. Thereupon Pope Conſtantine ſent his Legate Boniface into England; who called a Councell at London; wherein, after proofe made of Egwins viſions, there was an act made for Image-worſhip. A figment ſo groſſe, that euen their Baronius and

                  Binius fall foule vpon it, with a (facile inducimur, &amp;c.) we are eaſily induced to beleeue it to be a lie. Their ground is, that it is deſtitute of all teſtimony of Antiquitie; and beſides, that it doth directly croſſe the report of Beda, who tells vs that our Engliſh, together with the Goſpell, receiued the vſe of Images from their Apoſtle Augustine; and therefore needed not any new viſion for the entertainment thereof. Let vs inquire then a little into the words of Beda;
                  Beda Eccleſ. hiſt. Angl. l. 1. c. 25. &amp;c. 
                  At illi (but they, Auguſtine and his fellowes) non daemoniaca &amp;c. came armed not with the power of Deuils, but of God, bearing a ſiluer Croſſe for their Standard, and the image of our Lord and Sauiour painted in a Table, and ſinging Letanies both for the ſaluation of themſelues, and of them whom they came to conuert. Thus he.
               This ſhewes indeed, that Augustine and his fellowes brought Images into England, vnknowne here before;

(A point worthy of good obſeruation) but how little this proues the allowed worſhip of them, will eaſily appeare to any reader, if hee conſider, that Gregorie the firſt and Great was he, that ſent this Auguſtine in England, whoſe iudgement concerning Images is cleerely publiſhed by himſelfe to all the world in his fore-cited Epiſtle, abſolutely condemning their adoration; Auguſtine ſhould haue been an ill Apoſtle, if he had herein gone contrarie to the will of him that ſent him. If withall he ſhall conſider, that within the verie ſame centurie of yeeres, the Clergie of England, by Albinus Bedes Scholler, ſent this publique declaration of their earneſt diſauowing both of the doctrine and practice of Image-worſhip.
               
                  
                  SECT. II. Image Worſhip againſt Scripture.
                  AS for Scripture. We need not to goe further then the verie ſecond Commandement; the charge whereof is ſo ineuitable, that it is very ordinarily (doubtleſſe, in the guiltineſſe of an apparent checke) left out in the deuotionall Bookes to the people. Azorius Inſtitut. l. 9. c. 6. cites for this opinion. Alex. p. 3. q. 30. memb. 3. art. 3. Albert. 3. d. 9. art. 4. Bonauent. 3. d. 9 1. q. Richard. 3. d. 9. art 2. q 1. Palud. 3. d. 9. q. 1. Marſil. 3. q. 8. Henriq. quod· lib. 10 q. 6. Cent. 2. c. 5.
                      Others, ſince they cannot raze it out, would faine limit it to the Iewes, pretending that this precept againſt the worſhip of Images was only Temporall, and Ceremoniall, and ſuch as ought not to be in force vnder the Times of the Goſpell;
                  Wherin they recal to my thoughts that which Epiphanes the ſonne of Carpocrates anſwered, When his luſt was checked with the command of (Non concupiſces). True, ſaid hee, that is to be vnderſtood of

the Heathen, whoſe Wiues and Siſters wee may not indeed luſt after.
                  Some more modeſt ſpirits are aſhamed of that ſhift, and fly to the diſtinction of Idols and Images; a diſtinction, without a difference; of their making, not of Gods; Of whom we neuer learned other,
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . ſept. ſimulachr. verſ. Acts 7.41. &amp; 15.20. 1. Cor. 12.2. 1. Iohn 5.21. then that as euery Idoll is an Image of ſomething ſo euery Image worſhipped turnes Idoll: The Language differs, not the thing it ſelfe:
                  To be ſure, God takes order for both, Yee ſhall make you no Idoll,
                     Leuit. 26.1. Deut 16.22. Eſay 42.17. &amp; 45.16. Mich 5.13. Abac. 2.18, 19. Zach. 10 2. Eſay 2 8. &amp; 3
                           •
                        .22. &amp; 41 7 &amp; verſe 22, 23, 24 29. &amp; Eſay 44.12. Ier. 7.18 &amp; 8.9. &amp; 10.8. Ezec. 6.3. &amp; 13 &amp; 20.28.32. Ezec. 23.27. Oſe 8.4, 5. Mic. 1.7. 
                     nor grauen Image, neither reare you vp any ſtanding Image, neither ſhall you ſet vp any Image of ſtone in your Land to bow downe to it;
                  Yea, as their owne vulgar turnes it, Non facies tibi, &amp;c. ſtatuam, Thou ſhalt not ſet thee vp a Statue which God hateth. The Booke of God is full of his indignation againſt this practice.
                  Wee may well ſhut vp all with that curſe in Mount Gereſim, Curſed

bee the man that maketh any grauen,
                     Deut. 27.15. 
                     or molten Image, an abhomination vnto the Lord; the worke of the hands of the craftſman, and putteth it in a ſecret place. And all the people ſhall ſay, Amen. Surely, their Durandus after he hath cited diuers Scriptures againſt Idols, as Exod. 20. Leuit. 26. Deut. 4. Numb. 21. &amp;c. at laſt concludes,Durand. Ration. l. 1. c. 3. Ex his &amp; ſimilibus anthoritatibus reprobatur 
                           •
                        imius imaginem vſus. 
                     Ex his &amp; ſimilibus, &amp;c. By theſe and the like authorities is condemned the too much vſe of Images.
                  Now becauſe many eyes are bleared with a pretence of worſhipping theſe, not as Gods, but as reſemblances of Gods frends; Let any indifferent man but read the Epiſtle of Ieremie (Baruch 6.) (canonicall to them, though not to vs) and compare the eſtate and vſage of thoſe ancient Idols, with the preſent Images of the Roman Church, and if hee doe not finde them fully paralleld, let him condemne our quarrell of iniuſtice.
                  But wee muſt needs thinke them

hard driuen for Scripture, when they run for ſhelter vnder that Text, which profeſſedly taxeth them, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , &amp;c. In illicitis Idolorum cultibus, ſaith Saint Peter.
                     
                        1. Pet. 4.3. We turne it well abhominable Idolatries. Greg. Val. l. 2. Apol. de Idol. c. 7. Ne
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         abſurde profecto putaueris. B. Patrum inſinuauiſſe cultum aliquem ſimulachrorum rectum eſſe, &amp;c. contra Herbrandum. In vnlawfull Idolatries; ſpeaking of the Gentiles; Therefore, ſaith Valentia, there is a lawfull worſhip of Idols. As if that were an Epithete of fauour, which is intended to aggrauation; So hee that ſhould call Satan an vncleane Deuill ſhould imply that ſome Deuill is not vncleane; or, deceiuable luſts, ſome luſts deceitleſſe; or hatefull wickedneſſe, ſome wickedneſſe not hatefull; The man had forgot that the Apoſtle ſpake of the heatheniſh Idolatrie; wherein himſelfe cannot plead any colour of lawfulneſſe: May this therefore befrend them to call Idolatrie abhominable, the Scripture is theirs; neither can they looke for 
                        ••
                     y other countenance from thoſe ſacred monuments.
               
               
                  
                  SECT. III.
                  WHat need wee ſeeke any other reaſon of Gods prohibition then his will: And yet God himſelfe hath giuen abundant reaſon of his prohibition of Images erected to himſelfe.
                  
                     Eſay 40.18.To whom will yee liken God, or what likeneſſe wil ye compare vnto him. Yee ſaw no manner of ſimilitude in the day that the Lord ſpake to you in Horeb.Deut. 4.15. It is an hie iniurie to the infinite and ſpirituall nature of God to bee reſembled by bodily ſhapes;
                        Eſay 42.8. Si quis puram creaturam propter quamcun
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         excellentiam colit cultu &amp; honore maiori quam puro humano, culius hic iam accedit ad cultum religioſum &amp; per conſ. ad diuinum Spalat. de Rep. Eccl. l. 7. c. 12.
                      And, for the worſhip of Images erected to himſelfe, or his creature. I am the Lord, that is my name, and my glorie will I not giue to another, nor my praiſe to molten Images. The holy ielouſie of the Almightie will not abide any of his honour diuided with his creature; and what euer worſhip more then meere humane is imparted to the creature, ſets it in riualitie with our Maker.
                  
                     The man is better then his picture;Sed ne
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         Elias adorandus eſt, etiamſi in viuis ſit, ne
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         Ioannes adorandus, &amp;c. Epiphan. cont. Collyrid. her. 79. Acts 10 26. Reuel 19.10. Diog. Laert. and if religious worſhip will not bee allowed to the perſon of man, or Angell, how much leſſe to his Image; Not to man; Saint Peter forbids it; Not to Angell, himſelfe forbids it. What a madneſſe then is it for a liuing man to ſtoope vnto a dead ſtocke; vnleſſe (as that Cynicke had wont to ſpeake vnto ſtatues) to vſe himſelfe to repulſes?
                  This curteſie was too ſhamefull in the Pagans of old, how much more intolerable in Chriſtians: And as for that laſt ſhift of this vnlawfull deuotion, that they worſhip not the Image, but, by it, the perſon repreſented; Haec a Paganis afferri ſolebat,
                     Per illa colitur Deus Leſſ. de Iure, &amp;c. de relig. l. 2.36. dub. Caſſand. Conſ. Art. 21.
                      This (ſaith Caſſander, out of the euidence of Arnobius and Lactantius, to whom he might haue added Saint Auguſtine) was the verie euaſion of the old Heathen; (Nec valebat tunc illa ratio) Neither would this colour then ſerue, how can it hope now to paſſe and finde allowance?
                  
                     The doctrine therefore and practice of Image-worſhip, as late as erroneous, is iuſtly reiected by vs; who according to Saint Ieroms profeſſion,Nos non dico Martyrio reliquias &amp;c. Hier. ad Riparium. worſhip not the reliques of Martyrs, nor Sunne, nor Moone, nor Angels, nor Archangels, nor Cherubim, nor Seraphin, nor any name that is named in this world, or in the world to come; and vniuſtly are we hereupon eiected.
               
            
            
               CHAP. XI. The newneſſe of Indulgences and Purgatorie.
               
                  NOthing is more palpable then the noueltie of Indulgences, or pardons, as they are now of vſe in the Romane Church; the intolerable abuſe whereof,Hiſ
                        •••
                     
                     ▪ Concil. Tr
                        ••
                     . l. 1.
                   gaue the firſt hint to Luthers inquirie; Pope Leo had

gratified his ſiſter Magdalene with a large Monopoly of German pardons; Aremboldus her Factor was too couetous, and held the market too high: The height of theſe ouerrated wares cauſed the chapmen to inquire into their worth; They were found as they are, both for age and dignitie; for age ſo new, as that Cornelius Agrippa,
                  De'vanit. ſcient. c. 61. De Inuent. rep. lib. 8. c. 1. Dies Indulgentiam referuntur ad poenitentias pro vita iniunctas. Gerſ. reg. moral. and Polydore Virgil, and Machiauell (and who not?) tells vs Boniface the eighth, who liued Anno 1300. was the firſt that extended Indulgences to Purgatorie, the firſt that deuiſed a Iubilee for the full vtterance of them; The Indulgences of former times were no other then relaxations of Canonicall Penances, which were enioyned to hainous ſinners; whereof Burchard the Biſhop of Wormes ſet downe many particulars, about t
                     •
                  e 1020. For example, if a man had committed wilfull murder, hee was to faſt fortie dayes together, in bread and water, (which the common people calls a Lent) and to obſerue

a courſe of penance for ſeuen yeeres after; Now theſe yeeres of penance, and theſe Lents were they, which the pardons of former times were vſed to ſtrike off, or abate, according as they found reaſon in the diſpoſition of the Penitent; which may giue light to thoſe termes of ſo many Lents and yeeres remitted in former Indulgences. But that there ſhould bee a ſacred treaſure of the Church, wherein are heaped vp piles of ſatisfactions of Saints, whereof onely the Pope keepes the keyes, and hath power to diſpenſe them where hee liſts, is ſo late a deuice, that Gregorie of Valence is forced to confeſſe, that not ſo much as Gratian, or Peter Lombard (which wrote about 400. yeeres before him) euer made mention of the name of Indulgence;
               Well therefore might Durand &amp; Antonine grant it not to bee found either in the Scriptures,Greg. de Val. &amp; Bellar. l. 2. de Indulgent. or in the writings of the ancient Doctours; and our B. Fiſher goes ſo farre in

the acknowledgement of the newneſſe hereof, that hee hath run into the cenſure of late Ieſuites.
               Iuſt and warrantable is that challenge of learned Chemnitius,
                  Chemn. Exam. de Indulgen. c. 4.
                   that no teſtimony can bee produced of any Father, or of any ancient Church, that either ſuch doctrine, or practice of ſuch Indulgences was euer in vſe, vntill towards one thouſand, two hundred yeeres after Chriſt. Talium indulgentiarum: Some there were in the time immediately foregoing; but ſuch as now, they were not. Beſides, Eugenius his time which was too neere the Verge;Ibid. for the words of Chemnitius are For well-neere a thouſand two hundred yeares. 
                  (Per annos fermè mille ducentos) Bellarmine inſtances in the the third Councell of Lateran, about the yeere 1116. wherein Pope Paſchal the ſecond gaue Indulgences of fortie dayes to thoſe which viſited the threſhold of the Apoſtles; but it muſt be conſidered, that wee muſt take this vpon the bare word of Conradus Vrſpergenſis. Secondly, that this Indulgence of his

is no other but a relaxation of Canonicall penance.
               For hee addes, which Bellarmine purpoſely concealeth (ijs qui de capitalibus, &amp;c.) to thoſe that ſhould doe penance for capitall ſinnes, hee releaſed fortie dayes penance; So as this inſtance helpes nothing; neither are the reſt, which hee hath raked together within the compaſſe of a few preceding yeeres, of any other alloy.
               Neither hath that Cardinall offered to cite one Father for the proofe of this practice; the birth whereof was many hundred yeeres after their expiration; but cunningly ſhifts it off with a cleanly excuſe,Bellar. lib. 2. de Indulgent. c. 17.
                   
                  Neque mirum, &amp;c. Neither may it ſeem ſtrange if wee haue not many ancient Authors, that make mention of theſe things in the Church, which are preſerued only by vſe, not by writing: So he: He ſayes, Not many authors; hee ſhowes not one: And if many matters of rite haue been traduced to the Church without

notice of pen, or preſſe; yet, let it be ſhowne what one doctrine, or practice of ſuch importance (as this is pretended to bee) hath eſcaped the report, and maintenance of ſome Eccleſiaſticke Writer, or other, and we ſhall willingly yeeld it in this; Till then, wee ſhall take this but for a meere colour, and reſolue that our honeſt Roffenſis deales plainly with vs; who tells vs, Quam diu nulla fuerat de Purgatorio cura, &amp;c. So long as there was no care of Purgatorie, no man ſought after Indulgences; for vpon that depends all the opinion of pardons; If you take away Purgatorie, wherefore ſhould wee need pardons? Since therefore Purgatorie was ſo lately knowne, and receiued of the whole Church, who can maruell concerning Indulgences, that there was no vſe of them in the beginning of the Church. Indulgences then began, after men had trembled ſomewhile at the torments of a Purgatorie; Thus their Martyr, not partially for vs, but ingenuouſly

out of the power of truth profeſſes the noueltie of two great Articles of the Roman Creed; Purgatorie and Indulgences. Indeed, both theſe now hang on one ſtring; Although there was a kinde of Purgatorie dreamed of,Aug. Enchir. c. 69. De Ciuit. Dei, l. 21. c. 26. Quicquid ſit quod illo ſignificatur ſum Abbrabae confeſſ. l. 9 c. 3. Serm. de Temp. 232. Qui cum Chriſto regnare non meruerit, cum diabolo abſque dubitatione peribit &amp;c. ibid. and the like De civitate Dei, l. 21. cap. 25. Cypr. contra Demetrian. ad finem. Hic etiam nobis eſt. prompta medela, Poſt autem clauſa eſt omnis medicina ſalutis. before their pardons came into play: That deuice peept out fearefully from Origen; and pull'd in the head againe, as in Saint Austens time, doubting to ſhow it; Tale aliquod, &amp;c. That there is ſome ſuch thing (ſaith hee) after this life it is not vtterly incredible, and may be made a queſtion: And elſewhere. I reproue it not, for it may perhaps be true. And yet againe, as retracting what hee had yeelded, reſolues; Let no man deceiue himſelfe my brethren, there are but two places, and a third there is none: Before whom Saint Cyprian is peremptorie; Quando iſtinc exceſſum fuerit; When wee are once departed hence, there is now no more place of repentance, no effect of ſatisfaction; Here is life either

loſt, or kept;Naz. Car. de rebus ſuis. Carm. 1. fig. 13. c. Ambroſ. orat. de obitu Theodoſ. ad medium, &amp;c. And Gregorie Nazianzens verſe ſounds to the ſame ſenſe. And Saint Ambroſe can ſay of his Theodoſius, that being freed from this earthly warfare; Fruitur nunc luce perpetua, &amp;c. hee now enioyes euerlaſting light, during tranquillitie, and triumphs in the troopes of the Saints. But, what ſtriue wee in this? Wee may well take the word of their Martyr, our Roffenſis for both: And true Eraſmus for the ground of this defence;Eraſ. Epiſt. l. 20. Hier. Agathio. (Mirum in modum &amp;c. They doe maruellouſly affect the fire of Purgatorie, becauſe it is moſt profitable for their Kitchins.
               
                  
                  SECT. II. Indulgences and Purgatorie againſt Scripture.
                  THeſe two then are ſo late comne ſtrangers, that they cannot challenge any notice taken of them by Scripture; Neither were their names euer heard of in the language of Canaan; yet the Wiſedome of that all-ſeeing Spirit, hath not left vs without preuentions of future errours, in blowing vp the very grounds of theſe humane deuiſes.
                  The firſt and mayne ground of both is the remainders of ſome temporall puniſhments to be paid after the guilt, and eternall puniſhment remitted: The driblets of veniall ſinnes to bee reckond for, when the mortall are defraied. Heare what God ſaith,Eſay 43.25. 
                     I, euen I, am he that blotteth out thy tranſgreſsions for mine owne ſake; and will not remember thy ſinnes. Loe, can the Letter bee read

that is blotted out? Can there be a back-reckoning for that which ſhal not be remembred?
                  
                     I haue done away thy Tranſgreſsions as a Cloud:
                     Eſay 44.22. What ſinnes can bee leſſe then tranſgreſſions? What can bee more cleerely diſperſed then a Cloud?
                  
                     Waſh me,
                     Pſal. 51.7. 
                     and I ſhall be whiter then ſnow: Who can tell where the ſpot was, when the skin is rinced?
                  
                     If we confeſſe our ſinnes,
                     1. Iohn 1.9. 
                     he is faithfull to forgiue our ſinnes, and to cleanſe vs from all vnrighteouſneſſe. Loe, he cleanſeth vs from the guilt, and forgiues the puniſhment:
                  What are our ſinnes but debts?Mat. 6.12. What is the infliction of puniſhment, but an exaction of payment? What is our remiſſion, but a ſtriking off that ſcore? And when the ſcore is ſtrucke off, what remaynes to pay? Remitte debita; Forgiue our debts is our daily Prayer.
                  Our Sauiour tels the Paralitick, Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee;Mar. 2.5. In the ſame words implying the remouing

of his diſeaſe; the ſinne bee gone, the puniſhment cannot ſtay behind: We may ſmart by way of chaſtiſement, after the freeſt remiſſion, not by way of reuenges; for our amendment, not for Gods ſatisfaction.
                  The ſecond ground is a middle condition betwixt the ſtate of eternall life and death; of no leſſe torment for the time, then Hell it ſelfe; whoſe flames may burne off the ruſt of our remayning ſinnes; the iſſues where-from are in the power of the great Paſtor of the Church: How did this eſcape the notice of our Sauiour?
                  
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        , &amp;c· Iohn 5.24.
                     Verify, verily I ſay vnto you, hee that heareth my Word, and beleeueth in him that ſent mee, hath euerlaſting life, and comes not into iudgement (as the Vulgar it ſelfe turnes it) but is paſſed from death vnto life;
                  Behold a preſent poſſeſſion, and immediate paſſage, no iudgement interuening, no torment;
                  How was this hid from the great Doctor of the Gentiles, who putting

himſelfe into the common caſe of the beleeuing Corinthians, profeſſes; Wee know,
                     2. Cor. 5.1. 
                     that if once our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle bee diſſolued, wee haue a building of God, not made with hands, eternall in the Heauens.
                  
                  The diſſolution of the one is the poſſeſſion of the other; here is no interpoſition of time, of eſtate.
                  The wiſe man of old could ſay. The ſoules of the righteous are in the hand of God;
                     Wiſd. 3.1. 
                     and there ſhall no torment touch them. Vpon their very going from vs they are in peace.
                     Verſe 3. (
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     ) as Saint Iohn heard from the heauenly voyce;Reuel. 14.13. 
                     From their very dying in the Lord is their bleſſedneſſe.
                  
               
               
                  
                  SECT. III. Indulgences againſt Reaſon.
                  IT is abſurd in reaſon, to thinke that God ſhould forgiue our Talents, and arreſt vs for the odde farthings; Neither is it leſſe abſurd to thinke, that any liuing ſoule can haue ſuperfluities of ſatisfaction; when as all that man is capable to ſuffer, cannot be ſufficient for one; (and that the leaſt) ſin of his owne; the wages whereof is eternall death. Or,Collegia clericorum &amp; conuentus religioſorum aſpergunt &amp; incenſant corpus Papae, &amp; abſoluunt. Sacr. Cerem. that thoſe ſuperfluities of humane ſatisfaction ſhould peece vp the infinite, and perfitly meritorious ſuperabundance of the Sonne of God; Or that this ſuppoſed treaſure of diuine and humane ſatisfactions; ſhould bee kept vnder the key of ſome one ſinfull man; Or that this one man who cannot deliuer his owne ſoule from Purgatorie, no not from hell it ſelfe, ſhould haue

power to free what others hee pleaſeth from thoſe fearefull flames; to the full Iaole-deliuerie of that direfull priſon: which though his great power can doe, yet his no leſſe charitie will not, doth not.
                  Or that the ſame pardon which cannot acquit a man from one houres tooth-ach, ſhould be of force to giue his ſoule eaſe, from the temporarie paines of another world.
                  Laſtly, guilt and puniſhment are relatiues; and can no more be ſeuered then a perfect forgiueneſſe, and a remaining compenſation can ſtand together.
                  This doctrine therefore of Papall Indulgences, as it led the way to the further diſcouery of the corruptions of the degenerated Church of Rome, ſo it ſtill continues iuſtly branded with noueltie and errour, and may not bee admitted into our beleefe; and wee for reiecting it are vniuſtly refuſed.
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. XII. The newneſſe of Diuine Seruice in an vnknowne tongue.
               
                  THat Prayers and other Diuine offices ſhould bee done in a known tongue, vnderſtood of the people,Cai
                        •
                     t. in 1. Cor. 14. Ex hac Paul
                        •
                      doctrina h
                        •
                     betur quod 
                        ••
                     eli
                        •
                     s ad aediſ
                        ••
                     ation. in Eccleſiae eſt orationes publicas quae audiente po
                        •
                     u
                        ••
                      dicantur dici lingua communi clericis &amp; po
                        •
                     ulo quàm dici Latine. Lyr. ibid. Concil. Later. Anno 1215.
                   is not more auailable to edification (as their Caietan liberally confeſſeth) then conſonant to the practice of all antiquitie; In ſo much as Lyranus freely, In the Primitiue Church, bleſſings and all other ſeruices were done in the vulgar tongue.
               What need wee looke backe ſo farre, when euen the Lateran Councell, which was but in the yeere 1215. vnder Innocent the third, makes this decree. Quoniam in plaeriſque, Becauſe in many parts within the ſame Citie and Dioceſſe, people are mixed of diuers languages hauing

vnder one faith diuers rites and faſhions, wee ſtrictly command, that the Biſhops of the ſayd Cities or Dioceſſes prouide fit and able men, who according to the diuerſities of their rites and languages may celebrate diuine ſeruices, and adminiſter the Sacraments of the Church to them, inſtructing them both in word and example. Cardinall Bellarmines euaſion is verie groſſe. That in that place Innocentius and the Councell ſpeake onely of the Greeke, and Latine tongue: For then (ſaith he) Conſtantinople was newly taken by the Romans, by reaſon whereof there was in Greece a mixture of Greekes and Latines; in ſo much as they deſired that in ſuch places of frequence two Biſhops might be allowed for the ordering of thoſe ſeuerall Nations. Whereupon it was concluded, that ſince it were no other then monſtrous to appoint two Biſhops vnto one See; it ſhould be the charge of that one Biſhop to prouide ſuch vnder

him as ſhould adminiſter all holy things to the Grecians in Greeke, and in Latine to the Latines. For who ſees not that the Conſtitution is generall, Plaeriſque partibus, for verie many parts of the Chriſtian world, and (Populi diuerſarum ling
                        •
                     arum) People of ſundrie languages; not as Bellarmine cunningly, (diuerſae linguae) of a diuerſe language: And if theſe two only languages had been meant, why had it not bin as eaſie to ſpecifie them, as to intimate them by ſo large a circumlocution? This Synode is ſaid to be vniuerſall, comprehending all the Patriarkes; ſeuentie ſeuen Metropolitans, and the moſt eminent Diuines of both Eaſt and Weſt Churches; to the number of at leaſt 2212. perſons, or, as ſome others, 2285. beſides the Embaſſadours of all Chriſtian Princes of ſeuerall languages; Now ſhall wee thinke that there were in all their Territories and Iuriſdictions no mixtures of inhabitants, but onely of Grecians

and Romans? or, that all theſe Fathers were careleſſe of the reſt? Eſpecially, ſince the end which they profeſſe to propoſe vnto themſelues herein, is the inſtruction of the people, of what nation or language ſoeuer; which end, as it was neuer meant to bee limited to two ſorts of people, ſo could it neuer be attained without this libertie of language fitted to their vnderſtanding: To which may bee added, that the Greekes and Latines, of all other, had the leaſt need of this prouiſion, ſince it was famouſly knowne that they had their ſeuerall ſeruices already of receiued and currant vſe, before this conſtitution was hatched.
               Neither, is it of any moment, which hee addeth, that in Italy it ſelfe this decree was not extended to the vſe of vulgar tongues; for that it is euident that Saint Thomas (who liued ſoone after) compoſed in Latine the Office of the feaſt of Corpus Chriſti; not in the Italian;Thom. Aquinin
                        •
                      Cor. c. 4.
                  
                  
although the ſame Aquinas confeſſes that that the vulgar tongue of Italy at that time was not Latine; For, what childe cannot eaſily ſee, that if their great Doctor would write an office for the publique vſe (as is intended) of the whole Church; hee would make choyce to write it in ſuch a language as might improue it to the moſt common benefit of all the Chriſtian world? not confining it to the bounds of a particular Nation; Beſides what was the Italian (in thoſe times eſpecially) but a broken and corrupt Latine differing more in Idiome and termination, then in the ſubſtance of ſpeech: That which Radeuicus about the yeere 1170. records for the voyce of the people, in the election of Pope Victor, Papa Vittore Sancto Pietro l'elege, makes good no leſſe; for what ſuch difference is betwixt this, and Papam Victorem Sanctus Petrus elegit; So as this inſtance doth nothing at all infringe that iuſt decree of the Roman

Fathers. Howſoeuer, that obſeruation of Eraſmus is true, and pregnant to this purpoſe,Nec lingua vulgaris populo ſubtracta eſt, ſed populus ab e a receſſit. Eraſ. declarat. ad Cenſur. Purif. tit. 12. ſect. 14. Bed hiſtor. l. 1.
                   
                  (Nec lingua vulgaris &amp;e.) Neither was the vulgar tongue (i. the Latine) withdrawne from the people, but the people went off from it.
               And as for our Anceſtours in this Iſland; Our venerable Bede witneſſes, that in England the Scriptures were read by them in fiue languages, according to the number of the bookes wherein the Law of God was written, namely Engliſh, Scottiſh, Brittiſh, Pictiſh, and Latine; which ſaith hee in meditation of the Scriptures is made common to all the reſt. A point which the ſayd Author ſpecifies for a commendation of the well-inſtructedneſſe of thoſe people, not, as purpoſing to intimate that the vſe of the Latine did thruſt out the other foure; for, he there tells vs that in all foure they did not only ſearch, but confeſſe, and vtter the knowledge of the higheſt truth. This reſtraint

then is not more new then enuious and preiudiciall to the honour of God, and the ſoules of men.
               
                  SECT. II. Againſt Scripture.
                  AS for Scriptures. Were this practice ſo old as it is pretended;Longaeuae 
                           〈…〉
                         non 
                           〈…〉
                         ritas 
                           〈…〉
                         con
                           •
                        uet, &amp;c the rule is (Longaeuae conſuetudinis, &amp;c.) the authoritie of an ancient cuſtome is not to be ſleighted, ſo long as it is not againſt the Canons: Nothing can be more againſt the Canons of the bleſſed Apoſtle, then this; who, did he liue in theſe our dayes, and would bend his ſpeech againſt the vſe of a language not vnderſtood in Gods ſeruice, could not ſpeake more directly, more punctually, then hee doth to his Corinths. How doth hee tell vs, that the ſpeaking in a ſtrange tongue

edifies not the Church,1. Cor. 14.5, 6 profits not the hearers; produces a neceſſarie ignorance of the thing ſpoken; Makes mee a Barbarian to him that ſpeaketh,Verſe 9. and him that ſpeakes a Barbarian to me.
                  How doth hee require him that ſpeaketh in an vnknowne tongue to pray that hee may interpret.Verſe 11. And if hee muſt pray that hee may doe it;Verſe 13. how much more muſt he practice it, when he can doe it?
                  How doth hee tell vs that in a ſtrange languaged prayer the vnderſtanding is vnfruitfull.Verſe 14. 
                     Verſe 19. That it is better to ſpeake fiue words with vnderſtanding, that wee may teach others, then ten thouſand words in an vnknowne tongue.Verſe 23. That thoſe which ſpeake with ſtrange tongues are but as mad men to the vnlearned, or vnbeleeuers.
               
               
                  
                  SECT. III. Against reaſon.
                  IN which Scriptures (beſides authoritie) the Apoſtle hath comprized vnanſwerable, and conuincing reaſons againſt this Romiſh abuſe; Amongſt the reſt is intimated that vtter fruſtration of the vſe of the tongue in Gods ſeruice: For it is a true rule which Salmeron cites out of Lactantius (Nihil valet ex ſe &amp;c.
                     Salmeron in illa vos eſtis ſal terrae. Ex Lactanctio.) That thing is to no purpoſe which auailes not vnto the end whereto it ſerues: Silence doth as much expreſſe the thought, as a language not vnderſtood: In this ſenſe is that of Laurentius too well verified,Laurent. Preſbyt. Piſanus, Paradox. Euangelic. 
                     Sacerdos imperitus mulier ſterilis: A Prieſt vnable to expreſſe himſelfe is as a barren woman; vncapable of bringing forth children to God:Quid prodeſt fons ſignatus? As good no tongue as no vnderſtanding; What good doth a Well ſealed vp, as Ptolome ſayd of the Hebrew Text.
                  
                     Wherefore doe we ſpeake, if we would not bee vnderſtood: It was an holy reſolution of Saint Auguſtine, that hee would rather ſay Oſſum in falſe Latin, to be vnderſtood of the people, then Os in true, not to be vnderſtood: This practice, howeuer it may ſeeme in it ſelfe ſleight and vnworthy of too much contention, yet in regard of that miſerable blindneſſe and miſ-deuotion, which it muſt needs draw in after it, it is ſo hainous, as may well deſerue our vtmoſt oppoſition: The vnauoydableneſſe of which effects hath carried ſome of their Caſuiſts into an opinion of the vnneceſſarineſſe of deuotion in theſe holy buſineſſes; ſo as one ſayes, He that wants deuotion ſinnes not; Another,I
                           •
                        c. Graph. deciſ. aur. Sylu quaeſt. 80. Artic. 9.
                      Though it bee conuenient that the Communicant ſhould haue actuall deuotion, yet it is not neceſſarie: Alas, what ſeruice is this which poore ſoules are taught to take vp with; which God muſt be content to take from hoodwinkt ſuppliants? This doctrine,

this practice, thus new, thus preiudiciall to Chriſtians, we bleſſe God that we haue ſo happily diſcarded; and for our iuſt refuſall are vniuſtly eiected.
               
            
            
               CHAP. XIII. The newneſſe of forced Sacramentall Confeſsion.
               
                  Concil. Trid. Si quis dixerit in Sacram. Poenitentiae ad remiſſionem, &amp;c. Anath. &amp;c. Seſſ. 14. Gloſſ. Grat. de Poenit. diſt. 5. c. In poenitentia. Graeci ſolummodo Deo confitendum dicunt. de poenit. d. 1.
                  
                  THe neceſſitie of a particular, ſecret, full, Sacramentall Confeſſion of all our ſins to a Prieſt; vpon paine of Non-remiſſion, is an Act or Inſtitution of the Romane Church, For, as for the Greeke Church it ownes not either the doctrine, or practice. So the Gloſſe of the Canon Law directly; Confeſsio apud Graecos, &amp;c. Confeſſion is not not neceſſary amongſt the Grecians;

vnto whom no ſuch Tradition hath beene deriued.
               That Gloſſe would tell vs more;Multa alia &amp; magni ponderis emendata ſunt. In notis ibid. and ſo would Gratian himſelfe, if their tongues were not clipt by a guiltie expurgation. But in the meane time the Gloſſe of that Canon (hitherto allowed) plainly controules the Decree of that late Councell; For if the Neceſſitie of Confeſſion be only a Tradition, and ſuch a one, as hath not beene deduced to the Greeke Church, then it ſtands not by a Law of God, which is vniuerſall; not making differences of places, or times; like an high-eleuated Starre which hath no particular aſpect vpon one Region.
               That there is a lawfull, commendable beneficiall vſe of Confeſſion was neuer denied by vs; but to ſet men vpon the racke, and to ſtraine their ſoules vp to a double pin, of abſolute neceſſitie (both praecepti and medij) and of a ſtrict particularitie; and that by a ſcrew of Ius diuinum,
                  
Gods Law, is ſo meere a Romane noueltie, that many ingenuous Authors of their owne haue willingly confeſſed it.
               
                  Bellar. de poenit. l. 3. c. 1. In Annot. Hier. ad Ocean. In notis Tertull. de poenitent. &amp;c.Amongſt whom Cardinall Bellarmine himſelfe yeelds vs, Eraſmus, and Beatus Rhenanus, two noble Witneſſes; Whoſe ioynt-Tenet he confeſſes to be, Confeſsionem ſecretam, &amp;c. That the ſecret Confeſſion of all our ſinnes is not only not inſtituted, or commanded Iure Diuino, by Gods Law; but that it was not ſo much as receiued into vſe in the Ancient Church of God. To whom he might haue added, out of Maldonates account (omnes decretorum, &amp;c.) all the Interpreters of the Decrees, and amongſt the Schoolemen, Scotus.
               
               We know well thoſe ſad and auſtere Exomologeſis, which were publikely vſed in the ſeuere times of the Primitiue Church: whiles theſe tooke place, what vſe was there of priuate? Theſe obtayned euen in the Weſterne or Latine Church, till

the dayes of Leo; about 450. yeares.De presbyt. poenitentiarijs, vide Socrat. l. 5. c. 19.
                   In which time they had a graue publike Penitentiarie for this purpoſe. Afterwards (whether the noted inconueniences of that practice, or whether the cooling of the former feruour occaſioned it) this open Confeſſion beganne to giue way to ſecret; which continued in the Church, but with freedome, and without that forced and ſcrupulous ſtrictneſſe which the later times haue put vpon it.Beat. Rhenan. Argum. in Tert. de poenitentia. It is verie remarkable which learned Rhenanus hath (Caeterum Thomas ab Aquino, &amp;c.) But (ſaith hee) Thomas of Aquine and Scotus (men too acute) haue made confeſſion at this day ſuch,Argentoratum, &amp;c. as that Ioannes Geilerius a graue and holy Diuine, which was for many yeeres Preacher at Strasburgh, had wont to ſay to his frends, that according to their rules it is an impoſſible thing to confeſſe; Adding, that the ſame Geilerius being familiarly conuerſant with ſome religious Votaries, both Carthuſians and Franciſcans,

learned of them, with what torments the godly mindes of ſome men were afflicted, by the rigour of that confeſſion, which they were not able to anſwer; and thereupon he publiſhed a booke in Dutch, entitled The ſickneſſe of confeſsion. The ſame therefore which Rhenanus writes of his Geilerius, he may well apply vnto vs; Itaque Geilerio non diſplicebat, &amp;c. Geilerius therefore did not diſlike confeſſion, but the ſcrupulous anxietie which is taught in the ſummes of ſome late Diuines, more fit 
                     ••
                  deed for ſome other place, then for Libraries. Thus he. What would that ingenuous Author haue ſayd, if hee had liued to ſee thoſe volumes of Caſes which haue beene ſince publiſhed, able to perplex a world; and thoſe peremptorie deciſions of the Fathers of the Societie, whoſe ſtrokes haue beene with Scorpions, in compariſon of the rods of their Predeceſſors. To conclude; This bird was hatched in the Councell of Lateran, (Anno
                  
1215.) fully plumed in the Councell of Trent; and now lately hath her feathers imped by the moderne Caſuiſts.
               
                  SECT. II. Romiſh Confeſsion not warranted by Scripture.
                  SInce our quarrell is n
                        •
                     t with confeſſion it ſelfe, which may bee of ſingular vſe and behoofe; but with ſome tyrannous ſtraines in the practice of it, which are the violent forcing and perfit fulneſſe thereof; It ſhall be ſufficient for vs herein to ſtand vpon our negatiue; That there is no Scripture in the whole booke of God, wherein either ſuch neceſſitie, or ſuch intireneſſe of Confeſſion is commanded; A truth ſo cleare, that it is generally confeſſed by their owne Canoniſts. Did we queſtion

the lawfulneſſe of Confeſſion, we ſhould be iuſtly accountable for our grounds from the Scriptures of God; now that we cry downe only ſome iniurious circumſtances therein, well may wee require from the fautors thereof their warrants from God; which if they cannot ſhow, they are ſufficiently conuinced of a preſumptuous obtruſion:
                  Indeed, our Sauiour ſayd to his Apoſtles, and their ſucceſſours, Whoſe ſinnes yee remit they are remitted,
                     Iohn 20.23. 
                     and whoſe ſinnes ye retaine they are retained. But did hee ſay, No ſinne ſhall bee remitted, but what yee remit? Or, no ſinne ſhall be remitted by you, but what is particularly numbred vnto you.
                  
                     Iames 5.16.Saint Iames bids, Confeſſe your ſinnes one to another; But would they haue the Prieſt ſhrieue himſelfe to the penitent, as well as the penitent to the Prieſt? This act muſt bee mutuall, not ſingle.
                  
                     Acts 19.18.Many beleeuing Epheſians came and confeſſed, and ſhewed their

deeds. Many, but not all, not Omnes vtriuſque ſexus, they confeſſed their deeds; Some that were notorious, not all their ſinnes.
                  Contrarily rather,Iohn 20.21. ſo did Chriſt ſend his Apoſtles, as the father ſent him, He was both their warrant and their patterne; But that gracious Sauiour of ours many a time gaue abſolution, where was no particular confeſſion of ſinnes: Only the ſight of the Paralyticks faith fetcht from him, Sonne be of good cheere,
                     Mat. 9.2. 
                     thy ſins be forgiuen thee; The noted ſinner in Simons houſe, approuing the truth of her repentance by the humble and coſtly teſtimonies of her loue, without any enumeration of her ſinnes, heard, Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee.
                  
               
               
                  
                  SECT. III. Against reaſon.
                  IN true Diuine Reaſon this ſuppoſed dutie is needleſſe, dangerous, impoſſible. Needleſſe in reſpect of all ſinnes, not in reſpect of ſome; for how euer in the caſes of a burdened conſcience, nothing can bee more vſefull, more ſoueraigne, yet, in all, our peace doth not depend vpon our lips; Being iuſtified by faith,Rom. 5.1. wee haue peace with God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.
                  Dangerous, in reſpect both of exprobration, as Saint Chryſoſtome worthily,Chryſ. in Pſ. 50.
                      
                     Sayr. Summa Caſ. Nauar. and of infection; for delectabile carnis (as a Caſuiſt confeſſeth) Fleſhly pleaſures the more they are called into particular mention, the more they moue the appetire. I doe willingly conceale from chaſte eyes and eares what effects haue followed this pretended act of

deuotion, in wanton and vnſtayed Confeſſours.
                  Impoſſible, for who can tell how oft he offendeth; He is poore in ſin that can count his ſtocke; and hee ſinnes alwayes that ſo preſumes vpon his innocence, as to thinke hee can number his ſinnes: And, if hee ſay of any ſinne, as Lot of Zoar, is it not a little one? as if therefore it may ſafely eſcape the reckoning, it is a true word of Iſaac the Syrian,Iſaac. Syr. presb. Antiochen. de Contempt. mundi. &amp;c. 
                     Qui delicta &amp;c. Hee that thinkes any of his offences ſmall, euen in ſo thinking falls into greater.
                  This doctrine and practice therfore, both as new and vnwarrantable, full of vſurpation, danger, impoſſibilitie is iuſtly reiected by vs; and wee for ſo doing, vniuſtly eiected.
               
               
                  
                  SECT. IV. The noueltie of Abſolution before Satisfaction.
                  LEſt any thing in the Romane Church ſhould retaine the old forme, how abſurd is that innouation which they haue made in the the order of their penance and abſolution. The ancient courſe, as Caſſander and Lindanus truly witneſſe,Caſſand. conſult. Art. de Confeſſ. Lind. Pan
                           •
                        pl. l 4.
                      was that abſolution and reconciliation, and right to the Communion of the Church was not giuen by impoſition of hands vnto the penitent, till hee had giuen due ſatisfaction by performing of ſuch penall acts, as were enioyned by the diſcreet Penitētiary;C
                           •
                        ſſ. ibid. yea, thoſe works of penance (ſaith he) when they were done out of faith, and an heart truly ſorrowfull; and by the motion of the holy Spirit, preuenting the minde of man, with the helpe of his diuine grace, were thought not a

little auailable to obtaine remiſſion of the ſinne, and to pacifie the diſpleaſure of God for ſinne; Not, that they could merit it by any dignitie of theirs, but that thereby the minde of man is in a ſort fitted to the receit of Gods grace; But now, immediately vpon the Confeſſion made, the hand is layd vpon the penitent, and he is receiued to his right of Communion, and after his abſolution, certaine workes of pietie are enioyned him, for the chaſtiſement of the fleſh, and expurgation of the remainders of ſinne. Thus Caſſander. In common apprehenſion this new order can bee no other then prepoſterous; and (as our learned Biſhop of Carlile) like Eaſter before Lent. But for this,Reſp. ad Fiſherum. 
                     Ipſi viderint; it ſhall not trouble vs how they nurture their owne childe.
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. XIV. The newneſſe of the Romiſh Inuocation of Saints.
               
                  OF all thoſe errours which we reiect in the Church of Rome, there is none that can plead ſo much ſhow of Antiquitie,Spalat. de Reſp. Eccl. l. 7. c. 12. § 16.
                   as this of Inuocation of Saints: which yet, as it hath beene practiſed and defended in the latter times, ſhould in vaine ſeeke either example or patronage amongſt the Ancient; How euer there might be ſome grounds of this deuotion ſecretly muttered, and at laſt expreſſed in Panegyricke formes, yet, vntill almoſt fiue hundred yeeres after Chriſt,Rex Iacob. praemonit. ad Principes, &amp;c. it was not in any ſort admitted into the publique ſeruice. It will be eaſily graunted that the bleſſed Virgin is the Prime of all Saints; neither could it be other then iniurious, that any other of that heauenly ſocietie ſhould haue the precedencie

of her: Now the firſt that brought her name into the publike deuotions of the Greeke Church,Niceph. l. 15. c. 28.
                   is noted by Nicephorus, to be Petrus Gnapheus, or Fullo, a Preſbyter of Bithynia; afterwards the Vſurper of the See of Antioch, much about 470 yeeres after Chriſt; who (though a branded heretick) found out foure things (ſaith he) verie vſefull and beneficiall to the Catholike Church; whereof the laſt was,Eccleſiae Catholicae commodiſſima, ibid. 
                  (Vt in omni precatione &amp;c.) that in euerie prayer the Mother of God ſhould bee named, and her diuine name called vpon; The phraſe is verie remarkable wherein this riſing ſuperſtition is expreſſed.
               And as for the Latine Church, we heare no newes of this Inuocation, in the publique Letanies, till Gregories time, about ſome 130. yeeres after the former.
               And in the meane time, ſome Fathers ſpeake of it fearefully and doubtfully; How could it bee otherwiſe, when the common opinion

of the Ancients,Ioſ. Scalig. Notis in Nouum Teſt. euen below Saint Auſtens age did put vp all the ſoules of the faithfull, except Martyrs in ſome blinde receptacles, whether in the Center of the earth, or elſewhere, where they might in candida expectare diem Iudicij, as Tertullian hath it foure ſeuerall times; And Stapleton himſelfe ſticks not to name diuers of them thus fouly miſtaken.Stap. l. de author. ſcr.
               
               Others of the Fathers haue let fall ſpeeches directly bent againſt this Inuocation (Non opus eſt patronis, &amp;c.
                  
                     Chryſoſt. Homil. de poenitentia, hom. 4. Which place, the Margine of the Latine Edition of Venice, ſet forth by the authoritie of the Inquiſition, tels vs, (and wee muſt beleeue it) makes nothing againſt Inuocation of Saints. Vide Ibid.
                  ) There is no need of any Aduocates to God, ſaith Saint Chryſoſtome; and moſt plainly elſewhere, Homines ſi quando &amp;c. If wee haue any ſuit to men (ſaith he) wee muſt fee the porters, and treat with ieſters and paraſites, and goe many times a long way about; In God there is no ſuch matter; he is exorable without any of our Mediatours, without mony, without coſt, he grants our petitions: It is enough to cry for thee with thine heart alone, to powre out thy teares, and preſently thou haſt

won him to mercie. Thus hee.
               And thoſe of the Ancients, that ſeeme to ſpeake for it, lay grounds that ouerthrow it; Howſoeuer it be, all holy Antiquitie would haue both bluſhed, and ſpit at thoſe formes of Inuocation, which the late Clients of Rome haue broached to the world; If perhaps they ſpake to the Saints (tanquam deprecatores,
                  Spalat. l. 7. c. 12. § 26. Gul. Altiſ. in 4. ſent. &amp;c. Dea, primas Coeli, &amp;c. praecipe Angelis vt nos cuſtodiant. In Roſar. Canon. Reg. Anonym. Diuidunt coram Patre inter ſe mater &amp; ſilius pietatis officia, &amp; condunt inter ſe reconciliationis noſtrae inuiolabile teſtamentum. Arnold. Carnot. de laudibus 5. virg. Lud. Ʋiues in Aug. de Ciuitat. Dei l. 8. c. vlt. 
                  vel potius comprecatores) as Spalatenſis yeelds; mouing them to bee competitioners with vs to the throne of grace, not properly, but improperly, as Altiſiodore conſtrues it; how would they haue digeſted that blaſphemous Pſalter of our Ladie, imputed to Bonauenture, and thoſe ſtiles of meere Deification which are giuen to her; and the diuiſion of all offices of pietie to mankinde, betwixt the mother and the Sonne. How had their eares glowed to heare, Christus orauit, Franciſcus exoranit, Chriſt praied, Francis preuailed; How would they haue brooked that which Ludouicus Viues
                  
freely confeſſes, Multi Chriſtiani &amp;c· Many Chriſtians worſhip (diuos, diua
                        •
                     que) the Saints of both ſexes, no otherwiſe then God himſelfe; Or that which Spalatenſis profeſſes to haue obſerued that the ignorant multitude are carried with more entire religious affection to the bleſſed Virgin,Nam &amp; plebem rudiorem religiose &amp;c. Et magis plurimos interne religioſo affectu erga Beatam Ʋirg. &amp;c. quam erga Chriſtum, Spalat. de Re. Eccl. l. 7. c. 12. ſ. 28.
                   or ſome other Saint, then to Chriſt their Sauiour. Theſe foule ſuperſtitions are not more hainous then new, and ſuch, as wherein we haue iuſtly abhorred to take part with the practices of them.
               
                  SECT. II. Inuocation of Saints againſt Scripture.
                  AS for the better ſide of this miſ-opinion; euen thus much colour of Antiquitie were cauſe enough to ſuſpend our cenſures (according

to that wiſe and moderate reſolution of learned Zanchius;Ego certè ab Autiquitate non recedo niſi coactus Zanch. in Coloſſ.) were it not that the Scriptures are ſo flatly oppoſite vnto it; as that, we may iuſtly wonder at that wiſdome, which hath prouided Antidotes for a diſeaſe, that of many hundred yeares after, ſhould haue no being in the World. The ground of this Inuocation of Saints is their notice of our earthly condition, and ſpeciall Deuotions;Iob 14.20, And behold thou preuayleſt euer againſt man, and he paſſeth; thou changeſt his countenance, and ſendeſt him away;Verſe 21. His ſonnes come to honour and hee knowes it not, and they are brought low and he perceiueth it not, ſaith Iob. The dead know nothing at all,
                     Eccleſ. 9.5, ſaith wiſe Salomon; Alſo their loue, and their hatred, and their enuie is now periſhed,
                     Verſe 6. 
                     neither haue they any more a portion for euer, in any thing that is done vnder the Sunne; No portion in any thing, therefore not in our miſeries; not in our allocutions. If we haue a portion in them, for their

loue and Prayers in common for the Church, they haue no portion in our particularities, whether of want, or complaint.Eſay 63.16. 
                     Abraham our Father is ignorant of vs (ſaith Eſay) and Iſrael acknowledges vs not. Loe, the Father of the faithful aboue knowes not his own children, till they come into his boſome; and hee that giues them their names, is to them as ſtrangers;2. Kings 22.20. 
                     Wherefore ſhould good Ioſiah bee gathered to his Fathers as Hulda tels him, but that his eyes might not ſee all the euill which ſhould come vpon Ieruſalem?
                  
                  Wee cannot haue a better Commenter,Auguſt. de cura pro
                           •
                        n ort. gerend. cap. 13. then Saint Auguſtine, If (ſaith hee) the ſoules of the dead could be preſent at the affaires of the liuing, &amp;c. Surely my good Mother would no night forſake me, whom whiles ſhe liued, ſhee followed both by Land, and Sea; Farre be it from mee to thinke, that an happier life hath made her cruell, &amp;c. But certainly, that which the holy Pſalmiſt tels vs, is true; My Father and my

Mother haue forſaken me, but the Lord tooke me vp; If therefore our Parents haue left vs, how are they preſent or doe intereſſe themſelues in our cares, or buſineſſes? And if our Parents do not, who elſe among the dead know what wee doe, or what wee ſuffer? Eſay the Prophet ſaith; Thou art our Father, for Abraham is ignorant of vs, and Iſrael know vs not; If ſo great Patriarkes were ignorant, what became of that people, which came from their loynes, and which vpon their beliefe was promiſed to deſcend from their ſtocke, how ſhall the dead haue ought to doe either in the knowledge, or aide of the affaires, or actions of their deareſt Suruiuers? How doe we ſay that God prouides mercifully for them who die before the euils come, if euen after their death, they are ſenſible of the calamities of humane life, &amp;c.
                  How is it then that God promiſed to good King Ioſiah for a great bleſſing, that hee ſhould die before

hand, that he might not ſee the euils which hee threatned to that place and people.
                  Thus that diuine Father. With whom agrees Saint Ierome;
                     Hieron. in Eccleſ. 3. ad fin. 
                     Nec enim, poſſumus, &amp;c. Neither can we (ſaith hee) when this life ſhall once be diſſolued, either enioy our owne labours, or know what ſhall bee done in the World afterwards.
                  But could the Saints of Heauen know our actions, yet our hearts they cannot: This is the peculiar skill of their Maker,Pſal. 7.10. 
                     Thou art the ſearcher of the hearts and reines, O righteous God;
                     Pſal. 4
                           •
                        .22. &amp; 139, 1.4. &amp; 13. Prou. 15 11. &amp; 17.3. &amp; 24.12. 
                     God only knowes (abſcondita animi) the hidden ſecrets of the ſoule. Now, the heart is the ſeat of our Prayers. The lips doe but vent them to the eares of men: Moſes ſaid nothing,Ier. 21.20. &amp; 17.10. &amp; 20.12. when God ſaid, Let me alone Moſes. O therefore thou that heareſt the Prayers, to thee ſhall all fleſh come.
                     1. Kings 8.39. 
                     Salomons argument is irrefragable; Heare thou in Heauen thy dwelling place; and doe, and giue to euery man according to his wayes:

whoſe heart thou knoweſt; For thou, euen thou only, knoweſt the hearts of all the children of men.
                  
                  He only ſhould be implored that can heare; hee only can heare the Prayer that knowes the heart:
                  Yet could they know our ſecreteſt deſires. It is an honour that God challengeth as proper to himſelfe, to bee inuoked in our Prayers;Pſal. 50.14. 
                     Call vpon me in the day of thy trouble, and I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.
                  
                  
                     There is one God, and one Mediator betwixt God and man,
                     1. Tim. 2.5. 
                     the man Ieſus Christ. One, and no more, not only of redemption, but of interceſſion alſo; for through him (onely) we haue acceſſe by one Spirit, vnto the Father; and he hath inuited vs to himſelfe;Epheſ. 2.1
                           •
                        . 
                     Come to me all yee that labour and are heauie laden.
                  
               
               
                  
                  SECT. III. Againſt reaſon.
                  HOw abſurd therefore is it in reaſon, when the King of heauen cals vs to him, to run with our petitions to the Guard or Pages of the Court? Had we to doe with a finite Prince, whoſe eares muſt be his beſt informers, or whoſe will to help vs were iuſtly queſtionable, wee might haue reaſon to preſent our ſuits by ſecond hands; But ſince it is an Omnipreſent and Omniſcious God with whom wee deale, from whom the Saints and Angels receiue all their light, and loue to his Church, how extreme folly is it to ſue to thoſe Courtiers of Heauen, and not to come immediately to the Throne of Grace? That one Mediatour is able (and willing alſo) to ſaue them to the vtmoſt,Heb. 7.25. that come vnto God by him; ſeeing he euer liueth to make interceſſion for them.
                  
                     Beſides, how vncertaine muſt our deuotions needes bee, when we can haue no poſſible aſſurance of their audience; for who can know that a Saint heares him? That God euer heares vs, wee are as ſure, as wee are vnſure to be heard of Saints: Nay, we are ſure wee cannot bee all heard of them: For what finite nature can diuide it ſelfe betwixt ten thouſand Suppliants at one inſtant, in ſeuerall regions of the world, much leſſe impart it ſelfe whole to each? Either therefore, wee muſt turne the Saints into ſo many Deities, or wee muſt yeeld that ſome of our prayers are vnheard; And whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.
                  
                  As for that heauenly glaſſe of Saint Gregories, wherein the Saints ſee vs, and our ſuits (confuted long ſince by Hugo de Sancto Victore) it is as pleaſing a fiction,Hugo de Sancto Vict. de ſacr. l 2
                      as if we imagined therefore to ſee all the corners of the earth, becauſe we ſee that Sun which ſees them. And the ſame eyes that ſee in God the particular

neceſſities of his Saints below, ſee in the ſame God ſuch infinite grace and mercie, for their releefe, as may ſaue the labour of their reflecting vpon that diuine miroir in their ſpeciall interceſſions.
                  This doctrine therefore and practice of the Romiſh inuocation of Saints, both as new and erroneous, againſt Scripture and reaſon, wee haue iuſtly reiected; and are thereupon eiected as vniuſtly.
               
            
            
               CHAP. XV. The newneſſe of ſeuen Sacraments.
               
                  Summa Caranzae, &amp;c.
                  THe late Councell of Florence indeed inſinuates this number of ſeuen Sacraments, as Suarez contends: But the later Councell of Trent determines it,Concil. Trid. Ceſſ 7. Can. 1.
                   
                  Si quis dixerit aut plura, &amp;c.
                  
If any man ſhall ſay, that there are either more, or fewer Sacraments then ſeuen, viz. Baptiſme, Confirmation, &amp;c, or that any of theſe is not truly and properly a Sacrament, Let him be Anathema.
               
               It is not more plaine that in Scripture there is no mention of Sacraments, then that in the Fathers there is no mention of ſeuen. Cardinall Bellarmines euaſion, that the Scripture and Fathers wrote no Catechiſme, is poore and ridiculous; No more did the Councels of Florence and Trent, and yet there the number is reckoned and defined.
               So as the word Sacrament may be taken (for any holy, ſignificant rite) there may bee as well ſeuentie as ſeuen; So ſtrictly as it may be, and is taken by vs, there can no more bee ſeuen, then ſeuentie. This determination of the number is ſo late, that Caſſander is forced to confeſſe,Caſſand. Conſult. Art. 13. de numero ſacr. 
                  Nec temerè, &amp;c. You ſhall not eaſily find any man before Peter Lombard, which hath ſet downe any certaine

and definite number of Sacraments. And this obſeruation is ſo iuſt that vpon the challenges of our writers, no one author hath bin produced by the Roman Doctours, for the diſproofe of it,Luther de capti
                        ••
                     t. Babyl. I
                        •
                      loc. com. Caſſ
                        ••
                      l. ibid. Thus all Antiquitie runnes upon two. 
                     
                        •
                     em recognit. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . A
                     
                        •
                      
                     2 tertull de 
                        〈◊〉
                      Milit. &amp; 
                        〈…〉
                      
                     2. Epiſt. 1. 
                     
                        〈…〉
                      Auguſt, &amp;c. elder then Hugo, and the ſaid Maſter of Sentences. But, numbers are ceremonies. Both Luther, and Philip Melancthon profeſſe they ſtand not much vpon them; It is the number numbred (which is the thing it ſelfe miſ-related into that ſacred Order) that we ſticke at. There we find that none but Chriſt can make a Sacrament; for none but he who can giue grace, can ordaine a ſigne and ſeale of Grace; Now it is euident enough, that theſe adſcititious Sacraments were neuer of Chriſts inſtitution. So was not confirmation, as our Alexander of Hales, and Holcot; ſo was not Matrimony,Suar. Tom. 4. diſp. 
                        
                           •
                        9. ſ. 2. Vid Mort. Ap
                     
                        •
                     ell. l. 2. c. 26. §. 5.
                   as Durand; So was not Extreme Vnction, as Hugo, Lombard, Bonauenture, Halenſis, Altiſiodore, by the confeſſion of their Suarez. Theſe were ancient rites, but

they are new Sacraments; All of them haue their allowed, and profitable vſe in Gods Church, though not in ſo high a nature; Except that of Extreme Vnction; which as it is an apiſh miſ-imitation of that extraordinarie courſe,Marc. 6.13. Iames 5. which the Apoſtolike times vſed in their cures of the ſicke, ſo it is groſſely miſ-applyed to other purpoſes, then were intended in the firſt inſtitution. Then it was (Vngebant &amp; ſanabant;) the oyle miraculouſly conferring bodily recouerie; but now, (Non niſi in mortis articulo adhibetur) it is not vſed, but vpon the verie point of death, as Caietan and Caſſander confeſſe, and all experience manifeſts;Franc. Iun. Animadu. in Bellar. l. de verb. Dei. 4.
                   and by Felix the fourth, drawne to a neceſſitie of addreſſe to eternall life.
               
                  
                  SECT. II. Seuen Sacraments beſide Scripture.
                  NOt to ſcan particulars, which all yeeld ample exceptions, but to wind them all vp in one bottome; Whoſoeuer ſhall looke into the Scripture ſhall finde it apparent, that as in the time of mans innocence, there were but two Sacraments, the tree of life, and the tree of knowledge; So, before, and vnder the Law (how euer they had infinite rites) yet in the proper ſenſe, they had but two Sacraments; the ſame in effect with thoſe vnder the Goſpel; The one, the Sacrament of Initiation, which was their Circumciſion; Paralleld by that Baptiſme which ſucceeded it; The other, the Sacrament of our holy Confirmation, that ſpirituall meat and drinke which was their Paſchall Lambe and Manna, and water from the

rocke; prefiguring the true Lambe of God, and bread of life, and bloud of our redemption. The great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, that well knew the Analogie, hath compared both; Moreouer, brethren,
                     1. Cor. 10.1. 
                     I would not haue you ignorant, how that all our fathers were vnder the cloud, and all paſſed thorow the ſea;
                     Verſe 2, 3. 
                     And all were baptized in the cloud, and in the ſea; And all did eat the ſame ſpirituall meat,
                     Verſe 4. &amp;c. 
                     and all did drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke, for they dranke of that ſpirituall Rocke, that followed them, and that Rocke was Chriſt. What is this in any iuſt conſtruction, but that the ſame two Sacraments of Baptiſme and the Lords Supper, which wee celebrate vnder the Goſpell, were the verie ſame with thoſe, which were celebrated by Gods ancient people, vnder the Law; They two, and no more; Hoc facite (Doe this) is our warrant for the one; and Ite baptizate, &amp;c. and Go teach and baptize, for the other: There is deepe ſilence in the reſt.
               
               
                  
                  SECT. III. Againſt reaſon.
                  IN reaſon it muſt bee yeelded, that no man hath power to ſet to a ſeale, but he whoſe the writing is; Sacraments, then, being the ſeales of Gods gracious euidences, whereby hee hath conueyed to vs eternall life, can bee inſtituted by no other, then the ſame power that can aſſure and performe life to his creature. In euerie Sacrament therefore muſt bee a diuine inſtitution and command of an element that ſignifies, of a grace that is ſignified, of a word adioyned to that element, of an holy act adioyned to that Word: Where theſe concurre not, there can bee no true Sacrament; and they are palpably miſſing in theſe fiue Adiections of the Church of Rome.
                  Laſtly; The Sacraments of the new Law (as Saint Auſten often)

flowed out of the ſide of Chriſt; None flowed thence, but the Sacrament of water, which is Baptiſme, and the Sacrament of bloud in the Supper; Whereof the Author ſaith, This cup is the new Teſtament in my bloud, which is ſhed for you. The reſt neuer flowing either from the ſide, or from the lips of Chriſt, are as new and miſ-named Sacraments iuſtly reiected by vs, and we thereupon as vniuſtly cenſured.
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. XVI. The newneſſe of the Doctrine of Traditions.
               
                  THe chiefe ground of theſe, and all other errours in the Church of Rome,Concil. Trid. Seſſ. 4.
                   is the ouer-valuing of Traditions; which the Tridentine Synode profeſſeth to receiue, and reuerence with no leſſe pious affection,In his rebus de quibus nihil certi flatuit ſcriptura diuina, mos populi Dei vel inſtituta maiorum pro lege tenenda ſunt. Auguſt. Epiſt. 86.
                   then the Bookes of the Old, and New Teſtament; and that, not in matter of Rite, and Hiſtorie only, but of faith and manners alſo; Wherein, as they are not vn willing to caſt a kind of imputation of imperfection vpon the written Word; ſo they make vp the defects of it, by the ſupply of vnwritten Traditions; to which indeed they are more beholden, for the warrant of the greater part of their ſuper-added Articles, then to the Scriptures of God:
               
                  Both which, are points ſo dangerouſly enuious, as that Antiquitie would haue abhorred their mention: Neither is any thing more common with the holy Fathers of the Church, then the magnifying the complete perfection of Scripture, in all things needfull, either to be beleeued, or done.
               What can be more ful and cleere,Aug. l. 2. de doctrina Chriſt. c. 9 In his quae apertè poſita ſunt in Scriptura inueniuntur illa omnia quae continent fidem moreſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      viueundi. Bell. l. 4. de verb. Dei. 6.11.
                   then that of Saint Auſten, In his quae apertè, &amp;c. In theſe things, which are openly laid forth in Scripture, are found all matters that containe either faith, or manners.
               Cardinall Bellarmines eluſion is not a little preiudiciall to his owne cauſe. He tels vs, that Saint Austen ſpeakes of thoſe points, which are ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation for all men; All which hee acknowledges to be written by the Apoſtles; But beſides theſe, there are many other things (ſaith hee) which wee haue only by Tradition; Will it not therfore hence follow, that the common ſort of Chriſtians need not looke

at his Traditions? That commonly men may be ſaued without them? that Heauen may bee attained, though there were no Traditions; Who will not now ſay, Let mee come to Heauen by Scripture, goe you whither you will by Traditions? To which adde, that a great, yea, the greater part (if wee may beleeue ſome of their owne) of that which they call religion, is grounded vpon only Tradition; if then Tradition bee only of ſuch things as are not ſimply unneceſſary to ſaluation, then the greater part of their miſ-named Religion, muſt needs be yielded for ſimply vnneceſſary to all men: And if wee may bee ſaued without them, and bee made Citizens of Heauen, how much more may we without them, be members of the true Church on Earth? As for this place, Saint Auguſtines words are full, and comprehenſiue, expreſſing all thoſe things, which containe either faith, or manners, whether concerning Gouernours,

or people: If now, they can finde out any thing, that belongs not either to beleefe, or action, wee doe willingly giue it vp to their Traditions, but all things which pertaine to either of thoſe, are openly comprized in Scripture.
               What can bee more direct, then that of holy Athanaſius?
                  Athanaſ. l. 4. cont. Gent. Initio 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , &amp;c. Sufficiunt per ſe vertit Nannius. Tert. lib. aduerſ. Hermogenem. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c. The holy Scriptures inſpired by God, are in themſelues all-ſufficient to the inſtruction of truth; and, if Chemnitius conſtrue it, All truth, this needs not raiſe a cauill; The word ſignifies no leſſe; for if they bee all-ſufficient to inſtruction, they muſt needs be ſufficient to all inſtruction in the truth intended; Tertullian profeſſes openly, Adoro Scripturae pleni
                        •
                     udinem, &amp;c. I adore the fulneſſe of Scripture; Let the skill of Hermogenes ſhow where it is written; if it bee not written, let him feare that woe which is pronounced againſt thoſe, that adde or detract. Thus he. Who can but feare that the

Cardinall ſhifts this euidence againſt his owne heart? For (ſaith he) Tertullian ſpeakes of that one point. That God created all things of nothing, and not of a pre-exiſtent matter, as Hermogenes dreamed; now, becauſe this truth is clearely expreſſed in Scripture, therefore the fulneſſe of Scripture, as concerning this point is adored by Tertullian; And for that Hermogenes held an opinion contrarie to Scripture, he is ſaid to adde vnto Scripture, and to incurre that malediction; Now, let any reader, of common ſenſe, iudge, whether the words of Tertullian be not generall; without any limitation; and if the firſt clauſe could bee reſtrained, the ſecond cannot; Scriptum eſſe doceat &amp;c. Whatſoeuer therefore is not written, by this rule may not be oberuded to our beleefe; Neither doth he ſay, If it be written againſt; but, If it be not written; and his challenge is (nuſquam legi) that the words are no where read, as if this were quarrell enough,

without a flat contradiction to what is read.
               So as the Cardinals gloſſe meerely corrupts the Text; How eaſie were it for me to tire my reader, with the full ſuffrages of Origen, Cyprian, Chryſoſtome, Baſil, Cyrill, Epiphanius, Hierome, Ambroſe, Theodoret, Hilarie, Vincentius Lirinenſis, and in a word with the whole ſtreame of Antiquitie, which though they giue a meet place to Traditions of Ceremony, of hiſtorie, of interpretation, of ſome immateriall verities, yet reſerue the due honour to the ſacred monuments of Diuine Scriptures. Our learned Chemnitius hath freely yeelded ſeuen ſorts of Traditions, ſuch as haue a correſpondence with, or an atteſtation from the written word, the reſt, we do iuſtly (together with him) diſclaime, as vnworthy to appeare vpon that awfull Bench, amongſt the inſpired Pen-men of God.
               
                  
                  SECT. II. Traditions againſt Scripture.
                  IT is not to be imagined that the ſame word of God, which ſpeakes for all other truths, ſhould not ſpeake for it ſelfe; how fully doth it diſplay it's owne ſufficiencie and perfection.2. Tim, 3.16. All Scripture (ſaith the Choſen Veſſell) is giuen by inſpiration of God; and is profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe. Profitable,Bellar. de verbo Dei, l. 4. c. 10.
                      ſaith the Cardinall, but not ſufficient; Many things may auaile to that end whereto they ſuffice not; So meat is profitable to nouriſh, but without naturall heat it nouriſheth not: Thus hee. Heare yet what followeth.2. Tim. 3.17. That the man of God may bee perfited, and thorowly furniſhed vnto all good workes. Loe it is ſo profitable to all theſe ſeruices, that thereby it perfects a Diuine; much more an ordiarie

Chriſtian: That which is ſo profitable, as to cauſe perfection, is abundantly ſufficient, and muſt needs haue full perfection in it ſelfe; That which can perfit the teacher, is ſufficient for the learner. The Scriptures can perfit the man of God, both for his calling in the inſtruction of others, and for his owne glorie.2. Tim. 3.15. 
                     Thou haſt knowne the Scriptures from a childe (ſaith Saint Paul to his Timothy) which are able (not profitable only) to make thee wiſe vnto ſaluation, through faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus. It is the charge therefore of the Apoſtle, not to bee wiſe aboue that which is written: The ſame with wiſe Salonons, The whole word of God is pure: Adde thou not vnto his words,
                     Prou. 30.5, 6. 
                     lest he reproue thee, and thou be found a lier. Loe, hee ſaith not, Oppoſe not his words, but, Adde not to them: Euen addition detracts from the maieſtie of that Word; For the Law of the Lord is perfect,Pſal. 19.7, 8. conuerting the ſoule, the teſtimonie of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple.

The ſtatutes of the Lord are right, reioycing the heart, the Commandement of the Lord is pure, enlightning the eyes.
                  As for thoſe Traditions which they doe thus lift vp to an vniuſt competition with the written Word, our Sauiour hath before hand, humbled them into the duſt: In vaine doe they worſhip me,
                     Matth. 15.9. 
                     teaching for doctrines the commandements of men; Making this a ſufficient cauſe of abhorring both the perſons, and the ſeruices of thoſe Iewes, that they thruſt humane Traditions into Gods chaire, and reſpected them equally with the inſtitutions of God. Cardinall Bellarmine would ſhift it off with a diſtinction of Traditions; Theſe were ſuch, ſaith hee (quas acceperant à recentioribus, &amp;c.) as they had receiued from ſome later hands, whereof ſome were vaine, ſome others pernicious, not ſuch as they receiued from Moſes and the Prophets: And the Authors of theſe reiected Traditions hee cites

from Epiphanius to be R. Akiba, R.
                     Epiphan. in haereſ. Ptolom. Hieron. in c. 8. Iſa. Et in Epiſt. ad Algaſ. q. 10.
                      
                     Iuda, and the Aſamoneans; from Hierome, to bee Sammai, Hillel, Akiba. But this is to caſt miſts before the eyes of the ſimple: For who ſees not that our Sauiours challenge is generall, to Traditions thus aduanced, not to theſe, or thoſe Traditions: And, where he ſpeakes of ſome later hands, he had forgotten, that our Sauiour vpon the mount tells him (
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     ) That theſe faulted Traditions were of old.Matth. 5.21, 27, 33. And that he may not caſt theſe vpon his Sammai and Hiliel, let him remember that our Sauiour cites this out of Eſay (though with ſome more cleerneſſe of expreſſion) who farre ouerlooked the times of thoſe pretended Fathers of miſ-traditions. That I may not ſay, how much it would trouble him to ſhew any dogmaticall Traditions, that were deriued from Moſes and the Prophets; in parallel whereof, let them be able to deduce any Euangelicall Tradition from the Apoſtles, and we are ready

to imbrace it with all obſeruance. Shortly, it is cleere that our Sauiour neuer meant to compare one Tradition with another, as approuing ſome, reiecting others, but with indignation complaines, that Traditions were obtruded to Gods people, in a corriualitie with the written word; which is the verie point now queſtioned.
               
               
                  SECT. III. Traditions against reaſon.
                  EVen the verie light of reaſon ſhowes vs that as there is a God, ſo, that he is a moſt wiſe, &amp; moſt iuſt God; needs therefore muſt it follow, that if this moſt iuſt and wiſe God will giue a Word whereby to reueale himſelfe and his wil to mankinde, it muſt bee a perfect Word; for, as his wiſdome knowes what is

fit for his creature to know of himſelfe, ſo his iuſtice will require nothing of the creature, but what hee hath enabled him to know and doe; Now then, ſince hee requires vs to know him, to obey him, it muſt needs follow that hee hath left vs ſo exquiſite a rule of this knowledge and obedience, as cannot admit of any defect, or any ſupplement. This rule can bee no other then his written Word; therefore written, that it might be preſerued entire, for this purpoſe, to the laſt date of time: As for orall Traditions, what certaintie can there be in them? What foundation of truth can be layd vpon the breath of man? How doe wee ſee the reports varie, of thoſe things, which our eyes haue ſeene done? How doe they multiply in their paſſage, and either grow, or dye vpon hazards?
                  Laſtly, we thinke him not an honeſt man, whoſe tongue goes againſt his owne hand; How hainous an imputation then doe they caſt vpon

the God of truth; which plead Traditions deriued from him, contrarie to his written Word? Such, apparently, are the worſhip of Images, the mutilation of the Sacrament, Purgatorie, Indulgences, and the reſt which haue paſſed our agitation. Since therefore the authoritie of Romiſh Traditions is (beſides noueltie) erroneous; againſt Scripture and reaſon, we haue iuſtly abandoned it, and are thereupon vniuſtly condemned.
                  As for thoſe other dangerous and important innouations, concerning Scriptures, their Canon inlarged, their faultie verſion made authenticall, their fountaines pretended to be corrupted, their miſ-pleaded obſcuritie,Serious Diſſwaſiue, &amp;c. their reſtraint from the Laitie, we haue already largely diſplaid them in another place.
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. XVII. The newneſſe of the vniuerſall Head-ſhip of the Biſhop of Rome.
               
                  THoſe tranſcendent Titles of Head-ſhip, and Vniuerſalitie, which are challenged to the Biſhop,Haereſeos mater eſt principatus cupiditas, Chryſoſt. in Gal. 5.
                   and Sea of Rome, are knowne to bee the vpſtart brood of noted ambition. Simple and holy Antiquitie was too modeſt, either to require, or tolerate them. Who knowes not the profeſſion of that holy Martyr in the Councell of Carthage; (Neque enim, &amp;c.) There is none of vs,Neque enim quiſquam noſtrum Epiſcopum Epiſcoporum ſe conſtituit, aut tyrannico terrore ad obſequendi neceſſitatem ſuos, adigit. Orat. Cypr. in Syn. Greg. Epiſt. l. 4. Epiſt. 32. &amp; 34.
                   that makes himſelfe a Biſhop of Biſhops; or by a tyrannous feare compels his Vnderlings to a neceſſitie of obedience; But perhaps, at Rome it was otherwiſe; Heare then with what zeale their owne Pope Gregorie the Great, inueighs againſt the arrogance of Iohn Biſhop

of Conſtantinople, for giuing way to this proud ſtile; His Epiſtles are extant in all hands; ſo cleare and conuictiue,Et lib. 6. Ep. 24.
                   as no art of Sophiſtrie can elude them; wherein hee calls this title (affected by the ſaid Iohn, and Cyriacus, after him,) a new name, a wicked, profane, inſolent name,Nouum, ſceleſtum, profanum, &amp;c. Et lib. 4. Epiſt. 38.39. &amp;c. the generall plague of the Church, a corruption of the Faith, againſt Canons, againſt the Apoſtle Peter, againſt God himſelfe; as if he could neuer haue branded it enough.
               And leaſt any man ſhould cauill that this ſtile is only cryed downe in the Biſhops of Conſtantinople, which yet might bee iuſtly claymed by the Biſhops of Rome; Gregorie himſelfe meetes with this thought, and anſwers beforehand;Nunquam pium virum huiuſmodi titulis vſum eſſe, &amp;c. nullum praedeceſſorum meorum, &amp;c. 
                  Nunquam pium virum, &amp;c. that neuer any godly man, neuer any of his Predeceſſors vſed thoſe Titles; and, more then ſo, that whoſoeuer ſhall vſe this proud ſtile, hee is the very fore-runner of Antichriſt. If in a

fore-ſight of this vſurpation, Gregorie ſhould haue beene hired to haue ſpoken for vs, againſt the Pride of his following Succeſſours; he could not haue ſet a keener edge vpon his ſtile. Conſonant whereto, it is yet extant in the very Canon Law (as quoted by Gratian out of the Epiſtle of Pope Pelagius the ſecond) Vniuerſalis autem nec etiam Romanus Pontifex appelletur;Pelag. 2. omnibus Epiſcopis illicite à Ioanne &amp; Decret. p. 1. diſt. 99. c. 4. Nullus, &amp;c. Not the Biſhop of Rome himſelfe may bee called Vniuerſall;
               Yet how famouſly is it knowne to all the World, that the ſame Gregories next Succeſſour, ſaue one, Boniface the third, obtained this title of vniuerſall Biſhop from the Emperour Phocas; which the ſaid Emperour gaue him in a ſpleene againſt Cyriacus Patriarch of Conſtantinople,Baron. An. 606.
                   for deliuering Conſtantina the Wife of Mauritius and her Children; or (as ſome others relate it) vpon a worſe occaſion: And accordingly, was this haughty title communicated by the ſame

power to the See of Rome, and by ſtrong hand euer ſince maintained.
               This qualification their Regiſter Platina confeſſes,Plat. in vita Bonif. 3.
                   was procured not without great contention. And Otho Friſingenſis fully and ingenuouſly writeth thus.Gregorius migra
                        •
                     it ad dominum, &amp;c. A quo, &amp;c. vt ipſius authoritate, &amp;c. Otho Friſing. l. 5. c. 8.
                   
                  Gregorie departed hence to the Lord; After whom (the next ſaue one) Boniface obtained of Phocas, that by his authoritie the Romane Church might bee called the head of all Churches; For at that time the See of Conſtantinople (I ſuppoſe, becauſe of the ſeat of the Empire tranſlated thither) wrote her ſelfe the firſt. Thus their Biſhop Otho: Now if any man ſhall think that hence it will yet follow, that the See of Rome had formerly enioyed this honour, how euer the Conſtantinopolitan for the preſent, ſhouldred with her for it; Let him know the ground of both their challenges, which (as it was ſuppoſed by Otho) So, is fully (for the ſatisfaction of any indifferent iudgement) layd forth in the Generall

Councell of Chalcedon.Concil. 5. Gener. Act. 15.
                   The ſame (ſay thoſe Fathers) we determine of the priuiledges of the moſt holy Church of Conſtantinople, called New Rome: For the Fathers haue iuſtly heretofore giuen priuiledge to the Throne of old Rome, becauſe that Citie was then the Gouerneſſe of the world; and vpon the ſame conſideration were the hundred and fiftie Biſhops (men beloued of God) moued to yeeld equall priuiledges to the Throne of new Rome, rightly iudging, that this Citie, which is honoured with the Empire, and Senate, and is equally priuiledged with old Rome the then Queene of the world, ſhould alſo in Eccleſiaſticall matters bee no leſſe extolled and magnified. Thus they. And this act is ſubſcribed, Bonifacius Presbyter Eccleſiae Romanae ſtatui &amp; ſubſcripſi. I Boniface Presbyter of the Church of Rome haue ſo determined and ſubſcribed; (Et caeteri &amp;c.) And the reſt of the Biſhops of diuers Prouinces and Cities ſubſcribed. What

can be more plaine? This headſhip of the Biſhop was in regard of the See; and this headſhip of the See was in regard of the preeminence of the Citie; which was variable, according to the changes of times, or choyce of Emperours. But Binius wrangleth here; Can we blame him when the free-hold of their Great Miſtreſſe is ſo neerely touched? This act (ſaith he) was not Synodicall,Seuer. Bin. in notis Concil. Chalced. as that which was cloſely and cunningly done, in the abſence of the Popes Legates, and other Orthodox Biſhops, at the inſtance of Anatolius, Patriarch of Conſtantinople, an ambitious man, by the Eaſterne Biſhops only. How can this plea ſtand with his owne confeſſed ſubſcription? Beſides that their Caranza in his Abridgement,Caranz. Epitom. Concil. ſhowes, that this point was long and vehemently canuaſſed in that Councell, betweene Lucentius and Boniface, Legates of the Romane Church, and the reſt of the Biſhops; and at laſt, ſo concluded, as we haue

related;Sedes Apoſtolica Nobis praeſentibus humiliari non debet. Ibid. not indeed without the proteſtation of the ſayd Legates, Nobis praeſentibus &amp;e. The Apoſtolike See muſt not in our preſence be abaſed: Notwithſtanding, this act then carried; and, after this, Pope Simplicius ſucceeding to Hilarius made a decree to the ſame purpoſe,Conſtantinopolitano, Epiſcopo damnato Eccleſia
                        •
                     um omnium primam eſſe Romanam, Caranz. Epit. not without alluſion to this contention for precedencie, that Rome ſhould take place of Conſtantinople: Yea, ſo vtterly vnthought of was this abſolute Primacie and headſhip of old; as that when the Roman Dition was brought downe to a Dukedome, and ſubiected to the Exarchate of Rauenna, the Arch-Biſhop of Rauenna, vpon the verie ſame grounds, ſtucke not (as Blondus tells vs) to ſtriue with the Biſhop of Rome for prioritie of place. So neceſſarily was the riſing or fall of the Epiſcopall Chaire annexed to the condition of that Citie, wherein it was fixed.
               But in all this, we well ſee, what it is that was ſtood vpon; an arbitrable

precedencie of theſe Churches, in a prioritie of order; and according thereunto, the Biſhop of Rome is determined to be primae ſedis Epiſcopus,
                  Concil. Carthag. 3. Can. 20. De
                        •
                     r. p. 1. d. 99. 
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      pri
                     
                        •••
                     eg
                        •
                     um conceſſum à Iuſtiniano. S
                        •
                     ncimus ſenior
                        •
                      Rome Papam primum eſſe omnium ſacerdo
                        ••
                     m. Praerog. ante alios refidendi. Cod. de ſacr
                        •
                     ſ. Eccl. decernimi
                        •
                     s. the Biſhop of the firſt See. A ſtyle, which our late learned Soueraigne profeſſed with Iustinian not to grudge vnto the moderne Biſhops of that See; But as for a Primacie of Soueraignty ouer all Churches, and ſuch an Headſhip, as ſhould enforme, and enliue the body, and gouerne it with Inf
                        •
                     uentia vitae. Capiſtran. Inf
                        •
                     uentia regiminis. Auguſt. Triumph. infallible influences, it is ſo new, and hatefull, as that the Church in all ages hath oppoſed it to the vtmoſt; neither will it bee endured at this day by the Greeke Church, notwithſtanding the colourable pretence of ſubſcription hereunto, by their dying Patriarch Ioſeph of Conſtantinople,Bin. in Concil. Florent. in the late Florentine Councell, and the letters of vnion ſubſcribed by them, Anno 1539.
               Yea, ſo farre is it from that, as that their Emperour Michael Paleologus, for yeelding a kinde of ſubiection

of the Eaſterne Biſhops to the Roman, would not bee allowed the honour of Chriſtian buriall, as Aemilius hath recorded.P. Emyl. hiſt. Gall. And in our time Baſilius the Emperour of Ruſſia (which challengeth no ſmall part in the Greeke Church) threatned to the Popes Legate (as I haue beene informed) an infamous death, and buriall, if hee offered to ſet foot in his Dominions, out of a iealous hate of this vſurpation.
               
                  SECT. II. The newneſſe of challenged Infallibilitie.
                  THe particularities of this new arrogation of Rome are ſo many, that they cannot be pent vp in any ſtrait roome. I will only inſtance in ſome few.
                  The Popes infallibilitie of Iudgement

is ſuch a paradoxe, as the very Hiſtories of all times, and proceedings of the Church doth ſufficiently conuince. For, to what purpoſe had all Councels beene called; euen of the remoteſt Biſhops, to what purpoſe were the agitations of all controuerſall cauſes in thoſe Aſſemblies (as Eraſmus iuſtly obſerues) if this opinion had then obtained? Or how came it about that the ſentences of ſome Biſhops of Rome were oppoſed by other Sees; by the Succeſſours of their owne, by Chriſtian Academies, if this conceit had formerly paſſed for currant with the World; How came it to paſſe, that whole Councels haue cenſured, and condemned ſome Biſhops of Rome for manifeſt Hereſies, if they were perſwaded, before hand, of the impoſſibilitie of thoſe errours: Not to ſpeake of Honorius,
                     Multi Pontifices in errores &amp; haereſes lapſi eſſe leguntur Concil. Baſil. in Ep. Synod.
of Liberius
                     ▪ and others; the Councell of Baſil ſhall be the voyce of common obſeruation; Multi Pontifices, &amp;c. Many Popes (ſay

they) are recorded to haue falne into errours and hereſies: Either all ſtories mocke vs, or elſe this paraſiticall dreame of impeccancie in iudgement, is a meere ſtranger: and his diſguiſe is ſo foule,Auentin. l. 7.
                      that it is no maruell if (Errare non poſſum) (I cannot erre) ſeemed to Eberhardus, Biſhop of Saltzburgh, no other then the ſuit of an Antichriſt.
               
               
                  SECT. III. The newneſſe of the Popes Superioritie to Generall Councells.
                  HOw bold and dangerous a noueltie is that which Cardinall Bellarmine, and with him the whole Societie, and all the late Fautors of that See (after the Florentine Synode) ſticke not to auouch,Bell. l. 2. de Concil. c. 17.
                      
                     Summus Pontifex, &amp;c. The Pope is abſolutely

aboue the whole Church, and aboue a Generall Councell, ſo as hee acknowledges no Iudge on earth ouer himſelfe: How would this haue reliſhed with thoſe (well neere) a thouſand Fathers in the Councell of Conſtance,Concil. Conſt. Seſſ. 4. &amp; 5. Caranz. Anno 1415.
                      who punctually determined thus. Ipſa Synodus, &amp;c. This Synode lawfully aſſembled in the Holy Ghoſt, making a Generall Councell, repreſenting the Catholike Church militant vpon earth, hath immediately power from Chriſt; whereunto euery man, whoſoeuer he be, of what ſtate, or dignitie ſo euer, although he be the Pope himſelfe, is bound to obey, in thoſe things, which pertaine to faith, or to the extirpation of ſchiſme. And fifteene yeeres after that,
                        Anno 1431. the Generall Councell of Baſil, wherein was Preſident Iulianus Cardinal of Saint Angelo, the Popes Legate, defined the ſame matter, in the ſame words. It is no maruell if Cardinall Bellarmine, and ſome others of that ſtrain, reiect theſe, as vnlawfull Councels;

but they cannot deny, firſt, that this decree was made by both of them; Secondly, that the Diuines there aſſembled, were (in their allowance) Catholique Doctors; and ſuch as in other points adhered to the Roman Church; in ſo much as they were the men by whoſe ſentence Iohn Huſſe, and Hierome ſuffered no leſſe then death; and yet euen ſo lately did theſe numerous Diuines in the voyce of the Church, define the ſuperioritie of a Councell aboue the Pope; What ſpeake we of this, when wee finde that the Biſhops of the Eaſt excommunicated in their aſſembly,Sozom. l. 3. c. 11.
                      
                     Iulius the Biſhop of Rome himſelfe, amongſt others, without ſcruple, as Sozomen reporteth.
                  How ill would this doctrine or practice now bee endured? In ſo much as Gregorie of Valence dare confidently ſay, that whoſoeuer he be that makes a Councel ſuperior to the Pope, fights directly (though vnawares) againſt that moſt certaine point of faith concerning

Saint Peters, and the Romane Biſhops primacie in the Church.
               
               
                  SECT. IV. The new preſumption of Papall Diſpenſations.
                  FRom the opinion of this ſupereminent power hath flowed that common courſe of Diſpenſations with the Canons and decrees of Councells, which hath beene of late a great eye-ſore to moderate beholders.Fr. Ʋictor. Rele
                           •
                        t. de poteſt. Papae &amp; Concil. pag. 151.
                      
                     Franciſcus à Victoria makes a wofull complaint of it, profeſſing to doubt whether in the end of the the yeere, there bee more that haue leaue by this meanes to breake the lawes, then thoſe that are tied to keepe them. Thereupon wiſhing (for remedy) that there were a reſtraint made of thoſe now-boundleſſe Diſpenſations; and at laſt, obiecting

to himſelfe that ſuch a decree of reſtriction would bee new, and not heard of in any former Councell, hee anſwers; (Tempore Conciliorum antiquorum, &amp;c.) In the time of the ancient Councels, Popes were like to the other fathers of thoſe Councells, ſo as there was no need of any act for holding them backe from this immoderate licence of diſpenſing; yea, if wee doe well turne ouer the lawes, and hiſtories of the Ancient, wee ſhall find that Popes did not preſume ſo eaſily, and commonly, to diſpenſe with decrees of Councels, but obſerued them as the Oracles of God himſelfe: Yea, not onely did they forbeare to doe it ordinarily, but perhaps not once did they euer diſpenſe at all, againſt the Decrees of Councels; But now (ſaith he) by little, and little, are we growne to this intemperance of diſpenſations, and to ſuch an eſtate as that wee can neither abide our miſchiefes, nor our remedies. Thus that learned Spanyard, in an honeſt confeſſion 

of the degenerate courſes of the late Popes from the ſimple integritie of their Predeceſſours.
                  
                     Pontificalis authoritas à iuramento fid. 
                           •
                        at
                           •
                        s abſoluit. decr p. 2 15. q. 6. 
                        
                           •
                        liùs. Almain de poteſt. Eccleſ. &amp; 
                           •
                        aica c. 12. 
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         was the rule of old.What ſhould I adde vnto theſe the preſumptuous Diſpenſations with Vowes, and Oathes, with the Lawes of God himſelfe, with the Law of Nature; A priuiledge ordinarily both yeelded, and defended by flattering Canoniſts; and that which meets with vs, at euerie turne, in Hoſtienſis, Archidiaconus, Felinus, Capiſtranus, Triumphus, Angelus de Clauaſio, Petrus de Ancorano, Panormitan,
                     Diatrib. Papa Antichriſt. l. 4. cap. 9.
                      as is largely particularized by our learned Biſhop of Dery.
               
               
                  
                  SECT. V. The new challenge of Popes dominering ouer Kings and Emperours.
                  I May well ſhut vp this Scene, with that notorious innouation of the Popes ſubducing himſelfe from the due obedience of his once-acknowledged Lord, and Soueraigne, and endeuouring to reduce all thoſe Imperiall powers, to his homage, and obedience.
                  The time was,Greg. lib. 4. Ep. 32. &amp; ſereniſſimis iuſſionibus obedientiam praebeo. Ibid. when Pope Gregorie could ſay to Mauritius, Vobis obedientiam praebere deſidero; I deſire to giue you due obedience: And when Pope Leo came with cap and knee, to Theodoſius, for a Synod to be called, with Clementia veſtra concedat, as Cardinall Cuſanus cites it, from the hiſtorie; The time was, when (Nemo Apoſtolicae &amp;c.) No man did offer to take vpon him the ſteering of the Apoſtolike Barke, till

the authoritie of the Emperour had deſigned him,Hieron. Balb. de Cor. as their Balbus out of their owne Law. That of Pope Gregorie is plaine enough, Ecce ſereniſſimus,
                     Ecce ſereniſſimus dominus Imperator fieri ſimiam le
                           ••
                        em iuſſit, &amp;c. Greg. Epiſt. 5.
                      
                     &amp;c. Behold (ſaith he, ſpeaking of his owne aduancement to the Biſhopricke of Rome) our gracious Lord the Emperour hath commanded an Ape to be made a Lion; and ſurely at his command it may be called a Lion,Qui virtutis miniſterium infirmo commiſit, ibid. G
                           •
                        i
                           •
                        ciard. l. 4. Hiſt. Imperante Carolo domino noſtro. but it cannot be one; ſo as hee muſt needs lay all my faults and negligences, not vpon mee, but vpon his owne pietie, which hath committed this Miniſterie of power to ſo weake an Agent.
                  The time was when the Popes of Rome dated their Apoſtolique letters with the ſtyle of the raigne of their Lords,Paſchalis Anno Euangelij 1070. primus omiſſis Imperatoris annis ſui pontifica
                           •
                        us annos ſubſcripſit. In data. Apoſtolatus noſtri, Anno 1. Dein Pontificatus. Lib. Sacr. Cerem. the Emperours; now, euer ſince Pope Paſchal, they care onely to note the yeere of their owne Apoſtleſhip, or Papacie.
                  The time was, when the holy Biſhops of that See profeſſed to ſucceed Saint Peter in homely ſimplicitie, in humble obedience, in pietie, in

zeale, in preaching, in teares, in ſufferings; now ſince, the caſe is altered; the world ſees, and bluſhes at the change; for now (Quanta inter ſolem &amp; lunam, &amp;c.
                     Greg. l. 1. de maior. &amp; obed. ex Innoc.) Looke how much the Sunne is bigger then the Moone; ſo much is the Papall power greater then the Imperiall; Now, Papa eſt Dominus Imperatoris;
                        Capiſ
                              •
                           r. 77. The Pope is the Emperours Lord (ſaith their Capiſtranus) and the Emperour is ſubiect to the Pope as his miniſter or ſeruant, ſaith Triumphus,
                     Aug. Triumph. q. 44.1. 
                        Ʋide diatr. Derenſ. Epiſc. l. 4. c. 3. §. 2. Vnde habet Imperator Imperium niſi à n
                           •
                        bis: Imperator quod habet totum habet à nobis, ecce in poteſtate noſtra eſt vt demus illud cui volumus. Hadrian. Epiſt. apud Auentin. l. 6 Innoc. 4. in cap. licet. de foro compet. and leſt this ſhold ſeem the faſhionable word of ſome clawing Canoniſt only, heare what Pope Adrian himſelfe ſaith, Vnde habet, &amp;c. Whence hath the Emperour his Empire, but from vs? all that hee hath, hee hath wholly from vs, Behold it is in our power to giue it, to whom we liſt.
                  And to the ſame purpoſe is that of Pope Innocent the fourth, Imperator est aduocatus, &amp;c. The Emperour is the Popes Aduocate, and ſweares to him, and holds his Empire of him.
                  
                     But perhaps this place is yet too high for an Emperour; a lower will ſerue;Lib. ſacr. Cerem. 
                     Fit Canonicus, &amp;c. The Emperour is (of courſe) made a Canon, and brother of the Church of Lateran.
                  
                     Etiam Imperator aut rex aquam ad la
                           •
                        andas eius manus ferre debet; primum item ſerculum, &amp;c. ibid. In proceſſionibus, &amp;c. ibid. Stapham equi papalis tenet, &amp;c. ibid. Sellami
                           •
                        ſam eum Pontifice humeris ſuis aliquantulum portare debet, Ibid.Yet lower; He ſhall be the Sewer of his Holineſſes Table, and ſet on the firſt diſh, and hold the Baſin for his hands.
                  Yet lower, he ſhall be the Trainbearer to the Pope in his Walking Proceſſions. He ſhall be the Quirie of his Stable, and hold his ſtirrope in getting vp on his Horſe: He ſhalbe, laſtly, his very Porter to carrie his Holineſſe on his ſhoulder. And all this, not out of will, but out of dutie.
                  
                     Alm. de poteſt. Eccl.Where now is Augustus ab Augendo, as Almain deriues him, when he ſuffers himſelfe thus diminiſhed. Although there is more wonder in the others exaltation; Papae!
                     Caſſan. 4. parte. Conſid. 7. C. de libellis 10. diſt. Men are too baſe to enter into compariſon with him, His authoritie is more then of the Saints

in Heauen, ſaith one, yet more,Aug. Triumph. de pot. Ecc. q. 18 Vid. Derenſ. vbi ſupra. Caſſan. Glor. mundi 4. part. Conſ. 7. Innocent. &amp; Hoſt. in c. 4. de Tranſt. hee excelleth the Angels in his Iuriſdiction; ſaith another, yet, more once. The Pope ſeemes to make one and the ſame Conſiſtory with God himſelfe; and, which comprehends all the reſt, Tues omnia, &amp; ſuper omnia; Thou art all, and aboue all, as the Councell of Lateran vnder Iulius.
                  
                  Oh ſtrange alteration, that the great Commanders of the World ſhould be made the drudges of their Subiects, that Order and Soueraigntie ſhould leeſe themſelues in a pretence of Pietie! That the profeſſed Succeſſor of him that ſaid, Gold and ſiluer haue I none, ſhould thus trample vpon Crownes; That a poore ſilly Worme of the Earth ſhould rayſe vp it ſelfe aboue all that is called God, and offer to crawle into the glorious Throne of Heauen.
               
            
            
               
               CHAP. XVIII. The Epilogue both of Exhortation and Apologie.
               
                  NOt to wearie my Reader with more particularities of Innouation; Let now all Chriſtians know, and be aſſured, that ſuch change as they ſenſibly find in the head, they may as truly (though not ſo viſibly) note in the bodie of the Roman Church, yea rather in that ſoule of Religion, which informeth both: And if thereupon, all our endeuour (as we proteſt before God, and his holy Angels) hath beene, and is, only, to reduce Rome to it ſelfe; that is, to recall it to that originall Truth, Pietie, Synceritie, which made it long famous through the World, and happy, how vniuſtly are we eiected, perſecuted, condemned?
               But, if that Ancient Miſtreſſe of the World ſhall ſtand vpon the

termes of her honour, and will needs plead the diſparagement of her retractations, and the age and authoritie of theſe her Impoſitions, let me haue leaue to ſhut vp all, with that worthy and religious conteſtation of Saint Ambroſe, with his Symmachus.
               
               That eloquent Patron of Idolatry had pleaded hard for the olde Rites of Heatheniſme; and brings in Ancient Rome ſpeaking thus, for her ſelfe▪ 
                  Optimi Principes, &amp;c.
                  Inter Epiſtolas Ambrosij lib. 2. Epiſt. 11.
                   Excellent Princes, the Fathers of your Countrey, reuerence yee my yeares, into which my pious Rites haue brought me: I will vſe the Ceremonies of my Anceſtors, neither can I repent mee. I will liue after mine own faſhion, becauſe I am free. This Religion hath brought the World vnder the ſubiection of my Lawes; theſe ſacred Deuotions haue driuen Hannibal from our walles, from our Capitoll; Haue I beene preſerued for this, that in mine old age I ſhould be reproued? Say, that I did ſee what

were to bee altered,Sera tamen &amp; contumelioſa eſt emendatio ſenectutis. ibid. Ambroſ. Epiſt. l. 2. Ep. 12.
                   yet late and ſhamefull is the amendement of age. To which that holy Father no leſſe wittily and elegantly anſwers, by way of retortion, bringing in Rome to ſpeake thus, rather. I am not aſhamed in mine old age to be a Conuert, with all the reſt of the World. It is ſurely true, that in no age it is too late to learne. Let that olde age bluſh that cannot mend it ſelfe; It is not the grauitie of yeares,Nullus pudor eſt ad meliora tranſire, ibid. but of manners, that deſerues prayſe. It is no ſhame to goe to the better; And when Symmachus vrges (Maiorum ſeruandus est ritus) wee muſt obſerue the Rites of our forefathers; Dicant igitur, (ſaith Saint Ambroſe) Let them as well ſay, that all things ſhould remayne in their owne imperfect Principles, that the World once ouer-couered with darkneſſe, offends in being ſhined vpon by the glorious brightneſſe of the Sunne; And how much more happie is it, to haue diſpelled the darkneſſe of the ſoule, then of the bodie; to bee

ſhined vpon by the beames of Faith, then of the Sunne. Thus he; moſt aptly to the preſent occaſion; wherto did that bleſſed Father now liue, he would doubtleſſe, no leſſe readily apply it: Nec erubeſcas mutare ſententiam, ſaith Hierome to his Ruffinus, Neuer bluſh to change your minde;Non es tantae authoritatis vt erraſſe te pudeat, &amp;c. Hier. Apol. adu. Ruffin. you are not of ſuch authoritie as that you ſhould bee aſhamed to confeſſe you haue erred: Oh that this meeke ingenuitie could haue found place in that once famous, and Orthodoxe Church of Chriſt; how had the whole Chriſtian World beene as a Citie at vnitie in it ſelfe, and triumphed ouer all the proud hoſtilities of Paganiſme? But, ſince wee may not bee ſo happie, wee muſt ſit downe; and mourne for our deſolations, for our diuiſions. In the meane time wee waſh our hands in innocence. There are none of all theſe inſtanced particulars (beſides many more) wherein the Church of Rome hath not ſenſibly erred in corrupt additions

to the faith; ſo as herein wee may iuſtly (before heauen and earth) warrant our diſagreement of iudgement from her. The reſt is their act, and not ours; wee are meere patients in this ſchiſme; and therfore go, becauſe we are driuen; That we hold not communion with that Church, the fault is theirs; who both haue deſerued this ſtrangeneſſe by their errours, and made it by their violence; Contrarie to that rule which Cato in Tully giues of vnpleaſing frendſhip, they haue not ript it in the ſeame, but torn it in the whole cloth.
               Perhaps, I ſhall ſeeme vnto ſome, to haue ſpoken too mildly, of the eſtate of that debauched Church: There are that ſtand vpon a meere nullitie of her being, not reſting in a bare deprauation; For mee, I dare not goe ſo farre: If ſhe be foule, if deadly diſeaſed (as ſhe is) theſe qualities cannot vtterly take of her eſſence, or our relations.
               Our Diuines indeed call vs out of Babylon, and wee run; ſo as here is

an actuall ſeparation, on our parts; True, but from the corruptions (wherein there is a true confuſion) not from the Church; Their verie charge implies their limitation; as it is Babylon, we muſt come out of it, as it is an outward viſible Church,Fr. Ian. de Eccleſia. we neither did, nor would: This dropſie, that hath ſo ſwolne vp the body, doth not make it ceaſe to bee a true body, but a ſound one. The true Principles of Chriſtianitie, which it maintaines, maintaine life in that Church; the errors which it holds,Capitis autem male ſaniet deliri contagia vitanda ſunt, ne &amp; ipſi artus peſtilenti humore labeſierent. F. Pic. Mirand. Theor. 23.
                   together with thoſe Principles, ſtruggle with that life, and threaten an extinction: As it is a viſible Church then, we haue not detrected to hold communion with it (though the contemptuous repulſe of ſo many admonitions haue deſerued our alienation) as Babylon, wee can haue nothing to doe with it. Like as in the courſe of our life; we freely conuerſe with thoſe men in ciuill affaires, with whom we hate to partake in wickedneſſe.
               
                  But will not this ſeeme to ſauour of too much indifferencie? What need wee ſo vehemently labour to draw from either part, and triumph in winning Proſelytes; and giue them for loſt, on either ſide, and brand them for Apoſtates that are won away; if (which way ſo euer we fall) wee cannot light out of a true viſible Church of Chriſt? What ſuch neceſſitie was there of Martyrdome, what ſuch danger of relapſes, if the Church bee with both.
               Let theſe Sophiſters know, that true charitie needs not abate any thing of zeale. If they bee acquainted with the iuſt value of truth, they ſhall not enquire ſo much into the perſons, as into the cauſe. What euer the Church be, if the errours be damnable, our bloud is happily ſpent in their impugnation; and wee muſt rather chuſe to vndergoe a thouſand deaths, then offend the Maieſtie of God, in yeelding to a knowne falſhood in religion; neither

doth the outward viſibilitie of the Church abate ought of the hainouſneſſe of miſ-opinions, or the vehemence of our oppoſitions. Were it Saint Peter himſelfe, if hee halt in Iudaizing, Saint Paul muſt reſiſt him to his face; neither is his fault leſſe, becauſe an Apoſtles: Yea, let me ſay more; Were the Church of Rome, and ours, layd vpon ſeuerall foundations, theſe errours ſhould not be altogether ſo deteſtable, ſince the ſymbolizing in many truths makes groſſe errours more intolerable, as the Samaritan Idolatrie was more odious to the Iewes then meerely Paganiſh:Maldon. In. 4. Ioan. If the deareſt daughter of God vpon earth ſhould commit ſpirituall whoredome, her vncleanneſſe is ſo much more to be hated, as her obligations were greater. Oh the glorious crownes therfore of thoſe bleſſed Martyrs of ours, who rather gaue their bodies to bee burnt to aſhes, then they would betray any parcell of diuine truth.
               
                  Oh the wofull and dangerous condition of thoſe ſoules, which ſhutting their eyes againſt ſo cleere a light, either willingly ſit downe in palpable darkneſſe, or fall backe from the ſincerity of the Goſpel into theſe miſerable enormities both of practice and doctrine. It is not for me to iudge them; that, I leaue vnto that high and awfull Tribunall, before which I ſhall once appeare with them; but this I dare ſay, that if that righteous Iudge ſhall puniſh either their obſtinacie, or relapſes with eternall damnation, he cannot but bee iuſtified in his iudgements, whiles in the midſt of their torments, they ſhall bee forced to ſay, Thou,
                  Nehem. 9.33·
                   
                  O God, art iuſt in all that is befalne vs; For thou haſt done right, but we haue done wickedly.
               
               For vs, as wee would ſaue our ſoules, let vs carefully preſerue them from the contagion of Romiſh ſuperſtition; Let vs neuer feare that our diſcretion can hate errour too much; Let vs awaken, our holy

zeale to a ſerious and feruent oppoſition, ioyned with a charitable endeuour of reclamation. Shortly, let vs hate their opinions, ſtriue againſt their practice, pittie their miſ-guiding▪ neglect their cenſures, labour their recouerie, pray for their ſaluation.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

