
   
      
         
            Epistles the first volume: Containing II. decads. By Ioseph Hall
            Epistles. Vol. 1
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1608
            
         
         Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02534
            STC 12661.7
            ESTC S103637
            99839386
            99839386
            3800
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02534)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3800)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1175:08)
         
         
            
               
                  Epistles the first volume: Containing II. decads. By Ioseph Hall
                  Epistles. Vol. 1
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [16], 190, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes] for Samuel Macham &amp; E. Edgar: &amp; are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Bull-head,
                  At London :
                  1608.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  The first leaf is blank; the second blank except for marginal rules and signature-mark "A2"; the last blank except for marginal rules.
                  Variant: extra errata on a pasted-in slip headed "Errata alia".
                  Identified as STC 12663 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-08
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               EPISTLES
The
FIRST VOLVME:
Containing
II. DECADS.
            
               *⁎*

By IOSEPH HALL.
            AT LONDON
Printed by H. L. for Samuel
Macham &amp; E. Edgar:
&amp; are to be ſold in
Pauls Church-yard,
at the ſigne of the
Bull-head.
1608.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE HIGH
AND MIGHTIE PRINCE,
HENRIE, PRINCE OF GREAT
Britaine, Sonne and Heyre Apparant to
our Soueraigne Lord, IAMES, King
of Great Brit. &amp;c. all glorie in
either world.
            
               MOſt gracious Prince:
            
            IT is not from any conceit
of ſuch worth in my
labors, that they durst
looke ſo hye. A lower Patronage
would haue ſerued an hyer work.

It were well, if ought of mine
could bee worthie of popular
eyes. Or if I could wring ought
from my ſelfe, not vnworthie
of a iudicious Reader; I knowe
your Highneſſe wants neither
preſents, nor counſells: preſents
from strangers, counſells from
your teachers; neither of them
matcheable by my weakeneſse:
Only duty herein excuſes mee
from preſumptiō. For, I thought
it iniustice to deuote the fruite
of my labour, to any other hand
beſide my Maisters: which alſo
I knewe to bee as gratious, as
mine is faithfull. Yet (ſince euen

good affections cannot warrant
too much vileneſſe in gifts to
Princes) leſt while my modeſty
diſparages my worke, I ſhould
hazard the acceptation; heere
ſhall your Grace finde varietie,
not without profite. I hate a
Diuine, that would but pleaſe;
and, withall, thinke it impoſsible
for a man to profit, that pleaſeth
not. And if, while my ſtile fixeth
it ſelfe vpon others, any ſpirituall
profite ſhall reflect vpon
your H. how happie am I! who
ſhall euer thinke, I haue liued to
purpoſe, if (by the beſt of my studies)
I ſhall have done any good

office to your Soule. Further
(which theſe times account not
the least prayſe) your Grace ſhal
herein perceiue a new faſhion of
diſcourſe, by Epistles; new to
our language, vſual to others: and
(as Noueltie is neuer without
ſome plea of vſe) more free, more
familiar. Thus, we do but talke
with our friends by our pen, and
expreſse our ſelues no whit leſse
eaſily; ſome-what more digestedly.
            Whatſoeuer it is, as it cannot
be good enough to deſerue that
countenance; ſo, the countenance
of ſuch Patronage ſhall make it

worthie of reſpect from others.
The God of Princes protect
your perſon, perfect your graces,
and giue you as much fauour in
heauen, as you haue honour on
earth.
            
               Your Graces
humbly-deuoted
ſeruant,
IOS. HALL.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               EP. 1.
TO IACOB WADSWORTH,
Lately reuolted, in Spayne.
               Ep. 1. Expoſtulating for his departure, and
perſwading his returne.
               
                  HOw vnhappily is my
ſtile changed! Alas,
that to a friend, to a
brother, I muſt write
as to an Apoſtate, to
an aduerſary! Dooth
this ſeem harſh? you haue turned it,
by beeing turned your ſelfe. Once,

the ſame walls held vs in one louing
ſociety; the ſame Dioceſs, in one honourable
function; Now, not one
Land, and (which I lament) not one
Church: you are gone, we ſtand and
woder. For a ſheep, to ſtray through
ſimplicitie, is both ordinarie and lamentable:
but, for a ſhepheard is
more rare, more ſcandalous. I dare
not preſume ouer-much, vppon an
appeale to a blinded conſcience.
Thoſe, that are newly come from a
bright candle into a dark roome, are
ſo much more blinde, as their light
was greater; and the pureſt yuorie
turneth with fire into the deepeſt
black. Tell vs yet by your old ingenuitie,
and by thoſe ſparks of good
which yet (I hope) ly couered vnder
your cold aſhes, tell vs, what diuided
you? Your motiues ſhall once
bee ſcanned before an higher barre.

Shame not to haue the weake eyes
of the world ſee that, which once
your vndeceiueable Iudge ſhall ſee,
and cenſure. What ſawe you, what
heard you a-new, that might offer violence
to a reſolued minde, &amp; make
it either to alter, or ſuſpend? If your
reaſons be inuincible; informe vs, that
we may follow you: but if (as they
are) ſlight and feeble; returne you
to vs: returne, and thinke it no ſhame
to haue erred, iuſt ſhame to continue
erring. What ſuch goodly beautie
ſawe you in that painted, but ill-fauored
ſtrūpet, that ſhould thus bewitch
you, ſo to forget your ſelfe, and
contemne the chaſte loue of the
Spouſe of your Sauiour? I ſawe
her, at the ſame time in her gayeſt
dreſſe: Let my ſoule neuer
proſper, if I could ſee any thing
worthie to commaunde affection.

I ſaw, and ſcorned: you ſaw, and adored.
Would God your adoration
were as farre from ſuperſtition,
as my ſcorne from impietie. That
God iudge betwixt vs, whether heerin
erred: yea, let men iudge, that are
not drunke with thoſe Babyloniſh
dreggs. How long might an indifferent
eie looke vpon the comicall and
mimick actions in thoſe your myſteries,
that ſhould be ſacred, your magicall
exorciſmes, your clericall ſhauings,
your vncleanly vnctions, your
croſſings, creepings, cenſings, ſprinklings,
your cozening miracles, gariſh
proceſſions, burning of noonedaie,
chriſtning of bells, marting of
pardons, toſſing of beades, your
ſuperſtitious hallowing of candles,
waxe, aſhes, palmes, chriſme, garments,
roſes, ſwords, water, ſalt, the
Pontificall ſolemnities of your great-maſter,

and what-euer your new mother
hath (beſides) plauſible, before
he ſhould ſee ought, in all theſe, worthy
of anie other intertainment, then
contempt! Who can but diſdaine,
that theſe things ſhould procure anie
wiſe proſelyte? Cannot your owne
memorie recount thoſe trulie religious
ſpirits, which having ſought Rome
as reſolued Papiſtes, haue left the
World as holie Martyrs; dying for
the deteſtation of that vvhich they
came to adore? Whence this? They
heard and magnified that, which they
novv ſavve, and abhorred. Their
fire of zeale brought them to the
flames of Martyrdome. Their innocent
hopes promiſed them Religion:
they founde nothing but a
pretence; promiſed deuotion, and
beholde idolatrie: they ſaw, hated,
ſuffered, and now raigne; vvhiles

you wilfully, and vnbidden, will loſe
your ſoule, where others meant to
loſe, and haue found it. Your zeale
dyes, where theirs began to liue:
you like to liue, where they would
but die. They ſhall comfort vs,
for you: they ſhall once ſtand vppe
againſt you: While they would rather
dye in the heat of that fire, then liue
in the darkeneſſe of their errors;
you rather dye in the Egyptian
darkneſſe of errours, then liue in
the pleſant light of truth: Yea, I
feare, rather in another fire, then
this light.
               Alas! what ſhall wee looke-for of
you? Too late repentance, or obſtinate
errour? Both miſerable. A Spira,
or a Staphylus? Your friends, your
ſelfe, ſhall wiſh you rather vnborne,
then either.
               O thou, which art the great ſhepheard,

great in power, great in mercie,
which leaueſt the ninetie &amp; nine
to reduce one, fetch home (if thy
will bee) this thy forlorne charge:
fetch him home, driue him home to
thy fold, though by ſhame, though by
death. Let him once recouer thy
Church, thou him, it is enough.
Our common Mother I knowe not
whether more pitties your loſſe, or
diſdeignes thus to bee robb'd of a
ſonne: Not for the neede of you; but
her owne pietie, her owne loue.
For, howe many troupes of better
informed ſoules hath ſhee euerie
day returning into her lap; now
breathing from their late Antichriſtianiſme,
and embracing her knees
vppon their owne? Shee laments
you, not for that ſhee feares ſhee
ſhall miſſe you; but, for that ſhee

knovves you ſhall want her. See you
her teares, and doo but pittie your
ſelfe as much as ſhee you. And,
from your Mother, to deſcende to
your Nurſe; Is this the fruit of ſuch
education? Was not your youth
ſpent in a ſocietie of ſuch comely order,
ſtrict gouernment, wiſe lawes,
religious care (it vvas ours, yet
let mee praiſe it to your ſhame) as
maie iuſtlie challenge (after all
bragges) either RHEMES, or
DOVVAY, or if your Ieſuites haue
anie other denne more cleanlie, and
more worthie of oſtentation? And
coulde you come out, freſh and vnſeaſoned,
from the middeſt of thoſe
ſalt waues? Could all thoſe heauenlie
ſhowers fall beſide you; vvhile
you, like a Gedeons fleece, want moiſture?
Shall none of thoſe diuine
principles, which your youth ſeem'd

to drinke in, check you in your new
errours? Alas! how vnlike are you
to your ſelfe, to your name? Jacob
wreſtled with an Angell, and preuailed:
you grapple but with a Ieſuite,
and yield. Jacob ſupplanted his brother:
an Eſau hath ſupplanted you.
Jacob changed his name for a better,
by his valiant reſiſtance: you, by
your cowardlie yielding, haue loſt
your owne. Jacob ſtroue with God,
for a bleſſing: I feare to ſaie it, you
againſt him for a curſe; for, no common
meaſure of hatred, nor ordinarie
oppoſition can ſerue a reuolter:
Either you muſt be deſperatelie violent,
or ſuſpected. The mightie one
of Iſrael (for hee can doo it) raiſe you
fallen, return you wandred; and giue
you grace at laſt to ſhame the Diuel,
to forſake your ſtepmother, to acknowledge
your true Parent, to ſatisfie

the world, to ſaue your owne
ſoulē. If otherwiſe; I will ſay of you,
as Ieremie of his Iſraelites (if not rather
with more indignation) My ſoule
ſhall weepe in ſecret for your reuolt, and
mine eyes ſhall drop down teares, becauſe
one of the Lords flocke is carried away
captiue.
               
            
            
               
               To my Lord and Patron,
the Lord DENNY, Baron
of Waltham.
               EP. 2. Of the Contempt of the world.
               
                  MY Lord, my tongue, my
penne, and my heart,
are all your ſeruants;
when you cannot heare
mee, through diſtance,
you muſt ſee me in my Letters. You
are now in the Senate of the Kingdom,
or in the concourſe of the City,
or perhaps (tho more rarely) in the
royal face of the Court. All of them,

places fit for your place. From all
theſe, let mee call off your minde to
her home aboue; and, in the midſt
of buſineſſe, ſhowe you reſt: If I may
not rather commend, then admoniſh,
and before-hand confeſſe my
counſell ſuperfluous, becauſe your
holy forwardneſſe hath preuented it.
You can afford theſe, but halfe of
your ſelfe: The better part is better
beſtowed; Your ſoule is ſtill retired,
and reſerued. You haue learned to
vouchſafe theſe worldly things, vſe,
without affection; and knowe to
diſtinguiſh wiſely, betwixt a Stoicall
dulneſſe, and a Chriſtian contempt: &amp;
haue long made the world, not your
God, but your ſlaue. And, in truth
(that I may looſe my ſelfe into a bold
and free diſcourſe) what other reſpect
is it worthy of? I would adore it on
my face, if I could ſee any Maieſtie,

that might commaund veneration.
Perhaps, it loues me not ſo much, as
to ſhowe me his beſt. I haue ſought it
enough: And haue ſeene what others
haue doted on; and wondred at their
madneſſe. So may I look to ſee better
things aboue, as I neuer could
ſee ought heere, but vanitie &amp; vileneſſe.
               What is fame, but ſmoke? and
metall, but droſſe? and pleaſure, but
a pill in ſuger? Let ſom gallants condemne
this, as the voice of a Melancholike
ſcholler: I ſpeake that which
they ſhall feele, and ſhall confeſſe.
Tho I neuer was ſo, I haue ſeen ſom
as happy, as the worlde could make
them: and yet I neuer ſaw any more
diſcontented. Their life hath beene
neither longer, nor ſweeter, nor their
heart lighter, nor their meales hartier,
nor their nights quieter, nor their

cares fewer, nor their complaints.
Yea, wee haue knowen ſome, that
haue loſt their mirth when they haue
found wealth; and at once haue ceaſed
to be merrie and poore. All theſe
earthly delights, if they were ſound,
yet how ſhort they are! and if they
could be long, yet how vnſound! If
they were ſound, the
                     •
                   are but as a
good day betweene two agues, or a
ſunne-ſhine betwixt two tempeſts.
And if they were long, their hony is
exceeded by their gall. This ground
beares none but maples, hollow, and
fruitleſſe; or, like the bankes of the
dead ſea, a faire apple, which vnder a
red ſide containes nothing but duſt.
Euery flower in this garden either
prickes, or ſmells ill. If it be ſweet, it
hath thornes: and if it haue no thorns,
it annoies vs with an ill ſent. Go then,
ye wiſe idolatrous Paraſites, &amp; erect

ſhrines, and offer ſacrifices to your
God, the World; and ſeeke to pleaſe
him with your baſe and ſeruile deuotions:
It ſhall be long enough ere
ſuch religion ſhall make you happy.
You ſhall at laſt forſake thoſe altars,
empty and ſorrowfull. How eaſie is
it for vs Chriſtians, thus to inſult ouer
the worldling, that thinkes himſelfe
worthy of enuie? How eaſie to
turne off the World with a ſcornefull
repulſe; and when it makes vs the Diuels
proffer, All theſe will I giue thee,
to returne Peters anſwer, Thy ſiluer
&amp; thy gold periſh with thee? How eaſie
to accoūt none ſo miſerable, as thoſe
that are rich with iniurie, and growe
great by being conſcious of ſecret euils?
Wealth and honor, whē it coms
vpon the beſt terms, is but vain; but,
when vpō ill conditions, burdenſom.
When they are at the beſt, they are

ſcarce friends; but, when at the worſt,
tormentors. Alas! how ill agrees a
gay coate, and a feſtered heart? what
auailes an high title, with an hell in
the ſoule? I admire the faith of Moſes:
but, preſuppoſing his faith, I
wonder not at his choice. He preferred
the afflictions of Iſrael, to the
pleaſures of Egypt; and choſe rather
to eate the Lambe, with ſowre herbs,
then all their fleſh-pots: For, how
much better is it to be miſerable then
guilty? and what compariſon is ther
betwixt ſorrow and ſinne? If it were
poſsible, let mee bee rather in hell
without ſinne, then on earth wickedly
glorious. But, how much are wee
bound to God, that allowes vs earthlie
fauours, without this oppoſition!
That GOD hath made you at once
honourable and iuſt, and your life
pleaſant and holy, and hath giuen you

an high ſtate with a good heart; are
fauours, that looke for thanks. Theſe
muſt bee acknowledged, not reſted
in: They are yet higher thoughts
that muſt perfect your contentment.
               What God hath giuen you, is nothing
to that he meanes to giue: He
hath beene liberall; but, hee will be
munificent. This is not ſo much as
the taſte of a full cup. Faſten your
eyes vpon your future glory, and ſee
how meanly you ſhall eſteeme theſe
earthly graces. Here, you command
but a little pittance of mould (great
indeede, to vs; little, to the whole):
there, whole heauen ſhall bee yours.
Heere you commaund, but as a ſubiect:
there you ſhall raigne as a King.
Heere, you are obſerued; but ſometimes
with your iuſt diſtaſte: There,
you ſhall raigne with peace, and ioy.
Heere, you are noble among men;

there, glorious amongſt Angels.
Here, you want not honour; but you
want not croſſes: there, is nothing
but felicity. Here, you haue ſome
ſhort ioyes: there, is nothing but eternity.
You are a ſtranger, heere;
there, at home. Here, Satan tempts
you, and men vexe you: there, Saints
and Angels ſhall applaud you; and
God ſhall fill you with himſelfe. In a
word, you are onely bleſſed here, for
that you ſhall be.
               Theſe are thoughts worthy of
greatneſſe: which, if we ſuffer either
imployments, or pleaſures to thruſt
out of our doores, wee doe wilfully
make our ſelues comfortleſſe. Let
theſe ſtill ſeaſon your mirth, &amp; ſweeten
your ſorrowes, &amp; euer interpoſe
thēſelues betwixt you &amp; the world.
Theſe, only, can make your life happy,
and your death welcome.
            
            
               
               To my Lord HAY, H. and P.
               EP. 3. Of True Honour.
               
                  MY Lord, It is ſafe to complaine
of Nature where
Grace is; and to magnifie
Grace, where it is at once
had, and affected. It is a fault of
Nature, and not the leaſt, that as ſhe
hath dim eies, ſo they are miſ-placed.
Shee lookes ſtill, either forward, or
downward; forward to the obiect ſhe
deſires, or downward to the meanes:

Neuer turnes her eyes either backward,
to ſee what ſhe was; or vpward,
to the cauſe of her good: Whence, it is
iuſt with God to with-hold what hee
would giue, or to curſe that which he
beſtowes; and to beſot carnall minds
with outward things, in their value, in
their deſire, in their vſe: Whereas
true wiſedome hath cleare eyes, and
right ſet; and therefore ſees an inuiſible
hand in all ſenſible euents, effecting
all things, directing all things to
their due end; ſees on whom to depend,
whom to thanke. Earth is too
lowe, and too baſe, to giue bounds
vnto a ſpirituall ſight. No man then
can truely knowe what belongs to
wealth, or honour, but the gracious;
either how to compaſſe them,
or how to prize them, or how to vſe
them. I care not how manie thouſand
wayes there are to ſeeming honour,

beſides this of vertue: they
all (if more) ſtill leade to ſhame: Or
what plots are deuiſed to improue
it; if they were as deepe as hell, yet
their end is loſſe. As there is no
counſell againſt God: ſo there is no
honour without him. Hee enclines
the hearts of Princes to fauour; the
hearts of inferiours to applauſe.
Without him, the hand cannot
moue, to ſucceſſe; nor the tongue,
to praiſe: And what is honour without
theſe? In vaine doth the world
frowne vpon the man, whom hee
meanes to honour; or ſmile, where
hee would diſgrace. Let mee then
tell your L. who are fauorites in the
Court of heauen; euen whiles they
wander on earth: Yea, let the great
King himſelfe tell you, Thoſe that honour
mee, I will honour. That men
haue the grace to giue honour to

God, is an high fauour: but, becauſe
men giue honour to God (as
their duty) that therfore God ſhould
giue honour to men, is to giue, becauſe
hee hath giuen. It is a fauour of
God, that man is honoured of man
like himſelfe: but, that God alloweth
of our endeuours as honour
to himſelfe, is a greater fauour
then that vvherewith hee requires
it.
               This is the goodneſſe of our God:
The man that ſerues him, honours
him: and whoſoeuer honours him
with his ſeruice, is crowned with honour.
I challenge all times, places,
perſons: who euer honour'd God,
and was neglected? VVho wilfully
diſhonoured him, and proſpered?
Turne-ouer all Records;
and ſee howe ſucceſſe euer bleſſed
the iuſt, after manie daungers, after

manie ſtormes of reſiſtance, and
left their concluſion glorious; how
all godleſſe plots, in their looſe,
haue at once deceiued, ſhamed,
puniſhed their Author. I goe no
further: Your owne breſt knowes,
that your happie experience can
heerein iuſtifie GOD. The world
hath noted you, for a follower of
vertue; and hath ſeene howe faſt
Honour followed you: VVhiles you
ſought fauour with the GOD of
heauen, hee hath giuen you fauour
with his Deputie on earth.
               Gods former actions are patternes
of his future: Hee teaches
you what hee will doe, by what
hee hath done. Vnleſſe your hand
be wearie of offering ſeruice, hee
cannot either pull-in his hand from
rewarding, or hold it out empty. Honour
him ſtill, and God pawnes his

honour, on not failing you. You cannot
diſtruſt him, whom your proofe
hath found faithfull. And, whiles
you ſettle your heart in this right
courſe of true glorie; laugh, in ſecret
ſcorne, at the idle endeuours of
thoſe men, whoſe policies would
out-reach God, and ſeize vpon honour,
without his leaue. (GOD
laughes at them in heauen. It is a
ſafe and holie laughter, that followes
his.) And pittie the prepoſterous
courſes of them, which make religion
but a foote-ſtoole to the ſeat of aduancement;
which care for all things
but heauen, which make the worlde
their ſtanding marke; and doe not ſo
much as roue at GOD. Manie had
ſped well, if they had begun well,
and proceeded orderlie.
               A falſe method is the bane of manie
hopefull endeuours. God bids

vs ſeek firſt his kingdome; and earthly
things ſhall find vs, vnſought. Fooliſh
nature firſt ſeekes the world: and
if ſhe light on God by the waie, it is
more then ſhe expects, deſires, cares
for; and therfore failes of both, becauſe
ſhe ſeekes neither aright. Manie
had been great, if they had cared
to bee good; which now are croſſed
in what they woulde, becauſe they
willed not what they ought. If Salomon
had made wealth his firſt ſuite,
I doubt he had been both poore and
fooliſh; now, he asked wiſdome, and
gained greatneſſe; Becauſe he choſe
well, he receiued what he asked not.
O the bountie and fidelitie of our
God! becauſe we would haue the beſt
he giues vs all: Earth ſhall wait vpon
vs, becauſe wee attende vppon heauen.
               Go-on then, my Lord, go-on happily

to loue religion, to practice it:
let God alone, with the reſt. Be you
a Pattern of vertue; hee ſhall make
you a Precedent of glory. Neuer
man loſt ought, by giuing it to God:
that liberall hand returnes our gifts,
with aduantage. Let men, let God
ſee that you honour him; and they
ſhall heare him proclaime before
you, Thus ſhalt it bee done to the man
whom the King will honor.
               
            
            
               
               To Mr NEVVTON,
               Tutor to the Prince.
               EP. 4. Of Gratulation, for the hopes of our
Prince; with an aduiſing apprecation.
               
                  SIr, God hath called you to a
great and happy charge; You
haue the cuſtody of our cō
                  mon
Treaſure: Neither is there any
ſeurice comparable to this of yours;
whether wee regard God, or the
world. Our labours, oft-times beſtowed
vpon many, ſcarce profit one:
yours, beſtowed vpō one, redounds

to the profit of manie millions: This
is a ſummarie waie of obliging al the
World to you. I incourage you not
in your care: you haue more comfort
in the ſucceſſe of it, then all
Worlds can giue you. The verie ſubiect
of your paines would giue an
hart to him that hath none. I rather
congratulate, with you, our common
happineſſe, and the hopes of
poſteritie, in that roiall and bleſſed
iſſue. You haue beſt cauſe to be the
beſt witneſs of the rare forwardneſſe
of our gratious Maiſter: and I haue
ſeen enough, to make me think I can
neuer be enough thankfull to God for
him. That Princes are fruitfull, is a
great bleſſing: but, their children
are fruitful in grace, &amp; more eminēt
in place then vertue, is the greateſt
fauour God can doo to a State.
The goodneſs of a priuate man is his

owne; of a Prince, the whole worlds.
Their wordes are Maximes, their
actions examples, their examples,
rules. When I compare them with
their royall Father (as I doo ofte and
chearfully) I cannot ſay whether he
bee more happie in himſelfe, or in
them. I ſee both in him, and them; I
ſee &amp; wonder, that God diſtributes
to naturall princes giftes proportionable
to their greatneſs. That vviſe
Moderator of the world knows what
vſe is of their parts: he knowes that
the head muſt haue all the ſenſes that
pertaine to the whole bodie: And
how neceſſarie it is, that inferiours
ſhould admire them no leſſe for the
excellencie of their graces, then for
the ſwaie of their authoritie. Whereupon,
it is, that hee giues heroicall
qualities to Princes: and, as he hath
beſtowed vpon them his own name;

ſo alſo he giues them ſpeciall ſtamps
of his own glorious image. Amōgſt
all other vertues, what a comfort is it
to ſee thoſe yeares, and thoſe ſpirits
ſtoope ſo willingly to deuotion? Religion
is growen too ſeuere a Miſtreſſe
for yong and high courages to
attend. Verie rare is that Nobility of
blood, that doth not chalenge libertie;
and that libertie, that endes not
in looſeneſſe. Lo, this example teaches
our gallants, how wel euen Maieſtie
can ſtand with homage; Maieſtie
to men, with homage to God.
               Farre be it from mee, to do that
which my next clauſe ſhal condemn:
but, I thinke it ſafe to ſay, that ſeldome
euer thoſe yeares haue promiſed,
ſeldom haue performed ſo much.
Only God keep two miſchiefes euer
from within the ſmoke of his Court;
Flatterie and Trecherie: The iniquity

of times may make vs feare theſe;
not his inclination.
               For, whether as Engliſh, or as
men, it hath been euer familiar to vs
to faune vpon Princes: Tho, what
do I beſtow two names vppon one
vice, but attyred in two ſundry ſutes
of euill: For, Flatterie is no other
than gilded treaſon; nothing elſe
but poyſon in golde: This euill is
more tame; not leſſe daungerous.
It had beene better for many great
ones not to haue beene, then to haue
beene in their conceites more then
men. This, Flatterie hath done: and
what can it not? That other, Trecherie,
ſpills the blood; this, the vertues
of Princes. That takes them
from others: This bereaues
them of themſelues. That, in
ſpight of the actours, doth but
change their Crowne: this ſteales it

from them for euer. VVho can but
wonder, that reades of ſom not vnwiſe
Princes, ſo bewitched with the
inchantments of their Paraſites, that
they haue thought themſelues Gods
immortall, and haue ſuffred thēſelues
ſo ſtiled, ſo adored? Neither temples,
nor ſtatues, nor ſacrifices haue
ſeemed too much glory to the greatneſs
of their ſelfe-loue; Now none of
all their actions could be either euil,
or vnbeſeeming; Nothing could proceede
from them worthy of cenſure,
vnworthy of admiration: Their very
ſpots haue beene beautie, their humors
iuſtice, their errors wittie, their
Paradoxes diuine, their exceſſes heroicall.
O the damnable ſeruilitie of
falſe minds! which perſwade others
of that which themſelues laugh to ſee
beleeued. O the dangerous credulitie
of ſelfe-loue which intertaines

all aduantages if neuer ſo euill, neuer
ſo impoſsible. How happy a ſeruice
ſhal you do to this whole world of
ours, if you ſhal ſtil ſetle in that princely
minde a true apprehenſiō of himſelfe;
and ſhal teach him to take his
owne height aright; and euen from
his childhood to hate a paraſite, as the
worſt traytor: To breake thoſe falſe
glaſſes, that would preſent him a face
not his owne: To applaud plaine
truth, and bend his browes vpon exceſsiue
prayſes. Thus affected, hee
may bid vice do her worſt. Thus ſhal
he ſtriue with vertue, whether ſhal
more honour each other. Thus ſincere
and ſolid glory ſhal euery where
follow, and crowne him. Thus, when
he hath but his due, hee ſhal haue ſo
much, that he ſhal ſcorne to borrow
the falſe colors of adulation. Go-on
happily in this worthy and noble

imployment. The worke cannot
but ſucceed, that is furthered
with ſo many prayers.
            
            
               
               To Sr. THOMAS CHALLONER,
               EP. 5. A report of ſome Obſeruations in
my trauell.
               
                  
                     SIr, beſides my hopes, not my
deſires, I traueled of late; for
knowledge partly, &amp; partly
for health. There was nothing that
made not my iourny pleaſāt, ſaue the
labour of the way: which yet was ſo
ſweetly deceiued, by the ſociety of Sr
                  Edmund Bacon (a Gentlemā truly honorable,
beyond al titles) that I found
ſmal cauſe to cōplain. The ſea brookt

not me, nor I it; an vnquiet element,
made only for wonder and vſe, not
for pleaſure. Alighted once from
that wodden conueyance, and
vneuen way, I bethought my ſelfe
how fondly our life is committed to
an vnſteadie and reeling peece of
wood, fickle windes, reſtleſſe waters;
while wee may ſet foot, on ſtedfaſt
and conſtant earth. Lo, then euery
thing taught me, euery thing delighted
me; ſo ready are we to be affected
with thoſe forraine pleaſures,
which at home we ſhould ouer-look.
I ſaw much, as one might in ſuch a
ſpan of earth, in ſo fewe months. The
time fauored me: for, now newly had
the key of peace opened thoſe parts
which war had before cloſed; cloſed (I
ſay) to all Engliſh, ſaue either fugitiues
or captiues. All ciuill occurrences
(as what faire Cities, what

ſtrange faſhions, entertainement,
dangers, delights we found) are fit
for other ears, and winter euenings.
What I noted, as a diuine within the
ſphere of my profeſsion, my paper
ſhal not ſpare in ſom part to report;
and that to your ſelf, which haue paſſed
a longer way, with more happie
fruit of obſeruatiō. Euē little ſtreams
emptie themſelues into great riuers;
and they againe into the Sea. Neither
do I deſire to tell you what you
know not: it ſhall be ſufficient that I
relate ought, which others ſhall think
memorable.
               Along our way, how many Churches
ſaw we demoliſhed! Nothing
left, but rude heapes, to tell the paſſenger,
there had beene both deuotion
and hoſtilitie. O the miſerable
foot-ſteps of war, beſides bloodſhed,
ruine and deſolation! Furie hath don

that there, which Couetouſneſſe would
do with vs; would do, but ſhall not:
The truth within, ſhal ſaue the walles
without. And, to ſpeak truely (whateuer
the vulgar exclaime) Idolatrie
pull'd downe thoſe walles; not rage.
If ther had beene no Hollander to
raze them, they ſhould haue fallen alone,
rather thē hide ſo much impiety
vnder their guiltie roofe. Theſe are
ſpectacles not ſo much of crueltie, as
iuſtice; Crueltie of man, Iuſtice of
God. But (which I wōdred at) Churches
fall, and Ieſuites Colledges rife,
euery where: There is no City, where
thoſe are not either rearing, or built.
Whence commeth this? Is it, for that
deuotion is not ſo neceſſarie as Policy?
Thoſe men (as we ſay of the Fox)
fare beſt, when they are moſt curſed.
None ſo much ſpighted of their
owne; none ſo hated of all; none

ſo oppoſed by ours: and yet theſe
ill weedes growe. Whoſoeuer liues
long, ſhall ſee them feared of their
owne, which now hate them; ſhall
ſee theſe ſeuen leane kine deuoure
all the ſatte beaſtes that feede on
the medowes of Tyber. I prophecie,
as Pharaoh dreamed: The euent ſhal
iuſtifie my confidence.
               At Bruxelles, I ſaw ſome Engliſh-women
profeſſe themſelues Veſtalls;
with a thouſād rites, I know not whether
more ridiculous, or magicall.
Poore ſoules! they could not be fooles
enough at home. It would haue made
you to pitty, laugh, diſdaine (I know
not which more) to ſee by what cunning
ſleightes and faire pretences
that weake ſexe was fetcht into a
willfull bondage; and (if thoſe
two canne agree) willingly conſtrained
to ſerue a maiſter whome they

muſt and cannot obey: Whom they
neither may forſake for their vow,
nor can pleaſe for their frailty. What
followes hence? Late ſorrow, ſecret
miſchiefe, miſery irremediable.
Their forwardneſſe, for will-worſhip,
ſhall condemne our coldneſſe for
truth.
               
                  I talked there (in more boldneſſe,
perhaps, then wiſdom) with Coſterus a
famous Ieſuite; an old man, more teaſty
then ſubtle, and more able to wrā
                  gle
then ſatisfie. Our diſcourſe was
long &amp; rouing; &amp; on his part ful both
of words &amp; vehemency. He ſpake as
at home; I as a ſtranger: yet ſo, as he
ſaw me modeſtly peremptory. The
particulars would ſwell my Letter
too much: It is enough, that the
Truth loſt leſſe then I gayned.
At Gaunt (a Citie that commaunds
reuerence for age, and wonder

for the greatneſſe) wee fell vpon a
Cappucine nouice, which wept bitterly,
becauſe he was not allowed to be
miſerable. His head had now felt the
razor, his backe the rod: all that Laconicall
diſcipline pleaſed him well;
which another, being condemned
to, would iuſtly account a torment.
What hindred then? Piety, to his mother,
would not permit this which he
thought piety to God: He could not
be a willing begger, vnleſſe his mother
muſt begge vnwillingly. He was
the onely heire of his father, the onely
ſtay of his mother: the comfort of
her widow-hoode depended on this
her orphane; who now naked muſt
enter into the worlde of the Capucines,
as hee came firſt into this; leauing
his goods to the diuiſion of the
fraternity: The leaſt part whereof
ſhould haue beene hers, whoſe hee

wiſhed all: Hence thoſe teares, that
repulſe. I pitied his ill-beſtowed
zeale; and rather wiſhed, then durſt
teach him more wiſedome. Theſe
men for deuoute, the Jeſuites for
learned and pragmaticall, haue ingroſſed
all opinion, from other Orders.
O hypocriſie! No Capucine
may take or touch ſiluer: for, theſe
are (you knowe) the quinteſſence of
Franciſcan ſpirits. This metall is as
very an Anathema to theſe, as the
wedge of gold to Achan; at the offer
whereof he ſtarts back, as Moſes from
the ſerpent: Yet he caries a boy with
him, that takes and caties it; and neuer
complaines of either metall or
meaſure. I ſawe, and laughed at it;
and, by this open trick of hypocriſie,
ſuſpected more, more cloſe. How
could I chooſe? while commonly the
leaſt appeares of that which is; eſpecially

of that which is loathſom in appearance,
much more in nature. At
Namurs, on a pleaſant and ſteep hilltop,
we found one that was tearmed a
maried Hermite; approuing his wiſdome
aboue his fellowes, that could
make choice of ſo cheerfull and ſociable
a ſolitarineſſe. Whence, after a delightful
paſſage vp the ſweet riuer Moſa,
wee viſited the populous and rich
Clergy of Leodium. That great Citie
might well bee dichotomized into
Cloiſters, &amp; Hoſpitalls. If I might aduenture,
I could here play the Critick,
after all the ruins of my neglected Philology.
Olde monumnts, and after
them our Lipſius, call this people Eburones:
I doubt whether it ſhould
not rather bee written Ebriones; yet
without ſearch of any other Records,
ſaue my owne eyes: While yet I
vvould thoſe ſtreetes vvere more

moiſt with wine, then with bloud;
wherein no day, no night is not diſmall
to ſome. No law, no Magiſtrate
layeshold on the knowen murderer,
if himſelfe lift: For three dayes after
his fact; the gates are open, and iuſtice
ſhut: priuate violence may purſue
him, publique iuſtice can not:
whence, ſome of more hote temper
carue themſelues of reuenge; others
take-vp with a ſmal pecuniarie ſatiſfaction.
O England, thought I, happie
for iuſtice, happy for ſecuritie!
There you ſhall finde in euery corner
a Maumet; at euery door a Begget,
in euery diſh a Prieſt. From
thence we paſſed to the Spa, a village
famous for her medicinall and
minerall waters, compounded of yron
&amp; Copperice; the vertue whereof
yet the ſimple inhabitant aſcribes
to their beneficiall Saint, whoſe heauie

foote hath made an ill-ſhaped impreſsion,
in a ſtone of hisThe name of the vpper Well of the Spa.
                   
                  Sauenir;
A water more wholſome then pleaſant,
&amp; yet more famous then wholſome.
The wilde deſerts (on which
it borders) are haunted with three
kindes of ill cattell; Free-booters,
Wolues, Witches; Although theſe
two laſt are oft-times one. For, that
ſauage Ardenna, is reputed to yield
many of thoſe monſters, whom the
Greekes call 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; they, Lougarous;
we (if you wil) Witch-wolues:
Witches that haue put on the ſhape
of thoſe cruell beaſts. Wee ſawe a
boy there, whoſe halfe-face was deuoured
by one of them neere the
village: yet ſo, as that the eare was
rather out then bitten off. Nor many
dayes before our comming, at Limburgh
was executed one of thoſe miſcreants,
who confeſſed on the wheele

to haue deuoured two and fourtie
children in that forme. It would aske
a large volume, to ſcan this Probleme
of Lycanthropy. The reaſons, wherewith
their relation furniſht mee on
both parts, would make an Epiſtle tedious.
This in ſhort I reſolued; A ſubſtantiall
change is aboue the reach of
all infernall powers, proper to the
ſame hand that created the ſubſtance
of both: Herein the Diuell playes the
double Sophiſter; yea, the Sorcerer
with Sorcerers. Hee both deludes
the Witches conceite, and the beholders
eyes.
               One thing I may not omit, without
ſinfull ouer-ſight; A ſhort, but
memorable Storie, which the Grephier
of that Towne (though of
different religion) reported to more
eares then ours. VVhen the laſt
Inquiſition tyrannized in thoſe parts,

and helpt to ſpende the Faggots of
Ardenna; one of the reſt, a confident
Confeſſour, beeing led farre to
his ſtake, ſung Pſalmes along the
way, in an heauenlie courage, and
victorious Triumph: the cruell Officer
enuying his laſt mirth, and
grieuing to ſee him merrier then his
tormentours, commaunded him ſilence;
Hee ſinges ſtill, as deſirous
to improoue his laſt breath to the
beſt. The view of his approaching
glorie, bred his ioy; his ioy
breakes forth into a cheerefull confeſsion:
The enraged Sheriffe cauſes
his tongue, drawen foorth to the
length, to be cut off neere the rootes.
Bloudie wretch! It had beene good
Muſicke to haue heard his ſhreekes:
but, to heare his Muſick was torment.
The poor Martyr dies in ſilence, reſts
in peace. Not many moneths after,

our butcherly officer hath a ſonne
born with his tongue hanging down
vpon his chinne, like a Deare after
long chace; which neuer could bee
gathered vp within the bounds of his
lippes. O the diuine hand, full of iuſtice,
full of reuenge! Goe now, Lipſius,
and write the new miracles of thy
Goddeſſe; and confirme ſuperſtition
by ſtrange euents.Hiſtoire et Miracles, &amp;c. Iudge you that
haue ſeene, if euer the Chappell of
Halle or Zichem haue yielded ought
more notable.Que le 8. iour du mois de Septembre an dict an. 1603. eſtant Feſte de la Natiuitè de noſtre Dame, le nombre de Pelerins a eſtè euuiron 20000. Pag. 35. We met euery where
Pilgrimes to thoſe his Ladies: two
Ladies ſhall I call them, or one Lady
in two ſhrines? If two, why do they
worſhippe but one? If but one, why
doth ſhee that cure at Zichem, which
at Halle ſhe could not? O what pitty
it is, that ſo a high a wit ſhould in the
laſt be ſubiect to dotage! All the
maſculine broode of that braine wee

cheriſhed, and (if neede were) admired:
but, theſe his ſilly virgins, the
feeble iſſue of diſtempered age, who
can abide? One of his darlings, at
Louan, tolde mee from his owne
mouth;Virgo Hallenſis. that the elder of theſe two
daughters, was by him in ten dayes
got, conceiued, borne, chriſtened.
I beleeued, and wondred not. Theſe
acts of ſuperſtition haue an inuiſible
father, and mid-wife: beſides that it
is not for an Elephant to goe three
yeares with a Mouſe. It was tolde
mee in the ſhop of his Moretus, not
without ſome indignation, that our
King, when hee had well viewed the
booke, and read ſome Paſſages,
threw it to the ground with this Cenſure;
Damnation to him that made it,
and to him that beleeues it. Whether
a true ſtory, or one of their Legends,
I inquire not: I am ſure, that ſentence

did nor ſo much diſcontent them, as
it ioyed mee. Let mee tell you yet,
ere I take off my pen, two wonders
more, which I ſaw in that wonder
of Cities, Antwerp; One, a ſolemne
maſſe in a ſhambles, &amp; that on Gods
day: while the houſe was ful of meat,
of butchers, of buyers; ſome kneeling,
others bagaining, moſt talking,
all buſie. It was ſtrange to ſee one
houſe ſacred to God, and the belly;
and how thoſe two ſeruices agreed:
The Prieſt did eate fleſh, the butchers
ſold fleſh in one roofe, at one
inſtant. The butcher killed, and ſold
it by peeces; the Prieſt did ſacrifice,
and orally deuour it whole: whether
was the more butcher? The like wee
might haue ſeen at Malines.
                  Mechlinia. The
other, an Engliſh-man,One Goodwin a Kentiſh-man. ſo madly deuout,
that hee had willfully mur'd
vp himſelfe as an Anachoret; the

worſt of all priſoners: There ſate
hee pent-vp, for his further merite,
halfe hunger-ſtarued for the charitie
of the Citizens. It was worth
ſeeing, how manly hee could bite-in
his ſecret want, and diſſemble
his ouer-late repentance. I cannot
commend his mortification, if hee
wiſh to be in heauen, yea, in purgatorie,
to be deliuered from thence:
I durſt not pittie him; becauſe his
durāce was willing, &amp; (as he hoped)
meritorious: But, ſuch incouragement
as hee had from mee, ſuch
thanke ſhall hee haue from God;
who in ſteade of an Euge, which
hee lookes for, ſhall angerly challenge
him, with Who required
this? I leaue him now, in his
owne fetters; You, to your
worthie, and honourable imployments.
               
                  
Pardon me this length. Loquacity
is the naturall fault of Trauailers:
while I profit any, I may well bee
forgiuen.
            
            
               
               To Sr DAVID MVRRAY,
               EP. 6. Concerning the Miracles of our
time.
               
                  INdeede the worlde abounds
with miracles.
Theſe, while they fill the
mouthes of many, ſway
the faith of ſome, and
make all men wonder. Our nature
is greedy of newes; which it will rather
faine, then want. Certainly, ere
long, miracles will bee no wonders,
for their frequence. I had thought,

our age had had too many graye
hayres, and with time experience,
and with experience craft, to haue
deſcryed a iuggler: but, now I ſee,
by the ſimplicitie, it declines to his
ſecond childhood. The two Lipſian
Ladies, the charmes of Bluntſtones
boye, and Garnets ſtrawe, what a
noyſe haue they made! I only wonder
how Faux and Catesby eſcaped
the honor of Saints, and priuiledge
of miracles. Heerein you aske my
ſentence; more ſeaſonably, then you
hoped. For, I meant to haue wrote
a iuſt volume of this ſubiect, and
furniſht my ſelfe accordingly in that
region of wonders; but that I feared
to ſurcharge the nice ſtomach of
our time, with too much. Neither
would my length haue ought auailed
you; whoſe thoughts are ſo taken
vp with thoſe hie and ſeruiceable

cares, that they can giue no leaſure
to an ouer long diſcourſe. May it
pleaſe you therefore to receiue, in
ſhort, what I haue deliberately reſolued
in my ſelfe, and think I can make
good to others.
               I haue noted foure ranks of commonly
named Miracles: from which,
if you make a iuſt ſubduction, how
fewe of our wōders ſhal remaine either
to beleefe or admiration? The
firſt meerely reported, not ſeene to
be done; the next ſeeming to be don,
but counterfaited; the third, truely
done, but not true miracles; the laſt,
truely miraculous, but by Satan. The
firſt of theſe are bred of lyes, and
nouriſhed by credulitie: The
mouth of fame is full of ſuch blaſts.
For theſe, if I liſted awhile to rake
in the Legends, and booke of Conformities,
an ingenuous Papiſt could

not but bluſh, an indifferent Reader
could not but lay his hand on his
ſpleene, and wonder as much that anie
man could bee ſo impudent to
broach ſuch reports, or any ſo ſimple
to beleeue them; as the credulous
multitude wonders that any ſhould
be ſo powerfull to effect them. But, I
ſeeke neither their ſhame, nor others
laughter. I dare ſay, not the Talmud,
not the Alcoran, hath more impoſsible
tales, more ridiculous lyes.
Yea, to this head, Canus himſelfe (a famous
Papiſt) dare referre many of
thoſe antient miracles reported, and
(by all likelihood) beleeued of Bede,
and Gregory. The next are bred of
fraud, &amp; cozenage, nouriſhed by ſuperſtition.
Who knowes not, how the
famous Kentiſh I do I moued her eies,The Rood of Grace at Boxley Abbey.
                  
and hands, by thoſe ſecret gimmers,
which now euery Puppet-play can

imitate? How Saint Wilfreds needle
opened to the penitent, and
cloſed it ſelfe to the guiltie? How
our Lady ſheds the teares of a bleeding
vine? and doth many of her
daily feates, as Bel did of olde eate
vp his banket, or as Picens the Eremite
faſted fourty dayes. But, theſe
two euery honeſt Papiſt wil confeſſe,
with voluntarie ſhame and griefe;
and grant that it may grow a diſputable
queſtion whether Mountebāks
or Prieſts are the greateſt cozeners.
Viues, beyond his wont vehemently,
tearmes them execrable and ſatanicall
impoſtors. The third are true
workes of GOD, vnder a falſe title:
God giues them their being, men
their name: vniuſt, becauſe aboue
their nature; wherein, the Philoſopher
and the ſuperſtitiouſly-ignorant,
are contrarily extreame: while

the one ſeekes out naturall cauſes
of Gods immediate and metaphyſicall
works; The other aſcribes ordinary
effectes, to ſupernaturall cauſes.
If the violence of a diſeaſe ceaſe,
after a vow made to our Ladie; If a
ſouldier, armed with this vow, eſcape
gunſhot; a captiue, priſon; a Woman
traueling, death; the vulgar
(and I would they alone) cry out,
A miracle. One loadſtone hath
more wonder in it, then a thouſand
ſuch euentes. Euerie thing
drawes a baſe minde to admiration.
Franceſco del Campo (one of
the Arch-dukes Quiryes) told vs,
not without importunate deuotion,
that in that fatall fielde of Newport,
his vow to their Virgin helpt him to
ſwimme ouer a large water, when
the oares of his armes had neuer
before tryed any waues. A dogge

hath done more, without acknowledgement
of any Saint. Feare
giues ſudden inſtincts of skill, euen
without precept. Their owne Coſterus
durſt ſay, that the Cure of a
diſeaſe is no miracle: His reaſon,
becauſe it may be done by the power
of Nature, albee in longer time.

                     
                        •
                     n l' an mil ſix cents &amp; trois, y fureut comptez cent &amp; trente cin
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      potences &amp; iambes de bo
                        •
                     s de perſonnes boyteuſes y apportées au ſeul eſpace de quatre ou cinc
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      mois. Hiſtoire &amp; Miracles. c. 12. p. 34.Yeeld this, and what haue Lipſius
his two Ladies done? wherefore
ſerues all this clamour, from the two
hilles? I aſſented not; neither will
bee herein thus much their enemy:
For, as well the manner of doing, as
the matter, makes a miracle. If Peters
handkerchiefe, or ſhadow, heale a
diſeaſe, it is miraculous, though it
might haue been done by a Potion.
Many of their recoueries, doubtleſſe,
haue beene wrought through
the ſtrength of Nature in the Patient;
not of vertue in the Saint.

How many ſicke men haue mended,
with their phyſicke in their pocket?
Tho many other alſo (I doubt not) of
thoſe Cures haue fallē into the fourth
head; which indeed is more knotty,
and requires a deeper diſcourſe.
Wherein, if I ſhal euince theſe two
things, I ſhal (I hope) ſatisfie my
Reader, and cleare the Truth: One,
that miracles are wroght by Satā; the
other, that thoſe which the Romiſh
Church boaſteth, are of this nature,
of this author. I contend not of
words: we take miracles in Auguſtines
large ſenſe; wherein is little difference
betwixt a thing maruelous &amp;
miraculous; ſuch as the ſpirite of
GOD in either inſtrument calles

                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ,Or 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                   &amp; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Perhaps, it would
bee more proper to ſay, that God
workes theſe miracles by Satan: for,
as in the naturall and voluntarie motions

of wicked men; ſo in the ſupernatural
acts of euil ſpirits (as they
are acts) there is more then a meere
permiſſion. Satan, by his tempeſt,
bereaues Iob of his children: yet
Iob, looking higher, ſayth The Lord
hath taken. No ſophiſtrie can elude
this proofe of Moſes; that a Prophet
or dreamer may giue a true
ſigne or wonder, and yet ſay Let vs
goe after strange Gods:
                  Deut. 13. 1 nor that of
our Sauiour, who 
                     •
                  oretels of falſe
Chriſts, falſe Prophets that ſhall giue

                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; ſignes and wonders,
and thoſe great. The are ſome
too great, I grant, for the hand of all
infernall powers: by which, our Sauiour
inuincibly proues the truth of
his deity: Theſe neuer graced falſehood,
neither admitte any precedent
from our times. As to the reſt ſo frequent
and common, for mee, I could

not beleeue the Church of Rome
were Antichriſtian, if it had not boaſted
of theſe wōders. Al the knot lyes
then, in the application of this to
Rome, and our imaginarie Lady: How
ſhall it appeare, that their miracles
are of this kinde? Ludouicus Viues
giues ſixe notes to diſtinguiſh Gods
miracles, from Satans; Lipſius three:
Both of them too many, as might eaſily
bee diſcouered by diſcuſsing of
particulars. It is not ſo much the
greatneſſe of the worke, not the beleefe
of witneſſes, not the qualitie
nor manner of the action, nor trueth
of eſſence, that canne deſcrie the immediate
hand which worketh in our
miracles. That alone is the true and
golden rule which Iuſtin Martyr (if
at leaſt that booke bee his) preſcribes
in his Queſtions and Aunſwers; How
ſhall it bee knowen that our miracles

are better then the Heathens,
although the euent countenaunce
both alike?By the faith and worſhip of the true God. 
                  Reſp. Ex fide &amp; cultu
veri dei: Miracles muſt bee iudged
by the doctrine which they confirme;
not the doctrine, by the miracles.
The dreamer, or prophet, muſt
bee eſteemed, not by the euent of his
wonder; but, by the ſubſtance and
ſcope of his teaching. The Romaniſts
argue prepoſterouſly, while
they would prooue the trueth of
their Church by miracles; whereas
they ſhould proue their miracles by
the trueth: To ſay nothing of the
faſhion of their Cures, that one is
preſcribed to come to our LADIE,
rather on a Fridaye, as
*Henrie Loyez; another, to waſhe
nine Dayes in the Water of
MONT—AIGV, as Leonard
Stocqueau;
                  Pag. 7. another, to eate a peece

of the Oke where the image ſtood,
Hiſtoire &amp; miracles de noſtre Dame. pag. 73. pag. 102.as Magdaleine the widow of Bruxelles.
All which if they ſauour not
ſtrong of magical receits, let the Indifferent
iudge. Surely, either there
is no ſorcery, or this is it. All ſhall bee
plaine, if the doctrine confirmed by
their miracles be once diſcuſſed: for,
if that be diuine truth, we do vniuſtly
impugne theſe workes as diabolicall;
if falſhood, they do blaſphemouſly
proclaime them for diuine.
Theſe workes tend all chiefly to this
double doctrin; that the bleſſed virgin
is to bee inuoked, for her mediation;
That God &amp; Saints are to be adored
in &amp; by Images; Poſitions that would
require a volume, and ſuch as are liberally
diſputed by others: whereof
one is againſt ſcripture; the other
(which in theſe caſes values no leſſe)
beſides it. One deifies the virgin;

the other, a ſtocke or ſtone. It
matters not what ſubtile diſtinctions
their learned Doctors make
betwixt mediation of Redemption,
and Interceſsion, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , and

                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , the Saint and the Image:
Wee knowe, their common people,
whoſe deuotion inriches thoſe
ſhrines (by confeſsion of their
owne Writers) climbe the Hill of
Zichem with this conceite,Examen Pacifique de la doctrine des Hugenots. that
Marie is their Sauioreſſe;Oſauuereſie ſauue moy. Manuel of French praiers, printed at Liege, by approbatiō and authoritie of Anton. Gheuart Inquiſitor, &amp;c. that the
ſtocke is their Goddeſſe: which
vnleſſe it bee true, how do their
wonders teach them lyes! and
therefore how from GOD? But,
to take the firſt at beſt (for, the
ſecond is ſo groſſe, that were not
the ſeconde commaundement by
Papiſtes purpoſely razed out of
their Primiers, children and carrers
would condemne it) it cannot be

denied, that all the ſubſtance of
prayer is in the heart; the vocall
ſound is but a complement, and as
an outwarde caſe wherein our
thoughts are ſheathed. That
Power cannot knowe the prayer,
which knowes not the heart: either
then the Virgin is God, for that
ſhee knowes the heart, or to knowe
the heart is not proper to GOD:
or to knowe the heart, and ſo our
prayers, is falſely aſcribed to the
Virgin: and therefore theſe wonders,
which teach men thus to honour
her, are Doctors of lyes; ſo,
not of GOD. There cannot be
any diſcourſe, wherein it is more
eaſie to bee tedious. To ende;
If prayers were but in wordes, and
Saints did meddle with all particularities
of earthly thinges, yet
bleſſed Marie ſhould bee a God,

if ſhee could at once attend all her
Suiters. One ſolicites her at Halle,
another at Scherpen-heuuell, another
at Luca, at our Walſingham
another; one in Europe, another in
Aſia; or perhappes another is one
of her newe Clientes in America:
Tenne thouſande deuout Supplyants
are at once proſtrate before
her ſeuerall ſhrines. If ſhee cannot
heare all; why pray they? If ſhee
canne, what canne GOD doe
more? Certainely (as the matter
is vſed) ther cannot bee greater
wrong offered to thoſe heauenly
ſpirits, then by our importunate
ſuperſtitions to be thruſt into Gods
throne; and to haue forced vppon
them the honours of their Maker.
There is no contradiction in heauen:
a Saint cannot allowe that an
Angell forbids. See thou doe it not,
                  
was the voyce of an Angell: if all
the miraculous blocks in the world
ſhall ſpeake contrarie, wee knowe
whome to beleeue. The olde rule
was,Let no man worſhip the Virgin Marie.
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : Either
that rule is diueliſh, or this practice.
And if this practice bee ill, GOD
deliuer mee from the immediate authour
of theſe miracles. Change
but one Idoll for another, and
what differ the wonders of Apolloes
Temples, from thoſe of theſe
Chappelles? Wee reuerence (as
wee ought) the memorie of that
holy and happie Virgin: Wee
hate thoſe that diſhonour her; wee
hate thoſe that deifie her. Curſed
bee all honour, that is ſtollen
from God.
               This ſhort ſatisfaction I giue,
in a long queſtion; ſuch as I dare
reſt in; and reſolue that all Popiſh

miracles are either falſely reported,
or falſely done, or falſely miraculous,
or falſely aſcribed
to heauen.
            
            
               
               
               To Mr. WILLLIAM BEDELL,
at Venice.
               EP. 7. Lamenting the death of our late
Diuines and inciting to their imitation.
               
                  WE haue heard, how full of
trouble, &amp; dāger, the Alpes
were to you; and did at
once both pittie your difficulties,
and reioyce in your ſafetie. Since
your departure from vs, Reynolds
is departed from the World. Alas;
how many worthy lightes haue our
eyes ſeene ſhining and extinguiſht?
               
                  
How many loſſes haue wee liued to
ſee the Church ſuſtaine, and lament;
of her childrē, of her pillers; our own,
and forraine? I ſpeake not of thoſe,
which (being excellent) would needs
be obſcure: whom nothing but their
owne ſecrecie depriued of the honor
of our teares. There are, beſides, too
many whome the world noted and
admired; euen ſince the time that our
common mother acknowledged vs
for her ſonnes. Our Fulk ledde the
way; that profound, readie and reſolute
Doctor, the hāmer of heretickes,
the champion of Truth: whome our
younger times haue heard oft diſputing
acutely, and powerfully. Next
him, followed that honour of our
ſchools, &amp; Angel of our church, learned
Whitakers; then whom, our age
ſaw nothing more memorable: what
clearnes of iudgemēt, what ſweetnes

of ſtile, what grauity of perſon, what
grace of cariage was in that man?
Who euer ſaw him, without reuerēce?
or heard him, without wonder? Soone
after, left the world that famous and
truly illuminate Doctor, Francis Iunius,
the glory of Leiden, the other
hope of the Church, the Oracle of
Textuall and ſchoole-diuinity: rich in
languages, ſubtil in diſtinguiſhing, &amp;
in argument inuincible: and his cō
                  panion
in labours, Lu. Trelcatius,
wold needs be his cōpanion in ioyes;
who had doubled our ſorrow &amp; loſs,
but that he recōpenced it with a ſon
like himſelf. Soon after, fell old reuerend
Beza; a long-fixed ſtar in this
firmament of the Church: who, after
many excellent monuments of learning
and fidelity, liued to proue vpon
his aduerſaries, that hee was not
dead at their day. Neither may I

without iniury, omit that worthie
payr of our late Diuines, Greenham,
and Perkins: whereof the one excell'd
in experimentall diuinity; and
knew well how to ſtay a weake conſcience,
how to raiſe a fallen, how to
ſtrike a remorſe-leſſe: The other, in
a diſtinct iudgement, and a rare dexterity
in clearing the obſcure ſubtilties
of the ſchoole, and eaſie explication
of the moſt perplex diſcourſes.
Doctor Reynolds is the laſt; not in
worth, but in the time of his loſſe.
Hee alone was a well-furniſht librarie,
full of all faculties, of all ſtudies,
of all learning: The memorie, the
reading of that man, were neere to a
miracle. Theſe are gone, amongſt
many more, whom the Church
mournes for in ſecret: would God
her loſſe could be as eaſily ſupplied,
as lamented. Her ſorrowe is for

thoſe that are paſt; her remainder of
ioy in thoſe that remaine; her hope
in the next age. I pray God the cauſes
of her hope, and ioy, may bee equiualent
to thoſe of her griefe.
               What ſhould this worke in vs, but
an imitation, yea (that word is not
too bigge for you) an emulation of
their worthineſſe? It is no pride, for a
man to wiſh himſelfe ſpiritually better
then he dare hope to reach: nay,
I am deceiued, if it be not true humility.
For, what doth this argue him,
but lowe in his conceite, high in his
deſires onely? Or if ſo; happy is the
ambition of grace, and power of ſincere
ſeruiceableneſſe to God. Let
vs wiſh, and affect this, while the
world layes plots for greatneſſe: Let
me not proſper, if I beſtowe enuie on
them. He is great, that is good: and
no man, me thinks, is happy on earth,

to him that hath grace for ſubſtance,
and learning for ornament. If you
knowe it not, the Church (our mother)
lookes for much at your hands:
ſhee knowes how rich our common
father hath left you: ſhee notes your
graces, your opportunities, your imployments:
ſhe thinks you are gone
ſo farre, like a good Merchant, for no
ſmall gaine; and lookes you ſhal com
home well laded. And for vent of
your preſent commodities (tho our
chiefe hope of ſucceſſe bee cut-off
with that vnhoped peace) yet what
can hinder your priuate traffique for
God? I hope (and who doth not?) that
this blow wil leaue in your noble Venetians
a perpetuall ſcar; &amp; that their
late irreſolution ſhal make them euer
capable of all better counſels; and
haue his worke (like ſome great Eclipſe)
many yeares after. How happy

were it for Venice, if as ſhe is euery
yeare maried to the ſea, ſo ſhee were
once throughly eſpouſed to Chriſt!
In the meane time, let mee perſwade
you to gratifie vs at home, with the
publication of that your exquiſite
Polemicall diſcourſe; wherto our cō
                  ference
with M. Alabaſter, gaue ſo
happy an occaſion: You ſhall heereby
cleare many truthes; and ſatisfie
all Readers: yea, I doubt not, but an
aduerſary (not too peruerſe) ſhall acknowledge
the Truthes victorie and
yours. It was wholſom counſell of a
Father, that in the time of an hereſy euery
man ſhould write. Perhaps, you
complaine of the inundations of
Francford: How many haue been diſcouraged
from benefiting the world,
by this conceit of multitude! Indeed
we all write; and, while we Write, cry
out of number.
               
                  
How well might many be ſpared,
euen of thoſe that complaine of too
many? whoſe importunate babbling
cloyes the world, without vſe.
            
            
               
               To my Lord, the Earle of ESSEX.
               EP. 8. Aduiſe for his Trauailes.
               
                  MY Lord, both my duty
and promiſe make my
Letters your debt; and,
if neither of theſe, my
thirſt of your good. You
ſhall neuer but neede good counſell,
moſt in trauaile: Then are both our
dangers greater, and our hopes.
               I neede not tell you the eyes of
the world are much vpon you, for
your owne ſake, for your fathers:
Only let your eyes be vpon it again,

                     〈1 page missing〉
                  
                  
and pittied, which haue brought nothing
from forraine Countries, but
miſſhapen cloathes, or exoticall geſtures,
or new games, or affected liſſpings,
or the diſeaſes of the place,
or (which is worſt) the vices? Theſe
men haue at once wandered from
their Countily, and from themſelues:
and ſome of them (too eaſie to inſtance)
haue left God behinde them;
or perhaps, in ſtead of him, haue after
a looſe and filthy life brought home
ſome idle Puppet in a boxe, whereon
to ſpende their deuotion. Let
their wracke warne you: and let their
follies bee entertained by you, with
more dereſtation then pitty. I knowe
your Honour too well to feare you:
your young yeares haue been ſo graciouſly
preuented with ſoueraigne
antidotes of truth and holy inſtruction,
that this infection deſpaires of

preuailing. Your very bloud giues
you argument of ſafety: yet, good
counſell is not vnſeaſonable, euen
where danger is not ſuſpected. For
Gods ſake, my Lord, whatſoeuer you
gaine, loſe nothing of the truth; remit
nothing of your loue and pietie
to God; of your fauour and zeale to
religion. As ſure as there is a God,
you were trained vp in the true
knowledge of him. If either Angell,
or Diuell, or Ieſuite, ſhould ſuggeſt
the contrary, ſend him away, with defiance.
There you ſee and heare, euerie
day, the true mother and the fained,
ſtriuing and pleading for the liuing
childe. The true Prince of peace
hath paſt ſentence frō heauen, on our
ſide. Doe not you ſtoope ſo much as
to a doubt, or motion of irreſolution.
Abandon thoſe from your table and
ſalt, whom your owne or others experience

ſhall deſcry dangerous;
Thoſe ſerpents are full of inſinuations:
But, of all, thoſe of your owne
Country: which are ſo much more
pernicious, by how much they haue
more colour of priuiledge of entireneſſe.
Religion is the greateſt care:
aduiſes for cariage, &amp; improuement
of trauaile, chalenge the next place.
I neede not counſell you to keepe
your ſtate, with affability; and ſo to
menage your ſelfe, as that your curteſie
may be more viſible, then your
greatneſſe. Nature hath taught you
this, and hath ſecretly propagated it
from your Father: who, by his ſweetneſſe
of diſpoſition, wonne as many
hearts, as by his valour and munificence.
I rather tell you, that a good
nature hath betrayd many; who, looking
for that in others which they
haue found in themſelues, haue at laſt

complained of their owne credulity,
and others deceit. Truſt not Strangers
too much; with your counſell,
with your perſon: and, in your greateſt
familiarities, haue an eye to their
common diſpoſition, and infirmities.
Thoſe natures, wherewith you conuerſe,
are ſubiect to diſpleaſure; and
violent, in purſuit of ſmal indignities.
Yeſterday heard I named, from no vnfaithfull
report, a French Courtier,
that in ſingle combat hath ſent 18.
ſoules from the field to their place:
yet he euer as the patient in the quarrell;
and for this, mentioned with
more then excuſe: I cenſure not how
iuſtly. This is others care: Onely
hence I argue the rifeneſs of vnkindneſſe
taken, and purſued. You ſhall
ſee, that the ſoile is not ſo diuerſe, as
the inclination of perſons: vvho,
in all Climates, though they differ in

particulars, yet ſtill agree too well in
cōmon falls. The Italian deepe, cloſe,
and crafty; the French raſh; the Germain
dull. One not forward to offer
wrongs; but, apprehenſiue of a ſmall
wrong offred: another, prone either
to take, or giue them; but, not vneaſie
to remit: another, long in conceiuing,
long in retaining. What doe I exemplifie?
Ther are long Catalogues of
peculiar vices, that haunt ſpeciall
places; which, if they were not notoriouſly
infamous, my charity would
ſerue me to particularize: It were pittie
ther ſhould be fewer vertues, locall
and proper. There are good vſes
to bee made of others enormities; if
no more, by thē to correct our owne:
who loathes vice in another, is in good
forwardnes to leaue it in himſelf. The
view of the publique calamities, and
diſorders of other Churches, ſhall

beſt teach you thankfulneſſe for the
better ſtate of ours: But, better vſe of
their vertues; by how much it is more
excellent to knowe what wee ſhould
doe, then what we ſhould not. You
muſt now looke vpon all things, not
with the eyes of a ſtranger onely, but
of a Philoſopher, but of a Chriſtian;
which accounts all loſt, that is not reduced
to practice. It is a great praiſe,
that you are wiſer by the contemplation
of forraine things; but, much
greater, that you are better. That you
haue ſeene Cities, and Courts, and
Alpes, &amp; Riuers, can neuer yield you
ſo ſound comfort, as that you haue
lookt ſeriouſly into your ſelfe. In vain
doe we affect all forraine knowledge,
if we be not throughly acquainted at
home. Thinke much, and ſay little;
eſpecially in occaſions of diſpraiſe:
wherein, both a little is enough, and

oft-times any thing is too much. You
cannot enquire too much: that, which
in vs inferiours would bee cenſured
for dāgerous curioſity, in your greatnes
ſhall be conſtrued as a cōmendable
deſire of knowledge. Ask ſtill after
men of greateſt parts &amp; reputation:
&amp; where you finde Fame no lier,
note &amp; reſpect them. Make choice of
thoſe for conuerſation, which either
in preſent, or in hope, are eminent:
&amp; when you meet with excellencies
in any faculty, leaue not without ſom
gaine of knowledge. What are others
graces to you, if you onely admire
them; not imitate, not appropriate
them? Lo, your equals in time growe
vp happily in the Colledge (ſo I may
tearme it) of our young, and hopefull
Court, which you haue left; and, aboue
all, that gracious Preſident of
worthineſſe and perfection: whom

while in all other things you ſerue,
you may without reproofe emulate
for learning, vertue, pietie. My ſelfe
am witneſſe of their progreſſe; which
I do ioyfully gratulate to the ſucceeding
age. Beware, leaſt their diligēce
ſhall out-ſtrip you, and vpbraid you
with that auncient check of Going
farre and faring worſe. I am bolde
&amp; buſie in counſelling: you abound
with better monitors; and the beſt
you carrie about, I hope, in your own
boſome. Tho theſe ſhould be needleſſe,
yet they argue my humble affection,
and diſcharge my dutie. My
prayers are better then my counſels;
both of them heartie and vnfained
for your good. God guide and returne
you ſafe, from a iourney not
more happy and proſperous then I
wiſh it.
            
            
               
               
               To St. ROBERT DRVRY, and
his Lady.
               EP. 9. Concerning my Remooueall from
them.
               
                  WIth how vnwilling an
heart I leaue you, hee
knowes that ſearches
the heart: Neither
durſt I go, but
that I ſenſibly ſee his hand pulling
mee from you. Indeed, deſire of cō
                  petencie
betrayed mee, at firſt; and

drew mine eyes to looke aſide: but,
when I bent them vppon the place,
and ſaw the number and the neede of
the people, together with their hunger
and applauſe, meeting with the
circumſtances of Gods ſtrange conueyance
of this offer to mee; I
ſaw, that was but as the fowlers feather,
to make mee ſtoope: and,
contemning that reſpect of my ſelfe,
I ſincerely acknowledged hyer motiues
of my yeelding; and reſolued
I might not reſiſt. You are
deare to mee, as a Charge to a Paſtor;
If my paines to you haue not
proued it, ſuſpect mee: Yet I
leaue you. God calls mee to a
greater worke: I muſt followe
him. It were more eaſe to mee, to
liue ſecretly hidden in that quiet obscuritie,
as Saul amongſt the ſtuffe,
then to bee drawen out to the eye

of the world, to act ſo hye a part before
a thouſand witneſſes. In this
point, if I ſeem to neglect you, blame
me not; I muſt neglecte and forget
my ſelfe. I can but labour, whereſoeuer
I am. GOD knowes how
willingly I do that, whether there or
here. I ſhall dig, and delve, &amp; plant,
in what ground ſoeuer my Maiſter
ſets mee. If hee take mee to a larger
fielde, complaine you not of
loſſe, while the Church may gaine.
But, you are my owne charge; No
wiſe father neglectes his owne in
compaſsion of the greater neede of
others: yet conſider, that euen
carefull Parentes, when the Prince
commaundes, leaue their families,
and go to warfare. What if God
had called mee to heauen; would
you haue grudged my departure? Imagine
that I am there, where

I ſhall bee; altho the caſe bee not to
you altogether ſo hopeleſſe: for, now
I may heare of you, viſit you, renue
my holy counſels, and bee mutually
comforted from you; there, none of
theſe. Hee, that will once tranſpoſe
mee from earth to heauen, hath now
choſen to tranſpoſe mee from one
peece of earth to another: what is
heere worthy of your ſorrow, worthy
of complaint? That ſhould bee for
my owne good: this ſhall bee for the
good of many. If your experience
haue taught you, that my labours doe
promiſe profit; obtaine of your ſelfe
to deny your ſelfe ſo much, as to reioyce
that the loſſe of a fewe ſhould
bee the aduantage of many ſoules.
Tho, why do I ſpeake of loſſe? I ſpeak
that, as your feare, not my owne: and
your affection cauſes that feare, rather
then the occaſion.
               
                  
The God of the harueſt ſhal ſend
you a Laborer, more able, as carefull:
That is my prayer, and hope, and
ſhall bee my ioy. I dare not leaue,
but in this expectation, this aſſurāce.
What-euer become of me, it ſhall be
my greateſt comfort to hear you cō
                  mend
your change; and to ſee your
happy progreſs in thoſe wayes I haue
both ſhewed you, and beaten. So ſhal
wee meete in the ende, and neuer
part.
            
            
               
               
               Written to Mr. I. B. and Dedicated
to my father, Mr. I. HALL.
               EP. 10. Against the feare of Death.
               
                  YOu complaine, that you
feare Deathe: Hee is no
man, that doth not. Beſides
the paine, Nature ſhrinkes
at the thought of parting. If you
would learne the remedie, knowe
the cauſe; For that ſhee is ignorant▪ &amp;
faithleſſe. She would not be cowardly,

if ſhee were nor fooliſh. Our feare is
from doubt, and our doubt from vnbeliefe:
and whence is our vnbeleefe,
but chiefly from ignorance? Shee
knowes not what good is elſe-where:
ſhee beleeues not her part in it. Get
once true knowledge and true faith,
your feare ſhall vaniſh alone. Aſſurance
of heauenly things, makes vs
willing to part with earthly. He cannot
contemne this life, that knowes
not the other. If you would deſpiſe
earth therefore, thinke of heauen. If
you would haue death eaſie, thinke
of that glorious life that followes it.
Certainely if we can indure paine, for
health; much more ſhall we abide a
fewe pangs, for glorie. Thinke how
fondly wee feare a vanquiſht enemy.
Lo, Chriſt hath triumpht ouer Death:
hee bleedeth and gaſpeth vnder vs;
and yet we tremble. It is enough to

vs, that Chriſt died: Neither would
he haue died, but that we might die
with ſafetie, and pleaſure.
               Thinke, that death is neceſſarily
annexed to nature: Wee are for a
time on condition that wee ſhall not
be; wee receiue life, but vppon the
tearmes of redeliucrie. Neceſsitie
makes ſomethings eaſie; as it vſually
makes eaſie things difficult. It is a
fond iniuſtice to embrace the couenant,
and ſhrinke at the condition.
               Thinke, there is but one common
rode to all fleſh: There are no by-paths
of any fairer, or neerer way;
no, not for Princes. Euen companie
abateth miſeries: and the commonneſſe
of an euill makes it leſſe fearefull.
What worlds of men are gone
before vs; yea, how many thouſāds
out of one field? How many crownes
and ſcepters ly piled vp at the gates

of death, which their owners haue
left there, as ſpoyles to the Conqueror?
Haue wee beene at ſo many
graues, &amp; ſo oft ſeene our ſelues die
in our friends; and do wee ſhrinke
when our courſe commeth? Imagine
you alone were exempted from the
common law of mankinde, or were
condemned to Methuſalahs age; aſſure
your ſelfe death is not now ſo
fearefull, as your life would then bee
weariſome.
               Thinke not ſo much what Death
is, as from whom hee comes, and
for what. Wee receiue euen homely
meſſengers from great perſons;
not without reſpect to their maiſters:
And what matters it who hee bee, ſo
hee bring vs good newes? what newes
can bee better then this. That God
ſends for you, to take poſſeſſion of a
kingdome? Let them feare death,

which knowe him but as a purſuiuant
ſent from hell; whome their conſcience
accuſes of a life wilfully filthy;
and bindes-ouer ſecretly to
condemnation: Wee knowe whither
wee are going, and whom wee
haue beleeued; Let vs paſſe on
cheerefully▪ through theſe blacke
gates, vnto our glory.
               Laſtly, knowe that our improuidence
only addes terrour vnto
death. Thinke of death, and you
ſhall not feare it. Do you not ſee,
that euen Beares, and Tigres,
ſeeme not terrible to thoſe that
liue with them? Howe haue wee
ſeene their keepers ſport with them,
when the beholders durſt ſcarce
truſt their chaine? Bee acquainted
with Death; though hee looke
grimme vppon you, at the firſt,
you ſhall finde him, yea, you ſhall

make him a good companion. Familiaritie
cannot ſtand with feare. Theſe
are receites enow. Too much ſtore
doth rather ouerwhelme then ſatiſfie.
Take but theſe, and I dare promiſe
you ſecuritie.
               FINIS.
            
         
         
            
            The ſecond Decade
of Epiſtles.
            
               
               
               To Sr. ROBERT DARCY.
               EP. 1. The eſtate of a true, but weake Chriſtian.
               
                  IF you aske how I fare:
Sometimes, no man better;
and, if the fault were
not my owne, Alwayes.
Not that I can commaund health, &amp;
bid the world ſmile when I li
                     •
                  t. How
poſsible is it for a man to bee happie
without theſe; yea in ſpight
of them? Theſe thinges canne

neither augment, nor empaire thoſe
comforts, that come from aboue.
What vſe, what ſight is ther of the
ſtarres, when the ſunneſhines? Then
onely can I finde my ſelf happy, when
(ouer-looking theſe earthly things) I
can fetch my ioy from heauen. I tell
him that knowes it, the contentments
that earth can afford her beſt Fauourites,
are weake, imperfect, changeable,
momentary; and ſuch, as euer
end in complaint. Wee ſorrow that
wee had them; and, while wee haue
them, we dare not truſt them: Thoſe
from aboue are full, and conſtant.
What an heauen do I feele in my ſelf,
when (after many trauerſes of meditation)
I finde, in my heart, a feeling
poſſeſſion of my God! When I can
walke, and conuerſe with the God of
heauen, not without an openneſſe of
heart, and familiarity: When my ſoule

hath caught faſt and ſenſible hold of
my Saviour; and either pulls him
down to it ſelfe, or rather lifts vp it
ſelfe to him; and can and dare ſecretly
auouch, I knowe whom I haue beleeued:
When I can looke vpon all
this inferiour creation, with the eyes
of a ſtranger, &amp; am trāſported to my
home in my thoughts; ſolacing my
ſelfe in the view and meditation of
my future glory, and that preſent
of the Saints: When I ſee wherefore
I was made, and my conſcience tells
mee I haue done that for which I
came; done it, not ſo as I canne
boaſt, but ſo as it is accepted;
while my weakeneſſes are pardoned,
and my actes meaſured by my deſires,
and my deſires by their ſinceritie;
Laſtly, when I can finde my ſelfe
(vpon holy reſolution) made firme
&amp; ſquare, fit to entertaine all euents;

the good with moderate regard, the
euill with courage and patience, both
with thanks; ſtrongly ſettled to good
purpoſes, conſtant and cheerefull in
deuotion; and, in a word, ready for
God, yea full of God. Sometimes
I can be thus, and pity the poore and
miſerable proſperity of the godleſſe;
and laugh at their moneths of vanitie,
and ſorrow at my owne: But
then againe (for why ſhould I ſhame
to confeſſe it?) the world thruſts it
ſelfe betwixt me and heauen; and, by
his darke and indigeſted parts, eclipſeth
that light which ſhined to my
ſoule. Now, a ſenſeleſſe dulneſſe ouer-takes
mee, and beſots mee; my
luſt to deuotion is little, my ioy none
at all: Gods face is hid, and I am troubled.
Then I begin to compare my
ſelfe with others, and thinke, Are all

men thus blockiſh and earthen? or,
am I alone worſe then the reſt,
and ſingular in my wretchedneſſe?
Nowe I carie my carcaſſe vp and
downe careleſly, and (as dead
bodies are rubbed, without heate)
I doe in vaine force vpon my ſelfe
delights, which others laugh at:
I endeuour my wonted worke, but
without an heart; there is nothing
is not tedious to mee, no not my
ſelfe.
               Thus I am, till I ſingle my ſelfe
out alone, to him that alone canne
reuiue mee: I reaſon with my ſelfe,
&amp; confer with him; I chide my ſelfe,
and intreat him: and, after ſome
ſpirituall ſpeeches interchanged, I
renue my familiaritie vvith him; and
he the tokens of his loue to me. Lo,
then I liue againe, and applaud my
ſelfe in this happineſſe, and wiſh it

might euer continue, and think baſely
of the world in compariſon of it.
Thus I hold on, riſing and falling; neither
knowe, whether I ſhould more
praiſe God for thus much fruition of
him, or blame my ſelfe for my inconſtancie
in good; more reioice, that
ſometimes I am well, or grieue that
I am not ſo alwaies. I ſtriue, and wiſh,
rather then hope, for better. This is
our warfare; we may not looke to triumph
alwaies: wee muſt ſmart ſometimes,
&amp; complaine; and then againe
reioyce that we can complaine; and
grieue that we can reioyce no more,
and that we can grieue more, Our
hope is, If wee be patient, wee ſhall
once be conſtant.
            
            
               
               To Sr. EDMVND BACON.
               EP. 2. Of the benefit of Retiredneſſe, and
ſecrecie.
               
                  SVſpect (if you can) that, becauſe
now many cold winds
blowe betwixt vs, my affection
can be cooler to you.
True loue is like a ſtrong ſtreame,
which the further it is from the head,
runnes with more violence. The
thoughts of thoſe pleaſures I was
wont to finde in your preſence, were
neuer ſo delightful, as now when I am

barred from renuing them. I wiſh
me with you; yea (if I could or might
wiſh to change) I ſhould wiſh mee
your ſelfe. To liue hidden, was neuer
but ſafe, and pleaſant; but now, ſo
much better, as the world is worſe.
It is an happineſſe, not to bee a witneſſe
of the miſchiefe of the times;
which it is hard to ſee, and bee guiltleſſe.
Your Philoſophical Cell is a ſafe
ſhelter from tumults, from vices, frō
diſcontentments. Beſides that liuely,
honeſt, and manly pleaſure, which ariſes
from the gaine of Knowledge in
the deepe myſteries of Nature; How
eaſie is it, in that place to liue free
from the common cares, from the
infection of common euils. Whether
the Spaniard gaine or ſaue by his
peace, and how hee keepes it; and
whether it were ſafer for the States
to lay downe armes, and bee at once

ſtill and free; Whether the Emperours
truce, with the Turke, were honourable
and ſeaſonable; or whether
Venice haue wonne or loſt by her
late iarres; are thoughts that dare
not looke-in at thoſe doores. Who is
enuied, and who pittied at Court;
Who buyes hopes, and kindeneſſe
deareſt; who layes ſecret mines to
blowe vp another, that himſelfe may
ſucceede, can neuer trouble you:
Theſe cares dare not enter into that
Sanctuarie of Peace. Thence you
cā ſee how all, that liue publique, are
toſſed in theſe waues, and pitty them.
For, great places haue ſeldome ſafe
and eaſie entrances: and (which is
worſt) great charges can hardly bee
plauſibly wielded, without ſom indirect
policies. Alas! their priuiledges
cannot counteruaile their toile.
Wearie dayes, and reſtleſſe nights,

ſhort liues and long cares, weake bodies,
&amp; vnquiet mindes attend lightly
on greatneſs. Either Clients break
their ſleepe in the morning, or the intention
of their minde driues it off
from the firſt watch: Either ſutes or
complaints thruſt themſelues into
their recreations; and Packets of
Letters interrupt their meales. It is
euer Terme with them, without Vacation.
Their buſineſſes admit of no
night, no holiday: Lo, your priuacie
frees you from all this, and what-euer
other glorious miſerie. There you
may ſleepe, and eate, and honeſtly
diſport, and enioy your ſelfe, and cō
                  maund
both your ſelfe and others.
And, whiles you are happy, you liue
out of the reach of Enuie; vnleſſe my
praiſes ſend that gueſt thither: which
I ſhould iuſtly condemne as the fault
of my loue. No man offers to vndermine

you, none to diſgrace you: you
could not want theſe incōueniences
abroad. Yea, let a mā liue in the open
world, but as a looker on, hee ſhall be
ſure not to want abundance of vexations.
An ill minde holds it an eaſie
torment, to liue in continuall ſight of
euill; if not rather a pleaſure: but, to
the well diſpoſed, it is next to hell.
Certainly, to liue among Toades &amp;
Serpents, is a Paradiſe to this. One
ieſts pleaſantly with his Maker: another
makes himſelf ſport with Scripture.
One fills his mouth with oathes
of ſound: another ſcoffes at the religious.
One ſpeakes villany; another
laughes at it; a third defends it. One
makes himſelf a Swine; another a Diuell:
Who (that is not all earth) can
endure this? who cannot wiſh himſelf
rather a deſolate Hermite, or a cloſe
priſoner? Euery euill we ſee, doth either

vexe, or infect vs. Your retiredneſſe
auoids this; yet ſo, as it equally
eſcapes all the euills of Solitarineſſe.
You are full of friends; whoſe ſociety,
intermixed with your cloſenes, makes
you to want little of publique. The
Deſert is too wilde, the City too populous:
the Country is only fit for reſt.
I knowe, there want not ſom obſcure
corners, ſo haunted with dulneſs, that
as they yield no outward vnquietnes,
ſo no inward cōtentment. Yours
is none of thoſe; but ſuch as ſtriues rather,
with the pleaſure of it, to require
the ſolitarineſſe. The Court is for honour,
the City for gain, the Country
for quietneſſe; A bleſsing, that neede
not (in the iudgement of the wiſeſt)
yield to the other two. Yea, how many
haue we knowen, that hauing nothing
but a cote of thatch to hide thē
frō heauen, yet haue pittied the carefull

pomp of the mighty? How much
more may thoſe which haue full
hands, and quiet hearts, pitty them
both? I do not ſo much praiſe you in
this, as wonder at you. I know many
vpon whom the conſcience of their
wants, forces a neceſſary obſcurity;
who if they can ſteale a vertue out of
neceſsity, it is well: but, I no where
knowe ſo excellent parts ſhrouded
in ſuch willing ſecrecie. The worlde
knowes you, and wants you; and yet
you are volūtarily hid. Loue your ſelf
ſtil; &amp; make much of this ſhadow, vntill
our cōmon mother call you forth
to her neceſſary ſeruice, &amp; charge you
to neglect your ſelfe, to pleaſure her.
Which once don; you know where to
finde Peace. Whether others applaud
you, I am ſure you ſhall your ſelf: and
I ſhall ſtill magnifie you, and (what I
can) imitate you.
            
            
               
               
               TO Mr. IOHN WHITING.
               EP. 3. An Apologeticall diſcourſe of the Mariage
of Eccleſiaſticall perſons.
               
                  I Knowe not, whether this
quarrell bee worthy of an
anſwer, or rather of a ſilent
ſcorne; or if an anſwere,
whether merry or ſerious. I doe not
willingly ſuffer my penne to wade
into queſtions: Yet, this argument
ſeemes ſhallowe enough for an Epiſtle.
If I free not this Truth, let

me be puniſhed with a diuorce. Som
idle table-talk cals vs to plead for our
wiues. Perhaps ſom gallants grudge vs
one, who can be cōtent to allow thē
                  ſelues
more. If they thought vviues
curſes, they would afford thē vs. Our
mariage is cenſured (I ſpeak boldly)
of none but them, which neuer knew
to liue chaſtly in mariage; who neuer
knew Gratians true diſtinction of
Virginitie.
                  
                     
                        virg.

                              Carnis,
                              Mētis
                           
                        
                     
                   What care we for their cē
                  ſure,
Cauſ 35. q. 5. C. Tunc ſa
                        ••
                     bitur.where God approues? But ſome
perhaps maintain it,M
                        •
                     lier ſuam virginitatem bene ſecuat, ſi
                        ••
                     eo nubat vt filios pariat ad iuſtitiam. out of iudgemēt:
Bid them make much of that, which
Paul tells them, is a doctrine of Diuels.
Were it not for this opiniō, the church
of Rome would want one euidēt brād
of her Antichriſtianiſme. Let their
ſhauelings ſpeak for thēſelues; vpon
whom, their vnlawfull Vow hath forced
a wilfull &amp; impoſsible neceſsity.
I leaue them to ſcan the olde rule of

                  In turpi voto muta decretum;
                  Profitentur continentiā corporum, in incontinē tiam debacchantur animorum. De Rom. Cler. Saluianus. if they
had not rather, Cautè ſi non caſtè. Euen
moderate Papiſts will graunt vs
free, becauſe not bound by vow; no
not ſo farre as thoſe olde Germans,
pro poſſe et noſse. Or what care wee, if
they grant it not? while wee holde vs
firme to that ſure rule of Baſil the
great;Qui vetat quod Deus, praecepit. aut praecipit quod Deus vetuit, maledictus habeatur ab omnious qui amant Dominum. In Moralib. ſum. ca 14. 
                  He that forbids what God inioynes,
or inioynes what God forbids, let
him bee accurſed. I paſſe not what I
heare men, or Angels ſay, while I hear
God ſay, Let him be the husband of one
wife. That one word ſhal cōfirme me,
againſt the barking of all impure
mouths. He that made mariage, ſaies
it is honorable: what care wee for the
diſhonour of thoſe that corrupt it?
yea, that which Nature noteth with
ſhame, God mentions with honour,

                     Heb. 13. The Mariage Bed is honorable.
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ;Non quia peccatum ſit coniugibus commiſceri: hoc enim opus caſtum non habet culpā in coniuge, &amp;c. Gregory in Pſal. Poenit. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Socrat. hiſt. eccleſ. 
                  Greg. with the title of opus
caſtū; Paphnutius, of 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , chaſtity.

But, if God ſhould be iudge of this
controuerſie, it were ſoone at an end;
who, in the time euen of that legall
ſtrictneſſe, allowed wedlocke, to the
miniſters of his ſanctuarie. Let Cardinall
Panormitan be heard ſpeake.
Continentia non eſt in clericis ſecularibus de ſubſtantia ordinis, nec de iure diuino. 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  Continencie, ſaith he, in Clergie men
is neither of the ſubſtance of their order,
or appointed by any law of GOD.
And Gratian, out of Auguſtine, yet
more.
               
                  Copula ſaſacerdotalis nec legali, nec Euangeli
                        ••
                      nec Apoſtolica authoritate prohibetur. 26. q 2. c ſors. ex Aug. Their mariage, ſayth hee, is neither
forbidden by legall, nor Euangelicall,
nor Apoſtolike authoritie.
               God neuer impoſed this law of Cō
                  tinence: who then?Only ex ſtatuto Eccleſiae. Durand. 4. Diſt. 37. q 1. Tom. in 2. 2. q. 88. art. 11. The Church.
As if a good ſpouſe would gaineſay
what her husband willeth: But, how
well? Heare, O ye Papiſts, the iudgement
of your owne Cardinall; and
confeſſe your mouths ſtopped.Sed credo pro bono &amp; ſalute eſſe animarum (quod eſſet ſalubre ſtatutum) vt volentes poſſint contrahere; quia experientia docente, cō
                     trarius prorſus effectus ſequit
                        •
                     r ex illa lege cō
                     tinent ae; cū hodie non viuant ſpiritualiter nec ſint mundi, ſed maculā
                     tur illicito coitu cum eorum grauiſſimo peccato, vbi cū propriâ vxore eſſet caſtitas. Panormit. de Cler. Comug. cap. Cum olim. 
                  But
I beleeue (ſaith hee) it were for the

good and ſafetie of many ſoules, and
would be an whole ſome law, that thoſe
which would, might marrie; For that,
as experience teacheth vs, a contrarie
effect followes vpon that lawe of
Continencie; ſince at this day they liue
not ſpiritually, neither are cleane, but
are defiled with vnlawfull copulation,
to their great ſinne: whereas with
their owne wife it might bee chastitie.
Is this a Cardinall, thinke you, or an
Huguenot? But, if this red hat bee
not worthie of reſpect; Let a Pope
himſelf ſpeake out of Peters Chaire.
Pius the ſecond, as learned as hath
ſitte in that roome this thouſande
yeares;Sacerdotibus magna ratione ſublatas nuptias, maiore reſtituendas videri: In the record of Platina himſelfe In vita Pij. 2. 
                  Marriage ſayth hee, vpon
great reaſon was taken from the Clergie;
but, vpon greater reaſon is to
bee reſtored. What neede wee other
iudge? How iuſt this law is, you
ſee; ſee now how ancient: For, ſome

doctrines haue nothing to plead for
them, but Time. Age hath beene
an old refuge for Falſhood. Tertullians
rule is true; That, which is firſt,
is trueſt. What the auncient Iewiſh
Prelates did, Moſes is cleare: what did
the Apoſtles? Doth not
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , &amp;c. 1. Cor. 9. 5. &amp;c. 
                  Paul tell
vs that both the reſt of the Apoſtles,
and the brethren of the Lord, and
Cephas, had wiues, and (which is
more) carried them ſtill along in
their trauells? For that childiſh eluſion
of
                     Rhemiſts read it a woma
                        •
                      aſister. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , who canne abide,
but to laugh at? Doth not

                     Clemens, citatus etiam ab Euſeb. l. 3. c. 13▪ 
                     Petrum cum vxorem ſuā ad mortem ducicerneret hortatum &amp; conſolatum his verbis. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
                  Clemens of Alexandria (a father
not of more antiquitie, then credit)
tell vs, that Peter, Philip, and Paul
himſelfe, were maried? and this laſt
(tho vnlikeſt) how is it confirmed by
Ignatius, in his Epiſtle to the Philadelphians?
Yea, their owne Cardinall,
learnedIn illud. ad Philip. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . 
                  Caietane, doth both auouch

and euince it. This was their
practice: what was their Conſtitution?
Looke in theſe Canons,
which the Romiſh Church fathers
vpon the Apoſtles, and Franciſcus

                        •
                     urrian their leſuite ſweates to defend
it in a whole volume: There
you finde, Canon. 5. enacted that
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      (non eijciat) 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Can. Apoſt. 5. 
                  no
Biſhoppe, Presbyter, Deacon, ſhall forſake
his wife (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) in pretence
of religion, vpon paine of depoſition.
It would moue laughter, to
ſee how the Ieſuites gnaw vpon this
bone, and ſuck-in nothing but the
blood of their owne iawes;
                     Conſtant. 6 l. 3. Can. Quoniam. Canon Apoſtolicae 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Nos, ſequē
                     tes veterem Canonem Apoſtolicae 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , &amp; conſtitutiones ſacrorū virorum, legales suptias amodò valere volumus, &amp;c. while
the ſixt Generall Councell auerres
and proclaimes this ſenſe truely
Apoſtolicall, in ſpight of all contradiction.
               Follow the times now, and
deſcende lower; what did the
ages ſucceeding? Search recordes:

What-euer ſome palpably-foyſted
Epiſtles of Popes inſinuate; they
married, without ſcruple of any contrarie
iniunction. Many of thoſe ancients
admired virginitie; but, impoſed
it not. Amongſt the reſt,Qui a Chriſtianis parentibus enutriti ſūt, &amp;c. maximè ſi fuerint ex patribus ſacerdot
                        •
                     li ſede dignificatis. i. Epiſco patus, presbyteratus, aut diaconatus ne glorientur. Orig. Tract 8. in Matth▪
                   
                  Origen
(tho himſelfe a wilfull Eunuch)
is faine to perſwade the ſonnes of
Clergie men, not to bee proud of
their Parentage. After this, when the
fathers of the Nicene Councell went
about to enact a law of Continency,
Socrates the Hiſtorian expreſſes it
thus:Viſum erat Epiſcopis legē nouam introducere in Eccleſiam. Socr. l. 1. c. 8. 
                  It ſeemed good (ſayth hee) to
the Biſhoppes to bring in a new law into
the Church.
                  Signa per Paphnutium non m
                        •
                     nus quàm dudum per Apoſtolos ſiebant. Ruff. n. l. 1. c. 4. Pathnutium, miraculis &amp; pietate clarus, obtinuit in Nicena ſynodo habendum pro caſtitate cū propriavxore concubitum Socra. l. 
                        •
                     . c. 8 It was then newe, and
they but would haue brought it in;
therefore before it was not: where
we know how Paphnutius, himſelfe a
Virgin, famous for holineſſe, famous
for miracles; riſing (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) cryed
loud, that they ought not to lay

this (
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ) heauie yoke, vpon
men of the Church. His Arguments
wan aſſent. Hee ſpake and
preuailed. So this libertie was ſtill
continued and confirmed. If this
bee not plaine enough; HolyIn Epiſt. ad Dracont.
                   
                  Athanaſius,
a witneſſe paſt exception,
ſhall ſerue for a thouſand hiſtories
till his age.
               
                  Multi ex epiſcopis matrimonia nō inierūt; Monach
                        •
                      cōtrà parentes 
                        •
                     iberorū facti ſūt: quemad modū viciſſim Epiſcopos filiorum patres, &amp; Monachos generis poteſtatē nō quaeſiuiſſe animaduertas. Athana
                           •
                        . Epiſtola. ad Dracon
                           •
                        ium.
                   
                  Many Biſhoppes, ſayth hee haue
not married; and contrarily Monkes
haue beene fathers of children: as
contrarily, you ſee Biſhoppes the fathers
of children; and Monkes that
haue not ſought poſteritie. Would
you yet haue inſtances of the former,
and the next age? Here you
haue
                     Numidicus presbiter, qui vxorē concrematā &amp; adhae a rentem lateri laetus aſpexit. Cyprian. l. 4. Ep. 10. 
                  Numidicus the Martyr, a maried
Presbyter;Ex D
                           •
                        oniſio. Euſeb. l. 6. c. 41 
                  Cheremon of Nilus, a
married Biſhoppe;
                     Euſeb. l. 7. cap. 29. Euſeb. l. 8. c. 9. Gregorios verò apud Nazianzum oppidum in locum patris ſui epiſcopus ſubrogatus Ruffin. l. 2. c 9. 
                  Demetrianus Biſhop
of Antioch, whoſe ſonne Domnus
ſucceeded Paulus Samoſatenus;

Philo
                        •
                     omus and Phileas BB.
of the Thmuites; Gabinius brother
of Eutychianus BB. of Rome; The
father of Nazianzen, Baſil, and the
other
                     Gregor. Naſſen frater Baſilij, teſte Nicephoro, vxoratus, vxorem &amp; liberos habuit: ſed non propterea fuit inrebus et exercitijs diuinis inferior vel deterior. Sozom▪
                     
                   
                  Gregorie, Hilarius, and that
good Spiridion Biſhop of Cyprus,
of whom Sozomen giues ſo direct teſtimony.
To omit others▪ what ſhold
I ſpeake of many Biſhoppes of
Rome, whoſe ſonnes not ſpurious,
as now a-dayes, but (as Pope Vrban
himſelfe witneſſes)De legiti nis coniugiis nat. lawfully begot
in wedlocke, followed their fathers
in the Pontificall chaire.Cùm ergo ex ſacerdotibus nati in ſummos Pontifices legantur eſſe promoti, non ſunt intelligendi de fornicatione ſed de legitimis connubiis nati; quae ſacerdotibu
                        •
                      vbique ante prohibitionem licita erant, et in Orientali eccleſia vſque bodie eis licere probantur, Diſt. 56. Ceno
                           •
                        an.
                   The reaſon
whereof, that Pope himſelf ingenuouſly rendereth; for that mariage
was euery where lawfull to the Clergy,
before the prohibition (which muſt

needes bee late) and in the Eaſterne
Church to this day is allowed. What
need we more teſtimonies or more
exāples? What euerThe author of the Aeth
                        •
                     opick hiſtorie. 
                  Heliodorus, Biſhop
of Trica (a man fitter for a wanton
loue-ſtorie, then a Church controuerſie)
brought into the Church
of Theſſalia, Socrates thus flatly writes
of thoſe Biſhoppes of his time;Nam non pauci illorum, dū Epiſcopatū gerunt, etiā liberos ex vxore legitimâ procreant. Socrat. l. 5. cap. 21. 
                  For
many of them in the place and function
of Biſhops, beget children of their lawful
wiues. This was practiced: ſee what
was decreed in that ſixt general
                     The words of that Councel are thus truly tranſlated by Chemnitius; Quoniam in Romana eccleſia, loco canonis ſeu decieti, traditum eſſe cognouimus, vt ij qui digni habē di ſunt ordinatione diaconi vel pieſa byteri piofiteātur ſe deinceps cum vxoribus ſuis nō congreſſuros; nos ſequentes veterem canonem Apoſtolicae, ſincerae, exquiſitae &amp; ordinatae conſtitutionis, legitimas ſacrorū virorū cohabitationes coniugales etiā ex hodierno die in poſter
                        •
                      valere ratas &amp; firmas eſſe volumus; nullo modo eorū cum vxoribus propriis coniūctionē ſeu copulationē diſſoluentes. Ita
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ſi quis dignus inueniatur &amp;c. is minime prohibēdus eſt ad hūc gradū aſcēdere, ideo quòd eū legitimâ vxore cohabitet. Nec tēpore ordinationis ſuae ab eo poſtuletur, ſeu cogatur vt abſtinere velit aut debeat legitimo cōgreſſu cū propriâ vxore. Coū
                  cel
of Conſtantinople, to this purpoſe,
to the confuſion of all replyers. If any
Proteſtant Church in Chriſtendome
can make a more peremptory, more
full and abſolute, more cautelous decree

for the mariage of Eccleſiaſtical
perſons, let mee bee condemned as
faithleſſe: A place, I grant, miſerably
handled by our aduerſaries; and becauſe
they cannot blemiſh it enough,
indignely torne out of the Councels.
What dare not impudency doe? Againſt
all evidences of Greeke Copies,Citat a Nilo Theſalonicenſi.
againſt their owne Gratian, againſt
pleas of antiquity. This is the
readieſt way; Whom they cannot anſwer,
to burn; what they cannot ſhift
off, to blot out; and to cut the knot,
which they cannot vntie. The Romaniſts
of the next age were ſomewhat
more equall: who, ſeeing themſelues
preſſed with ſo flat a decree,
confirmed by authoritie of Emperours,
as would abide no deniall, began
to diſtinguiſh vpon the point; limiting
this libertie onely to the Eaſterne
Church, and granting that all

the Clergy of the Eaſt might marry,
not theirs. So Pope Steuen the ſecond
freely confeſſes:Aliter ſe Orientaliū habet traditio Eccleſiarū: aliter huius ſanctae Romanae Eccleſiae. Nam eorum ſace
                        •
                     dotes, diaconi, 
                        •
                     ut ſubdiacont. matrimonio copulantur: Iſtius autem eccleſiae vel occidentaliū nullus ſacerdotum, a ſubdiacono vſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ad epiſcopum, licentiam habet coniugiun ſortiendi. diſ. 31 
                  The tradition (ſaith
hee) of the Eaſterne Churches is otherwiſe,
then that of the Roman Church.
For, their Prieſts, Deacons, or Subdeacons
are maryed; but, in this Church,
or the Weſtern, no one of the Clergie, frō
the Subdeacon to the Biſhop, hath leaue
to mary.
               
               Liberally; but not enough: and if
he yield this, why not more? ſhall that
bee lawefull in the Eaſt, which in the
Weſt is not? Do the Goſpels or laws
of equity alter according to the foure
corners of the world? doth God make
differēce betwixt Greece &amp; Englād? If
it be lawefull, why not every where?
if vnlawful, why is it done any where?
So then you ſee, we differ not from
the Church in this; but from the Romiſh
Church: But this ſacred councel

doth not only vniuerſally approue
this practice (with paine of depoſition
to the gainſayers) but auouches it
for a decree Apoſtolical. Iudge now,
whether this one authority be not enough
to weigh down an hundred pety
Conuenticles, and many legions
(if ther had beene many) of priuate
cōtradictions. Thus, for ſeauen hundred
yeares, you finde nothing but
open freedom: All the ſcuffling aroſe
in the eight age; wherein yet this violent
impoſition found many &amp; learned
aduerſaries, &amp; durſt not be obtruded
at once. Lo, euē then, Gregorie the
third, writing to the BBs. of Bauaria,
giues this diſiunct charge;Nemo ſcor ta aut concubinam alat: ſed aut caſtē viuat, aut vxorem ducat; quā repudiare fas non eſto. 
                  Let none
keep an harlot or a cōcubine: but either
let him liue chaſtly, or marrie a wife;
whom it ſhall not be lawfull for him to
forſake: According to that rule of
Clerks cited fromDiſt. 23. 
                  Iſidore, and renued

in theAnno. 813 Councell of Mentz, to the
perpetual ſhame of our iuggling aduerſaries.
Nothing can argue guiltines
ſo much, as vniuſt expurgations.
Clerici caſtimoniā inuiolati corporisperpetuò conſeruare ſtudeant; aut certè vnius matrimonij vinculo foederentur. Iſid. reg. cleric.
                  Iſidore ſayth, Let them containe, or let
them marie but one: They cite him, Let
them containe; and leaue out the reſt:
ſomewhat worſe thē the Diuell cited
ſcripture. But, I might haue ſpared al
this labor of writing, could I perſwade
whoſoeuer either doubts, or denies
this, to reade-ouer that one Epiſtle
whichWhether Huldericus or (as hee is ſomwhere intitled) Voluſianus, I inquire not: the matter admits of no doubt. Huldericus Epiſcopus Auguſtae. Anno. 860. Aeneas Sylu. in ſuā Germ. Hedion. Eccl. hiſt. l. 8. c. 2. Fox, in Act. &amp; Monum. hath it fully tranſlated.
                   
                  Huldericus BB. of Auſpurge
wrote learnedly, and vehemently, to
Pope Nicolas the firſt, in this ſubiect:
which if it do not anſwer all cauils, &amp;
ſatisfie all Readers, and conuince all
(not wilfull) aduerſaries, let mee bee
caſt, in ſo iuſt a cauſe. There you ſhal
ſee, how iuſt, how expedient, how ancient
this liberty is; together with the
feeble and iniurious grounds of forced

continencie: Reade it, and ſee
whether you can deſire a better aduocate.
After him (ſo ſtrongly did he
plead, &amp; ſo happily) for two hundred
years more, this freedom ſtil bleſſed
thoſe parts; yet, not without extreme
oppoſition. Hiſtories are witneſſes of
the buſie, &amp; not vnlearned cōbats of
thoſe times, in this argument. But
now, when the body of Antichriſtianiſme
began to be complete, and to
ſtand vp in his abſolute ſhape, after a
thouſand yeares from Chriſt; this libertie,
which before wauered vnder
Nicolas 1. now by the hands of Leo 9.
Nicolas 2. and that brand of hell,
Gregorie 7. was vtterly ruined, wiues
debarred, ſingle life vrged:
                     Auentinus l. 5. Gratū ſcortatoribus, quibus pro vna vxore ſex centas iā malierculas 
                        ••
                     re l
                        •
                     cebat. A good
turne for whoremaiſters (ſaith Auentine)
who now for one wife might
haue ſix hundred Bed-fellowes.
               But, how approued of the better

ſort appeares (beſides that the Churches
did ring of him, ech-where, for
Antichriſt) in that at theAnno. 1076. Councell
of Wormes the French and German
BB• depoſed this Gregorie, in this
name (amongſt other quarells) for
Maritos ab vxoribus ſeparat.ſeparating man and wife. Violence
did this; not reaſō: neither was Gods
will here queſtioned; but, the Popes
wilfulneſſe. What broyles hereon inſued,
letEx Interdicto ſacerdotum coniugio, grauiſſiam ſeditio gregem Chriſti perculit: nec vrquam talis lues populum Chriſti afflixit. Auent. l. 5. Henric. Huntingdon. de Anſelmo. l 7. de An. 1100 in ſynodo Londinenſi: Prohibu
                        ••
                      ſacerdotibus vxores, antè non prohibitas: Anſelm. (ſaith that Hiſtorian) was the firſt that forbad mariage to the Clergie of England (and this was, about the yeare of our Lord, 1080) Till then euer free. Item Fabianus Liberos aijt fu
                           •
                        ſſe ſacerdotes per annos 1080. 
                  
                     
                        •
                     uentine witneſſe.
               The bickeringes of our Engliſh
Clergie, with their Dunſtanes, about
this time, are memorable in our
owne Hiſt. which teach vs how late,
how repiningly, how vniuſtly, they
ſtooped vnder this yoke. I had rather
ſend my Reader to Bale and Fox, thē
abbridge their monumēts, to enlarge
my owne.
               
                  
I haue (I hope) fetcht this truth
farre enough; and deduced it lowe
enough, through many ages, to the
midſt of the rage of Antichriſtian tyrannie.
There left our libertie; there
began their bondage. Our libertie
is happily renued with the Goſpell:
what God, what his Church hath
euer allowed, we do inioy. Wherein
wee are not alone: The Greeke
Church, as large for extent as the
Roman (and, in ſome parts of it, better
for their ſoundneſſe) do thus;
and thus haue euer done.
               Let Papiſts and Atheiſts ſay what
they will; It is ſafe erring with GOD
and his purer Church.
            
            
               
               To my Siſter, Mrs. B. BRINSLY.
               EP. 4. Of the Sorrow not to be repented
of.
               
                  IT is ſeldome ſeene, that a
ſilent griefe ſpeedes well:
for, either a mā muſt haue
ſtrong hands of reſolution
to ſtrangle it in his boſome;
or elſe it driues him to ſome
ſecret miſchiefe: whereas ſorrow reuealed,
is halfe remedied, and euer abates
in the vttering. Your griefe was
wiſely diſcloſed; and ſhall bee as

ſtrangely anſwered. I am glad of your
ſorrow; and ſhould weepe for you, if
you did not thus mourne. Your ſorrow
is, that you cānot enough grieue
for your ſinnes. Let me tell you, that
the Angells themſelues ſing at this
lamentation; neither doth the earth
afford any ſo ſweete muſicke in the
eares of God. This heauineſſe is the
way to ioy. Worldly ſorow is worthy
of pitie, becauſe it leadeth to death:
But, this deſerues nothing but enuie
and gratulation. If thoſe teares were
common, hell would not ſo enlarge
it ſelfe. Neuer ſinne, repented of, was
puniſhed: and neuer any thus mourned,
and repented not. Lo, you haue
done that, which you grieue you
haue not done. That good GOD,
whoſe act is his will, accounts of our
wil as our deed. If he required ſorrow
proportionable to the hainouſneſſe

of our ſinnes, there were no end of
mourning. Now, his mercy regards
not ſo much the meaſure, as
the truth of it; &amp; accounts vs to haue
that which we complaine to want. I
neuer knew any truly penitent, which
in the depth of his remorſe, was afraid
of ſorowing too much; nor any vnrepentant,
which wiſht to ſorrow more.
Yea, let me tell you, that this ſorrow
is better, and more, then that deep
heauineſſe for ſin, which you deſire.
Many haue beene vexed with an extreame
remorſe for ſom ſin, from the
gripes of a galled cōſcience, which yet
never cam wher true repētance grew;
in whō the cōſciēce plaies at once the
accuſer, witnes, Iudge, tormētor: But,
an earneſt grief, for the want of grief,
was neuer found in any but a gratious
heart. You are happy, &amp; complaine.
Tell me, I beſeech you; This ſorrow

which you mourne to want, is it a
grace of the ſpirit of God, or not? If
not, why do you ſorrow to want it? If
it be, oh how happy it is to grieue for
wāt of grace! The God of all truth &amp;
bleſſednes hath ſaid, Bleſſed are thoſe
that hunger and thirst after righteouſneſſe;
and, with the ſame breath, Bleſſed
are they that mourne: for, they ſhall
be comforted. You ſay, you mourne;
Chriſt ſaith, you are bleſſed: you ſay
you mourne; Chriſt ſaith, you ſhall
bee comforted. Either now diſtruſt
your Sauiour, or elſe confeſſe your
happineſſe, and with patience expect
his promiſed conſolation. What do
you feare? you ſee others ſtand like
ſtrong Oakes, vnſhaken, vnremoued:
you are but a reed, a feeble plant, toſſed
&amp; bowed with euery winde, and
with much agitation bruſed: Lo, you
are in tender and fauourable hands,

that neuer brake any, whom their ſins
bruiſed; neuer bruiſed any whom
temptations haue bowed. You are
but flax; and your beſt is not a flame,
but an obſcure ſmoke of grace: Lo,
here his ſpirit is as a ſoft winde, not
as cold water; he will kindle, will neuer
quench you. The ſorrow you
want, is his gift: Take heede leaſt
while you vex your ſelfe with diſlike
of the meaſure, you grudge at the giuer.
Beggers may not chooſe. This
portion hee hath vouchſafed to giue
you, if you haue any, it is more then
he was bound to beſtow: yet you ſay,
What, no more? As if you tooke it
vnkindely, that he is no more liberal.
Euen theſe holy diſcontentments are
dangerous. Deſire more (ſo much as
you can) but repine not, when you
do not attain. Deſire; but ſo as you be
free from impatience, free from vnthankfulnes.

Thoſe, that haue tried,
cā ſay how difficult it is to complain,
with due reſeruation of thanks. Neither
know I whether is worſe, to long
for good things impatiently, or not
at all to deſire them. The fault of
your ſorrow, is rather in your conceit,
then in it ſelf. And, if indeed you
mourne not enough, ſtay but Gods
leiſure, and your eyes ſhall run ouer
with teares. How many doe you ſee
ſport with their ſinnes, yea bragge of
them? How many that ſhould die for
want of paſtime, if they might not ſin
freely, and more freely talke of it?
What a Saint are you to theſe, that
can droup vnder the memory of the
frailty of youth, and neuer think you
haue ſpent enow teares! Yet ſo I encourage
you in what you haue, as
one that perſwades you not to deſiſt
from ſuing for more. It is good to be

couetous of grace, and to haue our
deſires heerein enlarged with our receits.
Weepe ſtill, and ſtill deſire to
weepe: but, let your teares be as the
raine in a ſun-ſhine; comfortable and
hopefull: and let not your longing,
ſauour of murmur, or diſtruſt. Theſe
teares are reſerued; this hunger ſhall
be ſatisfied; this ſorrow ſhall be cō
                  forted:
There is nothing betwixt
God and you, but time. Preſcribe
not to his wiſedome: haſten not his
mercy. His grace is enough for you:
his glory ſhall bee more then enough.
            
            
               
               
               To Mr. HVGH CHOLMLEY.
               EP. 5. Concerning the Metaphraſe of the
Pſalmes.
               
                  FEare not my immoderate
ſtudies. I haue a body that
controlls mee enough in
theſe courſes; my friends
neede not. There is nothing whereof
I cold ſooner ſurfet, if I durſt neglect
my body to ſatisfie my minde:
But, vvhiles I affect knowledge,
my weakeneſſe checks me and ſaies,
Better a little learning then no health.
I yield, and patiently abide my ſelfe

debarred of my choſen felicity. The
little I can get, I am no niggard of:
neither am I more deſirous to gather,
then willing to impart. The full
handed, are cōmonly moſt ſparing.
VVee veſſels, that haue any emptie
roome, anſwer the leaſt knock with a
hollow noiſe: you, that are full, ſound
not. If we pardon your cloſeneſs, you
may well beare with our profuſion: If
there be any wrong, it is to our ſelues,
that we vtter what we ſhould lay vp.
It is a pardonable fault to do leſs good
to our ſelues, that we may doe more
to others. Amongſt other indeuors,
I haue boldly vndertaken the holy
meeters of Dauid; how happily, iudge
you by what you ſee. Ther is none of
all my labors ſo open to all cenſures;
none, wherof I wold ſo willingly hear
the verdit of the wiſe, and iudicious.
Perhaps, ſome think the verſe harſh;

whoſe nice eare regards roundneſſe,
more then ſenſe: I embrace ſmoothneſſe,
but affect it not. This is the
leaſt good quality of a verſe; that intends
any thing but muſicall delight.
Others may blame the difficulty of
the tunes: whoſe humour cannot be
pleaſed without a greater offence.
For, to ſay truth, I neuer could ſee
good verſe written in the wonted
meaſures. I euer thought them moſt
eaſie, and leaſt Poeticall. This fault (if
any) will light vpon the negligence
of our people; which endure not to
take paines for any fit variety: The
French &amp; Dutch haue giuen vs worthy
examples of diligence, &amp; exquiſiteneſſe
in this kinde. Neither our
eares, nor voices are leſſe tunable.
Heere is nothing wanting, but will to
learne. What is this but to eate the
corne out of the eare, becauſe we wil

not abide the labour to grinde, and
knead it? If the queſtion be, whether
our verſe muſt deſcēd to thē, or they
aſcend to it; a wiſe moderatiō I think
would determine it moſt equall, that
each part ſhould remit ſomwhat, and
both meet in the midſt. Thus I haue
endeuored to do, with ſincere intent
of their good, rather then my own applauſe.
For, it had been eaſie to haue
reached to an higher ſtraine: but I
durſt not; whether for the graue
Maieſtie of the Subiect, or benefit
of the ſimpleſt Reader. You ſhall
ſtill note, that I haue laboured to
keepe Dauids entire ſenſe, with numbers
neither lofty, nor ſlubbred:
which meane is ſo much more difficult
to finde, as the buſineſſe is more
ſacred; and the liberty leſſe. Manie
great wits haue vndertaken this
taske; which yet haue either not effected

it, or haue ſmothered it in their
priuate desks, and denied it the common
light. Amongſt the reſt, were
th
                     •
                  ſe two rare ſpirits of the Sidnyes;
to whom, Poëſie was as naturall as it
is affected of others: and our worthie
friend, Mr. Syluester, hath ſhewed
mee, how happily he hath ſometimes
turned from his Bartas, to
the ſweete Singer of Iſrael. It could
not bee, that in ſuch aboundant
plentie of Poëſie, this worke ſhould
haue paſt vnattempted: would God
I might liue to ſee it perfected, either
by my owne hand, or a better.
In the mean time, let me expect your
vnpartial ſentence, both concerning
the forme, and ſenſe. Lay aſide your
loue, for a while; which too oft blinds
iudgement. And as it vſes to be done
in moſt equal proceedings of Iuſtice,
ſhut me out of doores, while my verſe

is diſcuſſed: yea, let mee receiue not
your cenſure onely, but others by
you: this once (as you loue me) play
both the Informer and the Judge.
Whether you allow it, you ſhall encourage
me; or correct, you ſhall amend
me:
                     
                        Aſteriſcus.
                        Veru.
                     
                   Either your ſtarres or your
ſpits (that I may vſe Origens notes)
ſhall be welcome to my margent. It
ſhall bee happy for vs, if God ſhall
make our poore labours any way ſeruiceable
to his Name, &amp; Church.
            
            
               
               To Mr. SAMVEL SOTHEBY.
               EP. 6. A Preface to his Relation of the Ruſſian
affaires.
               
                  TRauell perfiteth wiſedome;
and obſeruation giues perfection
to trauell: without
which, a man may pleaſe his eyes,
not feede his braine; and, after much
earth meaſured, ſhall returne with a
wearie body, and an empty minde.
Home is more ſafe, more pleaſant;
but leſſe fruitfull of experience: But,
to a minde not working and diſcurſiue,

all heauens, all earths are alike.
And, as the end of trauell is obſeruation;
ſo, the end of obſeruation is the
informing of others: for, what is our
knowledge if ſmothered in our ſelues,
ſo as it is not knowen to more? Such
ſecret delight can content none but
an enuious nature. You haue breathed
many &amp; cold ayres, gone farre,
ſeen much, heard more, obſerued all.
Theſe two yeares you haue ſpent in
imitation of Nebuchadnezars ſeuen;
cōuerſing with ſuch creatures as Paul
fought with, at Epheſus. Alas! what a
face, yea what a backe of a Church
haue you ſeene? what manners? what
people? Amōgſt whō, ignorant ſuperſtitiō
ſtriues with cloſe Atheiſme, trechery
with cruelty, one Diuel with another;
while Truth &amp; Vertue do not
ſo much as giue any chalenge of reſiſtāce.
Returning once to our England
after this experience, I imagine you

doubted whether you were on earth,
or in heauē. Now thē (if you wil heare
me, whō you were wont) as you haue
obſerued what you haue ſeen, &amp; writtē
what you haue obſerued; ſo, publiſh
what you haue writtē: It ſhal be a
grateful labor, to vs, to poſterity. I
am deceiued, if the ficklenes of the
Ruſsian ſtate, haue not yielded more
memorable matter of hiſtory thē any
other in our age, or perhaps many
centuries of our predeceſſors. How
ſhal I think, but that God ſēt you thither
before theſe broils, to be the witnes,
the regiſter of ſo famous mutations?
He loues to haue thoſe iuſt euils
which hee doth in one part of the
world, knowen to the whole; &amp; thoſe
euils, which men doe in the night of
their ſecrecie, brought forth into the
Theater of the world; that the euill
of mens ſinne being compared with
the euill of his puniſhmēt, may iuſtifie

his proceedings &amp; condemne theirs.
Your worke ſhall thus honour him;
beſides your ſecond ſeruice, in the
benefit of the Church. For, whiles
you diſcourſe of the open Tyranny
of that Ruſsian Nero, John Baſilius;
the more ſecret, no leſſe bloodie
plots of Boris; the ill ſucceſſe of a
ſtolne Crowne; tho ſet vpon the head
of an harmleſſe ſonne; the bolde attempts
and miſerable end of a falſe,
yet aſpiring chalenge; the perfidionſneſſe
of a ſeruile people, vnworthy
of better gouernours; the miſcariage
of wicked gouernours, vnworthy
of better ſubiects; the iniuſt vſurpations
of men, iuſt (tho late) reuenges
of God, cruelly rewarded with
bloud, wrong claimes with ouerthrowe,
trecherie with bondage; the
Reader, with ſome ſecret horror, ſhal
draw-in delight, and with delight inſtruction:

Neither knowe I any relation
whence he ſhall take out a more
eaſie leſſon of iuſtice, of loyaltie, of
thankfulneſſe.
               But, aboue all, let the world ſee &amp;
commiſerate the hard eſtate of that
worthie and noble Secretarie, Buchinski.
Poore gentleman! his diſtreſſe
recalles euer to my thoughts
Eſops Storke, taken amongſt the
Cranes: Hee now nouriſhes his
haire, vnder the diſpleaſure of a forraine
Prince; At once in durance, and
baniſhmēt. He ſerued an ill maſter;
but, with an honeſt heart, with cleane
hands. The maſters iniuſtice doth no
more infect a good ſeruant, then the
truth of the ſeruant can iuſtifie his ill
maſter. A bad workeman may vſe a
good inſtrument: and oft-times a
cleane napkin wipeth a foule mouth.
It ioyes me yet to think, that his pietie,

as it euer held friendſhip in heauen,
ſo now it wins him friends in this
our other world: Lo, euen from our
Iland inexpected deliuerance takes
a long flight, and bleſſeth him beyond
hope; yea rather, from heauen,
by vs. That GOD, whom hee
ſerues, will be knowen to thoſe rude
and ſcarce humane Chriſtians, for a
protector of innocence, a fauourer
of truth, a rewarder of Pietie. The
mercy of our gratious King, the cō
                  paſsion
of an honorable Councellor,
the loue of a true friend, and (which
wrought all, and ſet all on worke) the
grace of our good God, ſhal now looſe
thoſe bonds, and giue a glad welcome
to his libertie, and a willing farewel to
his diſtreſſe. Hee ſhall, I hope, liue
to acknowledge this; in the meane
time, I do for him. Thoſe Ruſsian affaires
are not more worthie of your

records, then your loue to this friend
is worthie of mine. For, neither cold
this large Sea drowne or quench it,
nor time and abſence (which are wont
to breed a lingring conſumption of
friendſhip) abate the heat of that affection,
which his kindneſſe bred, religion
nouriſhed. Both rareneſſe, and
worth ſhall commend this true loue;
which (to ſay true) hath beene now
long out of faſhiō. Neuer times yeilded
more loue; but, not more ſubtle.
For, euery man loues himſelfe in another,
loues the eſtate in the perſon:
Hope of aduantage is the loadſtone
that drawes the yrō harts of men; not
vertue, not deſert. No age afforded
more Paraſites, fewer friends: The
moſt are friendly in ſight, ſeruiceable
in expectation, hollow in loue, truſtleſſe
in experience. Yet now Buchinski,
ſee &amp; cōfeſſe thou haſt found one
friend, which hath made thee many:

on whome while thou beſtowedſt
much fauour, thou haſt loſt none. I
cannot but thinke how welcome, Libertie
(which tho late, yet now at laſt
hath lookt backe vpon him) ſhall bee
to the Cell of his affliction; whē, ſmiling
vpon him, ſhee ſhall lead him by
the hand, and (like another Angel) open
the yron gates of his miſerable
captiuitie, and (from thoſe hard Preſtaues
and ſauage Chriſtians) carry
him by the haire of the head, into this
paradiſe of God. In the meane time
I haue written to him as I could, in a
knowen language, with an vnknowen
hand; that my poor Letters of gratulation
might ſerue as humble attendants
to greater.
               For your work, I wiſh it but ſuch
glad intertainment, as the profit, yea
the delight of it deſerues; and feare
nothing, but that this long delay of

publicatiō will make it ſcarce newes:
Wee are all growen Athenians, and
account a ſtrange report like to a
fiſh, and a gueſt. Thoſe eyes and
hands ſtaid it, which might do it beſt.
I cannot blame you, if you thinke
it more honored by the ſtay of his
gratious peruſall, then it could be by
the early acceptatiō of the world. Euē
the caſt garments of Princes are pretious
Others haue in part preuented
you; whoſe labors, to yours, are but as
an Eccho to a long period: by whom,
we heare the laſt ſound of theſe ſtirs,
ignorant of the beginning. They
giue vs but a taſte in their hand: you
lead vs to the open fountaine. Let
the Reader giue you but as much
thank, as you giue him ſatisfaction;
you ſhal deſire no more.
               Finally, GOD giue vs as much
good vſe, as knowledge of his iudgements;

the world, helpe of your labors;
your ſelfe, incouragement;
Buchinski, libertie.
            
            
               
               To STANISLAVS BVCHINSKI,
late Secretarie to DEMETRIVS
Emp. of Ruſſia.
               EP. 7. Of the comfort of Impriſonment.
               
                  THe knowledge, that the eie
giues of the face alone, is
ſhallow, vncertaine, imperfect.
For, what is it, to ſee the vtmoſt
skin, or fauour of the viſage;
changeable with diſeaſe, changeable
with paſsion? The eare (mee thinks)

doth both moſt clearely diſcloſe the
mindes of others, and knit them faſter
to ours: which, as it is the ſenſe
of diſcipline, ſo of friendſhip; commaunding
it euen to the abſent, and
in the preſent cheriſhing it. This
thing we haue lately proued in your
ſelfe, moſt noble Staniſlaus: neerer
examples wee might haue had; better,
we could not. How many, how
excellent things haue wee heard of
you, from our common friend, tho
moſt yours, which haue eaſily won
our beleefe, our affections! How oft,
how honourable mention hath hee
made of your name! how frequently,
how ſeruētly haue we wiſht you, both
ſafety, and libertie! And now, Lo
where ſhe comes, as the Greekes ſay,

                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp; viſites her forlorne Client.
Altho, I would not doubt to ſay
that this outwarde durance of the

body, hath ſeemed more harſh to the
behoulders, then to your ſelfe, a
wiſe man, and (which is more) a
Chriſtian; whoſe free ſoule, in the
greateſt ſtraights of the outer man,
flies ouer Seas and Lands, whither it
liſteth; neither can, by any diſtance
of place, nor ſwelling of waues, nor
height of mountaines, nor violence
of enemies, nor ſtrong barres, nor
walles, nor guards, bee reſtrained
from what place it ſelfe hath choſen.
Lo, that enioyes God, enioyes it ſelf,
and his friends; and ſo feedes it ſelfe
with the pleaſure of enioying them,
that it eaſily either forgers, or contemnes
all other things. It is no Paradoxe,
to ſay that A wiſe Chriſtian cannot
bee empriſoned, cannot bee baniſhed:
Hee is euer at home, euer free.
For, both his libertie is within him,
and his home is vniuerſall. And

what is it, I beſeech you (for you haue
tried) that makes a priſon? Is it ſtraitneſſe
of walls? Then you haue as
many fellowes, as there are men. For,
how is the ſoule of euerie man pent
within theſe clay-walles of the body,
more cloſe, more obſcure
                     •
                   whence,
ſhee may looke oft, through the
grates of her buſie thoughts; but, is
neuer releaſed in ſubſtance, till that
God, who gaue vs our Mittimus into
this Gaole, giue vs our Deliuerie,
with a Returne yee ſonnes of Adam:
Thus, either all men are priſoners,
or you are none. Is it reſtraint? How
many (eſpecially of that other ſexe
in thoſe your Eaſterne partes) chamber
vp themſelues, for ſtate; ſo as
they neither ſee the Sunne, nor others
them? How many ſuperſtitious
men, for deuotion? How many
obſcure Aglai, for eaſe and careleſneſſe,

keepe themſelues in their
owne Cottage, in their owne village;
&amp; neuer walke foorth ſo much as to
the neighbour townes? And what is
your Ruſſia to all her inhabitants,
but a large priſon, a wide Gally? yea,
what other is the world to vs? How
can hee complaine of ſtraitnes, or reſtraint,
that roues all ouer the world,
and beyond it? Tyranny may part
the ſoule from the body; cannot
confine it to the bodie. That which
others do for eaſe, deuotion, ſtate,
you doe for neceſsitie: why not as
willingly, ſince you muſt do it? Do
but imagine the cauſe other; &amp; your
caſe is the ſame with theirs which
both haue choſen, and delight to
keepe cloſe; yet hating the name of
priſoners, while they embrace the
condition. But, why do I perſwade
you, not to miſlike that, which I pray

you may forſake? I had rather you
ſhould bee no priſoner at all; then to
be a cheerfull priſoner vpon neceſsitie.
If the doores bee open, my perſwaſion
ſhall not hold you in: Rather
our prayers ſhall open thoſe doores,
and fetch you foorth into this common
libertie of men; Which alſo
hath not a little (tho an inferiour)
contentment. For, how pleaſant is
it to theſe ſenſes, by which wee men
are wont to be led, to ſee &amp; be ſeene,
to ſpeake to our friends, and heare
them ſpeake to vs; to touch and kiſſe
the deare hands of our Parents and
with them at laſt to haue our eyes
cloſed? Either this ſhall befall you;
or what hopes, what paines (I adde
no more) hath this your careful friend
loſt? and we, what wiſhes, what conſultations?
It ſhall bee; I dare hope,
yea beleeue it: Only thou our good

God giue ſuch ende, as thou haſt
done entrance into this buſineſſe; and
ſo diſpoſe of theſe likely indeuours,
that whom we loue and honour abſent,
we may at laſt in preſence
ſee and embrace.
            
            
               
               
               To my father in law, Mr. GEORGE
WENYFFE.
               EP. 8. Exciting to Christian cheerefulneſſe.
               
                  YOu complaine of dulneſſe;
a common diſeaſe, and incident
to the beſt mindes,
and ſuch as can moſt contemne vanities.
For, the true Worldling
hunts after nothing but mirth; neither
cares how lawleſſe his ſport be,
ſo it be pleaſant: hee faines to himſelfe

falſe delights, whē he wants: and,
if he can paſſe the time, and chaſe away
Melancholy, hee thinkes his day
ſpent happily. And thus it muſt needs
bee; while the world is his God, his
deuotion can bee but his pleaſure:
whereas the mortified ſoule, hath
learned to ſcorne theſe friuolous and
ſinfull ioyes; and affects either ſolid
delights, or none; and had rather be
dull for want of mirth, then tranſported
with wanton pleaſures. When the
world, like an importunate Minſtrel,
thruſts it ſelfe into his chamber, and
offers him Muſicke, vnſought; if hee
vouch-ſafe it the hearing, it is the
higheſt fauour he dare, or can yield:
Hee rewards it not, hee commends
it not; Yea, hee ſecretlie loathes
thoſe harſh and iarring notes, and
reiects them. For, hee findes a better
conſort within, betwixt GOD

and himſelfe, when hee hath a little
tuned his heart with meditation.
To ſpeake fully, the World is like an
ill foole in a play: the Chriſtian is a
iudicious ſpectator, which thinkes
thoſe ieſtes too groſſe to bee laught
at; and therefore entertaines that
with ſcorne, which others with applauſe.
Yet in truth, wee ſinne, if
wee reioyce not: There is not
more errour in falſe mirth, then in
vniuſt heauineſſe. If Worldlings
offende, that they laugh when they
ſhould mourne; wee ſhall offende
no leſſe, if wee droupe in cauſe of
cheerefulneſſe. Shall wee enuie, or
ſcorne, to ſee one ioy in redde and
white droſſe, another in a vaine title;
one in a daintie diſh, another
in a ieſte; one in a booke, another in
a friend; one in a Kite, another in
a Dogge; vvhiles vvee enioy the

God of heauen, and are ſorrowfull?
What dull metall is this we are made
of? We haue the fountaine of ioy, and
yet complaine of heauineſſe. Is there
any ioy, without God? Certainly, if
ioy be good, and all goodneſſe be frō
him; whence ſhould ioy ariſe, but
from him? And if hee be the Author
of ioy; how are we Chriſtians, and reioyce
not? What? doe wee freeze in
the fire, and ſtarue at a feaſt? Haue we
a good conſcience, and yet pine and
hang down the head? When GOD
hath made vs happy, do we make our
ſelues miſerable? When I aske my
heart Dauids queſtion, I knowe not
whether I bee more angry, or aſhamed
at the anſwer; Why art thou ſad,
my ſoule? My body, my purſe, my
fame, my friends; or perhaps none
of theſe: only I am ſad, becauſe I am.
And what if all theſe, what if more?

when I come to my better wits, Haue
I a father, an aduocate, a comforter, a
manſion in heauen? if both earth and
hell conſpired to afflict me, my ſorrow
cannot counteruaile the cauſes
of my ioy. Now I can chalenge all
aduerſaries; and either defie all miſeries,
or bid all croſſes, yea death it
ſelfe, welcome. Yet GOD doth not
abbridge vs of theſe earthly ſolaces,
which dare weigh with our diſcontentments,
&amp; ſometimes depreſs the
balance. His greater light doth not
extinguiſh the leſſe. If God had not
thought them bleſſings, hee had not
beſtowed them: and how are they
bleſsings, if they delight vs not?
Bookes, friends, wine, oyle, health, reputation,
competency, may giue occaſions,
but not bounds to our reioycings.
We may not make them Gods
riualls, but his ſpokeſ-men. In themſelues

they are nothing; but, in God,
worth our ioy. Theſe may be vſed;
yet ſo as they may be abſent without
diſtraction. Let theſe goe; ſo God alone
be preſent with vs, it is enough:
He were not God, if he were not All-ſufficient.
Wee haue him, I ſpeake
boldly; Wee haue him in feeling, in
faith, in pledges, and earneſt; yea, in
poſſeſsion. Why doe wee not enioy
him? Why doe we not ſhake-off that
ſenſeleſſe drowſineſſe, which makes
our liues vnpleaſant; and leaue-ouer
all heauineſs, to thoſe that want God;
to thoſe that either knowe him not,
or knowe him diſpleaſed?
            
            
               
               To Mr. W. R. Dedic. to Mr. THOMAS
BVRLZ.
               EP. 9. Conſolations of immoderate Griefe
for the death of friends.
               
                  WHile the ſtreame of ſorrow
runnes full, I knowe
how vaine it is to oppoſe
counſell. Paſsions muſt
haue leaſure to digeſt. Wiſedome
doth not more moderate them,
then time. At firſt, it was beſt to
mourne with you, and to mitigate
your ſorrow, by bearing part; wherein,
would GOD my burden could

be your eaſe. Euery thing elſe is leſs,
when it is diuided; And then is beſt,
after teares, to giue counſell: yet, in
theſe thoughts I am not a little ſtraited.
Before you haue digeſted grief,
aduiſe coms too early; too late, when
you haue digeſted it. Before, it was
vnſeaſonable; after, would be ſuperfluous.
Before, it could not benefit
you: after, it may hurt you, by rubbing-vp
a skinned ſore afreſh. It is as
hard to chooſe the ſeaſon for counſell,
as to giue it: and that ſeaſon is,
after the firſt digeſtion of ſorrow; before
the laſt If my Letters then meet
with the beſt opportunity, they ſhall
pleaſe me, and profit you: If not, yet
I deſerue pardon, that I wiſhed ſo.
You had but two Iewels, which you
held precious; a Wife, and a Sonne:
One was your ſelf diuided; the other,
your ſelfe multiplied: You haue loſt

both, and well-neere at once. The
loſſe of one cauſed the other, &amp; both
of them your iuſt griefe. Such loſſes,
when they come ſingle, afflict vs; but,
when double, aſtoniſh vs; and, tho
they giue aduātage of reſpite, would
almoſt ouerwhelme the beſt patient.
Lo, now is the trial of your manhood,
yea of your Chriſtianity: You are
now in the liſts, ſet-vpon by two of
Gods fierce afflictions; ſhowe now
what patience you haue, what fortitude.
Wherefore haue you gathered,
and layd-vp, all this time, but for
this brunt? Now bring forth all your
holy ſtore to light, and to vſe; and approue
to vs in this difficulty, that you
haue all this while beene a Chriſtian
in earneſt. I knowe, theſe euents
haue not ſurpriſed you on a ſuddain:
you haue ſuſpected they might com;
you haue put-caſes if they ſhould

come. Thinges that are hazardous,
may be doubted: but, certaine things
are, and muſt bee expected. Prouidence
abates griefe, and diſcountenances
a croſſe. Or, if your a
                     •••
                  ction
were ſo ſtrong, that you 
                     〈◊〉
                   not
fore-thinke your loſſe; take it equally
but as it falls. A wiſe man and a
Chriſtian, knowes death ſo fatall to
Nature, ſo ordinary in euent, ſo gainfull
in the iſſue, that I wonder hee can
for this either feare or grieue. Doth
GOD onely lend vs one another,
and doe wee grudge when hee calls
for his owne? So I haue ſeene ill
debters, that borrow with prayers,
keepe with thankes, repay with enmitie.
Wee miſtake our tenure:
Wee take that for gift, which GOD
intendes for loane; Wee are Tenants
at will, and thinke our ſelues
owners. Your wife and childe are

dead: Well; they haue done that for
which they came.
               If they could not haue died, it
had beene worthy of wonder; not at
all, that they are dead. If this condition
were proper onely to our families;
and friends, or yet to our climate
alone; how vnhappy ſhould we
ſeeme to our neighbours, to our
ſelues! Now it is common, let vs
mourne that wee are men. Lo, all
Princes and Monarchs daunce with
vs in the ſame ring: yea, what ſpeake I
of earth? The God of Nature, the Sauiour
of mē, hath trod the ſame ſteps
of death? And doe wee thinke much
to follow him? How many ſeruants
haue wee knowen, that haue thruſt
themſelues betwixt their Maiſter &amp;
death; which haue died, that their maſter
might not dy? and ſhall we repi
                     •
                  e
to die with ours? How truly may we

ſay of this our Dauid, Thou art worth
ten thouſand of vs; yea, worth a world
of Angels: yet he died, and died for
vs. Who would liue, that knowes his
Sauiour died? who can be a Chriſtian,
and would not be like him? Who
can bee like him, that would not die
after him? Thinke of this, and iudge
whether all the world can hire vs not
to die. I need not aske you, whether
you loued thoſe whō you haue loſt:
Could you loue them, and not wiſh
they might bee happy? Could they
be happy, and not die? In truth, Nature
knowes not what ſhee would
haue; Wee can neither abide our
friends miſerable in their ſtay, nor
happy in their departure: Wee loue
our ſelues ſo well, that we cannot be
content they ſhould gaine by our
loſſe. The excuſe of your ſorrow is,
that you mourn for your ſelfe. True:

but, compare theſe two, and ſee whether
your loſſe or their gain be greater.
For, if their aduantage exceede
your loſſe; take heed, leaſt while you
bewray your loue in mourning for
them, it appeare that you loue but
your ſelfe in them. They are gone to
their preferment, and you lament:
your loue is iniurious. If they were
vaniſhed to nothing, I could not
blame you, tho you tooke vp Rachels
lamentation: But now, you knowe
they are in ſurer handes then your
owne: you knowe, that he hath taken
them, which hath vndertaken to keep
them, to bring them againe: You
knowe, it is but a ſleepe, which is miſcalled
Death; and that they ſhall,
they muſt awake, as ſure as they lie
down; and wake more freſh, more
glorious, then when you ſhut their
eyes. What do we with Chriſtianitie, if

we beleeue not this? and if wee doe
beleeue it, why doe wee mourne as
the hopeleſs? But the matter, perhaps,
is not ſo heauie as the circumſtance:
Your croſſes came ſudden,
and thicke; You could not breathe
from your firſt loſſe, ere you felt a
worſe. As if hee knew not this, that
ſent both: As if he did it not on purpoſe.
His proceedings ſeeme harſh;
are moſt wiſe, moſt iuſt. It is our
fault, that they ſeeme otherwiſe then
they are. Doe we thinke, wee could
carue better for our ſelues? O the
mad inſolence of Nature, that dares
controll, where ſhe ſhould wonder!
Preſumptuous clay! that wil be checking
the Potter. Is his wiſedome,
himſelfe? Is he, in himſelfe, infinite?
is his Decree out of his wiſedom; and
doe wee murmur? Doe wee, fooliſh
wormes, turne againe when he treads

vpon vs? What? doe you repine at
that which was good for you, yea
beſt? That is beſt for vs, which God
ſeeth beſt: and that he ſees beſt, which
he doth. This is Gods doing. Kiſſe
his rod in ſilence, and giue glory to
the hand that rules it. His will is the
rule of his actions; and his goodneſs,
of his will. Thinges are good to vs,
becauſe he wills them: He wills them,
becauſe they are good to himſelfe. It
is your glory that he intends, in your
ſo great affliction. It is no praiſe to
wade ouer a ſhallow Ford: but, to cut
the ſwelling waues of the Deepe,
commendes both our ſtrength and
skill. It is no victorie, to conquer
an eaſie and weake croſſe.
Theſe maine euils haue crownes anſwerable
to their difficulty: Wreſtle
now, and goe away with a bleſsing.
Bee patient in this loſſe, and you

ſhall once triumph in your gaine. Let
God haue them with cheerefulneſſe,
and you ſhall enioy God with them
in glory.
            
            
               
               To Mr. I. A. Merchant.
               EP. 10. Against Sorrowe for worldly
loſſes.
               
                  IT is fitter for mee to begin
with chiding, then
with aduice: what means
this weake diſtruſt? Go
on, and I ſhall doubt whether I write
to a Chriſtian. You haue loſt your
heart, together with your wealth:
How can I but feare, leaſt this Mammon
was your God? Hence was

Gods iealouſie in remoouing it; and
hence your immoderate teares for
loſing it. If thus; God had not loued
you, if he had not made you poore.
To ſome, it is an aduantage to leeſe:
you could not haue beene at once
thus rich, and good. Now, heauen is open
to you, which was ſhut before; &amp;
could neuer haue giuen you entrāce,
with that lode of iniquitie. If you be
wiſe in menaging your affliction, you
haue changed the world for GOD,
a little droſſe for heauē. Let me euer
loſe thus, and ſmart when I cōplain.
               But, you might haue at once retained
both. The ſtomach, that is purged,
muſt bee content to part with
ſome good nouriſhment, that it may
deliuer it ſelfe of more euill humors.
God ſaw (that knowes it) you could
not hold him ſo ſtrongly, while one
of your hands was ſo faſtened vpon

the world. You ſee, many make them
ſelues wilfully poore: why cannot you
be content God ſhould impoueriſh
you? If God had willed their pouerty,
he would haue cōmanded it: If he
had not willed yours, he would not
haue effected it. It is a ſhame for a
Chriſtiā, to ſee an Heathen philoſopher
laugh at his owne ſhipwracke;
while himſelfe houles out, as if all his
felicity were imbarked with his ſubſtāce.
How ſhould we ſcorn, to think
that an heathen man ſhould laugh either
at our ignorance, or impotence?
ignorāce, if we thought too highly of
earthly things; impotēce, if we ouerloued
them. The feare of ſome euils
is worſe thē the ſenſe. To ſpeake
ingenuouſly; I could neuer ſee, wherin
pouerty deſerued ſo hard a cōceit.
It takes away the delicacy of fare, ſoftneſſe
of lodging, gayneſſe of attyre,

and perhaps brings with it cōtempt:
This is the worſt, and all. View it now
on the better ſide: Lo, there quiet
ſecuritie, ſound ſleepes, ſharpe appetite,
free meriment; no feares, no
cares, no ſuſpicion, no diſtemper of
exceſſe, no diſcontentment. If I were
Iudge, my tongue ſhould be vniuſt, if
pouertie went away weeping. I cannot
ſee, how the euills it brings, can
cōpare with thoſe which it remoues;
how the diſcommodities ſhould
match the bleſsings of a mean eſtate.
What are thoſe you haue loſt, but
falſe friends, miſerable comforters?
Elſe they had not left you. Oh ſlight
and fickle ſtay, that windes could bereaue
you of! If your care could go
with them, here were no dammage:
and, if it go not with them, it is your
fault. Grieue more for your fault,
then for your loſſe. If your negligence,

your riotous miſſpence had
empaired your eſtate, then Satan had
impoueriſht you; now would I haue
added to your griefe, for your ſinne,
not for your aſfliction: But now,
ſince windes and waters haue done
it as the officers of their maker; why
ſhould not you ſay with mee, as I
with Job, The Lord hath taken? Vſe
your loſſe well, and you ſhall finde
that God hath croſſed you with a
bleſsing. And if it were worſe then
the worlde eſteemes it, yet thinke
not what you feele, but what you deſerue:
You are a ſtranger to your
ſelfe, if you confeſſe not, that God
fauours you in this whip. If hee had
ſtripped you of better things, and
ſcourged you with worſe, you ſhould
ſtill haue acknowledged a mercifull
iuſtice: If you now repine at an eaſie
correction, you are worthy of ſeueritie.

Beware the next, if you grudge
and ſwell at this. It is next to nothing
which you ſuffer: what can be further
from vs, then theſe goods of outward
eſtate? You need nor abate either
health, or mirth, for their ſakes. If
you do now draw the affliction neerer
then hee which ſent it, and make
a forraine euil domeſticall; if while
God viſits your eſtate, you fetch it
home to your body, to your minde;
thank your ſelfe that you will needes
be miſerable: But, if you loue not to
fare ill; take croſſes as they are ſent,
and go lightly away with an
eaſie burden.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            Errata.
            Pag. 86. line 2. falls for faults. pag 98. li. 1. nor for not.
            
         
      
   

