
   
      
         
            The great impostor laid open in a sermon at Grayes Inne, Febr. 2.1623. By Ios. Hall D.D.
            Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
         
         
            
               1623
            
         
         Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02537
            STC 12665
            ESTC S116594
            99851810
            99851810
            17102
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02537)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17102)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:01)
         
         
            
               
                  The great impostor laid open in a sermon at Grayes Inne, Febr. 2.1623. By Ios. Hall D.D.
                  Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656.
               
               [4], 63, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by J. Haviland for Nath. Butter,
                  London :
                  1623.
               
               
                  Several pages stained.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE GREAT Impoſtor, LAID OPEN in a SERMON at GRAYES INNE, Febr. 2. 1623.
            By IOS. HALL D. D.
            LONDON, Printed by J. Havilano for Nath. Butter. 1623.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE MOST NOBLE, AND WORTHILY Honoured Societie OF GRAYES INNE: AT WHOSE BARRE This IMPOSTOR was openly arraigned: J. H. HVMBLY DEDICATES THIS PVBLIKE LIFE OF HIS WEAKE AND VNWORTHY LABOVR.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE GREAT IMPOSTOR, Laid open, out of IER. 17.9. The heart is deceitfull aboue all things.
            
               I Know where I am; in one of the famous Phrontiſteries of Law, and Iuſtice: wherfore ſerues Law and Iuſtice, but for the preuention or puniſhment

of fraud and wickedneſſe? Giue me leaue therefore to bring before you, Students, Maſters, Fathers, Oracles of Law and Iuſtice, the greateſt Cheator and Malefactor in the world, our owne Heart. It is a great word that I haue ſaid, in promiſing to bring him before you; for this is one of the greateſt aduantages of his fraud, that he cannot be ſeene: That as that old Iugler Apollonius Thyanaeus, when he was brought before the Iudge, vaniſhed out of ſight; ſo this great Impoſtor, in his very preſenting before you, diſpeareth and is gone; yea ſo cunningly, that he doth it with our owne conſent, and we would be loth that he

could be ſeene: Therefore as an Epiphonema to this iuſt complaint of deceitfulneſſe, is added Who can know it? It is eaſie to know that it is deceitfull, and in what it deceiues, though the deceits themſelues cannot bee knowne, till too late; As wee may ſee the ſhip, and the ſea, and the ſhip going on the ſea, yet the way of a ſhip in the ſea (as Salomon obſerues) wee know not: God askes, and God ſhall anſwer; What he askes by Ieremie, he ſhall anſwer by S. Paul, Who knowes the heart of man?
               1 Cor. 2.11. 
               Euen the ſpirit of man that is in him. If then the heart haue but eyes enow to ſee it ſelfe by the reflection of thoughts, it is enough: Ye ſhall

eaſily ſee and heare enough (out of the analogie and reſemblance of hearts) to make you both aſtoniſhed and aſhamed.
            The heart of man lies in a narrow roome, yet all the world cannot fill it; but that which may be ſaid of the heart, would more than fill a world: Here is a double ſtile giuen it; of deceitfulneſſe; of wickedneſſe; either of which knowes no end, whether of being, or of diſcourſe. I ſpend my houre, and might doe my life, in treating of the firſt.
            See then, I beſeech you, the Impoſtor, and the Impoſture; The Impoſtor himſelfe, The heart of man; The Impoſture, Deceitfull aboue all things.
            
            
               As deceitfull perſons are wont euer to goe vnder many names, and ambiguous, and muſt be expreſt with an [aliàs] ſo doth the heart of man; Neither man himſelfe, nor any part of man hath ſo many names, as the heart alone; For euery facultie that it hath, and euery action it doth, it hath a ſeuerall name: Neither is there more multiplicitie, than doubt in this name; Not ſo many termes are vſed to ſignifie the heart, as the heart ſignifies many things.
            When ye heare of the heart, ye thinke ſtraight of that fleſhie part in the center of the body which liues firſt, and dies laſt; and whoſe beatings you finde

to keepe time all the body ouer; That is not it which is ſo cunning; Alas, that is a poore harmeleſſe peece; meerely paſſiue; and if it doe any thing, as the ſubminiſtration of Vitall ſpirits, to the maintenance of the whole frame, it is but good; no, it is the ſpirituall part that lurkes in this fleſh, which is guilty of ſuch deceit. We muſt learne of witty Idolatry to diſtinguiſh betwixt the ſtocke and the inuiſible powers that dwell in it. It is not for me to be a ſticklor betwixt the Hebrewes, and the Greeke Philoſophers, and Phyſitians, in a queſtion of naturall learning, concerning the 
                  〈◊〉
                of the ſoule; nor to inſiſt vpon the

reaſons why the ſpirit of God rather places all the ſpirituall powers in the heart, than in the braine; Doubtleſſe in reſpect of the affections there reſident, whereby all thoſe ſpeculatiue abilities are drawne to practiſe; It ſhall ſuffice vs to take things as we finde them, and to hold it for granted, that this Monoſyllable (for ſo it is in many languages) compriſes all that intellectiue and affectiue world which concerneth man; and in plaine termes to ſay, that when God ſaies The heart is deceitfull, he meanes, the vnderſtanding, will, affections are deceitfull.
            The vnderſtanding is doubly deceitfull; It makes vs beleeue

it knowes thoſe things which it doth not; and that it knowes not thoſe things which it doth: As ſome fooliſh Mountebanke, that holds it a great glory to ſeeme to know all things; or ſome preſuming Phyſitian, that thinkes it a ſhame not to profeſſe skill in any ſtate of the body, or diſeaſe; ſo doth our vaine vnderſtanding; therein framing it ſelfe according to the ſpirits it meets withall; if they be proud and curious, it perſwades them, they know euery thing; if careleſſe, that they know enough.
            In the firſt kinde; What hath not the fond heart of man dared to arrogate to it ſelfe? It

knowes all the ſtarres by their names; Tuſh, that is nothing; It knowes what the ſtars meane by their verie lookes, what the birds meane by their chirping, as Apollonius did; What the heart meanes, by the features of the face; it knowes the euents of life by the lines of the hand: the ſecrets of Art, the ſecrets of Nature, the ſecrets of State, the ſecrets of others hearts, yea the ſecrets of God in the cloſet of heauen; Yea, not only what God hath done, but what he will doe: This is (Sapiens ſtultitia) a wiſe folly, as Irenaeus ſaid of his Valentinians; All Figure-caſters, Palmeſters, Phyſiognomers, Fortune-tellers, Alchymiſts, fantaſticke

proiectors, and all the rabble of profeſſors of thoſe 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,Acts 19.19. not ſo much curious as idle Arts, haue their word giuen them by the Apoſtle, Deceiuing and deceiued; neither can theſe men make any worſe fooles, than their hearts haue made themſelues;
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . and well may that Alexandrian taxe bee ſet vpon them in both names, whether of actiue, or paſſiue folly: And (as it commonly fals out, that ſuperfluous things rob the heart of neceſſary) in the meane while, thoſe things which the heart may and ſhould know, it lightly miſ-knowes: As our ſenſes are deceiued by diſtance, or interpoſitions, to thinke the ſtars beamie

and ſparkling, the Moone horned, the Planets equally remote, the Sunne ſometimes red, pale other ſome: ſo doth alſo our vnderſtanding erre, in miſ-opinion of diuine things; It thinkes it knowes God, when it is but an Idoll of fancy, as Sauls meſſengers, when they came into the roome, thought they had the true Dauid, when it was but a Wiſpe; it knowes the will of God, when it is nothing but groſſe miſ-conſtruction: ſo as the common knowledge of men, though they thinke it a Torch, is but an Ignis Fatuus to leade them to a ditch: How many thouſand Aſſyrians thinke they are in the way to the Prophet,

when they are in the midſt of Samaria? How many millions thinke they walke fairely on to heauen, when indeed they are in the broad way that leads to deſtruction? Oh poore blind Pagans, halfe-ſighted Turkes, bleare-eied Iewes, blind-folded Papiſts, Squint-eied Schiſmaticks, purblind ignorants, how well doe they finde themſelues pleaſed with their deuotion, and thinke God ſhould bee ſo too; when it is nothing but a mixture of meſpriſon, ſuperſtition, conceitedneſſe; and (according to the ſeldome-reuerently-vſed prouerb) whiles they thinke they haue God by the finger, they hold a deuill by the toe;

and all this, becauſe their heart deceiues them. If careleſſe, and loth to bee at the paines of knowing more, it perſwades them they know enough; that they cry out of more, as he did on the ointment, (Vt quid perditio haec?) What needs all this waſte? and makes them as conſcionable for knowledge, as Eſau was for cattle, I haue enough, my brother, keepe that thou haſt to thy ſelfe; or as contentedly-reſolute, as the Epicure in the Goſpell: Soule take thy eaſe, thou haſt knowledge enough laid vp for many yeeres.
            
            From whence it is, that too many reſt ſimply (yea wilfully) in their owne meaſure, not ſo much as wiſhing more skill in

Soule-matters; applauding their owne ſafe mediocritie; like the credulous blinde man that thought he now ſaw a ſhimmering of the Sunne-beames, when indeed his backe was towards it: Hence it is that they ſcoffe at the fooliſhneſſe of preaching, ſcorne the forward bookiſhneſſe of others, fearing nothing but a ſurfet of Manna, and hating to know more than their neighbours, than their fore-fathers; &amp; thus are led on muffled vp in an vnfelt ignorance, to their graue, yea, (without the mercy of God) to their hell.
            And as in theſe things there is a preſumption of knowing what we doe not; ſo contrarily,

a diſſimulation and concealement of the knowledge of what we doe vnderſtand; The heart of man is a great lier to it ſelfe this way; Saint Paul ſaies that of Pagans, which I may boldly ſay of Chriſtians, they haue the effect of the law written in their hearts; yet many of them will not bee acknowne of one letter ingrauen there by the finger of God: Certaine common principles there are (together with this law) interlinearily written in the tables of the heart, as that we muſt doe as we would be done to; That there is a God; That this God is infinite in iuſtice and truth, and muſt be ſerued like himſelfe; theſe they

either blot out, or lay their finger on, that they may not bee ſeene, purpoſely, that they may ſinne freely; and faine would perſwade themſelues they neuer had any ſuch euidence from God: ſo putting off the checks of conſcience with bold denyalls; like the harlot of Iericho, (but worſe than ſhe) that hath hid the Spies, and now out-faces their entertainment: Wherein the heart doth to it ſelfe, that which Nahaſh the Ammonite, would haue done to Iſrael, put out his owne right eie, that it may not ſee that law whereby it might be conuinced, and finde it ſelfe miſerable. Thus the vnderſtanding of man is euery

way deceitfull in ouerknowing, miſ-knowing, diſſembling; in all which it is like an euill and vnfaithfull eye, that either will be ſeeing by a falſe glaſſe, or a falſe light, or with diſtortion; or elſe wilfully cloſes the lids that it may not ſee at all; and in all this deceiues vs.
            The will is no leſſe cunning; which though it make faire pretences of a generall inclination to good, yet (hîc &amp; nunc) in particulars, hangs towards a pleaſing euill; Yea though the Vnderſtanding haue ſufficiently informed it of the worthineſſe of good, and the turpitude of euill, yet being ouercome with the falſe delectableneſſe of ſinne, it

yeelds to a miſſe-aſſent; Reaſon being (as Aquinas ſpeakes) either ſwallowed vp by ſome paſſion, or held downe by ſome vicious habit: It is true, ſtill the Will followes the Reaſon, neither can doe otherwiſe; but therefore, if Reaſon miſ-led be contrary to Reaſon, and a ſchiſme ariſe in the ſoule, it muſt follow that the Will muſt needs be contrary to Will and Reaſon; Wherein it is like a Planet, which though it be carried about perpetually by the firſt mouer, yet ſlily creepes on his owne way, contrary to that ſtrong circumuolution: And though the minde be ſufficiently conuinced of the neceſſitie, or profit of a good act, yet

for the tediouſneſſe annexed to it, in a dangerous ſpirituall acedie, it inſenſibly ſlips away from it, and is content to let it fall; As ſome idle, or fearfull Merchant, that could be glad to haue gold, if it would come with eaſe, but will not either take the paines, or hazard the aduenture to fetch it: Thus commonly the Will (in both reſpects) Waterman-like lookes forward, and rowes backward; and vnder good pretences doth nothing but deceiue.
            The affections are as deceitfull as either; whether in miſſe-placing, meaſure, or manner.
            Miſ-placing: They are fiery where they ſhould be coole; and

where they ſhould burne, freeze; Our heart makes vs beleeue it loues God, and giues him pledges of affection; whiles it ſecretly doats vpon the world; like ſome falſe ſtrumpet, that entertaines her husband with her eyes, and in the meane time treads vpon the toe of an Adulterer vnder the board: That it loues iuſtice, when it is but reuenge; That it grieues for the miſſing of Chriſt, when indeed it is but for the loaues and fiſhes; That it feares God, when indeed it is but afraid of our owne torment; That it hates the ſinne, when it is the perſon; That it hates the world, when it thruſts God out of doores to lodge it.
            
               Meaſure: That we loue God enough, and the world but enough, when as indeed the one loue is but as the cold fit of an ague, the other an hot; we chill in the one, no leſſe than we glow in the other; when wee make God only a ſtale to draw on the world; That wee doe enough hate our corruptions, when (at our ſharpeſt) we doe but gently ſneape them, as Hely did his ſons; or as ſome indulgent parent doth an vnthriftie darling, whom he chides, and yet feeds with the fewell of his exceſſe; That we haue grieued enough for our ſinnes, when they haue not coſt vs ſo much as one teare, nothing but a little faſhionable

winde, that neuer came further than the roots of our tongue; That we doe enough compaſſionate the afflictions of Ioſeph, when we drinke wine in bowles; That wee feare God more than men, when wee are aſhamed to doe that in preſence of a childe, which wee care not to doe in the face of God.
            Manner: That our heart loues, and hates, and feares, and ioyes, and grieues truly, when it is an hypocrite in all; That it delights conſtantly in God, and holy things, when it is but an Ephraims morning dew; That our anger is zealous, when it is but a flaſh of perſonall malice, or a ſuperſtitious furie; That we

feare as ſonnes, when it is as cowards, or ſlaues; That we grieue as Gods patients, when we fret, and repine, and ſtruggle like franticks againſt the hand of our Maker. Thus (to ſumme vp all) the heart of man is wholly ſet vpon cozenage; the vnderſtanding ouer-knowing, miſ-knowing, diſſembling; The will pretending, and inclining contrarily; The affections mocking vs in the obiect, meaſure, manner; and in all of them the heart of man is deceitfull.
            Ye haue ſeene the face of this Cheater; looke now at his hand; and now ye ſee who this Deceiuer is, ſee alſo the ſleights of his deceit; and therein, the faſhion,

the ſubiect, the ſequell of it; from whence we will deſcend to our Demeanure towards ſo dangerous an Impoſtor.
            The faſhion of his deceit is the ſame with our ordinary Iuglers; either cunning conueyance, or falſe ſemblance. Cunning conueyance, whether into vs, in vs, from vs.
            The heart admits ſinne, as Paradiſe did the Serpent; There it is, but by what chinkes or cranies it entered, we know not; ſo as we may ſay of ſinne as the Maſter of the feaſt in the Goſpell ſaid to his ſlouenly gueſt, Quomodo intraſti? How cameſt thou in hither? Corruption doth not eat into the heart as our firſt Parents

did into the apple, ſo as the print of their teeth might bee ſeene, but as the worme eats into the core, inſenſibly; Neither is there leſſe cloſeneſſe when it is entered; I would it were as vntrue a word, as it is an harſh one, that many a profeſſedly-Chriſtian heart, lodges a deuill in the blinde roomes of it, and either knowes it not, or will not be acknowne of it; euery one that harbours a willing ſinne in his breſt, doth ſo: The malicious man hath a furious deuill; the wanton an vncleane deuill, a Beelphegor, or a Tammuz; the proud man a Lucifer, the couetous a Mammon; Certainly, theſe foule ſpirits are not more truly

in hell, than in a wicked heart; there they are, but ſo cloſely, that I know not if the heart it ſelfe know it; it being verified of this citadell of the heart, which was ſaid of that vaſt Niniue, that the enemie had taken ſome parts of it, long ere the other knew it: What ſhould I ſpeake of the moſt common, and yet moſt dangerous gueſt, that lodges in this Inne of the heart, Infidelity? Call at the doore, and aske if ſuch a one hoſt not there; They within make ſtrange of it, deny it, forſweare it; Call the officers, make priuy ſearch, you ſhall hardly finde him: Like ſome Ieſuite in a Popiſh dames chamber, he is

ſo cloſely contriued into falſe floores, and double walls, that his preſence is not more eaſily knowne, than hardly conuinced, confeſſed. How eaſie is it to ſay, that if infidelity did not lurke in the hearts of men, they durſt not doe as they doe; they could not but doe, what they doe not? Durſt they ſin if they were perſwaded of an hell? durſt they buy a minute of pleaſure with euerlaſting torments? Could they ſo ſleight heauen if they beleeued it? Could they be ſo loth to poſſeſſe it? Could they thinke much of a little painfull goodneſſe to purchaſe an eternity of happineſſe? No, no, men, fathers, and brethren;

if the heart were not Infidell, whiles the face is Chriſtian, this could not bee. Neither doth the heart of man more cunningly conuey ſinne into, and in it ſelfe, than from it; The ſin that ye ſaw euen now openly in the hands, is ſo ſwiftly paſt vnder the board, that it is now vaniſhed; Looke for it in his forehead, there it is not; looke for it vnder his tongue, there is none; looke for it in his conſcience, ye finde nothing; and all this by the legier-de-maine of the heart: Thus Achan hath hid his wedge, and now he dares ſtand out to a lot; Thus Salomons Harlot hath wip't her mouth, and it was not ſhe: Thus Saul will lie-out his

ſacriledge, vntill the very beaſts out-bleat, and out-bellow him; Thus the ſwearer ſweares, and when he hath done, ſweares that hee ſwore not; Thus the vncleane fornicator bribes off his ſinne, and his ſhame, and now makes challenges to the world of his honeſty. It cannot be ſpoken how peeuiſhly witty the heart of man is this way; neither doubt I but this wilineſſe is ſome of the poyſon that the ſubtile ſerpent infected vs with in that fatall morſell: They were three cunning ſhifts which the Scripture recordeth of three women (as that ſex hath beene euer noted for more ſudden pregnancie of wit) Rachel, Rahab, and

the good wife of Bahurim; The firſt hiding the Teraphim with a modeſt ſeat, the ſecond, the ſpics with flaxe-ſtalkes, and the third Dauids ſcouts with corne ſpred ouer the Well; but theſe are nothing to the deuices that nature hath wont to vſe for the cloaking of ſinne; God made man vpright, ſaith Salomon, but he ſought many inuentions: Is Adam challenged for ſinne? Behold all on the ſudden it is paſſed from his hand, to Gods; The woman that thou gaueſt me: Is Saul challenged for a couetous and diſobedient remiſſeneſſe? the ſinne is ſtraight paſſed from the field to the Altar; I ſaued the fatteſt for a ſacrifice to the Lord thy God; So the one

begins his ſinne in God, and the other ends it in him: Is Dauid bewitched with luſt to abuſe the Wife? the Husband muſt bee ſent home drunke, to hide it, or if not that, to his long home, in a pretended fauour of his valour: Is a griping Vſurer diſpoſed to put his money together to breed a monſter? hee hath a thouſand quirks to cozen both law and conſcience: Is a Simoniacall Patron diſpoſed to make a good match of his peoples ſoules? it ſhall be no bargaine, but a gift: hee hath a liuing to giue, but an horſe to ſell. And ſure I thinke in this wiſe age of the world, Vſurers and Simoniſts ſtriue who ſhall finde the

wittieſt way to hell: What ſhould I ſpeake of the ſecret frauds in contracts, booties in matches, ſubornation of inſtruments, hiring of oathes, feeing of officers, equiuocations of anſwers, and ten thouſand other tricks that the heart of man hath deuiſed for the conueiances of ſinne; in all which it too well approues it ſelfe incomparably deceitfull.
            The falſe ſemblance of the heart is yet worſe; for the former is moſt-what for the ſmothering of euill; this is for the iuſtifying of euill, or the diſgrace of good; In theſe two doth this act of falſhood chiefly conſiſt; in making euill good, or good

euill. For the firſt; The naturall man knowes well how filthy all his brood is, and therefore will not let them come forth, but diſguiſed with the colours and dreſſes of good; ſo as now euery one of natures birds is a Swan; Pride is handſomneſſe, deſperate fury, valour; lauiſhneſſe is noble munificence, drunkenneſſe ciuility, flattery complement, murderous reuenge, iuſtice; the Curtizan is bona foemina, the Sorcerer a wiſe man, the oppreſſor a good huſband; Abſolom will goe pay his vowes; Herod will worſhip the Babe. For the ſecond; ſuch is the enuy of nature, that where ſhee ſees a better face than her

owne, ſhe is ready to ſcratch it, or caſt dirt in it; and therefore knowing that all vertue hath a natiue beauty in it, ſhe labours to deforme it by the fouleſt imputations. Would the Iſraelites be deuout? they are idle; Doth Dauid daunce for ioy before the Arke? he is a foole in a Morris: Doth Saint Paul diſcourſe of his heauenly Viſion? too much learning hath made him mad. Doe the Diſciples miraculouſly ſpeake all the tongues of Babel? They are full of new wine: Doe they preach Chriſts Kingdome? they are ſeditious; The reſurrection? they are bablers. Is a man conſcionable? he is an Hypocrite: Is he conformable? he

is vnconſcionable: Is he plaine dealing? he is rudely vnciuill: Is he wiſely inſinuatiue? he is a flatterer: In ſhort, ſuch is the wicked craft of the heart, that it would let vs ſee nothing in it owne forme; but faine would ſhew vs euill faire, that we might be inamored of it, and vertue vgly, that we might abhorre it; and as it doth for the way, ſo doth it for the end; hiding from vs the glory of heauen, that is laid vp for ouer-commers, and ſhewing vs nothing but the pleaſant cloſure of wickedneſſe; making vs beleeue that hell is a palace, and heauen a dungeon, that ſo we might be in loue with death; and thus both in cunning conueyance,

and falſe ſemblance, The heart of man is deceitfull aboue all things.
            
            Ye haue ſeene the faſhion of this deceit; caſt now your eies vpon the ſubiect: And whom doth it then deceiue? It doth deceiue others, it can deceiue it ſelfe, it would deceiue Sathan, yea God himſelfe. Others, firſt: How many doe we take for honeſt and ſound Chriſtians, who yet are but errant hypocrites? Theſe Apes of Sathan haue learned to transforme themſelues into Angels of light; The heart bids the eies looke vpward to heauen, when they are full of adultery; It bids the hands to raiſe vp themſelues towards

their Maker, when they are full of bloud; It bids the tongue wagge holily, when there is nothing in the boſome but Atheous profaneneſſe; It bids the knee to bow like a Camel, when the heart is ſtiffe as an Elephant; yea if need bee it can bid a teare fall from the eie, or an almes or iuſt action fall from the hand, and all to gull the world with a good opinion; In all which, falſe chapmen and horſe-courſers doe not more ordinarily deceiue their buyers in ſhops and faires, than wee doe one another in our conuerſation: Yea, ſo crafty is the heart that it can deceiue it ſelfe; By ouer-weening his own powers,

as the proud man; by vnder-valuing his graces, as the modeſt; by miſ-taking his eſtate, as the ignorant; How many hearts doe thus groſſely beguile themſelues? The firſt thinkes hee is rich, and fine, when hee is beggerly and naked; ſo did the Angell of Laodicea: The ſecond is poore in his owne ſpirit, when he is rich of Gods ſpirit: The third thinkes that he is a great fauorite of heauen, when he is rather branded for an out-caſt; that he is truly noble, when he is a ſlaue to that, which is baſer than the worſt of Gods creatures, ſinne: Let the proud and ignorant worldling therefore know, that though others may

mocke him with applauſes, yet that all the world cannot make him ſo much a foole as his owne heart.
            Yea, ſo cunning is the heart, that it thinkes to goe beyond the deuill himſelfe: I can (thinks it) ſwallow his bait, and yet auoid his hooke; I can ſinne, and liue; I can repent of ſinning, and defeat my puniſhment by repenting; I can runne vpon the ſcore, and take vp the ſweet and rich commodities of ſinfull pleaſure; and when I haue done, I can put my ſelfe vnder the protection of a Sauiour, and eſcape the arreſt: Oh the world of ſoules that periſh by this fraud, fondly beguiling

themſelues, whiles they would beguile the Tempter.
            Yet higher: Laſtly, as Satan went about to deceiue the Son of God; ſo this fooliſh conſort and client of his goes about to deceiue God himſelfe: The firſt paire of hearts that euer was, were thus credulous, to thinke they ſhould now meet with a meanes of knowledge and Deifying, which God either knew not of, or grudged them, and therefore they would be ſtealing it out of the ſide of the apple, without God, yea againſt him: Tuſh, none eye ſhall ſee vs; Is there knowledge in the moſt high, ſaith the ſottiſh Atheiſt? Lord, haue not we heard thee preach in out

ſtreets? haue not we caſt out Deuils in thy name? ſayes the ſmoothing hypocrite; as if he could fetch God ouer for an admiſſion into heauen. Thou haſt not lied to man, but to God, ſaith S. Peter to Ananias. And pettiſh Ionas, after hee had beene cooled in the belly of the Whale, and the Sea, yet will be bearing God downe in an argument to the iuſtifying of his idle choler, I doe well to be angry to the death. But as the greateſt Politicians are oft ouertaken with the groſſeſt follies (God owes proud wits a ſhame) the heart of man could not poſſibly deuiſe how ſo much to be foole it ſelfe, as by this wicked preſumption:Pſal. 94.10, 11. 
               Oh yee fooles, when will ye vnderſtand? He

that formed the eye, ſhall he not ſee? Hee that teacheth man knowledge, ſhall not he vnderſtand? The Lord knoweth the thoughts of man, that they are vanitie. A rod for the backe of fooles, yea a rod of iron for ſuch preſumptuous fooles, to cruſh them in peeces like a Potters veſſell.
            
            Ye haue ſeene the faſhion and the ſubiect of this deceit: the ſequell, or effect followes; euery way lamentable; For hence it comes to paſſe that many a one hath had his heart in keeping fortie, fiftie, threeſcore yeeres, and more, and yet is not acquainted with it; and all becauſe this craft hath kept it at the Priſcillianiſts locke, Tu omnes, te nemo;

It affects to be a ſearcher of all men, no man is allowed to come aboard of it; And if a man whether out of curioſitie, or conſcience, bee deſirous to inquire into it (as it is a ſhame for a man to be a ſtranger at home; Know ye not your owne hearts, ſaith the Apoſtle;) it caſts it ſelfe, Proteus-like, into ſo many formes, that it is very hard to apprehend it. One while the man hath no heart, (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) ſaith Salomon; Then hee hath (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) an heart, and an heart,Pſal. 12. ſaith Dauid; and one of his hearts contradicts another; and then how knowes he whether to beleeue? And what certainty, what ſafety can it be for a man to liue

vnacquainted with himſelfe? O
                  •
                this vnacquaintance, ſecondly, ariſes a dangerous meſ-priſon of a mans ſelfe, in the nature and quantity of his ſinne, in the quality of his repentance, in his peace and intireneſſe with God, in his right to heauen, and (in a word) in his whole ſpirituall eſtate. Of this meſ-priſon, thirdly, ariſes a fearefull diſappointment of all his hopes, and a plunging into vnauoidable torments: Wherein it is miſerable to ſee, how cunningly the traiterous hearts of many men beare them in hand all their liues long; ſoothing them in all their courſes, promiſing them ſucceſſe in all their waies, ſecuring them

from feare of euills, aſſuring them of the fauour of God, and poſſeſſion of heauen (as ſome fond Bigot would bragge of his Bull, or Medall, or Agnus Dei; or, as thoſe Prieſts that Gerſon 
               Qui publicè volunt dogmatizareſcupraedicare popu
                     •
                  o, quod ſi quis audit miſſam in illo die non 
                     〈◊〉
                   coe
                     •
                  us, nec moriet
                     •
                  r morte ſubitanea, nec carebit ſufficienti ſuſtetatione, &amp;c taxes, who made the people beleeue that the Maſſe was good for the eye-ſight, for the mawe, for bodily health, and preſeruation) till they come to their deathbeds; But then when they come to call forth the comforts they muſt truſt to, they finde them like to ſome vnfaithfull Captaine, that hath all the while in Garriſon filled his purſe with dead paies, and made vp the number of his companies with borrowed men; and in time of

eaſe ſhewd faire; but when hee is called forth by a ſudden alarum, bewraies his ſhame and weakneſſe, and failes his Generall when he hath moſt need of him; right thus doe the perfidious hearts of many, after all the glorious bragges of their ſecurity, on the bed of their laſt reckoning, finde nothing but a cold deſpaire, and a wofull horror of conſcience; and therefore too iuſtly may their hearts ſay to them, as the heart of Apollodorus the Tyran ſeemed to ſay vnto him; who dreamed one night that hee was fleaed by the Scythians, and boyled in a Caldron; and that his heart ſpake to him out of the kettle (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) It is I that haue drawne thee to all this. Certainly neuer man was, or ſhall bee frying in hell, but cries out of his owne heart, and accuſes that deceitfull peece as guilty of all his torment: For let Satan be neuer ſo malicious, and the world neuer ſo paraſiticall, yet if his owne heart had beene true to him, none of theſe could haue hurt him. Let the reſt of our enemies doe their worſt, only from the euill of our owne hearts, good Lord deliuer vs.
            It were now time for our thoughts to dwell a little vpon the meditation, and deploration of our owne danger and miſery, who are euery way ſo inuironed

with ſubtlety. If wee looke at Satan, his old title is, that old Serpent; who muſt needs therefore now, by ſo long time and experience, bee both more old and more Serpent. If we looke at ſinne, it is as crafty as he; Leſt any of you be hardened through the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne: If at our owne hearts, we heare (that which we may feele) that the heart is deceitfull aboue all things. Oh wretched men that we are, how are we beſet with Impoſtors on all hands; If it were more ſeaſonable for vs to bewaile our eſtate, than to ſeeke the redreſſe of it; But ſince it is not ſo much worth our labour to know how deepe the pit is, into which wee are

fallen, as how to come out of it, heare rather (I beſeech you) for a concluſion, how wee may auoid the danger of the deceit of our falſe heart; euen iuſt ſo as we would preuent the nimble feates of ſome cheating Iugler, Search him, watch him, Truſt him not.
            Looke well into his hands, pockets, boxes, ſleeues, yea, vnder his very tongue it ſelfe; There is no fraud ſo ſecret, but may be deſcried; were our hearts as crafty as the deuill himſelfe, they may be found out;
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . We are not ignorant (ſaith Saint Paul) of Satans deuices; much more then may we know our owne; Were the hearts of men (as Salomon
               
ſpeakes of Kings) like vnto deepe waters, they haue a bottome, and may be fathomed; Were they as darke as hell it ſelfe, and neuer ſo full of windings, and blind waies, and obſcure turnings, doe but take the lanthorne of Gods law in your hand, and you ſhall eaſily finde all the falſe and foule corners of them; As Dauid ſaith of the Sun, nothing is hid from the light thereof; Proue your ſelues, ſaith the Apoſtle; It is hard if falſhood be ſo conſtant to it ſelfe that by many queſtions it bee not tripped: Where this duty is ſlackened, it is no wonder if the heart bee ouer-run with ſpirituall fraud; Often priuy ſearches ſcarre away

vagrant, and diſorderly perſons, where no inquiry is made, is a fit harbour for them; If yee would not haue your hearts, therefore, become the lawleſſe Ordinaries of vncleane ſpirits, ſearch them oft; Leaue not a ſtraw vnſhaken to finde out theſe Labaniſh Teraphim that are ſtolne, and hid within vs; And, when wee haue ſearched our beſt, if we feare there are yet ſome vnknowne euills lurking within vs (as the man after Gods owne heart prayes againſt ſecret ſinnes) let vs call him in that cannot be deceiued; and ſay to God with the Pſalmiſt, Search thou me ô Lord, and trie me; Oh let vs yeeld our ſelues ouer to bee

ranſackt by that all-ſeeing eye, and effectuall hand of the Almighty. All our daubing, and cogging, and packing, and ſhuffling lies open before him, and he only can make the heart aſhamed of it ſelfe.
            And when our hearts are once ſtript naked, &amp; carefully ſearcht, let our eyes be euer fixedly bent vpon their conueyances, and inclinations; If we ſearch and watch not, wee may be ſafe for the preſent, long wee cannot; for our eye is no ſooner off, than the heart is buſie in ſome practiſe of falſhood; It is well if it forbeare whiles wee looke on, for The thoughts of mans heart are only euill continually; and many a

heart is like ſome bold and cunning theefe, that lookes a man in the face, and cuts his purſe: But ſurely, if there be any guardian of the ſoule, it is the eye; The wiſe mans eye (ſaith Solomon) is in his head; doubtleſſe, on purpoſe to looke into his heart: My ſonne, aboue all keepings keepe thy heart, ſaith he; If we doe not dogge our hearts then in all our wayes, but ſuffer our ſelues to loſe the ſight of them, they run wilde, and we ſhall not recouer them till after many ſlippery tricks on their parts, and much repentance on ours. Alas, how little is this regarded in the world? wherein the moſt take no keepe of their ſoules, but ſuffer themſelues

to run after the wayes of their owne hearts, without obſeruation, without controlement; What ſhould I ſay of theſe men, but that they would faine be deceiued, and periſh? For after this looſe licentiouſneſſe (without the great mercy of God) they neuer ſet eye more vpon their hearts, till they ſee them either fearfully intoyled in the preſent iudgements of God, or faſt chained in the pit of hell, in the torments of finall condemnation.
            Thirdly, If our ſearches and watches ſhould faile vs, wee are ſure our diſtruſt cannot; It is not poſſible our heart ſhould deceiue vs, if we truſt it not; Wee

carry a remedy within vs of others fraud; and why not of our owne? The Italians not vnwiſely pray God (in their knowne prouerbe) to deliuer them from whom they truſt; for wee are obnoxious to thoſe we relie vpon, but nothing can leeſe that which it had not; Diſtruſt therefore can neuer be diſappointed: If our hearts then ſhall promiſe vs ought (as it hath learned to profer largely, of him that ſaid, All theſe will I giue thee) although with vowes &amp; oathes, aske for his aſſurances; if he cannot fetch them from the euidences of God, truſt him not: If he ſhall report ought to vs, aske for his witneſſes; if he cannot

produce them from the records of God, truſt him not: If he ſhall aduiſe vs ought, aske for his warrant; if he cannot fetch it from the Oracles of God, truſt him not; And in all things ſo beare our ſelues to our heart, as thoſe that thinke they liue amongſt theeues and cozeners; euer iealouſly and ſuſpiciouſly; taking nothing of their word, ſcarce daring to truſt our owne ſenſes; making ſure worke in all matters of their tranſactions. I know I ſpeake to wiſe men, whoſe counſell is wont to be aſked, and followed, in matter of the aſſurances of eſtates; whoſe wiſdome is frequently imployed in the triall, euiction, dooming

of malefactors: Alas, what ſhall it auaile you that you can aduiſe for the preuention of others fraud, if in the meane time you ſuffer your ſelues to be coz
                  •••
               d at home? What comfort can you finde in publike ſeruice to the ſtate againſt offenders, if you ſhould carry a fraudulent and wicked heart in your owne boſomes? There is one aboue whom wee may truſt, whoſe word is more firme than heauen; When heauen ſhall paſſe, that ſhall ſtand; It is no truſting ought beſides, any further than he giues his word for it. Mans Epithet is, Homo mendax, and his beſt part, the hearts, deceitfull. Alas, what ſhall wee thinke, or

ſay of the condition of thoſe men, which neuer follow any other aduice than what they take of their owne heart? Such are the moſt; that make not Gods Law of their counſell; As Eſay ſaid of Iſrael,Eſa. 57.17. 
               Abijt vagtis in viacordis ſui: Surely they are not more ſure they haue an heart, than that they ſhall be deceiued with it, and betraied vnto death; Of them may I ſay, as Salomon doth of the wanton foole, that followes an harlot;Pro. 7.21. 
               Thus with her great craft ſhe cauſed him to yeeld, and with her flattering lips ſhe intiſed him: And he followed her ſtraightwayes, as an Oxe that goes to the ſlaughter, or as a foole to the ſtocks for correction. Oh then, deare

Chriſtians, as euer yee deſire to auoid that direfull ſlaughter-houſe of hell, thoſe wailings, and gnaſhings, and gnawings, and euerlaſting burnings, 
                  •••
               ke carefully to your owne he
                  •
               rts; and what euer ſuggeſtions they ſhall make vnto you, truſt them not, till you haue tried them by that vnfaileable rule of righteouſneſſe, the royall law of your Maker, which can no more deceiue you, than your hearts can free you from deceit.
            Laſtly, that wee may auoid not onely the euents, but the very enterpriſes of this deceit, let vs countermine the ſubtill workings of the heart. Our

Sauiour hath bidden vs be wiſe as Serpents; What ſhould bee wiſe but the heart? And can the heart be wiſer than it ſelfe? 
                  〈…〉
                wiſdome of the heart remedie the craft of the heart? Certainly it may. There are two men in euery regenerate breſt, the old and the new; And of theſe (as they are euer plotting againſt each other) wee muſt take the better ſide, and labour that the new man, by being more wiſe in God, may out-ſtrip the old: And how ſhall that be done? If we would diſpoſſeſſe the ſtrong man that keepes the houſe, our Sauiour bids vs bring in a ſtronger than hee; and if wee

would ouer-reach the ſubtiltie of the old man, yea, the old Serpent, bring in a wiſer than hee, euen the Spirit of God, the God of wiſdome; 
                  〈◊〉
                would haue Achitophels wicked counſels croſſed, ſet vp an Huſhai within vs: The fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer than the wiſdome of men. Could wee but ſettle God within vs, our craftie hearts would bee out of countenance, and durſt not offer to play any of their deluding tricks before him from whom nothing is hid; and if they could bee ſo impudently preſumptuous, yet they ſhould be ſo ſoone controlled in their firſt motions, that there would

bee more danger of their confuſion, than of our deceit. As yee loue your ſelues therefore, and your owne ſafetie, and wo
                  •
               ld bee free from the perill of this ſecret broaker of Satan, your owne hearts, render them obediently into the hands of God; giue him the keyes of theſe cloſets of his owne making; beſeech him that hee will vouchſafe to dwell and reigne in them; ſo ſhall wee be ſure that neither Satan ſhall deceiue them, nor they deceiue vs; but both wee and they ſhall be kept ſafe and inuiolable, and preſented glorious to the appearance of our Lord IESVS CHRIST: To whom

with the FATHER, and the HOLY GHOST 
                  •
               e all honour and glor
                  ••
                for euer and euer AMEN.
            FINIS.
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
         
      
   

