
   
      
         
            The liues, apprehensions, arraignments, and executions, of the 19. late pyrates Namely: Capt. Harris. Iennings. Longcastle. Downes. Haulsey. and their companies. As they were seuerally indited on St. Margrets Hill in Southwarke, on the 22. of December last, and executed the Fryday following.
         
         
            
               1609
            
         
         Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02673
            STC 12805
            ESTC S103778
            99839523
            99839523
            3952
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02673)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3952)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 725:21)
         
         
            
               
                  The liues, apprehensions, arraignments, and executions, of the 19. late pyrates Namely: Capt. Harris. Iennings. Longcastle. Downes. Haulsey. and their companies. As they were seuerally indited on St. Margrets Hill in Southwarke, on the 22. of December last, and executed the Fryday following.
               
               [60] p.   
               
                  Printed [by E. Allde] for Iohn Busby the elder,
                  London :
                  [1609]
               
               
                  The pirates' names are bracketed together on the title page.
                  Printer's name and publication date from STC.
                  Signatures: A-G⁴ H² .
                  Running title reads: The liues, araignments, &amp;c. of the late pyrates.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Pirates --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.
               Trials (Piracy) --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-10
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-10
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE LIVES, APPrehensions, Arraignments, and Executions, of the 19. late Pyrates. Namely:
            
               
                  
                     Capt.
                     Harris.
                     and their companies.
                  
                  
                     Iennings.
                  
                  
                     Longcastle.
                  
                  
                     Downes.
                  
                  
                     Haulsey.
                  
               
            
            As they were seuerally indited on St. Margrets Hill in Southwarke, on the 22. of December last, and executed the Fryday following.
            
            LONDON ¶ Printed for Iohn Busby the elder.
            
               〈1… pages missing〉
            
         
      
      
         
            
               
               he loued, and reioyce in the sonne that hath sinned and laments.
               But to my purpose, hauing in so many voyages gone forth and returned so successiuely and to approue, that the state of fortune, is like the spokes of a wheele, that is carried aswell downward as vpward, that this worldly felicity ioyes and pleasure, in which we so trust: which we study to know, labour to purchase, and are so carefull to keep, 
                     •…
                  re but like the day that is giuen vs to vse, and vanisheth away euen in the growing▪ That while we think we stand sure on the pynackles of Fortune, we are on the suddaine ouerthrowne to lye gr
                     •…
                  ueling in shame, pleasure and sorrow, being indeed twins (as shall appeare by me) the one no sooner hatched, but the other is at hand to s
                     •…
                  plant her, and therefore I may fitly compare mans happines heere to a fruitles smile, the which is presently turned into sorrowe and teares: 
                     •…
                  e a dreame, the ioy whereof vanisheth euen as we wake: to a painted Sepulchre, faire without and putrified within, or to a Syren beautifull in shew and deceit
                     •…
                  ul to intice, glorious aboue to bewitch you with gasing, but l
                     •…
                  oke downe to the hinder part, to the bot
                     •…
                  ome of that which he
                     •…
                  re we ran mad for, we shal finde this tempting faire to haue the taile of a Scorpion, who in the handling giues such a blow▪ that it benummeth our bodies, and the sence of vnderstanding, and stingeth our soules with an irrecou
                     •…
                  rable death.
               For while I thus wallowed in my inclination, mastred by my affections, and making my felicity out of others mens miseries, while I thought prosperity at sea, as sure in my gripe, as the power to speak was free to my tongu
                     •…
                  , my actions were 
                     •…
                  o imboldened, and my heart so hardned, that I held if a cowardise to dispaire to attempt, and effeminacy to pitie whosoeuer did perish. So that my fortunes, like a byas-bowle, being all this while throwne vp a hill, and gayned not the top o
                     •…
                   safety, whereon it might rest, it must of force fall downe againe. So I feareles to

venture, and dreadles of daunger, in the straights meeting with the Turkes Gallies▪ well appointed in a man of war, my surprised prise, waiting my becke, &amp; making for B
                        •…
                     stow, the Turkes road vp to me I was soone ha
                     •…
                  ld, but my ordnance made answer, and disdayning so much as to giue them friendly words, in regard my desperate boldenes thought me free from their rage, we enterd fight, where what either was their encounter, or our resistance, I will be partiall to report: but the end was, I was taken prisoner, conueid to Tunes, from a Christian transformd to a slaue, had my head and face shauen, and in their needfull seruice, as an inforced wretch, could striking, blowes brusing, and hunger pinching, I was compeld to row in their Gallies: necesstiy hath no resistance, and to this misery I was enforced to obey three year
                     •…
                  s, when I continued it out, some of the time with winde, water and b
                     •…
                  owes, brusing me at the seas, and the other part with Iron &amp; hunger, torturde a shore.
               In all whi
                     •…
                  h time, I had occasion inough offered me, to haue laid repentance at my heart, to haue sorrowed for my iniquities past, and to haue vowed to my conscience, that if euer God were the blessed worker, to redeeme me from this thraldome and captinitie, without whose helpe, I lay groueling &amp; desperate, I would account that minut the houre of my birth, and so consecrate my after life to the obeying of his will, that I would conuert my violence to patience, my Tyranny to temperancee. all my vices to vertues, and re
                     •…
                  orme my 
                     •…
                  ife to his blessed word, when on the contrary this affliction of my body, did not so chastise my minde, that I imputed this correction, to be laid vpon me by the hand of heauen, as a iust whip for my offences past, but the continuance thereof did so harden my heart, so fire my spleene, and inflate my spirit, that I vowed my liberty gained, should be to others losse, my freedome prooue fatall to other mens good haps, and that if euer I had againe the swindge of my wit, which was to cōmaund

must haue their wils, and they haue wils may reprooue whatsoeuer I say. Then since the lawe as from the fountaine of my offences, hath had power to drawe my life from me, and the world euen after my death, may haue a strength to condemne me, words vttered with teares but request of them this, that since my body shall haue power to blunt the edge of affliction, my fall may haue force to abate the keene sharpenesse of their rumoring tongues: and if any thirsty or vnsatisfied spleen either reioycing at my fall o
                     •…
                   bemoning my ruine, shall desire to see vnraueled the whole web of my life, here shall he behold the peece of my trauailes wherein I desire him to wash from his memory the staines of my name, here shall he read my diurnall transgressions, which I request him to pardon and not to reprooue, since no curre is so cruell to bite the dead, here as in a mirror shall he
                     •…
                   looke into my miseries handyworke, my sinne, my sorrow, my life, my death, and the building of my owne labour, begunne from the time I was brought by the Sherefe of Middlesex to Newgate, wrought vpon in the Marshalseyes, and conclude most vntimely at Wapping.
               For my place of birth then I must call it in Bristoll where my education was such, as did credit my louing and carefull father, and was obeyed by me as a dutyfull sonne: I grew vp like a streight plant, and was expected of the worthiest of that Citie, and hoped sor of the best of my countrye, to haue prooued the timber of a fruitfull trée: my company to our gentry was accounted so welcome, that they esteemed me for pleasure, more then expenses, and the contempt I held to assosiate with the base, had brought my faire de
                     •…
                  aner to be beloued of the best. So that my fellowship intirely desired, and my condition held honest, my father was proud to call me his happy sonne.
               In which flourishing expectation in my youth soiourned

in Bristoll, where I so farre preuailed in the loue of our Marchants, that I was soone encouraged to goe to sea, the first imployment I vndertooke was more to see the state and fashions of forraine countries, and to inrich my vnderstanding with experience, then any greedines of gaine, to strengthen riotte. So that in her late memorable maiesties reigne, when the diuision of league was betweene this kingdome and Spaine, I went but Purser sent forth in a man of Warre of Bristoll▪
                   in which charge of mine how carefull I gouerned, let my owne hand neglect to record, and the Marchants themselues when my body is in dust, impartially report, I neuer returning home but with sayles of successe profitable to the venturers, comfort to my father, and credit to his sonne: whereby from degree to degree deseruing aduancement I was at length set forth as Captaine my selfe, in which commaund ab oad howe manly I swayed let my enemies pratie that haue felt me at sea: which credit lent me, how well I repaid, let Bristoll speake, that in this my extremitie hath labour
                     •…
                   my peace &amp; pardon (euen with the price of eight hundred pound) felt of my purchase and feasted my paines.
               I haue sate with the Aldermen when my fathar hath wept to heare them discourse, and the teares he hath shed (against the nature of childhood) hath encouraged my valour as if I would say, father of me thou shalt weepe againe. But death must haue no praises, and though successe being like a spring tide, that rolles so high, till it ouerflow the bounds, I was as auidous to goe to warre, as my stomacke hungry I had an appetite to eate: I complaind of nothing, for I held my wounds the banners of heraldry borne before me to my graue, and all my study was how to make my father in his death but be comforted by his son, and the sonne to reioyce as in such a father. Your pitie Reader then is but this, neither of father nor of sonne: pitty the father, that hath lost him

he loued, and reioyce in the sonne that hath sinned and laments.
               But to my purpose, hauing in so many voyages gone forth and returned so successiuely and to approue, that the state of fortune, is like the spokes of a wheele, that is carried aswell downward as vpward, that this worldly felicity ioyes and pleasure, in which we so trust▪ which we study to know, labour to purchase, and are so carefull to keep, are but like the day that is giuen vs to vse, and vanisheth away euen in the growing: That while we think we stand sure on the pynackles of Fortune, we are on the suddaine ouerthrowne to lye groueling in shame, pleasure and sorrow, being indeed twins (as shall appeare by me) the one no sooner hatched, but the other is at hand to s
                     •…
                   plant her, and therefore I may fitly compare mans happines heere to a fruitles smile, the which is presently turned into sorrowe and teares: te a dreame, the ioy whereof vanisheth euen as we wake: to a painted Sepulchre, faire without and putrified within, or to a Syren beautifull in shew and deceitful to intice, glorious aboue to be witch you with gasing, but looke downe to the hinder part, to the bottome of that which heere we ran mad for, we shal finde this tempting faire to haue the taile of a Scorpion, who in the handling giues such a blow▪ that it benummeth our bodies, and the sence of vnderstanding, and stingeth our soules with an irrecouerable death.
               For while I thus wallowed in my inclination, mastred by my affections, and making my felicity out of others mens miseries, while I thought prosperity at sea, as sure in my gripe, as the power to speak was free to my tongue, my actions were fo imboldened, and my heart so hardned, that I held if a cowardise to dispaire to attempt, and effeminacy to pitie whosoeuer did perish. So that my fortunes, like a byas-bowle, being all this while throwne vp a hill, and gayned not the top of safety, whereon it might rest, it must of force fall downe againe. So I feareles to

venture, and dreadles of daunger, in the straights meeting with the Turkes Gallies▪ well appointed in a man of war, my surprised prise, waiting my becke, &amp; making for Bostow, the Turkes road vp to me I was soone ha
                     •…
                  , but my ordnance made answer, and disdayning so much as to giue them friendly words, in regard my desperate boldenes thought me free from their rage, we enterd fight, where what either was their encounter, or our resistance, I will be partiall to report: but the end was, I was taken prisoner, conueid to Tunes, from a Christian transformd to a fl
                     •…
                  ue, had my head and face shauen, and in their needfull seruice, as an inforced wretch, could striking, blowes brusing, and hunger pinching, I was compeld to row in their Gallies: necesstiy hath no resistance, and to this misery I was enforced to obey three yeares, when I continued it out, some of the time with winde, water and blowes, brusing me at the seas, and the other part with Iron &amp; hunger, torturde a shore.
               In all which time, I had occasion inough offered me, to haue laid repentance at my heart, to haue sorrowed for my iniquities past, and to haue vowed to my conscience, that if euer God were the blessed worker, to redeeme me from this thraldome and captinitie, without whose helpe, I lay groueling &amp; desperate, I would account that minut the houre of my birth, and so consecrate my after life to the obeying of his will, that I would conuert my violence to patience, my Tyranny to temperancee▪ all my vices to vertues, and reforme my 
                     •…
                  ife to his blessed word, when on the contrary this affliction of my body, did not so chast
                     •…
                  e my minde, that I imputed this correction, to be laid vpon me by the hand of heauen, as a iust whip for my offences past, but the continuance thereof did so harden my heart, so fire my spleene, and inflate my spirit, that I vowed my liberty gained, should be to others losse, my freedome prooue fatall to other mens good haps, and that if euer I had againe the swindge of my wit, which was to cōmaund

at sea, my fortunes should aspire to their 
                     •…
                  ormer eminence and my pleasure grow to their an
                     •…
                  ient scope, or my body should fall for it.
               But see 
                     •…
                  he iust will of the heauens (and be forewarnd by my fall you succeeding ages) that I should be the Prophesierto my self of my owne mishap, and the fatal rauen to c
                     •…
                  oke out mine owne ruine.
               For while I lay plunged in this sea of affliction, cloide with misery and without hope of releefe, It fortuned one Captaine Bishop, with a wealthy prise he had then tane, to put in for Tunes, and in a small time hauing made sale of his goods, he hauing (by what rumour I neuer v
                     •…
                  
                  derstood) ha
                     •…
                   intelligence of my thraldom there, of my extreame vsage, and in
                     •…
                  ortunat mishap, of his own frée nature he enquired me out, and demanded of me if I were that Captaine Harris so talked of in Bristow, who had bene so fortunate to inrich others, and was now deiected in this misfortune my selfe? when hauing little pleasure to heare my prayses spoken, or vnmindful to renew their memory by talke, but rather desirous of some comfort to supply my present want, although I euer held it a contemptible basenes to begge: he demaunded twice ere I made him an answere, till at length, the report of the place, my mother, country, nurse, and raiser, and the present memorie of my ancient father, being by his question put in my minde, I resolued him thus:
               What I was he witnessed, what I had bene by his owne tongue belike had heard, what I might be (vnles a dead man) in my present case he could hardly guesse, yet not-withstandnig all this, I was borne at Bristoll: who bring struck presently with an in-ward pity, to se
                     •…
                   me lye chayned inso miserable a case, so deformed without hatre on my head or face, so ghastly in shewe, so hollow-eyd, and so pined away in flesh, I might perceiue the teares to startle in his eies, while his hand priuately into mine put fiue duckets, and departing the

prison, he spake to me thus, be of good cheere Sir, God hath in store, in our greatest neede, and friends no doubt but will be your helpe, when I, not without cause, thanking him for his present curtesie, without demaunding his name, or little expecting his kindenes succeeded, for that instant we were both deuided.
               When Capta
                     •…
                  ne Bishop, as he hath often related vnto me since, being 
                     •…
                  eturned backe to his chamber, he was struck with a forcible impression to the heart in pity of my state, and the oftner remembring what Bristoll had spoke of me, he vowed to his soule he would proue my 
                     •…
                  nlarger, if al the riches he had but lately broght in, might purchase my ransome, with which curtesie of his (oh let no man forbid me to commend him, although for his offences like mine he deserues to be condemned) he neither telling me of his purpose, feeding my hope▪ or flattering my expectation, he so labourd with the Crosimon and Gouernours of Tunis, that for three hundred d
                     •…
                  ukets, which he franckly paid ere I knew by what meanes or by whome I was set at liberty, when in a generous disposition, inuiting me to his lodging I had my entertainementin such forme, as my present fortunes had equald his, where in regard of my long captiuity, he was as my Phisition, to minister to my health, allowing me all meanes possible, and commaunding withall that nothing were wanting might repaire my body to a strengthned estate: which when I found to be in my selfe, as he had perfectly enabled me within, (according to my degree, and the dignitie of his bounty) with variety of sutes he repaird me without, so that one day after being alone together, being iocund and frolick, for in al societies he accounted me his friend and companion, he on a suddainebrake with me thus.
               Captaine Harris what saist thou my heart, how art thou resolued man, whether as occasion shall offer thee, to make for England, and there to be held bold and beholding to thy old, but wauering acquaintance, or to abide

with me, &amp; venture thy fortunes with thy certain friend. It is not strange vnto thee, that since the late death of her memorable maiestie, our most royall Soueraigne, and his prudent and graue counsell, on approoued considerations best knowne to his grace and the state, and not requisite for vs that are subiects to enquire, hath lessend by this generall peace the flourishing imployment, that we sea
                     •…
                  aring men do bleede for at sea: In those 
                     •…
                  aies of bickering (quoth he) we haue spent our houres in a high floud, and it will be vnsauory for vs now, to pick vp our crums in a lowe 
                     •…
                  bbe: to liue in basenes, and want meanes euen to sustain nature, to walke vnder the checke of some such as haue pearkt vp their heads to authoritie in this time of quiet, whome we durst haue buffeted I and their heyres too in daies of warre. Then say, if for England thou resoluest thy course, such is my loue to thy welfare, I will not leaue thy company, till I see thee ashore, and then leaue me to shift for my selfe, But it with me and my loue to thee, thouwilt fasten thy fortunes, I will call thee my brother, and in the riches I haue gayned I will make thee a sharer.
               With which speech of his, hauing had intelligence that his purchase was great, seeing his riot and expenses huge, and hauing found his curtesie towards my misery manifest, I f
                     •…
                  und my inclination yeelding, and was almost caught at the first angling, yet for that instant, I desired some small respite, to consider of his will, and to my request he as soone consented.
               In which respite, nothing diminishing his bounty, nor neglecting his former fauour, for his purse was as open to me as to himselfe, it happened that one Captaine Gilbert Roup while Captaine Bishops ships anchord in the road, and he with his men did reuell▪ shoare, with a rich prise he had lately tane, was come also to Tunis: betwéene whome their acquaintance being former, there was no neglect of gratulatiōs in the highest imbracement,

and my company at the present was welcometo both: when againe, Captaine Bishops, in the presence of Captaine Roup, began to solicite me in his former purpose whose words were by Captaine Roupe as readily secūded &amp; theeir persuasions so inlarged▪ being as I thought bound euen to my life, by the curtesie of the one, and fyred now also with the riches the other had brought in, neither of them were so ready to aske of my consent as I of free will was foreward to graunt: whose company both of them seeming with gladnesse to be welcomed, Captaine Roupe hauing made sale of his commodities, Captaine Bishop and my selfe reuelling out the time with him, a ship well mand and prouided for me, and we three combind together in one faction: let the reader thinke we a
                     •…
                  e now at sea, whe
                     •…
                  e we thriued so succesfully that I blu
                     •…
                  h to report the rapine that the hands of so fewe did execute on the bodies and substa
                     •…
                  ce of many: onely this that part of the purchase in this voyage we had gain
                     •…
                   wee made sale off at Sophi, and Sancta-cruci in Barbary, and the remainder with out sailes we conueid to Tunis, when Captaine Bishop, finding himselfe not per
                     •…
                  ectly in health, after his ease and superfluous reuelling here a shoare, nine shares of our pillage being deuided betwéene him, Captaine Roup and my selfe, he was contented for a while to continew at Tunis, and Captaine Roupe prepard his ship to put off againe for Sophy in Barbarie, where I heard imediatly after, he met &amp; consorted with Captaine Iennings: and I on the other side rigging my vessell, and redying my men: Captaine Bishop then, neither deducting any part out of my share for the ship at his owne charge he had furnished forth for me, I now put forth for a voyage my selfe. When encountring with rough winds, and vnseasonable tempests, and my men many of them falling sicke, and in their sicknesse perished, with the best expedition that experience could teach, with the rest which

remained, we made way for the coast of Ireland, and ere long we anchored in Baltimore, where finding yt coast cleare, our ariuall out of daunger, and our entertainment free, we there repaired and fresh victuald our ship, and there receaued in the most part of my present company namely Iohn Spencer, and Thomas Spencer brothers, Samuell Read, and Richard Baker: the rest which I then tooke in, being not now taken, and in hope they may liue to doe their King and countrey better seruice, I hope no indifferent man, will condemne me for concealing their names. With whose assistance being againe strengthned and my ship in fresh plight, I put on for the coast of Spaine, where nere the Ilands of Meuera, I met with a french ship called the Margaret of Maruill, sayling from Lisborne whose chiefest lading was suger, twixt whom and vs, there was no great encounter, before my frenchman (although he seemed somewhat hot at the) first began to submit, whome wee presently boorded and ransacking her lading (which as before we discoured was but sugers) we found her beneath to be better stuft then aboue, for at the bottome of her hould we tooke out eight thousand french crownes, and so much of her chiefest lading, as we thought fit for our present sale and burthen, giuing the ship backe to the Maister to make for Fraunce, or without offering to him or his men any other hurt. After which keeping still at sea, I met with a Duch ship, of a farre greater burthen then my owne I was Captaine of, whome I gessing more auailable for me in the enterprise I had in hnad, I compelled him to change with me, more for feare then for loue, &amp; so gaue them leaue to depart without further outrage: the tenth of May following and in this present yeare of his maiesties reigne, I met also with another french ship, called the Mary, of a Marchant of Saint Malos laden with wine, twixt whom and vs there was a small fight, but their resistance being in vaine, she was

made our owne: when Ierome Lockey a fellow though poore in shew yet he was cruell at sea &amp; foreward in fight, who getting downe into the hould (before I had notice) and the ship had yeelded, when meeting the Marchant, and perceiuing his lading to be nothing but wines (not of my knowledge I protest before God) he tooke three or foure cable ends and most cruelly I confesse abused the Frenchman, to make him expresse what other lading then was extant in sight, his vessell contained? who streight brought him to eight hundred Dollers so conningly hid, without which course I faithfully beleeue wee should neuer haue found them. And which summe I must graunt he presented to me, the coine I deny not but I willingly receiued, yet I neglected not to checke him for abusing the man. Which ship, and the riches of the Margarite I had taken before, for as yet I had made no sale of her goods, I had aduised my maister Peter Brush and though I say a skilfull mariner, to bend his course againe for Ireland, and expressely for Baltimor: the course was by him and in generall disliked, since wee had bene their so lately and my name so fresh in memory about the coast, although not as yet proclaimed for a Pirat: but see the will of Heauen, that against all persuasion I should bea maine furtherer of mine own ruine &amp; the ouerthrowe of my men, for no persuasion nor resistance would alter me, but our course must be readily for Baltimore.
               
               But see how it happened, the Frenchman whom I first tooke in the Margarit and the Duch also whom I compelled to change ships with me, hauing made for England, had deliuered my name and iniurie done vnto them, to the right honourable of the Councell, as also that not long before their surprisal I had made my reside &amp; victualed my ship at Baltimor, the which belike amongst diuers talke some or other of my men had made knowne to them, which their Lordships vnderstanding, and

to preuent such outrages committed to their neighbour nations and friends with whom they had league, they presently caused one of the Kings maiesties ships, ouer whome Sir William Saint Iohn was Captaiue, not so much alone to scoure the coast, and surprise me, as to preuent that place, to be a nourisher and ayde to any such offenders in that case as my selfe. Which Gentleman, in the Kings ship lying at road, had intelligencers lay vppon the mountaines in the mouth of the harbor, who were alwayes ready to giue him instructions of the neare arriuall of any man of warre, or other ship whomsoeuer: when to my fate it so vntimely happened, that I was the first, and the spies by the bearing our topsaile and conducting our prise, had giuen him to vnderstand for certaine, there was a man of warre comming in, who presently caused his ship should be haled vp close vnder a place called Iustice Crookes Castell, where she was impossible to be descried, &amp; least our espial should make vs keepe off: So that we were on the sudden fallen withinhis commaund, and vnpossible to retire ere that we had any notice to be forewarnd, or power to resist our dāger, in which distresse not without much terror perceiuing our case, vppon his first sommons we yeelded our selues, when Sir William Saint Iohn caused his long boat to be sent out to vs, and himselfe in person came vs aboard vnto whom I did (as (at my arraignment) we all resolued to plead this excuse,) that being as true it is, I was prisoner in Tunis, and from that thraldome released by Captaine Bishop, I was bound to obey him, and all that I did was vnder his commaund, that at our last watering at Ballimor, Captaine Bishop was in our company, which now I must confesse to be an vntruth, and that there by his constraint and sleights, most of my men being brought aboard and by him compelled to vndertake this busines we hauing now got this aduantage, in a suddaine storme and growne sea to loose

his company, our purpose of comming in was to yeeld our selues: not doubting but his maiestie in commisseration of my estate being neuer detected before, bought from a slaue, Bishop being Lord of me, and compeld to his will, I should sooner obtaine his mercy, in which Kings beare the tipes to be Gods on earth, then the rigor of Iustice, which hath power to condemne my wretched yet innocent life, and that himselfe whose worthinesse I had heard of, would be so gratious a friend to the integrity of our cause, that my men also, whom I then protested to be compeld to the action, since we all yeelded without any violence offered, himselfe would be the testimony in our behalfe: Who very wisely contested vnto vs, that so farre as our dealings had bene honest, &amp; our iustification true, he would be our friend to the vtmost, and our foe in no part: so seazing vppon our ship and goods and imprisoning my selfe and company, wee were by his commission directed from Baltimor to Dublin, from Dublin to Bristoll, where my friends morsorrowed to see me now, then euer they reioyced to bee hold me before, yet neuer neglected to visit my company, allowing me meanes to beare me like a Gentleman, nor ceasing since both with purse and paines to haue recouered my peace.
               But what be fore I had so cunningly excused, by the prouident and searching eye of the Councell, was found to be faulty, andrruth being waighed in the scailes of Iustice we were found too light, so that hauing remained twenty daies in Bristoll, I was from thence from Shiriffe to Shiriffe directed to Newgate, my brother comming along and bearing me company, who labouring like the carefull Bee in my businesse neuer idle, solliciting here and labouring there, and who had hopefull expectation and promises I should find mercy that had for my offences deserued none, I built not yet my trust on so shaking a foundation, but although to supply the

company of mymultitude of friends whose loue came daily to visit me, I bare an outside of mirth, I h ad a hart peece of sorrow, &amp; considering in my thoughts how I had wronged the stranger, and those whose losses I could neuer right, how I had vndone many &amp; had but a lifeto satisfie all, I desired not now to build, for that where I might not continue, but labour for that where I should liue for euer. I thought it not requisite now, to forget Heauen for earth, the soule for the bodie, nor heauenly pleasures for temporall goods: I acknowledge now that in a worldly building the stones must be broken, hewen and squared, ere they be fit to make vp the worke: the corne must be thrashed, winnowed and purified before it be ready for nourishing bread: the whirlewind must first blow ere Elias be rapt into heauen, so euery sinner must be cut, hewen and squared, with the blowes that beat vppon his guilty conscience, be threashed wi nnowed and purified with prayers, repentance and amendement of life: and sighes must make way both for body and soule, if we meane ere to come to our heauenly Ierusalem. I remembred now that vncookt meat is vnwholesome for man, and vnmortified men be no creatures for God: which made me in my chamber in the houres of quiet alone, neuer haue the Pensiue-mans practise out of my hand, nor the penitent mans-practise outof my heart: therefore I must say to him, it was vrgently done who informed the Counsell, that the Saterday, be fore my tryal &amp; first imprisonment in the Marshalsies and in my imprisonnement, my first meeting with Captaine Iennings, who at sea together did call brothers, and being with him but orderly mercie, he reported to their Lordships we were mad drunke: this was informed to be done, and whosoeuer did it, I must needes tell him it was but a homely message, since it is no good nor charitable office to heape vniust iniuries vppon miserable men: for I protest, I had that testimony in my selfe, that my

sorrow had washed away my foulenesse, and loathing my life I inuited my death, knowing there is no death where there is no sinne, for by sinne death entred into the world, and the wages of sinne is death, so that what I was to loose, I was sure to loose as soone as I had life, but the life that I looked for should neuer haue death, which patience and resolution of mine, the diligent Preacher that both labourd and found in me I doubt not (for truth) but he will speake and confirme, which Christian end of mine I expect, that insteed of me it shall encrease comfort in my friends, and be a sufficient satisfaction to my aduersaries, of whom on the bended knees of my heart I humbly craue pardon, from whome being men I feare not deniall, since I am sure it is sealed of our Maker in heauen, &amp; so from a free and vnburthened heart, a patient mind and willing steps, I goe out of my chamber in the Marshalstes, the Friday morning being the two and twenty day of December to make my death-bed at Wapping.
               Of whom Reader if thou destrest more, though he be the first of number placed in the booke, he was the last of seauenteene that suffered: first he made his deuotion and prayers with an affirmatiue tongue, threw away his hat as he went bouldly vp the ladder, and being demanded of a straunger stood by him, If as yet he had heard no good newes from the King? he answered him, none sir but from the King of Kings: and therefore with Peter I must resolue and say I looke for a new heauen and a new earth, according to his promise wherein dwelleth righteousnesse: he sung (to a sillable) the one and twenty Psalms, dyed a repentant sinner and a Christian, and by the diligence of his naturall brother, was brought to the keeper of Newgates house in Newgatemarket, and from thence as a Christian was buried in Christe-Church.
            
            
               
               The discourse of Captaine Iennings.
               
               SInce you are thus farre (gentle Readers) led on with this discourse of Captaine Harris, I doubt not but you will expect the like of the rest, which cannot in Captaine Iennings be so well performd as in the former, for the education of his youth was 
                     •…
                  o meane and low, he could neither write nor read, yet notwithstanding it is not brought to your eyes vnder his owne hand, the report for certaine was taken from his tongue, and thus it is.
               From my childehood (quoth he) I was wholy addicted to martiall courses, espetially in the manly resolution of seafaringmen, I was not disaniamated at the reports of others dangers past, nor afeard my self to encounter with tempests to come, whereby in many voyages returning from Sea, I grew to beare the name of a skilfull Marriner, which so soone pu
                     •…
                  t vp a selfe conceit in my thoughts, that I grew ambitious straight, to haue a whole commaund, and held it basenes to liue vnder checke. It likt me well a shipboard to see the Captaine but bid, and his will in all things was straight obeyd, and such a one in my ambitiō I resolud to be, wc authority and place, finding my present meanes &amp; friends vnpossible lawfully to raise me vnto, I bluntly resolued, as we vse to say, to attaine to it then by hooke or by crooks. To which purpose, comforting my selfe with a retchles crue, and such as loued ryot as well as my selfe (for I must truely confesse it was one of my sinnes) we were not long before we had made vp our company, furnished vs of a ship, and by the name of Captaine Iennings I was knowne at Sea, so that in the Queenes maiesties raigne, during the continuance of the dissention betwixt the King of Spaine &amp; the Hollanders, I found such a safe refuge and retirement, into Dunkerk, after many haynous spoyles committed on their Dutch Fly-boates. Pinkes and passengers in them, that my

name grew so odious, my offences so multiplied, that being knowne to the state, I was proclaimd a Pyrate, and seueral ships both from England and Holland, made out to lie in waight for my apprehention, which though long first was at last so effected, that by the English I was taken, &amp; brought prisoner to the Marshalseys, expecting nothing but for my time of tryall, and hoping for nothing but present death.
               When my louing sister so labourd with petitions to the states that lay heere, and to diuers Marchants, I had formerly wrongd, wherein was my promise of reformation of life, and vowes of seruice to their country, which they both knew, and I was certaine I could able them in, proudly spoken of my selfe, that not a man in Christendome could stop a leake vnder water better then I, and but without boasting I could say hardly so wel, which vertue known to them, with other my many resolutions, they pittied my fal, were petitioners for me to the Queene, contented themselues to sustaine their losse by me, and twice by this meanes they procurd my pardon, a grace from them so sufficient, that if I had had grace to haue conceiud it so, &amp; made good vse of their fauours, my sins had not bene so many, my reputation more, my fauour might haue bene greater, and the contempt of me lesse, my seruice haue still bene held acceptable▪ &amp; I a good member in the common wealth: but see how I requited the last of their graces. Namely not only my pardon procurde, paying my charges and setting me at liberty, but also transporting me ouer, gaue me commaund ouer a Flyboat, and in their seruice sent me to sea, in which imployment, my enterprises not thriuing so successiuely as before, and the pride of my heart not stooping, but cōtemningto attend their reproofe, who had saued my life, taking fit aduantage by the forehead, with their ship &amp; furniture, &amp; such men as I had drawn to my part, I leaue their seruice, intend now to serue for my selfe, and by this 
                     〈◊〉
                   hauing taken a Spanish Caruell by the way, I am

ariued at Sophie in Barbary, where vpon my arriuall, vpon some displeasure that was concein
                     •…
                   against other Pirates, concerning the breaking certaine contractes they had made with the Gouernour, and during the time of examining o
                     •…
                   my goods, I was kept prisoner, but at length was released and 
                     •…
                  ound such fauour, that my prize was sold to 
                     〈◊〉
                   best aduantage, for which 
                     •…
                  auour I not neglecting my thankefulnes to the Gouernour, and diuers others I had found my friends, I was contented to spend there the latter end of the yeare, in which time I came acquainted with Captaine Bishop and Captaine Roupe, who did so combinde our selues together, that the following spring we went forth, Bishop Admirall, Roupe Uiceadmirall, and my selfe rearadmirall, where what purchase we tooke of any nation in this voyage, still we returnd and made sale of onely at Sophie, which amounting to so great a summe, it is incredible to report, I will onely satisfie you that the most part was consumed in excesse: and so to this discourse.
               These prizes we had thus taken being heere sould, there was some difference fell betwixt vs three concerning our shares, which dissention betw
                     •…
                  ene Captaine Roup
                        •…
                     
                   and my selfe was soone attoned: but Captaine Bishop because we would not yeeld he should haue a full part more then vs both, here we left company, and Captaine Roup
                        •…
                     
                   and my selfe put forth to Sea for a voyage againe, when after a seauen daies sale; a leake sprung in Captain Roups ship, which growing so forcible it could by no meanes be stopped, Captaine Roupe and his company were compeld to come aboard of mine, and his ship sunke immediately after.
               Our strengths being thus confinde into one hould, w
                     •…
                   were by this time come to the I
                     •…
                  e of Silly, where we met with a ship called the Iohn Euangelist, and without much paines made her our prize, the twenty six of October immediately following, and making for Ireland, we tooke als
                     •…
                  
                  
a french ship laden with brasse and other rich commodities, and so bearing vp to Baltimor, we sent the purse
                     •…
                   with the long boat a shore, to deale with the kernes for hogges to victuall withal, &amp; vnder that pretence shew them their bills of lading: for it is to be vnderstood, that this part of Ireland and the kernes the inhabitants, haue their best strength &amp; support by the putting in and nourishing o
                     •…
                   Pyrates. It is also to be noted, that as soone as any Capta
                     •…
                  e h
                     •…
                  h taken any ship, a cals to the Maister for a bill of his lading, and demaunds what belongs to the Marchant, what to the Master, and what to the Marriners? so that if he leaue them their ship, he takes away none but the Marchants goods, and by this meanes he knowes hereafter what he is driuen to be accomptable for.
               But to the purpose, hauing safely put in here to Baltimor made sale of her goods they had then taken, and victuald their ship in readines to depart, Captaine Iennings being a shore, it happened him to fall in liking with an Irish woman, and what with golde and perswasion he so farre preuailed with her, that he wonne her to spend her company at Sea with him, and so hoysing sailes away they depart.
               At whose going out of the road, his iniuries being spread and whose name the third time proclaimd a Pyrate, they happened vpon one of the Kings ships called the Trementany, sent out against them, ouer whome Captaine Williams was Captaine, and for this disseigne had strengthned himselfe with some of Captaine Hews company, betwixt whom being a most corragious encounter, the Captains on both sides brauely behaued themselues, the one fighting for honor and the other for safety, but Captaine Iennings finding himselfe the weaker, since his cause was the worser, his ship being of swift speede and hauing wind as it appeares, could goe off at his pleasure, fearing the danger, was glad by flight to be freed of his foe: so that the shaking ague of this feare, ended the burning feauer rose in both the Captaines mindes, namely Captaine Iennings
                  
and Captaine Roupe, and they vowd now whosoeuer they met though the 
                     •…
                  oe had the oddes, they would dare him to fight, and so put on to the coast of Spaine, where in their sayling they met with two Spanish ships, made vp to them, with all speed possible, and being come each of the other, within reach of shot, either without haling th
                     •…
                  m, or commaunding them to strike, the 
                     〈◊〉
                   newes they heard was abroad side, by which vnwelcome messengers vnderstanding at full, what their neighbours were, and to what vniust comming their purpose was, being two ships wa
                     •…
                  likely appointed, and their enemie but one, they redied themselues for a needfull defence, so that betwixt them straight was a cruell fight▪ the Spaniards not doubting in respect of their oddes to goe off with ease, and the other resoluing with the help of their resolutions to conquer at pleasure: for the space of full foure houres was this fight cruell, one fighting in hope of spoile, and the other to saue what their paines had got: sometimes victorie promising fairely to the one, to the disharting of the aduerse, and anon declining from them to looke cheerefully on the other, to the discouraging of the countrary.
               But the vallour of the Captaines (though it was resolute and desperat) being waid in scales of tryall, it proued too light to counterpoise the iust o
                     •…
                  ence and resistance of the Spaniards, so that ten or eleuen of Captaine Iennings company in this rash enterprise being 
                     •…
                  aine, himselfe hurt and twenty more of the same confederacy dangerously, shot, their ship s
                     •…
                  re beaten, and the sound terrifide, with the best wings of hast which their sailes could flye withall, they are glad now to be quit of those foes which euen now they were so head-strong to quarrell with, and the Spaniards on the other 
                     •…
                  de, not scaping so well they could boast of the day, any more but this, they were glad of escape, by this they were both quit of the others company.
               
                  
Which two disasters hapning to them one in the necke of another, namely their escape from Captaine Williams, and their mischieuous conflict in their attempt against these two Spaniards, the whole company began to murmure against Captaine Iennings, gathered the voyce thereof from thus ground, and was this vttered, that no doubt their crosses past and daungers present, so many of their consorts being sore hurt, and their ship so out of order, it was as a iust iudgement of God against them, in suffering their Captaine to bring his whore aboard &amp; there to wallow in his 
                     •…
                  urucie, when counsell was to be held for their future safety: others strengthning it with this, why should he haue his 
                     •…
                  hore for himselfe any more then the rest? al cōdemning the permissiō, &amp; exclayming against disorder, amongst whome there was no order, they pretended straight to haue a redresse, Which being subtilly vnderstood by Captaine Rou
                        •…
                     , he hauing men of his owne to strengthen his part, and finding it the fittest aduantage for his aduancement, he soothd them on to the action in hand, and vrgd them with this, that successe in their con
                  
                     •…
                  ition was neuer found, when a woman was more Maister of the Captaine, then the Captaine of his men, that in all the purchase (though vnlikely yet) they should euer take, through the inticing flatteries, with which he seemed to be besotted and bewitched, the maine profit thereof should redow
                     •…
                  d to her, and they like thrashers should labour and sweat to bring the sweete vnto other mens mouthes, whereupon the strength of their spleenes being heere incouraged, the heat of their murmur grew vp to muteny, and in a gi
                     •…
                  y maner breaking into their Captaines cabbin, whome they found set and imbraced by his Irish Mistres, they boldly began to reprooue his course, condemne his vndertakings, and exclaime against his 
                     •…
                  osenes; whose haughty spirit boyling to heare his condition controld (especially in the eare of her he was now ioying with) by those whome he held his commaund might

checke, with a trunch
                     •…
                  on that lay nere to him he struck 
                     •…
                  ne of them on the head, cleares his cabbin of the rest, and hauing beaten them all to a bay, he cals thus to Captaine Roupe: Captaine Roupe will you suffer me to be thus 
                     •…
                  aunted and abused by the madnesse of rascals, whome a spot of mischance doth driue to dispaire? But he not hasty to succor his expectation, hi
                     •…
                   company made good ag
                     •…
                  inst him, and by their violence and outrage compelled him to retire to the Eune-roome, where to auoide the he 
                     •…
                  t of their fury, manning the dore, one of his cōpany discharged a musket vppon him, but his life being reser
                     •…
                  d to a future shame for his actions, it most vnfortunably mist him, and the fire of their rage, being alla
                     •…
                  d by the perswasion of Captaine Roup which in this heat would haue consumed his life, it was onely agreed, and their tempest satisfied to haue him discarded from his Captaine-ship and confind from the pleasure and company of his wench, by being detained in the gun-roome, ouer whome Captaine Roup was made keeper, and instituted also their Captaine both of them and their ship: onely here is to be noted, in this ship there was great store of riches, and so they now put out to the southward Cape.
               In which time, Captaine Iennings remaining prisoner with patience (since he found resistance was bootlesse) he so insinuated with Captaine Roup that he brought Captaine Roup to preuaile with his men, that they gau
                     •…
                   their consents for his liberty of the ship, and then againe dealing priuatly with Lodge, Williams and others, he had wrought them now to repent their rashnes, and the rather for that Gilbert Roup hauing the power in his commaund, he did not seeme so wholy to rely on the trust of them who had formerly ben of Captaine Iennings company, as he did on those had bene of his owne, neither in countenance and outward shewe (seemed any way so kind and affable to them) being, indeed a man of more

sterne and obdurate nature then Iennings was, which they disliking in him in heart, but not daring to vtter, his owne affection being the stronger, they were compelled to be content.
               So that being now in the southward Cape, they hapned vppon a French pinck with rich lading, against whose assailement the Frenchman making a forceable resistance, they were at length come to grapple, when Captaine Roup &amp; his men as well in the ayme of credit to be seene forwarder then Iennings or his men, h
                     •…
                  pe of riches which they guest they had in chase, as also by the politicke persuasion and egging of them on by Captaine Iennings, when they came to boarding, Captaine Roup and most or al of his company being ransacking the pincke, Iennings tu
                     •…
                  nd now to perswade his men thus: that the ship was his owne, and he had bene their Captaine, that much riches they had purchased together, and he had giuen them their faithfull shares, that occasion was now offered to shewe their loues friends to him, that if any thing had bene amisse, his vallour should redeeme it, and his courtesie amend it, &amp; that Captaine Roup made but instruments of them for his present vse, who by his cruell and stubborne nature, they might perceiue he would requite with vnthankefulnesse and no doubt with their ruines, when aduantage should further it.
               With which pers
                     •…
                  asion of his, he so forcibly preuailed, that they in an instant called their Captaine, and began to ready themselues, to resist Captaine Roup &amp; his forces in the pincke when he should offer to come aboord againe, which he intending to doe as also 
                     •…
                  o fraight their ship with most &amp; the best of the luggage they violently withstood him, nay told him further, that if for their former labour, they might not freely share in the profit was found, they were now to become as eager foes to him and his company as before to the Frenchman.
               When Captaine Roup iudging of the tricke, an
                     •…
                  
                  
knowing his strength too weake to disable them he thought it best to come to composition, and be glad of part, least compelled by necessitie he should loose all, so that a frendly agreement is made betweene them: Captaine Iennings is Captaine of his owne ship, Captaine Roup of the French pincke, all are friends and they put now for the coast of Ireland.
               When in the way, Captaine Iennings hauing regaind his former riches, charge, and a share in the spoile Roupe had tane from the Frenchman, he began now to consider of the 
                     •…
                  cklenes of his estate, the vnconstancy of his men, and the dangers that were instant to the course of his life, he desired now in heart he might make his peace and procure the liberty of his country againe, although with the tender of all he had, to which purpose he entended to order his actions, when safe occasion should suffer him, though concealing his intent to himselfe, and so they put into Baltimor, which harbor lies in my Lord of Clāricards country, and to whome he meant to submit himselfe, but by no meanes (whether his men suspecting his intent or no I am vnresolued) he could not be suffred to goe ashore, onely foure of his company being sent out with the long-boate, namely Thomas Renolds, Iohn Lodge, Iohn Williams who was Botson of the ship, and one Iames a 
                     •…
                  renchman who was Trumpeter, to discry if the coast were cleare and their arriuall might be in safety, who being landed resolued with themselues, neuer to returne to carry him newes, but euery one to make shift for one, and so ashor
                     •…
                   to auoide suspition they betooke their course to seuerall waies, Iames the Trumpetter hyring an Irish kerne to b
                     •…
                   his guide, by his conductor had his throat cut. Renolds was first taken, by a Captaine of my Lord of Clanricards, and brought before my Lord in his Castle, who confessing how and with whome he came in, he was with a charge conueid to the Castle in Dublin, but Lodge and Williams came not till a fortnight after.
               
                  
But Iennings now seeing their returne doubtfull, began straight to suspect himselfe, and put off againe from Baltimor vp to the riuer of Limbrincke, which is my Lord of Toumonds country, yet desiring still to yeelde vp himselfe, if safely he might, where lying at anchor both with Captaine Roupes ship and his owne, yet so far wi
                     •…
                  hout reach of my Lord of Toumonds Castle, that he might goe off and come on at pleasure, he now in his long boat himselfe put on neare the shoare, and caused a parle to be sommond to the Castell, of which sommons my Lord vnderstanding, he sent downe to him one of his sonnes and diuerse of his men to know what they would? which being deconded, Iennings expressed to them that he desired some conference with my Lord whom if it pleased his honour he would attend in his own Castle, onely that offering thus voluntary to put himselfe (being in danger) into his Lordships hāds, he would haue a couple left aboard his ship as hostage for his safe returne, which vnderstood at ful by my Lord, his request was graunted, &amp; Iennings was cō
                  ducted vp to the town &amp; two of my Lords chiefest men sent as pledges aboord, when y• next morning Iennings being brought in presēce before my Lord, he presently related the story of his life, &amp; offered to submit himselfe, his whole cōpa ny, the estate &amp; purchase he had, vnder his Lordships protection, with condition, this: his Lordship would be his mediator for the Kings maiesties mercy, and procure his pardon, when his Lordship in wisdome finding it not requisite to articulate with him further then he required, since two of his followers I and kinsmen too were aboard his ship, and seing both the ships as well his owne as Roupes, with their whole companye
                     •…
                   and fading, except himselfe, to lye so aloo
                     •…
                  e they might goe off at pleasure in spight of controule, he grauely thought it fit to giue this fish line till he might more iustly choak him, with the baite he coueted: and the reuppon gaue him his protection for a named time, for himselfe and his company,

seemed 
                     •…
                  o regard him with intire respect and promised him withall, that so farre as w
                     •…
                   his honnour he fastly might, he would proue his honourable friend to procure his p
                     •…
                  rdon, vppon which hope, Iennings emboldned, he rioted in pleasure and reuelled in the towne, carried one of my Lords sonnes and diuers gentlemen inhabiting there about, diuers times aboord his ship, where his entertainement to them was wonderfull, and presents giuen vnto euery hand, shewing them withall, his Lordships protection, and relating the honorable promise his eares receiued from his owne tongue, which was he would do his best to procure his pardon, which inticing promise of my Lords, though Iennings had heard it, and in regard of the protection, was brought to beleeue, neither Roup nor the rest would be brought to trust, onely now and then some two or three by turnes going a shore for fresh victuall and so returned againe.
               For the space of a fortnight they thus continued, in all which time by no persuasion of Iennings, nor hope of my Lord could Roup or the ships be brought within checke, neither my Lords men who were left in hostage for Iennings be deliuered a shoare. Till one day hauing feasted voluptuously with them aboord, and drunke hard, he out of his owne motion made the offer vnto them, that that night they should goe with him and reuell it a shoare: from this he was disuaded by some who at this instant were more staid then himselfe, but he neglecting their councell, the long boat is cald for, they are set a shoare and reuelling it in Limbricke, and the next morning no doubt had returned againe had not this which followeth happened that night.
               Captaine Roup hauing intelligence that my Lords men were gone with him to land, comming aboord the ship, he contriued with the maister, and into his long boat conueyed out of the gun-port most of Iennings shot and powder, as with purpose but to borrow it, and the next

neede to repay it againe: with which being stored he hoysed sailes, and away goes he: and the Maister of Iennings ship in the morning missing the pinck, seeing neither Captaine norpledges returnd aboord, doubting some trechery, he doth the like, and my Lord of Toumond taking note how the ships were gone, and that the limit of his protection giuen, had expirde the date: he commaunds Iennings to more safe custody, yet with expresse charge to be worthily vsed, and hauing by this space directed his letters to Sir Robert Chichester Lord deputy of Ireland, of all these proceedings, there is by this, a warrant come to my Lord Toumonds hands, from the counsell of Ireland, to direct his prisoner to Dublin, who not onely gratiously vsing of him while he was in his charge, but by expresse commaund, resigning him ouer to those had order for his safe conduct, he gaue him out of his owne coffers a hundred pownd starling, to defray his expence.
               Being now come vnto Dublin, and examied before the Councell, he denied not what he bad bene, and pleaded for mercy since he came in voluntary, which by this that followeth may appeare no doubt had bene graunted, had not his former life bene so contemptible: for during the time of his stay in Dublin which was aboue three moneths, the right honourable Earle of Clanricard, and Lord Toumond who in thatspace was present there, had so labord for him that he had all the lybertie of the country within ten mile about both to hawke and to hunt and none to attend him but only on Iames a musition, who was my Lord of Clanricards man prouided this he returnd to the castle for hislodging atnight.
               Nay, after that, by the direction of the Councell here, he was to be sent for England: and that they had receiued true and perfect instructions what an ill liuer he had bene, in that they would not seeme to dishearten him in the iourney he was to take, they dischargd him of custody, and as it had bene to haue imployd him in some affaires of import,

gaue him charge of a letter to the Maior of Chester, whose purpose was to conuey him to London. From Chester he was conducted to the Marshalseyses in Southwark, where remayning euen since May last, to the eye of men, he liued a careles life, or dreadles of that he did thinke was to come: one being mery a drinking with him once, demaunded of him thus: faith Captaine Iennings and how did you liue when you were at Sea? how (quoth he) I reioyced more to heare the Cannons voyce that bid me to fight, then the Church-bell that cald me to prayer: I fought not as chickens fight, for their meat to sustaine nature, but for store of gold, to maintaine ryot: Another time being drinking in the parlor, where they vse to dine in the prison, it being somewhat afore Bartholmewtide, in hot weather, he sat iust with his face in the sun, when one demanded of him, Captaine Iennings why doe yor sit with your face in the Sun, it will make your head ake: fogh pox quoth he what do you tell me of the head-ake, that shall hang in the sun shortly when my necke shall ake, and I do but practise now how I shal fry then. The same day that Captaine Harris was brought into prison, being the satterday before the arraignement, which was the monday following, he was in the Marshalseys yard, throwing of snowbals, iust as Captaine Harris was comming in at the gate, who hauing a snow-ball at that instant in his hand, ready to throw, one cald vnto him aloud, Captaine Iennings Captaine Iennings, Captaine Harris is comming, Captaine Harris quoth he, I loue him well, but and the hangman himselfe were comming I would throw out my throw first: these haue I set down to signifie to the world the desperatenes of his course, the intemperance of his actions, and the slight regard, he seemed outwardly to take of his soule, in that little walke was giuen him to looke vpon, betwixt his life and death. The time of his tryall being come, he was the first that stood indited and arraigned for those seuerall piraces before recited, and with

these of his company, namely Thomas Renolds shoomaker, Iohn Williams Marriner and Botson of his ship, and Iohn Lodge, who being demanded what they could seuerally say to the inditement, Captaine Iennings began to intercept the clark, &amp; in this maner to plead in their excuse. Alas my Lord what would you haue these poore men say? they can say nothing to it, if any thing they haue done they were compeld vnto it by me, and I must answer for it. To this excuse by that honourable court he was thus answerd, that they doubted not but his owne conscience bore witnesse against him, that he had heard inough in his seuerall enditements, to answer for himselfe, and so they wished him let euery one of them, and if it should appeare either by testimony or circumstance, as heinfer
                     •…
                   they were cleere, the whole Court should be glad of it, and to that purpose they should be heard themselues, or any for them at full. Wherevpon Thomas Renolds, by the name of Thomas Renolds shoomaker, was againe called, &amp; demanded of the Clarke of the Admiralty, what he pleaded to the enditement, whether guilty or not guilty? who answering not guilty, and desierd of their Lordships, he might with their gratious fauour be heard, and which being by the honourable of the counsell vpon his request presently graunted, he pleaded thus, That at the time of Captaine Iennings anchoring in Baltimor, he was a Iourniman shoomaker resident in Corcke, whome Captaine Iennings sent for, (as he might haue done for any other) to bring bootes or shooes to furnish both himselfe and his whole company, who with a couple of boyes in hope to make a way his maisters ware with profit, came aboord his ship, and fitted them also farre as his ware wold serue, for which, according to his owne price, he was from Captaine Iennings owne hand orderly paid, and he deliuered the mony to one of the boyes to carry, and sent them to stay for him some respite a shore, while he being inticed by the Captaine and others to rest a while and be merry with

them, was with the ouercharging of many made so drunke that he fell in a sleepe, in which time the winde seruing, and they hauing compassed themselues of all thinges fit, the fi
                     •…
                  st time he waked he found himselfe at Sea, and the Captaine and others in fight with one of those ships, for which he stood now indited, and for proofe heereof he brought in another shoomaker, to iuis
                     •…
                  fie that at the same time he then inferd, he was working in Corke, and liued honestly by his labour so that if any thing he had done, it was done in the company of them by whome he was compeld vnto it, and therefore quoth he, I humbly desire both your honours and the Iury, to mingle mercy with iustice, conscience with equity, &amp; so commisserate my case. Which tale of his hauing so good a relish of credit, he being the first that expressed the forme, though many after (both of Captaine Iennings, Captaine Harris, and Captain Longcastle
                        •…
                     
                   cōpanies) endeuoured to follow the course, their honours leauing his defence to the good consideration of the Iury to determine how true it was, he onely by their verdit was returnd not guilty, and the rest (with their Captaine) conuicted as fellones and pyrates vpon the high seas, and in maner and forme as they stood invited. And after their conuiction and iudgement they were conueied backe to the Marshalseys, from thence on Fryday morning to Wapping, the place appointed for their execution: where Captaine Iennings being the first that was cald to goe vp to his death, and seeing that he had bene al this while deluded with a fruitles hope (for vpon my knowledge both Captaine Harris 
                  
                     •…
                  nd he the day before their execution, did report they were repreiued) he did now in soule repent him of his sinne, complayned of his lusts and ryots, as the causers of his ruine, confest that before this he had receiued pardon for his heynous transgressions, and had not the goodnesse to desist from ill: he desired God of his mercy to receiue his soule, &amp; the world at his death to pardon his body, &amp; so desiring the multitude of spectators

to pray for him and sing a psalme with him, he was the first was turnd of the ladder, and after him both Lodge and Williams, as his consorts and confederates found guilty in his actions, did likewise suffer death.
            
            
               The discourse of Captaine Longcastle alias Lancaster, &amp; them of his company that sufferd, namely William Tauerner and Iohn Moore.
               
               THis William Longcastle was directly knowne, and so accused by one of the right honourable of the Counsell, at the time of his tryall, to be an arch-pyrate, and formerly a confederate with that famous Ward, although both himselfe, Tauerner and the other did stifly deny to stand guilty according to their inditement, or to deserue wherby to be accused for robbing the Susan of Bristoll, of whome one Anthony Wye was Maister, which piracy was thus committed.
               One maister Hal a credible marchant of this honorable Cittie, furnishing forth a ship of his called the Vlisses of London, for the west Indies, and instituting in this his venture (which amounted to a thousand pound) one of his men as gouernour and factor thereof, she from the riuer of Thames, puts out to sea, where meeting with seuerall disasters, both to her selfe and her men, in the many alterations incident on the waters, the Factor thought it fit (hauing by the marchants appointment the whole order and trust) to put in about Plimouth, to strengthen and repaire their former mishaps, when inquiring for Marriners that were best and ablest to venture themselues in so long a voyage, and furnishing their wants with all that before their necessity asked, he came acquainted, and did take into his company &amp; aid, these three by the names of Longcastle, Tauerner and Moore, and with these he puts on to Sea, in hope of successe, where anchoring to take in fresh water at Sophy in Barbary, they met with y• 
                  Susan
                  
of Bristoll, ouer whome was maister, Anthony Wye, of the same City: betweene whome, being both trauellers from one nation, there was friendship &amp; congratulations enterchangeably offerd (betweene these two houses and householders) on the waters, as formally as then they had met ashore: as, one day the Susan to feast the Vlisses, and the next day the Susans men to come aboord of her, which occasion now this Captaine Longcastle not loosing the aduantage of, he practised priuately with this Tauerner and Moore, for the surprisall of the Susan, and to the furthering and finishing of this vniust enterprise, he wrought with Maister Hals Factor, to inuite the Maister Anthony Wye, with as many of the others as he gotinstructions had commaund in the Susan, to come to banquet and reuell aboard their Vlisses, of which curtesie offerd, Master Wye hauing no occasion to conceiue any suspition, of any mischiefe inuented, since they had formerly enterchangeably dealt in the same curtesies, and espetially lying both at refuge now in Sophie road, and so neere vpon the shore, their desire is condiscended vnto, and he with his agents in the long boate belonging to the Vlisses, is brought a boord, their feast is furnished, their entertainement welcome, and the healths goe round, when these three, eying their opportunity, in the edge of their entring, they slip away by turnes, and with some other whome they had won to be linked as their consorts, they priuately man out the long boat, and comming neere the Susan, making their pretence to bring backe their maister, and the rest of their friends, they presently board her, clap her men vnder hold, and ceeze on her goods, hoyse sayles, and by the helpe of this stratagem, in this ship of Bristoll, they are out at Sea, which Maister Wye hauing notice of, and iudging by their flight of the innocency of the Factor, the Vlisses makes on for her West-Indian voyage, the Maister Anthony Wye is left at Sophie, and after as conuenience would affoord him, makes his returne to England,
                  
where complaining to the high Court ofadmiralty of this outrage offerd, it was needfull and iust for him, in his owne discharge, to g
                     •…
                  ue in the names of these three as actors of this pyracy, till time should giue meanes for their apprehension and answer.
               But see how if happened, there was with Captaine Longcastle in this ship of the Vlisses a Negro, who not a month before, he had bought to be his boy and brought to be a Christian, who in the rashnesse to surprise and hast to get off, he had neglected to take with him him left, in the Vlisses, whereby the Factor was constrained to take him along with him, and at his returne deliuered him to maister Hall at London, vnto whom also (vrging his owne innocencie) he related the mischance had happened, disco
                     •…
                  sed the manner, and to his maister (as it is here recorded) deliuered their names, who for his owne discharge, and the discharge both of his ship and goods, he deliuered so much to the Lord high Admirall, and so his factor as the season serued with the like trust is sent to sea againe: in whose absence, this Captaine Longcastle hauing his name infamous for a Roner, noterious for a Pirate, and knowne for certaine to be a confederat with Ward, he belike not doubting so much of himselfe as was here manifest, he puts secretly in at Causon bay neare Plimmoth, and with this Tauerner and Moore, thought to liue priuatly, till they could fully compound with this Anthony Wye, for his iniury past, being certaine no other Englishman could witnes against them. And this is a thing worthy note amongst these pirates, they neuer see or knowe of their aduersarie, but they are as perfect as himselfe, for how much they must compound, which may seeme strange to some, since amongst theeues it is vnlikely there should be any order but all hauock, and catch that catch may to be all their stake. But with these sort of robbers it is not so, for being once sure the burthen is their owne, the Captaine

cals straight for the maister or marchant, and demaundes forthwith for their billes of lading, whereby he knowes what belongs to the marchant, and what to the mariners, when the marchants venture is alwaies taken for lawfull prize, but the sailors goods is most commonly restord, and this bill doth the pirate Captaines most carefully keep and lay vp, and as they call it, for their owne discharge.
               But to our purpose, this Long castle liuing thus lurking to and fro about Cornwal, the infamy of his name brought him in more suspition then any ready accusstion that was extant against him: so that this report of him being carried about by rumoring tongues, and buzd abroad in somany ears it was at last brought to a right worshipful Knight and a Iustice of peace, who calling him before him, he demaunded from him of his course of life, &amp; as how and where for the last three yeares he had orderly spent his time? who being able to render no confident and resoluing answer, he thought it good in his discretion to commit him to prison, yet pretending no further, but till he could put in sufficient sureties for his good behauiour: when in the meane time this prouident Gentleman, sent first to the Uiceadmirall to enquire against his name, and after to the high Court of admiralty, if nothing were inferd against him, when after search it appeared vppon record the former piracy against the Susan of Bristoll, and the maister thereof Anthony Wye, and his deposition against Longcastle and Moore to the same purpose, whereuppon they were all three, committed to Exceter Gaole, in the County of Deuonshire: and against their time of tryall, as the other remooued to the Marchalseys, and at their day of arraignement according to Iustice stood indited for the same offence, vnto which invitement they pleaded not guilty, wherevpon Anthony Wye by name of Anthony Wye of Bristoll mariner and maister of the Susan, was in person called to giue in euidence against them, who being seene

the day before in Court, and not now making his personall appearance to iustifie according to his eath, it was then demaunded of Longcastle (the Court hauing notice of asmuch) if that during the time of his late imprisonment in the Marchalsies, he at no time had conference with the said maister? he denyed not but he had, as also if that neither himselfe nor any other for him▪ had priuatly dealt to giue any secret composition with the said Wye, to neglect his appearance, and so to hinder the iust and lawfull proceedings against his life? which he thus answeared: for mine owne part (quoth he) I neuer offered him peny for the saue-guard of my selfe or any of my company, neither had he any reason for it, since they were not the men that were then at the fact: yet he had heard that some friend of his in his behalfe, had offered him in full satisfaction, restitution to the valour of all his goods lost, as also in gratuity to himselfe fifty pound, in consideration he would be silent▪ it was then demannded of him who that friend should be? he answered he knew not, whereuppon by one of the Councell it was vrged, how vnlikely it was that any man should offer a composition for him of so much mony, and he be a straunger to the motion: besides what reason had any friend to make such an offer if his friend were cleare since the lawe is so iust in euery mans case, nay when the Kings maiestie himselfe in the care of his subiects, sends both his Councell of state and Councell at lawe to sit euen as vmpires betweene Iustice and their liues. Whereuppon maister Hall was called, to certifie whether his man at his returne, had not giuen in to him the perfect names of those three men as they stood there indited, and the true description of their statures, who answered the names and statures of three such men his man had giuen him, but whither they were the men, he neither durst nor could not say, for he had neuer seene them (and his man was now at sea) till they were now arraigned: in which doubt they

cald earnestly vppon the Court, Anthony Wye being absent M. Halls factor at sea, and none as yet personnally to giue euidence against them, that their Lordships would be mercifull vnto them, and not to cast away their innocent liues vpon meere presumptions, that no other euidence as yet comming in, it was thought of the spectators and all (but the Court who knew there the men) they should then haue bene quitte: when straight was called the Negro who before had bene his man and reserued in piruate to se how long their impudence would hould out, when first being demaunded if Longcastle had bene his maister, he answeared yes: then was asked of Longcastle if the Moore had bene his boy, who resolued that he had: the boy was then questioned, if he was not at sea with him in the Vlisses? the boy affirmed it, and Longcastle being demaunded the same question, although he staggerd at the first, could not strongly deny it. Uppon which affirmation, the euidence being strong against Longcastle, it was pleaded by the other, and especially by Tauerner that they were not the men who were then at the action: and whereas there was no more but the direct title of their names against them, there was no doubt many more of the same name, of Tauerner &amp; Moore in this spatious Kingdome besides themselues: to the resoluing of which doubt, then Moore was called againe and demannded by the Court whether they three namely William Longcastle, William Tauerner, and Iohn Moore, were not the men each in particuler Maister Hals factor tooke in for the better furnishing his ship and performance of his voyage at P
                        •…
                     imoth? he answeared they were: whether they three were not the three men feasted with Anthony Wye in y• road of Sophy in Barba rie in the cōpany of the aforesaid factor in y• said ship of the Vlisses? he answeared they were, and whether the said Longcastle, Tauerner and Moore, leauing their promised voyage in the ayde of the Vlisses of London, did not

according to their former practise, offer their ontrage against the Susan of Bristoll in manner and forme as they stood invited? when he affirmed directly they were the men.
               Upon which, Longcastle desirde of their Lordships to be heard, and inferd that he denied him not to be his boy, but intreated of the Court, that the tongue of a Pagan, an Infidel, whose testimonies were no euidence to confirme the Iury, and whose words were to be held in no regard, might not be the are to hew downe the tree of his life, but if that his transpressions against the law had deserued death, I beseech your Lordships quoth he, let the tongue of a christian and not of a Pagan cut off my life.
               Which words appeared vnto all eares that were present, to be vttered from the vch
                     •…
                  ncy of his soule, and from the Court he was thus resolued. That where he desired to haue the oath of a Christian, himselfe, &amp; the Moore had confest he had made him one, which was the most vertuo
                     •…
                   &amp; blessedst deede that he did showe in his whole life: but then Lordships tould him withall they must giue him to vnderstand, that it was not the approouement of his tongue, nor that he had b
                     •…
                  ne his boy which made them giue credit, that now they stood guilty, but the resolued oath of Anthony Wye, whose ship they robbed and whose goods they ransackt, who had seene them, spoke with them, swor
                     •…
                   against them, I and themselues had labourd to compound withall (and wonne to keepe out of the Court for the iniury they had done him) whereby it appeared and so now they must satis
                     •…
                  e the Iury, no sunne can shine clearer to shewe vs a moate, then this eui
                  
                     •…
                  ent testimony to witnesse thair blemish: besides, that from the time of their imprisonment in Exeter Gaole, till this houre of their arraignment, not one of them all that can well bring in a credible certificat how well or ill they haue spent their times, vppon which instructions giuen to the Iur
                     •…
                  , and the s
                     •…
                  ale so put into their hands, to

weigh y• condition of their liues the Iurywent forth &amp; staid not lōg ere they brought thē in guilty, at which sentence against them, Longcastle &amp; Moore spake neuer a word, but Tauerner whether he thought he could out face the cause, or y• he feared death more then the rest, for my part I will not iudge, but he grewe vehement, and called for a booke to sweare in his innocence, although I was credibly certified both his Captaine and himselfe did after in the prison with these words confesse, that we are hartily sorry we shall be hanged now for a petty action, that haue merited talke in matters of worth. So hauing their sentence, they were conueyed backe to the Marshalsies, where I must credibly speake of them, they behaued their liues so carefully for the future comfort of their soules, as if they had neuer bene the men, the whole course of whose actions, had bene addicted to such an vngodly purposes, making their way to the gate of saluation, by confessing their sinnes, and knocking thereat for entrance, with sorrowfull sighes, and repenting hearts, which no doubt flewe open vnto them: they were three men who were neuer seene to laugh from the sentence of death to the power of execution thereof: they desired not the company of their friends▪ but made prayers their acquaintance, they lamented now that (in hope to gaine a little breath which they must be sure to loose) they had slandered and belyed their consciences in denying their crimes, they freely cōmended their transgressions to the lawe that was ordaind to punish them, they willingly resignd their bodies to the earth, the mother of mankind, and made for their graue, and most religiously gaue vp their soules vnto Heauen from whence it was giuen them: and so from creatures of wickednesse hauing created themselues Angels of goodnesse, from practisers of folly, proued counsellers to faith, and so from the sea of mischiefe, through which their whol
                     •…
                   pilgrimage had trauailed, making their bodies the fit sepulchre of repentance, from the

Marshalseys as the rest, they were conueid in a barge to Wapping the siluer ore borne before them as an embleme before their eyes, that riches they looked for, and vniustly sought to finde it at Sea, where the Captaine first, and the other two after (as they confest they had deserued) according to Iudgement they suffred death.
            
            
               The discourse of Minas.
               
               THis William Minas was a Marriner, married and had his abiding in Cornewall, who not contented with that sufficient meanes that God and nature had prouided for him, being (as so was most of them all) a man of comely personage, and of an able body, by vniust courses thought to strengthen his fortune, so that vsing meanes to get to sea in a pretty ship, called the Concord of Plimouth, vpon the coast of Fraunce he met with a Frenchman, and as the custome of Pyrates is, being the stronger party, without asking her leaue, he ransacked her goods: but as it is certaine, he that once endeuours to begin to steale, doth straight endeuour and learne to lye, since lying and stealing are as inseperable companions as a theefe and receiuer, so that Minas had a colourable tale at the time of his araignment, bearing some likelihood of truth to excuse his theft. Namely that making home from Spaine to his abiding in Cornewall, his ship (the Concord) beaten with weather, began to saile and put himselfe and men in distresse, neere the 
                     •…
                  ast of Fraunce, where he met with this Frenchman, so that he hauing farre to saile, and the Frenchman neere his arriuall, he compounded and gaue him satisfaction to exchange ships with him, &amp; so dismissed his lading from his to the Frenchmans, and the Frenchmans to his, promising withall, with this condition, that the Frenchman shold receiue his ship here in Englād, but named no place: they thus agreed the Frenchman departs for Fraunce, &amp; Minas he priuatly

in the night puts into his abiding in Cornewal, presently absents himselfe for three quarters of a yeare, giues order to his wife vnder that cu
                     •…
                  ur to labor his protection with the viceadmirall, and leaues the ship without guide or owner, as a derelict due to the Lord Admirall, at A
                     •…
                  izor in the bay. The Frenchman now hauing bene robd of his ship &amp; goods, and knew by an Englishman, comes and expresses his iniury to the high court of admiralty, and there directly deposes, that he was robd, neuer inquiring for his ship nor feeding himselfe with hope that ere he should heare of her till at last welcome tidings is brought where his ship anchors, and as a derelict she was ceazed to the Lord Admirals vse, vnto whose honour by petition complayning of his wrong, and proouing the godds to be his, his Lordship giues order she is straight restord him, and warrants are directedout for the apprehension of Minas, which he hauing intelligence of, lurking close or not daring yet to be seene abroad, he vseth an inward meane by agreement to stop the Frenchmans complaint: the Frenchman on the other side, knowing he had lost his goods, and considering belike, that his life might make him some satisfaction, but no restitution, consents to the composition, take 
                     •…
                  his mony, Nay, is content (in regard he was bound to it) to goe to the Uiceadmirall, or Court of admiralty, and there to vnsay what before he had iustified, that is to say, that his shippe was lent and not stolne, which being done, Minas appeares, not like an owle thats seene but in the night, but like a bisd that flutters by day, reuels it gallantly and securely, and thinkes now in his heart that all is safe.
               But he that hath commission vnder the Lord Admirall for the discouering and routingout of such infectious members, and the law most carefully on the other side, not suffering such offenders to 
                     •…
                  ubberouer their iniquities, to the encouraging of others, and hartning them to these co
                     •…
                  ses, brings me this Pyrate to apprehention, from apprehention

to arraignement, where his owne confession and the former circumstances duely examined, it was made euident by the Court to the Iury, how euident this packe and close far
                     •…
                  le of knauery, was ripped vp: wherevpon according to the Inditement, he was brought in by verdit guilty, and accordingly receiued sentence, from the Marshalseis he was conueid to Wapping, where repenting him of his sinnes, he confest the fact, onely labourd to acquit the reputation of a worshipfull Gentleman, that stood tainted in suspition to haue contriued and dealt with him in concealing this pyracy, and so yeelded himselfe to death.
            
            
               
                  Of Thomas.
               NOt to lengthen out paper with this poore fellow, of more then appeared either by his confession, arraignment or execution, it is onely thus, he was apprehended vpon suspition, making saile of some goods, and being strictly examined, he presently confessed what he had done, whome he had robd, and in whose company: namely in the company of one Lawding Barry, that is a pyrate new, and was set on shore in Ireland: vpon which confession being arraignd, &amp; condemned he amongst the other suffred death.
               Thus Reader haue I truely brought to thine eyes, the discourse of Captaine Ieames Harris, vnder his own hand, the course of his life which men should be sorry for, and the goodnes of his death, who (though enforced to be vntimely) yet men should reioyce in it: eight of his company with those that suffered with him, namely Peter Brush Fisherman and Maister of his ship, Iohn Spencer and Thomas Spencer brothers, at whose death it drew pitty in all the beholders, for the elder suffering first, and then the younger turned off, he hung beating his hands on his brothers breast: be sides these was Samuell Read, Richard Baker,

Ierom Lockey, Ieames Smith, and Roger Notting, yet these, though they be first placed, they were of seauenteens the last that finished the act of the tragedy: to make woefull the rest of the sceane, was Captain Iennings, Iohn Lodge and Iohn Williams of his company, and to make dolefull the whole proiect, was Captaine William Longcastle, William Tauerner, and Iohn More of his company, and betwixt whom as miserable Chori, comes in Thomas 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  Minas, to deuide the act: these seauenteene on Friday in the forenoone, made their last testament, so that of nineteene that were condemned in this great sessions of Pyrates, before as honnorable a bench, and as faire &amp; orderly proceedings, as in such cases mans memory can witnesse: two onely from that present execution, who for part of that following day, reioycingly gladded themselues with hope of continuing life: namely, Captaine Downes and Captaine Halse, but their peace being cro
                     •…
                   by the Kings maiesty and the counsell, more at large vnderstanding and considering of the cruelty and heynousnes of their seuerall offences, betweene foure and fiue a clock in the afternoone, almost at high water, they were also executed: of whose liues and deaths reader, if thou beest pleased with the former, and desirest to be satisfied of the rest, to giue thee content, I haue writ as followeth.
            
            
               The discourse of Captaine Downes.
               
               THis Downes had somtimes liued a hopefull marchant in a place called Langraue neere Colchester in the countie of Essex, till his superfluous expence &amp; retchles life made him crack his credit amongst men ofworth and those he had trading with, his word was esteemed as sufficient as his bond, and his seale would haue bene acceptably receiued for larg
                     •…
                   sommes, till neglecting his trafick and following the sensualleties of his pleasures, he had so farre disparaged both, that hauing brought

himselfe behinde hand, and in danger to those, had put him in trust, that for feare of imprisonment he durst not be seene, he resolued vpon these vniust courses of piracy: he was a fellow but wearish &amp; simple in show, but more violent, cruell and merciles, then any of the rest: when he was at sea he considered not what belonged to the actions he vndertooke, but resolued, that the finishing of whatsoeuer he pretended was well, so it were don: in which resolution furnishing himselfe to wrong, as by his owne confession it appeared both at his araignment, and was read against him vpon record, namely that about midsomer last was three yeares he came into Foy, in Cornwal, in a Portugal Caruil, laden with Sugers, Wines, and other commodities, which he and his company tooke about the Madera
                        •…
                     s: and as he inferred by vertue and strength of a commission graunted from the states of the Low Countries, and the Captaine of the ship, being one Albret Albertson of Ankmers in Holland, and which prize they had lawfully tooke, and sold the most part of the purchase thereof in Foy, either by generall or particuler sale, to whomesoeuer would bye it.
               Upon which coulourable excuse, though there were more then this inditement against him, and he manifested to the honourable of the Court to be a knowne offender, it was yet askt of him, where that commission was to beare testimony in his innosence? which he not being able to show, it was by the Court told him it was no maruail that he could not, since vpon their knowledge, about the time he related there was a strict prohibition by Proclamation for any English to combine with the hollanders in any such attempts, so that he being driuen to silence in that behalfe, and his excuse confuted with apparant truth, it was yet demanded of him who and what they were, that were then in his company besides the Captaine, Albert Albretson, at the time of this pyracy? to which article he answered there was one Iohn Giles, maister Richard Ward and

                  P
                        •…
                     hlip Downes saylors, Water Cox, Hercules Kellam &amp; one Robert Gilly of Perin, but the rest of there names, being most of them Dutchmen, he could not remember, if these then (answered the court) weare in thy company and as thou saiest the outrage committed was don by commission from the states: to purge thy selfe and that it may appeare though heere thou standst accused thou art yet both a good seruant to God and a faithfull subiect to thy King, deliuer then where thou partedst company with them, when thou l
                     •…
                  ftest them, and how in thine own behalfe they may be heard of, the which without halting it appearing to the Court he was not able to doe, his owne examination taken before the right worshipfull S. Daniell Don Iudge, and others of the high Court of Admiraltie, vnto which he had set his hand, was directly read against him, the purpose whereof appeared as it followeth.
               That the sixt of October was twelue months, or there abouts, he shipped himselfe at Plimouth, with one Captaine Browne in a small barke of some sixteene tunnes, bound for Ginny as the company told him, being manned with fifteene men all English, which Browne and himselfe neere Silly met with Captaine Tomkins, in whose company shipping themselues they plyed for Seuerne, but in their course they were forced ashore neere Swansey in Wales, where some suspition rising against them, through their misordered life, the whole company being a land, frō the Pincke. and Tomkins, one Garret and himselfe, more bold to put themselues in hazzard then the rest, they were apprehended by Lewis Mansell and by him committed to the common Gaole at Cardiffe, where after instructions taken how they had liued, they were from Constable to Constable, directed towards London, and were forward on their way so farre as Reading, at a village neere the which, lodging all night, and the Constable not vnderstanding what a charge he had in hand, leauing but a slight guard to attend them, the next morning before day, they

brake out of the hous
                     •…
                  
                  ▪ and from them who had them in charge, and so escaped for London.
               As also being demaunded what riches they had, where they forsooke the Pincke, he confest he had in his pur
                     •…
                  e, twenty barbery duckets of gold, the which one Roger Place of Cambridge had from him, and two little wedges of gold worth forty duckets: that he had a cha
                     •…
                  e and a Iewell, and 80. peeces of Barbery 
                     •…
                  d▪ the which one Dau
                        •…
                     
                   had from him vpon somecomposition between them and which Dauis is perfectly known to Sir Robert Mansel: that one Griffin Bayliffe, likewise had from Tomkins, three small g
                     •…
                  ds of gold and certaine Barbery duckets but all according to his iudgement not amounting to the valew of aboue twenty pound, &amp; that this with some few yards of spanish cloth, was all the riches he had at his first apprehention: being then demaunded of whome, &amp; by what meanes, directly or indirectly he came by that gold &amp; cloth by him confessed, to be held in his custody? he answered, it was most part giuen him in regard of their long acquaintance and friendship together by Captaine Tomkins and the rest, from some of his company hee won at dice: being then questiond, if in Tomkins cōpany or in any ship of his own he had neuer bene vniustly at the 
                     •…
                  āsacking of any Marchant at sea? vnto the which he pleaded he had neuer, but as he formerly confest in the Spanish Caruill, and in the company of Albert Albr
                        •…
                     son, which Caruill they brought into Foy, and new built her there, made her a crosse saile, and there lay at anchor fiue weekes, from whence with the said duch man going to sea againe they met with a fleet of Hollanders of twenty eight saile, who took him prisoner with the whole company cōuayed them to Amsterdam where after three weekes imprisonment, 
                     •…
                  their integrity vnderstood of, they were without further charge discharged by the States.
               Unto which examination of his standing stiffely and appro
                     •…
                  ing▪ hi
                     •…
                   innocence, It was then demanded of him if be

                  had neuer heard of a scotch ship, called the Royall of Lesth? at the very name of which he was presently astonished, for he did expect &amp; was confident, that although his owne conscience bare record against him, for many offences committed in that case, yet hoping that the testimony of that Pyracy would not be brought in against him, he doubted not but for want of euident witnesse to acquit himselfe of all the rest.
               
               
                  Yet to the demaund replying with a a faint answer, he said, he had neuer knowne of any such ship, neither as was suggested against him, had he euer bene Captaine in a man of warre at sea: vpon which answere, by the name of Iohn Downes of Longraue, in the county of Essex, marchant, he was the second time endited for apyracye, committed on the high seas, vpon a Scottish ship of Leeth, called the Royal, and the lading in the same, vnto which inditenient, he pleaded not guilty, wherevpon was called to giue euidence against him, Iohn Shipman of the Citty of Bristoll Marchant, and being swore to giue true and perfect testimony against the prisoner at the bar, concerning the pyracy and spoile aforesaid, and the maner and forme thereof, the purpose and euidence was expressed as followeth.
               
            
            
               The euidence that was giuen a
                  gainst Captaine Downes.
               THat acording to the charge of his oath, himselfe and his brother Thomas Shipman being at Portugall, about the end of May last was twelue months did there hyer and fraught the sayd ship, the Royall of Leeth, of one Iohn Matherson, maister thereof, to transport and bring from thence such trafficke and commodities, as they had there

ready to lade for Bristoll: vpon which agreement made &amp; confirmed betwixt the maister &amp; them, himselfe and his brother did then lade on boord the said Royall, fifty tunnes of salt, and aboue a hundred pound of Royalls of plate, being in sixe bags of pepper, one pack of Calecutes, two hundreth waight of Tobacco, fiue hundreth waight of cordage, for the account of themse
                     •…
                  ues and their partners.
               With which ship and goods making for Bristoll, betwixt Padslow and S. Iues, vpon the coast of Cornewnll, on Thursday being the 28. of Aprill, 1608. early in the morning they espied a sail a head, who shortly came vp to them; haled them and demanded of whence they &amp; their ship was? who presētly resolued them they were of Bristol, and were thither bound: and then on the other side questioned them accordingly, of whence they were? who auswered them they were of the sea, and therevpon stearnely commaunded the maister to strike his top sailes, who resolued them he would not: wherevpon some small fight being entertaind betweene them, the Royall being to weake for the man of warre, both in men and munition, they presently laid their vessell aboord, and many of them to the number of ten entred her hold, and there tooke out this Iohn Shipman, his brother Thomas Shipman, the scotch maister Iohn Mathewson, and the whole company, except two or three boyes, and put them in the Cockboat: so leauing them to the mercy of the mercilesse

windes &amp; waters, to be driuenso ashore, frō which it was 7. or 8. leagues at the least, 
                     •…
                  d when doubtles they had all perished, the Cocke being so ouerladen, had it not pleased God euen when they were almost driuen out of sight of thē that Captaine Downes and his company, suspecting belike &amp; as it after appeared, that they in this wretchednes, on the sodain dismissed had carried their mony with thē, they in that opinion set saile with all the speed that might be, &amp; fetched vp the co
                     •…
                  kboat againe, &amp; took them into their ship, first threatned them, then stripped 
                     •…
                  hem, and searched them for their money, but finding none, the Captaine cōmaunded them to be stowed in the hold, &amp; there kept them in terrible feares for the space of 12. houres; in which respit they tooke two of the ship boyes hung them vp and whipped them with whips, stil demanding of them betwixteuery lash, what mony they knew or had beard the maister or marchant had in the ship, &amp; where it was lodged? who poore soules willing to hold out (til 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •…
                  mitie cōpeld the contrary) for their maisters 
                     〈◊〉
                  , they walled them about the heads with small ropes, wrinching their foreheads and temples with such cruell torture, It would haue made a sauadge ryrant euen in pitty haue wept, to haue heard them crye and lament, so that the vtmostwhich they did know, &amp; morethen euer they had heard of, in hope to gaine some respit of ease, they were forced to confesse.
               Then tooke they this Iohn Shipman himself, and

bound him to the fore-mast, and beat him with a 
                     〈◊〉
                  , the wretched man cryed, and his brother lam
                     •…
                  ed to heare him: he begd for pitty, but they were flinty hearted: and though that he had told them the truth of all they had, they esteemed it for falshood, and commaunded straight he should be hanged vp by the necke, whose will like a cruell theefe was straight obeyd, and poore Shipman cut downe againe ere he was a quarter dead, &amp; there left either to recouer by the mercifull hand of God, or there to perrish by the vniust hands of 
                     •…
                  leines: while they not fully satisfied with what he liad confessed and they partly had found, they fell to ransacking a fresh, and tooke this Iohn Shipmans chest and his brothers, and tooke out from his own chest fiue rugs and two suites of apparel, and three rings, wherein were set two fine diamonds, two sutes of clothes, and a paire of corrall bracelets: out from his brothers, together with a whole chest of apparrell, some diamonds, Tobacco, and other things belonging to one M. Anthony Wye, worth a hundred Marks: and so rifling them of all their goods &amp; commodities but their salt, they deliuered them backe againe their ship and departed in the euening.
               Being then demaunded whether Iohn Downes were Captaine, and did appeare vnto them to haue the chiefe commaund of that man of warre which tooke them, as also what manner of vessell she was, and of what burt hen?
               To which article he answered, that the sayde

                  Iohn Downes arraigned and indited, was Captaine and expresse commaunder in that man of warre the which surprised them, and that their ship was a barke of Perin, of 25. tunnes or thereabouts, which belonged to Iohn Bates of Perin, and now one of these Pyrates, as also that of his assisting company, was Thomas Martin of Salcous, Peter Newman of Lalant, William Hatch of Foy, Fletcher of Perin, Richard Nowell of Pensance, Thomas Lamlet of Cargraue neere Salth
                        •…
                     sh. Iohn Trayes of Minifer In Cornewall, Iohn Mathew, Edward Higgins of Colbrooke, Iohn Clarke of London, Iohn Barber of Dartmouth, one Garret of Dublin, and two or three others, whose names he knoweth not: farther, that comming home with his ship to Bristol, and being so certaine of these men both by their names and countenances, his brother and himselfe were both eager in their pursuit, not so much he protested in desire of their bloods, as to haue some satisfaction for the goods they had rob bed from them of other mens, and was put in their trust, though not caring for their owne: in which dilligentinquest, it was the fortūe of this examinates brother Thomas Shipman, to happen vpon this Captain Downes, &amp; caused him to apprehended in Wales, from whence he was sent towards London, but by the way making an escape, which caused their pursuit to be fresh against him they were the meanes that after he was arrested in Cornewall, committed prisoner by one Maister Resworricke, this is the man, and all this is

the man, and this is the perfect truth by the oath he hath taken.
               
               Unto all which he neither hauing power to deny, nor excuse so shamefull a truth, but by his filence to the euidence approued his guilt, he as the former was by verdit conuicted: and though by labor of his father, and the assistance of some friends, and in especially of such whome he had formerly wronged, in hope to draw some satisfaction from him, he was repreeued that morning when the other seauenteene were executed: but his gratious maiesty hauing from his prudent and graue counsell, had vnderstonding of the iust proceedings, and the ouerlooking of the in
                     •…
                  ements, euidence and examinations of them all and finding his actions more hatefull then any of the rest in the morning had suffered, expresse charge was sent for his present execution, while he stood imboldened with hope of life, as one vnworthy to liue or haue taste of any fanour, when other of more merrit, partly for the like, yet not for so grieuous offences had suffered death, So that at foure of the clocke in the afternoone, he was conueyd from the Marshaiseys to Wapping, where as strange was his life, so stubborn was he at his end, scarce making any outward shew or appearance of a mortified man: heauen graunt that he made him more rectified within: since not two houres before his execution, he was heard boastingly to report of the worth of his robberies, as if there had bene credit in doing ill, namely how many seueral pyracies he &amp; his cōpany cōmitted in the habit of maskers, with visards on their faces, and without speaking a word, making cruelty the organ to vtter their mindes, wherby neither their names nor their fauours were to that day knowne to the iniurd Marchants, notwithstanding they had seuerally &amp; many times robd those who had formerly knowne him: of whose end, wishing others to be forewarnd by him, he desperately dyed.
            
            
               
               The discourse of Captaine Halfe.
               
               THis Captaine Halfe was a Gentleman of good discent, of mi
                     •…
                  de behauiour faire of speech, and 
                     •…
                  teous of conditions, yet to approoue that the diuell sometimes hath his working in the most gratious subiects, it shall appeace in this was confessed by himselfe. Being resident (quoth he) about Cornewall, not thinking so ill as these bad intents. I met with one Read an expert Gunner, and who had formerly bene of my antient acquaintance, when after some familiarity passed betwixt vs, finding me belike a fit subiect to be wrought vpon for his purpose, he perswaded me downe to Casen Bay, where he brought me
                     •…
                   acquainted with Captaine Sacall, with whose delightfull discourse of the life at Sea, his itching pronuses of the raising of my fortunes, and the aspect of the riches which he gaue 
                     •…
                  e to behold, I was so alterd from what I had bene, so coynd to a new disposition, and so bewitched with his inticements that my heart had consented to be one of their crue, ere he had fully perswaded me, or my tongue could vtter my voluntary &amp; free resolution: for which forwardnes of mine, in a neat ship be readily had called the Iacob, by the perswasion of the Gunner, and some liking it seemed he tooke towards me himselfe, he made me Captaine and to Sea we are bound, where neere the straights, wee met with a welthy prize, entertaind a long and cruell fight with her, the victory yeelding to neither part, till most of the men on the aduerse part were either slaine or hurt, whereby at length, our pursuit being eager, and their necessity preuailing with them, they were at length compeld to yeeld, of whose goods we hauing made saleof to our best aduantage, when we came to parting euery single share, the worst and meanest in the ship came to forty pound, wherein I must needes say Captaine Sacall made it a conscience to giue euery one his due, rather with the

most to a pound then to deduct a penny from any: of this prize Captaine Sacall had for his share three thousand pound and I had fifteene hundred, with which purchase and profit 
                     •…
                  o highly encouraged, I continued for the most p
                     •…
                  rt spending it as loosely ashore, as it was gaind 
                     •…
                  autly at Sea, approouing it to be true, that goods got by the Deuill, are most commonly spent vpon his dam: or as we vse to say in English, b
                     •…
                  ly gaind and worse spent: for whores doe infecte the soule with more leprosie and lothed spots then the body: in whose company I was taught to make my actions to be reasonable, the which I now approue to be frantick rashnes, where my wil learnt to haue power aboue my vnderstonding, by whome wearing the sight that Lust had giuen me, I accoūted yt beacōs of strumpets eies (who neuer blaze but they betoken il) the 
                     •…
                  dstone of my life and the seamarkes of my safety, by whome being guided as the markes of falce knowledge, I am now runne on the rocks of destruction, whose allurements are worse the spiders cobwebs for they weare their fatall weapons, not to catch birds but flies but these make their 
                     •…
                  nchantments so strong, that neither miad wife, husband youth nor age, whosoeuer they happen on, but if they will attend theft Syrens notes, ware is not sooner melted by the fierce fire, then they wasted by the flame of them: husbands neglect their wiues, wiues loath their children, youth their profit, age their health
                     •…
                   and in the wasting of all this, they are accompaned with ryot, who shines like a gallant in silke to day, &amp; is turnd to be more miserable then an hospitall to morrow: dicing in the day, drinking at night, throwing with one hand our wealth away from vs and tossing infirmities and drop
                     •…
                  es into our bodies with the other. But the report of these sinnes being no refuge to my shame and more fitter to be repented, then by me to be recorded, I must now tell, I arriued in England, and my name being knowne, there was strict waite laid for my apprehention. But see how it happened: a kinsman of

mine who bore my name being by some officers, who had my search in charge, was suspected and imprisoned for me, and in the end knowing of my abiding, compeld to giue a loath intelligence for his owne discharge, he being hardly set against by those were my aduersaries: vpon whose instructions I being apprehended in the west country, and from thence conueyd to the Marshalseys, I there continued since the beginning of the last sommer, till the time of my conuiction, where as in a Mirror I beheld the miseries of other men, and began now to consider of mine owne: after my conuiction I was repreeud, by the painefull labour and purse of some of my allies, to restore the memory of our name vndetected: &amp; now when I little feard or thought of death, I am brought to be executed: at which place humbled before the seat of his mercy, I aske pardon at the hands of God, and forgiuenes from the hearts of men, and so thus goe vp the lather to my death, to goe down I doubt not to a peaceful graue, and to rise at length to my sauiour in heauen.
               
                  Of all which Pyrates, gentle Reader, if thou hast had intelligence, of more then I haue heere set downe, I should haue bene glad to haue had thy instructions, But to him that before this hath not knowne so much, I pray him to take these collections thankfully, onely of Captaine Iennings himself &amp; William Tauerner, of Captain Longcastles company somewhat omitted at the time of their execution, I will remember now to set downe.
               
               
                  Captain Iennings being the first in the commission directed to maister Smith the marshall of the Admiralty, as he was first arraigned and conuicted, so he was the first at the appointed place to

suffer execution: and being called by his name, to commit himselfe to God and to goe vp the ladder &amp; suffer death, he made answer thus: That he hopedno friendly nor christianly censurer would hould so vnconscionably an opinion of him to e
                     
                        •…
                     emso carlesly of the good &amp; future estate of his 
                        •…
                     oule, asto come in the face of so many spectators and the tree appointed for his execution, with a conscience laden with any thoughts, but repentance or trust in any thing but in the mercy of the redeemer of all mankinde: and therefore what he had to speake, was not to theworld, but to those of his company, whome he had partly drawne to this folly, &amp; bene causers of their fall: vnto whom turning he spake thus: my friends, you see we are brought to take our earthly farwell the one of the other, and I am to conduct you, the way I haue heretofore lead you on in place of danger, more induring then when bullets like haile haue falne about our eares, yet you fearelesly and venterously haue followed me, your Captaine, who haue as brauely brought you of as I haue bouldly brought you on: be not dismaid now to do the like, for where heertofore I haue driuen you through the footsteps of transgression on earth, I now wish you be all as resolu'd as I goe before you the highway to my saluation in heauen, where we shall meete amongst the fellowship of Angels, although we are here deuided from the company of men: then be no more dreaded to follow, then I guided by the mercy of Christ,
                  
outdaring death, clime vp this hill he hath built for me: and also resolutly going vp the ladder without saying any other but his prayers, and his thankes giuing, singing a psalme he was turnd of. And as for Tauerner he neere seemed to looke downe on the ground, from the time of his comming to the execution place to the instant of his death: aduancing vp the ladder he said thus: I doe faithfully assure my selfe this is Iacobs ladder, on whose steps I assure I shall be reard vp to heauen, and so he suffered execution. So reader for thy further satisfaction giuing thee the two euidences which were read and personally giuen to the conuiction of Captaine Iames Harris, and for the true testimony what is recorded in this discourse, our report is ended.
            
            
               The examination of Giles Amee Marchant of St. Mallowes.
               
               
                  GIles Amee of St. Mallowes in Brittaine Marchant, aged 22. yeares or thereabouts, sworn and examined before the Iudges of the Admiral
                  
                     •…
                  y, by the interpretation of Thomas Barrel, speaking

the English and French languages, sworne truely to interpret, and hauing Iames Harris, Peter Brush, &amp; the rest prisoners confronted before him by charge of his oath, saith, that he was Marchant of a Ship called the St. Mary of St. Mallowes, which was laden at Cales in Spaine, with forty buts of Sacke, sixteene Tunnes of Salt, two hundred double pistolets in gold: and comming from thence, bound for St. Mallowes, the said ship, and her said lading, was taken about twentyleagues to the Westward the twenty day of May last, by a Flyboat hauing six peeces of ordnance, and ninetie men or thereabouts, whereof Captaine Harris was their Captaine, which being the said Captaine Harris being now prisoner in Newgate, and whome he saw on thursday last, when he was examined before the said Iudges, and who kept him twelue daies prisoner at sea: that the goods properly belongd to this examinate, &amp; Masye Ceferre Marchant of S. Mallowes.
            
            
               The examination of Oliuer Picket.
               
               
                  OLiuer Picket of Maruine in Fraunce, by the interpretation of Thomas Burrill, saith, that he was Marchant of the Margaret of Norsidan, and

knoweth that the same ship came from Layeborne in Portugall in May last, hauing in the said shippe eight thousand french crownes, in royals of plate and Pistollets, being the somme o
                     •…
                   money for linnen clo
                     •…
                  h and wheat he had sold there.
               And being come neere the northern cape, the same ship where of William Gillin was Maister: This company was violently assaulted and taken, on the 26. of may last, by captaine Harris and his company. And that this examinar gaue Captaine Harris a ring of gold, worth 30. crownes or therabout, kept him prisoner about 5. dayes and then dismist the french man and his ship: the riches did belong to him and his partners, Marchants of Venice.
            
            
         
      
   

