
   
      
         
            A sermon preached in the cittie of Glasco in Scotland, on the tenth day of Iune, 1610 At the holding of a generall assembly there. By Christopher Hampton, Doctor in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie.
            Hampton, Christopher, 1552-1625.
         
         
            
               1611
            
         
         Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02610
            STC 12739
            ESTC S103775
            99839520
            99839520
            3948
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02610)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3948)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:8)
         
         
            
               
                  A sermon preached in the cittie of Glasco in Scotland, on the tenth day of Iune, 1610 At the holding of a generall assembly there. By Christopher Hampton, Doctor in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie.
                  Hampton, Christopher, 1552-1625.
               
               [4], 32 p.   
               
                  Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Henry Fetherstone, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Rose,
                  London :
                  1611.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Running title reads: The copie of a sermon preached at Glasco, 1610.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-07
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2008-07
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A SERMON PREACHED IN the Cittie of Glaſco in Scotland, on the Tenth day of June, 1610. At the holding of a generall Aſſembly there. By CHRISTOPHER HAMPTON, Doctor in Diuinitie, and Chaplaine to the Kings most Excellent Maieſtie.
            
               LONDON: Printed by T. S. for Henry Fetherſtone, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Roſe. 1611.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE MOST HIGH AND RENOWned Prince, JAMES, by the grace of God King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland: Defender of the faith, &amp;c.
            
               MOST gracious Soueraigne, I haue preſumed to offer this Copie of my Sermon to your Maiestie, as an accomptant for that which I did in your ſeruice. Not for any doubt I haue of the Serenitie of your alowance: but to conuince the calumniations of a tragicall trifler, ſo farre tranſported for the loſſe of his Helena, that he forgets all duties, becomes a reuiler of the Prince of the people, a falſe accuſer of the brethren, and an inhumane diſquieter of a ſoule that liues with God. Tantaene ais coeleſtibus irae? The brethren to whom hee ſends his narration, are Reuerend in deed, but ſo reſpectiue of the Churches tranquilitie, that the idle ſound of his Trumpet will make no Alarum. Their conſents did runne in the action: or if a ſmall number were doubtfull for a

while, ſome perſons of Honour, and right good place, are yet aliue to teſtifie, that moſt of them came willingly at the end of this Sermon; to acknowledge their ſatiſfaction. Where ſuch independencie is, as hee inſinuateth, it may be ſhewed fairely and regularly, without his Potlids or ſtaues in corners. But if our premiſes haue incongruous concluſions: what validitie is there in his concluſions, that haue no premiſes at all? Superbo oculo veritas non videtur, ſyncero patet. God open his eyes that he may ſee the Princely care, ſingleneſſe, and zeale of your Royall heart, ſparing no charge for ſetling this gouernment, which hath beene most auncient and profitable in the Church: That hee may praiſe God for the ſweetneſſe of your Nature, as his countrymen vſe to doe: And pray to God for the length of your dayes, &amp; continuance of your happy Raigne, as all your ſubiects haue iuſt cauſe to doe. So ſubmitting my poore labours to the cenſure of your clemencie, I will euer rest
            
               Your Maieſties dutifull ſubiect and deuoted Chaplaine Chriſtopher Hampton.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE COPIE OF A SERMON PREACHED AT GLASCO; IN THE generall Aſſembly, 1610.
            
               PSAL. 122.
               I reioyced greatly when they ſaid vnto me, we will goe into the houſe of the Lord.
            
            
               YOV ſhall better vnderſtand the occaſion that induced the Prophet Dauid to write this Pſalme, if you will firſt remember certaine things written of the Tabernacle, in the Booke of Exodus and elſe-where.
            It was called, The Tabernacle of the Congregation, becauſe the people did aſſemble together at it for the ſeruice of God: of Teſtimonie, becauſe it carryed manifeſt euidences of Gods preſence amongſt them. It was portable, and all things belonging to it were ſo, becauſe the people themſelues had then no ſetled place of abode, but

wandred like pilgrimes in the wildernes by the ſpace of fortie yeares.
            And ſome whiles after they came into the Land of Promiſe, it was carryed from place to place: being firſt pitched in Gilgall, Ioſu▪
                4. afterward in Silo, Ioſu. 18. From thence the Arke was brought into the campe of the Iſraelites, 1 Sam. 4. It was taken by the Philiſtimes, ſent back to Bethſhemeſh; and laſt of all, placed in Kiriath-iearim, not in any publicke ſeate, but in the houſe of Abinadab a priuate man. So little was the care and reſpect that Saul had to Religion, that the Arke of God was neglected, and not ſought vnto in his dayes. 1 Chron. 13.3.
            But good Dauid inlarged it, and with ſolempnitie of ioy brought it to Sion his owne Citie. Where firſt he put it within a tent or Tabernacle. For albeit God had foretold that he would not alwayes wander too and fro, but would finde out a place of reſt, where his Sanctuarie ſhould abide: that place being not yet reuealed to Dauid, he prouided curtaines and a tent, whereunto it had beene wonted almoſt a thouſand yeares.
            But when he vnderſtood that the Lord had choſen the hill of Sion to be an habitation for himſelfe, that there ſhould be his reſt for euer: and that the people with vnanimitie did willingly entertaine the exerciſes of Religion in the ſame place. As he was abaſhed to dwell in a houſe of Cedar, and to leaue the Arke of God vnder Curtaines, and thereupon reſolued to build an houſe for God, till the charge thereof was committed ouer to Salomon his Sonne: ſo in teſtification

of his owne gladneſſe, that Religion ſhould now grow to a ſetled certaintie, hee conceiued and writ this Pſalme.
            Thus much of the occaſion. which giueth vs inſtruction; namely that the ſupreame power and authoritie of ſetling Religion; and the oeconomie or diſpoſition of the ceremonies thereof belongeth to the King. Dauid performed both moſt happily, without controulement: and that could not haue wanted here, more then it did in his faire purpoſe of building the Temple, if the bounds of his vocation had beene exceeded in this, as they were in that.
            God requireth double ſeruice from Kings: one is of obedience, as they be men: the other of prouiſion, by reaſon of their office, and as they are Kings: therein they muſt ſerue God extraordinarily aboue all other men, by making holy Lawes, not for the ciuill ſtate of their Kingdomes alone, but in matters alſo concerning diuine Religion, and government of the Church. If this were not an incident of the Royall office, the holy Ghoſt would not haue attributed the deformities of Religion, and miſ-gouernment of the Church to the want of a King. It is an vſuall acclamation in the Booke of Iudges, and the ordinary cenſure of the holy Ghoſt in thoſe caſes, Then there was no King in Iſrael. But how ſhould the want of a King occaſion diſorder in religion, if the rectifying of ſuch things were not within his verge and charge?
            
               Dauid here held it a part of his duetie, ſo did Salomon his Sonne after him: and (leaſt any ſhould imagine that theſe two were priuiledged for thoſe affaires

by particular warrant,) ſo did Aſa: ſo did Ichoſaphat: ſo did Ezechias: ſo did Ioſias, as appeareth in the Bookes of Kings and Chronicles: ſo did Constantine the firſt Chriſtian Emperour: ſo did Theodoſius: ſo did Gratian: ſo did Iuſtinian: ſo did Charles the great, as the Eccleſiaſticall Stories teſtifie: ſo Eleutherius a Biſhop of Rome aduiſed Lucius to doe, that was King of Britaine about 150. yeares after Chriſt, and giueth this reaſon of his aduiſe; Quia Vicarius Dei estis in veſtro regno: you (ſaith the Biſhop of Rome vnto the King) may make Lawes for religion, becauſe you are Gods Lieutenant, Vicar, and Deputie within your owne Kingdome: ſo the municipal Lawes of our kingdome intendeth: for they account not the Prince a meere Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall perſon, as they doe others, but mixt: by reaſon of the power that he hath in both.
            So Paul determineth of this point for the new Teſtament, when hee willeth prayers to be made for Kings and men in authoritie, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty. And what meanes can wee haue from Kings for godlineſſe and honeſty? none verily but by their authoritie and power, whereby as Guardians of both Tables of the Law of God, they make Edicts for obſeruation of the one and other.
            Now to the Pſalme, which conſiſteth of three parts: the firſt expreſſeth Dauids ioy: the ſecond containeth the cauſes thereof: the third hath a praiſe of Ieruſalem, and a prayer for the ſame; my purpoſe is to treat of the two former.
            
               
               1 Part.
               
               Dauids ioy teacheth vs that Gods children be not Stoiks: a kinde of Philoſophers that deſired to be without affections. And further it informeth vs, that godlineſſe ſtandeth not in ſolempne or ſowre lookes. The moſt godly haue their affections: God planted them in man, when he ſtood in perfect integritie vnſtained with ſin. And Chriſt himſelfe was not without them.
            Then it is no part of holineſſe to ſhake off all affections: but to ſubdew and temper the heate of them, when they are blowne with the bellowes of concupiſcence, that no flame be kindled againſt God, againſt our neighbours, againſt our ſelues, againſt our owne ſaluation: this is a ſpeciall kinde of godlineſſe, of pietie, of holineſſe, of Chriſtianitie.
            Take away ſorrow in afflictions, and all chaſtiſement of diſcipline ſhall proue vaine. Where will that godly ſorrow be that worketh repentance not to be repented of? Take away ioy in proſperitie, and no place will be left for thankes-giuing. Take away both, &amp; the Apoſtles rule muſt ceaſe, reioyce with them that reioyce, and weepe with them that weepe.
            
            Seeing then the affection of Ioy is naturall, planted in our hearts by the Creator, of great vſe and neceſſitie for performance of many good offices, the concluſion followeth, that it cannot be but lawfull. Yet the corruption of our nature doth peruert many things that be good and lawfull, and by our abuſe we make them euill and vnlawfull. So we doe in this particular affection, when we ſtudie, when we ſpend our thoughts and time in chearing vp our owne hearts, without regard of our ſinnes, without regard of the afflictions

of Ioſeph, without all feeling and feare of Gods iudgements. In like ſort a great number peruert and change the nature of this affection, when they ſet their whole ioy and delight in circumuenting their brethren: others when they wallow in the mire of their owne filthineſſe and ſenſualitie: others in heapes of their riches with the foole in the Goſpell: in their ſurfets, drunkenneſſe, and exceſſiue riot, with the rich Glutton: in the venime and poyſon of their ſlanderous tongues, with Dauids Tyrant. Pſal. 52. All theſe and ſuch like, are glad when they haue done euill, and reioyce in the worſt things: therefore wee will call their ioy carnall. Chriſt pronounceth a woe to them; Woe vnto you that laugh now, for you ſhall weepe: You paſſe your dayes in ioylities, and in a moment you ſhall goe downe into hell. Iob. 20. Momentaneum eſt quod delectat, aeternum vero quod cruciat. O remember that your pleaſures are but tranſitorie, and your torments euerlaſting.
            There is another kinde of ioy, called Spirituall, becauſe it proceedeth from the holy Ghoſt, and is reckoned amongſt the fruits of the Spirit. Gal. 5. It is promiſed to the faithfull, Eſay 35. They ſhall obtaine ioy and gladneſſe, and ſorrow and mourning ſhall flie away. The Apoſtles felt the fruit hereof, when they departed from the Councill reioycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer rebuke for his name. The like comfort befell thoſe Saints, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to, yee ſuffred with ioy▪ the ſpoiling of your goods, knowing in your ſelues how that yee haue in heauen a better and an enduring ſubſtance. Hebr. 10.
            
               Of this ſort was Dauids ioy here, as by the cauſes thereof ſhall appeare.
            
               2 Part.
                The firſt cauſe of his Ioy was, the readineſſe, the alacritie and chearefulneſſe that hee obſerued in the people, ſtirring vp one another, with a ſweete correſpondencie or conſent, and encouraging themſelues with mutuall exhortations, to go into the houſe of the Lord. This good Prince knowing the manifold graces of God that be diſpenſed in the Church, reioyceth in ſpirit and heart to ſee his people inflamed with a deſire of that place where they might enioy them all.
            By this example hee doth teach and admoniſh vs to conceiue double ioy when God by his holy ſpirit doth not onely frame euery one of vs to the obedience of his word, but bringeth others alſo with vs into the ſame obedience, that wee may all hold a kinde of harmonie and fellowſhip in faith. Therefore if wee will be like Dauid, wee muſt ioy, wee muſt take a delight and pleaſure in the pietie of our brethren: and as euery one is firſt called, ſo to labour and ſtirre vp others to the like vocation. We ought to doe it, firſt in reſpect of Gods glory, which we are commanded to aduance. And if God be to be glorified in all things of vs that are created for no other purpoſe: How carefull ſhould wee be to ſeeke his glory in the ſaluation of mankinde, the moſt pretious thing in the world, if you value it by the price? Or if the friends of the woman did reioyce with her, when ſhee found her groat, how much more worthily may we triumph in an holy and ſpirituall kinde of ioy at the finding of

that pretious groat which carryeth the ſtampe and Image of our heauenly King. Againe, this care is recommended vnto vs in that charitie which wee are commanded to yeeld vnto our brethren. That charging vs with a ſpeciall care of their temporall liues, their name, and goods, doth impoſe a more holy care for their religion, faith, ſoules, ſaluation, and all things thereto belonging. Therefore I make that anther note out of this place and example, that we ought to call vpon our brethren, and to exhort one another to the exerciſes of religion.
            Deſpiſe not this example, but imagine that theſe words be now no more the ſpeach of the Iſraelites incouraging one another, but of the holy Ghoſt, rowſing vs all to the like endeauour. We will goe into the houſe of the Lord.
            
            The benefits that God diſpenſeth in his houſe are of ſuch conſequence that they may well breed in euery man a loue and liking of the Church.
            Whether you looke to the Tabernacle, the Temple, or the Church, God promiſeth his preſence and propitiation to euery one of them particularly. For the Tabernacle, he ſaith, Exod. 25. They ſhall make me a ſanctuary, and I will dwell in the middeſt of them.
            
            Of the Temple, 1 Kings 9. I haue heard thy prayer and ſupplication that thou haſt made before mee. I haue hallowed this houſe, and my eyes, and my eares, and hart ſhall be there perpetually.
            
            Of the Church, where two or three he gathered together in my name, I am in the midſt of them.
            
            Now where God is preſent and ready to help, what

good thing can be, that is not there to be found? Seeing he is the fountaine of all goodneſſe, no good thing can be lacking where he dwelleth. There is peace, ioy, ſaluation, comfort, and happineſſe.
            On the other ſide, where God is not preſent, no miſchiefe is wanting: nor anguiſh, nor affliction, nor heauineſſe, nor feare, nor the worme that dyeth not, nor the fire that cannot be quenched. How miſerably was Saul diſtreſſed when God left him? 1 Sam. 18. euen ſo are the godly, as oft as they are bereaued of of the Tabernacle, of the Temple, of the Church: becauſe they want Gods preſence, they thinke themſelues to be in a kinde of hell. Woe is mee that I am conſtrayned to dwell with Meſech, and to haue my habitation amongst the tents of Kedar.
            
            Beſides Gods preſence in the Church wee haue Chriſt ther alſo our Mediator. Ther he exerciſeth the office of his headſhip: there he gouerneth, guideth, quickneth, and nouriſheth his members, and as a true head, communicateth his owne liuelihood, and happineſſe with them. Furthermore in the Church the holy Ghoſt is inſpired by the diſtribution and influence of his graces vpon the faithfull. Laſt of all, in the Church and holy aſſemblies, the power of Gods word and Sacraments is moſt effectuall.
            And if the Queene of Saba did account them happie which attended King Salomon, to heare his wiſedome: how much greater is their happineſſe, that attend the places where they heare wiſedome, not of man, but the heauenly wiſedome of Almightie God ſounding effectually in his word?
            
               If we ſeeke our owne eaſe, we neede not to goe far for it, as the Iewes did to Ieruſalem: it is brought home to our dores; euery man may talke of it with his neighbour vnder his Vine and figge-tree. If we looke for profit: it is godlineſſe onely that hath promiſes of this life, and of the world to come.
            What would you haue, that is not in it? Pleaſure? O taſte and ſee how ſweet and gracious the Lord is. The testimonies of the Lord are right, and reioyce the heart: more to be deſired then Gold, yea, then much fine gold, ſweeter alſo then hony and the hony combe.
            
            If the pleaſure that commeth out of the Word be ineſtimable: ſuch as eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, and neuer entred into the hart of man. If godlines be great riches▪ that pretious pearle which is to be purchaſed of wiſe Marchants with the loſſe of all we haue. If nothing be more eaſie for vs then to heare the word of God, and to feede our ſoules, at the Lords ſacred Table. If this be that one thing that our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith is neceſſarie: then I beſeech you by the mercifulneſſe of God, and in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, that yee come to it henceforth with more preparation and diligence; heare it with more heede and attention; and practiſe it with more zeale and obedience, then you haue done formerly. And God the father of lights, from whom euery good and perfect gift commeth, bleſſe vs all with the grace of his holy ſpirit, that we may ſo doe indeed.
            
            Theſe Iewels and treaſures, which cannot be found out of the caſquet of the Church, may kindle a burning flame of loue and affection to it: but the commandement

of GOD doth increaſe it yet further. Leu. 17.5. The children of Iſrael ſhall bring their offrings (which they would offer abroad in the fields) and preſent them at the doore of the Tabernacle of the congregation, and he that faileth herein, that man ſhall be cut off from his people. The equitie of this law is great, and remaineth ſtill: viz. that nothing be attempted in the worſhip of God without ſpeciall direction, and warrant of his word Which equitie in this particular of bringing their offrings to the doore of the Tabernacle, is grounded vpon two reaſons, Firſt, that the Miniſters of the Altar might thereby haue a due proportion of maintenance. Secondly, that by theſe publike aſſemblies the puritie of doctrine might be kept inviolate. As for the firſt, there is an honour due vnto the Miniſters for their intertainment. Who goeth a warfare of the owne coſt? Who planteth a Vineyard and eateth not ſo the fruit thereof? Who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not of his milke of the flocke?
            
            That which was commanded in the Law to be giuen, was the Tenth part of all their increaſe: which being once ſequeſtred from priuate vſes, and conſecrated to the worſhip of God, may not, for any thing I ſee, be altered. For I take Tythes to be due to the Miniſters of the Word by the lawes of God and Nature: a matter that will be thought hard to proue. Yet firſt vnderſtand the errour of thoſe that ſuppoſe Tythes to haue drawen their originall from the Leuiticall Law: and that being abrogated, they imagine Tythes alſo to ceaſe, or at leaſt to remaine by poſitiue law alone. Behold a double miſconceit: Firſt, Tythes

were payd amongſt Gods people long before any Law was giuen. As we read of Abraham, Gen. 14. he gaue vnto Melchiſedech the tenth of all his ſpoyles. And Iacob vowed in Bethel, that hee would giue God the Tythe of all he had. Gen. 28.
            Againe, in caſe the originall of Tythes had beene by the Leuiticall Law: yet Tythes need not ceaſe, as ſoone as that was abrogated. I hold this for a rule, that thoſe Lawes are perpetuall, which haue a perpetuall cauſe. But the Law of Tythes hath a perpetuall cauſe, namely, the entertainment and maintenance of the ſeruice of God: Therefore the Law of Tythes is perpetuall. Conſider againe what Abraham did? he gaue the tenth of all things. To whom? To Melchiſedech the Prieſt of the high God. When? Surely 400. yeares before GOD gaue any Law for Tythes. Whereupon I doe infer that this Law of Tythes was grauen in the heart of man before it was written in Tables: And ſo conſequently it was the Law of Nature. Elſe how came it to paſſe, that Iacob did vow, and Abraham did pay nothing but Tythes? What ſhould we thinke? That Tythes were payd by Abraham, and vowed by Iacob at all aduenture? And ſo they ſtumbled by chaunce vpon that which God afterward eſtabliſhed by Law? No, no: theſe Patriarches (though they were reuerend and holy men) gaue God no precedent to make his Law by: But God by a ſecret inſtinct moued theſe holy men to doe thoſe things before Law, which afterward he eſtabliſhed for Law. When the Gentiles hauing no Law, yet by nature doe the workes of the Law, are they not
               
(ſaith the Apoſtle) a Law to themſelues? And why? becauſe they ſhew the worke of the Law written in their hearts. After this ſort he moued Iudah to giue ſentence againſt whoredome, before any Law was written to puniſh it. So he moued Noah to condemne Cham for his vnreuerend behauiour, before the commandement was giuen to honour father or mother. So he moued Iacob to deteſt theft, and to challenge Laban for his wrongfull imputation, before the Law had ſaid, thou ſhalt not ſteale. And euen thus he moued Abraham to pay Tythes to Melchiſedech the Prieſt of the high God, before the Law was ordayned to pay Tythes. And the Law ye know ordayned Tythes to be payd to the children of Leuie: But Abraham payd Tythes to Melchiſedech, whoſe Prieſthood was of another order, then the children of Leuie were: to giue vs to vnderſtand, that Tythes were due to all Prieſts, whether they were vnder the Law, afore the Law, or after the Law.
            Here me thinks, I heare ſome aske, how it happened then, that Chriſt, that the Apoſtles of Chriſt, made no expreſſe mention of Tythes to be payd in the new Teſtament?
            The anſwere is eaſie, that whileſt Chriſt liued, the Prieſthood of the Law was not abrogated. And after it continued ſome ſpace in the Apoſtles time, vntill the diſſolution of that common-wealth: that the ceremonies ordayned of God himſelfe, might be honorably buried. During which time, it was vnſeaſonable for Chriſt or his Apoſtles, to ſnatch Tythes vnto themſelues, which by Law were yet ſetled in the

Leuites. But after that legall Prieſthood was aboliſhed, then to whom Tythes belonged, Chriſt himſelfe declareth, not in words but by his fact &amp; deed. Vpon which I build the foundation of my argument, thus:
            That which Chriſt receiued in right of his Prieſthood of the new Teſtament, is due to all the Miniſters that ſucceede him in the ſame. But Chriſt receiued Tythes in right of his Prieſthood of the new Teſtament: Tythes therefore are due to all the Miniſters of the ſame. The aſſumption is proued in the 7. Chap. to the Hebr. Ver. 9. And to ſay as the thing is, Leuie alſo which receiueth Tythes, payd Tythes in Abraham: For he was yet in the loynes of his father Abraham when Melchiſedech met him. The Apoſtles purpoſe in that place is to proue the Prieſthood of Chriſt greater then the Prieſthood of Aaron. He proues it by two reaſons. 1. The leſſe is bleſſed of the greater. Chriſt in Melchiſedech bleſſed Abraham and Leuie. Therefore Abraham and Leuie are leſſe then Chriſt.
            His ſecond reaſon is drawne from the matter that I haue in hand. The leſſe payeth Tythe vnto the greater. Abraham the father of Leuie payd Tythes to Chriſt in Melchiſedech. Therefore Leuie did acknowledge Chriſt to be greater Prieſt. How? becauſe Leuie payd Tythes that were due to the Prieſt, into the hand of Melchiſedech the figure of Chriſt.
            Here two things are remarkable: Firſt, that Tythes were perpetually allotted to the Prieſt, elſe the Apoſtles argument had carried no great ſoliditie.
            Secondly, that Melchiſedech neither giueth the bleſſing,

nor receiueth Tythes in his owne name: but in the perſon and right of Chriſt. So as that which Melchiſedech did in figure, was in deed and truth done by Chriſt. It was Chriſt that gaue the bleſſing vnto Abraham, as wee may ſee by the efficacie thereof. It was Chriſt that receiued Tythes, as the Apoſtle doth conclude; not wrongfully. He commanded in particular termes to giue vnto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars: In generall doctrine, to yeeld euery man his owne. Therefore no man can well imagine that hee would foreſtall, or intercept any others due, but receiued his owne. By what right? Sure, not in the right of his Godhead, whereby the ſupreame dominion of all things reſteth in him. But by the title and in the right of his Prieſthood: for ſo the Apoſtle argueth.
            You that be hearers may make this vſe of my ſpeech, that ſeeing Tythes were payd by Abraham, vowed by Iacob, preſcribed by the inſtinct of nature, before the Law: allotted to the Prieſts vnder the Law: continued ſince the Law: ſeeing the Church hath beene in iuſt and good poſſeſſion of them aboue 4000 yeares: ſeeing they were dedicated to the ſeruice of God: ſeeing they were deuoted vnto God: And the title or right, that man had before donation: doth by the act, and from any ſuch time of donation, remaine the proper poſſeſſion of God, vntill the worlds end, vnleſſe himſelfe renounce, or relinquiſh it. Yeeld your Tythes willingly, becauſe you cannot hold them from your Miniſters without impietie. In ſuch caſes the Lord loueth a cheerefull giuer: Et nos libenter accipimus

beneficium quod profit danti. Nobis quidem in hoc benefacitis, ſed vobis melius. Beatius est dare, quam accipere.
            
            Beſides the entertainment of Miniſters, there is another reaſon for publique aſſemblies: that the puritie of ſincere Doctrine might be kept inuiolable by that meanes from the corruption of Gentilitie, the poyſon of Hereſie, and the rage of Schiſme: whileſt the worſhip of God is not left arbitrarie, or voluntarie, but hath a preſcript forme from whence it is vnlawfull to decline. For that hath beene, and alwayes will be dangerous.
            It is noted for a ſpecial blemiſh and ſtaine amongſt the Iſraelites in the booke of Iudges; That euery one did what he thought good in his owne eyes, without regard of law, of order, of vniformitie in Church or common-wealth.
            And where lawes eyther be not at all, or want due execution: that our wauering mindes be not held in a conformitie: It is the eaſieſt thing in the world, for man vaine and curious by nature, and delighted with change, to fall into confuſion and groſſe idolatrie.
            Let Ieroboam be the example hereof, who had no ſooner withdrawne his followers from thoſe aſſemblies that were appointed by better authoritie, but ſtraight-waies both himſelfe fell into Schiſme, and to Idolatrie: and wrapped all his adherents in the like offences. So the Scripture markes him out euerie where. Ieroboam that made Iſraell to ſinne.
            
            Let Ieroboam carry this marke alone, and let it neuer be found or felt in this Church. For if the publike

miniſterie be defaced by any, not maintained by others, but neglected: deceiuers will creepe into priuate families, and lead captiue ſimple women (and men too) laden with ſinnes, and led with diuers luſts, euer learning, and neuer able to come to the knowledge of truth. Not vnlike to mothers which bring forth Monſters, which they hide in corners and ſecret places, ſhaming to ſhew them openly, and yet priuily doe feede and nouriſh them.Be
                     •••
                  rd. in Can
                     •
                  . ſer. 65
                
               Vbi Apoſtolica forma &amp; vita quam iactatis? illi clamant, vos ſuſurratis: illi in publico, vos in angulo: illi vt nubes volant, vos in tenebris, at ſubterraneis domibus deliteſcitis: Quidſimile illis in vobis oſtenditis? Thus hath beene hatched elſewhere, the hereſies of Papiſts, the frenſies of Anabaptiſts, the ſchiſmes of raſh brethren, and the prophane impieties of Atheiſts, of ill egs, worſe chickens.
            The remedie for theſe inconueniences is, to cut off arbitrarie worſhip, to reſtraine and ſuppreſſe whiſpering or corner diuinitie. Therefore to the entent we may not haue, here is Chriſt, or there is Chriſt, we muſt all ioyne together in cheriſhing, intertaining, and frequenting one publicke miniſterie, one preſcript and ſetled forme of prayers and Eccleſiaſticall rites. This is not mine owne conceit, I learned it from Mr. Caluin:
               Epiſt. ad protect. Angl. 87. pag. 69.
                
               Concerning the forme of prayer (ſaith he) and Eccleſiaſticall rites, I doe very well like that they ſhould be certaine in a preſcript order, and that the Paſtors be not ſufferd to ſwerue from it: aſwell for the help of the ſimple, as alſo that a conſent of all Churches may be held; and laſtly, to preuent the raſhneſſe of thoſe that affect nouelties.
            
            
               The Miniſterie was ordained for this end, as the Apoſtle doth teach vs, Epheſ. 4.14. that wee ſhould no more wauer like Children and be carried too and fro with euery blaſt of doctrine: whereby it appeareth that the ſpirit of God hath faſtned vs to the publike miniſterie, the better to hold vs in a conſtant loue of the truth. And therefore addreſſing our ſelues vnto it, let vs alſo reioyce to goe into the houſe of the Lord.
            A matter (as ſome will obiect) eaſie to be ſaid and done amongſt the Iſraelites, becauſe, firſt, the Tabernacle, &amp; afterward the Temple, were viſible &amp; known to be deſtinated to the worſhip of God. Now the houſe of God is not ſo conſpicuous nor commonly knowne: doubts and queſtions are ſtill moued which is the Church.
            That theſe allay no part of your forwardneſſe: heare I beſeech you how they may be cleared: and heare it not from me, but from S. Auguſtine: Inter nos &amp; Donatist as quaeſtio eſt, vbi ſit Eccleſia? quid ergo facturi ſumus? in verbis noſtris eam quaeſituri, an in verbis capitis ſui Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti? Puto quod in illius potius verbis eam quaerere debemus, qui veritas eſt, &amp; optime nouit corpus ſuum. Nouit enim Dominus qui ſunt ſui. Nothing is ſought for with more endeuor then the Church, and nothing miſtaken with greater error. The cauſe is apparant, for that wee ſeeke it in the markes that wee frame of it to our ſelues, and not in the notes that Chriſt hath giuen vs to know it by. Men would haue the Church to be conſpicuous and viſible, but wee cannot make that a marke of the

Church, vnleſſe wee infringe an article of our Faith: I beleeue the Catholike Faith. When I ſee a thing, there needes no faith for it: Faith in the Apoſtles doctrine is of things inuiſible, that cannot be ſeene.
            Succeſſion is as much vrged for knowledge of the Church: and it is plaine enough that the ancient fathers did vſually alledge their continued ſucceſſion of Biſhops againſt Heretiques: But the principall point of their allegation conſiſted in the ſucceſſion, not of place or perſon, but of doctrine, which the good Biſhops had kept in a long deſcent from the Apoſtles times.Tertul. de. praeſcript. 
               Percurre Eccleſias apud quas ipſae adhuc Cathedrae Apoſtolorum praeſidentur, ſonantes vocem, &amp; repreſentantes faciem vniuſcuiuſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  .
            
            Amplitude and diffuſion is made another marke of the Church: and that had beene a very deceiueable cogniſance, when the Arrian hereſie ouerſwayed all. But may it not now be returned in preiudice of thoſe that alledge it? who ſees not the fall of great Babilon, and the waine or abatement of the Biſhop of Rome his Hierarchie.
            Laſt of all, Antiquitie is brought for a note of the Church: and if that were a certaine or perpetuall euidence, then was the Church ancient as ſoone a
                  •
                it began. Auguſtine found the vncertaintie and invaliditie of theſe markes that men deuiſe, and ſaith,De vnitat. eccleſiae cap. 3
                
               nolo humanis documentis ſed diuinis oraculis ſanctam Eccleſiam demonſtrari The markes that Chriſt hath giuen to the Church will be ſurer: firſt, becauſe he is truth: ſecondly, becauſe hee knoweth his owne body beſt; this is a firme Maxime, that the Lord knoweth who

are his. Mat. 28. when he ſent his Apoſtles to ſubdue the world by gathering him a Church, three things were giuen them in charge: firſt, that they ſhould preach the Goſpell vnto euery creature: ſecondly, that they ſhould baptiſe them, in the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt: thirdly, that they ſhould teach thoſe that beleeued and were baptiſed, to obſerue all that hee had commanded. Behold the things that the Maiſter of the houſe commanded to be in his houſe: are not they true markes of the houſe? firſt, the ſincere doctrine of the Goſpell: ſecondly, the right adminiſtration of the Sacraments: thirdly, that forme of diſcipline (I meane not any certaine manner, for that was neuer yet proued) which may bring obedience to Chriſts commandements: let them that vnchurch vs ſo eaſily at their pleaſures, ioine iſſue with vs vpon theſe markes, and they ſhall ſee that we haue no cauſe through the grace of God to ſhun the triall.
            The Church of Rome hath the Word of God indeed contained in their Bibles, we deny it not: but as Hierome ſaith of certaine Heretiques,In 1. cap. Eſa. ſo we ſay of it; Heretiques corrupt the truth of the Goſpel with their falſe conſtructions: and are like our worst kind of brewers, that make wine water, whereas cleane contrary, our Sauiour turned water into wine: ſo they haue the goſpell, but not truely expounded, nor taught ſincerely.
            Firſt, becauſe they refer not their conſtructions to the glory of God, according to the rule of our Sauiour, qui quaerit gloriam meam verax eſt: but the church of Rome attributing ſaluation to their owne merits, aduancing free-will, extenuating originall ſinne, &amp;c.

ſeeke not the glory of God, but their owne gaine: therefore they are not true.
            There is another reaſon of their vntrue conſtructions: becauſe they interpret not the Scripture according to the proportion of faith, as Paul willeth, Rom. 12 Let him that propheſieth do it according to the proportion of faith. As all gold was not holy, but that only which belonged to the temple: ſo euery ſenſe that is without compaſſe of Scripture, though it ſhine and gliſter with neuer ſo much ſharpnes of wit, yet is it not holy. By the ſame ſpirit that the Scriptures were written, by the ſame they muſt be interpreted and vnderſtood: this is the golden rule to know truth from error; Scripture muſt be interpreted by Scripture; not alwayes literally, not alwayes allegorically, not alwayes anagogically, not alwayes tropologically; but the darker places by thoſe that be more plaine or eaſie. And as Tertul writeth, oportet ſecundum plura intelligi pauciora:
               Contra Praxeam. 
               &amp; ne vnus ſermo multa alia ſubuertat: ſecundū omnia, potius quam aduerſus omnia intelligendus erit.
            
            
               Thou art Peter, and vpon this rocke will I build my Church: if we looke to the proportion of faith, Chriſt vndoubtedly is that pretious rocke, not Peter, as they would haue it: for the Church cannot be built but by faith, and that may not reſt vpon Peter, or any other creature. Againe, Vnto thee will I giue the Keyes of the kingdome of heauen: hereupon they would perſwade the world, that the power of their Keyes which is Eccleſiaſticall, ſhould locke vp and let looſe the power of the ſword, and ciuill Magiſtrate. If you will iudge hereof by the Analogie of faith, you ſhall ſee the

bounds and limits of both powers. Paul ſubiecteth euery ſoule to the Ciuill power, and excepteth none. Etiamſi ſis Apoſtolus, though thou be an Apoſtle, an Euangeliſt, a Prophet, or whatſoeuer elſe thou be, thou muſt be ſubiect to the ciuill power. For this ſubiection (ſaith Chriſoſtome) is no hinderance to godlineſſe.Chriſoſt. in Epiſt. ad Rom. hom. 23.
                The Apoſtle perſwadeth this ſubiection, not for humilitie, or by way of curteſie, but inioynes it of neceſſitie; Wee muſt needes be ſubiect, id
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   propter conſcientiam: and that which is due of conſcience, is ſo neceſſarie to be done that it cannot be omitted without hainous ſin. Neceſſitie and Conſcience, be ſtrong obligations for ciuill obedience.
            Giue me leaue on the other ſide to let you ſee the ſtrength and ſinewes of Eccleſiaſticall power. Then looke vpon the decrees of the Church, ſingle as they are in themſelues, and ſeuered from the Princes countenance. The decree that the Gentiles ſhould abſtaine from things offered vnto Idols, is of that nature, Act. 15. And is it not limited by the Apoſtle of the Gentiles? 1 Cor. 10. Whatſoeuer is ſolde in the ſhambl
                     •
                  s, eate, and aske no queſtion for conſcience ſake: But if any man ſay vnto you, this is ſacrificed vnto Idols, eate it not, becauſe of him that ſhewed it, and for conſcience: the conſcience I ſay, not thine but of the other.
            
            Compare Paul, with Paul: power, with power: bond, with bond: and Law, with Law. Ciuill authoritie requireth a neceſſitie of obedience: Eccleſiaſticall, giueth a libertie to the Conſcience. The ciuill Magiſtrate muſt be obayed ſimply: The Eccleſiaſticall admits caution, and reſpect. This bindes

me onely in caſe of ſcandall: the other, as well out of offence, as in offence.
            Though I had Gyges ring, and liued without controlement of any eye, yet am I bound in conſcience to obey the poſitiue Lawes. I am bound to obey both powers, but with diſparitie: The ciuill ordinances, for clearing mine owne conſcience from ſinne: and Eccleſiaſticall decrees, for comelineſſe, for order, for ſauing my brother from ſtumbling and offence. Iudge then whether authoritie is greater: the Myter, or the Scepter? Both theſe offices are now conioyned in Chriſt: and is he not greater in his Kingdome? He ſtands at the right hand of God as an aduocate and Prieſt: he ſitteth as a King. This puts a Scepter, the other giueth a Cenſer into his hand. His Prieſthood reacheth but to the Elect: his Kingdome iudgeth quicke and dead. He is ſweet in his Prieſthood, but in his kingdome, high, potent, and magnificall. This is enough for the falſhood of their conſtructions.
            Touching the Sacraments, which is the ſecond note, the Church of Rome doth no way rightly adminiſter them: ſaue onely that it retayneth the eſſentiall forme of Baptiſme. Otherwiſe they prophane it moſt groſly, in applying it to dead and ſenſleſſe things. They mingle it with oyle, ſpettle, and ſalt, which cannot be done without ſacriledge. is not the element of water, which Chriſt inſtituted, ſufficient to repreſent his precious bloud for our regeneration, without theſe mixtures?
            The other Sacrament, namely the Supper of the Lord: the Church of Rome hath not onely defiled,

but quite altered, &amp; changed it into a curſed, and an abhominable Idol of their Maſſe: and ſo haue peruerted vtterly, and annihilated Chriſts holy inſtitution.
            1. For whereas two things be neceſſarie in Sacraments: the ſigne, and the thing ſignified: In this Sacrament they take away the ſignes for eſtabliſhing their tranſubſtantiation.
            2. That which ſhould be diſtributed vnto others, they keepe onely to themſelues, and ſo make it a priuate banquet, whereas it ſhould be a common feaſt.
            3. They keepe the Cup from the people, which our Sauiour commanded to be giuen to all.
            4. Laſtly, in the Lords Supper, he offereth himſelfe to vs: and they offer him to GOD the Father: which cannot be done but by his eternall ſpirit: nor without his death, that died but once for euer.
            Where theſe things are done; the Eſſentiall parts of the Sacrament is not kept: and therefore no Supper, no Sacrament, but an horrible prophanation and plaine ſacriledge. Hereby it may appeare how vniuſtly they complaine of vs for Apoſtaſie &amp; forſaking of them. Nullus pudor est ad meliora tranſire. And if a man do leaue and depart from a particular Church in body, and yet forſake not the Communion &amp; fellowſhip of the Apoſtles doctrine, nor the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, but holdeth them with all other ſincere Churches: he cannot be Apoſtata.
            Our Rhemiſh Seminaries, ſay Luther, Caluin, &amp;c. came out of their Church, not they out of ours. And that is the Catholique Church which is forſaken. But the right Apoſtaſie is a falling away from the true

Catholique and Apoſtolique Church of Chriſt, and that by reuolting from the Apoſtles doctrine, &amp; the communion of the Catholique faith. We departed from them vpon ſuch occaſion, and in ſuch ſort, as Moſes ſometimes departed out of Egipt: or S. Auguſtine from the Manicheis. De veſtris fuimus (ſaith Tertullian) nec mirum, fiunt enim non naſcuntur Chriſtiani.
            
            The Church of Rome is neither Catholique, nor Apoſtolique: and therefore by leauing it we incurre no Apoſtacie. Not Catholique becauſe it is particular as the Church of Alexandria, Milan, Epheſus, &amp;c. The Catholique Church is vniuerſall, and whereſoeuer the faithfull be found. It is not pinned vp in one place, but diſpeirced farre and neere.
            Did the Goſpel begin at Rome? was it not brought from Ieruſalem, firſt to the Grecians, and after to the Romanes? So then that Church was not the firſt: and if there were a Catholique Church before Rome had any Church, I ſee no cauſe but there may be ſtill a Catholique Church without it.
            An Apoſtolique Church it is not, becauſe it reſteth not vpon the doctrine of the Apoſtles, but is fallen from it, defending inuocation of Saints, that the Apoſtles taught not: forbidding marriage againſt the Apoſtles Caueat. Anathematizing the Apoſtles doctrine of Iuſtification by faith onely. Denying the faith, by aduancing of traditions, aboue the word. And therefore ſeeing we departed from that Church, where neither the word of GOD could be purely taught, the Sacraments adminiſtred, nor God rightly worſhipped: and haue forſaken that Church that

now it is: not that which once it was. The Church of Rome is rather guilty of Apoſtaſie, then we: becauſe it is fallen away from them from whom it receiued the Goſpell, Faith, Religion, and their Church. Why hath the Citie of Rome forſaken her ſeauen hils, whereon that Citie was once built: and is now come downe to the plaine? Happily they will ſay that their Conduits and water courſes did faile them in thoſe hils, without which they could not well liue. Then let them yeeld vs the like libertie for the waters of life: that they themſelues haue taken for their common water. That water of life began to faile them in the Church of Rome: They had broken all the Conduits and Pipes: they had ſtopped vp all. Veines, and had mingled the fountaines of water of life with mire and dirt: and ſo brought in a thirſt and hunger, not of bread and water, but of hearing the word of God. And was it not then time to leaue them?
            Let them refuſe their Synagogues, forſake their broken Cyſternes that will hold no water: returne to that true &amp; auncient faith that was renowned through the world: and we will giue them the right hands of fellowſhip. With ioy will wee ioyne together with them, and goe into the houſe of the Lord.
            If they will not: I call heauen and earth to record againſt them this day: that they are fallen from the Goſpell, from truth, from word, from Sacraments, from Religion, from the houſe of God, from God himſelfe. And all theſe our Churches ſtudie with great endeuour to maintaine in their perfect integrity.

O pray, pray, forget not to pray for that moſt excellent inſtrument of GOD that hath eſtabliſhed theſe things amongſt vs by holy Lawes, and good authoritie: Peace be within his walls, and plentiouſneſſe within his Pallaces. Yea the God of peace and plenty bleſſe him, for theſe bleſſings that hee hath brought vpon vs, a thouſand, and ten thouſand fold, both here, and in the world to come.
            And beloued, ceaſe not to crie out vnto God to fill our hearts with praiſe, and our mouthes with thankes-giuing for theſe ineſtimable mercies. When Gods benefits are receiued with thankfulnes and due account, then hee doth multiply them exceedingly. Seeing then that all the enemies wee haue, cannot ſhew one point of doctrine maintained contrarie to the wholeſome forme ſet downe in the word, and proportion of faith: ſeeing they cannot iuſtly reproue our adminiſtration of the Sacraments. Let not theſe graces of God towards our Churches be extenuated by ſcornefull reproofes, or ſlaunderous Pamphlets: leaſt there follow queſtions, whether they be the houſes of God, or no? leaſt they be forſaken by fanaticall and giddie ſpirits, as if they were the Synagogues of Sathan.
            Theſe be the fruits that vnaduiſed whiſperings wil bring forth: and this vſe the enemie of mankinde hath made of them. They haue ſerued him, as a pedagogie, an A B C, or introduction of Schiſme, of frenzie, of Anabaptiſticall confuſion.
            Two errors I haue obſerued that are the grounds, and occaſions of theſe enormities. The firſt, is an

immoderate deſire of Chriſtian libertie. The ſecond, an importunate challenge of equalitie in gouernement of the Church.
            As to the former, many are deceiued therein, and deceiue others: whileſt they ſet Chriſtian libertie vpon Tenter-hookes, and ſtretch it further then the nature thereof will beare: ſeeking not onely a liberty of minde and conſcience in things indifferent, but a freedome alſo in their actions. Chriſtian libertie hath place in minde and conſcience alone: It contenteth it ſelfe if there be no burthen of merit, of iuſtification, of holineſſe, or pleaſing God vrged vpon the conſcience: that is the ſeate of Ieſus Chriſt, and if that be left free vnto him, Chriſtian libertie is ſafe and ſound. It reſpecteth nothing but that which is betweene God and thee. And is not this a goodly libertie, when we know that ſuch and ſuch things doe neither iuſtifie nor condemne vs afore God? If this content you not, vnleſſe you may haue freedome alſo in your actions to doe what you will: you haue left Chriſtian libertie, which reacheth not to our actions, and reſpecteth not that which is betweene thee, and thy neighbour: and thou act come to a licentious immunitie.
            This difference being obſerued, may appeaſe manie controuerſies about indifferent things. Wherein if brethren will hold but that moderation which true Diuinitie teacheth, and retaine this freedome, our Chriſtian libertie in their conſciences, which is not infringed; and conforme their actions, that they doe not ouerthwart good order, to the diſturbance of the

Church, and offence of the Magiſtrate: How ioyfully might we all goe vp into the houſe of the Lord, and ſing in the tune of Angels. Ecce quam bonum, &amp; quam iucundum habitare fratres in vnum?
            
            For as much therefore as God hath warranted the Magiſtrates authoritie in theſe caſes, and required our obeience: let vs no more thinke how to finde out pretences. Studia abeunt in mores. But if there be any conſolation in Chriſt, any comfort of loue, any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, any compaſſion and mercie, fulfill this ioy: that ye be like minded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one accord and iudgement, that nothing be done through contention, or vaine glory, but that in meekeneſſe of minde euery one eſteeme other better then himſelfe. That we may all with one way, and one heart, goe vp into the houſe of the Lord.
            As for equalitie, which is the other errour: when one aduiſed Lycurgus, to eſtabliſh it amongſt the Lacedemonians, that ſo the leaſt and meaneſt might beare like ſway with the greateſt: The wiſe man anſwered: that he which called for it ſhould begin it firſt at home in his owne houſe. And if all men be carefull to exclude paritie out of their priuate families: if men experienced in policie and gouernement, will not admit it into the common-wealth, becauſe that cannot be preſerued with equalitie, but by authoritie and rule: Why are not men as ſenſible of the houſe of God, as of their owne houſes? or why ſhould equalitie, that is found intollerable in all other ſocieties, be obtruded onely to the Church? Becauſe diſtinctions and inequalitie of Paſtors cannot be proued by

Scripture. That is not ſo. There were diuers Paſtors vnder the Law: but they were not equall. For there was one high Prieſt, as it were a tranſcendent aboue them all. But his eminencie was to expreſſe the ſoueraignetie of Ieſus Chriſt: Then there were Captaines of euery family of the Leuites: and that proues an inequalitie. Laſt of all, there were two ioyned with the high Prieſt, which are called rulers of the houſe of God, 1 Chro. 24.5.
            In the new Teſtament there was diſtinction and inequalitie betweene the Apoſtles themſelues, or elſe Paul would neuer haue called Peter and Iames, and Iohn, chiefe and pillars of the Apoſtles. There was diſtinction and inequalitie betweene the twelue Apoſtles, and the ſeauentie Diſciples. We reade of manie Paſtors at Epheſus, Act. 20. And in the Reuelation Iohn writeth to the Angel of the Church of Epheſus, which euicteth neceſſarily, that there was one greater then the reſt Par in parem non habet imperium. But Paul gaue Timothie authoritie ouer Paſtors: Therefore hee ordayned and intended an inequalitie, and no paritie amongſt the Paſtors of the Church. The reaſons of thoſe that call for equalitie in the Miniſters, are not made to build vp, and they are too weake to pull downe.
            
               Abraham ſaith grauely vnto Lot: Let there be no contention betweene mee and thee; for wee are brethren▪
                that is one reaſon. Againe, the Cananite and the Pherizite are yet in the Land: another motiue. In which caſe who knowes not, that the aduerſaries of our doctrine, will ſooner be ouercome with vnited

then diſtracted forces? and ſo we that fight the Lords battailes cannot diſioyne our ſelues without preuarication and bootie. Away then with all ſingularitie and admiring of our owne opinions. Know yee not that it is the ſeminarie of inward contention? the Spirit of the Prophets muſt be ſubiect to the Prophets. Let vs haue but one heart, and one way, that wee may fill the Lords houſe with garlands of victories: that wee may beate our aduerſaries from humane merits, and bring them to the diuine mercies: from free-will, and the poſſibilities of Nature, to the grace of God: from traditions, to the written Word: from elauation, adoration, circumgeſtation, tranſubſtantiation of the Sacrament, to the commemoration of Chriſts death, and a ſweet fruition thereof by faith. From their Hierarchie and viſible Monarchie, to the headſhip of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. From ſuperſtition, to the true vvorſhip of GOD.
            O how glorious are theſe holy triumphs? how inſtantly doe they call vpon vs to combine our ſelues together, that the conuerſion and offering vp of the Papiſts may be acceptable and ſanctified. I will not diſmiſſe you of the Laitie without ſome ſhort exhortation to peace. The very name of peace is a ſweet word, but the work is ſweeter. I cannot alwayes ſpeake of it: But that which I cannot alwayes ſpeake of, that you may keepe alwayes. As for example. He that praiſeth God, with his tongue cannot doe it euer: but he that praiſeth God with his life and conuerſation, may euer doe it. Euen ſo doe I commend the words and works

of peace vnto you. Or if you thinke me vnworthie to commend ſuch a diuine bleſſing: looke if it be not the word of our great and worthieſt King. He commandeth it vnto vs from the Author of peace. Beati pacifici. Not pacidici, but pacifici. Bleſſed are, not the praiſers, but the practiſers of peace. Let the mountaines bring peace, and the little hils righteouſneſſe vnto thy people, O thou Prince of peace. And ſo the God of peace that brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus, the great Shepheard of the ſheepe, through the bloud of the euerlaſting Teſtament, make you perfect in all good works, workking in you that which is pleaſant in his ſight through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe for euer and euer, Amen.
            
            FJNJS.
         
      
   

