
   
      
         
            A relation of a voyage to Guiana Describing the climat, scituation, fertilitie, prouisions and commodities of that country, containing seuen prouinces, and other signiories within that territory: together, with the manners, customes, behauiors, and dispositions of the people. Performed by Robert Harcourt, of Stanton Harcourt Esquire. The pattent for the plantation of which country, his Maiestie hath granted to the said Robert Harcourt vnder the Great Seale.
            Harcourt, Robert, 1574?-1631.
         
         
            
               1613
            
         
         Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02626
            STC 12754
            ESTC S103834
            99839579
            99839579
            4011
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02626)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4011)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 889:02)
         
         
            
               
                  A relation of a voyage to Guiana Describing the climat, scituation, fertilitie, prouisions and commodities of that country, containing seuen prouinces, and other signiories within that territory: together, with the manners, customes, behauiors, and dispositions of the people. Performed by Robert Harcourt, of Stanton Harcourt Esquire. The pattent for the plantation of which country, his Maiestie hath granted to the said Robert Harcourt vnder the Great Seale.
                  Harcourt, Robert, 1574?-1631.
               
               [16], 71, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Beale, for W. Welby, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Churchyard at the signe of the Swan,
                  At London :
                  1613.
               
               
                  Running title reads: A voiage of discouerie to Guiana.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Guyana --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-11
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-12
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-12
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
RELATION
OF A VOYAGE
TO GVIANA.
            DESCRIBING THE CLIMAT,
Scituation, fertilitie, prouisions and commodities
of that Country, containing seuen Prouinces, and
other Signiories within that Territory: Together,
with the manners, customes, behauiors, and
dispositions of the people.
            
               Performed by ROBERT HARCOVRT, of
Stanton Harcourt Esquire.
            
            The Pattent for the Plantation of which Country,
his Maiestie hath granted to the said ROBERT
HARCOVRT vnder the Great Seale.
            NOMB. 14. 7, 8.
            
               The Land which we walked thorow to search it, is a very good Land.
               If the Lord loue vs, he will bring vs into this land, and wil giue it vs.
            
            AT LONDON
Printed by IOHN BEALE, for W. WELBY, and
are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church yard at the
signe of the Swan. 1613.
         
         
            
            
            
               ❧To the high and
Mighty Prince, CHARLES, Prince
of GREAT BRITAINE:
            
               
                  HAuing had tryall
(most worthy Prince)
of your most renowned
Brother Prince Hē
                  rie
his many fauours
towardes mee, and
princely furtherance of my humble sute
vnto his Maiestie your royall Father, and
our dread Soueraigne, for obtayning for
mee his gracious Letters Pattents for the
planting and inhabiting of all that tract of
Land, and part of Guiana, betweene the
riuers of Amazones, &amp; Dessequebe, scituate

in America, vnder the Equinoctiall
Line: Whereof I haue taken possession to
his Maiesties vse, and discouered the maritime
parts. I was greatly thereby incouraged
to proceed in the enterprise, and had
(vnder his Maiesties fauour) deuoted my
selfe vnto his seruice. But now seeing (by
Gods permission) your excellent Brother
his princely Honour, by right of succession
is fallen vpon your Highnesse, and verily
hoping, that you will not onely equall, but
also exceed him in vertuous exercises, and
aduancing all honorable actiōs, and worthy
enterprises; I haue in like maner religiously
vowed the best fruits and effects of my
indeauors vnto your Highnesse seruice.
And for as much as that part of the world
which wee now call America, was heretofore
in the yeere of our Lord 1170. discouered,Gutyn Owen.
conquered, and possessed by Madoc,
one of the sons of Owen Gwyneth prince
of north-Wales: I therfore (in all humble

reuerence) present the prosecution of this
high Action vnto your gracious Patronage,
principally belonging of right vnto you, being
the honourable, true, and worthy Successor
to the Principality of VVales. If
my trauell &amp; seruice therein shall perform
ought, woorthy of your Princely regard,
I shall much glory thereat, and account it
my happiest fortune, and greatest honour:
And shall heartily pray vnto the King of
Kings, to continue in your Highnesse a pious,
and inuincible heart; and to giue you a
conquering and victorious hand; and the
dominion of many rich and mighty Kingdomes
in this world, and in the worlde to
come, a Crowne of Glorie, in his eternall
Kingdome.
            
               Your Highnesse
most humble deuoted seruant,
ROBERT HARCOVRT.
            
         
         
            
            
            
               ❧To the Readers,
ADVENTVRERS, FAVORERS,
and wel-willers to the Plantation
in GVIANA.
            
               IT is the part of valiant and noble spirites to
apply their indeuours to honourable and
woorthie atchiuements: but chiefely to
frame their actions therein by the rule of
vertue, and accomplish the end for which
they were created, which is in their vocations
to serue and glorifie GOD, and to doe good vnto others:
For the better performance of their dueties in that behalfe,
let them examine their inclinations and dispositions
in the course of their life, and what they finde themselues
most inclined vnto, to that let them seriously bend their forces;
either to cherish or suppresse it; to follow or forsake it,
according as it tendeth to vertue or vice; to honour or
disgrace.
            As touching the courses of life, inclining to the better
part, some men are naturally giuen to bee schollers, either in
Diuinity, Philosophy, or other learning; some are more inclined
to be Statists; some to be Souldiers, and trauellers; some desire
to bee Citizens, and Merchants; and some like best to leade
Coun
                  •
               trey life, and follow husbandry; and othersome are

wholly inclined to the Mechannicall trades, and handy crafts.
In all which professions, as men are naturally addicted more,
or lesse, they attaine to perfection, and may thereby accomplish
the end for which they were created. But to vndertake any profession
contrary to a mans naturall inclination, is a losse of time,
a worke that yeldeth no profit, but breedeth many inconueniences,
and destroyeth nature: For the meere Scholler will neuer
bee good Statist, Souldier, Merchant, nor Mechanicall
tradesman, (yet learning is a singular helpe in all these professions)
neither will the professed Souldier euer attaine to exquisite
perfection in learning, or in the other professions; so likwise
of the rest. The naturall inclination of man, may bee somwhat
restrained, corrected, and reformed, but is rarely and
hardly altered.
            Naturam expellas furca licèt, vsque recurret
            In these and all other professions whatsoeuer, men may so
proceede in their particular societies, that each seuerall company
in his proper vocation, may bee a help, comfort, and support
vnto the rest: and they are firmely bound both by the
law of God, and Nature, to exercise and follow their professions
for the benefit of others: not coueteously seeking their owne
gaine only thereby; but charitably, respecting first the glory of
God, and then the honour of their Prince, and profit of their
Countrey, which is the end for which they were created
            To the end therefore that our Countreymen of all professions
in this Kingdome may bee worthily induced to performe their
duties in that kinde not only at home in their owne Countrey,
but also abroade in foraigne parts, wheresoeuer any of our
Nation shall be imployed, eyther by discouery or conquest, for
the reducing of vnknowne and barbarous people (void of all
knowledge of God, and ciuill gouernement) to Christianity and
the subiection and obedience of of our Soueraigne, and that
such others as want imployment, or competent meanes to follow

their professions, and are slipt aside from vertuous exercises,
and honourable enterprises, to idle wantonnesse, effeminate
disorders, and other extrauagant courses of life, may bee recalled,
reformed, and encouraged (by better endeuours) to performe
their duties to God, their Prince, and their Countrey.
I thought it conuenient to propound vnto them a worthy and
memorable enterprise: (for the prosecution and accomplishing
whereof, it hath gratiously pleased his Maiesty to grant mee
priuiledge by Pattent) namely, the discouery and plantation of
a part of the great, rich, &amp; mighty Empire of Guiana: wherein
they shall finde variety of imployments to spend their times
worthily in their seuerall vocations; plentifull meanes to supply
all wants and necessities; and many worthy aduentures to
obtaine immortall renowne and perpetuall fame.
            And for as much as all mens actions are subiect to miscensure,
and some (perhaps) may thinke the labour lost, which is
bestowed in this enterprise, foreiudgeing the Countrey being
rude, barbarous and heathen, to bee vnprofitable; I will therefore
here particularly shew wherein our Countreymen of the seuerall
professions before mentioned, may profitably labour in
this worke, and performe thereby to God a seruice most acceptable,
and register their fame to all posteritie.
            First, the Scholler in diuine learning may worthily labour
the conuersion of infinite numbers of vnbeleeuing people, who
may be reduced to a quiet, sober, and ciuill life: the scoller in
Philosophy, and other Learning, may doe much good by training
vp of the youth in the knowledge of the litterall arts, and
by the practise of his skill in Phisicke and Chirurgery: the Statist
may highly aduance his Princes seruice, and his Countries
good, by giuing ayd vnto this action, and his discreet and
prouident furtherance in managing the businesse thereof: The
Souldier and Traueller, by bearing armes in the execution of
this noble enterprise, and by memorable discoueries of strange

and vnknowne Countries and Nations, may open the way to
increase and inlarge the Dominion of our Soueraigne: the
Merchant by assisting the plantation there, and by erecting
conuenient factories for that purpose, may highly increase the
trade of merchandise, by returning thence the riches and
commodities there found and gathered. The Countrey-man
that professeth busbandry and tillage of the earth, may also be
sufficiently imploied for the increase of corne and catell, and
in planting, gathering, and getting as many rare and necessary
fruits and prouisions, as shall be needefull for the life of man.
And lastly, the Mechannicall tradesman, and such as exercise
the handy crafts, (in which company I include all sorts of labourers)
may by this action of Guiana, highly aduance their
trades and occupations, to their owne vnspeakable profit, and
benefit of others, by their diuers and sundry workes for seuerall
vses, and for persons of all quallity whatsoeuer; and may
teach the people of that Countrey (being once conuerted to christianity,
and brought to the knowledge of ciuill gouernement)
such seuerall trades, as our experience shall finde necessarie for
them, and conuenient for vs.
            Hauing heere particularly shewed wherein our Countrey-men
of diuers professions may worthily follow their vocations,
and imploy their endeuours in this action: I leaue the matter
whereon they are to worke, to be more fully expressed in the
following discourse.
            And because they may the better be encouraged in this enterprise,
by examples of the like nature: let vs looke into the discoueries
and conquests, performed by the Spaniards, in the
East and West Indies; but chiefely in the West: where with a
small number, and as it were with a handfull of men, Hernando
Cortez a Spaniard, in the yeere of our Lord 1519.
discouered and conquered that great, mighty, and rich Kingdome
of New Spaine, and the Citie of Mexico.
            
            
               
And in the yeere of our Lord 1531. Don Francisco Pizarro
attempted the conquest of the great Kingdome of Peru; he
vanquished Atibalipa, the King of that Countrey, conquered
and subdued many spacious and rich Prouinces; and in the end
after infinite perils and dangers by practise of the Indians
and much variety of fortune, by ciuill warres with his owne
Nation, he atchiued his enterprise. The particulars of these
discoueries and conquests, are more at large recounted by Peter
Martyr in his Decades, by Benzo, and diuers other Authors,
to which for breuities sake I referre you. The honour
these Spaniards gained by these discoueries and conquests, was
doubtlesse great: but the benefit that ensued to the Crowne of
Spaine, and all the Spanish Nation thereby, was infinite beyond
expectation, as amply may appeare in the Authors late
mentioned, and in the Naturall and Morrall history of the East
and West Indies, written by Iosephus Acosta.
            
            Let vs also note the wonderfull workes of God in those Countries,
and his great mercy thereby shewed to the Indians, who
by their continuall conuersation with Christians, are reduced
from their abhominable life and cruell manners, to the
knowledge of God and their former infidelity, and to the fruition
of the holy Ghost in Baptisme; for in all those great Prouinces,
conquered in New Spaine, the people are generaly conuerted
to Christianity: for about the yeere of our Lord 1524.
there went diuers learned men into those parts, who by learning
the Indians languages, and their painefull diligence in
teaching and instructing youth, did so effectually proceed in
that laborious worke, that within the limits of many hundred
leagues, there are few or none vnchristened. The beginning
of that Worke was very difficult, by reason of the vnaptnesse
of the Indians, so long imbrued in cruell sacrifices of humane
blood, and abhominable Idolatry, and by the continuall malice
of the diuell, rebelling against God, and striuing to maintaine

his owne kingdome: but in the end their constant and painefull
indeuours so farre preuailed, that Christian religion
increased amongst them, to the establishing of many Bishopricks
in New Spaine, besides diuers Schooles of learning. So likewise
in Peru, and diuers other Countries, conquered by the
Spaniards, the conuersions of the people haue proceeded to no
lesse admirable effects.
            As touching the state of common wealth, they haue all
sorts of Gouernours, and magistrates in great honour and reputation;
houses of Nobility and Gentry flourish, and increase
amongst them; Souldiers, and trauellers are regarded highly,
and worthily rewarded; Merchants, and tradesmen prosper,
and gather wealth in extraordinary measure; what shall
I say more, there bee few or no professions or trades amongst vs,
in these parts of Christendome, but the same are vsed, followed,
and practised in great perfection, both in New Spaine,
Peru, and other parts of the Indies, where the Spaniards haue
preuailed by their Conquests.
            By these memorable examples may our Nation (being in
valour inferiour to none other vnder Heauen) bee moued and
stirred vp to the vndertaking of this noble action of Guiana;
which in respect of the climate, firtility of the soile, and tractable
disposition of the people (whereof in the following discourse
I haue spoken more at large) doth assure vs that (with Gods fauour
and assistance) as great effects may bee wrought in
the conuersion of these Nations, and as great benefit, and
commoditie may arise to the Realme and Crowne of England,
both in generall, and particular, as euer was performed or obtained
by the Spanish Nation, since the first beginning of their
trauels and discoueries.
            For if they in New Spaine, and Peru, haue Cuchenille,
Anir, and Cotton wooll; wee in Guiana haue also Cotton
wooll Tobacco, Suger-Canes, diuers good commodities for

Dyers, and likewise in all likelihood Cuchenille; and sundry
sorts of excellent wood for ioyners worke, and other vses. If
they haue variety of Apothecary drugges, and Balsome for
Phisicke, and Chirurgery; so also haue wee, and those that
are of admirable vertue. If they haue gold, siluer, and other
mettalls; Pearles, and pretious stonnes; so doublesse wee in
time may haue the like, hauing had good testimony thereof
already; as plainely shall appeare hereafter, when time better
serueth.
            Moreouer, in singular aduantage wee haue before them to
further, and aduance our enterprise, by the peculiar loue and
affection of the people in those parts, towards our Nation before
all others. For whereas the Spaniards were constrained
by great labour, bloudy battailes, and much cruelty (for which
they lost their hearts) to subdue the Indians; wee contrariwise
are well entertained, and friendly receiued by them, being
willing to hold commerce with vs; whereby wee haue a more
secure and ready meane, to establish a peaceable and assured
Commonwealth amongst them, for the imployment of all the
seuerall professions of men mentioned before.
            Finally, for your better inducement to the worthy vndertaking
of this high action; let vs call to remembrance one excellent
and materiall obseruation; that is the discouery of this
Countrey of Guiana, was heretofore attempted by Sr. Walter
Raleigh, who made an honourable entry thereinto by the riuer
of Orenoque; what hee then, and there discouered, and how
great and assured his hopes were, of gaining to our Countrey
inestimable riches, and subduing to the Crowne of England
a potent Empire, was effectually, and faithfully published to
the world by his owne penne; which excellent discourse I wish
you to peruse, preceeding from so wise and iudiciall an
Author; who if some knowne fortunes had not crossed his
first intendiments, for the prosecuting of that enterprise) had

(in all likelihood) long before this time increased the honour
of our Nation, by the reputation of the most famous and rich
discouery and conquest that the world could afford.
            Let vs herewithal obserue, that before his time it was often
attempted by the Spaniards, but to small effect; for eyther by
misfortune of shipwrack, discention amongst the most eminent
persons in their Troopes, mutiny of the souldiers, mistaking
of the Commanders, or violent fury of the Indians (who beare
an inueterate and mortall hatred against them) they haue euer
failed of their purpose: whereof the said discourse of Sr.
Walter Raleigh maketh particular mention more at large.
            The continuall losse, and great misfortunes that haue followed
the Spaniards from time to time, in all their attempts of
this discouery and conquest, for the space almost of an hundred
yeeres; and the fortunate successe that most happily fauoured
the other in his first attempt thereof, may bee a great presumtion,
and may giue vs an assured hope, that the powerfull hand
of God doth worke for vs in this behalfe; and hath reserued
the execution of this action for honour of our Nation.
            Which forcible considerations, gaue me great encouragement
to repaire the decay of so worthy an enterprise, not with intent
to rob him of his honour, who first of all our Nation (nobly
with great iudgement and valour) gaue the onset; but rather
to doe him more honour, by working vpon his foundation,
and prosecuting this proiect, according to his first designes,
which doubtlesse aimed at the glory of God, his Soueraignes
seruice, and his Countries good.
            Hereupon I made triall of my fortune in the attempt, and
haue found the successe so prosperous and hopefull, (although
it hath been chargeable vnto mee) and my acceptance so free
and friendly amongst the Indians, that it hath giuen not only
to my selfe, but also to the rest of my associats, (who with the
loue and good liking of the people, haue liued and remained in

               Guiana for the space of three yeares) good assurance of repaying
the charge past with trebble recompence; and a resolued
courage to proceed in the enterprise, to the prosecution whereof,
we haue deuoted both our substance and our selues.
            And because the life of this Action consisteth in the timely
progresse thereof, and requireth the assistance of many Aduenturers;
I thought it very needful to lay before you these former
examples, and materiall considerations: and therewithall doe
recommend vnto your view this following Discourse (wherein
I haue compiled the hopefull fruites of my painefull trauels)
thereby to moue you to wipe away from your eyes, the cloudie
incredulous blindnesse that possessed our forefathers in the
dayes of Henry the seuenth, when they reiected the offer made
by Batholomew Columbus, in the behalfe of his brother
Christopher Columbus, and therby lost the fruition of those
inestimable riches in the West Indies, which now we see possessed
by the Spanish Nation: And also doe inuite and summon
my Country-men in generall, to rouze vp their valour, to quicken
and spurre on their endevours, to be coadi
                  •
               utors with vs in
this action, both of honour and profit.
            And because it may be obiected to the discouragement of
such as may haue otherwise a desire to inhabit Guiana, that
the Spaniards inhabiting about Cumana, Margarita, and
Trinidado, may disturbour Plantation, and indanger the liues
of those that shall make the first settlement there; I thought
good to resolue all such as haue affection to make themselues
Conquerors of that goodly Countrey, that from the King of
Spaines Indies nothing can offend them; for Guiana being
seated in the head of the Brises, and to the wind-ward of al the
Spanish Indies, the current also of the Sea setting to the West,
maketh it impossible for any Shipping to turne it vp from the
forenamed places towards vs. The Spaniard therefore can no
way offend vs but by a preparation out of Spaine it selfe. And

whensoeuer he shall finde himselfe at so great leisure, as to send
a Fleet out of Spaine to seeke vs out vpon the shallow coast of
Guiana, eyther we shall frustrate that attempt by raising a
Fort defensible for two or three moneths (for they must famish
if they stay longer) or else by setting our selues aboue two or
three of the ouerfalles of the Riuers, where one hundred men
will defend themselues against fiue thousand. But I am perswaded
that the Spaniards will take great deliberation, and be
well aduised of all insuing accidents, before they giue any attempt
vpon vs: for we doe not finde that they haue yet attempted
any thing vpon Virginia, which lieth in their way homeward
from the West Indies, albeit there haue passed many years
since the first Plantation there. And surely, if Virginia had
not a sharpe Winter, which Guiana hath not (which Countrey
of Guiana is blest with a perpetuall Summer, and a perpetuall
Spring) and that it had that store of victuals which Guiana
hath, it would in a short time grow to be a most profitable place.
But thus much I can auow truely, that from Guiana, without
any great labour, there may be returned within the yeare, good
store of Cotton Wooll, very rich Dyes, diuers sorts of Gummes,
many sorts of Fethers, all kindes of rich Woods, Balsamums,
Iasper, and Porpherie stone, Waxe, Honey, and Tobacco, and so
euery yeare may we pay the Transportation, vntill we encrease
in people to make Sugars, and discouer Mines.
            If the paines past bestowed in my first attempt, may taste of
your gratefull acceptance, and that I may obtaine your willing
furtherance in the future, I shall then thinke my paines well
imployed, and delight my selfe in labouring for your profit; and
we all shall gaine honour and reputation, by vndergoing the
burden of so worthy a worke; whereby our Nation shall bee
greatly enriched, the Dominion of our Soueraigne much enlarged,
and Gods seruice in those Countries highly aduanced.
            
               R. H.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A RELATION
OF A VOYAGE TO
Guiana performed by Robert
Harcourt of Stanton Harcourt in the
Countie of OXFORD
Esquire.
            
               IN the yeare of our Lord
1608. and the three and
twentieth of March,23, of March 1608. when
I had furnished my selfe
with one ship of fourescore
Tunnes called the Rose;
a Pinnesse of sixe and thirtie
Tunnes called the Patience;
and a Shallop of
nine Tunnes called the Lilly, which I built at Dartmouth;
and had finished my other businesse there, and
prepared all things in readinesse to begin my voyage,
the winde reasonably seruing, I then imbarked my
companie, as followeth.
            In the Rose,The Rose. I was accompanied with captaine Edward
Fisher, captaine Edward Haruey, master Edward
Gifford, and my cosen Thomas Harcourt: And besides
them, I had of Gentlemen and others one and thirtie

land men, two Indians, and three and twentie Mariners
and Saylers.
            In the Patience,
               The Patience. my brother captain Michael Harcort
had with him of gentlemen and others twentie land-men,
and eleuen Mariners and Saylers.
            In the Lilly,
               The Lilly. 
               Iesper Lilly the Master, had one landman,
and two Saylers: so that my iust number (too great
for so few ships of no greater burden) was in all fourescore
&amp;Land men 60. seuenteen, wherof threescore were land-men.
            Being thus imbarked, wee set saile from the Rainge
at Dartmouth the said three and twentieth of March;
but the winde altering vpon a sudden,They set saile the 23. of March. put vs back againe
that euening; and about two of the clock the
next morning (it comming better for vs) we weighed
anchor, and put to Sea: the euening following we lost
sight of the Lyzart, and steered away for the Canaries.
            Vpon Saturday the first of Aprill 1609.The first of April 1609. towards
the euening the winde increased and grew so violent,The Shallop in danger to be lost.
that my Shallop (which we towed in a Cablet by reason
of the foule weather) was that night seperated
from vs; for by the rage and fury of the winde and
Sea, the Cablet brake in sunder, and the little Barke
was in great danger to be cast away, but it pleased God
to preserue her, for the next morning we discryed her
to Leeward of vs, contrary to our expectation, hauing
giuen her lost.
            Then holding on our course, the seuenth day wee
fell with Alegranza and Lancerote, two Islands of the
Canaries: wee stoode in with Alegranza and came to
anchor on the South-west side thereof;They ariue at Alegranza.
                that euening
and the next day I landed my company to exercise
their limbs on shoare: in this Island we found no inhabitants,

nor fresh-water, neither fruitfull tree,
plant, herbe, grasse, nor any thing growing that was
good, onely an abundance of vnwholsome Sea-foule,
which after one meale were vnsauory &amp; distasteful, &amp; a
few wilde Captitos, or wilde Goats, which the craggy
rocks defended frō our hands, and hungry mouthes.
            The eighth of Aprill we departed from Alegranza,
and directed our course for Tenerife,
               Tenerife. another of the Islands.
The eleuenth day I sent the Pinnesse, and the
Shalloppe to water at the calmes, and there to attend
my comming; but with my Shippe I held my course
for Orotauo, a towne on the other side of the Island, in
hope to get some wine amongst the Merchants there;
but not being able (by reason of a contrary winde) to
double Punta de Nega, wee altered our course from
wine to water. And the twelfth day wee Passed by
Santa Cruz, and watered that euening at the Calmes.
            This watering place is very conuenient for all such
as passe by those Islands,An excellent watering place. and is thus to bee found;
there is a wooden crosse neere vnto it, the high Pike
of Tenerife beareth due North from it. There is also a
ledge of rockes to the Eastward of the landing place,
which is a short Sandy bay. When you are landed,
you shall finde▪ the place about fourty or fifty yardes
from the Sea side.
            The next day we met againe with the Pinnesse and
the Shalloppe, who missing of the right place, had not
yet watered, wherefore wee stood backe againe to
guide them to it; but the winde preuenting vs, enforced
them to seeke for water elsewhere, which with
some dificulty they obtained vpon the fifteenth day
in the morning.
            
               
Then wee stood on our course for the riuer of Wiapoco
in Guiana, hauing aprosperous winde, faire weather,
and a smooth Sea. The ninth day of May, wee
fell into the current of the great and famous riuer of
Amazones,
               The riuer of Amazones.
                which putteth out into the Sea such a
violent and mighty streame of fresh water,Fresh water in the Sea 30 leagues from land. that being
thirty leagues from land, wee drunke thereof, and
found it as fresh and good as in a spring or poole.
            This riuer for the great and wonderfull breadth,
(contayning at the mouth neere Sixty leagues) is
rightly termed by Iosephus Acosta the Empresse and
Queene of all flouds:Iosepth Acosta. and by Hieronimus Giraua Tarraconensis:
               Hieron. Giraua Tarraconensis.
it is said to bee the greatest not only of all India,
but also of the whole world; and for the greatues
is called of many the sweete Sea: It riseth and floweth
from the Mountaines of Peru, and draweth out her
streams in many windings &amp; turnings vnder the Equinoctiall,
for the space of one thousand &amp; fiue hundred
leagues and more: although from her fountaines and
springs vnto the Sea it is but six hundred. When wee
entred into the aforesaid current, wee sounded, and
had fouerty fouer fadome water, sandy sounding.
The tenth day the colour of the water changed, &amp; became
muddy, whitish, and thicke; then wee sounded
againe at twelue of the clocke at noone, and had thirteene
fadome; and seauenteene at fower in the after
noone.The 11 of May they made land in Guiana.
                The eleauenth day at eight of the clocke in
the morning we made land, the vttermost point thereof
bearing West from vs, and came to anchor in fiue
fadome water.
            At night the Patience putting in to neare the shoare
came to anchor in 2½ fadome water vpon the floud,

which fell from her vpon the ebbe,The Patience in danger of wracke. and left her
dry vpon the Oaze, and the next floud comming in,
did so shake and beate her against the ground, that before
shee could get off, her rudder was beaten away,
and her ribbes so rent and crased, that if Almighty
God had not preserued her, she had been wrackt: but
(God bee thanked) with much adoe shee came off
into deeper water, and mended her rudder, as well as
the time and place would afford meanes. Then wee
followed on our course, coasting along to the North-north-west,
the land so trending. It is very shoale all
along this coast, the ground soft oaze, but no danger
to bee feared, keeping our ship in fiue fadome water.
            When wee came to the latitude of two degrees and
a halfe,Islands called Carripapoory.
                wee anchored in a goodly bay, by certaine
Islands, called Carripapoory I did at that time forbeare
to make particular discouery of this coast, intending
(if God spare me life) to make a perfect discouery of
the famous riuer of Amazones, and of her seuerall branches,
and countries bordering vppon it, and of all this
tract of land from the Amazones, vnto the riuer of Wiapoco,
which containeth many goodly Prouinces, and
Signiories, which are in this discourse, but briefely
mentioned: For at this time I purpose onely to prosecute
my first proiect, which hastened mee vnto another
place.
            From hence I stood along the coast,The Bay of Wiapoco.
                and the seauenteenth
of May, I came to anchor in the Bay of Wiapoco:
where the Indiands came off vnto vs in two or
three * Canoes,Indian boats. as well to learne of what Nation
wee were, as also to trade with vs, who vnerstanding

that wee were English men boldly came aboard vs
one of them could speake our language well, and was
knowne to some of my company to bee an Indian,
that sometime had been in England, and serued
Sr. Iohn Gilbert many yeeres: they brought with them
such dainties as their country yeeldeth; as hennes, fish,
pinas, platanaes, potatoes, bread of Cassaui, and such
like cates, which were heartily welcome to my hungry
company: In recompence whereof, I gaue them
kniues, beades, Iewes trumpes, and such toies, which
well contented them. But when I had awhile entertained
them, and made knowne vnto them the returne
of the Indian Martyn their country man, whom
I brought with mee out of England, they seemed exceeding
ioyfull, supposing that hee had been dead,
being aboue foure yeares since hee departed from
them.
            The Indian before mentioned to haue serued Sr.
Iohn Gilbert (whose name was Iohn) whilest hee liued
(for he is now dead, and died a Christian) was a great
helpe vnto vs, because hee spake our language much
better then either of those that I brought with mee,
and was euer firme &amp; faithful to vs, vntill his death. By
him I vnderstood that their town was scituate vpō the
east side of the hil in the mouth of Wiapoco, &amp; was called
Caripo: that the Indian Martin was Lord therof, and
that in his absence his brother was chiefe. Moreouer
hee certified me that the principall Indian of that riuer
was called Carasana, (who by good fortune) was
then at Caripo,
               A village called Caripo.
                and so hauing spent sometime in other
conference and friendly entertainement, they tooke
their leaue, and departed for that time. I sent one of

my company with them to giue notice to Carasana,
&amp; the rest of the Indians of Caripo,
               A messenger sent to the Indians. that I had brought
home their Countrymand Martin, whom they all
thought to be dead, and another of their Nation also,
who had kindred and friends amongst them: to desire
him to come aboord my ship, and to bring with him
the principall Indians of Caripo, that I might declare
vnto them the cause of my comming into their Country,
and conferre with them of other matters intended
for their good. The next day I came into the riuer
of Wiapoco, and Anchored ouer against the Sandy
Bay.
            
            The day following the Indians came aboord as I
had desired and brought vs good store of their Country
prouision:The Indians came aboord. 
               Carasana, and one or two more of them
were attired in old clothes, which they had gotten of
certaine Englishmen, who (by the direction of Sir
Walter Raleigh) had traded there the yeere before; the
rest were all naked both men and women; and this I
obserued amongst them,The chiefe men of the Nation of the Yaios couer their priuities. that although the better sort
of men (especially the Yaios) doe couer their priuities,
by wearing ouer them a little peece of Cotton cloth
pretily wouen after their manner; yet did I neuer see
any of their women couered in any part,The women generally goe all naked. either aboue
or beneath the waste, albeit they daily conuersed amongst
vs, but were all (as the plaine prouerbe is) euen
starke belly naked.
            At their comming aboord my ship; first Carasana
as the principall amongst them, and after him the
rest, saluted and welcōmed vs after their rude maner.
I vsed them with all curtesie, and entertained them as
wel as the straight roome would giue me leaue, giuing

them good store of Aquauitae, which they loue exceedingly:
I presented to their view their two countrymen,
Martyn the Lord of their towne, and Anthony
Canabre, who was a christian, and had liued in England
fourteen yeers, both which I had brought home vnto
them: when they beheld them, and after salutations,
and some conference knew to bee the same persons,
whom they supposed had been long since dead, they
expressed much ioy and contentment: aud vnderstanding
(from their owne mouthes) how well I had
vsed them, they seemed to bee better pleased with our
comming: and when their rude salutations to their
new come countrymen were ended, I tooke them apart,
and thus declared the cause of my comming.
            First,Their conference with the Indians. I brought to their remembrance the exploits
performed by Sr. Walter Raleigh in their country, in
the raigne of our late Soueraigne Queene Elizabeth,
when (to free them from seruitude) hee most worthily
vanquished the Spaniards at Trinidado: burned their
towne: tooke their Gouernour Don Anthonio de Berreo
prisoner; deliuered fiue of the Indian Kings imprisoned,
and bound by the necke with collers of Iron;
and with great labour and perill discouered the
riuer of Orenoque, and the countryes adioyning, as far
as the Prouince of Aromaya, the countrey of Topiawary,
and the riuer of Caroly beyond it. And that their
countreymen called the Orenoqueponi,
               The Orenoqueponi rendred themselues subiects to Queene Elizabeth.
                (who are the
borderers of the Orenoque) did then most willingly
submit and render themselues vnder the subiection of
the late Queene; all which they well remembred, and
said, that Sr. Walter Raleigh promised to haue returned
againe vnto them long since.
            
               
Then I excused his not returning according to his
promise, by reason of other imployments of great importance
imposed vpon him by the late Queene:
shewing them moreouer, that when he could not (for
that cause) returne himselfe, hee sent Captaine Keymis
to visite them, and to bring him true intelligence of
their estate, (supposing that he had left no Spaniards
behind him at Trinidado of power to molest them) to
the end that releef &amp; aid might be prepared for them,
according to their necessities, and oppression of their
enemies. Then I told them of the death of the late
Queene, whereby that businesse of theirs was againe
hindered.
            Moreouer I declared vnto them, that our gracious
Soueraigne Lord King IAMES, who now raigneth
ouer v3, (being the onely right and lawfull heire, and
Successor, to the Crowne and dignity of the Realme
of England, after the death of the late Queene) was
throughout the whole land proclaimed King of England;
and so comming to raigne ouer vs, hath been
euer since busied in ordering the State and affaires of
the Kingdome, which being (by his great wisdome)
setled in tranquillity and peace, like a good, gracious,
and worthy King, doth now permit his subiects to
trauell abroad into forraigne Countryes, and Nations
to aid and assist all such as are vniustly molested
by their enemies. Whereupon I, and the rest of these
worthy Gentlemen my associats and friends,Possession of the Countrey taken at Wiapoco, by Captaine Lee to his Meiestics vse. hauing
intelligence by some that had been followers of Captaine
Charles Lee, (who was a man well knowne amongst
them, and heretofore had taken possession of
their Countrey to his Maiesties vse, and was planted

diuers yeares in Wiapoco, where he lyeth buried) of the
great variance and discord depending betweene them
the allyed nations, the Yaios, Arwaccas, Sappaios, &amp; Parago
                     •
                  tos;
and their enemies the Charibes; (all inhabiting
betweene the riuers of Amazones, and Dessequebe)
haue made a long and dangerous voyage into those
parts, to appease their discentions, and defend them
against the Charibes, or other enemies that shall molest
or oppresse them: and now being there arriued,
do intend to make search in those Countries for conuenient
places, where such of our Nation as shall
hereafter come to defend them, may bee fitly seated
to dwell amongst them; that if any of those Nations
shall attempt at any time to disturb the quiet liuing of
their neighboures, they may haue store of English
friends at hand and amongst them, that will not spare
their paines to appease their discords, nor their liues
to defend them from harme.
            When I had thus declared vnto them the cause of
my comming, they made this answere; that with our
comming they were well pleased; but our number
of men they thought too great, that they wanted
meanes to prouide vs bread sufficient for them all, hauing
but a small Towne, few gardens, and slender prouision
for their owne companies, because since Captaine
Lee his death, and his mens departure from
them, they neuer made prouision for any strangers.
            I replied, that albeit their towne was small, and
their gardens few, (for the grounds wherein they
plant their Cassaui, whereof they make their bread,
they call their gardens) yet their Countrey was full
of inhabitants, and had store of gardens to supplie

our wants of bread, and was plentifully stored with
other prouisions sufficient for a greater number,
which I desired might be weekely brought vnto vs, as
need required, for that I meant not to take it without
recompence, but would giue them for it such commodities
as should well please them, which they
wanted: as axes, hatchets, kniues, beades, lookingglasses,
Iewes trumps, and such like things wherein
they most delight.
            Then they desired to consult amongst themselues,The Indians goe to councel.
which I permitted, and expected their answere aboue
two howres, which time they spēt in debating the matter
after their maner, &amp; drinking Aquauitae, and in the
end desired my presence, and made me this answere.
            That they were contented and well pleased wee
should liue amongst them;Their answer. that they would furnish
vs with houses to lodge in, and prouide all necessaries
for vs in the best manner they could. But whereas
I said our King would permit his people to liue &amp;
abide amongst them, and defend them against their
enemies; they answered, it was a thing they greatly
desired, and had expected long, and now they made
much doubt thereof, and said they were but words,
hauing heretofore been
                  By Sr. Walt. Raleigh, and Capt. Lee. promised the like, but nothing
performed. To resolue that doubt, and make
good my speeches, I told them that what I had spoken
should certainely bee performed, and to that end
would leaue my brother in their countrey, and some
of my company with him, to dwell amongst them,
vntill a greater supplie might bee sent from England
for their better defence. Then they seemed to giue
credit to my words: And so after much talke, and

many complements to please the naked people, I
gaue to Carasana a sword, and to the rest some other
things, which pleased them well: and then after their
manner taking their leaue, they departed. The next
day the Indian Martyn went ashoare,The Indian Martyn goeth ashoare. and seemed
ioyfull that hee had againe recouered his owne
home.
            The day following I tooke land, with my companies
in armes and colours displayed, and went
vp vnto the towne,The English take land. where I found all the women and
children standing at their doores to behold vs. The
principall Indians came out vnto me, and inuited me
into the Captaines house, which vntill the returne of
Martyn belonged vnto his brother,The English feasted by the Indians. as chiefe Lord
in his absence: I went vp with them, and was friendly
feasted with many kinds of their Country cates; when
I had well eaten and refreshed my selfe,The gratefull offer of Martyn.
                
               Martyn tooke
mee by the hand and said, that hee had not any thing
wherewith to require my kindnesse towards him, in
such manner as hee desired; neither had hee such delicate
fare, and good lodging for vs, as in England
heretofore wee had been vsed vnto: but humbly intreated
mee to accept of his house in good part for
my selfe, and the Gentlemen of my company; and
the rest should bee lodged in other Indian houses adioyning:
and that such prouisions as the Country
yeelded, should bee prouided for vs. His speech was
approued by the rest of the Indians present, who
tooke mee by the hand one after another, and after
their manner bade mee welcome. I gaue them many
thanks, &amp; some rewards for their kind entertainment;
and thē disposed my company in conueniēt lodgings:

but yet I kept a continual guard, as in time of warre.
            When I had thus setled my company at this village,The English setled at Caripo in Wiapoco.
               
I went out to view the scituation of the place,The strength of the place. and
the aduantages for defence thereof. It is a great rockie
Mountaine, not accessable by reason of fast woods, and
steepe rockes, but only in certaine places, which are
narrow foote-paths, very steepe and easie to bee defended:
whereby wee were lodged as in a Fort, and
most conueniently in respect the harbour was so neer,
for our shippes did ride at anchor vnderneath vs, ouer
against the foote of the hill.
            Being thus ariued vpon the Coast, I found the time
of the yeare so vnseasonable for our purpose, that (by
reason of continuall raines) wee were constrained to
lie still and doe nothing for the space of three weekes,
or a moneth; in which idle time I conferred with the
Indians, so metime with one, sometime with another;
and by helpe of my Indian Anthony Canahre, and the
Indian Iohn aboue mentioned (whom I vsed for my
interpreters) I gathered from them as well as I could,
the State of their Country; the manner of their gouernement
and liuing; how they stood with their
neighbours in tearmes of peace, and warre; and of
what power and strength they were. I inquired also
of the seasons of the yeare in those parts: of their diuision,
and account of times, and numbers; of the
prouisions of their Country for victuals, and other
necessaries; and made a diligent inquiry of all the
commodities their Country yeeldeth, &amp; what things
were of most estimation amongst them; all which I
haue briefely declared vnto your Highnesse in this
following discourse.
            
               
This goodly Country, and spacious Empire, is on
the North part bounded with the Sea,The bounds and limits of Guiana.
                and the great
Riuer of Orenoque, wherein Sr. Walter Raleigh performed
his worthy and memorable discouery: on the
East and South parts, with the famous Riuer of Amazones;
and on the West part with the Mountaines of
Peru.
            
            The westermost branch of the Riuer of Amazones
that falleth into the Sea;
                  Arrapoco a branch of Amazones.
                is called Arrapoco; vpō which
riuer are seated many goodly Signiories wel deseruing
a particular discouery, which shall (by Gods permission)
bee performed hereafter. To the North of Arrapoco
is the riuer of Arrawary,
               Arrawary. which is a goodly riuer,
discouering a gallant Country. From Arrawary vnto
the riuer of Cassipurogh extendeth the Prouince of Arricary;
containing the Signiories of Arrawary, Maicary,
               Maicary.
and Cooshebery;
               
                  Anaky-v-ry chiefe of the Yaios.
                of which Anakyury is principall,
who by Nation is a Yaio, and fled from the borders of
Orenoque for feare of the Spaniards, to whom hee is a
mortall enemy. Hee hath seated himselfe in the Prouince
of Arricary,
               Morooga. and now dwelleth at Morooga in the
Signiory of Maicari. To the N. Norwest of which, there
falleth into the Sea a riuer called Conawini,
               Conowini. wherevpon
the Signiory of Cooshebery bordereth;Cooshebery. whereof an Indian
named Leonard Ragapo is Chiefe,Leonard Rapago Lord of Cooshebery. vnder the subiection
of Anaki-v-ry. This Indian is christened, and hath
been heretofore in England with Sr. Walter Raleigh,
to whom hee beareth great affection; hee can a little
vnderstand and speake our language, and loueth our
Nation with all his heart. During my aboad at Wiapoco,
hauing intelligence of him, and of his Country,
and that certaine stones were found therein, supposed

to bee Diamonds: I sent my Cozen Captaine
Fisher to discouer the same, and to fetch some of those
stones, to bee resolued of the truth.
            At his comming thither, Leonard entertained him
with all kindnesse, not after the ordinary rude manner
of the Indians, but in more ciuill fashion, and with
much respect and loue, hee furnished him with guides
to conduct him through the Country to the place
where the Stones were found, being fifty miles
Southward vp into the Land: beyond which place
there is an high Mountaine appearing in sight, called
Cowob, and on the top thereof (as the Indians report)
a great Lake or Poole,A Mountaine called Cowob.
                full of excellent fish of diuers
kindes. The Country was as pleasant and delightfull,
as euer any man beheld; but the Stones not Diamonds:
yet they were Topases, which being well cut,
and set in Gold by a cunning workman,Topases in Cooshebery. doe make as
faire a shew, and giue as good a lustre as any Diamond
whatsoeuer: which yeeld good hopes of better to be
found hereafter: For where the Topas is found on the
Mountaines of Tenaseren, in the East Indies, the greatest
store of Diamonds are also found.
            When my kinsman returned, Captaine Leonard
came with him to Wiapoco, (being aboue an hundred
miles from his owne Country) only to visite mee and
my company; for the great loue hee did beare to Sr.
Walter Raleigh, and our Nation. I much maruelled to
see him, for assuredly hee is the brauest Indian of all
those parts.
            After hee had been with mee a day or two, hee earnestly
requested mee to send some of my company
into his Countrey, which hee greatly commended for

the wholsome ayre, and plenty of victuals, alleaging
that the place where then wee liued (by his owne experience)
was very vnhealthfull; that our men would
there bee subiect to sicknesse, and die: and for an instance
hee named Captaine Lee, and his company,
who formerly were planted there, and almost all dyed
by sicknesse in the same place: But hee assured me
that his owne Country Cooshebery was of a good ayre,
pleasant, and healthfull; that there they might haue
roome sufficient to build English houses in, (for those
were the words hee vsed) that thither they should be
welcome and should want nothing. Much hee perswaded
to draw mee to his desire, which by his importunity
I granted, and accordingly performed it;
finding his Country answerable to his report; being
for the most part champian ground,The quality of the Prouince of Cooshebery.
                naturally intermixt
of plaine fields, fruitfull meadowes, and goodlywoods,
in such admirable order, as if they had been
planted artificially by handy labour. The fields appearing
aboue the meadowes in pleasant and delightfull
manner, presenting here and there vnto the eye,
from stately Mounts, most beautifull and liuely prospects:
the meadowes bordering on euery side betweene
the fields and woods, the woods growing in
the lowest valleyes betwixt the meadowes, and commonly
are watered with sweete and pleasant fresh
stremes running through them: which strange &amp; rare
mixture of Mounts, valleies, meadowes, fields, and
woods, afford as excellent and healthfull habitations
as can bee wished or desired, but is not greatly peopled.
            From the riuer of Cassipurogh N. Westward to the

riuer of Arracow, and vp further into the land towards
the West, and Southwest, as farre as the riuer of
Arwy, (which falleth into Wiapoco aboue the ouerfalles)
extend the Prouinces of Arracoory,
               Arracoory &amp; Morrownia and Morownia,
which also to the landward (by the relation of my
Brother Captaine Michael Harcourt, and Captaine
Haruey, who haue trauelled and discouered those
parts) are pleasant and delightfull plaine Countries,
like vnto Cooshebery. The Arracoory Countrey is well
peopled, and their chiefe Captaine is called Ipero. Betwixt
the Wiapocoories and Arracoories there is no hearty
loue and friendship, yet in outward shew they hold
good quarter. In Morrownia, there is also store of
people, which are friendly Indians. In that Prouince
there is a very high Hill called Callipuny,
               An exceeding high Hill called Callipuny.
                fashioned
like a Sugerloafe, or a Pyramides, which ouervieweth
and discouereth all the Territories adioyning aboue
an hundred miles.
            Beyond the Country of Morrownia to the Southward
bordering the riuer of Arwy, is the Prouince of
Norrak;
               Norrak. the people thereof are Charibes, and enemies
both to the Morrowinnes the inhabitants of Morrownia,
and to the Wiapocoories; who are also vnder
the subiection of Anaky-v-ry,
               Anaki-v-ry. the Principall and greatest
Lord, or Cassique of all the Yaios in those Prouinces,
bordering vpon the Sea betwixt the Amazones,
South-eastward, and Dessequcbe North-westward.
            From the riuer of Amazones to the Bay of Wiapoco;
there fall into the Sea these riuers following:Riuers falling into the Sea betweene Amazones and Wiapoco.
                
               Arrapoco
(a branch of Amazones) Arrawary, Micary, Conawini,
and Cassipurogh: In the Bay of Wiapoco to the East
of the said riuer, there falleth into the Sea the riuer of

               Arracow; and into Arracow falleth the riuer of Watts.
To the North of Wiapoco there is a smal creeke called
Wianary,
               
                  Wianary a creeke. which letteth in the Sea a daies iorney Westward
vp into the land: some take this creeke to bee a
riuer, but they doe erre in that opinion, it hauing neither
spring nor fountaine from whence it falleth. To
the North, and N. west of the said creeke, there is a
ridge of high Mountains running towards the riuer of
Apurwaca, the soile whereof is excellent &amp; fertile for
Tobacco, and beareth the best of all those parts; so are
the Sugar-canes there growing the best and fairest
that are found vpon the Coast: and all the tract of
Land betwixt the riuers of Wiapoco, and Apurwaca, is
accounted the Prouince of Wiapocoory,
               The Prouince of Wiapocoory.
                containing the
Signiories of Wiapoco, and Wianary. Beneath the ouerfalles
in Wiapoco, (which are forty miles distant
from the Sea) there is much people, both of Yaios, and
Arwaccas:
               Carasana. of the Yaios in this riuer Carasana is chiefe.
Of the Arwaccas,
               Arriquona. 
               Arriquona is Principall. In Wianary
there are few Indians,Casurino. and Casurino is their chiefetaine.
            To the N. west of the Bay of Wiapoco, there fall into
the Sea the riuers of Apurwaca, Cowo, Wio, and Caiane.
               Riuers faling into the Sea, to the N. West of Wiapoco.
               
               Apurwaca is a goodly riuer, and well inhabited;
Cowo is void of inhabitants; Wio is a faire riuer and
leadeth many daies iourney into the high land, and
discouereth a firtile and hopefull Countrey. At Caiane
there is an excellent harbour for shipping of any
burden, which heretofore by Captaine Lawrence Keymis
was called Port Howard: On the Starboord side
as you enter this harbour there is an Iland of low land
called Muccumbro,
               
                  Muccumbro an Island. scituate betwixt the riuers of Caiane
               
and Meccoria, containing in circuit about sixteene
leagues. In this Island there are two Hils, the
one called Muccumbro, whereof the Island taketh the
name; the other called Cillicedemo: from these Hils the
greatest part of the Island may bee ouerviewed, which
containeth many goodly pastures, and meadowes intermixt
with some woods, and is full of Deere, both
red and fallow.
            On the Larboord side, as you enter Caiane there is
another Island of high Land, called Mattoory in
quantity much like vnto the first;
                  Mattoory an Island. this Island for the
commodious scituation, is of great effect for the defence
of the harbour, affording naturally two such
notable conuenient places for the planting of Ordinance
for that purpose, as no industry of art could deuise
better, or more auailable.
            The inhabitants of this Prouince of Caiane, are Charibes,
               
                  Arrawicary chiefe Captaine of the Caiane.
               
their principall commander is called Arrawicary,
who dwelleth at Cillicedemo before mentioned: we
haue found him trusty and faithfull to our Nation;
but to our friend Leoanard of Cooshebery,
               Foure or fiue men placed at Caiane.
                hee is a mortall
enemie. At this mans house I left foure or fiue
of my company, thereby to hold amity and friendshippe
with the Charibes, to learne their language,
and to keepe peace betweene them and the Yaios, Arwaccas,
and other nations their allies.
            To the South-westward of these Prouinces aboue
mentioned towards the high land, there bee many others
which hereafter shall bee more exactly discribed
by a second discouery.
            These Prouinces and Signiories to the Landward
are not plentifully inhabited; the greatest numbers of

people, are seated neere vnto the riuers, and trauell
from place to place in Canoes.
               The manner of their gouernement. There is no setled gouernement
amongst them, onely they acknowledge a
superiority, which they will obay as far as they please.
In euery Prouince or Signiory there is a Chiefe Cassique,
or Captaine, commanding all: So likewise in euerie
Towne and Village,Murder and Adultery punished by death. they commonly chastice murder
and adultery by death, which onely are the offences
punished amongst them, and certaine persons are
appointed by them to execute those punishments.
The Indians take wiues ouer whom they are extreamly
iealous,The Indians by nature iealous ouer their wiues. and expect great continencie in them; for if
they take them in adultery, they presently cause their
braines to be beaten out. The better sort of persons
haue euery one of them two or three wiues,The Indians haue manie wiues. or more,
the rest but one; accounting him that hath most wiues,
the greatest man. Their wiues (especially the elder sort)
are as seruants vnto them, for they make their bread
and drinke, dresse their meate, serue them at meales,
and doe all the other businesse about the house.
            These Prouinces are peopled with diuers Nations
of seuerall languages,Diuers languages in Guiana.
                namely, Yaios, Arwaccas, Sappaios,
Paragotos, and Charibes.
               The Charibes most ancient vpon the sea coast. The Charibes are the ancient
inhabitants, and the other Nations are such as haue
beene chased away from Trinidado, and the borders of
Orenoque. And forasmuch as they haue vnited themselues
in those parts, the Charibes haue held them in
continuall warres, but the Yaios and the other Nations
their Allyes, are growne so strong, that they haue constrained
the Charibes of the Sea cost to contract a peace
with them, yet beare no hearty loue the one Nation to
the other: But with the Charibes inhabiting the in-land

parts vpon the Mountaines, they haue as yet no peace
at all; for they doe often times come downe vpon
them in great numbers,The Indians make warre for their weomen. spoile and burne their houses,
kill their men, and carry away their weomen, which is
the greatest cause of warre and hatred amongst them:
whereof our men haue seene experience in Cooshebery;
where happened an accident worth the obseruing,
which I will here declare vnto your Highnesse. The
Indian Leonard Ragapo, before mentioned, is a Yaio,
who finding the Country of Cooshebery slenderly inhabited,
hath seazed vpon it for his owne Siguiorie; and
at his earnest request, I sent foure Gentlemen of my
company to remaine there with him. The naturall
inhabitants that dwell vpon the vttermost bounds
thereof, towards the South, and West, are Charibes, and
enemies to him, and to his Nation: for while our men
(vnknowne to the Charibes) staied at Cooshebery,
               The Charibes warre vpon Leonard.
                they
assembled themselues together to the number of 200.
or more, and came downe into his Signiorie, burned
and spoiled houses, roasted one woman, tooke many
prisoners, &amp; intended to assault him also: which to preuent
he armed about 50. of his Indians,The vsuall weapons of the Indians. with their vsuall
weapons; which are Bowes and Arrowes, long
staues sharpened at the point, and with fire hardened:
wooden Swords and Targets very artificially made of
wood,
                  Leonard desireth and of the English. and painted with Beasts, and Birds; He requested
also our men to aide and assist him with their muskets,
which I commanded them to doe, vpon all such
occasions offered: And so being all in readinesse, Leonard
(as their captaine) led them on to intercept his
enemies; and as I haue heard by Mr. Henry Baldwin,
(who then was present, and (to obserue the manner

of their warres) gaue him leaue to command all) hee
brauely performed that exploit, in good order after
their manner, and with great iudgement and resolution.
For in the Front, he first placed our foure Englishmen,The manner of ordering their men in the warres.
by two in a rancke; next to them, two Indians
armed with woodden Swords and Targets; then
two archers; and after them two men with sharpned
staues, insteed of pikes: and in like manner ordered,
and ranked all his Company. Being thus prepared, he
marched against the Charibs, who (neer at hand) were
comming in the same order towards him; but when
they approched, &amp; (vnexpected) perceued our English
men amongst the Yaios, they were much amazed, and
made a sudden stand:The Charibes amazed at the sight of the English. which Leonard perceiuing,
guessed rightly at the cause, and instantly did make
good vse of that aduantage. Hee commanded his
owne company to keepe their Station, himselfe with
a sword in his hand (which I had giuen him) and a
Target of his owne fashion, went boldly towards
them to parley with their Captaines. And hauing
called them out,
                  Leonard speaketh to the Charibes.
                hee reproued them for comming
(as enemies) into his Signiory, for burning and spoiling
his houses, and his people; hee demaunded satisfaction
for the hurt done, and restitution of the prisoners
taken; and warned them forthwith to depart
out of his Signiory, and desist from warre: which if
they refused to fulfill, hee was there ready with his
friends the Englishmen to fight with them, and
reuenge his wrongs: and said further, that if in the
conflict any of the English men were slaine, or hurt;
hee would then fetch all the rest from Wiapoco, and returne
to burne their houses, and cut them all in peeces.

Thus he boldly spake, with such a courage, shewing
also our men vnto them,The Charibes agree to peace for feare of the English.
                (who had their match in
cocke ready to discharge) that he strooke such a feare
into them all, by reason of our mens presence, that
they presently agreed to peace, performed what conditions
he required, and then departed home with all
their company. Here may your Highnesse note, the
factions among the Indian Nations; the discipline and
order they hold in war, the feare the Charibes conceiued
at the sight of our Englishmen, and the policy of
the Indian Leonard to take aduantage by their feare,
and make our men his Guard, and chiefe protection
against them. These things in time will much auaile
vs, being well obserued, and rightly applied according
to occasion. But to our former discourse.
            The power and strength of these Countries (being
so thinly peopled,) is not very great to withstand
the might of forraine enemies; the vsuall weapons of
the Indians, are before described, sauing that their arrowes
are oft-times poisoned. But since our trade and
commerce with them, they haue gotten a few good
swords, muskets, caliuers, and some small quantity of
shot and powder; and haue learned to handle their
peeces very orderly, and some of them are good
shot.
            The seasons of the yeere vpon this coast,The season of the yeere in Guiana.
                and in this
climate are diuers, for in the East parts of Guiana towards
the Amazones, the dry weather, which we call
their Summer,Teh summer beginneth in August. beginneth in August; and the violent
raines and tempestuous winds, which we count their
winter, doe begin in February: But in the Westerne
parts,The winter beginneth in February. towards Orenoque, the dry season beginneth in

October, and the raines and windes in Aprill. There
is little difference of heate and cold in this diuersity of
seasons beeing so neere the Equinoctiall, where the
day and night are alwaies equall, the sunne euer rising
and seting at six of the clocke or neere thereabout:
which climat by the ancient Philosophers (in respect
of the neerenes of the Sunne, which causeth excessiue
drowth and heate) was accounted the vnhabitable
and burning Zone:
               The burning Zone.
                but our dayly experience doth
assure vs of their certaine mistaking in that point: for
in those parts wee finde, that when the Sunne declineth
furthest from them towards the Tropicke of Capricorne,
the ayre is then cleerest, and the season of the
yeare most dry; as in the Easterne parts of Guiana in
August, September, October, Nouember and December:
and when the Sunne returneth towards the
Tropicke of Cancer, then doe the raines begin, increase,
and decrease, from February to Iuly: but sometimes
they begin to fall, and the riuers to rise, swell,
and ouerflow sooner or later by a moneth; and the
yeare is sometimes more or lesse windie and wet,
according to the disposition of the heauens, and of
the Planets: and as the Sunne approcheth, or declineth
little, or much, euen so the earth wanteth or aboundeth with water and moisture.
            The reasons of these strange diuersities from other
regions without the Tropickes, are very excellently
declared by Ioseph Acosta in the second book of his natural
&amp; morall history of the Indies,Ioseph Acosta. to which Author
I refer you for your better satisfaction therein: but
withall I must aduertise you, that when you reade
his first and second bookes, you haue regard to the

place where they were writtē, which was in Peru, reputed
by vs to be beyond the Equinoctiall, towards the
South, or Pole Antarticke, lest you erre by mistaking
his meaning: for in those two bookes, when hee
mentioneth any place beyond the Equinoctiall, hee
meaneth towards the North, or Pole Articke. And
also you must note that this generall rule for the heauens
temprature, is only limited to the Region of the
burning Zone, within the Tropickes.
            
            They haue no diuision or account of times or
numbers;Their account of times and numbers. they onely reckon by the Moones, as one,
two, three, foure, or fiue Moones: or by daies in like
manner. Their numbers they reckon thus, one,
two, three, and so to tenne: then they say tenne and
one, ten and two, tenne and three, &amp;c. And to shew
their meaning more certainely, they will hold vp one,
two, three, or more of their fingers, expressing the
numbers, still making signes as they speake, the better
to declare their meaning: when they will reckon
twenty, they will hold downe both their hands to
their feete, shewing all their fingers and toes, and as
the number is greater, so will they double the signe.
When they appoint or promise any thing to bee done
by a time limited, they will deliuer a little bundle of
sticks equall to the number of daies, or Moones, that
they appoint, and will themselues keepe another bundle
of the like number: and to obserue their appointed
time, they will euery day, or Moone take away a
sticke, and when they haue taken away all, then they
know that the time of their appointment is come, and
will accordingly performe their promise.
            As touching Religion, they haue none amongst

them,They vse no sacrifice, nor religious worship to anithing. that I could perceiue, more then a certaine
obseruance of the Sunne and Moone, supposing them
to bee aliue, but vse no religious worshippe towards
them, nor offer sacrifice to any thing: vnlesse they vse
a superstition in their drinking feasts, by sacrificing
Iarres of drinke: for at the death of any of their Cassiques,
Captaines,The manner of their drinking feast at the death of their Captaines. or great friends whom they esteeme,
they will make a solemne feast, (their chiefest prouision
being of their best and strongest drinke, which they
call Parranow) which feast shall continue three or
foure daies, or as long as their liquor lasteth, spending
their time in dancing, singing, and drinking excessiuely:
in which vice they exceede all other nations whatsoeuer,
accounting him that will bee drunke first, the
brauest fellow; during this solemnity of their drinking,
some woman being neerest of kin vnto the party
dead, doth stand by and cry extreamely; thus their
manner is vntill their drinke bee spent, and then the
feast is ended. Whether they vse any superstition in
this custome I know not; time will reueale, and also
reforme it.Their Peeaios or Priests haue conference with the diuel. It is most certaine that their Peeaios, (as
they call them) Priests, or Southsayers, at some speciall
times haue conference with the diuell, (the common
deceiuer of mankinde) whom they call Wattipa,
and are by him deluded; yet notwithstanding their
often conference with him, they feare, and hate
him much, and say that hee is nought: and not without
great reason, for hee will often times (to their
great terror) beate them blacke and blew.Their opinion of the dead. They beleeue
that the good Indians when they die, goe vp,
and will point towards the heauens, which they call
Caupo; and that the bad Indians goe downe, pointing

to the earth,At the death of a Cassique, they kill an Indian to serue him in the other world. which they call Soy. when any Cassique,
Captaine, or chiefe man dieth amongst them,
if hee haue a slaue or prisoner taken from their enemies,
they will kill him; and if he haue none such,
then wil they kill one of his other seruants, that hee
may haue one to attend him in the other world.The quality of the Land.
            
            The quallity of the land in those Countries,
is of diuers kindes, by the Sea side the land is
low, where the heate would bee most vehement, if it
were not quallified and tempered by a fresh Easterly
winde or Brieze, most forcibly blowing in the heate of
the day: in many places this low land is very vnhealthfull,
and little inhabited, by reason of the ouerflowing
of the waters: but for the most part it hath
goodly nauigable riuers, a fertile soile, much people,
and is a healthfull habitation. Vpon the Mountaines
there is a high land, where the ayre is coldest, in some
places it is fruitfull, in others not: but generally is
full of Mineralls, and mines of mettals, and yeeldeth
as many as any part eyther of the East, or West
Indies, both of the best, and of the basest whereof
we shall (by Gods permission) giue good testimony,
to the benefit of our Countrey, and honour of our
Nation in time conuenient: and in most places vpon
the Mountaines there is sound and healthfull dwelling.
There is also a middle sort of land, which is of a
meane height, and is most temperate, healthfull, firtile,
and most inhabited of all other; it aboundeth in meadowes,
pastures, and pleasant streames of fresh water,
in goodly woods, and most delightfull plaines, for
profit, pleasure, sport, and recreation: and also is not
void of Minerals.
            
               
The prouisions of this countrey for victuals,The prouisions for victuals. are
many; First of the roote of a tree called Cassaui, they
make their bread,The roote of Cassaui maketh their bread and drinke. in manner following; they grate
the roote vpon a stone, and presse out the iuice thereof,
which being rawe is poyson, but boyled with Guinea
pepper, whereof they haue abundance, it maketh
an excellent and wholsome sawce, then they drie the
grated roote, and bake it vpon a stone, as wee bake our
Oaten cakes in England. This bread is very excellent,
much like, but far better then our great Oaten cakes,
a finger thicke, which are vsed in the Moorlands, and
the 
                  
                     •
                  eake in Staffordshire and Darbyshire.
            There is a kinde of great wheat called Maix,
               
                  Maix, or Guinea wheat. of
some it is called Guinea wheat, which graine is a singular
prouision in those Countries, and yeeldeth admirable
increase, euen a thousand or fifteene hundred
for one, and many times much more: It maketh
excellent meale, or flower for bread; and very good
malte for beere or ale, and serueth well for sundry other
necessary vses for the reliefe of man.Their diuers kindes of drinke. Of the aforesaid
Cassaui bread, and this wheat the Indians
make drink, which they call Passiaw: it will not keep
long, but must bee spent within foure or fiue daies:
they make another kinde of drinke of Cassaui,
               An excellent drinke made of Cassaui.
                called
Parranow, very good and strong, much like vnto our
best March beere in England, and that kinde of drinke
will keepe ten daies; many sorts they haue which I
haue tasted, some strong, some small, some thicke, some
thinne, but all good, being well made, as commonly
they were amongst the Yaios, and Arwaccas, which are
the cleanliest people of all those Nations.
            There is great store of hony in the Country,Store of hony and although

it bee wilde (being taken out of trees, and buries
in the earth) yet is it as good as any in the world;
of which may be made an excellent drinke much vsed
in Wales, called meath. The hony and the waxe, are
also good commodities for marchandise.
            There be no Vines in that country,The soile excellent for Vines. but the Soyle
being rich and ferlile, and the climate hot, if they
were planted there, they would prosper exccedingly,
and yeeld good Sackes, and Canary wines,
which in those parts we finde to be very wholesome.
            Many other necessary prouisions sufficient for the
sustenance of man,Sundry kinds of beasts in Guiana.
                do there abound in plenty: Namely,
Deere of all sorts, wilde Swine in great numbers,
whereof there are two kinds, the one small, by the Indians
called Pockiero,
               Swine which haue the nauile in the backe. which hath the nauile in the
backe; the other is called Paingo, and is as faire and
large as any we haue in England. There be store of
Hares, and Conies, but of a kinde farre differing from
ours: There be Tigers, Leopards, Ounces, Armadils,
Maipuries which are in taste like beefe, and will take
salt: Baremoes or Ant-Beares, which taste like Mutton,
and other small beasts of the same taste, coloured like
a fawne, Elks, Monkies, and Marmosites of diuers
sorts, both great and small: of these beasts there be innumerable,
and by experience wee haue found them
all good meate. Many other kinds of beasts there are
of sundrie and strange shapes, which heereafter shall
bee figured in their true proportion according to the
life with their names annexed.
            Of Fowles there be diuers kinds;Great variety of Fowles namely, Wildducks,
Widgins, Teates, Wild-geese, Herons of diuers
colours, Cranes, Storks, Pheasants, Partriges,

Doues, Stock-doues, Black-birds, Curlewes, God-wits,
Wood-cockes, Snits, Parrats of sundry sorts,
many other kinds of great and small birds of rare colours;
besides great rauenous fowles; and Hawkes
of euery kinde.
            Of Fish the variety is great,Diuers kinds of fish. first of Sea-fish, there
is Sea-breame, Mullet, Soale, Scate, Thorneback, the
Sword-fish, Sturgion, Seale, a fish like vnto a Salmon,
but as the Salmon is red, this is yellow; Shrimps,
Lobstars,Oysters hang vpon trees. and Oysters which hang vpon the branches
of trees: There is a rare fish called Cassoorwa, which
hath in each eye two sights,A fish hauing 4. eyes, and the ribs, and backe like a man. and as it swimmeth it
beareth the lower sights within the water, and the other
aboue: the ribbes and backe of this fish resemble
those parts of a man, hauing the ribbes round and
the backe flat, with a dent therein, as a man hath; it is
somewhat bigger then a Smelt, but farre exceeding it
for dainty meate; and many other sorts there be most
excellent. Of fresh-water fish many kinds vnknowen
in these parts, but all exceeding good and dainty: And
I dare be bold to say, that this Country may compare
with any other of the world, for the great variety of
excellent fish both of the Sea, and fresh waters. There
is also a Sea-fish which vsually commeth into the fresh
waters, especially in the winter and wet season; it is of
great esteem amongst vs, and we account it halfe flesh,
for the bloud of it is warme; it commeth vp into the
shallow waters in the drowned lands, and feedeth vpon
grasse and weeds:The Sea-cow like beefe. the Indians name it Coiumero,
and the Spaniards Manati, but we call it the Seacow;
in taste it is like beefe, will take salt, and serue to
victuall ships, as in our knowledge hath beene proued

by our Countrimen: Of this fish may be made an excellent
oyle for many purposes; the fat of it is good
to frie either fish or flesh; the hide (as I haue heard)
will make good buffe: and being dried in the Sunne,
and kept from wet, will serue for Targets and Armours
against the Indian arrowes: In the wet season
the store of them are infinite; some of these hides
were heretofore brought into England, by Sr. Walter
Rawleigh.
            
            The seuerall kindes of fruits are many,Sundry kinds of fruits. the Pina,
Platana, Potato, Medler, Plummes of diuers sorts,

                  〈◊〉
                Nuts of strange kindes. The excellency of the
Pina I cannot expresse,Pina. for I dare boldly affirme that
the world affordeth not a more delicate fruit: In taste
it is like Strawberries, Claret wine and Suger. The
Platana is also a very good fruite,Platana. and tasteth like an
old Pippin.Potato. The Potato is well knowen. The Medler
exceedeth in greatnesse.Medler. The Plummes I cannot
commend,Plummes. for to eate much of them doth cause Fluxes,
which in those Countries are daungerous. The
Nuts are good being moderately eaten. Hauing thus
(most excellent Prince) declared the seuerall sorts of
prouisions for victuals and necessary foods,Nuts. it remaineth
that I now make mention of the variety of commodities
found in the Country for the trade of Marchandise,
which in few yeeres, by our paines and industry,
may be brought to perfection, and so setled in
those parts, that not only the vndertakers may receiue
reward for their indeuours, but our country also may
grow rich, by trading for the fruits of our labours.
            The first and principall commodity of estimation,
are the Suger-canes,The variety of Commodities. whereof in those parts there is

great plenty;Suger canes. the soile is as firtile for them as in any
other part of the world: They doe there grow to
great bignesse in a short time; by orderly and fit planting
of them, and by erecting conuenient workes for
the boyling and making of Sugers, (which at the first
will require som charge &amp; expence) may be yeerely returned
great benefit and wealth: the long experience
of the Portugals, and Spaniards, in Brasill, and the
Island of the Canaries; and of the Moores in Barbary,
may giue vs certaine assurance, and full satisfaction
thereof.
            The Cotton wooll is a generall commodity, beneficiall
to our Marchants,Cotton woll. and profitable to our Countrey,
by making of sustians, and seruing for bumbast,
and other vses: for making of Hamaccas, which are
the Indian beds most necessary in those parts, and also
of a fine cotten cloath for cloathing of the people.
There is a naturall Hemp or Flaxe of great vse,Natural hemp or flaxe. almost
as fine as silke as it may bee vsed; wee haue now found
out the best vse of it; and for making of linnen cloath
it is most excellent.
            There bee many rare and singular commodities for
Diers,Diuers commodities for Diers. of which sort there is a red Berry called Annoto,
which being rightly prepared by the Indians, dyeth a
perfect and sure Orange tawny in silke;Annoto. it hath been
sold in Holland for twelue shillings starling the pound,
and is yet of a good price. There is another berry
that dyeth blew. There is also a gumme of a
tree,A gumme which dyeth a yellow in graine. whereof I haue seene experience, that in cloath
dyeth a sure and perfect yellow in graine. There bee
leaues of certaine trees, which beeing rightly prepared,
doe dye a deepe red. There is also a wood

which dieth apurple, and is of a good price; and
another that dieth yellow. There is yet another
wood which dieth a purple when the liquor is hot,
and a crimson when the liquor is cold. Many other
notable things there are (no doubt) not yet knowne
vnto vs, which by our diligent labour and obseruation
in time will be discouered and found.
            The sweet gummes of inestimable value &amp; strange
operation in Phisick &amp; Chirurgery,Sweete Gummes. are innumerable;
there is yellow Amber, Gumma, Lemnia, Colliman,
or Carriman, Barratta, and many more which I omit.
The Colliman hath been proued by Mr. Walter
Cary of Wickham in Buckingham-shire, (a Gentleman
of great iudgement and practise in Phisicke) to bee of
speciall regard for many purposes:The vertues of Colliman or Carriman. this gumme is
black and brittle, much like in shew to common pitch;
if you put a little of it vpon burning coles, it filleth all
the roome with a most sweete and pleasant sauour.
He further reporteth of it, that certainely if you hold
your head ouer the fume thereof three, or foure
times a day, it cureth the giddinesse of the head, and is
also a most excellent comfort and remedy for a
cold, moist, and rheumaticke braine: it is olso good against
the resolution (or as the common sort call it) the
dead Palsie, whereof the giddines of the head is often
a messenger, and the fore-teller of that most pernitious
griefe. It is also of great vse for the paine that
many woomen haue in the lower part of their backes:
which is very common to such as haue had children:
for remedy whereof, it is to bee melted in a pewter
vessell with a gentle fire, then with a knife it must bee
spread lightly vpon a peece of leather, and laid warme

to the place grieued, vntill it come of it selfe. This
Plaister is also very good for aches, and doth greatly
comfort and strengthen the sinewes. Thus much
hath Mr. Cary written and reported of it, and hath
proued by his owne experience.The Colliman helpeth the gout. This Gumme is also
approued to bee an excellent remedy against the
Goute; and of singular vertue in the cure of wounds.
            The Barratta is a most soueraigne Balsamum farre
excelling all others yet knowen:Barratta a rare Balsamum. which by the same
Gentlemans experience is of admirable operation in
the cure of greene wounds: and being burned vpon
coales, is of a sweete and odoriferous sauour.
            There be many other sweet Gummes of great vse
for Perfumes;A perfume like sweet Margerome. whereof one doth make a very rare
perfume, much like vnto the sent of sweet Margerome,
very pleasant and delectable.
            For phisick there be also many excellent Druggs;Druggs and simples for phisicke.
namely, Spiknard, Cassia, Fistula, Sene; and the
earth yeeldeth Bole-Armoniacke, and Terra-Lemnia,
all which are knowen vnto vs. There bee other
Druggs and simples also of strange and rare vertue, in
these parts vnknowen; of which sort there is a little
greene Apple,An apple which prouoketh sleepe to death. by the Indians called in their language
the sleeping Apple; which in operation is so violent,
that one little bit thereof doth cause a man to sleep to
death: the least drop of the iuice of it, will purge in
vehement and excessiue manner, as dangerously was
proued by my Cosen Vnton Fisher, who first found it:
for biting a little of it for a taste, and finding it to
burne his mouth in some extremity, did sodainely
spit it out againe, but some small quantity of the iuice
(against his will) went downe into his stomack, which

for two or three daies space did prouoke in him an extraordinary
sleepinesse, and purged him with 60.
seates. This Apple, for the purging vertue in so small
a quantity, is like to be of good price, and great estimation
in the Practise of Physicke; for the learned
Physicions do well know how to correct the sleeping
quality thereof wherein the danger resteth. There is
a Berry in those parts very excellent against the bloody-fluxe,A berry curing the bloody Fluxe.
by the Indians it is called Kellette. The
iuice of the leafe called vppee,
               A leafe curing the wounds of the poisoned arrowes. cureth the wounds of
the poisoned arrowes. The iuice of the leafe called
Icari, is good against the head-ache. Many other
Druggs and simples are there found of singular properties
both in Physicke and Chirurgery,A leafe curing the headache. which if
they should be seuerally described according to their
valew and vvorthinesse, would containe a large volume.
            Moreouer the Tree wherewith they take their fish,A wood that maketh fish drunke.
is not a little to be esteemed, but chiefely the great
goodnesse of God therein is highly to be praised and
admired, who amongst so many admirable things by
him created, and planted in those parts, hath vouchsafed
to bestow vpon those barbarous people so great
a benefit, and naturall helpe, for the present getting
of their foode and sustenance. These Trees are commonly
growing neere vnto the places of their habitation
for their present vse: for when, at any time, they
goe to fish, they take three or fowre little sticks of this
tree, and bruise them vpon a stone, and then go into
certaine small creekes by the Sea shore, which at a
high water are vsually full of very good fish of diuers
kinds, which come in with the tide; and there they

wade vp and downe the water, and betweene their
hands rub those smal bruised sticks therein, which are
of such vertue, that they will cause the fish to turne vp
their bellies, and lie still aboue the water for a certaine
time: In which space they presently take as many as
they please, and lade them into their Canoes, and so
with little labour returne home sufficiently prouided.
            There is also a red speckled wood in that Country,
called Pira timinere, which is worth 30 or 40.
pounds a tunne: It is excellent for Ioyners worke; as
Chaires, Stooles, Bed-steds, Presses, Cupboords, and
for Wainscot. There are diuers kinds of Stone of
great vse, and good price, as Iasper, Purphery, and
the Spleene-stone.
            There is yet another profitable commodity to be
reaped in Guiana,
               Tobacco. and that is by Tobacco, which albeit
some dislike, yet the generality of men in this kingdome
doth with great affection entertaine it. It is
not only in request in this our Country of England
but also in Ireland, the Neatherlands, in all the Easterly
Countries, and Germany; and most of all amongst
the Turks, and in Barbary. The price it holdeth is
great, the benefit our Merchants gaine thereby is infinite,
and the Kings rent for the custome thereof is
not a little. The Tobacco that was brought into this
kingdome in the yeare of our Lord 1610. was at the
least worth 60. thousand pounds: And since that time
the store that yeerly hath come in, was little lesse. It is
planted, gathered, seasoned, and made vp fit for the
Merchant in short time, and with easie labour. But
when we first arriued in those parts, wee altogether
wanted the true skill and knowledge how to order it,

which now of late wee happily haue learned of the
Spaniards themselues, whereby I dare presume to
say, and hope to proue, within few moneths, (as others
also of sound iudgement, and great experience
doe hold opinion) that onely this commodity Tobacco,
(so much sought after, and desired) will bring
as great a benefit and profit to the vndertakers, as euer
the Spaniards gained by the best and richest Siluer
myne in all their Indies, considering the charge of
both.
            The things which the Indians desire from vs by
way of trade in exchange for the aboue named commodities,The commodities most esteemed by the Indians.
(whereby we hold society and commerce
with them) are Axes, Hatchets, Bil-hookes kniues, all
kinde of Edge tooles, Nailes, great Fishhookes, Harping-irons,
Iewes-Trumps, looking-glasses, blew, and
white Beades, Christall Beades, Hats, Pinnes, Needles,
Salt, Shirts, Bands, linnen and wollen Cloathes,
Swords, Muskets, Calliuers, Powder, and Shot: but
of these last mentioned, wee are very sparing, and part
not with many, vnlesse vpon great occasion, by way
of guift to speciall persons.
            For these toies, and such like trifeling things the Indians
will sell vnto you any of the aboue mentioned
commodities that can be gotten or prepared by them;
or any thing they haue, or that their Countrey yeeldeth;
and will performe any reasonable labour for
them. Thus haue I deliuered vnto your Highnesse,
the particulars of the seuerall commodities, which hitherto
we haue discouered, and found likely to bee
profitable in Guiana; (whereof examples are remayning
to bee seene in the hands of Mr. Henry Houenaer a

Dutch-man, who in the yeere of our Lord 1610. performed
a voiage to Guiana, to the places where our
Company was seated, and now abideth in Thames-streete,
neere vnto Cole-harbour: and I make no
doubt, that by continuance of time, our painefull trauels,
and diligent obseruations, wee shall discouer and
get knowledge of an infinite number of others, as
rich, necessary, and beneficiall as these already spoken
of, or any other whatsoeuer: if it please Almighty
God to fauour and blesse our proceedings.
            When the raines ceased, which was in Iuly, I began
to trauaell abroad in search of those Golden Mountaines,
promised vnto vs before the beginning of our
voiage, (by one that vndertooke to guide vs to them)
which filled my company so full of vaine expectation,
and golden hopes, that their insatiable and couetous
mindes (being wholy set thereon) could not bee
satisfied with any thing but oenly Gold. Our guide
that vainely made those great promises, being come
vnto the wished place to make performance, was then
possessed with a shamelesse spirit of ignorance, for hee
knew little, and could performe nothing. What other
intelligences (of Mines already fouud) I had from
other men in England, and from the Mr. of my ship,
who had bin heretofore in those parts, I foūd them by
experience false, and nothing true concerning Mines,
that was in England reported vnto me.
            Our greedy desire of Gold being thus made frustrate,
diuers vnconstant persons of my vnruly company
began to murmure,Disorders by mutiny. to bee discontented, to kindle
discords and discensions, and to stirre vp mutiny,
euen almost to the confusion and ruine of vs all: and

were vpon the point to shake off all obedience to their
commanders; to abandon patience, peace, &amp; vnity, and
wilfully to breake out into all mischeefe &amp; wretched
disorder, onely because they were deceiued of their
golden hopes &amp; expectations: but with good words,
and comfortable perswasions, I pacified them for the
time, and made them acquainted with my better
hopes conceiued of the commodities aboue mentioned.
I perswaded them in generall from idlenesse,
to trauell abroade, to search and seeke out amongst
the Indians what other nouelties they could (though
gold were wanting) whereby wee might hereafter
benefit our selues; and still I imployed them some one
way, and some another, to occupie their mindes by
doing something, the better to preuent discention,
which commonly is bred of idlenesse, the slouthfull
mother of all filthy vices.
            As I daily conuersed amongst the Indians, it chanced
one day, that one of them presented mee with a
halfe Moone of mettall, which held somwhat more
then a third part Gold, the rest Copper: another also
gaue mee a little Image of the same mettall; and
of an other I bought a plate of the same (which hee
called a spread Eagle) for an Axe. All which things
they assured mee were made in the high Countrey of
Guiana,
               The high Countrey of Guiana aboundeth with Images of Gold. which they said did abound with Images of
Gold, by them called Carrecoory. These things I shewed
to my company to settle their troubled mindes,
which gaue much contentment to the greater part of
them, and satisfied vs all that there was Gold in Guiana.
Shortly after that my Indian Anthony Canabre,
brought mee a peec of a rocke, of white Sparre,

whereof the high Countrey is full: And if the white
Sparres of this kinde,The rocks of the purest white Sparre are Mines of gold or siluer. which are the purest white of all
others, (for euery sort of Mine hath a sparre, and for
the most part white) bee in a maine rocke, they are
certainely Mines of Gold, or Siluer, or of both I
made triall of a peece of Sparre, which the same Indian
discouered vnto me, and I found that it held both
Gold, and Siluer, which (although it was in small
quantity) gaue mee satisfaction that there bee richer
Mines in the Countrey to bee found: but the best
lie deeper in the earth, and wee had not time nor
power to make search for them.
            Being thus informed, and sufficiently resolued of
the commodities of the Countrey, &amp; well satisfied of
the Minerals; I bent all my endeauours to finde out
the fittest places, and most conuenient for our first
plantations: at the last I found out many, and some of
speciall note, which are (for many respects) of great
importance; and when time serueth, our forces and
number of men being answerable, I will lay them open
to the knowledge of the world: and for wealth I
hope they shall fully answere all mens expectations.
            I trauelled vp the riuer of Wiapoco, to view the ouerfalles,
but the waters being high and strong, I could
not passe them. In August when they are fallen, with
some labour they may bee passed.Many ouerfalles in Wiapoco.
                This riuer hath
very many ouerfalles, lying one a good distance beyond
another, euen to the head thereof. Aboue some
of the first falles there dwelleth an Indian, called Comarian,
who is an old man of a free disposition; by
him I learned that a certaine distance aboue the first
falles, the riuer Arwy falleth into Wiapoco; moreouer

that certaine daies iourney beyond him towards the
high land, vpon the borders of Wiapoco, there is a Natiō
of Charibes hauing great eares of an extraordinary
bignes,People hauing great eares, who worship an Idoll of stone. hard to bee beleeued, whom hee called Marashewaccas:
amongst these people (as Comarian reporteth)
there is an Idole of stone, which they worship
as their God; they haue placed it in a house made
of purpose for the greater honour of it, which they
keepe very cleane and hansome.
            This Idole is fashioned like a man sitting vpon his
heeles,The proportion of the Idole. holding open his knees, and resting his elbowes
vpon them, holding vp his hands with the
palmes forwards, looking vpwards, and gaping with
his mouth wide open. The meaning of this proportion
he could not declare, although he hath been
many times amongst them, and hath often seene it.
What other Nations were beyond these he did not
know, hauing neuer trauailed so farre, but hee sayth
they be Charibes, and also enemies vnto them. It seemeth
there bee many Nations of those great eared
people: for in the Riuer of Marrawini I heard also of
the like, who dwell farre vp towards the high land, as
hereafter you shall heare and I suppose, by the trending
of the Riuers of Wiapoco, and Marrawini, are
all one people.
            Vpon the 14. day of August I went vnto a Mountaine,
called Gomeribo, being the vttermost point of
land to the Northward in the bay of Wiapoco; I found
the soile of it most excellēt for Tobacco, Maix, Cotton
trees, Annoto trees, Vines, &amp; for any other thing
that should be planted there. When I had taken good
view of the place, and found it commodious for many

purposes;Possession taken for the king at Gomeribo,
                then in the presence of Capt. Fisher, diuers
Gentlemen, and others of my company, and of
the Indians also, I tooke possession of the land, by
turfe and twig, in the behalf of our Soueraigne Lord
King IAMES: I tooke the said posession of a part,
in name of the whole continent of Guiana, lying betwixt
the riuers of Amazones and Orenoque, not being
actually possessed, and inhabited by any other Christian
Prince or State; wherewith the Indians seemed
to be well content and pleased.
            In like manner my Brother Capt. Michael Harecourt,
and Capt. Haruey, (whom I left as his associate,
and hee esteemed as an inward friend,) in a notable
iourney, which (to their great honour) they performed,
to discouer the Riuer of Arrawary, and the
Country bordering vpon it, (neere adioining to the
riuer of Amazones) did take the like possession of the
land there,The like possession taken at Arrawary.
                to his Maiesties vse.
            The dangers and great difficulties which they in
that attempt incountred, were memorabe, and such,
as hardly any of our Nation in such small Canoes (being
onely some-what longer, but not so broad as our
Thames wherries, and flat bottomed,) euer ouercame
the like. First the number of their owne attendants
besides themselues, was onely one man, and a boy:
Their troope of Indians 60. persons. Their iourney
by Sea vnto the Riuer of Arrawary was neere 100.
Leagues: wherein (by the way) they met with many
dreadful plunges, by reason of a high going sea, which
breaketh vpon the flats and shoales; especially, at
the next great cape to the North of Arraway, which,
in respect of the danger they passed there, they named

               Point Perilous.
               Point Perillus. Then their discouery vp the riuer, was
50. leagues more: where they found a Nation of
Indians, which neuer had seene white men, or Christians
before, and could not be drawne to any familiar
commerce, or conuersation, no not so much as
with our Indians, because they were strangers to
them, and of another Nation. The discouery of this
riuer is of great importance, and speciall note, affording
an entrance more behouefull for the▪ searching
and discouery of the inland parts of Guiana, then any
other riuer yet knowne vpon the Coast; for trending
Westward vp into the land, it discouereth all the
Countries and Nations to the Southward of Arricary,
Cooshebery, Morrownia, and Norrack, which I haue
mentioned before.
            Many weekes they spent in this aduenture, still
taking vp their lodgings in the woods at night. Prouision
of meate they wanted not,A great argument of plenty in the Countrey. for Fish were euer
plenty, and at hand: and the woods yeelded eyther
Deere, Tigers, or Foule: their greatest want was of
bread and drinke, which onely defect did hinder (at
that time) the accomplishment of that discouery. For
when the Indians perceiued their bread to bee neere
spent, and their drinke to bee corrupted, they could
not bee perswaded to proceede, hauing no meanes to
supply their wants amongst the Arrawaries, the Indians
of that riuer, who would not freely trade with
them vpon this first acquaintance, but alwaies stood
vpon their guard, on the other side of the riuer, where
they inhabited: yet they desiring to obtaine some of
our English commodities, and make triall of our Indians
friendshippe, afforded some small trade for their

present releefe during their aboade in that riuer: So
that of force they were constrained to breake off their
discouery, and hasten homeward.
            But here their dangers ended not, for as they returned,
arriuing at certaine Islands called Carripoory, and
passing betweene them &amp; the main land, much against
the wils of all the Indians, who knowing the danger
of the place, and more respecting their safety, then
their owne, (being themselues all expert swimmers)
would haue disswaded them from that hazard: but
they being ignorant of the perill, would needs passe
onne, and at the last met with such a Boore (as the Sea-men
terme it) and violent encounter of two tydes
comming in,A dangrous Boore at Carripoory.
                which like two furious inraged Rammes,
or Bulles, rushed togeather, and oft retired back, to returne
againe with greater violence, vntill the one (by
force had ouerborne the other: that if next vnder
God) the diligent care and paines of the Indians had
not preserued thē, they had been there destroyed, and
swallowed vp by that mercilesse Boore or breach of
waters; which (God be thanked) they escaped, and
returned home in safety.
            Here may your Highnesse fitly note and obserue
two things,Two speciall things to bee obserued. the one, the assured loue and fidelity of
the Indians to our Nation; who hauing in their power
for six weekes space, foure only of our company,
and two of those the chiefest of the rest; and if they
had been false &amp; trecherously minded towards them,The fidelity of the Indians
might easily haue drowned, starued, or slaine them;
yet did not only forbeare to practise harme against
them, but did also safely rowe their boats; night by
night prepare their lodgings in the woods, &amp; daily vse

their care and best endeauours to discouer and preuent
all dangers that might happen to them, and to
guide them, serue them, and prouide them meate.
Such trust and faithfulnesse is rarely found amongst
such barbarous infidels, and yet wee haue had three
yeeres experience thereof. The other thing to bee
obserued heere,The plenty of victuals. is the store and plenty of victuals in
Guiana; where sixty foure persons togeather in one
company, without any prouision of victuals (bread
and drinke excepted) before hand made, could trauell
abroade for six weekes space, most commonly
lodging in the woods, seldome in any towne or village,
and yet in all places wheresoeuer they came,
could readily get meate sufficient for them all: which
blessing God hath giuen to Guiana; for the comfort
of all such as shall bee willing to bee planters there.
            This, and much more could my Brother haue truely
auouched, if hee had liued; but (since his returne
into England) it hath pleased God, who gaue him
life, and preserued him from many dangers, to take
him to his mercy. But the other, Captaine Haruey,
suruiueth, whose life hath euer suted with a generous
and worthy spirit, professing Armes, and following
the warres: who also is generally well knowne, to be
a Gentleman, both honest, and of spotlesse reputation;
hee will auerre and iustifie for truth, what heere
is mentioned. But I will now returne from whence I
haue digressed.
            When I had (as before) taken possession at Gomeribo,
               
                  Gomeribo deliuered to an Indian as the Kings tenant.
in presēce of the said parties, I deliuered the possessiō
of that Mountain to my Indiā 
               Anthony Canabre, To
haue, hold, possesse, and enioy the same, to him, and to

his heires for euer, of our Soueraigne Lord King Iames,
his Heires and Successors, as his subiect; Yeelding and
paying yeerely the tenth part of all Tobacco, Cotton
wooll, Annoto, and other commodities whatsoeuer,
which should hereafter bee either planted or growing
within the said Mountaine, if it were demanded. The
Indian most gladly receiued the possession vpon these
conditions, and for himselfe, and his posterity, did
promise to bee true subiects vnto the Kings Maiestie:
his heires, and successors: And to pay the duties imposed
vpon them: and so that busines being finished,
I returned againe to Wiapoco.
            
            Now (most worthy Prince) there came vnto my
knowledge, an inconuenience happened by the carelesse
negligence of the Master of my ship, who had
the charge of prouiding and laying in the prouisions
and victuals for the voyage,The only cause of losse by the Voyage. which was the cause that I
gained no present profit by it, but left off all my discoueries
in the first beginning. I had a purpose at that
time to performe a businesse, which might haue proued
profitable, and honourable vnto vs, if I had been
able to haue staied the time, but it was not my chance
to bee so fortunate: for the Master, his Mates, and the
Steward of my Shippe, came vnto mee, and told me
plainly, that if I made any longer aboad in that Countrey,
I would neuer in those Shippes returne into
England: or if I did aduenture it, my selfe, and all my
company would starue at Sea for want of Beere, Syder,
and water, for all my Caske was spoiled, because
it was not Iron-bound; the woodden hoopes flew
off, by reason of the heate of the Clymate; and our
Beere, and Syder, (whereof wee had good store) did

leake about the shippe, that wee could hardly saue
sufficient to releeue vs, if wee made a longer stay vpon
the Coast; which was the Masters fault, hauing had a
speciall charge to bee carefull of that onely poynt. By
this default, I was constrained to make a vertue of necessity,
and prepare my selfe for England, and leaue
my former purposes to bee accomplished hereafter,
which shall bee done (God aiding mee) in time conuenient.
            Then disposing of my company,Capt. Michael Harcourt left commander of the company. I appointed my
Brother Captaine Michael Harcourt to remaine in
the Countrey, as chiefe Commander in my absence,
and to continue the possession on the Kings behalfe;
I gaue him directions to trauell abroad, as (occasion
serued) to discouer the Countrey, to spend sometime
at Cooshebery, and sometime also in other places; but
to make his chiefest residence at Wiapoco, (the onely
Rendeuous for shippes that trade vpon that Coaste)
and there to plant good store of Maix, for our reliefe
of bread and drinke, which is the chiefest thing to be
respected in those parts; for other victuals we need not
take much care being alwaies easily prouided. He performed
his charge with great reputation, discouered
many goodly Prouinces, and spacious Countries; and
worthily continued the possession full three yeeres
compleat. I left with him for his assistance, Captaine
Haruey, aboue mentioned, who hath nobly vowed his
time and fortune to bee imployed in the prosecution
of this honourable action. For his Liuetenant I appointed
Mr. Edward Gifford,
               Twenty men left with Captaine Harcourt at Waipoco.
                a valiant and worthy
Gentleman; and I left also with him of Gentlemen
and others, about twenty more, with all such necessaries

as I could spare, and thought conuenient for
them: and so commending them to God the eighteenth
day of August I departed from Wiapoco, and the
day following arriued at Caiane.
            
            At my comming to Caiane my Pinnesse receiued a
leake,The Pinnesse receiued a leake at Caiane.
                which would haue proued dangerous, if wee
had been far at Sea; whereby enforced to attend the
stopping thereof, and new trimming of the Pinnesse;
and vnwilling to bee idle in the meane space doing nothing,
I left my shippes there to repaire their defects,
and in my ship-boate departed thence, the twenty
three of August: taking with mee Captain Fisher,
who hath euer been (since wee first crept into the
world) my chiefe companion, both in Armes and
trauels; I tooke also with mee his brother Vnton Fisher,
Mr. Cradle the Masters mate of my ship, and about
six more. I followed the Coast to the Westward
stering due West,R. Meccooria.
                and passing by the riuer of Meccooria,
I lodged that night in the mouth of the riuer
Courwo:
               R. Courwo.
                which hath a narrow deepe entrance, and
within affordeth a good harbour, which may in time
to come (for some speciall purpose) bee of great
vse.
            The next day, and the night following I proceeded
Westward with full saile, and passing the riuers
of Manmanury,
               Riuers to the West of Courwo▪
                  
                
               Sinammara, Corassowini, Coonannonia,
Vracco, and Amanna; I arriued the twenty fiue day at
the riuer of Marrawini, which openeth a faire riuer,
but is shoale vpon the Barre, which lyeth two or three
Leagues off at Sea, hauing but two fadome water:
within the Barre, the Channel is three, foure, fiue, and
six fadome deepe. Fiue leagues within the ruier wee

passed by certaine Islands called Curewapory,
               Islands called Curewapory.
                not inhabited,
for at the rising of the waters they are alwaies ouerflowen,
of which sort the riuer hath very many: wee
lodged that night a litle beyond these first Islands at a village
called Moyemon, on the lefthand, the Captaine thereof
is called Maperitaka, of the Nation of the Paragotos,
a man very louing and faithfull to our Nation,
whereof wee haue had good proofe. The next day wee
proceeded vp the riuer three leagues, and stayed at a
towne called Coewynay on the right hand, at the house of
Minapa, (the chiefe Charib of that Signiory) to prouide
two Canoes to prosecute our iourney for the discouery
of this riuer.
            The twenty eight day wee went forward passing many
villages and townes,They proceede in discouery of Marrawini.
                which I forbeare to name, and
hauing gone about twenty leagues from the Sea, wee
found the riuer in a manner barred vp with rocks, ouer
which the water falleth with great violence, yet notwithstanding
wee aduentured to proceed,The riuer full of ouerfalles. and the further
wee went, the more dangerous we found the ouerfalles,
and more in number; but when we had passed the first
Mountaine, towards the high Countrey of Guiana, called
Sapparow, and discouered far off before vs other high
Mountaines called Matawere Moupanana,
               They went six daies iourney vp the riuer. and had proceeded
6. daies iourney vp the riuer (which was more thē
forty leagues) we met with such shoale rocky streame, &amp;
great ouerfalles, that there to our griefour iourny ended.
            Being thus for that time debarred from our intended
discouery, wee prepared our selues with Patience to returne
towards our shippes, and the third day of September
wee turned downe the riuer, shooting the ouerfalles
with more celerity then when wee came vp, dispatching
three daies iourney in one, and the fifth day returned

safe to Moyemon; but before I departed thence, Captaine
Fisher told mee of certaine plants which hee had
then found, much like vnto Rose-trees, growing about
halfe a yard in height, whereof (for the strangenesse of
them) I cannot forbeare to adde a word or two.
            These plants or little trees had assuredly the sence of
feeling,Trees which had the sense of feeling. as plainely appeared by touching them: for if
you did but touch a leafe of the tree with your finger,
that leafe would presently shrinke, and close vp it selfe,
and hang downe as if it were dead; and if you did cut
off a leafe with a paire of cisers, then all the other leaues
growing vpon the same tree would instantly shrinke and
close vp themselues, and hang downe as if they were dead
and withered, and within halfe a quarter of an hower,
would by degrees open themselues againe, and flourish
as before; and as often as you did either touch or cut
off any of them, they would doe the like; which did euidently
shew a restriction of the spirits, inuincibly arguing
a Sence. Howsoeuer this may seeme strange and incredible
to your Highnesse, and to them that haue not
seene it,Scallger, Exercit. 181. sect. 28. yet forasmuch as Scaliger, and Bartas make mention
of the like, I dare bee bold to affirme it vpon my
credit,Bartas, Eden, 1. day, 2. week. hauing seene and shewed it to forty others: I gathered
two of the plants, and did set them in pots in their
owne earth, and carried them aboord my shippe, where
I kept them fairely growing almost a fortnight, vntill
they were destroied by certaine Munkies that brake
loose, and pulled them in peeces: which might haue been
preuented, but that I was constrained to set them in the
open ayre, the better to preserue them.
            The seuenth day I went to Wiawia, a great towne of
Paragotos,
               
                  Viawia a Towne of 20 houses. and Yaios, foure leagues to the West of Marrawini,
whereof Maperitaka aboue mentioned, and Arapawaka
               
are chiefe Captaines. At this towne I left my
Cozen Vnton Fisher,
               Mr. Vnton Fisher and two others left at Wiawia▪
                and Humfrey Croxton an Apothecary,
to beare him company, and one seruant to attend him
called Christopher Fisher, hauing first taken order with
Maperitaka for their diet, and other necessaries, both for
trauell, and otherwise: who euer since (according to
his promise) hath performed the part of an honest man,
and faithfull friend.
            I gaue directions to my Cozen Fisher to prosecute the
discouery of Marrawini, and the inland parts bordering
vpon it, when the time of the yeere, and the waters better
serued; and if it were possible to goe vp into the high
Countrey of Guiana, and to finde out the City of Manoa,
mentioned by Sr. Walter Raleigh in his discouery.
He followed my directions to the vttermost of his ability,
being of a good wit, and very industrious, and inabled
to vndergoe those imployments, by obtaining the
loue, and gaining the languages of the people, without
which helpes, there is little or no good to bee done in
those parts.
            When the waters of Marrawini were risen, and the
riuer passable,Mr. Fisher trauelled eleuen daies iourney vp the riuer of Marra, viz. 100 leagues. (much differing from the riuer of Wiapoco,
which is not to bee trauelled, but in the lowest waters.)
He began his iourney for the discouery thereof, in
company of the Apothecary, his seruant Fisher, the Indian
Maperitaka, and eighteene others, and proceeded eleauen
daies iourney vp the riuer, to a towne of Charibes
called Taupuramune, distant from the Sea aboue an hundred
leagues;The Prouince of Moreshegoro.
                but was foure daies iourney short of Moreshego,
which is also a towne of Charibes, scituate vpon
the riuer side in the prouince of Moreshegoro: the chiefe
Captaine thereof is called Areminta: who is a proud and
bold Indian, much feared of all those that dwell within

his Territories,Indians with rough skins like Buffe. hauing a rough skin like vnto Buffe leather,
of which kinde there bee many in those parts; and
I suppose proceedeth of some infirmity of the body.
            Hee vnderstood by relation of the Indians of Taupuramune,
and also of Areminta, that six daies iourney beyond
Moreshego, there are diuers mighty Nations of Indians,
hauing holes through their eares, cheekes, nostrils,
and nether lippes, which were called Craweanna,
Pawmeeanna,
               Diuers mighty Nations of Indians far vp in Marrawini, towards the high land. 
               Quikeanna, Peewattere, Arameeso, Acawreanno,
Acooreo, Tareepeeanna, Corecorickado, Peeauncado,
Cocoanno, Itsura, and Waremisso: and were of strength
and stature far exceeding other Indians, hauing Bowes,
and Arrowes foure times as bigge: what the Indians also
report of the greatnesse of their eares, I forbeare to
mention, vntill by experience we shall discouer the truth
thereof. Moreouer hee learned that there fall into Marrawini
diuers great riuers,Riuers falling into Marrawini.
                called Arrennee, Topannawin,
Errewin, Cowomma, Poorakette, Arroua, Arretowenne, Waoune,
Anape, Aunime, and Carapio: whereof some he hath
seene himselfe.Twenty daies iourney from Taupuramune to the head of Marraw▪
                  
                That it was twenty daies iourney, from
Taupuramune, to the head of Marrawini, which is inhabited
by Arwaccas, Sappaios, Paragotos, and some Yaios;
and that a daies iourny from thence to the land-ward
the Countrey is plaine,The Country aboue the head of Mar. is plaine, and Champian ground. and Champian ground, with
long grasse. Hee passed in this iourney aboue eighty ouerfalles
of water, and many of them very dangerous: of
some of them I had experience the yeere before. Hee
proceeded no further at that present, being vnprouided
for so long a iourney, supposing that it had been neerer
(then hee found it) to the head of the riuer by a fortnights
trauell: and so returned backe in six daies space,
intending better preparation for a second iourney: but
his purpose was preuented by an vntimely death: for

shortly after hee was drowned by misfortune; whereby
we see, that man determineth, but God disposeth.
            The tenth day of September being Sunday,The tenth of September they left Guiana.
                I left the
main of Guiana, and in my ship-boat stood off into the sea
to seek my ships, which were forced to ride foure leagues
from shoare, by reason of the shoales; but as wee passed
ouer them,They were in danger to be cast away. wee were in danger to bee cast away by the
breach of a sea, which verily had sunke our boat, if with
great celerity we had not lightned her, by heauing ouerbord
many baskets of bread, of Cassaui, Maix, Pinas, Platanas,
Potatoes, and such like prouision, wherewith our
boat was loaden; by which meanes it pleased God to deliuer
vs from present destruction, and to bring vs safe vnto
our ships.
            When I came aboord, we weighed anchor, and steered
away from the Island of Trinidado, and vpon the 18. day
in the morning,They finde three English shippes at Pūta de Galea.
                we arriued at Punta de Galea, where wee
found three English ships at anchor, which was no small
comfort vnto vs, considering our great defects &amp; wants.
One of these shippes was called the Diana, belonging to
Mr. Lula Dutch merchant dwelling in London. The other
two, the Penelope, and the Indeuor, belonging to Mr. Hall,
a merchant also of London. We staied at this place 6. daies
to mend our bad caske, and to take fresh water: during
which time I was kindly intreated, &amp; feasted by the Merchants,
and had supply of al such things as I stood in need
of; which curtesie I requited in the best manner I could
for the present.
            Vpon Sunday the twenty foure of September we
weighed anchor, so likewise did the Diana (the other
two shippes being gone two or three daies before vs,)
but the wind shifting to the north-east▪ inforced vs backe
againe almost to the same place from whence we departed.

The twenty fiue we weighed againe, and plied along
the shoare towards Cape Brea,
               Pitch gotten in the earth, which melteth not with the Sunne. about three leagues. This
Cape is so called of the Pitch which is there gotten in the
earth, whereof there is such abundance, that all places on
this side of the world may be stored therewith.
            It is a most excellent Pitch for trimming of shippes
that passe into these Regions and hot Countries, for it
melteth not with the Sunne, as other Pitch doth.
            The twenty six day wee stood along againe, the
winde being still contrary and variable, intermixt with
many calmes,They arriue at Port ae Hispania.
                &amp; so continued vntill the second of October,
when we arriued at Port de Hispania.
            
            Within two daies after our arriuall there, Don Sanches
de Mendosa,
               
                  Don Sanches de Mendosa commeth aboord their shippe. the Teniente for that yeare, with certaine other
Spaniards came aboord vs: we gaue them the best
entertainement that our meanes, the time, and place
would affoord, and had much friendly conference together.
They told me, that they lately had a conflict with
the Charibes, wherein they had lost seuen or eight of their
men, and had many others hurt and wounded, whereof
some came to my Chirurgion to haue their wounds
dressed during our aboad there. And they plainely
confessed that they are verie much molested by the
Charibes,
               The Spaniards much molested by the Charibes. and knew not how by any meanes to suppresse
them.
            We staied at Porte de Hispania vntill the seuenth day,
in hope to get some good Tobacco amongst the Spaniards,
who daily fed vs with delaies and faire words, but
in truth they had none good at that present for vs, which
we perceiuing,They depart from Trinidado.
                departed thence vpon the 7. day, about
one of the clocke in the morning, leauing the other ships
to attend their trade, and stood away for the passages, called
Les
                     ••
                  iot boccas de Drago, and disembogued about

eight of the clocke the same morning. Then we steered
away for an Island called Meues,
               They arriue at Meues.
                and leauing the Islands
of Granado, Saint Vincent, Guadalupa, and Monserate, in
our starboord side, wee arriued there the twelfth day,
where wee stopped to take in Ballast, and more water,
for our shippes were very light.
            In this Island there is an hot Bath,An excellent hot Bath at Meues.
                which as wel for the
reports that I haue heard, as also for that I haue seen and
found by experience, I doe hold for one of the best and
most soueraigne in the world. I haue heard that diuers of
our Nation haue there been cured of the Leprosie, and
that one of the same persons now, or lately dwelt at
Wollwich neere the riuer of Thames, by whom the truth
may be knowne, if any man desire to bee further satisfied
therein. As for my owne experience, although it was
not much, yet the effects that I found it worke both in
my selfe, and others of my company in two daies space,
doe cause mee to conceiue the best of it. For at my comming
thither,An extreame cough cured by the Bath. I was grieuously vexed with an extreame
cough, which I much feared would turne mee to great
harme, but by bathing in the Bath, and drinking of the
water, I was speedily cured: and euer since that time, I
haue found the state of my body (I giue God thankes
for it) farre exceeding what it was before, in strength
and health. Moreouer, one of my company named Iohn
Huntbatch (seruant to my brother) as he was making a
fire,A mans hand burned with Gunpouder, and by the Bath cured in 24 houres. burned his hand with Gunpowder, and was in
doubt thereby to loose the vse of one or two of his fingers,
which were shrunke vp with the fire, but he went
presently to the Bath, and washed, and bathed his hand
a good space therein, which soopled his fingers in such
manner, that with great ease hee could stire and stretch
them out, and the fire was so washed out of his hand, that

within the space of twenty foure houres, by twice or
thrice washing and bathing it, the sorenesse thereof was
cured, onely the eye-sore for the time remained. Furthermore,
two or three others of my company hauing swellings
in their legges,Swellings in the legges cured in a day. were by the Bath cured in a day.
This can I affirme, and boldly iustifie, hauing been an eie
witnesse thereof.
            Hence wee departed the sixteenth day of October,They depart from Meues.
                in
the afternoone, and leauing the Islands of St. Christopher,
St. Martin, and Anguilla on the Starboord side,
wee dissembogued through the broken Islands on the
North side of Anguilla vpon St. Lukes day, where I thinke
neuer Englishmā dissembogued before vs: for we found
all our Sea-charts false concerning that place, those broken
Islands being placed therein, to the Southward of
Anguilla, betwene it and St. Martins, and wee found
them scituat to the Northward thereof.
            When wee had cleered our selues of the broken Islands,
wee stood away North-East, shaping our course
the neerest way wee could for Flores, and Corues, and so
continued with faire weather, the winde still mending
vpon vs, vntill the thirtieth day of October: about
twelue of the clocke that day there began a storme, with
contrarie windes, still variable, which continued vntill 4.
the next day in the afternoone. In this storme wee lost
the company of the Pinnesse in the night, but had fight
of her againe vpon the fourth of Nouember late in the
euening, and the next day shee came vp vnto vs, at two
of the clocke in the afternoone. Then the winde came
faire at West,They left the Pinnesse to follow after them. and wee steered away East by North, and
E. N. Eastamong. The seauenth of Nouember I relieued
the Pinnesse with more bread, and left her to follow
after vs, not being able to keepe way with vs before the

winde, which then blew strongly at West: for I was very
vnwilling to loose the benefit of a speedy passage,
which the cōtinuāce of that faire winde was like to afford
vs. And so following our course, on the eleuenth day in
the morning we had sight of Fayal,
               They fell with Fayal.
                one of the Islands
of the Terceras, which we left on our starboord side, and
steered away for England, the winde continuing faire vntill
the twenty foure day. But then it changed, first to the
East by North, and then to the East south-east, and became
so violent and furious, that for three daies space
we were not able to beare out saile, but did driue before
the winde at the least three leagues a watch,They are driuē by a storme into Ireland. out of our
course; and the first land wee made was Cape Cleere in
the South-west part of Ireland, where against our wils we
arriued at Crooke Hauen the twenty nine of Nouember.
            Our arriuall there at that present,Their great necessitie and want. was happy for vs,
considering our extreame wants, and great necessities;
for of all our store, we had remaining but one hogshed
of water, halfe a hogshed of beuerage (all our beere being
spent and wasted by leakage) sixe peeces of beefe, and
three of Porke, which was all our prouision: we had neither
fish, butter, oyle, cheese nor pease left to relieue vs,
whereby we had fallen into a lamentable distresse, if almighty
God had not in time brought vs vnto this harbour
where we supplied our wants, by the helpe of Captaine
Reignolds commander of his Maiesties Pinnesse called
the Moone, whom we fortunately met there altogether
vnexpected. But the winde continuing contrary
at the East, and like to hold still in that corner, presaged
new wants to insue, if a speedy remedy was not prouided.
To preuent the worst, I resolued to goe by land
to Yoghall, neere vnto which place remained some friends
and acquaintance of mine, by whom I might prouide

my selfe of meanes to defray my charge, vntill my returne
into England: and therefore gaue commandement
to the master of my shippe to wage a Pilot, and vpon
the first shift of winde (if it fauoured him in any time) to
bring the shippe about to Yoghall, where I ment to abide
his comming, resoluing thence to goe for Bristol. And I
appointed (if the winde did hold against him) to send
him mony to supplie their victuals, vntill it pleased God
to alter it: but he regarding his owne priuate ends, more
then my commaund and direction, vpon the first shift
of wind went away with my shippe (without my knowledge)
to Dartmouth in the west Country, and left me behind
in Ireland: whereof as soone as I had intelligence, I
presently tooke the opertunitie of a speedy passage in a
barke then reddy bound for Bristol, and so the next morning
being the fifteenth of December, I departed from
Yoghall, and arriued at Bristol the seuententh day.
            My Pinnesse which we left at Sea to follow after vs,The Pinnesse first arriued in Ireland, and afterward at Bristol.
was likewise by the aforesaid storme driuen into the west
of Ireland, to a place caled Dingen le Coushe: and there remained
along time wind-bound: but at the last (by Gods
permission) arriued at Bristol the second day of February.
            During the time of my voyage, we left but one landman,
who died in Guiana: and one sailer, and an Indian
boy,The number of those that died. who died at Sea in our returne: and during the space
of these three yeares last past since the voiage, of all the
men which I left in the country, being in number about
thirty, there died but six, whereof one was drowned: another
was an old man of threescore yeeres of age: and
another tooke his death by his owne disorder; the rest
died of sicknes, as pleased God the giuer of life: for which
small losse, his holy name be blessed now and euer.
            Hauing thus (most noble Prince) declared the whole

course of my voiage to Guiana, performed in the yeare of
our Lord 1609. I hold it needefull for the better satisfaction
of the fauourers, and wel-willers of this action,
by adding of a speciall note or two, and by a briefe reremembrance
of some points mentioned in the former
discourse, to expresse the worthinesse of the enterprise,
being of importance, and not to bee regarded lightly.
            In euery forraine action vndertaken by the subiects of
a Christian Prince,Three principall ends to be obserued in euery forraine action. they ought to haue especiall regard
to three principall ends and designes. First, that it may
bee for the glory of God: Secondly, for the honour of
their Soueraigne: Thirdly, for the benefit and profit of
their Countrey. Which three principall ends and intendements,
if they faithfully prosecute, and labour
to aduance with constant resolution, they shall infallibly
bring their vndertakings to blessed, prosperous, and honorable
end. And now if it shall appeare that this enterprise
for discouery and plantation in Guiana, is chiefely
grounded vpon these three designes; I hope there is not
any man (bee hee neuer so malitious and full of enuy)
that can with iust exp
                  •••
               tions scandalise it, or worthily
contemne it.
            First then for the glory of God,1. The glory of God. it hath been, and euer
will bee held cleere and vnquestionable, that God cannot
be more honoured, nor his holy name by any meanes
more glorified, then by the prosperous grouth and happy
increase of his Church, through the conuersion of
those that bee heathen and barbarous Nations to the
knowledge of him our true God, his Sonne Iesus Christ,
and the holy Ghost, the blessed indiuiduall Trinity, and
to the profession and practise of Christianity; which
heauenly and euer memorable worke, may through
Gods good blessing and assistance (without which (indeede)

all our trauell therein, and all the labour of the
world is but lost) bee easily effected and accomplished
in Guiana▪
                the people thereof being of a louing and tractable
nature towards the English, whom they loue and
preferre before all other strangers whatsoeuer: and by
whom (next vnder God) I verily hope, and am constantly
perswaded, it will bee their blessed happe to bee freed
from the seruitude of the diuell, that now so tyranizeth
ouer them, and to bee led out of that infernall darkenesse
wherein they liue, and bee drawen to Christianity:
for they will come vnto vs (already) at time of prayer,
shew reuerence, and bee very attentiue all the while, although
they vnderstand nothing: they will bee content
that wee baptize their children, and will after call them
by the Christian names wee giue them, suffer vs to bring
them vp, and in a sort acknowledge their ignorance, and
shew a kinde of willingnes to be instructed &amp; reformed.
            As touching the second, by what meanes may our gracious
Souraigne the Kings Maiestie doe God better seruice,2. The honour of our Soueraigne.
and honour him more, or vnder him bee more honored,
then by obtaining and gaining the Soueraignty
of so many great, spacious, and goodly Countries and
Territories, not yet actually possessed, and inhabited by
any Christian Prince or Sate whatsoeuer? which in that
Region, by the timely and worthy vndertakings of his
Subiects, (without bloodshed, and with the loue and
affection of the people) may bee possessed, planted, and
annexed to his Crowne, as the Nations and Countries
beyond, by the Emperour Charles the fifth, were annexed
to the Crowne of Spaine, whereby, what honour and
benefit the Spaniards haue gained, and to what a degree
of greatnesse they are thereby growen, these parts of the
world can witnesse, and wee for our parts haue had triall,
and might haue had woful experience of, if our God

that alwaies tooke our parts,An. 1588. had not crossed their bloody
designes, and put them to flight and confusion.
            And for the third,The profit of our Country. who can deny but that our Countrey
by this worthy action may bee enriched, through
diuers and sundrie commodities of great worth, in those
parts dayly found, and easily obtained? which before
are mentioned more at large, from page 31. to page 37.
and therefore needeles here to bee againe repeated.
            And for their further satisfaction, and more incouragement
in this enterprise, let them consider the nature
and disposition of the climate in this Region of Guiana,
which for healthfull and wholsome ayre, (some few places
onely excepted) I hold generally to bee inferiour to
none other vnder Heauen: for notwithstanding it bee
scituate vnder the Equinoctiall, by the ancient Philosophers
called the burning Zone;
               The burning Zone habituable. yet such are the wonderfull
workes of God for the benefit of man, that contrary
to their opinion, wee finde by late experience, that those
Regions which were in times past by them accounted
vnhabitable, through extremity of drougth, and heate;
are now found out to bee inhabited, temporate, and
healthful Countries, as plainely appeareth in diuers
patts of the East and West Indies, and especially in this
Countrey of Guiana, whereof I haue taken possession to
his Maiesties vse, being plentifully inhabited by people
of diuers Nations: the climate there pleasant, and agreeable
to our constitutions,The clmate pleasant, fruitfull, and healthfull. and the soile fruitfull, as before
hath been declared; affording as many admirable helpes
towards the leading of an happy life, as any knowne
part of the world: for whatsoeuer is necessary for the reliefe
of man: eyther for foode, Phisicke, or Chirurgery,
or for clothing and architecture, is here (by the prouidence
and goodnesse of God the creator) in plentifull

store euen naturally prouided.
            Moreouer the good inclination of the people towards
our Nation,The loue of the people towards our Nation. being willing to trade with vs, and become
subiects to his Maiesty, our Soueraigne; their louing
and gentle entertaining of vs, desiring to haue vs liue and
abide amongst them; and their tractable conuersation
with vs, not refusing to be instructed in Christianitie;
and coueting to imitate and learne any trade, or worke,
that they see vsed or practised by our men: are no small
motiues to perswade the prosecution of this action, and
plantation in Guiana.
            
            Furthermore,A good motiue to those that want imployment. all younge Gentlemen, Souldiers, and
others that liue at home in idlenesse, and want imployment,
may here finde meanes to abandon and expell
their slouthfull humors, and cast off their fruitlesse and
pernitious designes; and may worthily exercise their
generous spirits in honourable trauels, and famous discoueries
of many goodly and rich terretories, strange
and vnknowne Nations; and a multitude of other rarieties,
hitherto vnseene, and vnheard off in these parts of
the world: which may be thought incredible, but that
our own experience, &amp; the generall &amp; constant report
and affirmation of the Indians, doth assure vs thereof.
            And to conclude,An Empire may be gained to our Soueraigne. we may by the gracious assistance
of our good God, gaine vnto our Soueraigne the dominion
of a rich and mightie Empire, which if it may bee
once possessed by his Maiestie, and inhabited by his English
Subiects, will absolutely be inuincible, to the vnspeakable
honour &amp; renown of our natiō in al after ages.
            All these things respectiuely considered, what may be
more required? to moue &amp; induce all noble and worthy
dispositions, louing honour, and honourable attempts; all
Marchants desiring wealth &amp; riches; &amp; generally al the inhabitants

of this Kingdome, freely to giue assistance towards
the aduancement of this noble action, and plantation;
so much tending to the glory of God; the honour
of our Soueraigne, and the benefit of our Countrey.
         
         
            ¶The names of the Riuers falling into the Sea from
Amazones, to Dessequebe, and of the seuerall Nations
inhabiting those Riuers.
            
               RIVERS. NATIONS.
               Charibs.
  
                     1 Amazones.
                     2 Arrapoco, a branch of Amazones.
                     3 Arrawary.
                  
               
               Yaios and Charibs.
  
                     4 Maicary.
                     5 Connawini.
                  
               
               Arracoories
  
                     6 Cassipurogh.
                     7 Arracow.
                  
               
               Yaios and Arwaccas.
  
                     8 Wiapoco.
                     9 Wianary, a creeke or inlet of the sea.
                  
               
               10 Cowe, not inhabited.
               Charibs.
  
                     11 Apurwacca.
                     12 Wio.
                     13 Caiane.
                     14 Meccooria.
                     15 Courwo.
                     16 Manmanury
                     17 Sinammara.
                  
               
               18 Oorassowini, not inhabited.
               Arwaccas.
   
                     19 Coonannoma
                     20 Vracco.
                  
               
               Paragotos,
Yaios, Charibs,
Arwac.
   
                     21 Marrawini.
                  
               
               Charibs.
   
                     21 Amanna.
                     23 Camoure, or
    Comawin, a
    branch of Selinama.
                     
                     24 Selinama, or
    Surennamo.
                     25 Surammo.
                     26 Coopannomy
                     27 Eneecare.
    
                  
               
               Arwaccas
&amp; Charibs.
     
                     28 Coretine.
                     29 Berebisse.
     
                  
               
               Arwaccas.
    
                     30 Manhica.
                     31 Wapary.
                     32 Micowine.
                     33 Demeerare.
                  
               
               Charibs.

                     34 Matooronnee
                     35 Quiowinne,
    braunches of
    Dessequebe.
                     
                  
               
               Arwaccas
&amp; Charibs.
    
                     36 Dessequebe.
    
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            The Plantation in Guiana is most easie
to be performed, as is at large expressed in the former
Treatise: And may in briefe appeare by these notes following,
which are here added for the better comfort
and incouragement of the Aduenturers and Planters of
the meaner sort.
            FIrst, the climate in Guiana, although it bee hot, yet is
it habitable;The nature of the climate. Page. 23. and affordeth healthfull habitations:
for in three yeeres space that my Brother Captaine Michael
Harcourt and his company, remained in the Countrey,
of thirty persons there died but six.
            The naturall inhabitants of that Countrey are a louing,The disposition of the people.
tractable, and gentle people, affecting, and preferring
the Englishmen before all other Nations whatsoeuer,
and desiring commerce and conuersation with them:
with those barbarous people we may liue in safety, without
suspicion of trechery, or dread of danger; if wilfully
wee offer them abuse, and harme issue, the fault is ours;
for a worme being trodden on, will turne againe. If they
at any time doe giue offence to vs, they will suffer and
abide such moderate chastisements, as we in our discretions
shall thinke fit to lay vpon them.
            The soile of the land there,The quallity of the land. Page 27. as is said before, is exceeding
rich, neuer yet broken vp, nor ouerworne with tillage,
but still remaineth in the greatest perfection of
fertility.
            The prouisions of that Countrey for victuals, are already

mentioned before. But it is fit they bee againe remembred
for the comfort of the ordinary people,The prouisions of the Countrey page 27. 28. 30. and 31. that
in person shall aduenture in this action. There are great
store of Deere of all sorts; wilde Swine, Hares, and Conies;
besides diuers other beasts vnknowne in these
parts, Phesants, Partriges, wilde foule of all sorts, and euery
house hath Cocks, Hennes, and Chickens, as in
England; and the variety of Fish is wonderfull, without
compare: but the chiefest comfort for our Countreymen
is this, that the beast called Maypury, and the fish
called the Sea Cow (being seuerally as bigge as a Heifer
of two yeres old,A beast and a fish like Beefe &amp; of which kinde there are very many)
are in eating so like vnto our English beefe, that hardly in
tast wee can distinguish them, and may as well as beefe
bee salted, and kept for our prouision.
            There is also a beast in colour like a Fawne,A Beast like Mutton. but fuller
of white spots; in stature somewhat lesse then a small
sheep, and in tast like Mutton, but is rather better meate:
the Baremo is also of the same taste.
            These for the time will giue vs good content, vntill
wee can bee stored with the breed of our English sheepe
and cattell.
            The store of Maix,Good bread. or Guinea wheat in Guiana, is very
plentifull, which graine doth make an excellent good
bread, and very wholsome. So likewise doth the Cassaui,
whereof there is also great abundance; and much
more may bee,Drinke like March beere. as we please to plant.
            Of the Cassaui bread, the Indians do make good drink,
which in colour, taste, and strength, doth equall our
March beere in England.
            Of the Guinea wheat,Excellent strong Ale. we may make good Malt, which
also maketh as excellent strong Ale as can bee possible.
            The soile being rich, fruitfull, and neuer nipt with

frosts doth giue vs hope that in few yeeres space by planting
vines,Sacke, and Canary wine. we shal make good store of Sacke, and Canary
wine, which in those parts are needefull, and very wholsome,
and will greatly comfort and lighten the hearts of
our Countreymen, and make them iouiall and couragious
to vndertake and execute the greatest laboures, and
most difficult aduentures of discouery.
            The commodities already found in Guiana, are at large
declared in the former discourse;The commodities of the Country. pag. 31, and 32. yet for the better memory
of those that are disposed to aduenture in this action,
I haue againe in briefe remembred them. First within
a yeere without much labour, there may bee transported
thence good store of Cotton wooll; diuers kinds
of rich dies; sundrie sorts of gummes, drugges, and feathers;
many kindes of rich woods: Iasper, and Purphery
stone; Balsamum, waxe, hony, and Tobacco. And
hereafter within few yeeres, wee shall returne thence
great plenty of Sugers: and I hope discouer as rich
Mines, as euer the Spaniard found, eyther in new Spaine,
Peru, or any other part of the Indies.
            
               
               
                  FOrasmuch as it hath pleased his
Excellent Maiestie, for the planting and inhabiting
of all that part of Guiana, or continent
of America, lying betweene the riuer of Amazones,
and the riuer of Dessequebe, to grant his
gracious Letters Pattents to Robert Harcourt of Stanton
Harcourt in the County of Oxford Esquire, Sir Thomas
Challener Knight, and Iohn Rouenzon Esquire, and to the
heires of the said Robert Harcourt, of all the saide Countries,
Lands and Territories betweene the said two riuers
of Amazones and Dessequebe, and of all Islands, Lands and
Territories within twenty Leagues adiacent thereunto,
&amp;c. Together with all Prerogatiues, Iurisdictions, Royalties,
Priuiledges, Franchises and Preheminenses, both
for Gouernement, Trade, Trafficke, and otherwise, in as
large and ample manner, as either his Maiestie, or any of
his noble Progenitors, or Predecessors, haue heretofore
graunted to any Aduenturers, or Vndertakers of any Discoueries,
Plantations, or Trafficke, of, in, or into any forraigne
parts whatsoeuer. To haue, hold, possesse, and enioy
all and singular the premisses, to the sole and proper
vse of the saide Robert Harcourt, and his heires for euer.
And for that diuers honourable personages, Gentlemen,
and others, who are willing and desirous, for the Glory of
God, and the Honour of our Nation, to giue aide and assistance,
eyther in person, or purse, to the vndertaking of
this worthy Action, and Plantation, may truly vnderstand
and know, how, and in what maner they shall receiue benefit
and profit by their aduentures, and trauells therein;
It is thought fit and necessary, for their better content and
satisfaction, to publish these Articles insuing.
            THe Planters in generall, are all Aduenturers either in person,
or purse.
            
               
The meanest Aduenturer in Person, shall haue fiue hundred Acres
as a single share.
            Euery one that aduentureth twelue pounds tenne shillings, shall
haue fiue hundred Acres as a single share; and so ratably according
to the aduenture, be it more or lesse.
            The Plantation and Aduenture is intended to bee partly Generall,
and partly Particular.
            In the Generall Plantation and Aduenture, all persons of all
conditions and estates, euen to the poorest seruants, and laborers,
men, women, and children, may aduenture asmuch or as little as
they please, from ten shillings vpwards, and shall haue in fee simple
the assured ratable increase and gaine according to the quantitie
of his aduenture; So as for euery ten shillings aduentured, he
shall haue twenty Acres in inheritance, and so much yearely profit
as those twenty Acres may yeeld.
            A Register shall be truely kept of the names of euery Aduenturer
in person, and of euery Aduenturer in mony, and of the summe
by him aduentured, to the end that they may proportionably receiue
the full benefit of their Aduentures.
            During the first three yeres, the whole benefit shall goe towards
the aduancement of the Plantation.
            At the end of those three yeres, a fourth part of the cleere profites
remayning shall be diuided betwixt all the Aduenturers in
purse or person, ratably according to their shares, and aduentures.
            Yeerely for seuen yeares after the first three yeeres ended, three
parts of the whole cleere yeerely profit vpon euery returne shall be
in like maner diuided; and the other fourth part shall goe towards
the aduancement of the Plantation.
            In those tenne yeares the Land may be surueyed, &amp; fit distributions
&amp; alotments made thereof to the Aduenturers and Planters.
            After those tenne yeares it shall be free for euery one to make his
best of his alotment at his owne discretion by himselfe, or else to
trade and deale in common, as he did before with others, which perhappes
will be most conuenient for all small Aduenturers: And a
setled order shall for that end be continued, for a continuall, ioynt,
and common trade and commerce for euer; for otherwise it might
prooue hard for Aduenturers of small summes to reape any benefit

after the ten yeeres ended: but by a common continued commerce,
they, or their heires, or assignes, shall be sure to haue it.
            A Treasurer generall for the Plantation shall bee resident in
London, and when the returne of profit diuidable shall be, he shall
forthwith deliuer to a particular Treasurer resident in euery shire,
the proportionable part or profit due to the Aduenturers of that
shire, which particular Treasurer shall deliuer to the high Constables
of euery Hundred, the proportionable part due to the Aduenturers
of that Hundred: And the high Constables shal deliuer to
the Constables and Minister of euery Parish within their Hundreds,
where any Aduenturers shall be, the proportionable part
due to the Aduenturers of that Parish. And the Constable &amp; Minister
shal deliuer to euery person in that Parish his due, according
to the proportion of his aduenture.
            To this end a Register shall be kept by the Constable and Minister
of each parish, of the names of each Aduenturer in that Parish,
with their seueral aduentures, &amp; the time when they brought
in the same; So as such as he remooued out of a Parish where they
aduentured, to some other place, shall either themselues, or their
heires, or assignes receiue his proportionable profite in the parish
where he aduentured, without further trouble or trauell.
            The like Register shall remaine with the high Constables, of the
Aduenturers in their Hundred.
            And the like with the particular Treasurer of that shire, of the
Aduenturers of that shire.
            And the like of all the Aduenturers whatsoeuer, with the Treasurer
generall for the Plantation.
            But yet such as aduenture not before this next intended voyage;
(which wee account the first voyage for the Plantation) or before
the second, but stay longer expecting the euent, must not expect equall
shares with the first Aduenturers: but if his aduenture come
in after the second voyage, and before the third, he shall want a fift
part of that which the first Aduenturers shall haue. And such as
come in before the fourth voyoge, shall want two fift parts. And
such as come in before the fift voyage, shall want three fift parts.
And such as come in before the sixt voyage (which perhappes may
be the last voyage in the first three yeeres, a voyage being ses forth
euery halfe yeare) shall want foure fift parts of what the first Aduenturer

shall haue. And so a single share for so late an Aduenturer
of twelue pound tenne shillings, will be but one hundred Acres
in inheritance, and his profit accordingly in proportion, and so for
a greater or lesser rate, so lately aduentured,
            Euery Aduenturer in person, if he die hauing neyther wife, nor
childe in Guiana liuing, his next kinsman that will goe in person
at the next voyage or sending after his decease, shall haue his share
or part: but if none such will goe in person, then the next heire of
the deceased in England, shall haue a fift part of that share in inheritance,
being about one hundred Acres: And the residue being
foure hundred Acres, shall be disposed of to some other that will goe
in person, that so by the death of the party deceased, the number of
the Planters in person may not be diminished, and that yet his next
heire here, may haue some competent benefite by the aduenture of
his kinsmans person.
            If a man and his wife goe, each of them shall haue fiue hundred
acres; yet so, that the share of the wife be at the husbands dispose,
as is vsed by husbands in England, that marry women heires, who
cannot alien the same without the wiues consent.
            If a man &amp; his wife goe, the suruiuor shal haue the others share,
if they haue no children borne in Guiana; but if they haue children
borne there, then onely the suruiuor shall haue the share of the deceased,
vntill the childe be one and twenty yeeres olde, and then the
child shall haue it, for that the share of the personall aduenture of
the suruiuor, will be competent maintenance, so as the childe may
well haue the other share.
            If a man and his wife, and a childe of theirs goe, each shall haue
fiue hundred Acres.
            The shares of Commaunders, Officers, and men of place, and
qualitie, that aduenture in Person, are not to be rated according
to single shares of inferiour and common persons, that aduenture in
person: but according to their place, qualitie, and merite, in such
sort as shallbe fit to giue them content, and incouragement to aduenture
their persons in so honorable and worthy an Action.
            Diuine Preachers that wil imitate the glorious examples of the
Apostles (who ceased not to trauell amongst all sorts of Heathen
and sauage people for the plantation of the holy Gospel) are worthily
numbred amongst the persons of place &amp; qualitie, and shall haue

such worthy shares, for the aduenture of their persons, in 
                  〈◊〉
                seruice
of the blessed Trinitie, as shall giue them good content. Thus
much concerning the Generall Aduenture and Plantation.
            In the Particular Plantation and Aduenture, there shalbe certaine
Signiories or other Portions of land allotted and graunted to
such as like not to be partakers of the Generall Plantation and Aduenture;
but haue otherwise a desire to ioyne together in seuerall
companies or corporations of select friends and acquaintance, or
else to plant apart, and single by themselues, as Lords of Mannors,
or as Farmers.
            These Signiories or Portions of Land shalbe conueyed and assured
vnto them in Fee simple, with all such Royalties, Liberties,
Priuiledges, Franchises, and Commodities, as shalbe fit and necessary
for the aduancement of their Plantations, and can (by vertue
of the Pattent) be granted vnto them.
            They shall plant and people the same at their owne proper costs
and charges, and conuert the profits thereof to their owne vse and
behoofe, vnder the conditions following.
            They shal yeerely pay vnto such Officers as shalbe appointed for
that purpose, the fift part of all Ores of Gold and Siluer, as shall at
all times hereafter, be found and gotten within the bounds and limites
of the Signiories and Lands graunted vnto them, which fift
part of Oare, is by the Pattent reserued to his Maiestie.
            The fift part being deducted for his Maiestie, they shal also pay
to the Patentees, or vnto their Officers for that purpose appointed,
all such rents and dueties, as betwixt the said Patentees, and them,
shall be agreed vpon, and such as haue beene vsually payed by the
planters and inhabiters of the like Plantations, whereof there are
extant many presidents: And also from time to time shall obserue,
pay, &amp; performe, all such other customs, impositions, reseruations,
and limitations, as are mentioned &amp; expressed in the said Patent.
            And for their safety and defence in all the said particular Plantations,
they shall be ayded, protected, and defended, both by Sea,
and Land, against all assaulters, inuaders, and intruders, according
to the power and strength of the Vndertakers of the Generall
nerall Plantation, which I hope (with Gods assistance)
shall be sufficient to resist and repell the malice
of our greatest enemies.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

