
   
      
         
            An inquisition of the true church, and those that revolt from it being a sermon pronounced at the second session of the Parliament / by Christopher Lo. Archbishop of Armagh, and Primate of all Ireland.
            Hampton, Christopher, 1552-1625.
         
         
            
               1622
            
         
         Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02607
            STC 12737.5
            ESTC S4341
            24171043
            ocm 24171043
            27298
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02607)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27298)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1819:3)
         
         
            
               
                  An inquisition of the true church, and those that revolt from it being a sermon pronounced at the second session of the Parliament / by Christopher Lo. Archbishop of Armagh, and Primate of all Ireland.
                  Hampton, Christopher, 1552-1625.
               
               [8], 32 p.   
               
                  Printed by the Societie of Stationers,
                  Dublin :
                  M.DC.XXII. [1622]
               
               
                  Signatures: A-E⁴.
                  Imperfect: stained.
                  Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bible. --  N.T. --  Epistle of John, 1st, II, 19 --  Sermons.
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-07
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-07
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               AN INQVISITION OF THE TRVE CHVRCH, AND THOSE THAT REVOLT FROM IT.
            
            BEING A SERMON pronounced at the ſecond Seſsion of the PARLIAMENT.
            
               By CHRISTOPHER LO: Archbiſhop of ARMAGH, and Primate of all IRELAND.
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        •••
                     N. 21.10.
               
               Caſt out this bond-woman and her ſonne: for the ſonne of the bond-woman ſhall not be heyre with my ſonne Iſaac.
               
            
            
               DVBLIN, Printed by the Societie of Stationers.
            
               Anno M.D.C.XXII.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE ARTHVR LORD CHICHESTER, Baron of BELFAST, Lord high Treaſurer of IRELAND.
            
               
                  I
                Have dedicated this Sermon to your Lordſhip, who heard it pronounced in our late Parliament here; when you repreſented the State and Perſon of a great King. It was then expedient (as I thought) for the duety of my place, and instruction of the hearers in that Honourable preſence, out of holy Scriptures, and writings of ancient Fathers, to expreſſe ſuch markes or demonſtrations, as might distinguiſh and make the Spouſe of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, to be knowne from a ſtep-dame. The true mother nouriſheth her children healthfully with bread of life, and ſincere milke of the Word: the other ſetteth before them quelques choſes of humane inventions, and unſavory plants vvhich our heavenly Father never planted. My endevours therein, aymed at no other end, but to leave Noahs fatherly bleſſing behinde me: that is often in my mouth, and never from my heart; God perſwade Iaphet to dwell in the Tents of Sem: that living together

like friends and countrey-men, vvee might in ſome meaſure have our militant Church on earth, reſemble the triumphant congregation or citie of Angels and Saints in heaven. Amongſt whom, nothing is more peculiar and proper then 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , that happy agreement and conſent vvhich admitteth no ſtrife, no difference: Such holy concord vvould grow here with us (for all aſpire to be joyned to that bleſſed Society) if we were reduced into one Fold. It may be that ſome ſmall debates come from our own brethren &amp; comburgeſſes; moving unneceſſary and unprofitable questions in Ceremonies, things indifferent, and Christian liberty: and therin I think we may ſay with Debora; The diviſions of Reuben are great thoughts of heart. Thoſe will undoubted-ceaſe (as they abate daily) vvhen vve conteyne our ſelves under the rod and ſtaffe of our ſhepheard Ieſus Chriſt. Let him poſſeſſe us wholly, and ceremonies can give no impediment, as they be uſed in this Church. Wee put no merit, no matter of ſalvation, no worſhip of God in them: but uſe them to nouriſh peace, and charitie, to keepe order and decencie in the Church; not for exerciſes of pietie: And moſt of them were uſed in the Church long before Poperie did beare ſway. The abuſes mixed vvith them by the Romaniſts, vvee affect not, vve defend not, vve allow not: they have no portion, no right, no memoriall in Ieruſalem. Things that have beene abuſed, neede not to bee cleane aboliſhed: vvere that propoſition made generall, it overthroweth Churches, and many things elſe, as vvell as the Rites and Ceremonies of our Liturgy. Our vvorthy anceſtors (ſaith Saint Auguſtine) tooke the Temples dedicated to Idolls, and converted them to holy Oratories or houſes of prayer, vvhere CRIST IESVS is vvorſhipped ſincerely, and his Goſpel is purely taught. They tooke the revenues vvhich were devoted to the gods of the Gentiles, to Theaters, to Veſtals,

and turned them to the entertaynement of Miniſters, though they ſerved not Antichriſt before, but Belzebub the chiefe of the Divels. And Saint Auguſtine findeth no ſoleciſme or incongruitie in it. Hoc de illis fit quod de ipſis hominibus, cum ex ſacrilegis &amp; impijs in veram religionem immutantur. The grave and learned Father avoweth, that there is not any other thing done in matters of this kind, but that vvhich happeneth unto men themſelves, vvhen they are turned from ſacrilege and impietie, unto Chriſtian Religion. The ſacred Veſſells of the Temple had beene fouly abuſed in Babylon by Nebuchadnezzar and Balthaſſer, yet vvhen Cyrus had given commandement for the reſtoring of them againe, Zorobabel made no ſcruple to imploy them in their former holy uſes. It vvas Saint Auguſtine his practiſe, and is vvorthy to bee obſerved: Wee correct thoſe things vvhich Schiſmatiques or Heretiques have corrupted, vvhen they come unto us from them: but doe acknowledge and allow that vvhich they held, as they received it; leſt, ſuffering our ſelves to be carried away in offence vvith mens faults beyond the rules of Iuſtice, vve ſhould doe ſome vvrong to the things themſelves. For vvee ſee the Apoſtle Saint Paul even in an Altar of the Gentiles vvhere Idols vvere vvorſhipped, to confirme the name of GOD, rather then to diſavow it. I vvill adde no more to the concluſion of this point, but the leſſon vvhich Saint Ambroſe gave unto Saint Auguſtine, and vvas by him ever after esteemed as an Oracle: There cannot be a better diſcipline, nor more beſeeming a grave and diſcreet Christian, then to doe that vvhich hee ſeeth obſerved in the Church vvhereſoever hee commeth. For that is ever to be held indifferent and to be performed for their ſakes amongſt vvhom vvee live, vvhich is neyther againſt faith nor good manners.
            
               The nature and uſe of theſe indifferent things is fully deſcribed by Saint Bernard:
               Epiſt. 7. Certaine things are ſimply good in themſelves; and men can challenge no obedience that vvay: for they must be done, becauſe they are injoyned by GOD. Other things are altogether evill, and follow the ſame rule. Betweene theſe things that be good or evill in themſelves, there bee other vvhich bee indifferent, and may bee good or evill as they bee uſed. In this last ſort, the Christian Magistrate doth exerciſe his power (or elſe hee hath no power left him) and vvhen hee hath interpoſed his authoritie, then doe they in a manner change their nature, concerning the uſe of them: for they are not then left free to bee omitted, but are neceſſary to bee obſerved. In his fas non eſt noſtrum ſenſum ſententiae praeſcribere magiſtrorum. In his omnino praelatorum nec juſſio nec prohibitio contemnenda. In theſe indifferent things everie one may not follow his particular fantaſie (that vvould bring in confuſion, anarchy, and infinite tyranny) but all must comply vvith the Magiſtrate, vvith the Church, with the governors of it;1. Cor. 14. 
               The ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets.
            
            This limitation in the uſe of things indifferent, brings no diminution to the freedome and libertie of a Chriſtian: that hath place or ſeate in the mind,De votis Monaſtic. and as Luther teacheth gravely, it resteth in the points that are betweene God and mee; for example, If I beleeve and am perſwaded in minde and conſcience, that the Croſſe in Baptiſme, the Ring in matrimonie, Kneeling at the Lords Supper, &amp;c. worke nothing with God, and are not uſed in the Church to any ſuch purpoſe; I enjoy the full benefite of my Christian libertie, in the very uſe of theſe and the like Ceremonies: But if I goe about to draw my libertie into a freedome of actions too, and to the things vvhich are betweene my brother and mee, thinking

to doe vvhat I list in them (becauſe they are indifferent of themſelves, or in their owne nature) vvithout reverence to the Magistrates orders, and reſpect of the Churches decrees; I doe certainely bring my libertie out of her true bounds, and turne it to a licentious disturbance of the Church, the Magistrate, and every Christian brother vvhich is vviſe unto ſobrietie.
            Diligent care is to be taken, that wee give not offence to our weake brethren in the uſe of theſe indifferent things. And that will be diſcharged two wayes: firſt, if we conſider who they be that pretend offence in this kinde, Sure they are not weake ones (who are onely to be reſpected) but ſuch as esteeme themſelves ſtronger in faith then the reſidue. To theſe no juſt offence is given, but they take offence unjuſtly; not of weakeneſſe, but of curioſitie, and overprizing their owne inventions.
            Another, and the ſecond meanes to acquite and cleare the Church from theſe offences, conſiſteth in the faithfull labor of the Paſtors. Let them bee vigilant to teach their people the nature and true uſe of ceremonies, and things indifferent, aſſoone as any ſcandall ariſeth, (for ſo they ſhould doe) and the offence will wither in the bud, before it grow to ſtrength or maturitie to diſquiet the Church. But when they which ſhould extinguiſh offences, beſtow their thoughts and indevors to nouriſh them; impreſsions of doubts or ſcruples will be wrought in ſoft or tender minds eaſily: and it is not poſsible to remove them againe, without much difficultie and trouble. That can never bee welcome to the Church, neither is now ſeaſonable or ſuting with my yeares and infirmities: howbeit prepared I am, with the reſt of my brethren, to endure and devoure all paines or travayle that may breed peace, concord, and unanimitie amongſt us. And I have the greater hope to prevayle, eyther by perſwaſive

reaſons (which pleaſe me beſt) or by diſcipline (if the other be refuſed) for the noble aſsiſtance that your Lordſh. doth give me alwayes in the affayres of the Church. Continue thoſe honourable reſpects; for they will make your memory ſweet and gratefull to poſteritie, as they have obliged the Clergie now preſent to acknowledge your goodneſſe, and my ſelfe moſt of all to remaine,
            
               Your Lordſh. humble and affectionate ſervant, ARMAGH.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               AN INQVISITION OF THE TRVE Church, and thoſe that revolt from it.
            
               
                  
                     1. Iohn 2.19.
                  
                  They went out from us, but they were not of us: For if they had beene of us, they would have continued with us. But this commeth to paſſe, that it might appeare that they be not all of us.
               
            
            
               IN the former Verſe the Apoſtle maketh mention both of one, and manie Antichriſts. For (as Hilary writeth) everie one is Antichriſt, that doth not acknowledge Chriſt in the ſame manner that the Apoſtles preached him. So it commeth to paſſe that there be manie Antichriſts; according to Chriſt his prediction,

               There ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, to deceive (if it were poſsible) the verie Elect. Old father Simeons propheſie, when hee tooke our bleſſed Saviour into his armes, ſorted to the ſame concluſion. Immediatly before the good man did ſing his Swan-like ſong of Nunc dimittis, he pronounced freely, that which ſucceeding times have verified, That the childe Ieſus ſhould bee ſet as a ſigne to bee ſpoken againſt, not by one, but by many; Hee was in the world, and the world knew him not. he came unto his owne, and his owne received him not. But amongſt thoſe manie contraries that Chriſt ſhould have, the holy Ghoſt in the Scripture pointeth at one capital Antichriſt, who would exceed all the reſt. All are dangerous adverſaries, carefully to be avoided: to that end wee are admoniſhed of them. And indeed, who are more to be avoided of Chriſtians, then they who oppoſe thē
               ſelves againſt Chriſt our Lord? Yet none of them are to be eſchued with ſo much care or diligence, as thoſe which cover their oppoſitions againſt Chriſt with titles of pietie, of holineſſe, under the name and pretence of Chriſt; as if they were his Vicars, or Vicegerents, &amp; did all for him. Profeſſed hoſtilitie and open contradiction

could never have advanced the kingdome of Antichriſt: for who are ſo wretched, or Giant-like deſperate, to enterpriſe war with God? The divell himſelfe, being the Prince of darkeneſſe, when he would draw moſt awry, and ſeduce, is transformed into an Angell of light: even ſo doth Antichriſt, pretending the name of Chriſt, the keyes of Peter, his ſeate, his ſucceſsion, &amp; the alluring name of the Church, ſeduce great troupes of unheedefull ſoules, that he could never gaine with open profeſsion of impietie. Such is the efficacie of his deceiveableneſſe, ſuch is the myſterie of his iniquitie: under theſe habits or ſheepes clothing, hee diſguiſeth his Wolviſh ravin. Let us not then be miſcarried with outward ſhewes or titles, but examine and weigh everie thing by the ballances of the Sanctuarie.
            For our better information in this caveat, the Apoſtle, by the paſſage of my Text, doth brand this Antichriſtian troupe with a legible marke, whereby you may ſurely know them. They went out from us, they revolt, they fall away, they forſake and ſlide away from the Church, and the doctrine thereof: they depart from the fellowſhip and communion of Saints. Behold a

viſible marke, a true cognizance to diſcerne the Antichriſtian ſort. And needfull it is that wee ſhould have ſuch prints or characters to diſcover them, in regard of the great perrill &amp; danger which they bring to themſelves and others that are ſwayed by them. Quiſquis ab Eccleſia ſegregatus jungitur adulterae, à promiſsis Eccleſiae ſeparatur: nec pertinet ad Christi praemia, qui reliquerit Eccleſiam Christi. Alienus eſt, prophanus eſt, hoſtis eſt; habere jam non poteſt Deum patrem, qui Eccleſiam non habet matrem. It is the ſentence of S. Cyprian,
               De ſimplic. praelator. and verie orthodoxe: Each one that is ſevered from the true Church, &amp; joined to the falſe, as to an adultereſſe, is certainely cut off from the promiſes made to the Church: neither can hee be intereſſed in Chriſt his promiſes, which forſaketh Chriſt his Church. Hee is a ſtranger, hee is prophane, hee is an enemie, he cannot now have God to his father, which will not reverence and obey the Church as his mother.
            The uſe of this doctrine is, to admoniſh us to gather our ſelves into the ſocietie &amp; fellowſhip of the Church.Pſal. 84. 
               How amiable are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts? What happineſſe is it to be joyned in companie and conſort with the

Patriarches Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob? with the Prophets, with the Apoſtles, with the Martyrs, with the holy Angels of God, and with Chriſt himſelfe? Take heed therefore, beloved brethren, and beware that you bereave not your ſelves of the comforts diſpenſed unto you out of the Church: beware that you cut not your ſelves off from this heavenly communion or companie, through ſingularitie or headineſſe of courage. Plucke not up the Tares in prejudice or detriment to the Wheate; but ſuffer both to grow together untill the Harveſt, and let him ſeparate which hath the Fanne in his hand to purge the floore.
            I know it will here be objected, that the Antichriſtian ſort may be well diſcovered by their apoſtaſie and relinquiſhing the Church, when the Church it ſelfe is not controverted: but where the Church is ambiguous, that men make queſtion where the true Church is whether it be with thoſe that profeſſe the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt ſincerely, or amongſt ſuch as have addicted themſelves to the Biſhop of Rome▪ there the notice of apoſtaſie is not perſpicuous, it is not eaſily to bee taken: For as Waſpes make themſelves combes like to Bees;

ſo hereticks have their Conventicles, their Synagogues, which they adorne with the ſtile &amp; title of Churches. And this painting hath ever made a debate: Inter nos &amp; Donatiſtas quaeſtio eſt ubi ſit Eccleſia; Quid ergo facturi ſumus? In verbis noſtris eam quaeſituri an in verbis capitis ſui Domini nostri Ieſu Chriſti? puto quòd in illius verbis potius eam quaerere debemus qui veritas eſt, &amp; optimè novit corpus ſuum: novit enim Dominus qui ſunt ſui. When doubts are moved where the Church ſhould be, there are but two manner of enqueſts or trials to finde it: either by the markes which we have deviſed our ſelves; or by evidences which Chriſt Ieſus, the lively head of the Church hath preſcribed for the manifeſtation of it. And this latter inquiſition (by the judgement of Saint Auguſtine) is the ſurer and fairer proofe: for CHRIST is truth, and knoweth his owne bodie beſt. Doeth not the Lord knowe who bee his? Yes certainely, Hee calleth his owne ſheepe by name, Ioh. 10.
            On the other ſide, ſadde experience teacheth us that live in this age, how miſerably they are miſtaken, that goe about to point out the Church, not by anie certaine demonſtrations

out of the holy Scripture, but by deceiveable fantaſies of men. Wherein they commend Antiquitie firſt, for a ſpeciall marke of the Church: and conſider not that it may bee counterfeited or pretended without anie truth of right and juſt antiquitie. Did not the Gibeonites pleade it in that manner for their ragges, their over-worne ſhooes, and moulded bread: So they did, if they circumvented a wiſe and vigilant Governour, with ſuch colourable pleas: how much eaſier is it to beguile ignorant and ſimple people, or to put them into errour by maskes and pretences of feined antiquitie? And though wee have not anie cauſe to avoide or ſhunne the triall of true antiquitie, which commeth from the Ancient of dayes, nor our adverſaries to preſume of it: the unpartiall and due conſideration of the thing it ſelfe, will certainely evict, that Antiquitie cannot bee anie firme or individuall companion of the Church, and ſo no good marke. For then, the Church muſt have beene ancient in the verie infancie or beginning thereof; which is a thing impoſsible. Antiquitie is commendable: not in it ſelfe, or when it is alone, but as it is

joyned with veritie. Therefore I conclude this article with the ſame exhortation that the Prophet Ieremy uſed to the men of his time: Stand upon the wayes and conſider which is the olde way, and the good way, and walke in it, that you may finde reſt to your ſoules.
            
            Let us paſſe on further, to the conſideration of other markes, and you ſhall ſee, it cannot ſtand good to make the Church alwaies viſible or conſpicuous. That would take away an article of our Faith and Creed. VVhen wee beleeve there is a Church, we doe affirme plainely that it is not viſible, or ocularly to be diſcerned:Heb. 11. for Faith is an apprehenſion of things that cannot be ſeene. So beleeving there is a Church, (as is by all profeſſed) we acknowledge therein that the ſame is not viſible. Why ſhould anie ſpeake of multitudes to be a marke of the Church,Luc. 19. ſeeing Chriſt himſelfe calleth it a little flocke? Quid gaudendum ad multitudines? This marke of multitudes had beene a weake and impertinēt allegation, when all the world was drowned, but eight perſons ſaved in the Arke; and that was then the whole number of the Church. Or when the five cities were deſtroyed with fire, and Lot onely eſcaped with his

two daughters: or in Elias time, when hee cō
               plained he was left alone.
            The Church is not ever in one ſtate, but like the Moone, ſometimes encreaſing, ſometimes diminiſhing; ſometimes at the full, ſometimes in the waine: and therefore the multitude, or paucity of people in the Church being but accidents, and not eſſentially inherent in the Church: are made markes of the Church unproperly.
            Thus they are deceived, and deceive others, that ſeeke and ſet forth a Church in their owne words. Nolo humanis documentis, ſed divinis oraculis ſanctam Eccleſiam demonstrari. I will not have any demonſtration of the Church made unto me, ſaith S. Auguſtine) out of mens inſtructions, but from the oracles of God. Seeke then for the Church in the words of Chriſt, and the demonſtration thereof will be infallible. Our bleſſed Saviour ſendeth his Diſciples into all the world (that is the extent of the Church) he chargeth them to preach the Goſpell unto every creature, to baptize them in the name of the Father, of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt, and to teach them to obſerve all that he hath commanded. Theſe be the things which the Sonne

of God would have practiſed in his houſe, and by them you may eaſily finde out the Church of God. The ſincere doctrine of the Goſpell, the true and right adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and that forme of diſcipline which may bring obedience to his commandements: who can make that a Church where theſe things be wanting? who can deny it to bee a Church, where they be exerciſed? My ſheepe (ſaith our Saviour) heare my voyce. Therefore the Word of God muſt be read, it muſt be preached, it muſt ſound amongſt them; elſe how is it poſsible that they ſhould heare it? Ecce Scripturae communes:
               Aug. Epiſt. 166. 
               ecce ubi novimus Christum; ecce ubi novimus Eccleſiam. The Scriptures which are propounded to all men, ſaith S. Auguſtine, are the uſuall markes to know Chriſt and his Church by. So Chriſt ſaith himſelfe, If yee abide in mee, and my words abide in you, yee are verily my Diſciples. But alas how can his wordes abide in thoſe which heare not of them, that are forbidden to heare or know them? Non eſt pax ſed bellum,
               Cypr. de lapſ. Ser. 5. 
               nec Eccleſiae jungitur qui ab evangelio ſeparatur. There can be no peace but warre with ſuch people; neyther can they be joyned to the Church, that ſever themſelves 
                  ••
               om the Goſpel.

Or put caſe they have the Goſpell, yet if it bee not expounded truely unto them, if it bee not taught purely and ſincerely, what advantageth it them? As all gold was not holy, but that only which belonged to the Sanctuary; ſo every ſenſe that is without the compaſſe of Holy Writ, gliſtering without never ſo much otherwiſe, yet can it not be holy unleſſe it be conformed to the word of God.Hierony. in cap 5 ad Galatas. 
               Quicun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Scripturam aliter intelligit quàm ſenſus ſpiritus ſancti flagitat, licet de Eccleſia non receſſerit, tamen haereticus appellari poteſt. Whoſoever interpreteth the Scriptures otherwiſe then the holy Ghoſt meaneth, by which it is written, may well bee called an hereticke, although hee be not departed from the Church. Are not the interpretations from God? Ioſeph teacheth us they are from God, in expounding Pharaohs dreame: then much more are the interpretations of holy Scripture from God. By the ſame Spirit the Scriptures were written, by the ſame they muſt be interpreted and underſtood:2. Cor. 2. 
               For what man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the ſpirit of a man that is within him? even ſo the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God, and thoſe that are taught of God. Scripture is not of

private interpretation, but muſt be interpreted by Scripture; the darker places, by thoſe which be more plaine &amp; eaſie: and, as Tertullian writeth, oportet ſecundum plura intelligi pauciora: &amp; ne unus ſermo multa alta ſubvertat, ſecundū omnia, potius quam adverſus omnia intelligendus erit; The interpretations of the Scripture muſt be made according to the meaning of the more places: and leſt that one Text ſhould warre againſt many others, that is to be expounded in a correſpondency to all the reſt, rather then in a repugnancy unto them. And if you will try the Spirits whether they bee of God, or no (as S. Iohn adviſeth us) or examine every interpretation; we have two rules to meaſure them by: The firſt examination is, whether their interpretations and expoſitions bee referred to the glory of God or no? If they tend to the glory of God, our Saviour Chriſt giveth them a warrant of truth: Qui quaerit gloriam meam verax eſt; He that in his expoſitions ſeeketh my glory, is a true interpreter. Let us now in the name of God, come to the tryall of particulars by this rule. Is it poſsible for them to ſeeke the glory of God in the queſtion of Iuſtification, which refuſe the juſtification by Ieſus Chriſt, and attribute

ſalvation to their owne merites? who magnifie the abilities of humane nature, and extenuate the unſearchable riches of Gods grace? I conceive no poſsibility or apparance of it. Quid illis miſerius quorum ſaluti ſalus ipſa nō ſufficit? Alas, how miſerable are they, which will not have ſalvation it ſelfe ſufficient to ſave them? Beloved, let us not abrogate the grace of God: for S. Auguſtine writeth truly, Tutiores vivimus, ſi totum Deo damus; Wee live in more ſafety when wee aſcribe the whole worke of our juſtification to God.
            The ſecond tryall of interpretations, is, whether they be agreeable with the proportion of faith? For he that propheſieth, muſt doe it accorcording to the proportion of faith. Meaſure the doctrine of Romiſh Catholiques by this rule, and I thinke it will not prove Catholique. Can the invocation of Saints ſtand with the proportion of faith? will they beleeve in Saints? &amp; how can they call on them, in whom they have not beleeved? I cannot ſtand upon many ſuch particulars, which you all doe ſee might be alledged: but am forced through ſtraitneſſe of time to conclude them in this generall.Hierony. in cap. 1. ad Galatas. 
               De Evangelio Chriſti, hominis, faciunt Evangelium, aut quod

pejus eſt diaboli: Theſe interpretations of Scripture, which doe not agree with the proportion of faith, make of Chriſt, a mans Goſpell, or a divels, and that is worſe. The Arke of God and Dagon cannot ſtand together: there is no agreement betweene light and darkeneſſe: the purity of the Goſpel will never admit ſophiſticatiōs of humane deviſes; howſoever the Councell of Trent would have both to be received alike,Seſſ 4. namely, the bookes of both Teſtaments, and the unwritten Traditions, with equall piety and affection of reverence. It is true that the Apoſtles delivered many things ore tenꝰ, which Apoſtolike men received and delivered againe faithfully to their diſciples: but let that be wel remembred withall, which Ireneus writeth, that all theſe things were 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , they were all agreeable to the Scriptures, and their writings. Is it probable, or ſhall we beleeve, that the Apoſtles writing, wee ſhould take heed and beware of Images, did leave any tradition, that times would come, wherein the uſe of pictures and images would be requiſite or fitting in the Church? Is it credible, that the Idols of Iupiter, Mars, Mercury, &amp;c. ſhould be caſt out of all Temples by the Apoſtles doctrine;

and a tradition from the Apoſtles, to ſet up the portraitures of Chriſt, of the bleſſed Virgin Mary, or their owne pictures in place of the other? Is it poſsible, that they which taught us to worſhip and call upon one God alone, did ever give any tradition for themſelves alſo to be worſhipped and called upon, when they were departed this life? That they which writ, VVe have an Advocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, did ever order that themſelves alſo would be our advocates? No, no. It was impoſsible, it is incredible; it cannot be conceived without diſparagement to the Apoſtles, that men of their ranke and integrity, inſpired and governed by the holy Ghoſt, ſhould deliver or utter any thing by word of mouth, varying or diſſenting from the atteſtations they left in writing. The pure word of God, without addition or diminution, is the true marke of the Church; and ſo the Huckſters that chop and change it, to ſerve their owne inventions or turnes, carry not the right cognizance of Chriſtians.
            Touching Sacraments, and the due adminiſtration thereof, which is another marke of a true Church: they that are moſt confident,

and make greateſt vaunts of the Church, do no wayes adminiſter them rightly; ſave that by God his providence the eſſential forme of Baptiſme is reteyned amongſt them: otherwiſe they prophane it not a little, when they apply it to ſenſleſſe things, as to Bells; when they add Salt, Oyle, and Spittle. Is not the element of Water ſufficient, which Chriſt inſtituted to repreſent his precious bloud, to waſh away our ſinnes, without thoſe mixtures?
            The other Sacrament of the Lords Supper, they have not defiled, as they have done Baptiſme: but they have quite altered and changed it into a curſed and abhominable Idoll of their Maſſe. And ſo have prevented and annihilated Chriſt his holy inſtitution: For firſt, whereas two things bee neceſſary in Sacraments; the ſigne, and the thing ſignified: they take away the Signes, for eſtabliſhing of their Tranſubſtantiation. Secondly, they ſhould diſtribute it unto others, and they keepe it onely to themſelves, &amp; ſo make it private; whereas it ſhould be a publike banquet. Thirdly, they keepe the Cup from the people, which our Saviour commanded ſhould be given to all. Fourthly, in the Supper Chriſt offereth himſelfe to us, and

their Prieſts offer him unto God; who indeed cannot be offered but by his eternall Spirit; nor without his death, whereas hee died but once for ever. And where theſe things be done, the eſſentiall parts of the Sacrament are not kept; therefore no Supper, no Sacrament, but an horrible prophanation, and plaine ſacriledge. Adulterum eſt, impium eſt,
               Cypr de lapſ. 
               ſacrilegum eſt quodcunque humano furore inſtituitur, ut dispoſitio divina violetur. Whatſoever is inſtituted by humane temeritie, to violate God his ordinance, is adulterous, it is impious, it is ſacrilegious.
            As for thoſe mens diſcipline, whereby people ſhould bee brought to the obedience of Chriſt his commandements: the world ſeeth their wilfull negligence. In which caſe, I muſt needs approve of that which S. Chryſoſtome writeth to the people of Antioch:Hom. 17. 
               Mihi Civitas non habens bonos cives omni villa vilior eſt; The Citie that is not inhabited with good men, is more unpleaſing to mee then the baſeſt village.
            Seeing therefore the Church of Rome reteyneth not the ſincere puritie of the word: ſeeing it hath aboliſhed one of the Sacraments, &amp; corrupted the other prophanely: ſeeing it hath little or no care at all of godly diſcipline; men

may peradventure make doubt or queſtion, whether it be the Church of God, or no? I dare not wholly take away the name of a Church from it. I know that Antichriſt ſhall ſit in the Temple of God: that Baptiſme cannot bee adminiſtred out of the Church: And when the intire forme of Baptiſme is obſerved, S. Auguſtine is reſolved, Non haereticus, ſed haeretici manu Chriſtus baptiſat; There it is not the hereticke that baptiſeth, but Chriſt doth it by the hand of an hereticke. Therefore the Councel of Nice determined very gravely, that there ſhould bee no rebaptization, of ſuch as were baptized by heretickes. Yet I doe not allow the Romiſh Synagogue to bee a Church ſimply, but by equivocation and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . as the woman carrieth the name of your wife, which you did once marry, and afterward found her defiled with adultery; yet becauſe ſhe keepeth the marriage Ring, and ſome other pledges of her former wedlock, ſhe ſtill beareth the name of your wife. So it is with the Church of Rome; albeit for her adulteries ſhe hath deſerved a divorce juſtly: yet becauſe the Bridegroome hath not given her his bill of divorce, but ſuffered her hitherto to hold Baptiſme, as it

were the marriage Ring; I account it a Church, but miſerably deformed, and infected with infinite errors. I cannot reckon it leſſe then a part of diſcourteſie, &amp; of more advantage then Gods truth needeth ſo to contend with the adverſaries thereof, as not to admit of thoſe graces amongſt them, which God is pleaſed to vouchſafe unto them. Let us give every one his right: let our adverſaries in the name of God hold their due: let us willingly yeelde them all that doth appertaine unto them; and let us taxe their corruptions nevertheleſſe with all freedome. This is heroicall, this is Propheticall, this is Apoſtolicall, and much more then they will yeeld unto us. For without hearing of us, or our cauſe, they which are parties againſt us, take upon them to be our judges too, and to condemne us for heretickes, for ſchiſmatickes, and to have no Church at all. Like to Athalia, that ſeeing the right heyre Ioas crowned King of Iudah, cryed, Treaſon, treaſon, when ſhee was greateſt traytor her ſelfe. Indeed if wee unchurch Congregations for ſchiſme, or for ſimple hereſie, there will be no good warrant, unleſſe the hereſie impugne one of the three perſons of the holy Trinitie directly; then the

hereſie is not ſingle, but ariſeth to infidelitie, which is the bane &amp; cut-throat of all Churches.
            But our adverſaries doe charge us alſo with Apoſtaſie; and that is a marke of Antichriſt mentioned in our Text: They went out from us, but they were not of us. Hereupon our Rhemiſh Seminaries note, that Luther and Calvin went out of their Church, that is, of Papiſts became Proteſtants; but they came not out of ours: &amp; that is the Catholique Church which is forſaken. To admit that which will not eaſily bee proved, that England firſt received the Chriſtian faith from Rome, both in the time of Eleutherius their Biſhop, and alſo in the time of Auguſtine their Monke; yet wil it not thereon follow, that we muſt ſtill fetch our Religion from Rome, as from the chiefe fountaine and well-ſpring of all godlineſſe. For if any man fall away from that Church which is not Chriſt his ſpouſe, hee cannot be charged juſtly with Apoſtaſie: Nullus pudor eſt ad meliora tranſire; It is no ſhame to change for the better. Or if a man doe leave and depart from a particular Church in bodie, and yet forſake not the communion and fellowſhip of the Apoſtles doctrine, nor the Sacramēts rightly adminiſtred, but holdeth

them with all other ſincere Churches: that man is no Apoſtata.Chryſoſt. in Mat. hom. 46. 
               Non ille de Eccleſia exire videtur qui corporaliter exit, ſed qui ſpiritualiter veritatis Eccleſiaſticae fundamenta reliquit; Hee goeth not out of the Church that departeth corporally, but hee that ſpiritually hath forſaken the foundations of Eccleſiaſtical truth. The right apoſtaſie is a falling away from the true Catholique &amp; Apoſtolique Church of Chriſt, and therefore from Chriſt; and that by revolting from the Apoſtles doctrine, &amp; the communion of the Catholique faith. They went out from us. If Luther, Calvin, and our ſelves went out of the Church of Rome, wee incurre no crime of apoſtaſie therein: becauſe we left that Church which was neither Catholique, nor Apoſtolique. We left not Bethel, that is, the houſe of God, untill it became Bethaven, that is, the houſe of iniquitie.
            
            An Apoſtolique Church it is not, becauſe it reſteth not upon the doctrine of the Apoſtles, but is fallen from it, as wee have formerly ſhewed. In which caſe,De unitat. eccleſ. we have S. Auguſtines grave adviſe; Ne Catholicis quidem Epiſcopis conſentiendum eſt, ſicubi ſorte fallantur, &amp; contra canonicas Scripturas aliqui ſentiant. No conſent is to bee

given to thoſe Biſhops which are Catholique, when they are deceived, or hold any thing contrary to the canonicall Scriptures. Wee then in going out of that Church where the word of God is not purely taught, &amp; the Sacraments are not adminiſtred duely, according to our Saviour Chriſt his holy inſtitution, and God is not worſhipped after the Apoſtles doctrine; make no default or departure from the Church, but as Moſes went out of Egypt, Lot out of Sodom, Elias from Baals Prieſts: and that is no apoſtaſie, but a renunciation of their apoſtaſie, that wee might marſhall our ſelves under the Standard of our head and Captaine Chriſt Ieſus, and ſo enter into true Hieruſalem, which is mother of us all. If the Church of Rome give impediment to us in this paſſage, it is a ſtep-dame, no true mother, no Apoſtolike Church. Neyther is it the Catholike, but a particular Church, as the Churches were of Alexandria, Milan, Epheſus, &amp;c. The Church is called Catholike, firſt, in reſpect of place, when it is not appropriated or fixed to any certaine place (as the Iewes did dreame of Ieruſalem long agoe, and the Papiſts doe now dote of Rome) but reacheth unto all parts and places of the world:

ſecondly, it is called Catholike in reſpect of perſons comprehended in it, becauſe no ſort of people are excluded or refuſed. For now the wall of partition is pulled downe, and wee are all one in Chriſt Ieſus: thirdly, it is called Catholike in reſpect of time, that whenſoever it had beginning, yet it continueth for ever, eyther militant here upon earth, or triumphant in heaven. So the whole family or houſe of God is divided. Fourthly and laſtly, the Church is called Catholike, in reſpect of doctrine therein profeſſed: for it imbraceth &amp; maintayneth, not parts or portions, but the whole body of Prophetical and Apoſtolical doctrine. The Church of Rome is not Catholique in any of theſe reſpects; and therefore we pleade, Not guilty of apoſtaſie in leaving it. Let our adverſaries meditate rather how to cleere the Church of Rome of apoſtaſie: for it is fallen away from them of whom it received the Goſpell, Faith, Religion, and the name of a Church. Let them refuſe their Synagogues, forſake their broken ciſternes that will hold no water, returne to that true &amp; ancient faith, for which they were once renowned through the world; and wee ſhall runne together againe in an holy union

with them. If they will not, I call heaven and earth to record againſt them this day, that they themſelves are fallen from the Goſpell, from truth, from word, from Sacraments, from Religiō, from Chriſt, from the Apoſtles &amp; church of Chriſt: all which wee uphold with great endevour. For they have broken the bands, wherwith they were coupled to the Apoſtles: they have relinquiſhed that cōmunion, which formerly they held with the Church.
            Theſe bands be of two ſorts, outward and inward. The outward bands may bee cut in ſunder: as the profeſsion of true doctrine, and the right adminiſtration of the Sacraments. Both which bands are broken by our adverſaries; as wee have ſhewed ſome proofe of before: And they ſhall never be able to throw any juſt aſperſion upon us in that kind; the Lord of heaven and earth be praiſed for it. Amongſt the inward couplings, Election is firſt: for all that belong truely to the Church, are bound together in heaven in the bundle of life with their God. The other is the band of Chriſt his holy Spirit; which worketh the ſame faith and love in the members, that is in Chriſt our head. Theſe inward bands cannot be diſſolved, or

cut in ſunder: for neyther can God his eternall election be avoyded; neyther can the faith of thoſe that are elected, faile totally or finally. The viſible Church hath in it ſelfe, two different ſorts of people: the one make an outward bare profeſsion onely; the other by inward election, are firmely joyned unto Chriſt. The firſt are in the viſible Church alone, but not of the Church inviſible: They participate in the outward Sacraments of Chriſt, but not with the inward bleſsings of Chriſt; and ſo they may fall away: they may be in the Church, but not of the Church. They which are inwardly coupled to Chriſt by his election, and holy Spirit, cannot fall away from Chriſt &amp; his church. So our Text teacheth us their conſtancie and perſeverance; If they had beene of us, they would have continued with us. The outward joynts and participation may be diſſolved: for all they are not the Iſrael of God, which are of Iſrael. No; many of thē are Iſraelites: they were amongſt the multitude that was called, they were not of the ſmall number that was elected. Mali in Area nobiſcum eſſe poſſunt, in horreo non poſſunt: Hypocrites and falſe Goſpellers may bee in the Church with us; they cannot be of the church:

they are like Summer fruit, they hold not out, they continue not.
            On the other ſide, they that bee of us, they continue with us. After they be matriculated, &amp; have their names regiſtred in the holy Rolls of the Church, they doe not revolt, but are eſtabliſhed. All that the Father giveth me, ſhall come to mee; and him that commeth unto mee, I cast not away. The counſell of the Lord endureth for ever. 
               
                  
                     Ʋnde (ſaith Saint Auguſtine) niſi de nobis quos antea praeſcivit &amp; praedeſtinavit? Quis tollit praedeſtinationem Dei? ante mundi conſtitutionem vidit nos, fecit nos, emendavit nos, miſit ad nos, red
                        •
                     mit nos: hoc ejus conſilium manet in aeternum, haec ejus cogitatio manet in ſecula ſeculorum.
                How doth the Lords counſel endure for ever, but in us whom he hath ſeene and predeſtinated? Who can take away God his predeſtination? before the foundation of the world he did foreſee us, he made us, he reformed us, he ſent unto us, he redeemed us: this counſell of the Lord abideth for ever, this thought of the Almightie remayneth thoroughout all ages. Behold the ground and certainty of their faith; marke how they which are inwardly coupled to Chriſt &amp; his Church, cannot fall away from the one or the other:

for Chriſt ſayes, None can take them out of his hands. Another reaſon is expreſſed in the ſame place: My Father which gave them to mee, is greater then all; and none is able to take them out of my Fathers hands. Theſe reaſons were not good, if they might fall away from Chriſt which are inwardly coupled to him: for then Chriſt and his Father muſt bee weaker then hee that did take them out of their hands; and that is a blaſphemie worthy to be deteſted.
            If faith could fayle, the elect might periſh: for without faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God. But our Saviour Chriſt doth teſtifie, that it is not poſsible that the elect ſhould periſh: &amp; therefore their faith cannot fayle. If their faith could fayle, the elect ſhould be regenerate often: but the elect are borne of incorruptible ſeed; and as the ſeed is, ſo muſt the generation alſo be incorruptible. To that purpoſe S. Iohn writeth, Hee that is borne of God ſinneth not, neither can hee, becauſe the ſeed of God abideth in him. How ſhould faith be variable, that hath God his promiſe? I will put my feare in their hearts, that they ſhall not goe from me. If God will not have his to fall away, how ſhould they fayle? If he will put his feare into their hearts, that they ſhould not

fayle, how can they loſe that feare? No, no. Beſides that, they have a further preſervative, namely, the efficacie of Chriſt his prayers, Keepe them in thy truth, Ioh. 17: Againe, I have prayed for thee, that thy faith doe not faile, Luc. 22.
            
               The mountaines ſhall remove, and the hills ſhall fall downe; but my mercy ſhall not depart from thee neither ſhall the covenant of my peace fall away, ſaith the Lord, Eſay 54.
            
               Ioh. 15.
               You have not choſen me, but I have choſen you, and ordeyned you that you goe and bring forth fruit, and that your fruit remaine. If Chriſt hath ordeyned that their fruit ſhall remaine, who dare ſay that it ſhall not remaine?Rom. 11. 
               The gifts and graces of God are without repentance. Of Davids faith, of Peters, and others that fell into enormious ſins; I ſay with Tertullian, Caepit areſcere, ſed non exaruit: mota fuit, ſed non amota: concuſſa, ſed non excuſſa, nut extincta. Their faith began to wither, but it withered not: it was moved, but not removed: it was ſhaken, but not extinguiſhed. The grace of faith, and the holy Ghoſt, may be, and are often loſt even of them that are regenerate in part, concerning ſome certain gifts more or leſſe; but cannot be loſt wholly, becauſe the Lord reſerveth a ſeede in them. For example,

               David loſt the rightneſſe of heart, and integrity of ſpirit, when he fell into his foule ſinnes of adultery and murther: yet was he not bereaved of theſe wholly; for then hee could not have prayed for reſtitution unto them. How ſhall they call upon him, in whom they have not beleeved? Marke then in David that ſeed which S. Iohn ſaith is left. Oh the unſearchable riches of our God his goodneſſe and mercie, that reſerveth a ſeed of regeneration in our moſt heavie &amp; ſad downefalls! For except the Lord of Hoſts had left this ſeed, we ſhould all have beene as Sodome, and as Gomorra.
            
            
               Theophilact writeth to the like purpoſe, of Peter, upon Luc. 22. Although Peter thou ſhalt find a concuſsion for a while, yet haſt thou the ſeeds of faith left within thee: although the breath of the Tempter ſhake downe ſome leaves of thy faith, yet the root holdeth life, and thy faith ſhall not fayle. Will you ſee a lively repreſentation or ſpectacle hereof? Looke upon the ſame man, the ſame Peter, Mat. 14. when he was walking unto Chriſt upon the Sea, and trampling downe the proud waves thereof with his feet: he began to be drowned in that haughtie enterpriſe; but Chriſt, reaching out a

hand unto him, held him up. Bleſſed bee that ſweete, that comfortable, that helpfull, and healthfull hand of Ieſus Chriſt, which is reached out to us all in our ſeverall neceſsities. And ſo, to conclude this point with ſenſible divinitie, which moſt of us, that obſerve it, hath experience of; though our faith be often ſhaken (as Peters was) with our owne infirmities, yet it ſtandeth faſt by the mercies of God in Chriſt. Hee ſeeth no iniquitie in Iacob, nor tranſgreſsion in Iſrael: or if he looke upon it, hee beholdeth all the Items &amp; Obligations thereof cancelled, and faſtened to the Croſſe of his Sonne. So as indeed there is no condemnation left to them that are in Ieſus Chriſt.
               2. Cor. 4.8. 
               VVe are afflicted on every ſide, yet are we not in diſtreſſe: wee are in doubt, but wee deſpaire not: we are perſecuted, but not forſaken: caſt downe, but we periſh not.
            
            
               Hieronym. epiſt. ad Ruſticum
               Nihil Chriſtiano foelicius eui promittitur regnum coelorum: nihil laborioſius qui quotidiè de vita periclitatur: nihil fortius, qui vincit diabolum: nihil imbecillius qui à carne ſuperatur. Nothing more happie then a Chriſtian, becauſe hee hath promiſe of the kingdom of heaven: nothing more painfull, becauſe hee runneth in hazard of his life every day; nothing more valiant, becauſe

he overcometh the divell: nothing more feeble, becauſe he is vanquiſhed by his own fleſh. This ſumme is, that wee have a great treaſure given unto us of God in faith and beleeving his promiſes: but we carry this treaſure in earthen veſſels, ſubject to many knocks. Let us therefore worke out our ſalvation with feare and trembling: firſt, by diſtruſting our owne abilities, and attributing all to God through Ieſus Chriſt: Secondly, in beleeving his promiſes therein. So wee ſhall bee humble in our ſelves, with feare and trembling; yet confident in God, which worketh all in us, both to will &amp; to performe. When we are weake, he is ſtrong; and out of our weakeneſſe bringeth forth his owne power. He predeſtinateth us to be of his family by his eternall counſell, inrolleth us by our Baptiſme, calleth us by his holy word, nouriſheth us with the body and bloud of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, ſealeth and confirmeth us to conſtancie by the effectuall operation of his bleſſed Spirit. And ſo thoſe which revolt from us in theſe bands, what outward ſhew ſoever they make of Catholiques, yet are they not of the true Church: but ſo perſiſting, they have no portion; no right, no memoriall in Ieruſalem. Howbeit

let us pray the Father 
                  〈◊〉
                Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to take away the va
                  〈…〉
                
               
                  •
               s laid 
                  〈◊〉
                their hearts, to the intent 
                  〈…〉
               
               red together into one fold, to 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               hip, to 
                  •••
               
               feſſe, to call upon Father, Sonne, &amp; holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one God, prayſed and magnified in the Church throughout all generations. AMEN.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

