
   
      
         
            An answere to a papystycall exhortacyon pretendynge to auoyde false doctryne, vnder that colour to maynteyne the same.
            Bale, John, 1495-1563.
         
         
            
               1548
            
         
         Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02620
            STC 1274A
            ESTC S110821
            99846289
            99846289
            11249
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02620)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11249)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 22:06)
         
         
            
               
                  An answere to a papystycall exhortacyon pretendynge to auoyde false doctryne, vnder that colour to maynteyne the same.
                  Bale, John, 1495-1563.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  S. Mierdman,
                  [Antwerp :
                  ca. 1548]
               
               
                  By John Bale.
                  Imprint from STC.
                  In verse.
                  Prints and answers the exhortacion--STC.
                  Signatures: A B⁴ (-B4).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2004-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-04
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2004-04
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ An answere to a papystycall exhortacyon, pretendynge to auoyde false doctryne, vnder that colour to maynteyne the same.
            
               ¶ By ther frutes shall ye knowe them.
               Math. 7.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  EVerye pylde pedlar
               Wyll be a medlar
               Though ther wyttes be drowsye
               And ther lernynge lowsye
               Ther meters all mangye
               Rashe, rurall, and grangye
               Yet wyll they forwarde halte
               As menne mased in malte
            
            
               These vyle cannell rakers
               Are now becumme makers
               Ther poems out they dashe
               With all ther swyber swashe
               Ther darnell and ther chaffe
               Ther swylle and swynyshe draffe
               Soche pype soche melodye
               Soche bagge soche beggerye.
            
            
               Of pylde popyshe facyons
               They strowe exhortacions
               The people to infecte.
               With the sedes of ther secte
               Pretendynge to dyffyne
               Agaynst the false doctryne
               But soche dyrtye geare
               Ded menne neuer heare.
            
            
               They teache nat in meter
               With Paule Iohan and Peter
               The worlde to edyfye
               With goddes worde christenlye
               But scripturs they depraue
               
                  As madde men that do raue
               They daunce with the deuyll
               To magnysye ther euyll
            
            
               They drysle forth a dramme
               As he that to Christ camme
               To trappe hym in a snare
               Forsoth it is fonde ware
               Let christen menne take hede
               Vnto ther wycked sede
               For they seke for to blynde
               The syllye symple mynde,
            
            
               The papystes tytle. An exhortacy on to auoyde false doctryne.
               
                  The papyste.
                  My mynde can not perfughtelye endyre
                  Neyther my penne can trewlye wryte
                  As my hart doth desyre.
                  The cause onlye is for lacke of syght
                  In lernynge that is so perfyght and bryght
                  Wherfore pardō of good mē I requyred
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  
                  Your penne and your mynde
                  Are both of one kynde
                  And fyt for soche an hart
                  As owle in the nyght
                  Without gostly syght
                  Ye playe a knauyshe part.
                  Attendite a falsie prophetis qui venisitad vos.Math. 7.
                  
                  Of soche wolues beware
                  As laye forth a snare
                  Of outwarde holynes.
                  Queritis interficere hominē 
                     q veritatē locuiꝰ.Ioh
                           •
                        . 8.
                  
                  For they do nat elles
                  But playe the rebelles
                  Agaynst goddes ryghteousnes.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  If any man els be greued with thys
                  Let them take it euen as it is
                  And I praye God them to amende
                  I thynke with charyte them to tell
                  As I fynde written in the gospell
                  To the lawe of God we shuld attends.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Lyke a braynyshe dolte
                  Ye shote forth your bolte
                  As bolde as bayarde blynde
                  ye loue the gospell
                  As the deuyll of hell
                  Here after we shall it fynde
                  Attendite popule meus legem meam.Psal. 77
                  
                  Attende to goddes lawe
                  And to hys worde drawe
                  
                     All you that faythfull be
                  Cauete a fermento Phariseorsi quid est hipo.Luc. 12.
                  
                  The leuen eschewe
                  Of pharisees vntrewe
                  Yf ye loue the veryte.
               
               
                  The papyste
                  Some of late with them selues perswaded
                  Out of the shalowe so fayre they waded
                  That they felt no grounde.
                  They had thought vs to haue blynded
                  And of the trewth vs to haue wynded
                  But now ther deceytes be founde.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  If people be yll
                  They shall be so styll
                  For ought that ye brynge here
                  Your doctryne is chaffe
                  Your ryme dyrtye draffe
                  It is vnsauerye gere.
                  Linguis suis do lose agebant, iudica illos.Rom. 3.
                  
                  The language of lyes
                  A false harlot tryes
                  To seke a wycked praye.
                  Sicut nouacula acutafecisti dolum.Psa. 51.
                  
                  With colours to carpe
                  As a rasour sharpe
                  To wype goddes treuth awaye.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  Let no manne be so styffe necked
                  To thinke him self so hyghly in lerning decked
                  Standynge in hys owne conceyte.
                  For yf thou or he be in the wronge
                  
                     Thou nor he can not be so stronge
                  But the deuyll for the hath a beyte.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Stande you where ye lyst
                  Ye are a papyst
                  In lernynge verye basse
                  To cum for refuge
                  To soche a pylde iuge
                  Is for to seke an asse.
                  Si lumen quod in te est tenebre sint.Math 6.
                  
                  Your myndes are so darke
                  Ye seke but the barke
                  And therin ye remayne.
                  Velamen positum est super cor eorum.2. cor. 3.
                  
                  Ye holde fast the letter
                  And wyll haue no better
                  The spyryt ye do dysdayne.
               
               
                  The papyste
                  Ther were heretykes that neuer wolde cease
                  But from vs to take vnyte and peace
                  So amonge vs they dyd fyght.
                  In ther blyndenes so farre gone they were
                  That of God they had no dought or fere.
                  All to destruccion was ther delyght.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Is ther one alyue
                  Which canne ye depryue
                  Of that ye neuer hadde▪
                  
                  Of stryfe and debate
                  Sedicion and hate
                  Your kynde was euer gladde.
                  Contritio &amp; infelicitas in vijs eorum.Psal. 9.
                  
                  
                     Ye labour and speake
                  To destroye and breake
                  The vyneyarde of the lorde
                  Vinea domini exercituum domus Israel est.Esa. 5.
                  
                  Of the losse therof
                  Ye make a but a scof
                  As Esaye doth recorde.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  Christ wylleth vs to take good hede
                  Of these seducers for we had nede
                  To
                        •
                     e the scripture and se.
                  From ther folowers let vs refrayne
                  For small charyte in them remayne
                  As semeth vnto me.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Your self is the sede
                  Of deceytfull wede
                  As your frutes doth report
                  For lesse charyte
                  In men can not be
                  Than in your popyshe sort.
                  Nemo vos seducatinan ibus verbis.Eph. 5.
                  
                  The false craftye spyes
                  Come in with ther lyes
                  All men of them beware
                  Venit hora, vt omnis qui interficit vos.Ioh. 16.
                  
                  They haue not ther fylle
                  Tyll they slee and kylle
                  No innocentes they spare.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  And a man agaynst them wryte or speke
                  Some ther be wyll hym cruelly intrete
                  
                     I maruele they are so bolde
                  Ther was a thynge made of late
                  Some had indignacion therate
                  And openly beganne to scolde.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Whan we fynde ye bolde
                  In your poperye olde
                  Therof we do ye telle
                  Your poetes we touche
                  For shakynge ther pouche
                  And shewe wherof they smelle.
                  Imitantur illum, qui sunt ex parte illius.Sap. 2.
                  
                  They folowe the deuyll
                  Which seke to do euyll
                  And are vpon hys syde.
                  Vos expatre diabolo estis, &amp; opera.Ioha 8.
                  
                  The proude papystes all
                  With the prestes of ball
                  Do take hym for ther gyde.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  But trewly it shall not a whyt sliylle
                  Let them bable euen ther fylle
                  It is so hote it maye not abyde.
                  For an heretyke wyll they defende
                  By the kynges lawes iustly condempne
                  And saye a christen man he dyed.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Who are more bablars
                  And frautycke fablars
                  Than pratlynge papystes be ?
                  We knowe none heretykes
                  Nor trayterous scysmatykes
                  
                     But your affinite.
                  Nunquid potest homoignē abscōdere in sinue
                  The bosome hath fyreProu. 6.
                  
                  Of fleshly desyre
                  Where spirituall fathers be▪
                  
                  Masculi relicto naturali vsu femine exarserunt.Rom. 1.
                  
                  With conscience aduste
                  They burne in ther luste
                  And worke moche vanyte.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  Some be afrayed hys confession to shew opēly
                  In prynte the
                        •
                      wyll nat haue it verely
                  The cause ones knowne.
                  To hys part them selues somwhat bent
                  Now they fere they shall be shent
                  Soche gostlye sedes had they sowne.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Ye geue dyrte for flynte
                  The thynge is in prynte
                  That ye gruge at so sore
                  It is nat vnknowne
                  What sedes ye haue sowne
                  In thys realme here tofore.
                  Quod timetimpius, veniet supereum,Pro. 10.
                  
                  That the wycked dought
                  Shall lyght on ther snought
                  Ther churche must haue a fall.
                  Omnis plantatio quam non plantauit pate
                        •
                     
                     ▪
                     Math. 15
                  
                  What God hath not sowne
                  Nor the gospell knowne
                  Shall be turned ouer all.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  
                  Wo be to them that fayne so outwarde
                  And be so pestylent enuyous inwarde
                  To a graue maye I lyke them in dede.
                  That is without set full of goodly stones
                  Within full of stynkynge rotten bones
                  Loke the gospell and tede.
               
               
                  The christiane.
                  Lyke these, ratte, and mouse
                  The poore wydowes house
                  Your bellyes doth deuoure
                  Ye sucke vppe the fatte
                  For straynynge a gnatte
                  In your vsurped poure.
                  Ve vobis, quia similes estis sepulcris de albatis.Mat. 23.
                  
                  Who are the whyght graues
                  But soche romyshe knaues
                  And paynted hypocrytes.
                  Audite verbum domini principes sodomorū,Esa. 1.
                  
                  As vnder pretence
                  Of chaste contynence
                  Do playe the sodomytes.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  They that be full of iniquyte
                  Shall neuer com in christes companye
                  Except they do amende.
                  God commaundeth those people to walke
                  That agaynst men maliciouslye do talke
                  And with peace do contende.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  If Christe do refuse
                  All soche as abuse
                  The glorye of hys name
                  
                     Ye chaplaynes of ball
                  Must nedes haue a fall
                  And come to vtter shame
                  Discedite a me omnes q operamini iniquitatē.Math. 7
                  
                  Ye lobbryshe lurkars
                  And ydle workars
                  Hence fro me, sayth the lorde
                  Frustra me colunt docentes doctrinas.Marc. 7.
                  
                  Your owne wayes ye vse
                  And my lawes refuse
                  Lyke as your frutes recorde.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  Some heretylico of late as I thynke
                  Wer lothe that ther flesh shuld stynke
                  Aboue the erthe or within
                  They loked euer and hoped for a daye
                  But they were brent all thre by the waye
                  And taken in ther owne gynne.
               
               
                  The christiane.
                  Attraytours ye wynke
                  Natfelynge ther stynke
                  So many as hath bene
                  For a daye they wrought
                  Whan ye no lesse thought
                  Ye maye knowe what I mene.
                  In insidijs suis capiuntur inique▪ &amp;c▪
                     Pro. 10.
                  
                  In your popyshe maske
                  The grande captayne aske
                  Was trapped in hys turne
                  Durum est tibi contra stimulum calcitra▪
                     act. 9.
                  
                  Ye maye se by thys
                  What daunger it is
                  
                     Agaynst goddes ▪trewth to spurne
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  To speke of good workes it were a shame
                  They loued not to heare of that name
                  But sola fides and none other
                  Ther tonges ranne so moche vpon fayth
                  But ther hartes were farre thēs as Crist sayth
                  Ther lyppes and hartes were farre a sonder
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  They neuer denyed
                  Soche workes as fayth tryed
                  But your apyshe fantasyes
                  Your tunges and your hartes
                  Paye neyther good partes
                  In your lattyn memoryes.
                  Populus hic labijs me honorat cor eorum,Exe. 33.
                  
                  Your labour of lyppes
                  Is so drye as chyppes
                  God doth it nat esteme.
                  Vostransgredimini mandatum dei propterMath. 15
                  
                  Ye leaue goddes precepte
                  To haue your owne kepte
                  Wherin ye do blaspheme.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  Yf thou wylt take the byble boke
                  And vpon saynt Iames pystle loke
                  Ther you shall I trowe se
                  How fayth is ther trewly applyed
                  And good workes with hym tyed
                  Se how they do agre.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Paule only of fayth
                  
                     Of workes saynt Iames sayth
                  God doth vs iustifye
                  Before God fayth thanne
                  And workes before manne
                  Concludeth thys controuersye.
                  Fides sine operibus mortua est,Iaco. 
                           •
                        2.
                  
                  The workes that you make
                  Trew fayth do nat wake
                  For why they are but chaffe.
                  Nolite margaritas ponere ante porcos,Math. 7
                  
                  Goddes worde doth diffyne
                  That ye are but swyne
                  Yefede in s
                        •
                     oylle and draffe.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  Yf thou wylt a faythfull christen man be
                  Loke thou haue fayth, hope, and charyte
                  And do thou good for yll
                  Let thy mouthe &amp; thy hart be without enuye
                  That pleaseth God &amp; the kyng let it please the
                  And hys mynde fulfyll.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  All one are those thre
                  And neuer dysgre
                  Wher fayth is roted fast
                  Our lorde God and kynge
                  Ye haue wayed nothynge
                  In your olde practyse past.Pro. 24
                  
                  Time dominum filimi, &amp; regem
                  My sonne of all thynge
                  Feare God and thy kynge
                  Thus Salomon doth saye.
                  Achitophel contra Dauid consilium dedit▪
                     2. re. 17.
                  
                  
                     With achitophell
                  Ye papystes rebell
                  And all your kynges betraye.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  To speke of holy breade and holy water
                  I intende not to medle with that mater
                  But leaue it as it is
                  Let vs one for an other praye
                  With good hope as longe as we maye
                  That we maye com to heuyns blys
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  Olde hooles do nat cloute
                  Least ye be spyed oute
                  But tarrye yet a tyme
                  Heuyn wyll nat be gote
                  With your psalmes by note
                  Yt is to hygh to clyme.
                  Tu domine singulariter in speconstituistime,Psal. 4.
                  
                  All they hope in vayne
                  That styll do remayne
                  In the dregges op popyshe lawes.
                  Sapientia huius mundi stultitia est apud deum
                        
                           •
                        . cor. 3.
                  
                  Lyue they neuer so longe
                  Ther fryndes here amonge
                  They shall dye verye dawes.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  To praye for them that thys worlde hath past
                  I thynke surelye we maye not be agast
                  Loke the scripture of I lye.
                  Rede the Machabees softlye thorow oute
                  And ye shall fynde it no doute
                  Yf you your dylygencs do applye.
               
               
                  
                  The chrystiane.
                  Where Christ set no waye.
                  For dead men to praye
                  It canne not them auayle
                  That the Machabees tell
                  Shall be no gospell
                  Where other scripturs fayle.
                  Salubris est cogitatio pro defunctis exorate.2. ma. 
                           •
                        2
                  
                  To make any mone
                  For soules that are gone
                  It is vnfaythfulnes
                  Iustorum anime in manu dei sunt.
                        
                           •
                        api. 3.
                  
                  For they fele no rodde
                  In the handes of godde
                  But peace and quyetnes.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  I wryte not thys intendynge to preche
                  Neyther takynge vpon me any mā to teche
                  My lernynge is not mete
                  But because vnder holy pretente
                  We shuld not hyde these heretykes offence
                  But treade it vnder our fete.
               
               
                  The christiane.
                  Ye vtter soche trashe
                  And pylde haberdashe
                  As laye longe in your mynde
                  But loke ye styll hyde
                  All treason and pryde
                  Of your olde popyshe kynde.
                  Noui
                        •
                      dominus viam iustorū, &amp; iter impiorū.Psal. 1.
                  
                  All wayes of the iuste
                  The lorde hath discuste
                  
                     The prestes dwell in ther dreames
                  Dereliquerunt fontem aque viue, &amp; foderunt.Hie. 2.
                  
                  In ther donge they lye
                  Lyke boores in a stye
                  For mudde they leaue the streames.
               
               
                  The papiste.
                  They that thynke that barnes was holy
                  In ther braynes ther is great foly
                  Iuge other men what they canne
                  Surely he was by hym self alone
                  To contende with hym duest not one
                  He was so proper a manne.
               
               
                  The christiane.
                  As Paule doth recorde
                  We are of the lorde
                  To hym we stande or fall
                  Take hede least ye swerue
                  For he doth reserue
                  Ryght iugement for ye all
                  Abhominantur imp
                        •
                      eos, qui in recta via sunt.Eccl. 
                           ••
                        
                     
                  
                  Ye wycked papystes
                  In your drowsye mystes
                  Abhorre the symple sort
                  Quid nam est hoc? quae doctrina hec nouaMarc. 1
                           •
                        
                     
                  
                  Ye do not regarde
                  Goddes worde to be harde
                  But geue it yll report.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  
                  But yf the deuyll were here and brent
                  Some wolde hym pyteously lament
                  In ther hartes they be so kynde
                  Hys confession shuld be kept as treasure
                  And with some beleued aboue measure
                  They are now so blynde.
               
               
                  The christiane.
                  If they take hys part
                  That scripture peruart
                  Stande you amonge hys fryndes.
                  A dyrtye beleue
                  To the blynde ye geue
                  To recreate ther myndes
                  Non est in ore eorum veritas, cor eorum van
                        ••
                     .Psal. 5.
                  
                  Your fayth is so weake
                  No treuth can ye speake
                  But hate all godly wayes
                  O pastor &amp; idolum derelinquens gregem.Zach. 11
                  
                  Ye robbe christes flocke
                  And geue them a mocke
                  In all your iuglynge playes.
               
               
                  The papyste,
                  All yll thoughtes in our hartes let vs eschue
                  And lyke trew subiectes to our prince cōtynue
                  We shall fynde it ease.
                  To hys pleasure let vs inclyne
                  And not agaynst hys actes to repyne
                  So God we shall please.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  
                  The false foxe that gawde
                  Doth compas some frawde
                  By hys false statterynge toyes
                  Dyslemblars vntrewe
                  Many prynces rewe
                  Amonge these worldly Ioyes
                  In cogitatione tua regi non detraha
                        •
                     
                     Eccl. 10.
                  
                  Who doth a kynge hate?
                  But papystes that prate
                  Agaynst all godlynes
                  Sacerdotes beliscum suis cōcubinis in posturā.Dani. 14
                  
                  Bellys dyrtye dyuynes
                  With ther concubynes
                  Hath wrought all fylthynes.
               
               
                  The papyste.
                  Ther is not in the worlde so wyde
                  Set thys lyttle lande asyde
                  That hath so noble and gentle a kynge.
                  Wherfore let vs all in one praye
                  Euen to God both nyght and daye
                  That longe maye he ouer vo be 
                        •
                     aygnynge.
               
               
                  The chrystiane.
                  God saue christen kynges
                  From your practisynges
                  For myschef ye intende
                  Erom haters of treuth
                  Good seldom enseuth
                  Our prynce the lorde defende
                  Beatate▪ ra, cuius rex nobilis est.Eccl. 10.
                  
                  
                     Happy is that soyle
                  Wher christen men toyle
                  Vnder a faythfull kynge
                  Irritum fecistis pactum leui, propter quod▪
                     Mal. 2.
                  
                  Where prestys do remayne
                  And scripture dysdayne
                  It is an heuy thynge.
               
               Finis.
            
         
      
      
         
            ☞ The appendyce or conclusyon.
            
               NO bussarde so blynde
               But now sperueth hys mynde
               Now cometh hagge and tagge
               And shaketh out ther bagge
               They turne out ther trashe
               And shew ther haberdashe
               Ther pylde pedlarye
               And scalde scullerye.
            
            
               Our olde romyshe ruste
               Leapeth out of the duste
               With a cankred face
               All voyde of goddes grace
               Thynkynge ones agayne
               In Englande to reyne
               
                  And be hadde in pryce
               To maynteyne all vyce.
            
            
               Ser Iohan now is bolde
               In yche place to scolde
               Where men do not care
               For pylde popyshe ware
               He doth them accuse
               And saye they refuse
               The lawes of the lorde
               Bryngynge false recorde
            
            
               They haue a new caste
               The scripturs to wraste
               And wrynge out of frame
               To ther vtter shame
               From treuth they do swerue
               Ther purpose to serue
               And care not for godde
               Nor hys ryghtfull rodde.
            
            
               Lorde pyte thy flocke
               Whome now the prestys mocke
               Sturre vppe prynces hartes
               To stande on ther partes
               Least papystes haue powre
               Thy lammes to deuowre
               Whome vpon the rood
               Thou boutest with thy blood.
            
            Amen.
            ☞ God saue the kynge.
         
      
   

