
   
      
         
            The destruction of Sodome a sermon preached at a publicke fast, before the honourable assembly of the Commons House of Parliament, at St. Margarets Church in Westminster. By Iohn Harris, preacher there. Feb. 18. 1628.
            Harris, John, preacher at St. Margarets Church in Westminster.
         
         
            
               1629
            
         
         Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02674
            STC 12806
            ESTC S103787
            99839532
            99839532
            3963
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02674)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3963)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:10)
         
         
            
               
                  The destruction of Sodome a sermon preached at a publicke fast, before the honourable assembly of the Commons House of Parliament, at St. Margarets Church in Westminster. By Iohn Harris, preacher there. Feb. 18. 1628.
                  Harris, John, preacher at St. Margarets Church in Westminster.
               
               [2], 52, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes] and R. Y[oung] for G. Lathum, dwelling in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Bishops head,
                  London :
                  [1629]
               
               
                  Printers' names from STC.
                  The year is given according to Lady Day dating.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-04
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2005-05
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
DESTRVCTION
OF
SODOME:
A
SERMON PREACHED
at a publicke Fast, before the honourable
Assembly of the Commons
House of Parliament,
At St. MARGARETS Church in
Westminster. By IOHN HARRIS, Preacher there. Feb. 18. 1628.
            LONDON,
Printed by H. L. and R. Y. for G. Lathum,
dwelling in Pauls Church-yard, at the
signe of the Bishops head.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE
DESTRVCTION
Of SODOME.
            
               GEN. 19. 24.
               Then the Lord rained vpon Sodome and Gomorrah
brimstone and fire, from the Lord
out of Heauen.
            
            
               ABout fiue hundred yeares
after Christ, when the
Romans vast Dominion
began to decline, there
was great affliction and
trouble thoroughout the
world; plagues, and famines,
and warres, and
earth-quakes, and other
euils, conspir'd together to vexe all places: so
that the people of God, euery where, both in the
Greeke and Latine Churches, fearing their turne

might be next to come vnder the scourge, had
formes of holy Prayers, composed by their Prelates,
which the Greeke Church termedBasil. ep. 63. Niceph. lib. 14. cap. 3. 
               Litanies,
the Latine Rogations, to be spoken often into
the eares of the Lord of heauen and earth, to
preuent imminent iudgements; so godlily wise
were the Christians of old time, that those calamities,
which they knew, being present, all people
would bewaile with teares, being absent, they
laboured by their prayers to keep away.
            And if I take not my marke amisse, that's the
intention of this meeting:Iob 19. 12. Gods troupes of afflictions,
as holy Iob cals them, are abroad in the Christian
world, making hauocke of men and countries;
and wee, conscious to our selues, that our
sinnes deserue to haue them come, and to encampe
about our tabernacles, are met here together,
to make prayers to our God, to keepe them
away from vs: and to set a greater edge vpon our
deuotion, and the more to testifie our humiliation
to the World, and to Angels; a Fast is proclaimed,
which is to bee obserued by vs in a strict
manner: all the time is to bee spent in confession
of sinnes, in bitter lamentations, in deiection and
humiliation for transgressions, in abstinence from
meates and drinkes, and all other corporall delights,
that may cheare the heart, and so hinder it
from being truely sorrowfull and afflicted, in
almes deedes and visiting the sicke, in mourning
and weeping for angring God, and in crying
mightily vnto the Lord,
               Ionah 3. 8. to diuert iudgements approaching.
            
               
And to helpe to these exercises of repentance,
the Word of God must be preached, the sinnes of
a Nation must bee ript vp, Gods iudgements against
sinne must be denounced, for nothing doth
further more to humiliation and compunction,
than a serious consideration, how infinitely iniquity
doth anger God, and how seuerely he hath,
and doth, and will punish it. It was the course,
which God himselfe directed the Prophet Ieremiah
to runne, when Israel and Iudah were vpon
the point of destruction:Ier. 36. 1, 2, 3. 
               This word came vnto Ieremiah
from the Lord, saying, Take thee a roule of a
booke, and write therein all the words that I haue
spoken vnto thee against Israel, and against Iudah,
and against all the Nations, from the day I spake vnto
thee, from the dayes of king Iosiah, euen vnto this
day: it may be, that the house of Iudah will heare all
the euill which I purpose to doe vnto them, that they
may returne euery man from his euill way, that I may
forgiue their iniquity and their sinne. And in that
roule of the booke, the Rabbins say, was written
the booke of Lamentations:Six. Sen. lib. 2. Bibl. in which booke,
Ieremiah the Prophet, doth in a most mournfull
Elegie, lament the miserable condition, which
Ierusalem, because of sinne, was to come vnto. I
haue resolued to follow that tract, to speake vnto
you of a people, whose damnable impiety
brought vpon them such a misery, the relation
whereof, may make all, that worke vnrighteousnesse
with greedinesse, to tremble to heare it, and
so to abhorre and auoide crying sinnes, lest they
should proue likewise their ruine and confusion.
            
               
Then the Lord rained vpon Sodome and Gomorrah,
brimstone and fire, from the Lord
out of Heauen.
            You may please to obserue in the Text, these
particulars:
            1. An act: It rained.
            
            2. The agent: The Lord rained from the Lord;
Dominus Filius pluit à Domino Patre,
               Carranz. sum. Concil. The Lord the
Sonne rained from the Lord the Father: that interpretation
is giuen of the words, at a Councell
held at Ierusalem in the time of Constantius the
Emperour.
            3. The matter it rained: Brimstone and fire.
The Lord rained from the Lord brimstone and fire.
            4. The place from whence it rained: Out of
Heauen. The Lord rained from the Lord brimstone
and fire out of Heauen:
               Saluian. lib. 1. degub. Dei. 
               Super impium populum Gehennam
misit è Coelo; The Lord from the Lord
sent vpon a wicked people Hell out of Heauen.
            5. The patients vpon whom it rained; vpon
Sodome and Gomorrah in the Text: Vpon Sodome
and Gomorrah, Admah and Zeboim, in Deut. 29. 23.
Vpon Sodome, Gomorrah, Admah, Zeboim and
Segor, in lib. 1. St. Aug. de mirab. Script. Vpon all
the plaine, vpon all the inhabitants of the Cities, vpon
that which grew vpon the ground, in Gen. 19. 25.
            6. The time when it rained; Then: Then the
Lord rained vpon Sodome and Gomorrah brimstone
and fire, from the Lord out of Heauen.
            The time administreth occasion to discourse of
the Agents longanimity, and of the Patients
iniquity.
            
               
The act and the materials, giue way to treate of
Gods seuerity, and of Sodome and Gomorrah's
misery.
            Thus then wee will proceed, Gods grace assisting.
            First, speake of Gods clemency, and of Sodom
and Gomorrah's impiety.
            Secondly, declare Gods fury, and Sodom and
Gomorrah's calamity.
            Thirdly, conclude with an application of such
vses, as may be made by the story.
            First of Gods clemency, and of Sodome and 
Gomorrah's impiety.
            There is not a greater antipathy betwixt any
two natures in the world, than there is betwixt
the nature of God and sinne: You may sooner
reconcile fire and water, heate and cold, light and
darknesse, than God and Mammon, Christ and
Belial, the holy Ghost and Dagon. God hates
sinne wheresoeuer he findes it, be it in Heauen or
Earth, in Men or Angels, in Elect or Reprobates.
Indeed his Mercy, his sweet blessed Mercy, to
which mankinde hath beene euer much bound,
neuer ceaseth solliciting him to treat Adams children
with all the fauour hee may, and like to an
importunate suitor, neuer giueth ouer crauing of
him, vntill he make her a promise, that hee will not
execute the fiercenesse of his anger,
               Hosea 11. 9. otherwise the
world should heare oftner from him than it doth.
Howsoeuer though mercy doth much with God,
yet mercy doth not all, iustice may bee heard: if
the suspension of iudgement worke no remorse

in sinners hearts, to take pitie vpon their owne
soules, and to please God, iustice will procure
that God shall render indignation and wrath,
               Rom. 2. 8, 9. 
               tribulation
and anguish, vpon euery soule of man that
doth euill, to the Iew first, and also to the Gentile.
Misericordia Deo attribuitur secundum effectum,
               Aquin. p. 1. q. 21 3. 0. 
               non
secundum passionis affectum; Mercy is attributed
vnto God according to the effect, not according
to the affect of the passion: it doth neuer transport
him beyond himselfe, neither causeth it him vtterly
to stop his eares to his iustice, when it pleadeth
for indignation. Tis euident in holy Writ,
that Mercy is potent with God, hath a great hand
with him; hee will heare her mediating for the
most notorious malefactors in the world, if hee
can discerne in them any hope of amendment.
            How long did he protract Sodom's ruine, and
what courses did hee take to reclaime them? sent
Lot to preach to them, stirr'd vp foure Kings to
make warre vpon them, gaue them victory ouer
them, and when they had taken the people, and
were carrying of them into captiuity, prest Abraham
out to rescue them,Gen. 14. 15, 16. who diuided himselfe against
them, he and his seruants by night, and smote
them, and pursued them vnto Hoba, which is on the
left hand of Damascus, and he brought backe all the
goods, and also brought againe his brother Lot, and
his goods, and the women also, and the people. Yea,
when their sinnes cryed out for brimstone, flames
&amp; wrath was gone out from God, and he had dispatched
his ministring spirits to goe downe,
               Gen. 18. 21. 
               and see
whether they had done altogether according to the cry

of it which came vp vnto him. Hee protected vnto
Abraham, if hee could finde ten righteous men
there, he would not destroy them for tens sake.
               Gen. 18. 32. Gods
goodnesse towards them, doth surpasse all oratorie
to expresse, all cogitation to thinke; he would
haue spared them vpon any tolerable termes, they
might haue made their peace vpon any indifferent
conditions: God, I say, tooke no delight in
their desolation. At last, when hee saw that no
preaching, no warre, no captiuity, no redemption
from captiuity, could beget any piety among
them, Then the Lord rained vpon Sodome and Gomorrah
brimstone and fire, from the Lord out of
Heauen.
            
            Their sinnes were insufferable; not ordinarie,
but great, very great transgressions: they did
prouoke the iustice of God from the greatest of
them, to the littlest of them, they did euen against
nature and common reason agree to bee wicked,
they were not onely sinners, drawne to iniquitie
by the strong incitations of nature, but they were
wicked, industriously wicked, willingly wicked;
like to the house of Iacob,Micah 2. 2. 
               they deuised iniquity
vpon their beddes, and when the morning was light,
they practis'd it: They were scelerum principes, &amp;
inuentores, prime offendors, and inuentors of
new villanies: they tooke delight in damn'd
transgressions, their greatest glory was in the
greatest iniquity, and they were then most merry,
when the God of Abraham was most angry. I
reade of a people in Picenum, that were called

               Nequi nates; Wicked ones, à soli iniquitate, saith
the Geographer,Bertij tab. Geogra. from the naughtinesse of their
soile: the men of Sodome are call'd wicked ones
from the iniquity of their manners.Gen. 13. 13. 
               The men of
Sodome were 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , wicked and sinners
before the Lord exceedingly. Pride, a sinne, that
made of Angels Diuels, as Prosper saith;Prosp. lib. 3 de vit. cont. cap. 3. a sinne
that is fore-runner to destruction: as Solomon
shewes, Humility goeth before honour, and a haughty
spirit before a fall. A sinne, of which they that are
guilty, haue God alwayes at their backes to take
vengeance of them for it, as Seneca hath it, Sequitur
superbos vltor à tergo Deus, was in high esteem
among them: excessiue they were aboue measure;
a mortall iniquity, Diues epulo, est Parochianus Diabolo:
A rich Epicure, is a Parishioner to the Diuell.
The higher men feede, the more outragious
the bloud boiles, and the harder taske it is to resist
concupiscence.Deut. 32. 15. 
               Iesurun waxed fat and kicked;
thou art waxen fat, thou art growne thicke, thou art
couered with fatnesse; then hee forsooke God which
made him, and lightly esteemed the rocke of his saluation.
Idlenesse likewise, a sinne capitall by the
lawes of Draco;Ecclus. 33. 27. 
               A sin that teacheth much euill: A
sinne that choaketh vertue, nourisheth pride, frameth
a life fit onely for hell fire, a sinne, the
whole vniuersity of things cries downe, abounded
among them: whereas all other creatures
were perpetually in action; trees growing, waters
flowing, birds flying, oxen plowing, spheares
mouing, the men of Sodome, like to standing

ponds, like to Sodomes Salt-pits, stunke for lacke
of motion. The poore they did contemne; a
crying sinne: Negatur gutta, qui negauit micam,
               Aug. A
droppe of water is denied to Diues to coole his
tongue, being in hell in torments, who denied a
crumme from off his table to Lazarus, to allay his
hunger,Luke 16. liuing on earth in pleasures; These were
sinnes which the earth it selfe could no longer
endure: hearken, and I will shew you greater
abominations than these.
            Masculine beastiality; A sinne, none but a Diuell,
come out of Hell in the likenesse of a man,
dares to commit: a sinne, enough to defile the
tongue that talkes of it; a sinne, of which, if a man
were sure neither God nor man did know of it,
yet the turpitude of it should bee motiue enough
to make a reasonable creature disdaine it, was as
allowable among them by custome, as any other
act, in other Common-wealths, is by law: Nay,
Peccabant, &amp; publicabant; They did sinne, and
not for shame hide it,Aug. lib. 16. c. 30. de ciuit. Dei. but with ostentation they
did publish it, tis manifest. Gods rehearsing
Iudahs sinnes, saith, They declare their sinnes as Sodome
did: to doe euill, and to reioyce at it, tis a
desperate iniquity; deplorata nequitia: a lamentable
wickednesse;Caluin. for men to sinne, and to take
pastime in it, to anger the powers of Heauen, and
to ioy in it, to set their soules burning in the
flames of sinne, as Nero set Rome on fire, and to
behold them with affectation, like raging waues
of the sea, for men to some out their owne shame,
good Lord, that euer the children of women

should bee so transcendently wicked: it was impossible
for any but incarnate Diuels to excell
them in wickednesse. Furthermore, there was
publicke liberty of sinning; each man gaue his
consent for the allowance of villany, no man accusing,
or condemning, or correcting, or deploring
the iniquities that were among them: Onely
Lot perswadeth, I pray you, Brethren, doe not so
wickedly,
               Gen. 19. 7. and they frump him for it.Gen. 19. 9. 
               This one fellow
came in to soiourne, and hee will needes bee a Iudge.
There was such a habit of filthinesse, that vnrighteousnesse
was reputed for righteousnesse,
and the gainsayer of vncleannesse, was blamed
more than the actour. Their Magistrates, that
had regall power, neuer interposed their authoritie,
to bridle them in their beastly desires: And
(my beloued) that is a daring sinne, when the Magistrates,
that should bee to the people like gods
to imitate, shall be euery iot as wicked as the multitudes:
Inferiores sunt superiorum simiae,
               Herodot. Inferiours
they are the apes of superiours; whereby
it commeth to passe, that those which are called
to high places in the world, eyther carry many to
destruction with themselues, or bring many into
the way of saluation with themselues, as Fulgentius
saith to Theodorus a Senatour of Rome:Fulgent. ep. 6. ad Theod. Sen. Ecclus. 10. 2. 
               As
the Iudge of a people is himselfe, so are his officers, and
what manner of man the Ruler of a City is, such are
they that dwell therein. Now that the Rulers of
Sodome should be such, as did not only conniue,
winke at wickednesse, but euen tolerate, nay approue,
yea partake with the people in their abominations;

it was ominous, it did portend some
dreadfull iudgement comming vpon the whole
Nation. when the vices of inferiours are dissembled
and winked at by gouernours, they are reserued
for the iudgement of God. I had as liue see
a blazing starre burning in the Heauens, as a wicked
man in a place of power: an earth-quake is
not so prodigious as a wicked Ruler. Before God
broke downe the wals of Babylon, and burnt the
high gates with fire,Ier. 51. 57. hee threatned to make drunke
her Princes, and her Wisemen, and her Captaines, and
her Rulers, and her mighty men: An inundation of
vngodlinesse must needes ouerflow a Land, when
those that haue the ouersight, doe superintend,
and should bound wickednesse, are themselues
boundlesly wicked. Religion must of necessity go
downe the wind, as it did in Sodome, when those
that should vphold it, doe most prophane it; one
of the first in authority, and one of the last in
Christianity. Ethelbertus King of Kent in the
Heptarchy was wont to say, twas a signe of a very
euill man, singulus quis
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   homo, &amp;c. Euery particular
man is a part of the City and Kingdome
wherein he was borne,Aug. de ciuit Dei. lib. 4. cap▪
                be it neuer so ample; as a
letter is part of a word, saith Augustine. Some
bee like to capitall or text letters, as great men:
some to smaller characters, as men of low degree:
some be like to vowels, as men in authority: some
to mutes and liquids, as the vulgar sort: all men
goe to the making of a City or Kingdome, as all
letters go to the making vp of words. And as in a
word, if one letter be amisse, though but a mute,

it may danger to marre the word, though not so
much as if a vowell bee defaced; so in a City or
Kingdome, if one man be blotted with sinne, say
but a meane man, it may bring a destruction to
that City or Kingdome, yet not so soone as if a
man of higher place be blurd with impiety.
            Here were sins enow to set patience in a rage,
and to transforme the God of mercy into wrath,
and yet God respited their subuersion so long,
vntill their sins came bellowing vp into Heauen,
and were ready to lay an imputation of partiality
vpon his iustice. Three hundred and forty
yeares, Chronologie saith, passed betwixt the
drowning of the world with water, and the burning
of Sodome with brimstone and fire, all, or a
great part of which time, God was grieued with
that generation; and if euer they would haue bethought
themselues to alter their conditions, had
there beene but a sprinkling, a gleaning of good
people in her, one honest soule for a thousand reprobates,
God would haue repented him of his
purpose: at last, when the Lord looked, nay sent
downe from Heauen, saw there was no hope, they
were altogether corrupt, and become abominable
in their doings, there were none that did
good, no not Ten, Then the Lord rained upon Sodom
and Gomorrah brimstone and fire, from the Lord, ut
of Heauen.
            
            Tis recorded of Iulius Caesar, that hee neuer
entertained hatred against any man so deeply, but
he was willing to lay downe the same vpon occasion
offered;Sueton. vita Iul. Caes. and the author doth instance in this,

when C. Memnius put-in for the Consulship, hee
befriended him before others of the Competition,
notwithstanding that C. Memnius had made
bitter inuectiues against him. Our God, to whom
all the Caesars &amp; Kings of the earth are tributaries
and homagers, doth neuer hate (I take hatred as
tis an intention of God in punishing) so irreconcileably,
but true humiliation will worke a reconciliation;
that maketh him say, Patientia Dei pios
turbat; Gods patience doth euen distract good
men, maketh them to wonder at him, how hee
can indure such palpable dishonour, and suspend
vengeance: When Dauid saw the prosperity of
the wicked, hee saith, his feet were almost gone, his
steps had well nigh stipt. And when God, because
the Niniuites had turned from thier euill waies,
repented of the euill which he said he would doe
vnto them, and did it not, it displeased Ionah exceedingly,
               Ionah 4. 1.
               and hee was very angry. Hee hath suffered
likewise among wicked men for his clemency,
the damned Atheist draweth an argument from
thence against his omnipotency; saith he cannot,
because hee doth not banish all euill out of the
world. Auerroes the Philosopher, draweth an
argument from thence against his prouidence;
thinkes hee meddleth with nothing below the
spheare of the Moone, because of his slownesse to
anger. Ceacilius in Munitius Faelix, inferres a
conclusion from thence against his iustice: saith
that he is eyther inualidus,
               Munit. impotent, and not able
to redresse euils, or else iniquus, vniust, and not
willing to rectifie them.Psal. 21, 3
                     •
                  
                  ▪
                
               He doth preuent a man

with the blessing of goodnesse.
               Lam. 3. 23. 
               He renueth his kindnesse
euery morning. He must be called vpon once,
twice, thrice, to render vengeance: Lord, how
long shall the wicked;
               Psal. 94. 3, 4. 
               how long shall the wicked triumph;
how long shall they vtter and speake hard
things? I dare say by a 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Dolet quoties cogitur
esse ferox; Tis a griefe to our God, so often as
men constraine him, to bee cruell.Iudg 10. 16. 
               His soule is
grieued for the misery of Israel; HisIerem. 31. 20 
               bowels are
troubled for Ephraims sake. The rainbow is an
embleme of Gods mercy; tis planted in the
clouds, if you marke it, as if man were shooting at
God, and not as if God were shooting at man.
The situation of the Propitiatory, or Mercy-seat,
was an argument of his mercy:Exod. 25. 21. God commanded
it should be planted ouer the Arke, in which
was the testimony, the booke of cursings, that
so mercy might bee neare at hand to pronounce
sentence of absolution, when iustice is in hand to
denounce sentence of condemnation.Ambr. Epist. lib. 1. ep. 3. 
               Of such
infinite compassion was our Lord and Sauiour Christ
Iesus, that he would haue pardoned Iudas, it Iudas had
had grace to haue askt forgiuenesse. AugustineAug. lib. 13. cap. 7. de ciuit. Dei. saith,
that some of them were forgiuen, that murdered
Christ. In the 34. of Exodus, where himselfe
proclaimeth his nature by adiectiues, hee begins
with mercifull,Exod. 34. 6. 
               The Lord, the Lord God, mercifull,
&amp;c. as if mercy had a priority in him. In the 116.
Psalme, Verse 5. he doubles the epithite mercifull,
Mercifull is the Lord, and righteous; yea, and our God
is mercifull: as if he had two quantities of mercy
in him for one of iustice; as if no act of iustice

could passe from him, but thorow the gate of
mercy. Longanimity is as Gods naturall childe;
the holy Deity is in trauell with it: euen as any
thing great with young doth desire to bee rid of
the burthen, so doth God desire to poure forth
his mercy: neuer Nurse, when her breasts were
full of milke, was in greater paine for children to
sucke them, than God is in paine to haue children
to draw his mercy from him. Iustice commeth
from God, as a sting from a Bee, constrainedly;
Mercy floweth from him, as honey from a Bee,
most willingly: Mercy is as essentiall to him, as
light is to the sunne, or as heate is to the fire; hee
delights in mercy, as any sense or faculty of our
soules doe in their actions, the eye in seeing, or
the eare in hearing, or the memory in remembring:
Patience, and clemency, and mercy, and
compassion, and peace, are the fruits of his bowels,
the off-spring which the diuine nature doth
produce; fury, and rage, and anger, and affliction,
and warre, and flaming fire, are forced into him
by the prouoking exorbitances of the world.
            God doth all along the Scripture euen court
sinners to turne from their vicious courses; the
omnipotent Creatour doth euen turne begger, to
beseech his creatures to walke in his wayes; not
that tis any aduantage to him, if all the world
should worship him with a holy worship: Can a
man be profitable to God, as he that is wise is profitable
to himselfe? Is it any pleasure to the Almighty, that
thou art righteous, or is it gaine to him,
               Iob 22. 2. 3. 
               that thou
makest thy wayes perfect? saith Eliphaz the Temanite

to holy Iob. Our goodnesse extendeth not
to him; Non eget ipsâ iustitiâ hominis: He hath no
need,Aug. lib. 10. cap. 5. de ciuit. Dei. no not of mans righteousnesse. Ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   fonti se
quisquam dixerit profuisse si biberit, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   luci si viderit;
A man cannot say he doth the fountain good
by drinking of it, or the light by seeing by it, nor
that he doth God good by seruing of him; all the
worship man performes to God, is for mans profit,
not Gods: wherefore a man duely pondering
of that 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , that long suffering which is in
God, that beareth with many millions of misdemeanours
mortall men commit, whereby hee is
infinitely dishonoured, and of that free loue that
doth prouoke him to desire mans loue, whereby
he is in no respect benefited; if hee be not reprobate
siluer, if hee haue any reliques of Religion
left in him, how can it choose but inflame his
soule to loue the Almighty? Many a great dishonour
did God put vp before hee drowned the old
world; 1500. years and odde he patiently waited
they should amend their manners, before hee began
to affright them with any mention of a floud,
yea and after hee had threatned a deluge, hee gaue
them 120. yeares respit to change their courses,
afforded them all that time Noah to preach righteousnesse
vnto them: After all this, when the
1500. yeares were ended, and the 120. were exspired,
when the Arke was builded, and Noah
and his family were aboard in her, yet hee prolong'd
the time seuen dayes before he broke open
the fountaines of the great deepe,Gen. 7. 4. and opened the
floud-gates of Heauen. And so for the Sodomites,

               Ipsi extorserunt vt perirent; They themselues
wrested from God their owne destruction:Saluian.
their iniquities, like rebels, make a head, as if they
would bid Heauen a battell, and dare God and
his Angels to doe their worst; and God for many
yeares carried himselfe patiently: at last when no
forbearance could beget repentance, no procrastination
of their affliction in him, could procure
an alteration of manners in them, Then the Lord
rained vpon Sodome and Gomorrah brimstone and
fire, from the Lord out of Heauen.
            
            Or you may, if you please, let this (Then) in
my Text, answer to the (When) in the Verse next
before it, When Lot was entered into Zoar, Then
the Lord rained vpon Sodome and Gomorrah brimstone
and fire, from the Lord out of Heauen. And
from thence you may make an obseruation, how
deare in the sight of the Lord a righteous man is:
Sodome could not bee burnt before Lot was departed;
Haste thee, escape to Zoar: for I cannot doe
any thing till thou be come thither,
               Gen. 19. 22. saith the Angell
to Lot; the Angell had giuen him in commission
to be as prouident in Lots preseruation, as to bee
diligent in the Sodomites destruction: Haste thee,
escape thither: for I cannot doe any thing till thou
come thither. A speech, the more I meditate vpon
it, the more I am amazed at it. St. Augustine saith,
a certain Platonist, as Simplitianus told him, said
those words of St. Iohns Gospell: In the beginning
was the word, and the word was with God,
               Iohn 1. 1. 
               and the
word was God, the same was in the beginning with
God, were fit to be written in letters of gold,Aug. lib. 10. 
                     〈◊〉
                   ciuit. Dei. c. and to

be set vp to be read in the highest places of all
Churches; and the reason of this his high commendation
of that saying, is, because tis such a
strong text to confirme Christs diuinity: For, as
Ambrose well noteth,Ambr. de fide cont. Arrian. 
               erat, erat, erat, erat: ecce
quater erat; &amp; vbi inuenit Arrianus quod non erat?
the word was, it was, it was, it was: behold, St.
Iohn saith foure times it was in the beginning,
and where doth Arrius finde that it was not in
the beginning? Verily, this Scripture, Haste thee, escape
thither: for I can do nothing til thou be come thither,
deserueth to be inscribed vpon euery mans
heart, that God should so tender the welfare of
his seruant, as to professe plainly, hee could not
vindicate himselfe vpon his foes, vntill hee had
taken order for his safety: I am rapt to reade it, &amp;
pray you all to take speciall notice of it; When Lot
was entered into Zoar, Then, and not before then,
the Lord rained vpon Sodome and vpon Gomorrah,
brimstone and fire, from the Lord out of Heauen. And
to say continually as the Psalmist doth, Blessed is
the Lord,
               Psal. 35. 27. 
               which hath alwaies pleasure in the prosperity
of his seruant.
            
            Wicked men may likewise make to themselues
aduantage by this obseruation, and learne to respect
the righteous, because they fare the better
for it.Varro. 
               Mundus est magna homilli domus; The world
is the great house of little man, and faithfull men
are the buttresses and pillars, to vphold it from
ruine and confusion: they stand in the gappe betwixt
the world and Gods wrath, as Moses his
chosen did in the breach betwixt the Israelites

and Gods anger, when they had vext him at the
waters of strife, to turne away his indignation
from them,Psal. 106. 23. lest hee should destroy them. The
Nurse fareth the better oftentimes for the Childs
sake, and so doe the wicked for the children of
Gods sake: Abraham could haue compounded
with God for tenne righteous men for Sodomes
sinnes, and so haue saued the place and the inhabitants
from destruction. Yea Ierusalem, iam
iam
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   peritura,
               Hieron. euen now vpon the push of being
destroyed, is offered to Ieremiah to be spared, if
there could but a man bee found in it that executed
righteousnesse.
               Ierem. 5. 1. At such a high rate doth God value
one righteous man, that his holinesse shall ballance
many a thousands wickednesse. Good men
are sanguis mundi, the bloud of the world: when
they dye, a man may feare the very world lyeth
adying. When Eliah the Prophet was taken from
the head of his seruant Elisha, and carried vp into
Heauen, Elisha cryed out, My father, my father, the
chariot of Israel,
               2. Reg. 2. 12 
               and the horsemen thereof: As if he
should haue said, Eliah that good man, that was
the onely chariot and horsemen to defend Israel,
he had such power with God, because of his holy
life to hinder him from plaguing of it, is taken
from it. If God goe out against a place to ouerthrow
it, one iust man is a better fort to defend it,
than a rocke of marble, or a rampier of flint: A
good man hath a great deale of interest in God;
God will come to a parley with him, and yeeld
to him in any tolerable request: that speech which
God vsed to Moses on the Mount, is proofe sufficient

to informe wicked men, how gracious a
good man is with the great God. Israel had trespassed
greatly, turned the glory of the inuisible
God, into the similitude of an Oxe that eateth
grasse, and by that Idolatry angred Iehouah so
farre, that hee hath a thought to confound them;
and yet before hee will proceed to execution,
knowing Moses loue to them was such, he would
be making intercession, and knowing his owne
nature to bee such, that if Moses mediated, hee
could not choose but remit, the omnipotent God
doth petition fraile man not to interpose; Now
therefore let mee alone,
               Exod. 32. 10. 
               that my wrath may waxe hote
against them, and that I may consume them. And
when Moses would not bee perswaded from making
supplication, but fals vpon God for Abrahams
sake to take compassion, God offereth Moses
composition to let him alone: Let mee alone,
               Exod. 32. 10.
               that my wrath may waxe hote against them, and that
I may consume them, and I will make of thee a great
people: When nothing would beat Moses off from
being instant and earnest with God for their pardon,
the Text saith,Exod. 32. 
               The Lord repented of the euill
which he thought to do vnto the people: An example
that may moue a heart composed of hatred against
Gods chosen, and turne it into loue. Nay,
an after generation fareth the better oftentimes
for a good man of a former generation; it was
aboue too. yeares by computation, betwixt the
reigne of King Dauid and King Ioram, and yet
though the impieties of Ioram deserued to haue
his Kingdome rent away from him, The Lord

would not destroy Iudah for Dauid his seruants sake.2. Reg. 8. 19.
Two hundred seuenty and sixe men had their liues▪
               Acts 27.
saued for St. Pauls sake from shipwracke: God gaue
him all that sailed with him,
               Verse 24. as the Angell said.
Small reason therefore haue dissolute wretches
to contemne good people, if they consider it: It
was a base vnworthy speech of Haman, when hee
told King Ahashuerosh,Hest. 3. 8. 
               It was not for his profit to
suffer the Iewes; Himselfe and his kingdome fared
the better for such inhabitants. Make much of
honest men, my Beloued; make much of honest
men: they are medulla mundi, to the world as marrow
is to the bones, the strength and stay of it.
Thetares would quickly be weeded vp, were it
not for plucking vp the good corne also. So long
as there are good men, possibly the world may
endure: when once there is a generall dearth of
good men, adue this present world for euermore.
No maruaile Laban was so loath to part with Iacob,
and would come to a new composition with
him, rather than he should quit his seruice; he had
learnt by experience,Gen. 30. 27. 
               that the Lord had blessed him
for Iacobs sake. Dauid cries out in the 12. Psalme,
Helpe Lord:
               Psal. 12. 1. And why? what is the matter with
Dauid? O the godly man ceaseth, the faithfull faile
from among the children of men: And is that such a
matter to bee transported at? Yes, it is a fatall
signe,Esay 1. 9. when there is a decrease of good men; Except
the Lord of Hosts had left vnto vs a seed, wee
should haue been as Sodome, and we should haue been
like vnto Gomorrah.
            
            
               The Dragon that is wroth with the woman,
               Apoc. 12. 17 
               maketh

warre with the remnant of her seed; that is,
the Diuell who is wroth with the Church, in all
ages hath plotted the ruines of those which keepe
the commandements of God, and haue the testimony
of Iesus Christ, and infused a strong conceit
in the hearts of all his subiects, that they were
the causes of all calamities. If Tiber ouerflowed
her bankes, if Nilus did not water the fields, if
the heauens were brasse, or the earth quaked, if
there were a plague or famine in the Common-wealth
of Rome,Tert. Apol. the people cried, To the Lyon
with a Christian; as if their being had beene the
cause of all miseries. St. Augustine saith it grew
to a Prouerbe in Rome,Aug. de ciuit. Dei. lib. 2. cap. 3. 
               Pluuia defecit, Christiani
nominis gratiâ, Raine hath failed, because the
name Christian is tolerated. Alas, blinde Heathen,
were it not for Christianity, there would
soone bee an end of Infidelity: God blesseth the
Egyptians house for Iosephs sake, not Ioseph for
the Egyptians sake. God blest Sodome for Lots
sake, not Lot for Sodomes sake, tis euident here
in this Text: for while Lot remained within her
wals, it went well with her; when Lot was gone
out of her, Then the Lord rained vpon Sodome and
Gomorrah brimstone and fire, from the Lord out of
Heauen. The same day that Lot went out of Sodome,
it rained fire and brimstone from Heauen, and destroyed
them all: he that rained it beares record of it,
Luke 17. 29. And we know that his record is true.
            
                Secondly, of Gods fury, and of Sodome and
Gomorrahs misery.
            
               
God is no way so long suffering in bearing, that
he is not as iust in punishing; If a man will not
turne, he will whet his sword. God spun out the
thread of his loue to an immeasurable length, to
try whether the men of Sodome would lay hold
of it; hee did angle for them, sate in heauen, let
downe the line of his loue, and baited it with his
mercy, to proue whether the men of Sodome
would swallow it, that hee might catch their
soules. Twas long before he was prouoked, he did
smother indignation many yeares, before it
kindled and came to bee deuouring flame; and
when all would not preuaile, Then the Lord rained
vpon Sodome and Gomorrah brimstone and fire, from
the Lord out of Heauen.
            
            Here, my Beloued, I will giue you another obseruation:
As God is infinite in suffering, vrged,
thoroughly vrged, before he will breake out into
fury, so hee is violent and fierce in the execution
of his iudgement, when hee is resolued vpon it:
The longer the archer drawes before hee looses,
the sorer shot hee maketh; the longer God is before
he poureth forth his vengeance, the more
twill scorch. I need not search other Chronicles
for examples to verifie this collection, Sodome
and Gomorrah ratifie the truth of it. Strabo saith,
nature wrought this act,Strabo. Geog. lib. 16. and that the fire issued
out of the earth which consumed these cities; but
Strabo vnderstood not the Scriptures, nor the
power of God; he is but a prophane author, and
we are not to credit his report: Wee haue Moses
and the Prophets, and we must heare them; and

they say The Lord rained vpon Sodome and Gomorrah
brimstone and fire, from the Lord out of Heauen.
Fearfull raine.Tert. de Pallio. Tertullian saith, that the City called
Vid. Plin. lib. 2. cap. 52. 
               Vulsinium in Italy, was destroyed with fire
from heauen. Histories say, that in the yeare of
our Lord 717. when the Arabians and Saracens
lay at the siege of Constantinople,Basil. Menol. Bedae. fiery haile fell
from heauen and burnt their Nauie. In Exodus
9. 24. It rained haile,
               Exod. 9. 24. 
               and fire mingled with the
haile, very grieuous, such as there was none like it in
all the land of Egypt, since it became a Nation. Here
it rained brimstone, and fire mingled with the
brimstone, very grieuous, such as there was none
in all the world, since it was a world. From
whence came it? from the Lord out of heauen. Indeed
the Philosophers say there is an element of
fire aboue;Arist. lib. 4. de coel. c. 5. and though the elementary fire bee of
its owne nature vncapable to moue downward,
vnlesse it be forced, as also vncapable of voracity,
vnlesse a consuming faculty be supernaturally added
to it, yet wee know God can, and it may be
at this time did indue that simple fire with those
qualities, to make the miracle the greater. Iobs
cattell and his seruants were burnt with fire from
Heauen,
               Iob 1. 16. 
               the fire of God. So likewise fire came
downe from heauen at Eliah's call, and burnt the
two Captaines and their fifties.
               2. Reg. 1. But there are no
veines of brimstone aloft; what though? it may
be, God borrowed brimstone of the earth; it may
be he did command the Sunne to exhale vp some
to intermingle with his potion, which he administred
to diseased Sodome; it may be he turned

ayre into brimstone,Iohn 2. as hee did water into wine.
Whatsoeuer fire it was, simple or compound, and
wheresoeuer he had the brimstone, it matters not
much to dispute, sure I am it was the Lords doing,
raine it he did, and though it be maruellous
in our eyes, because supernaturall, the Heauens
not vsing to poure downe brimstone drops, yet
to him it was no more difficult to say to the brimstone,
Burne thou Sodome,Iob 37. 6. than to say to the
snow, Be thou vpon the earth.
            
            Alas, what became of the inhabitants? What
became of them? naught became of them; they
were all euery mothers childe fried in brimstone
flames: a terrible iudgement; take it into your
consideration, and wonder at it. The same morning
the sunne did arise in his wonted manner,
deckt all the plaine of Iordan with his glorious
raies, and before it was climb'd vp to the meridian,
tota rogus, regio est; Sodome is all in a flame,Tert. Sodom
                     •
                  .
her citizens bee all in a fire, her soile is poyson'd
with sulphur, her vines and oliue trees bee blasted
with filthy fume, the earth yawn'd and denounced
the ruines of the buildings, that were not of
combustible matter, together with the ashes of
the inhabitants: those that whilere did boile in
lust, doe now boile with fire, God meeteth their
strange lust with strange fire, quencheth the heate
of their concupiscence with the heate of brimstone,
fils their swallowes, that were accustomed
to bee fill'd with sauorie meates, with stifling
smoke, consumeth all, their bodies, their goods,
their cattell, yea their whole territory with a

shoure of fire from heauen. Infamem vitam famosa
poena consumit,
               Aug. lib. 1. de mirab. Script. A famous punishment finisheth
an infamous life. Some were smitten with blindnesse,
and rather run into, than from the scorching
flames: Others no sooner cry Fire, fire, but
their tongues burne with fire to stop their clamour:
A third scuds out of the City, and a sheete
of fire, like to a swift Herauld, maketh after him,
arrests him, and executeth the will of God vpon
him: Some leape into the water, hoping thereby
to be rescued from the fire, because of the naturall
contrariety that is betwixt those two elements;
and, as in the Egyptian plagues, I shall now tell
you a wonder, fire and water were made friends
together for that day: the fire had power in the
water,
               Wisd. 19. 20. 
               forgetting his owne vertue, and the water forgot
her owne quenching nature. In one streete the
hote tiles spring from off the flaming roofes,
braining those that passed vnder; in another lane
the scalding lead drops downe out of the gutters,
and lights vpon the hairy scalph of such as had
gone on in their wickednesse: Here is a hideous
noise heard with the downefals of houses, there
is a piteous cry to be heard, made by people sorely
tormented in that flame. The heauens thunder
fearfully, the lightning flasheth dismally, the
brimstone burnes inquenchably, the people
shreek vniuersally, the cattell bellow miserably,
God is angry terribly, because they had sinn'd
abominably. The flakes of fire,Iudges 15. like Sampsons
foxes with fire-brands at their tailes in the fields
of Philistia, scoure thorough the fields of Sodom

and Gomorrah, and the adiacent Cities, and
burne vp the standing corne, with the vineyards
and oliues. For all this Gods anger is not turned away,
               Esay 5. 25.
               but his hand is stretched out still.
            
            As Christ cursed the fig-tree, and said,Matth. 21. 19. Let no
fruit grow on thee henceforward for euer, so
God cursed the land of Sodome, and said, Let neuer
inhabitant dwell in thee more henceforward
for euer; the children were burnt with their parents,
that not a remnant of the bloud of Sodomites
might remaine. Iosephus writes, that all
that huge Army which Pharaoh led forth against
the Israelites, consisting of 50000. horsemen,
and 200000. footmen, was so vtterly defeated,
that there was not one left aliue to carry home
newes of the ouerthrow: and the Psalmist iustifieth
it, The waters couered their enemies, there was
not one of them left. A fearfull destruction,Psal. 106. 11. that
not one should be able to come off, of such a multitude,
yet twas not like this of Sodomes; though
they lost many of their people, yet there were
more Egyptians left behinde, Proletarij, to increase
and multiply; here was an vtter extirpation,
an euerlasting extinction of the whole race of
Sodomites: The nurse burnt with the childe at
her breast, the mother melted with her babe in
her belly, the father fryed with his posterity in
his loynes, young men were dissolued to ashes,
young maidens were consumed to cinders; and
not one only of a sort, but all of euery sort, all
that gaue sucke, all that were great with childe, all
that had beene, that were, or might be fit for procreation,

of both sexes, male and female, of all
ages, young and old,Amb. lib. 2 de vocat. gen
                     •
                  . c. 4. dyed in that dreadfull fire;
Quos vna impietas prophanauit, vna sententia deleuit.
So saith St. Ambrose of those that perished
by the floud, and so say I of those that perished by
this fire: For all this Gods anger is not turned away,
but his hand is stretched out still.
            
            God hath cursed the very climate, made it inhabitable,
hath so altered the condition of the
ground, that forreiners if they would aduenture
to plant colonies there, cannot by any industry
manure it so that it shall beare fruit. It hath Babylons
curse; It shall be no more inhabited for euer,
               Ier. 50. 39. 40.
               neyther shall it bee dwelt in from generation to generation;
no man shall abide there, neyther shall any son
of man dwell therein: Once it was the choisest seat
vnder the sunne, the very Paradise of the world,
holding resemblance with the garden of the Lord;
corne,Gen. 13. 10. and wine, and oile, did increase there so
abundantly; it was so fertile a soile, that people
beleeued it to be Gods peculiar habitation. Martin
Luther saith, that cruell raine hath made it so
barren, that the ground hath lost her foyson, it
cannot be till'd, the plowers cannot teare it vp into
furrowes, to harrow-in any kinde of graine.
God cursed the earth because Adam transgressed,Gen. 3. 18.
yet not so, but that it should bring forth thornes
and thistles: I cannot reade that eyther thorne or
thistle will grow on Sodomes soile; tis onely a
breeding place of nettles and salt-pits. God said,Zeph. 2▪ 9. he
would lay Babylon in that desolate taking; that
none but dolefull creatures should possesse it; as

Owles, Dragons, Satyrs: I cannot heare that eyther
Owle, or Dragon, or Satyr will dwell where
Sodome was; though the wildernesse of Arabia
border vpon it, and could spare plenty of such
creatures to people it, if they did not disdaine to
make their nests in it. Ierusalem for crucifying the
Lord of glory, was razed in that fashion by Titus
the Emperour, that those which came afterward
to see, could hardly be perswaded to beleeue that
there euer had been such a City as Ierusalem, Yet
Sion is become a plowed field. Troy,Ier. 26. 18. for the periury
of Laomedon, and for the adultery of Paris, was
burnt to dust and ashes; one Fimbria the day after,
to be sure Troy should not want desolation, went
ouer all the ruines, prying and searching where
any thing was standing, to raze that downe also,
yet iam▪ seges est vbi Troiae fuit,
               Ouid. epist. now grasse doth
grow▪ where the City of Troy was. The Land of
Sodome is like salt that hath lost his sauour, good
for nothing; neither will a fowle flye in her ayre,
nor a fruit ripen in her vallies, nor a fish spawne
in her riuer: A poole of water there is, rightly
call'd mare mortuum, the dead sea; because
Nequit proferre aliquam de gurgite gentem
squamigeram.Tert. Sodoma.
               
               It cannot bring forth out of the deepe gulfe
any of the scaly people.
Diuers Authors giue this sea diuers names; some
call it mare maledictum, the cursed sea: some mare
solitudinis, the desert sea: some mare Diaboli, the
Diuels sea. Philo the Iew saith it smokes still; and
therefore some say tis caminus gehennae, the very

chimney of hell. Yet here is not all: For all this
Gods anger is not turnd away form them, but his hand
is stretched out still. All this is but the beginning of
their sorrowes, there is a worser doome behinde
for these sensuall men: Whats that? fire and
brimstone againe. What brimstone? that streame
of brimstone the Prophet speaketh of,Esay 30. 33. that euerlasting
fire,
               Matth. 25. 41. such as is prepared for the diuell and his angels.
What, fire and brimstone here, and fire and
brimstone hereafter, fire and brimstone in infinitum,
doth it stand with diuine Iustice? I confesse,
calamities poured downe vpon good people, are
the earnest of an euerlasting inheritance; good
people,Psal. 126. 5. if they sow in teares, shall reape in ioy; but
the iudgements which the wrath of God raines
downe in this life vpon the wicked, such as the
Sodomites were, are but the preambles to future
woes; but entrances into, not exemptions from
ensuing miseries: Great plagues remaine for the
vngodly. Tis said,Psal. 32. 10. 
               that the heauie night which was
spread ouer the Egyptians, was but an image of that
darknesse which should afterward receiue them: And
I may say,Wisd. 17. 21. the fire and brimstone which fell vpon
the Sodomites in this life, was but a figure of that
fire and brimstone which shall feed vpon them in
the life to come. God, by the holy Prophet Nahum,Nahum 1. 9.
threatens his enemies to bring vpon them so
much tribulation, that affliction should not rise vp
the second time: There should be no need of a new
plague, he would pay them home at once. From
whence Pelagius concludes, God will not punish
sinners twice. Ah Pelagius, if they be such sinners

as the Apostle St. Paul speaketh of, that doe
not like to retaine God in their knowledge,
               Rom. 1. 28. as the Sodomites
were, tis not the vtter ruinating of their
dwelling places, and the rooting out of them and
their posterity from the earth, will acquit them
and satisfie Gods iustice; a worser doome is behinde,
infinite extremity, deuouring fire, euerlasting
burnings; the Sodomites suffer the vengeance
of eternall fire: and the reason is,Epist. Iud. ver. 7 wicked men, if
it were in their power, would liue without end,
that they might sinne without end; and therefore
tis agreeable to Gods iustice, that their soules
should neuer want woe in the next world, that by
their good will would neuer want wickednesse in
this. Let no man flatter himselfe in his owne
heart, because tis said,Psal. 103. 9. 
               God will not alwaies chide,
neyther will he keepe his anger for euer. Let no man
reason, Man sin'd but a time, and God will punish
him but for a time; rather let him know, hee that
sins against an infinite Maiesty, must expect to endure
infinite misery, if it be not preuented by infinite
mercy: Hee that neglects ineffable goodnesse,
must looke to bee exposed to ineffable fadnesse.
Man by sinne destroyed that good, which
if he had kept, would haue made him eternally
blessed; and loued that euill, which not repented
of, will make him eternally cursed, if it be imputed
to him, and not satisfied for by the bloud of
Christ. God doth not measure sinne temporis longitudine,
by the quantity of time in which it is
committed, nor proportion the punishment after
that rate; then a beastly Sodomite should haue

but a few minuts torment: he doth iudge of sinne
as Augustine saith,Aug. lib. 21. c. 11 de ciuit. Dei. 
               iniquitatis magnitudine, by the
greatnesse of the iniquity, and correspondent to
that allots the plague.
            Then are the Sodomites vtterly vnhappy;
first, to be turned to destruction; and then to bee
turned into hell: Who can help it? the Holy One
of Israel is not to be sleighted, is not to be neglected.
My heart danceth for ioy to muse vpon the
depth of his mercie, yet had wee best to be aduised
that wee abuse it not by presumption; hee is
not a God of wood, nor of stone, insensible of
dishonour, or carelesse of par
                  •
               ipension; if hee be
long prouoked, hee will at last awake like a gyant
out of sleepe, and teare those in his wrath, that
feare not the Lord and his strength: A wretched
people they were, the Sodomites were, to liue so
as to deserue to haue their country and their kinred
ruined so irreparably; yet more wretched, to
liue so as to deserue to haue their bodies and
soules damned eternally. Tis lamentable to
thinke of their iudgement past, tis more lamentable
to thinke of their iudgement to come: though
their bodies are consumed vnto dust, as small as
that which the whirlewinde scatters, yet God
will collect together all parts of euery one of
them (for tis as easie to him to raise a dead man
out of his graue, as tis for one of vs to raise a liuing
man out of his bedde) and when hee hath so
done, he will touch their flesh with such a touch
of immortality, that they shall fry in flames, bee
sensible of the paine, and yet not bee consumed

with the fire, as they were when they were Citizens
of Sodome, before that their mortall had
put on immortality; and as the moth is to the
garment, and the worme is to the wood, so sorrow
shall eate their hearts: poena sensus, &amp; poena
d
                     •
                  mni, the consideration of that which they shall
suffer, intermixt with the consideration of what
they are bereft of, will crucifie their soules with
vnspeakable woe.
            But, saith one to mee, omit the eternall iudgement,
and presse the temporall: for carnall men
will quake more to heare of the losse of their bodies
and estates, than of their soules. I can make
no farther illustration of it than this: There were
sundry goodly Cities, of which Sodome was the
Metropolis, fairely situated in a champian in the
plaine of Iordan, plentifully peopled with men,
women, and children, delicately prouided for, of
corne, and wine, and oyle, and all other necessaries
that might any way conduce to earthly content,
as it might be this morning, and on the same
day before noone, the soile was cursed with barrennesse,
the beasts suffered for their masters
transgressions, the people perished euery one, that
there might bee an end of the race of Sodomites;
The Lord from the Lord, God the Son from God
the Father being the agent of this astonishing
act, fire and brimstone being his instruments, crying
sinnes the incitements, and the reason Saint
Peter giueth, God turned the Cities of Sodome and
Gomorrah into ashes,
               2. Pet. 2. 6. 
               condemned them with an ouerthrow,
making them an ensample vnto those which

after should liue vngodly: and that Scripture brings
mee to my Application.
            I neede not search into the manners of other
Nations, nor lay my seene abroad to make application
of my discourse, it holds at home in many
things, and in some things better than I would it
did; we can vie blessings with Sodome, heauenly
and earthly blessings with Gomorrah, the blessing
of peace, the blessing of plenty, the blessing
of Gods Word that inestimable blessing, and wee
may tell sinnes with them too, and I feare ouertell
them: If I had a Catalogue of the number of
Sodomes sinnes, and a relation of their will and
greedinesse to commit them, and were tasked to
compare ours with theirs, I beleeue for quantity
and manner, wee are neare euen with them: Indeed,
Peccatum nefandum, that sin not fit to be named,
the high hand of God hath kept out of our
Countrey, and euer may it remaine a stranger, otherwise
I cannot set my thoughts to worke, to
muse of any sinne that I doe not finde acted in abominable
manner: Adultery is in the height,
hardly more ordinary in any land; doe not men
lay wait at their neighbours doores?
               Iob 31. 9. and do not women
sit blowzing in their windowes, looking for
their paramours,Iudg 5. 28. as the mother of Sisera did for
her sonne? Pride neuer rode in that state in the
streets of Sodome when it went abroad, nor was
bedeckt in that gorgeous fashion when it staid at
home. Idlenesse like to a pernicious tetter hath
ouerrun the land; there are among vs and abundance

of such people as those Thessalonians
were which the Apostle increpates, that walke inordinately,
working not at all: Of men many,2. Thes. 3. 11. of
women not a few, besides those sun-burnt vagabonds
that lye basking vnder hedges, and yawling
in high wayes, trusting charity with their
liues, rather than labour; which oftentimes failing
them, of beggers they become felons, and
so end their dayes oftentimes cursedly vpon a
tree; the iust iudgement of God vpon them for
their inordinate walking. How many men borne
of gentle bloud, and bred vp at the feet of Gamaliel
in the schooles of the Prophets and Seminaries
of learning, of pregnant capacities, and able
bodies, liue out of all honest vocations, sacrifice
all their time eyther to Morpheus the minister of
sleep, or to Bacchus the god of wine, or to Venus
the goddesse of beauty, as if neither the true God,
nor the Common-wealth deserued any time to
be spent in their seruice, all were due to the bed,
the tauerne, and the brothel-house?
            
               Edebant &amp; bibebant,
               Luke 17. 28. The men of Sodome did
eate and drinke, saith our Sauiour; Ecce peccatum
voluptatis, Behold the sinne of voluptuousnesse:
Take notice of the garbs of men of present times,
and trust mee not if you doe not see Sodome equalled,
if not outstript in gluttony: Could the
Manes of any man appeare, that euer dwelt within
the consines of that Country, at one of our
feasts, the ghost would say our feasts doe farre exceed.
If euer Nation was to bee condemn'd for
superfluity in fare, I doe bewaile this Land, in

which I was borne, and this City in which now I
breathe; good Lord, that thou shouldest giue vs
plenty, and we should spend it so profusely.
            
               Emebant &amp; vendebant,
               Luke 17. 28. The men of Sodome
did buy and sell, Ecce peccatum cupiditatis, Behold
the sin of couetousnesse: And had couetousnesse
a habitation in Sodome? and was filthy auarice a
cause of her desolation? then Lord bee mercifull
vnto our Land, that hath many a member in it,
who out of a couetous desire, haue made a marriage
with siluer, and giuen a bill of diuorce to Iesus
Christ! The Clergie in the Church, as in Prospers
generation,Prosp. lib. 1. c. 21 de vita con. 
               Non vt meliores, sed vt ditiores,
neo vt sanctiores, sed vt honor atiores sint caeteris festinant,
Make haste not to be better, but to bee richer,
not to be more holy, but to be more honourable
than other men; forgetting that of St. Paul
to Timothy,2. Tim. 2. 4. 
               No man that warreth ent angleth himselfe
with the affaires of this life, that he may please
him who hath chosen him to be a souldier. The Gentry
in the countrey, as in Augustines dayes,Aug. de ciu. Dei lib. 3. cap. 1. 
               magis
stama
                     •
                  hantur si villam malam habeant, quàm si vitam,
are farre more offended at the badnesse of
their Lordships, than at the badnesse of their
liues; neuer remembring that of Salomon, Riches
profit not in the day of wrath,
               Prou. 11. 4. 
               but righteousnesse deliuereth
from death. The Gallants in the Court, as
in Iugurtha King of Numidia's daies, are so prodigall,
that they will not keep goods themselues,
and so couetous, that they will not suffer others to
keepe theirs; making no vse of the Apostles precept,Rom. 13. 8.
               Owe no man any thing, but to loue one another.
               
The Aduocates and Pleaders at the barre, as in
Pope Eugenius his dayes, greedy of filthy lucre,Bern. lib. 1. de consid.
looke their Honorarium should be of such a value,
that a man had better take our Sauiour Christs
counsell litterally vnderstood,Matth. 5. 40. 
               If any sue him at the
law and take away his coate, let him haue his cloake
also, than contend for his coate againe; neuer remembring
that speech of our Sauiour to the Publicans,Luke 3. 13.
               Exact no more than that which is appointed
you.
            
            
               Aedificabant, &amp; plantabant, They planted,
               Luke 17. 28. they
builded; Ecce peccatum securitatis, Behold the sin
of security: And did security make her nest within
that for euer cursed countrey? Examine all that
euer breath'd out of English ayre, and let them
speake the truth from their hearts, and verily they
must certifie, none that euer were sprinkled with
the water of Baptisme, nuzzle themselues more in
security than wee. Stratonicus told the Rodes,
they builded as if they would liue euer, and eate
as if they would dye presently: For Gluttons;
those Epicures that desired of the gods neckes so
long as Cranes, that the delicious rellish of meats
and drinkes might remaine long, were not more
to be blamed than some among vs: And for builders,Gen. 10. 10.
Nimrod that was a prime agent in Babels
building, was not more ambitious of eternizing
his name than we; non Absolon,2. Sam. 18. 18. that built a tower
in the valley of Sauch to keepe his name in remembrance,
calling it Absolons plane.
            
            Nay, we are not cleare of that sinne of Sodom,
which cryed to Heauen for brimstone, with that

which cried lowdest, of reioycing in doing euill.
A sin not greater than can bee forgiuen; for what
sinne can bee so deadly, that the death of Christ
will not salue? but I dare say tis a sinne that must
haue an infinite measure of mercy, and an abundant
measure of teares to wash it away; and yet
tis among vs an vsuall sinne, and very vsuall sinne:
Marke it when you please, when two humours
meet that loue sinne alike, you shall heare the one
vaunting to the other of his wickednesse, and then
laugh himselfe at his owne beastlinesse, cheere vp
his heart at the repetition of his owne vngodlinesse.
O Lord, looke downe from heauen, behold
and visite the world, and restraine the sons of men
from this most grieuous iniquity.
            Ephraim and Manasses are in our land, fulnesse
of bread and forgetfulnesse of God. Gog
and Magog are in our mother City, pride and
plenty. Bloud maketh a clamour at the gates of
heauen for vengeance, oppression presseth him to
poure downe the vials of his wrath, blasphemy
and swearing challenge him for his long suffering;
Vsury, a sinne that maketh a man worse than
a theefe, worse than death, worse than hell, worse
than Iudas: worse than a theefe, because the theefe
robbeth onely in the night, the Vsurer robs both
day and night: worse than death, because death
kils onely the body, the Vsurer kils both body
and soule: worse than hell, because in hell onely
the bad shall bee punished, the Vsurer punisheth
both good and bad: lastly, worse than Iudas; for
Iudas restored the money againe which hee had

vniustly taken, but the Vsurer seldome makes restitution,
is had in more execration among
Turkes than Christians: for Viri boni Deum timete,
&amp; foenerari praetermittite; qui enim Vsurarij vivunt,
Daemoniaci resurgunt: Yee that be good men, feare
God, and put no money to vsury; for they that
liue Vsurers, doe rise Deuils, are the words in
their Alcoran. The times are growne monstrous;
there is discord in societies, fraud in merchants,
corruption in officers, conniuency in magistrates,
symonie in ministers; euery night brings forth a
theefe, euery day a deceiuer, euery minute a drunkard,
and euery weeke a murtherer: we are fallen
into such times the Prophet speakes of, Our hands
are defiled with bloud,
               Esay 59. 3. 
               and our fingers with iniquity,
our lips doe speake lies, and our tongues matter peruersnesse.
There was neuer that vice reign'd, but
now tis rife, yea I thinke I may say it, and not belye
the world; there bee many new vices reigne
now, which Sodome and Gomorrah neuer heard
of: there be new deuices to cousin with, new fashions
to be proud with, new oaths to blaspheme
with, new merits to iustifie by, new Articles of
Faith to beleeue, new Sacraments to receiue,
new gods found out to worship, and new Mediatours
to intercede: Fall to your prayers, and beg
feruently of God to send that new heauen and new
earth, of which St. Peter speaketh, wherein dwelleth
righteousnesse:
               2. Pet. 3. 13. 
               for this whole world lyeth in wickednesse,
               1. Iohn. 5. 19.
as St. Iohn saith: And for my part, I despaire
of it, doubt twill neuer be better before it
be purged with fire.
            
               
               Nulla aetas erat culpae immunis,
               Ambr. de Abra. patr. cap. 6. No age was free
from wickednesse in Sodome: the infants, whom
nature yet denied strength to perpetrate actuall
iniquity, had desire; and the old men that were
decayed in strength, had eyes full of adultery,
Omnes omni malo replerentur, They were all fil'd
with euery euill.Gen. 19. 
                     •
                  . The men of Sodome compassed
Lots house round, both old and young, all the people
from euery quarter, not ten righteous persons
could be found among many thousand soules. I
cannot say so of this Nation: for I doe resolue
my selfe, I may confidently speake as the Lord
did to Saint Paul in a vision by night concerning
Corinth:Acts 18. 10. 
               God hath much people in this City, more
in this Land, and daily may he adde to the number
of them: And as he did to Ezechiel the Prophet
in a vision concerning Ierusalem, There are
some that sigh and cry for all the abominations that
be done in the midst of vs, and daily may he adde to
the number of those likewise: But withall, when
I make an estimate of the multitude of people
that are contained within our borders, and obserue
so many marching furiously after their own
lusts, for so few following of Iesus Christ, I am
affraid of some vengeance approching, because I
doe not know what the will of the Lord is, whether
he will spare the place for their sakes. I doe
lay as much vpon Gods mercy as I may without
wronging his iustice, hee will not be moued to
poure forth his vengeance, vnlesse sinners superabound
in vices, neuerthelesse when and where
you find all iniquity planted, all rebellion against

God reigning, all the crying sinnes rousting, you
may take liberty to proclaime what you feare, saluation
stept aside, and destruction wing'd ready
to seize vpon that people for a prey.
            Eduardus the Confessor, one of the last of the
Saxon Kings, said vpon his death bed, that the
wickednesse of the English was complete and
growne to the height,Hollinsh. Chro. and the reuenge and punishment
thereof would shortly follow. Loth I
am to presage vnluckily of any grieuous calamitie
likely to betide my natiue Countrey, I had rather
promise the lengthning of tranquillity, were
it not that your selues and your sinnes would cry
out vpon me for flattery, if I should. I wish with
all my soule, that peace
               Psal. 122. 7. 
               may bee within your wals,
and plenteousnesse within your palaces. Long may
youIob 29. 6. 
               wash your steps with butter, and may the rockes
poure you outriuers of oyle. Long may your
               Psal. 126. 2. 
               mouths
be filled with laughter, and your tongues with ioy.
God blesse yourPsal. 132. 15. 
               victuals with increase, and satisfie
your poore with bread. Send that
               Psal. 144. 12, 13, 14. 
               your sons may
grow vp as the young plants, and that your daughters
may be as the polished corners of the temple: That your
garners may be full, and abounding in all manner of
store, and that your sheepe may bring forth thousands
and ten thousands in your streets; that your oxen may
be strong to labour, that there may bee no inuasion,
no leading into captiuity, no complaining in your
streetes: That you may dwell without feare,
               Reg. 4. 25. 
               euery
man vnder his vine, and euery man vnder his fig-tree,
hauing peace round about you, as Iudah and Israel
had. GodPsal. 132. 17, 18. 
               make the horne of our Dauid to bud,

clothe his enemies with shame, but on him let his
Crowne flourish; make his seed to endure for euer, and
his throne as the dayes of Heauen: All the good that
euer was conferd of all Nations, I wish heaped
vpon you. They were wont to say of Pericles,
that 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Suadela, the goddesse of eloquence sate
vpon his lips, he did by his Rhetorique so winne
the hearts of the Athenians to him. From the
bottome of my heart I wish our words were made
so powerfull, as to wooe all that heare vs to conuert
from their sinnes, and to turne vnto the Lord,
that so we might neuer need to fore-tell of anger
and wrath ready to descend from heauen: but the
intolerable head sinne hath got, kindleth in mee a
strong iealousie, that eyther the end of all things
is at hand, to make a cleane riddance of the wicked
and their wickednesse, or else that some bitter
iudgement is neare; it is neare, and hasteth
greatly to scourge vs for our iniquities.
            I haue no skill in diuination, yet let not my
words seeme to you, as the report the women
made of Christs resurrection seemed to the Apostles,

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , as an idle tale,
               Luke 24. 11. doe not sleight them
altogether, as Lots sons in-law did Lots counsell:
when hee told them God would destroy that Citie,
hee seemed to his sonnes in-law as though hee had
mockt.
               Gen. 19. 14. I doe not speake them out of any suddaine
flash of vndigested zeale, I haue made collection
vpon collection, and obseruation vpon obseruation,
and been at warre within my selfe in my meditations,
how to deliuer my minde discreetly
and christianly, to auoide the imputation of an

Enthusiasticke, and I find the times so out of measure
sinfull, vices of all sorts, bloudy, beastly vices,
so fowly committed, and so little punished,
vertue so sincerely preached and so little practised,
that I doe looke eyther for a sudden amendment
of all hands, (which I will bee plaine with
you I misdoubt: For can the Morian change his
skinne,
               Ier. 13. 23. 
               or the Leopard his spots? no more can they doe
well, that are accustomed to doe euill.) or else for
some punishment suddenly; and if it come not, tis
Gods extraordinary mercy, because his compassions
faile not.
            We may say in our prosperity we shall neuer be
remoued, God of his goodnesse hath made our
hill so strong; our poore shall bee satisfied with
bread, and our children within vs, our mowers
shall continue filling of their hands, and they that
gather vp the sheaues their bosomes: Yet heare
me,
               Ecclus. 33. 18. 
               heare me, ye great men of the people, and hearken
with your eare, yee that be rulers of the congregation:
Husband your prouisions neuer so frugally, replenish
your store-houses neuer so aboundanly,
barter with forreine Nations for wine to store
your cellars, send into your owne vallies for
wheate to fill your granaries, and be not carefull
of the Vineyard of the Lord of Hosts, to prune off
her rotten branches, if you doe not labour that
the Lord of heauen and earth may haue a plentifull
haruest, if you doe not set iustice as a weeding
hooke to the rootes of vices, to crop them maturely,
so sure as
               Ier▪ 46. 18. 
               Tabor is among the mountaines,
and as Carmel is by the sea, Thistles shall
               Iob 31. 40. 
               grow in

stead of wheate, and cockles in stead of barley: Your
               Psal. 107. 34. 
               fruitfull land shall be made barren, because of the
wickednesse of those that dwell therein.
            
            Againe, Heare me, heare me, yee great men of the
people, and hearken with your eares yee that be rulers
of the congregation: Giue order to cleanse your open
streetes from all annoyances that may breed
an infection, and to purge your priuate houses
from all scum and filth that may proue contagious;
yet if you doe not exercise your authority,
to sweepe away sinne out of your countries, and
cities, and villages, and priuate families, take
heed a pestilence, morbus incognitus medicis, a disease
the physitians know not what to make of,
such a one as kild in Israel 70000. people in three
dayes,
               2. Sam. 24. 15. doe not creep into your particular houses,
to kill your wiues out of your bosomes, and your
children in your cradles, and make your merchant
men to drop downe dead in your streetes,
as they are trotting to the Exchanges: dung in
your streetes will not breed a plague so soone, as
drunkennesse in your houses, nor wil the il-fauoured
serpent poyson a place so soon, as the wel-fauoured
harlot.
            Finally, Heare me, heare me, yee great men of the
people, and hearken with your eares yee that be rulers
of the congregation: Giue in charge to your Captaines
of hundreds, and Captaines of fifties, to
muster your fighting men yeare after yeare, and
to exercise them in the feates of armes; prouide
such horses as Iob speakes of, that will mocke at
feare,
               Iob 39. 23. 
               not turne backe at the ratling of speares, or

glittering of swords: Rigge vp your shipping, and
set out a Nauie to sea, aduise one with another to
make fortifications and impregnable bulwarkes
impossible to be scaled, for the safeguard of your
Country, vse all the art, and cost, and counsell
your Nation can yeeld to entrench your selues
from forreine foes, and doe not take a course to
quell the power of sinne, and take heed God doe
not bring vpon you an Armie of men bitter and
hasty, as those Caldeans the Prophet Habacuc
talkes of,Habac. 1. 6. fell, as those Arabians whom Esdras
cals the Nation of Dragons, fierce, as those Carnanians
the same man saith rage in wrath like the
wilde Boare of the wood,2. Esdr. 15. 2
                     •
                  . 30. hauing garments rolld
in bloud, that shall waste your Cities with miserie,
Ouerturne, ouerturne, ouerturne them, rauish
your wiues,Ezech. 21. 27. defloure your daughters, take no pity
of the fruit of your loines, but euen bloud their
swords in the bellies of women great with child,
that shall burne downe your Churches, and when
the Ministers of the Gospel begge for their liues,
shall answer them as Titus the Emperour did the
Priests of the Iewes, when they petition'd him
for their liues, Decet Sacerdotes cum templis int
                     •
                  
                  rire,
It is meet the Priests perish together with the
Temples; that shall driue you of the Laity in
whole droues away captiue, forbidding you vpon
paine of death to looke backe vpon the places
where you dwelt, as the Romanes forbade the
conquered Iewes to looke backe vpon Ierusalem;Euseb. Eccl. hist. lib. 4. cap. 6.
and if they spare any at home, make them to pay
an annuall tribute for their heads, as the Italians

doe the Iewes at this day; and imploy their children
to murther them that begat them, and to the
rooting out of that faith wherein they were borne
and baptized, as the Turke doth his Ianizaries,
the children of the Grecians. An vnrighteous
man will not consider this, neyther will a foole
vnderstand it;Psal. 92. 6. like as the Lord vpon whose hand
the King of Israel leaned, answered the man of
God when he fore-told him of plenty: Behold, if
the Lord would make windowes in heauen,
               2. Reg. 7. 2. 
               might this
thing be? so some one incredulous spirit or other
may obiect, If the Lord should cast vs altogether
out of his protection, might this thing be? Are
we not walled about with seas? Haue we not ammunition
and weapons of warre? Haue wee not
men of magnanimous resolutions? and may wee
feare forreine inuasion? My beloued,Lament. 4. 2. 
               the Kings of
the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world would
not haue beleeued, that the aduersary and the enemy
should haue entred into the gates of Ierusalem: and yet
Ierusalem is a heap of stones.
               Micah 3. 12. Let mee say vnto thee,
O thou Merchant City, that art a mart for Nations,
as the voice did to Phocas the Emperour,
Though thou build the wals of thy palaces as
high as heauen, yet if sin dwell in them, they may
easily be entered by an enemy. And giue me leaue
to say vnto thee, O thou carelesse Nation, as Nahum
the Prophet doth to Niniueh, to that great
City Niniueh,Nahum 3. 8, 9, 10. 
               Art thou better than populous No,
that was situate among the riuers, that had the waters
round about it, whose rampart was the sea, and
her wals were from the sea? Ethiopia and Egypt were

her strength, and it was infinite: Put and Lubin were
her helpers, yet was shee carried away, shee went into
captiuity, her young children also were dash'd in pieces
at the top of all the streets, and they cast lots for
their honourable men, and all her great men were
bound in chaines.
            
            Tremble therefore, thou secure Nation, and amend
thy manners, lest God to raze thee, and to
lay thine honour in the dust, doe call for Lucifer
the sonne of the morning, doe hisse for the Bee of
Ashur, do call for a rauenous bird out of the East,
doe plant the Syrians before, and the Philistins
behinde; giue them that charge hee gaue those
whom hee pressed to destroy Babylon, Put your
selues in array against (Britany) round about, all yee
that bend the bow shoote at her,
               Ier. 50. 14, 15. 
               spare no arrowes; for
shee hath sinned against the Lord: Take vengeance
vpon her, as she hath done, doe vnto her: And vpon
that set all your inhabitants in such a hurry and an
vp-roare, as the Citizens of Rome were in, when
Martius Coriolanus approached neare it with an
Army;Liuius. make the murmuring multitude to flocke
about the streets, and you that are Magistrates, to
be at your wits end, to send post after post, and messenger
after messenger, to shew the King that his country
is taken at one end,
               Ier. 51. 31. as the Babylonians did to
their King, when the King of the Medes had entered
the City: and when men shall say, O thou
sword of the Lord, how long will it be ere thou be quiet?
put vp thy selfe into thy scabberd, rest and be still;
as tis Ier. 47. 9. when the Priests, the Ministers of
the Lord, shall weep betweene the porch and the altar,

and say, Spare thy people, O Lord, and giue not thy
heritage to reproach, that strangers should rule ouer
them, as tis Ioel 2 1 7. he sit in heauen, laugh Priest
and People all to scorn, couer himselfe with a cloud,
that our prayer should not passe thorough, as tis Lament.
3. 44.
            To conclude all, the way to keep vs from these
fearfull punishments, are fasting, prayer, godly
sorrow for sins past, and the amendment of our
sinfull liues in the time to come: Not a day for a
man to afflict his soule,
               Esay 58. 5. 
               to bow downe his head as a bulrush,
to spread sackcloth and ashes vnder him, it is not
such a fast that the Lord hath chosen:
               August. 
               Opus est perpetuâ
poenitentiâ, quia perpetuò peccamus; We sin perpetually,
wherefore we had need to repent perpetually:
though wee doe draine our hearts dry of
water to day, wee shall haue need againe to morrow
to water our couches with our teares. Our
griefe for our sins must be equiualent, it must hold
proportion with the delight we haue taken in our
sins: our sins haue been wonderous great, and our
mourning must be maruellous deep: we haue bin
out of measure sinfull, and we must be out of measure
sorrowfull; we haue sinned with greedinesse,
and we must repent with bitternesse; we haue bin
transported with delight in the commission of
our sins, and wee must be swallowed vp with heauinesse
in our submission for our sins: Qui culpam
exaggerauit,
               Amb. lib. 1. de poenit, 
               exaggeret etiam poenitentiam; maiora
enim crimina maioribus abluuntur fletibm; He that
hath augmented his sin, must augment his repentance;

greater crimes are to be washt away with
greater lamentations. Some run abominable races,
act such iniquities the Angels of God wonder
at; and when they haue done, will say each man
for his owne particular, Miserere mei Deus, Lord
haue mercy on mee, and that too ex more magis
quàm ex animo, rather out of custome than heartily,
as Saul said to Dauid, when hee was going to
combate with Goliah,1. Sam. 17. 37. 
               Goe, and the Lord bee with
thee; and thinke then they haue repented compleatly.
O Lord God, that a man should dare to
sinne so damnably, and dreame to quit himselfe
of the guilt of it so eastly! tis not bare Lord haue
mercy vpon vs will doe it, there belongs more to
repentance than so; the faculties of our soules
must bee griped with griefe, and wearied with
groaning, and tired with supplications: we must
double our words as Daniel doth, and say, O Lord
heare,
               Dan. 9. 19. 
               O Lord forgiue, O Lord hearken, and deferre
not for thine owne sake, O our God. We must renue
our complaints with Dauid,Psal. 55. 17. 
               euening, and morning,
and at noone day, we must pray, and make a noise, and
God will hear our voice. We must weep and wipe
our eyes, and weep againe and wipe our eyes againe,
if we haue loued many sinnes, before many
sins can be forgiuen vs. We must draw a conclusion
in our owne bosomes, that no Nation hath
bin more bound to God than we, no Nation hath
sinned against God with a higher hand than wee;
and therfore no Nation hath greater cause to fast
and weepe, mourne and lament for their sins, than
we. We must giue way to the thoughts of our

hearts, to reflect vpon the distressed condition of
the Church of Christ abroad, and note how that
the bed doth not priuiledge the sick man, nor the
cradle the suckling babe, nor the great belly the
woman, nor the altar the Priest, nor the seate of
iustice the Magistrate, from the fury of the mercilesse
souldier: They fight and are kil'd, they
yeeld and are murthered, they flye and are pursued,
they remaine and are beleaguered, they hide
themselues and are hunger-starued, their corne
fields are deuoured by troupes of horses, their
streams of water are coloured red with the bloud
of men and beasts, and in some places their earth
is voide, as if it were returning into the Chaos againe;
as tis, Zech. 8. 10.Zech. 8. 10. 
               there is no hyre for man nor
beast, neither is there any peace to him that goeth out,
nor to him that commeth in, because of affliction; for
all men are set, euery man against his neighbour.
            
            And yet wee, a sinfull Nation, a people laden
with as much iniquity as any Nation in the Christian
world, are at rest; no trumpet is heard in our
streetes, no solitude ante ostia, no desolation is before
our gates, our plow-shares are not beaten
into swords, nor our mattockes into speares: the
seate of iustice is not interrupted, the Word of
God hath a free passage, we lay vs down to sleep,
and take our rest, God making vs to dwell in safety;
and vpon the comparison of these things, wee
must bethinke our selues, what vngratefull
wretches we haue bin to dishonour our God with
our sinnes, that hath and doth follow vs with so
much louing kindnesse aboue other people that

are more righteous than we; we must earnestly repent,
and be heartily sorry for our misdoings past,
and we must sweare vnto the Lord, and vow a vow
vnto the Almighty God of Iacob, to renounce our euill
waies, and to serue him in spirit and truth, in
sincerity and with good conscience in the time to
come; and then our God will not forsake vs, nor
giue vs vp for a reproach, that strangers should
rule ouer vs, but blesse vs all our lines long in bodies
and soules, and entaile the blessings more
firmly, than by any law you can deuise, to descend
vpon our posterity successiuely, so long as the
Sunne and Moone shall endure: And to that purpose,
let vs pray vnto him, and say, O most gracious
God, let not our manifold sins make a separation
betwixt thee and vs, let them not prouoke
thee to remoue thy spirituall and corporall blessings
from vs; Giue vs, O Lord giue vs, broken
hearts, contrite spirits, and bleeding soules, to
offer vp in sacrifice vnto thee, that thou mayest be
reconciled, and at an attonement with vs: Our
sins are great, Lord, we confesse it, but thy mercy
is greater, Lord, we beleeue it; mercy therefore,
deare Father, haue mercy vpon our King, vpon
our Queene, vpon our Nobility, vpon our Clergie,
vpon our Magistracy, vpon our Commonaltie,
vpon our whole Land, for thy Sions sake, for
thy Gospels sake, for thy beloued sonne Iesus
Christs sake. Giue, O Lord, giue thy Angels
charge ouer vs, let them pitch their tents about
vs, that no pestilence come among vs to deuoure
vs, no famine befall vs to starue vs, no sword of

an enemy inuade vs to destroy vs, and then, O
Lord our God, if thou wilt giue vs grace, we will
blesse thee, we will praise thee, we will magnifie
thee, wee will sing songs of thanksgiuing vnto
thee, wee will ascribe all honour and glory vnto
thee, and to thy Sonne, our blessed Sauiour and
Mediatour Iesus Christ, and to thy holy Spirit, to
which blessed and glorious Trinity of persons,
and but one God, bee giuen all
might, maiesty, dominion, and
praise, now and euer.
Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

