
   
      
         
            The baptizing of a Turke A sermon preached at the Hospitall of Saint Katherin, adioyning vnto her Maiesties Towre the 2. of October 1586. at the baptizing of one Chinano a Turke, borne at Nigropontus: by Meredith Hanmer, D. of Diuinitie.
            Hanmer, Meredith, 1543-1604.
         
         
            
               1586
            
         
         Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02614
            STC 12744
            ESTC S103823
            99839568
            99839568
            3999
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02614)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3999)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 463:10)
         
         
            
               
                  The baptizing of a Turke A sermon preached at the Hospitall of Saint Katherin, adioyning vnto her Maiesties Towre the 2. of October 1586. at the baptizing of one Chinano a Turke, borne at Nigropontus: by Meredith Hanmer, D. of Diuinitie.
                  Hanmer, Meredith, 1543-1604.
               
               [88] p.   
               
                  Printed by Robert Walde-graue dwelling without Temple-barre,
                  [London] :
                  [1586?]
               
               
                  Publication date conjectured by STC.
                  Signatures: [A] B-E F⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Chinano --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.
               Sermons, English --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-07
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-07
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE Baptizing of a Turke.
            
            ¶A Sermon preached at the Hoſpitall of Saint KATHERIN, adioyning vnto her Maieſties Towre the 2. of October 1586. at the Baptizing of one Chinano a Turke, borne at Nigropontus:
            By MEREDITH HANMER, D. of Diuinitie.
            Printed by Robert Walde-graue dwelling without Temple-barre.
         
         
            
            
            
               To the Right Worſhipfull RAPHE ROKEBY Eſquier, Maiſter of the Hoſpitall of S. Katherine, and alſo one of the Maiſters of her Maieſties Courte of Requeſts, health &amp; wealth in the Lord Ieſus.
            
               IT hath bene the maner of olde (Right worſhipfull) that if any ſtrange or new thing happened, within anie mans charge, the ſame as auncient hiſtories record, was immediately ſhewed vnto the ſuperiors. The Lieuetenant of Iudaea, certified the Emperour Tiberius, &amp; the Senate of Rome, of the fame of Chriſt, and eſpecially his reion, then rife in the mouthes of moſt men throughout Palaeſtina. Leaſt I ſhould ſeem forgetfull of good maners (being of diuers intreated to publiſhe this exerciſe) I haue thought good to ſhew vnto you the good newes here hapned throgh the mercy &amp; goodnes of our

gratious God, which hath brought home to his folde an erring ſheepe, by birth a Turke, borne at Nigropontus, hertofore by profeſſiō a Saracen, addicted vnto the ſuperſtitious lawe of Mahomet, but now by the miniſterie of our handes (not of worthines, but of fauour called to the function) after publike confeſſion of his true faith in Ieſus Chriſt, receiued into the congregatiō of the faithful, marked by Baptiſme for a vowed profeſſor, and ſealed vp in your Hoſpital of S. Katherine, (where the diuine prouidence hath alotted you, vnder her Maieſtie, heade gouernour) for the childe of God. Maners being not forgotten, and duetie thus remembred, the beholder and hearer haue ioynte cauſe to bee ioyful, for the pearle eſpied in the field, for the coyne found after ſearching, for the ſheepe called home from ſtraying, according vnto the parables in the Goſpell, and to praiſe our God, whoſe mercie endureth for euer. Of the other ſide wee haue cauſe to ſorrowe, when wee behold

the face of the earth in manner all couered with heathens, idolatrers and falſe worſhippers. Aſia in greatnes halfe the world, (though of olde reckoned for the third part) with the moſt famous gouernours Zambei of Arabia, the king of Narſinga, greate Cham of Tartaria, and the Indian Ilands, (if we may credit Marcus Paulus Ʋenetus) amounting to the number of twelue thouſand &amp; ſeauē hundred, all at this day (excepting a few Chriſtians here &amp; there ſcattred) are either Infidels, liuing as brute beaſtes without God, or followers of Mahomet, ioyning with the Turke in falſe worſhippe, yet not fearing his power: the which places haue beene of olde acquainted with the voice of Chriſt, and with the ſounde of the Apoſtles feete. Affrike (excepting the dominions of Presbiter Iohn the greate king of Aethiopia, who profeſſeth the faith in Chriſt, though not ſo purely as it is to be wiſhed) hath many Infidels, the reſt are Moores, Saracens, Nigroes, Barbarians, addicted to Mahomet, and obedient

to the great Turke. In theſe countries there are fewe Chriſtians ſeene. This triangle of Eaſt, South, &amp; Weſt, haue ſhaken off the faith, which of olde hath there beene profeſſed. Europe remaineth, though more peopled, yet a leſſer parte then Affrike, neyther is this part cleare from Mahomet. The great Turke hath taken Greece awaye, and ſeated himſelfe at Constantinople. Chriſtian religion is now couched in the North partes of the world, and ſo far that it ſeemeth (if we looke for fruits) all frozen. The profeſſors (according vnto the words of our Sauiour) are now a little flock. It is high time wee ſhould earneſtlie pray vnto God, that hee wil enlarge his kingdome, that hee will open the eyes of Infidels, that he will direct Idolatrers in the true woorſhip, that they which call vppon him in worde, maye followe him in deede, that his name may be glorified vpon earth, &amp; that al may be gathered together into one fold, to ſing holy, holy, holy, Lord God of Sabaoth. And here withal I ſuppoſe

it needfull to certefie your worſhip what moued this Turk to becom a Chriſtiā: not holie words, but workes, not the name of faith, but the viewe of fruites, not the learning of Clarks, but the liues of certain good Chriſtiās, whoſe loue &amp; kindnes did ſo rauiſh him (as he ſaide of himſelfe) that he cōfeſſed the God of the chriſtians to be the onely true God. And among others he named Sir F. Drake that worſhipful knight, &amp; W. Haukins that worthy Captaine. The tree is knowne by the fruits, Gods children are known by their holines, the true profeſſors are knowne by their loue. Hereby (ſaith our Sauiour) ſhall all men knowe that ye are my diſciples, if ye loue one another. The Iews gloried they were of God, their behauior declared thē (our ſauiour gaue ſētence) to be of the deuil: they ſaid they were of the ſeede of Abraham, their works denied them to be ſuch. This is the courſe that Chriſt tooke with the Scribes &amp; Phariſes for the ſtay of his credit: If I do not the workes of my Father, beleeue me not. Agayne:

though ye beleeue not me, beleue the works, This is the rule that Iewe and Gentile. that Turke &amp; Saracene, &amp; euery good Chriſtiā now marketh &amp; beholdeth, but at this day nothing rifer thē ſayyng, nothing rarer then doing. Wher be the almes-houſes, Hoſpitals, Colledges, and Churches nowe a daies founded &amp; builded? No doubt God hath his people, and they haue their fruites, though the ſame be very few. If wee were ſo deſirous to haue our lights (I mean our fruits) ſo ſhine vpon the earth in theſe North partes of the world, where Chriſtianitie is profeſſed, as we are gredily bent to gette the earthly commodities of Affrike, Aſia, and the hid treaſures of the far Indies, we ſhoulde no doubt prouoke them out of the ſaid coūtries to ſeek after our God, and to bee rauiſhed with the conuerſation and ſteppes of the Chriſtians, as they allure vs wyth fame of their commodities, to ſeeke after their forrain riches. And wheras now one ſilly Turk is won, ten thouſands no doubt woulde receiue the

faith. The heathens in far coūtries do wōder at the couetouſnes of the chriſtiās, &amp; the cruelty among other nations of the Spaniard. Presbiter Iohn in Affrike crieth out vpon the Chriſtian Princes for their diuiſion &amp; diſcorde. The great Turk at Cōſtantinople laugheth the pope &amp; his prelats to ſcorn for their pride, the Chriſtian churches he reuileth, and not without cauſe for their idols &amp; images. Reformation is to be ſought for of al men not onely in Religion (wherein ſome ouer-buſie themſelues, neuer ſatiſfied vntill they haue ouerthrowne all) but in liues &amp; maners, that they which are without ſeeing our good workes, may glorifie our father which is in heauen. Thus occaſioned by theſe circumſtances, my pen hath ouer-ruled me, I feare leſſe ouer tedious. Maye it pleaſe you to accept this remembrance proceeding from a willing mind, though other-wiſe not furniſhed to gratifie your kindnes. From Shordich the xii. of October, 1586.
            
            
               Yours in the Lord, Meredith Hanmer.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
                  
                     Math. 5. Verſe .16.
                  
                  Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father, which is in heauen.
               
            
            
               THe preſent occaſion heere offered, hath mooued mee (good people &amp; beloued in our ſauiour Chriſt) among other places of holy Scripture at this time, to deliuer vnto you the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt, written by the Euangeliſt Sainct Mathew: in the fifth Chapiter, which putte vs in remembraunce of our way, our walke, our workes, our lights and Chriſtian fruites, a meane to winne them that are without, and to mooue men to ſounde forth the glory and prayſe of God. It is high time to ſpeake, the matter concerneth the Maieſtie of God, the good ſucceſſe and furtheraunce of the Chriſtian faith. Fulgentius writing vnto Traſimund king of Vandals, of the miſterie

of the incarnation and mediatorſhippe betweene God and manne then called into queſtion, ſayth:Fulgent. lib. 1. ad Traſimund. 
               Cum de Deo res agitur non leuis reatus eſt, ſi ꝙ ad ſalutem pertinet, taceatur. When the matter concerneth God, it is no ſmall offence to be ſilent in that which toucheth ſaluation:Epheſ. 2. Wee are created (ſayth the Apoſtle) in Chriſt Ieſus ad bona opera to ſhewe forth good workes to the honour and glory of God. I haue iuſt cauſe togeather with you (laying other thinges aſide) greatlye to prayſe God,Pſal. 66. whoſe watchefull eye beholdeth continuallye the wretched wights of the world, who calleth into the vinearde agayne,Math. 20. and againe, the idle perſons ſtanding in the market place of the world, who graffeth of his meere mercy and fauour, the wild Oliue, in the true and naturall Oliue,Rom. 11. who fetcheth home, with his power, and carieth home as it were vpon his ſhoulder,Luke. 15. the wandering and loſt ſheepe into the folde, and at this preſent this ſilly Turke and poore Saracene vpō his confeſſion to be matriculated in the booke of the faithfull, and by Baptiſme to bee

ſealed vp for the childe of God, and inheritour of the kingdome of heauen. I haue againe to commend for example, to others of chriſtian light and conuerſation, certayne worthy perſons of this land, whome this Saracene termed moſt worthie chriſtians, whoſe light and behauiour, this ſillye Turke beholding was (as he confeſſeth) the rather moued to be of their faith and religion, but of them in the end, when I ſhall open vnto you the things that moued this Turk to receiue the chriſtian faith. Moreouer by occaſion that the Sacrament of Baptiſme is preſently to bee miniſtred, the time requireth I ſhoulde ſpeake of the principles of chriſtian religion, the rocke and foundation of this ſpirituall building and the corner ſtone, that cloſeth vp the whol, our Lord Ieſus chriſt. But for yt my ſpeache is to bee directed vnto you (good people) that are therein as I hope ſufficientlye perſwaded, and that this Saracene vnderſtandeth not the engliſh tongue, but as hertofore vppon priuate conference, and at this preſent alſo by an interpretor in the ſpaniſh

tongue, hee is readie, and ſhall deliuer before you all, a true confesſion of the faith in Ieſus Chriſt, therefore happelie of theſe thinges by the waye in the ſowing of the ſeede of Gods word. And at this time I haue purpoſed by Gods helpe, to lay before you, firſt the originall of Mahomet, that falſe Prophete with the nations of Mores, Saracens, and Turkes: ſecondly their falſe doctrin and wicked religion, wherewith they haue bewitched infinite ſoules: with a briefe confutation thereof. Laſtly that which concerneth our ſelues, howe wee may pleaſe God, with the way &amp; meane to winne them that are without, according vnto the rule of our Sauiour: Let your light ſo ſhine before menne, that they may ſee your good workes and glorifie your father which is in heauen. That this may be done to the glorie of God, and comforte of our ſoules and conſciences: I beſeech you ioine with me in prayer &amp;c.
            
               Our father &amp;c.
            
            
               According vnto promiſe I am to laye before you theſe three partes.

                  
                     1 The originall of Mahomet the falſe Prophet of the Turke, with the nations of Moores, Saracens, and Turkes.
                     
                  
                  
                     2 The falſe doctrine and wicked religion of Mahomet and theſe erring nations with a briefe confutation thereof.
                  
                  
                     3 The way to pleaſe God, &amp; meane to win them &amp;c.
                  
               
            
            Let your light ſo ſhine &amp;c.
            In the yeare of our Lord 597. (ſayth Mathaeus Palmer,
               Math. Palmer. Maſſaeus chron. lib. 13 Volfgang-Drechſler. Chronic. de Saracen. &amp; Turc. origine. 
               Maſſaeus &amp; Drechſlerus) &amp; in the raigne of Mauricius the Emperour when as Gregorius magnus was Biſhop of Rome, one Mahomet was borne of the line of Iſmaell the ſonne of Abraham by Agar the bondwoman, hauing to his father one Abdara, and to his mother one Emma being very obſcure and baſe Parentes, in Mecha a Citie of Arabia. His Parents deceaſed and left him a very yong Orphane, who in ſhorte time by miſaduenture was taken captiue, this beeing

knowne vnto his kinred,Volaterran. Geogr. lib. 12. one Abdemonaples (ſaith Volaterran) an Iſmaelite, bearing him great good will for his fauor, &amp; forwardnes of wit, paid his raunſome, made him his ſeruaunt, and factor in all his marchaundize. Not long after his maiſter dieth without iſſue, his ſeruant Mahomet, matched wt his miſtres a widowe of 50.
               Paul. Diac. rer. Rom. lib. 18. yeares of age called Eadigam &amp; (ſaith Paulus Diaconus) his own kinſwoman, ſo yt his maiſter being of great credit &amp; ſubſtance &amp; his miſtres (afterwards his wife) of no leſſe accōpt &amp; alſo ſhortly after departing this life,Sabellicus. Enead. 8. lib. 6. he ſuccedeth thē both in credit &amp; all their ſubſtāce &amp; by this means grew of great power. Sabellicus doubteth though hee were borne in Arabia, whether he were an Arabian or a Perſian, he affirmeth yt both is receiued, and yt his father was an heathen, &amp; his mother an Iſmaelite, and conſequently not ignorāt in the hebrew tōgue, not only this, but I find it reported by Ludouicꝰ Carrettꝰ a cōuert Iew yt 
               India, Aethiopia,
               Ludouicus Carrett. ad Iudaeos. lib. diuinorum viſorum. ye kīgdō of Preſbyter Iohn, &amp; Arabia hath many Hebrewes ſince ye time yt king Solomō
                furniſhed ye
               
Queene of Saba into her country with twelue thouſand of all the tribes of Iſrael, which being diſperſed throughout theſe countries multiplied and increaſed exceedingly, retaining for remembraunce amonge them, the Standard and Enſigne of their ſeuerall Tribe and familie.Paulus Diaconus. Rer. Com. lib. 18. Math. Pariſ. hiſt. Anglor. in Henric. 3. 
               Paulus Diaconus and Mathew Paris, deriueth his pedegree lineally from Iſmaell, the recital wherof I will omitte.
            This Diaconus ſaith further, that this Mahomet for the ſpace of tenne yeares, gaue him ſelfe ſecretely by perſwation to bewitch the people, &amp; other ten yeares after, together with Rognes and Vagabonds that repaired vnto him with force of Armes, with Sworde and ſhedding of blood, hee ſpent in ſubduing of Countries. And laſtly nine yeares, he openly and manifeſtly inioyed as a deceiuer, a falſe Prophet, and King ouer thoſe whom he had already infected and conquered throughout Arabia, and the adioyning Regions, his raigne began in Arabia, the 15. yeare of Heraclius, the Emperour, about the yeare of our

Lord 617. ye 
               Iſmaelites of which line he was, inhabited the wildernes of Madian, feeding of cattell, &amp; lying in Tents.Iſidor. Etymolog. lib. 14. cap. 3. Sabellic. Enead. 6. lib. 4. 
               Iſidor writeth that the coūtry of the Iſmaelites was called Nabathaea, of Nabaioth the ſonne of Iſmael, ſcituate betwene Iudaea, and Arabia, &amp; commonly accompted for part of Arabia, of ye ſame opiniō is Sabellicus. He had the falling ſickenes, which tooke him extremely, ſo that he groueled along the grounde, and fomed piteouſly at the mouth, his wife beeing of great honor and ſubſtance bewailed her harde hap, in matching with a beggerly Raſcall, and a diſeaſed creature, as Diaconus writeth. But he togeather with his wily companions (of whom I ſhall haue occaſion to ſpeake herafter) hauing taught a Doue to feed at his eare, wherein hee was wont to put graines of Corne) perſwaded his wife and others that he was a Prophet, that the ſpirite of God fell vpon him &amp; that the Angel Gabriel, in the forme of a Doue came to his eare, and reuealed him ſecrets, whoſe preſence he was not able to abide, therfore he proſtrated him

ſelf and lay in a Traunce, his wife, in a while beeing therein ſatiſfied, chatted the ſame among her Goſſippes ſaying: ſay nothing, my Huſbande is a Prophet. The women after their manner, whereof ſome of them all 
                  •
               anne keepe no counſell, blaſed abroade that Mahomet was a Prophet. 

                  Et taliter ex foeminis, fama (ſayth Diaconus) peruenit ad viros,
                  
                     and ſo by women menne came to know thereof.
                  
               
This once beeing broched they flocked vnto him from all parts of Arabia. He being throughly ſchooled in Satans ſubteltyes and well ſeene in Magicke obſerued the preſent oportunitye, ſaith Auentinus. The Romans,
               Auentin. Annal. lib. 3. and Perſians, warred togeather, Mahomet, with his Arabians, taking at the firſt, part with the Romans (for the Emperor had graunted him,Zonaras. Annal. tom. 3. ſayth Zonaras, a Region to inhabite) forſooke them, and thereby weakened that ſide. In a while after he eſpied the Perſians goe to wracke, and hauing diſpiſed the Romans, hee ſetteth leſſe by the Perſians, and ſetteth him ſelfe forth with might and mayne

togeather with his Captaynes, and Lieuetenauntes called Amiraei, to ſubdue Nations, and to deſtroye the Chriſtians, to the ende hee might eſtabliſhe that falſe Religion deuiſed by him and his wicked confederates. Hee preuailed wonderfully, and in ſhorte tyme after his deceaſe (when as the great Earthquake in Palaeſtina,
               Paul. Diac. and the ſigne 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                in heauen foreſhewed the ſucceſſe of the Arabians, Et omnes extimuerunt: And all men trembled for feare
               ) in the time of Ebubezer, and Haumar that ſucceſſiuely raigned after him in Arabia, the Region of Gaza, the Citie Boſtra, in Arabia, Damaſcus, Phoenicia, Aegypt, Palaeſtina, the Citie Ieruſalem, all Syria, Antioch, Edeſſa, Meſopotamia, all Perſia, (Choſroes the King beeing driuen away to ſaue his life) yea and in manner all Aſia, was ſubdued by the Arabians, in the Raigne of the Emperour Heraclius. I maye not forgette the ende of Mahomet. About fortie and odde yeares of his age, and in the yeare of our Lorde Ieſus 632.
               
               Volater. lib. Sigebert. Cronic. Elor. hiſtor. Sabellic. Enead 8. lib. 6.after the ſupputation of Sigebertus and Sabellicus this falſe Prophet departed this life after a ſhamefull maner. Mathew of Weſtmonaſter writeth, that this Mahomet in an euening ſitting vp late in his pallace, and hauing taken his fill of wine wherein one of his companions hadde poured ſome poiſon, felt his wonted ſickenes approching, made haſt forth, ſaying to them that were preſent he muſt needes depart, to conferre with the Angel Gabriell, and goe aſide leſt his glorious preſence would bee an occaſion of their death. Forth hee went and remembring that a ſoft place was beſt for his falling ſickenes, downe hee went vpon a dunghill, groueling along with great paine, foming at the mouth, &amp; gnaſhing with the teeth. And whereas hee to pleaſe the Iewes, forbade the eating of ſwines-fleſh, the ſwine about the donghill, fell vpon him, wounded him ſore, and had eaten him vp: had not his wife, and others of his houſe, heard the noiſe of the Hogges, and reſcued the falſe Prophete.Anton. Cropart. 2. tit. 13 cap. 5. 
               Antoninus reporteth that hee was not without ſundry diſeaſes,

which his intemperate diet brought him to: namely the Pleureſie &amp; a kinde of Letargie, for oftentimes his ſences ſeemed to bee taken away from him. He continued drooping ye ſpace of 14. daies at length he departed this life, his belly hadde ſuche a ſwelling, that it ſeemed ready to burſt, and his little finger bowed backwardes. In the time of his ſickenes he commanded them that were about him, that when breath departed his bodye they ſhoulde not ſtraight way burie him, for he ſaid that within three daies he would aſcend into heauen, but ye wicked ſpirit therin failed him. They kept him with a watch aboue grounde the third &amp; fourth day:Flor hiſtor. yea ſaith Flores Hiſtor. the ſpace of 30. daies, in great hope he wold riſe, and aſcend according to promiſe but they ſaw nothing, ſauing that they felt, an intollerable ſtinche ſo yt in great diſdaine (ſaith Antoninus)Antoninus. 
               
                  Eum long à domibus proijecêrunt,
                  
                     They caſt him farre from any dwelling.
                  
               
In a while after, his companions ſuche as concealed his falſhood and treachery, remembring themſelues, and iudging

that the diſdain of Mahomet would be their diſcredite, and the fall of his ſect their foyle, and ſhame, and the beaſtly end and death of him their deſtruction, they fetch him againe,Sabellic. Enead. 8. lib. 6. Naucler. generat. 22. they cheſt him in an Iron Cophin (ſaith Sabellicus, and Nauclerus) they bringe him to the famous temple of Mecha, in which Citie he was borne, with great ſolemnitte as if he hadde neuer beene ſcared vpon the dunghill with ſwine, they conuey to the roufe of the temple mightie lodeſtones, they lift vp the Iron Cophin, where the lodeſtones according to their nature draw to them the Iron, and hold it vp &amp; there hanges Mahomet on high. Ludouicus Romanus,
               Ludouic. Roman. Patritius nauigat. lib. 1. cap. 12. deſcribeth at large a certain Tombe below, builded for him as if he lay belowe. All this while you heare nothing of the Moores, the Saracens, &amp; the Turkes, but al of Mahomet. Now good people heare their original. The Moores called Mauri inhabite Mauritania in Affricke, they are (ſayth Iſidor) of the progenie of Cham,
               Iſid. Aetym. lib. 14. cap. 5. whoſe poſterity Noe accurſed, and no maruail

curſed people receiue the curſed doctrine of Mahomet.
               Sabellic. Enead. 1. lib. 5. 
               Sabellicus writeth there were ſome which thought that Mauri was corruptly readde for Medi, but I take that a corrupte opinion. Theſe people inhabiting Mauritania in Affricke, are becauſe of their hewe and colour of the Latins called Nigritae, in our vulgar ſpeach Nigros, and of the Grecians in the ſame ſenſe for their aduſt, and blacke colour called 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Moores. Theſe receauing the corruptions of Mahomet, are called Saracens, and why ſo, I am ready to declare.Stephan. 
               Stephanus thinketh that the people in Aſia are called Saracens, of Sarracca, a countrye in Arabia: This maye ſtande for a bare coniecture and no more.Anton. cron part. 2. cap. 5. But the pride of Mahomet it was, that firſt founde out the name of Saracen, to aduaunce hys faith and profeſſion. Hee knewe himſelfe Lineally to haue deſcended of Iſmaell, the Sonne of Agar, the Bonde-woman, yet bare hee the worlde in hande that hee came of Sara the

freewoman the wife of Abraham, and called himſelf &amp; his followers Saracens. Sabellicus writeth:Sabellicus Enead. 8. lib. 6. Volfgang. Drechſler. Cronic. 
               
                  The Grecians of ſpite are wont to call the Saracens, Agarens, for that they came not of Sara, but of Agar.
               
            
            But Mahomet (ſaith Drechſlerus) 

                  Seducing the Arabians and the people of Aſia called them Saracens.
                
The like hath Nauclerus:
               Nauclerus Generat. 22. 
               
                  The Perſians hauing receaued the Law of Mahomet, at his commandement laide aſide their olde wonted name and were called Saracens.
               
In this ſence all Nations who ſoeuer that embrace the lawe of Mahomet are called Saracens. Laſtly it remaineth that we ſpeak of the Turkes.
               Theodorus Gaza epiſt. ad franciſc. philelph. Strabo. lib. Laonicus Chalcondyl. de reb. Turc. lib. 1. Mathias â Michou de Satmat. Aſiatic. lib. 1. cap. 15. 
               Theodorus Gaza, is of opinion with Strabo, that theſe whom wee call Turkes, were of olde called Cyrtij, and Curti, a Scythian nation about the mount Caucaſus. Laonicus ye 
               Athenian, who wrote at large the hiſtorie of the Turkes, alleadgeth ſundry opiniōs of their original. Some helde they hadde their beginning of the Tartarians, and the reaſon yt lead them therto is, that they vſe the ſame maners and haue the ſame language, for they all

(ſaith Volatteran) ſpeake the Arabike tongue.Volater. lib. 12. Some other thinke they come of the Parthians. Again, there are that affirme them to be of Caeloſyria and Arabia. And others, that they iſſued forth of Turca a greate and a wealthie Citie of Perſia. But all confeſſe that at theyr firſt breaking forth they were rude, ſauage, and fieldiſh people.Andreas â Lacuna. de Turc. orig. cap. 1. 
               Solymannus the Tartarian gloried (ſayth Andreas â Lacuna) that hee came of the Troian bloud. Hereby ſome gather, that whereas the Troians were called Teucri, the worde might be corrupted, and the poſteritie called Turci, Turks,
                The conſēt of ye beſt hiſtoriographers is, that theſe Turks came frō ye vpper Scythia, being (as it hath bene alwaies noted of them) an vnquiet nation, liuing vpon ye ſpoile breaking foorth in great troupes to rob and ſteale, and ſeeke aduentures. So writeth Mathias â Michou of them,Mathias â Michou, cap 11.13. Laonicus lib. 1. Otho Friſingenſis. &amp; ſundrie other Scythian nations. Laonicus ſayth, that Turca ſignifieth a Sauage and fieldiſh man: Otho Friſingenſis reporteth, that in the yeare 760. long after the death of Mahomet, there

came of them out of Scythia, a greate number into Aſia and Arabia, &amp; beeing heathens, they ioyned with the Saracens in league, and receiued the Lawe of Mahomet. After theſe came others, ſo that the Saracens by their ayd grew to a wonderfull power, and the greate terrour of all Chriſtendome. There raigned from Mahomet the falſe Prophet,Bullinger in Apocalyp. concione. 41 as kings in Arabia, to the number of 25. Amiraei, ſo are their Princes called: the laſt Amiras, being the 25. called Mahumet, beeing king of Perſia &amp; Media, in the yeare 870. conceiued diſpleaſure againſt Imbrael prince of Babylon, a Saracene of his owne ſect and wickedneſſe, ſo that hee endeuoured to ſubdue him, and conquere his countrie. Heere Sathan againſt Sathan, Saracene againſt Saracene, the kingdome diuided within it ſelfe is ready to come to naught.Volater. Geogr. lib. 7 This Mahumet, or (as Volateran writeth) Maugmet, ſent to Scythia for ayde againſt Imbrael, but it turned to his owne confuſion, for hee prouiding ſorrowe for an other, endured it himſelfe. There came ayd from

               Scythia one Muchulet, with an infinite number of Turkes, rude and ſauage people, ready of themſelues to any miſchiefe whatſoeuer. They are no ſooner come, but they vanquiſhed Imbrael of Babylon, and immediately after they ſette vppon him that ſent for them, namely Maugmet king of Arabia, Perſia, and Media, they conquere his country, and raigne in his ſtead. Thus were the Saracens ſubdued, and became ſubiecte to the Turkes of Scythia. In a while after they wanted a gouernour, they woulde no Perſian or Arabian ouer them: So that in the yeare 900.
               Andreas â Lacuna de orig. Turc. cap. 1. as (Andreas â Lacuna writeth) one Solymannus a valiaunt and mightie warriour, choſen by conſent of them all, leauing his natiue ſoyle, brake foorth with a great hoſt out of Scythia, inuaded Perſia, and Aſia the leſſe. In the ſame place againe hee ſayth: 

                  Poſt Solymannum extinctum duce aliquo inſigni diu ipſi Turcae caruerunt. 
                  
                     After Solyman was deade, the Turkes of a long time were wythout any famous gouernour.
                  
               
            
            
               
               Iohannes Ramus writeth,Iohannes Ramus rer. Turc. lib. 3. that among theſe Turks or Scythians there were 4 families, called Aſambici, Candelori, Caramini, Othomanni, in the yeare 1280. which after the wearing out of the auncient houſes and nobilitie, contended among themſelues for the principalitie, and in the ciuill warres deſtroied one another. The laſt of them, &amp; yt which preuailed, was one Othomannus, which in the yeare 1300. began to beare rule. He was the firſt Emperor of the Turkes, of him lineally vnto this day the Emperours of the Turkes deſcende. Thus the kingdome of Mahomet, and raigne of the Saracens, theſe Turkes (ſaith Ramus) hauing receiued the Lawe of Mahomet:
               
                  fatali quadam ambitione de ſe, Regnum Turcicum appellauerunt. 
                  
                     By a fatall kinde of ambition, called it of themſelues the kingdome or empire of the Turkes.
                  
               
So that nowe the Calipha or Amiras of Babylon, the Soldan of Aegypt, the Sophie of Perſia, with the Tartarians, and ſundrie other nations, together with the great Emperour of the Turkes (whoſe ſeate is at

               Conſtantinople) doe worſhip the falſe Prophet Mahomet. And this greate Turke at this day (whome God ſuffereth to raigne for the ſinnes of his people) hath all Affrike (excepting the dominions of Presbyter Iohn) a greate parte of Aſia, and a piece of Europe ſubiect vnto him. Thus muche of theſe nations. Now in the ſecond place according vnto promiſe (beloued in our Sauiour Chriſt) of the falſe doctrine &amp; deteſtable religion of Mahomet, and theſe erring nations. We muſt be wiſe as ſerpents, and ſimple as doues,Math. 10. we muſt be cunning exchaungers, we muſt be able to diſcerne the ſpirituall leproſie of Mahomet,
               Leuitic. 13. we muſt be ſkilfull in trying of the ſpirites,1. Iohn. 4. Iudic. 12. we muſt learne to know Shiboleth from Siboleth (as the Apoſtle Iude writeth) diiudicantes, putting difference,
               
               Iud. Epiſt. wee muſt pray vnto God with Salomon,
               3. Reg. 3. that of his goodneſſe he will giue vs a wiſe &amp; an vnderstanding heart to diſcerne betwene good &amp; bad. This falſe Prophet Mahomet, hauing (as ſome write) an Heathen to his father, and an Hebrew to his mother,

and vrged of both ſides (as Sabellicus writeth) receiued nor the one law nor the other throughly,Sabellic. Enead. 8. lib. 6 but a ſmack of both. He vſed the companie of Chriſtians, of Iewes, and Infidels.

                  Et vt popularior eſſet eius lex, ex omnium gentium ſectis aliquid aſſumpſit.
                  
                     And to the end his law might be the more fauored, hee borrowed ſomewhat of euerye ſect.
                  
               
               Satan furniſhed him with three inſtruments,Faſcicul. Temporum as helpers, to bring his miſchieuous intent about. The firſt (ſaith Wer nerus Roleuinke) was a Iew, a great Aſtronomer, &amp; a Magitian, who opened vnto him at large the Iewiſh follies. The ſecond, one Iohn of Antioch. The third, one Sergius a Monke, both abhominable heretiks.Sabel. Enead. 8. lib. 6. Euerie one plaid his part. Sabellicus writeth, that to flatter the Chriſtians, he was baptized of Sergius, and that of theſe Heretikes hee learned with the Sabellians to denie the Trinitie, with the Manichees to eſtabliſh two beginnings, with Eunomius to deny the equal power of the father, and the ſonne, with Macedonius to call the holy Ghoſt a creature, &amp; with

the Nicolaites to allow the number of wiues, and wandering luſt.Anton. cron part. 2. tit. 13 cap. 5. 
               Sergius the Monke (ſaith Antoninus) perſwaded Mahomet in his Alcoran, (ſo is the booke of his law tearmed) to commend the humilitie of Chriſtian Monks and prieſts. He made him deliuer the Saracens a monks coule, which they vſe vnto this day. Alſo: 

                  Inſtarmonachorum multas genu-flexiones:
                  
                     Many duckings and crouchings after the maner of Monks,
                  
               
which is ſeene in their kind of ſalutation. Mathias â Michou addeth,Mathias â Michou de Sarmat Aſiana. lib. 1. lib. 7. Laonicus de reb. Turc lib. 3. that the ſect of Mahomet, vſe alſo ſhauing, and this no doubt was the Monks doctrine Laonicus the Athenian reporteth that the Turks cōfeſſe God to be ye gouernour of all thinges, and that Ieſus was the Apoſtle of GOD, begotten by the Aungell Gabriell vppon Marie the Virgine, which neuer knew man, and that hee was greater or woorthier then manne. Sabellicus addeth:Sabellic. Enead. lib. 6. they commende the bleſſed Virgin, they allowe the myracles, and approoue the Goſpell, as farre foorth as it agreeth wyth the Alcoran. This is but a

ſhadow of Religion, and a cloake couering a number of blaſphemies. In confeſſing a God, they denie the trinity of perſons, in ſpeaking of Ieſus, they moſt wickedly with the Arrians denye his Godhead, and that he is the Sonne of God. Al, that is ſpoken of the virgin, the miracles, and the Goſpell, by thoſe blaſphemous Turkes, though to ſeeme a praiſe, yet is it a diſpraiſe, when as the truth is not plainely and abſolutely deliuered, but maymed &amp; mingled with falſhood. The Apoſtle S. Iames ſayth: Iacob. 2. 
               
                  Whoſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Lawe, and yet fayle in one poynt, he is guilty of al.
               
The Saracens ieſt at the Chriſtians, for affirming that Ieſus the great frende of God, would ſuffer coutumely, reproche, and endure death by the handes of the Iewes, they denie that hee ſuffered, or that hee died, but that hee aſcended into heauen, and that the Iewes tooke an other in his ſtead,Naucler. Generat. 22. Anton. cron part. 2. tit. 13 cap. 5. &amp; executed him (which is an olde hereſie) ſo write Nauclerus and Antonimus, with others. Mahomet forgat here to deliuer vnto his people the teſtimonie of the Prophet Eſay,
               
which opened the truth of Chriſt:Eſay. 53. 
               
                  He was oppreſſed, and hee was afflicted, yet did he not open his mouth: hee is brought as a ſheepe to the ſlaughter, &amp; as a ſheepe before the ſhearer is dumbe, ſo hee opened not his mouth.
               
It followeth: 

                  And who ſhall declare his age?
               
It paſſeth mans reach, for he is God from euerlaſting. Our Sauiour teſtifieth of himſelfe, the willing minde he had to ſuffer, and to die, that ſinners might liue.Iohn. 6. 
               
                  The bread which I will giue is my fleſh, which I will giue for the life of the world.
               
Again:Iohn. 11. 
               
                  I am the good ſhepheard, the good ſhepheard giueth his life for his ſheepe, I lay down my life for my ſheepe. Therefore doth the Father loue me, becauſe I lay downe my life that I may take it againe. No man taketh it from mee, but I lay it downe of my ſelfe.
               
S. Paule yeeldeth teſtimony alſo to the truth, ſaying:Hebr. 9. 
               Hee offered vp himſelfe without spotte to God. When Peter went about to withſtand ſuch as came to apprehende him, he forbadde him, ſaying:Math. 26. 
               
                  What thinkeſt thou that I cannot now pray to my Father, and hee will giue me moe then twelue legions of Angels? how then ſhal the ſcriptures

be fulfilled, that it muſt be ſo?
               
Heere hee ſheweth his yeelding and conſenting mind.Irenaeus lib. 1. cap. 23.25. Epipan. hereſ. 24.28. That another ſuffred in his ſtead is an old damned hereſie which Mahomet reuiued after the death of Cerinthus, &amp; Baſilides. He hath forbidden his followers al pictures &amp; images in their temples, mingling (ſaith Mathew Paris) ſome hony with his poiſon,Math. Paris hiſt. Angl. in Henric. 3. Sabellic. Enead. 8. lib. 6. yt rather to deceiue the drinker. He receiueth the old teſtament correcting therin (ſo preſumptuous is this ſpirit) certain errors, hee alloweth after his manner of three Prophets, Moſes, Chriſt, &amp; Mahomet, whome he calleth Razales. Yet immediately he is found contrary to himſelf. The Chriſtians pray toward the Eaſt,Iacob. de Vorag. in vita Pelag. legend. 177. the Iews (ſaith Iacobus de Voragine) towards the Weſt, Mahomet cōmandeth his people to pray toward ye ſouth, he might haue turned himſelf for al his religiō to ye deuil towards ye north. The chriſtiās haue ſunday for their ſabaoth, the Iews Saturday,Laonic. lib. 3. Volater. lib. 12. &amp; Mahomet Friday (as Laonicus writeth) to diſſent frō ye Hebrews &amp; Chriſtians (as Volateran writeth) for yt he was made king vppon

that day,Anton. cron part. 2. tit. 13. cap. 5. Naucler. Generat. 22. or (as Antoninus writeth) in ye honour of Venus, the Goddeſſe of Arabia, therby the rather to win that country people, and ſo it may verie well be, for moſt of his religion ſtandeth vppon venerie, as I ſhal deliuer vnto you anō. He taught Circumciſiō, although (ſaith Antoninus) it is not found yt he himſelf was circumciſed. He forbad ye eating of ſwines fleſh, bloud, &amp; ſtrangled, he commaunded waſhings &amp; purifyings, ad ſimilitudinem Iudaeorum, after the maner of the Iews.
                He called himſelf a Prophet, &amp; that he was ſent of God to ſupply ye imperfection of al lawes, to lace ye remiſſe, &amp; to mittigate the ſeuere lawe. The Iews hearing the name of Moſes, ye abādoning of pictures, ye receiuing of ye old teſtament, ye uſing of purifications ye doctrine of circumciſiō &amp; ſwines fleſh,Flor. Hiſt. &amp; that he ſaid vnto them (as Flores hiſtoriarum writeth) he was ye promiſed Meſsias, they flocked about him, &amp; 10 of thē continued wt him to his dying day,Paul. Diac. rer. Rom. lib. 18. (as Paulus Diaconus writeth.) When they had heard his doctrine, &amp; ſeen ye maner of his diet &amp; conuerſatiō, they eſpied

that he eate Camels fleſh, &amp; therby perceiued he was not the man they looked for. Then they imagined what was to be done, to bee driuen to forſake him &amp; his religion for altogether, yt they iudged a diſgracing vnto them. They kept him company, &amp; fearing leaſt the Chriſtian religion, by the meane of Sergius, ſhould take much root (after their olde maner, ſhewing whoſe children therein they were) they continually pricke him forwards againſt the Chriſtians. Ther are ſix points chiefly, wherein the Iews differ from the Chriſtians.Ludouicus Carettus ad Iudaeos, lib. diuinorum viſor. 
               Ludouicus Carettus, a Iew conuerted to the chriſtian faith, ſhall indifferently reporte them for both ſides, for there-upon hee ſtood, afore hee was throughly perſwaded in the truth. The firſt is the trinity, which they denye, acknowledging one God, but denying ye three perſons. The ſeconde: the incarnation of the worde, which is the diuinitie of Chriſt, which they confeſſe not. Thirdly the manner of Chriſts cōming (as they dreame) to deſtroy kingdoms,Eſay. 62. Zachar 9. &amp; to raigne here vpō earth, but he came poore &amp; meek, riding

vpō an Aſſe accounted among the wicked, whoſe ſins he bare,Math. 21. Eſay. 53. Iohn. 18. for his kingdom was not of this world. The fourth is in the obſeruation of the law of Moſes, ye ceremonies &amp; traditions of the elders, in the which they are too much &amp; ſuperſtitiouſly addicted. The Chriſtians affirme the law to be fulfilled in Chriſt, &amp; the ceremonies which were but for a time, to bee abrogated, &amp; that there are no more precepts to bee kept, then concerne the loue of God &amp; their neighbor. The fifth conſiſteth in the ſaluation of the ſoule. The Iewes ſay, that man is to be ſaued by good works, &amp; that God wil rewarde euery man according vnto his works. The maner they miſtake: heere the Papiſtes ſhew whoſe children they are.Act. 4. Abacuk. 2. Act. 3. Luk. 17. The Chriſtians confeſſe no ſaluation, but by Ieſus Chriſt, and that the iuſt liueth by faith in him, &amp; that they are taught, when they haue doone all which they are commanded to ſay, they are vnprofitable ſeruants, &amp; that ye vertues &amp; workes which God crowneth or rewardeth in them, are not theirs, but his, that gaue them, &amp; whē he crowneth

them, he extolleth his own mercy wher by they are ſaued. The ſixt &amp; the laſt is the time of Chriſt, the Meſsias his comming. The Iews alledge many propheſies at his comming not to haue beene fulfilled, the reduction of ye exile, the reedifiyng of the temple, the reſtoring of Sodome &amp; Samaria into their former ſtate, ye whole earth to be filled with his glory, with many other things. The Chriſtians iuſtifie them all to be fulfilled, &amp; that the Iewes vnderſtanding all the promiſes, groſely, earthly, &amp; literally,2. Corinth. 3 do therin erre, &amp; deceiue themſelues: For the letter killeth, but the ſpirit it is that giueth life.
               Naucler. Generat. 22. Sabellic. Enead. 8. lib. 6 Suidas. 
               Mahomet eſpied the blindnes of this natiō, &amp; among other things rebuked them for denying, that Ieſus was borne of the Virgin Marie, as the prophets had foreſhewed. Suidas reporteth an hiſtorie, which hee learned of a Iew, that the phariſes at Ieruſalem called a counſell to finde out the father of Ieſus. They inioined certaine women to ſearch his mother, ye women affirmed they found her a virgin, then was it recorded in ye famous regiſter book of the

temple, Ieſus the ſonne of God, and of Mary the Virgin. This condemneth both Iew and Saracen,
               Laonic. de reb. Turc. lib. 3. furthermore this falſe Prophet ioyneth with the Rechabits, he forbiddeth the drinking of wine, yet I finde that he dranke him ſelfe drunke therewith, &amp; his people do it by ſtealth: If they bee taken they are ſette alonge vppon a planke with a gagge in their mouth, &amp; a ladell of boyling leade poured therein.Ieremy. 35 Math. 26. 1. Timoth. 5. Epheſ. 5. After the example of our ſauiour Chriſt, the Chriſtians drinke wine, but according vnto ye rule preſcribed: wherin there is no exceſſe. It is permitted the Saracens by this law to haue fowre wiues,Iacob. de Vorag. legend. 177. Laonic. de reb. Turc. lib. 3. Anton. cron though they be of nigh kin (ſaith Iacob) yea fiue (ſaith Laonicus) marrying them virgins, &amp; to take beſide as many, emptitias &amp; captiuas. Of them which they haue bought &amp; taken captiues,
                as their ability will ſerue to maintaine cōtrary to ye ordināce of God, there ſhal be two in one fleſh. Volaterran writeth.Volater. lib. 12. Geneſ. 
               
                  Voluptates corporis futurae foelicitati minime officere arbitrātur:
                  
                     They think that the pleaſurs of the body hurt not nether hinder at all the foelicity of the life to come.
                  
               
               
This doctrine is the ſinke of Sodome, the fleſh is the matter, ye burning luſt is a preamble of the fire falling from heauen, &amp; the iuſtice of God threatneth euerlaſting fire &amp; torments for ſuch Mahometical Sodomits. They are ielous ouer their wiues, whoſe faces, when they go abroad are couered, leaſt theſe fiery people be therewith inflamed. Mahomet (ſaith Coelius) had 40.
               Coelius. wiues, &amp; further he gloried of himſelfe,Nicol. Clenard. 1. Epiſt. Anton. cron part. 2. tit. 13 cap. 5. yt it was giuen him from aboue to exceede (ſaith Clenard) 10. mē (ſaith Antoninus) 50. men in carnall luſt &amp; venerie. An other abhominable fact he cōmitted, yt which a Chriſtian pen is loth to write, and a chaſt mouth loth to vtter, &amp; modeſt ears are loth to heare, yet ye filthines of this falſe Prophet may not be concealed, he cōmitted buggerie with an Aſſe.Bonfin. lib. 8 decad. Bernard in Roſar. part. 1. ſerm 14. Anton. vt ſupra 
               Bonfinius writeth it. Again, he cōmitted adultery with another mans wife, which was vpō diſpleaſure frō her huſband, &amp; fearing ye murmur of ye people, he fained yt he receiued a paper frō heauē, wherin it was permitted him ſo to do, to ye ende he might beget prophets &amp; worthy mē.

And herevpō the fooliſh law of diuorce vſed this day among the Saracens, is groūded, that a man may put away his wife three times, and ſo many times receiue her again, after that ſhe hath been ſo many times known by an other man. The Paradiſe this prophet deuiſed for his people, bewraieth his lewd diſpoſition. He promiſeth them garmentes of ſilke, with all ſortes of colours, bracelets of golde and Amber, parlours and banqueting houſes vpon flouds and riuers, veſſels of gold and ſiluer, Angels ſeruing them, bringing in gold milk, in ſiluer wine, lodginges furniſhed, cuſhings, pillows, &amp; down beds, moſt beutiful women to accompany thē, maidens &amp; virgins with twinckling eies, gardēs and orchards with harbors, fountaines ſprings, &amp; al maner of pleaſant fruit, riuers of milk, hony, &amp; ſpiced wine, al maner of ſweet odors, perfumes, &amp; fragrāt ſents, &amp; to be ſhort,Anton. Chronic. 
               
                  quicquid carnes ad edendum concupiſcunt,
                  
                     whatſoeuer the fleſh ſhall deſire to eate.
                  
               
Thus fleſhly people haue a fleſhly religiō,Iacobus de Vorag. legend. 177. &amp; a fleſhly paradiſe to inhabit. One thing I may not

ouerſhip which I referre to your ſelues either for the ſtrangenes thereof to caſt you into a dumpe or wonder, or elſe at the follie of the Prophet to moue you to a laughter. he ſaith they ſhal ſee in Paradiſe goodly Angels and theſe ſhall haue goodly eies, and one Angell ſhall haue as muche ſpace betweene both his eies as is in ye heauens betweene ſunne riſing, and ſunne ſetting. I haue not as yet ſaide any thing of their faſting, the ſame is continued the ſpace of one moneth in euery yeare, and preciſely kept from morning to night,Laonic. Volaterr. Anton. Math. Pariſ. in Henric. 3. Bernard. the Starres no ſooner appeare, but they fall to feaſting, they ſitte vp all nighte, they geue themſelues to ſurfeting, drunkennes, &amp; venerie: this is to waſh (ſaith Bernard) Laterem crudam, a greene tile,
                the more water ye poure thereon, the more durt ye make. To bee ſhorte (leaſt theſe extreame follies, bee ouer tedious vnto you) this falſe Prophet dieth, &amp; ſuch ſeruice, ceremonies, and ſuperſtition, he inioyned his people, the ſame they obſerued, Hee that ſucceeded him, commaunded Mahomets Tombe to be adorned,

the corps to be worſhipped, his anniuerſary or yerely remembrance to bee ſolē
               nized, pilgrimage from all places to be made to the temple of Mecha, where he lieth cheſted, the Saracenicall pilgrims haue promiſe of ſantitye and righteouſneſſe by viſiting his: Sepulchre 

                  Putantes ſe (ſaith Laonicus) hinc maxime colligere Religionē,
                  
                     Thinking that by this chiefly they gather Religion.
                  
                
Many repaire thither yearely from Aſia, Affricke, and Europe, for to worſhip, and many others ſtaying at home, deliuer them money, to offer for them, &amp; therin repoſe no leſſe holines. There is prouiſion made for theſe paſſingers two famous receptacles which we call Hoſpitalles not farre from Mecha, with all manner of Officers and Prieſtes to praye for the founders Soules: The manner of their worſhippe you ſhall alſo heare. The Arabians receiued and learned of the Indians, to worſhip the Goddeſſe Venus, Mahomet confirmed the ſame with a lawe ſo that in the honour of Venus, the Saracens, to this day (as I ſaid before) keepe friday

for their Sabbaoth. As the Indians worſhipped Venus naked, ſo Mahomet commanded the Saracens, men and women yearely to worſhip in the Temple of Mecha all naked, excepting a brieth or apporne to couer that which nature commaunded to bee kept in ſecrete, and therin to carry ſtones to throw about ye temple, &amp; to ſtone the deuill. Omitting theſe heatheniſh abhomination and not forgetting the ſuperſtition mentioned a little before. I woulde haue the church of Rome to beholde here in the lawe of Mahomet her founder in ſuperſtition, &amp; ſhameful enormities borowed either of Mahomet, or of the Heathens his aſſociats. The flocking to Tombs &amp; ſepulchres, ye worſhipping of dead corpſes, bones, &amp; reliques, ye viſiting Limina Petri, diriges, anniuerſaries, or yearely ſeruice ouer the dead, praying for ſoules pilgrimages to ſaintes, and ſhrines of the dead, ſending of money in their abſence, the opinion of holineſſe and religion therein, we neede not ſay it is popiſhe, nay it is Turkiſh and Mahometicall. And to the end they may be therin,

the better perſwaded let them,Laonic. rer. Turc. lib. 3. Antoninus Cron. part. 2. tit. 13. cap. 5. Cuſpinian. Ludouicus Rom. patritius. Nauigat. lib. 1. cap. 8. &amp; 13. peruſe Laonicus, Antoninus, &amp; Cuſpinianus with others that write thereof.
            Alſo as in the yeare one thouſand fiue hundred and three, one Ludouicus Romanus with a great number of Marchants paſſing by Mecha, founde the experience of Mahometicall Illuſions, for when the Idolatrous Prieſtes of Mahomet vnderſtood of the numbre of paſſingers which harbored not farre of (to the end there might be an opinion of holineſſe conceiued of this falſe Prophet) with certain deuices they caſt fire into the Aere, &amp; at midnight ran about like madde men, crying: 

                  Mahomet the Prophet of God is a riſing, O Prophet: O God. Mahomet will riſe. Pardon me O God.
In like ſorte of late yeares, wee haue been acquainted with faigned miracles, of Romiſh Idolatrie ſhewed at the Tombes of the deade beeing the feates of Satan: winking, ſmiling, ſweating, frowning, mouing, with other Illuſions, yea ſpeaking, and geuing of aunſwers. Bernarde came to a Church of Spire in Germany, whereas

he lifted vp his eies to behold the Images of the Church, ye Image of our Lady ſaid vnto him: Good morrow Bernard, He perceiuing (ſaith the hiſtory) Praeſtigias Demonis, the falſhood of Monkes by the inſtigation of the Deuill, made this aunſwere: 

                  Paule forbiddeth a woman to ſpeake in the Congregation.
               
               Ludouic. Rom. lib. 1. cap. 1. &amp; 18. Lib. 2. cap. 6. The Saracens vſe inuocation of mediatours to make interceſſion for them. They call vpon Abraham, and Iſaac, They honor Nabi, Bubacar, Othomar, Aumar, Fatoma, the followers of Mahomet with others. They haue Herenutes, and ſolitary men, ſuche as vowed chaſtitie in the ſeruice of Mahomet, in whom there is great opinion of holines, but what is holines, and chaſtitie, without knowledge of the true God and faith in Ieſus Chriſt? all without Chriſt is to no purpoſe,
            Now (good people, and beleued in our Sauiour Chriſt) as the deare children of God, who is ielouſe ouer you &amp; your ſeruice, haue great regarde vnto yourſelues and the foundation ye build vpon: leaſt your building fall. The wiſe

builder buildeth vpon the Rocke, Ieſus Chriſt, and that is vnremoueable. Lett your faith be fixed in Ieſus Chriſt, the true and onely Sauiour of the world,Math. 7. then hell-gates ſhall not be able to preuaile againſt you.Math. 16. 
               Mahomet vnwiſely hath builded vpon the ſand, his doctrine hath no ſure warrant, hee hath reiected the true corner ſtone, that cloſeth the building, Ieſus Chriſt, he hath lewdly mingled together his lome, and morter of Heathens, Iewes, and falſe Chriſtians, his timber warpeth, and ſhrinketh, beeing not ſeaſoned with antiquitie of the truth, but with the ſappe of late inuention, his walles are but painted papers, a ſhewe of religion, his lightes are but darkenes, wherein his followers ſtumble, and ſtumbling they fall, and falling, they plunge in euerlaſting perdition. There are reaſons and arguments to ſettle our minds, and ſtay our conſciences in the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, and to proue that Mahomets law is no true religion. Firſt Mahomets lawe is not warranted, or grounded vpon the only true &amp; pure word of God, therefore

               Mahomets law is no true religion, hee patched togeather his Alcoron of the lawes and doctrines of Heathens, Indians, and Arabians, of ſuperſtitious Iewes, of Rechabits, of falſe Chriſtians and Heretickes, as Neſtorians, Sabelliās, Manichees, Arrians, Cerinthians, Macedonians, Eunomians, and Nicolaits, of illuſions, and inuentions of his owne braine: and laſtly for further credit he borrowed ſome out of the old and new Teſtament. God will not be thus ſerued, he deliuered his mind of old vnto Iſraell in this ſort: and he continueth the ſame God ſtill:Deut. 12. 
               
                  Ye ſhall not doe euery man what ſeemeth him good in his owne eies. Whatſouer I commaund you take heede ye doe it, thou ſhalt put nothing thereto, nor take ought therefrom.
               
               Deut. 22. Againe: 

                  Thou ſhalt not plough with an Oxe and an Aſſe togeather, thou ſhalt not ſow thy Vineyard with diuers kindes of ſeedes, thou ſhalt not weare a garment of diuers ſortes, as of wollen, and linnen togeather.
               
Wee haue commandement not ſo eat the paſcal Lamb, boyled or ſodden in water:
               Exod. 12. 
               Chriſt Ieſus is our paſcal Lamb,

the water is mans traditions wherewith he may not be mingled,1. Corinth. 5 wee may not Math. 6. Eccle. 13.
               
                  ſerue God and Mammon. What fellowſhip (ſaith Syrach) hath Hyena with a dogge.
               
               2. Corinth. 6 
               ſaint Paule aduiſeth the Corinthians:
               
                  Bee not vnequally yoaked with the Infidels
               
By reaſon he ſheweth this may not be: 

                  For what felowſhip hath righteouſnes with vnrighteouſnes, and what communion hath light with darkenes? and what concord hath Christ with Belial? or what part hath the beleeuer with the Infidel? and what agreement hath the temple of God with Idols? for yee are the temple of the liuing God.
               
Our Sauiour rebuketh the Scribes and Phariſees for tranſgreſſing the commandements of God,Math. 15. by meane of their traditions, he pronounceth their worſhip vain, in teaching the doctrines &amp; precepts of men, the iudicial ſentence he geueth thereof is this: Euery plant (yt is all maner of doctrine) which my heauenly father hath not planted ſhalbe rooted vp. Secondly the religion of Mahomet
                conſiſteth in fleſhly &amp; naturall delightes in corporal pleaſures, therefore the law of Mahomet is a moſt wicked &amp; falſe

religion, the heathen Philoſophers by ye rule of naturall reaſon haue found this an abſurde opinion.Auicenna Metaphyſic. 
               Auicenna one of Mahomets owne ſecte hath miſliked with this, ſaying, 

                  The law which our Mahomet hath geuen vs ſheweth the perfection of felicity to conſiſt in thoſe things which concerne the body but there is an other promiſe which is comprehended onely by vnderſtanding, and therefore the wiſe and ſages of olde had a greater deſire to expreſſe the felicity of the ſoule then of the body, the which bodely felicity though it were graunted them, yet they regarded not, neither eſteemed it in compariſon of the felicitie which is coupled with the principall veritie:
               
His looſe doctrine of marriages, his abuſe of faſting, and his deſcription of Paradiſe (ſpoken of before) deliuer vnto vs that there is herein ſmall difference between Epicuriſme, Atheiſme, &amp; Mahometiſme,
               Luke. 16. The glutton in the goſpel that was cloathed in purple &amp; fine white and fared delitiouſly euery day, ſheweth vnto vs how God fauoureth &amp; accepteth of ſuch people.Rom. 14. 
               
                  The kingdome of God (ſaith the Apoſtle) Is not meate, nor drinke but

righteouſnes and peace, and ioy in the holy Ghost, for whoſoeuer in theſe things ſerueth Chriſt (herein the true felicitye conſiſteth) is acceptable vnto God, and approoued of men.
               
               Math. 4. Satan the ſchoolemaſter of Mahomet ſhewed a glotonous diſpoſition when he would haue had the ſtones to be made bread. His diſciple muſt content himſelf wt the anſwer made vnto ye maiſter:Deutr. 8. 
               
                  Man liueth not by bread onely but by euery worde that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord.
               
Our ſauiour ſaith:Ioh. 4. 
               
                  the true worſhippers ſhal worſhip the father (not in corporal delights &amp; pleaſurs) In ſpirit &amp; truth, (this is ye maner) For the father requireth euen ſuch to worſhip him.
               
Again an argumēt reduced of ye nature of God God is a ſpirite and they that worſhippe him muſt worſhip him in ſpirit &amp; truth. And yt I maye deliuer the whole vnto you in few wordes, perfect felicitie conſiſteth in knowing of God, in beleeuing in God, in louing of God, and enioying of God, warraunted by the wordes of our Sauiour.Iohn. 17. 
               
                  This is life euerlaſting that they knowe thee to bee the onely very God and whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Christ.
               
               
                Thirdly ye law of Mahomet was eſtabliſhed through wiles, deceit, ſubteltie, &amp; lies, therfore ye law of Mahomet is a moſt wicked religion. Firſt he hauing ye falling ſicknes perſwaded his wife &amp; others yt it was the power of God &amp; the preſence of the Angel Gabriell that fel him. Sergius the hereticall Monke was at hande &amp; bare falſe witnes to ye ſame, ſaith Zonaras.
               Ioh. Zonar. Annal. tom. 3. He told them yt the tame Doue which hee taught to feede at his eare was ſometime an Angell, &amp; ſometime the holy ghoſt. He had three leude companions to deuiſe &amp; face out lies wt him. Whē he perceiued ye mē gaue eare vnto him, he framed that the Angel Gabriell had caried him to Ieruſalem, and thence to haue lifted him vp to heauen, &amp; there to haue learned the ſecrets of his law.Anton. cron. part. 2. tit. 13. cap. 5. He made ye 
               Saracens beleeue (ſaith Antoninus) yt before God made ye world there was written in the throne of God: there is no god but ye god of Mahomet. whē he had framed his Alcoran &amp; boūd it vp faire he cauſed ſecretly a wild Aſſe to be takē &amp; the book to be bound about his necke, &amp; as he preached vnto ye people,

vpon a ſodain he ſtood amazed as if ſome great ſecretie were reuealed vnto him from aboue. He brake out &amp; tolde ye people: Behold god hath ſent you a law from heauen, go to ſuch a deſert there ye ſhal find an Aſſe, &amp; a book tied about his neck. The people ran in great haſt they found it ſo as he had ſaid. They take the Aſſe, they bring the book, they honor the prophet. Touching diuorced,Auierus lib. 2. cap. 12. Ioh. Leo. lib. 3. cap. 23. Aphric. &amp; ſeperated wiues, he tolde ye 
               Saracens he had receiued a paper from heauē. He vſed ſouth-ſaying &amp; diuination the which at Feſſa, a Citie of Mauritama vnto this day is called Zarragia.
               Bernard in. Roſar. part. 1. ſerm. 14 He perſuaded his folowers that at ye end of ye world he ſhould be trāſformed into the forme of a mightie Ram full of lockes &amp; long fleeces of wool. And that all that held of his Law ſhoulde bee as fleas ſhrooding themſelues in his fleeces, and that he would iumpe into heauen and ſo conuay them all thither. Theſe and ſuche like were his ſleightes and vntruthes without warrauntize of Gods word, without reaſon and probable ſhew of truth.Faſcicul. temporum. Satan being coniured to deliuer the truth

of the Alcoran of Mahomet ſaide, that therin were compriſed twelue thouſand lies, and the reſt was truth, by all likelihood very little:Deutr. 18. 
               
                  In the like reſpect God threatneth Iſrael,
                   ſaying: The Prophet that ſhall preſume to ſpeake, a word many name, which I haue not commaunded him to ſpeake, or that ſpeaketh in the name of other Gods, euen the ſame Prophet ſhall die. And if thou thinke in thine heart: how ſhall we know the word which the Lord hath not ſpoken? When a Prophet ſpeaketh in the name of the Lord, if the thing follow not, nor come to paſſe that is the thing which the Lord hath not ſpoken, but the Prophet hath ſpoken it preſumptuouſly.
                If we apply this rightly vnto Mahomet wee ſhall not finde any one thing in veritie and truth the whiche hee ſpake that came to paſſe but whatſoeuer hee wroughte was thorough wiles, fraude, and ſubteltie, let his prophecie of his aſſention after his death bee a preſident for all whiche was  not performed. Fourthly the law of Mahomet was thruſt in by ſecular power &amp; force of armes, by battels &amp; bloudſhed, therfore the law of Mahomet is a moſt wicked religion, Paulus Diaconus writeth

yt he ſpent ten yeares in Armes ſubduing to his raigne,Paul. Diac. rer. Rom. lib. 18. &amp; compelling to his religion, thereof writeth Mathew Paris in this ſort:Math. Paris hiſtor. Angl. Henric. 3. 
               
                  The law of the Saracens (the deuill inditing the ſame by the miniſtery of Sergius the Monke &amp; heretick) Mahomet wrote in the Arabike tōgue, &amp; taught them.
               
               
                  A gladio cepit, per gladium tenetur, &amp; in gladio terminatur:
                  
                     It began of the ſworde, it is helde by the ſworde, &amp; it is finiſhed or ended in the ſword.
                  
               
               Idem. 
               Mahomets own words vnto ye 
               Saracēs are theſe 

                  Non ſum cū miraculis aut indicijs ad vos miſſꝰ ſed in gladio rebelles puniturus &amp;c.
                  
                     I am not ſēt vnto you with miracles &amp; ſigns, but with the ſword to puniſh ſuche as reſiſt me. If any therefore receaue not my prophecy &amp; precept, &amp; wil not willingly enter into this our faith, if he be vnder our iuriſdiction he ſhall die or be cō
                        pelled to pay tribute the price of his incredulity &amp; ſo liue. They that are not of this faith &amp; dwel in other countries I charge &amp; commaūd that opē warrs be proclaimed &amp; armor taken againſt them vntill they bee cōſtrained to turne vnto the faith. They that will not conſent vnto our doctrine ſhall die the death, their wiues and children

ſhalbee committed to perpetuall ſlauerie to our Gallies.
                  
               
The Scythians from whence theſe Turkes came, are an impatient kind of people.Naucler. generat. 22. Whē they warred vnder Heraclius the Emperour againſt the king of Perſia they were too too erneſt for their pay. The Clark of the band, in their greedines called thē doogs, thereof roſe a mutine, they made their mone vnto the better ſort of their coūtry, they forſook their Emperor. This was their firſt fall from Chriſtiā kings &amp; Emperors wherof ther enſued great miſchief.Fulgoſ. Egnat. Sabell. This furious &amp; cruel diſpoſitiō an other of ye ſame name with this falſe prophet, an Emperor of ye 
               Turks ſhewed at Cō
                  ſtantinople. Miſſing an aple vpō a certaine tree in his Orchard, he gaue commandement that the bowels of three pages that were about him ſhould be ript that it might be knowne which of them had eaten it. The time at this preſent will not ſerue to ſhewe the infinite ſtreames of Chriſtian and Innocent bloude theſe enemies of God moſt cruelly ſhedde. There commeth to my remembrance among other hiſtories their

doings in Poland,
               Iohn Herburt. hiſt. Polon. lib. 7. cap. 4. where at one battell they ſlewe of Chriſtians as many, as their ſingle eares did fill nine greate ſackes. Theſe people are wild, ſauage, and cruel, Mahomet made them a law accordingly, ſaying:Paul. Diac. rer Rom. lib. 18. 
               
                  He that ſlayeth his enemie, or is ſlaine of his enemie. lette him enter and poſſeſſe paradiſe.
               
This is contrary to Gods word, in the old and new teſtament, this is contrary to the rule of charitie, which ſlayeth not, but forgiueth the enemie. The Paradiſe of Mahomet muſt then be the bottomles pitte of Hell. Of the contrary, the true word of God,1. Corinth. 2 and the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt was not plāted neither by force of arms, neither by eloquence of words, neither by enticing ſpeach of mannes wiſedome, but by the worke of the bleſſed ſpirite and power of God. S. Paule putteth the Corinthians in remembraunce thereof, ſaying: 1. Cor. 1. 
               
                  Brethren, you ſee your calling, howe that not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble, but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe, &amp; God hath choſen the weake thinges of the

world to confound the mightie things. And vile things of the world, and things which are deſpiſed hath God choſen, and things which ar not to bring to nought things that are, that no fleſh ſhould reioice in his preſence.
                
It might ſeeme very ſtrange, that 12. men, the ſeruants of any king or emperour, beeing abiect perſons, without weapon or armour, ſhoulde ſubdue vnto themſelues from the king or emperour, the whole dominion. It might ſeeme very ſtrange, that a few vnlearned &amp; vnlettered men ſhoulde confound &amp; put to ſilence all ſubtil Logitians, al ſage philoſophers, al ſkilful Aſtronomers, &amp; profound Diuines. It might ſeeme verye ſtrange, yt a few men naked &amp; frendleſſe, ſhould conquer the whole world. The 12 Apoſtles are ſent forth to preach according vnto the inſtitution of our ſauiour) &amp; cōmanded 

                  they ſhall poſſeſſe neither gold nor ſiluer,
                  Math. 10. 
                  nor money in their purſes, nor a ſcrip for their iurney, nor two coats, nor ſhoes nor a ſtaffe,
               
being ſimple men, vnlearned, &amp; of one language, yet haue they cōfounded the wiſe, cōfuted the learned, cōuerted all languages, &amp; conquered ye whole world vnto their maſter Chriſt. This is

it which Chryſoſtom calleth:Chryſoſt. in 1. cap. Act. apoſt. hom. 1 
               
                  Maximū miraculū, the greatest miracle: orbē terrarū abſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      miraculis, à duodecim pauperibus &amp; illiteratis hominibus attractū.
                  
                     That the whole world ſhould be caried away without miracles (alone) by 12. poore &amp; vnlearned men.
                  
                They woar no armor,Math. 10. they proclame no warres, they were authors of no ſeditiō, our ſauiour bequeathed vnto thē peace, they preached peace whē they came to city or houſe, their ſalutatiō was, peace be in this houſe, &amp; ye ſpirit of peace was reſiant amōg thē. They cōpelled no man, as Mahomet &amp; his diſciples did. Tertullian writeth:Tertul. ad ſcapulam. 
               Sed nec religionis eſt cogere religionem, quae ſpōte ſuſcipi debeat, nō vi: cū &amp; hoſtiae ab animo lubenti expoſtulētur. 

                     But it is not the nature of religiō to cōtrain religiō, which ought to be receiued willingly, not by cōpulſion, whē as ſacrifices are required of a willing mind.
                  
Lactantius hath ye like,Lactant. inſtitut. lib. 5. cap. 20. reaſoning wt ye infidels yt cōpelled ye chriſtiās to ſacrifice. 

                  Nō opus eſt vi &amp; iniuria, quia religio cogi nō poteſt.
                  
                     Ye need not vſe force &amp; violēce, for religiō may not be cōstrained.
                  
                He ſheweth ye practiſe of ye Chriſtians, and the reaſon thereof.
            
               
               
                  Nemo à nobis retinetur inuitus, invtilis eſt enim Deo qui fide ac deuotione caret.
                  
                     Wee holde no man againſt his wil, for he is vnprofitable to God that wanteth faith and deuotion.
                  
               
This compulſion is to be vnderſtood of Chriſtian toward Heathen, or Heathen towards Chriſtian, but when as any receiue the Chriſtian faith, vowe their ſeruice vnto the onely true GOD, matriculate their names in the congregation of the faithfull, and afterwardes decline, giuing themſelues vnto carnalitie, raiſing of ſchiſme, broaching of hereſies, and falſhoode, the whippe of Chriſt muſt be taken in hand to purge the houſe of God, the 
                  ••••
               e of diſcipline and correction muſt be vſed the magiſtrate muſt draw the ſworde, and execute Iuſtice according vnto the lawes of God, &amp; Chriſtian Princes, eſtabliſhed and decreed for the aduauncing of pietie, and rooting out of ſinne,Auguſt. ad Bonifac. Epiſt. 50. and all iniquity. Auguſtine diſcourſeth hereof at large, and ſheweth how heretikes and ſchiſmatikes by imperial lawes and conſtitutions, are forcibly to be reformed. Of olde the Chriſtians

gaue almes and reliefe vnto the poore of themſelues (charitie dieth) they are now taxed and ſeaſed: of olde Chriſtian deuotion moued men to faſt (deuotion dieth) they haue now daies &amp; times aſſigned them: of olde they repaired to the Church of great zeale, (zeale dieth) they are now enioined by penal Lawes: of olde being mindfull of Chriſts death, they frequented ſundrie times to the Lordes Table (forgetfulnes is come in place) they are now called vpon, certain times in the yeare: of olde Chriſt was ſincerely &amp; faithfully ſerued, his worde purely taught, Chriſtian Princes dutifully obeyed (the feare of God was before their eyes) but nowe a daies there is corruption crept in, papiſme, idolatry, treaſon &amp; conſpiracie, practiſed by falſe Chriſtians. They fall within compaſſe of the Lawes, they haue iuſtice ſhewed them, they are ſeuerely puniſhed &amp; chaſtiſed, this is no perſecution, this is no compulſion to the faith, but correction for falling from the faith, this is the rule of godlineſſe, which Mahomet obſerued not. Fifthly, the lawe of Mahomet is 
               
not witneſſed and confirmed by ſignes wonders, and miracles, therefore the Lawe of Mahomet is a muſt falſe religion. He ſaid vnto the Saracens of himſelfe:Math. Paris hiſt. Angl. in Henric. 3. 
               
                  Non ſum cum miraculis aut indiciis ad vos miſſus.
                  
                     I am not ſent vnto you with myracles and ſignes.
                  
               
There was no diuine power ſhewed in all his practiſe. This Lawe was not reuealed vnto himſelfe, he confeſſed himſelf to be altogether vnlearned, hee had three helpers, as I ſaide before, hee called himſelfe a prophet, when as the Law and prophets ende in Iohn the baptiſt. And after him we are to looke for no mo Prophets, The prophets of olde arrogated not any ſuch name or title vnto themſelues, but by long tract of time, their holineſſe of lifs, the wonders they wrought, and the truth of Gods word which they deliuered, declared them to bee no leſſe. As for this falſe prophet, his beaſtlines of life, his want of teſtimonie from aboue, his vntruthes and abſurdities, deliuer his doctrine to be moſt damnable.Exod. 19.20. Deutr. The law of God which Moſes receiued, was deliuered after a moſt wonderful manner.

God ſtood vpon mount Sinai, there was fire, there was thunder, there was lightening, there was darkenes, there was the ſounde of the trumpetes heard, the voice of the Lord was mighty, the foundations of the earth ſhooke, the mountaine ſmoaked, and the people trembled. The prophets and ſeruants of God ſucceſſiuely in the times and ages following, confirmed their meſſage and embaſies with ſtraunge ſignes &amp; tokens. The birth of our Sauiour Chriſt, the preaching of the Goſpell, the ſealing vp of the ſame with his bloud after moſte ſtrange &amp; marueilous ſightes, declared him to be ye only true Meſsias, &amp; ſauiour of the worlde, authoriſed his doctrine, &amp; confirmed ye faith of ye Chriſtians. A virgin to bring forth, Angels ſinging glory, ſhepheards rūning to ſearch a ſtrāg ſtar appearing, wiſemen cōming frō far, the heauēs opening, ye holy ghoſt deſcēding, the father ſoūding, this is my Son, Iohn
                ye baptiſt pointing wt ye finger, Beholde the lamb of God: The blind, ye deafe, ye dumb, the lame, the ſicke, all cured, &amp; the deade raiſed to life. Theſe deliuer vnto vs the

power of the moſte high and mightie God. Againe at his paſſion, palpable darkneſſe, the vaile of the temple renting, the earth ſhaking, the rockes cleauing, the graues opening, the deade riſing, and yeelding teſtimonie to the liuing of the truth in Chriſt. Laſt of all, his riſing from the deade, his inſtructing of the Apoſtles, his viſible Aſcenſion into the Heauens, and his ſending of the holy Ghoſt according vnto promiſe, perſwadeth ſufficiently in all reſpectes, that his doctrine is the moſte ſacred truth of the onely true and euerlaſting  GOD. Sixtly and laſtly, the Lawe of Mahomet is a confuſed kinde of doctrine, patched together of contraries, diſſenting and varying within it ſelfe, therefore the Lawe of Mahomet is a moſt wicked Religion. Sergius the Monke, Iohn of Antioch, and the ſuperſtitious Iewe, patched together, according vnto their variyng mindes, diuerſe doctrine, but in this they agreed, in ſetting downe lies and falſhood.Anton. cron part. 2. tit. 13 cap. 5. After the death of Mahomet (ſayth Antoninus) the diſciples of this falſe Prophet

could not agree in the reading,Ludouic. Rom. Patritius. nauigat. lib. 1. cap. 12. pointing vnderſtanding and expounding of the Alcoran. Some added, ſome diminiſhed ſome maymed, and ſome corrupted the Lawe. The Iewes put in what pleaſed them beſt, the Heretikes vrged their opinions, the Heathens alſo pleaded for themſelues, ſo that the Alcoran was deſpiſed, and of no reputation, and woorthely. In proceſſe of time, after greate diſſention, one Elehege beeyng choſen to rayne ouer them, commaunded all coppyes ſhoulde bee brought vnto hym, of them all he made one booke, which is the Alcoran, that they haue at this day, and the reſt he cauſed to be burned to aſhes. There are yet three thinges to bee conſidered in this falſe Religion, which I will briefly runne ouer. Firſt, what  was the occaſion of the beginning therof? Diſſention among Prynces, and diuiſion among thoſe that called themſelues Chriſtians. Sathan eſpyed it, and put foorth his Seruaunt Mahomet to woorke miſchiefe. Heraclius the Emperour, and Choſdroes Kyng of Perſia, were at deadly enmitie, warring

one againſt the other. The Scythian Nation fell from them both, and founde Mahomet to theyr ringe-leader. Againe, the Church of GOD was then lamentably diuided. Peter Archbiſhoppe of Conſtantinople, fell into a deteſtable hereſie, ſucked out of the ſchoole of Valentinus, Marcion, &amp; Manes the Heretikes. Iacobus Syrus (of him haue the Iacobits in the Eaſt their name) tooke part with Seuerus: he held that Chriſt neyther dyed, neyther ſuffered, but an other for him, which opinion Mahomet followed. So that the Church was troubled with Neſtorians Iacobites, Monothelits, and the Monkes of Benedicts order, which then began to ſwarme like locuſtes vppon the earth. Not onely this, but alſo ye Church of Rome beganne to lift vp her ſelfe in pride &amp; abhomination, the Pope calling himſelfe vniuerſall Biſhop. God was highly diſpleaſed with this wickednes, and ſuffered Mahomet to riſe as a rod or ſcourge to whippe his people. Wee are nowe to pray that GOD at length

will be reconciled with his people, and that hee will caſt the rodde into the fire. The ſecond thing we haue to conſider, is why this falſe religion of Mahomet
                is ſo vniuerſally receyued: Carnalitie and fleſhlineſſe is the cauſe. It intreateth of venerie, fleſhlie delightes, and temporall pleaſures, therefore it is become plauſible to manie.Flor. Hiſtor. 
               Mathew of Weſtmonaſter writeth: 

                  Vnde credo quod ſi hodie viueret, multos inueniret diſcipulos.
                  
                     Whereupon I beleeue if Mahomet lyued at this day hee ſhoulde finde many Diſciples.
                  
               
               Mathias â Michou de Sarmat. Aſian. lib. 1. cap. 5. In the yeare 1246 Innocentius 4. ſent to great Cham the Emperour of the Tartarians, perſwading him to receyue the Chriſtian faith, to leaue ſhedding of Innocent bloude, and to ſerue GOD in Spirite and truth.
            At that time alſo came the Embaſſadoures of the Saracens, pleadynge and vrgyng hym to the Lawe of Mahomet, alleadging that it was eaſier, more tollerable, full of pleaſures, and more fitte for Warriours, then the Chriſtian fayth. Cham liked of the

conditions, he was carnally giuen, &amp; embraced 
               Mahomet vnto this day. Thirdly and laſtly, why is the Religion of Mahomet continued, being knowne to bee wicked,Anton. cron part. 2. tit. 13. cap. 5. carnall, and fleſhly? Mahomet made it death to diſpute thereof. If any ſpeake againſt me (ſaith he) 
                  proditoriè occidatur,
                  
                     Let him be traiterouſlye put to death,
                  
               
Againe: 
                  Sine audientia occidatur,
                  
                     let him be put to death without comming to his aunſwere.
                  
               
               Sabellic. Enead. 8. lib. 6 
               
                  Qua ſanctione (ſaith Sabellicus) palam fecit, nihil ſinceri in ea lege eſſe, &amp;c. 
                  
                     By which decree hee made manifeſt, that there is nothing ſounde in that Lawe, the which he couered as an hidde mysterye, and forbadde to bee reaſoned of, that the vulgar ſorte ſhoulde not knowe what was decreed or eſtabliſhed.
                  
               
I am nowe comming to that which I haue laſtlye promiſed to deliuer vnto you, to wit: that which concerneth our ſelues the way to pleaſe GOD, and meane to win thoſe that are without:Math. 5. 
               
                  When as our light ſo ſhineth before men, that they ſeeyng our good woorks, may glorifie our Father which is in heauen.
               
            
            
               And I will bee the ſhorter herein, for that I doubt not but you haue bene here tofore by mee out of this place often exhorted thereto. I feare mee (béloued in our Sauiour Chriſt) leaſt that I haue beene ouer tedious in the premiſſes, I haue the longer waded therein, not hauing at othertimes the like occaſion offered me to diſcourſe of the like matter. Chriſtian lights, Chriſtian fruits, &amp; holy cōuerſatiō, hath now moued this Saracen to ſerue the true God in the faith of Ieſus Chriſt. He is about 40. yeares of age (as he ſaith himſelfe) born at Nigropontus, of olde called Chalcides, a Citie of great fame in the Iſle Euboea, &amp; belonging ſometime vnto the Dukedome of Venice, but taken and ſubdued by the Turke, through the treaſon of one Thomas Liburne, maiſter Gunner of Nigropontus, in the yeare 1471. This Turke was taken captiue by the Spaniard, where he continued in great miſery the ſpace of 25. yeares, whome the moſte worthy knight S. Frauncis Drake found at Carthaginia. God ſhewed great mercy vnto this poore Turke, in calling him

home (with the prodigall childe in the Goſpell) by miſery, ſlauery, and captiuity, &amp; in ſending him a deliuerer, not onely for the preſent ſorrowes and miſerye, but to his endleſſe ioy &amp; ſolace in Chriſt Ieſus, bleſſed be his name therefore.
            This Saracen beyng reaſoned withall, what ſhould moue hym at this preſente to receyue the Chriſtian fayth: made anſwere, that experience of the wicked world, at Nigropontus his natiue cuntry, his miſery and captiuitie vnder the Spaniards, his trauaile hither, and the view of this lande, had beaten into him (as he ſaide) the knowledge of the true God. And further he faide, that if there were not a God in England, there was none no where. Two things (he did confeſſe) moued him to the Chriſtian faith. The one before his comming to England, ye other at his arriuall. Before his comming, the vertue, the modeſtie, the godlines, the good vſage, &amp; diſcrete gouernment of the Engliſh Chriſtians, &amp; among others (as he chiefly noted) he was moſt beholden vnto the Right worſhipfull knight S. Frauncis Drake, and the

worhty captaine W. Haukins, tearming them moſt worthy Chriſtians. After his arriual, he ſaw curteſie, gentlenes, frendly ſalutations of the people, ſuccour for him &amp; his cuntrimen, pitie &amp; compaſſion of the Engliſh men, &amp; withal he learned that the poore, the aged, the impotent, ye ſicke &amp; diſeaſed Chriſtians were prouided for, wheras in his cuntry, &amp; wher he had bene in captiuitie, ye poore, &amp; ſicke, &amp; diſeaſed were ſcorned, deſpiſed, &amp; accoū
               ted of as dogs. Theſe things moued this ſillye Saracene to the Chriſtian faith, and thereupon it is that I haue choſen for my text, the wordes of our Sauiour tending to ye ſame purpoſe.Math. 5. 
               
                  Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good woorks, and glorify your Father which is in heauen.
               
Hee was demaunded why for the ſpace of 25. yeares, beeing the time of his captiuitie in Spayne, hee receiued not the Chriſtian fayth. His aunſwere was: that hee had beene by a Frier ſollicited thereto, &amp; that he heard no more of him but the name of Chriſt, without inſtruction, or opening to his comfort any poynt of the faith (as he

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
hath bene here comfortably inſtructed.) And againe, that there were two things which he vtterly miſliked in the Spaniard (which diſſwaded him from the faith) his cruelty in ſhedding of bloud, and his Idolatry in worſhipping of Images. He that will haue a view of the crueltie of the Spaniard, let him reade The Spaniſh Colonie, written in the Caſtilian tongue by a Fryer, afterwards Byſhop, one Bartholmew de la Caſas, and lately trālated into engliſh. As for his idolatry, I refer ye ſhame therof to the founder, ye Antichriſt of Rome. I am not odiouſly to note any Chriſtiā nation more then other, with any particular vice. If there riſe any iar betwen man &amp; wife, let ſon &amp; daughter look that they make it not worſe: if diſcord happē betwene maiſter &amp; miſtres, ye ſeruantes may not blow ye fire of hatred: if vnkindnes grow betwene Chriſtian kings and Princes (as at this day betweene England &amp; Spain) It is not the part of ſubiects to aggrauat ye diſpleaſure but in al dutifulnes to obey their own princes, &amp; pray vnto God to eſtabliſh peace among

thē we ſee what ye 
               Saracen cōmendeth, and moueth him to glorifie the God of the Chriſtians, and what he diſcommē
               deth, and diſſwadeth him from the faith. Mahomet himſelf confeſſed (as it is alleadged) and therein highly commended the chriſtian faith:Math. Pariſ hiſtor. Angl. in Henric. 3 
               
                  That Ieſus was borne of the Virgin Mary, that he liued without ſinne among men, that he was a Prophet &amp; more then a Prophet, and that he aſcended into the heauens. Moreouer what time the ſage and learned among them came to Ieruſalem, and required the Gospell, and new Teſtament to be ſhewed them they kiſſed the booke, and had the puritie &amp; cleannes of the doctrin which Chriſt had taught, in admiration, and ſpecially the Gospell after Luke: The Angell Gabriell was ſent &amp;c. the which the learned ſort of them doe reade, and often report.
               
The Nigros in the kingdome of Senega,
               Aloyſ. Cadamuſt. Nauigat. cap. 16 beeing of the faith of Mahomet (ſaith Aloyſius Cadamuſtꝰ) are not malicious nether ſtubbornely bent againſt the Chriſtians: 

                  They are delighted with the behauiour of the Chriſtians, and they gather our faith and religion to be the holier and the better

in that we are welthier and richer then they are, drawing their reaſon from temporall to eternall things, they adde further that wee are highly beloued of our God, and they are ſo perſwaded for that our God geueth his people ſuch great riches, &amp; beatifieth them with ſo many ornamentes and giftes of body and mind and that ſuch a law cannot poſſibly be but of a good law maker.
               
               Cap. 25. The king of Senega was in maner throughly perſwaded to renounce the lawe of Mahomet but he feared his Nobility, and the loſſe of his Crowne. A nephewe of the kings earneſtly intreated Cadamuſtus to deliuer there the word of God,Mathias â Michou de Sarmat Aſian lib. 1. cap. 5. Muſda Fa. Beg. ad Elizabeth. Angl. Reg. ſo was he in loue wt the puritye thereof. Cham the Emperour of the Tartarians confeſſeth Ieſus to be the power and ſpirite of the great God. Muſda fa Beg, ſecretary to the great. Turke of Conſtantinople yt now is writing to the Queene of England as appeareth by his letters bearing date the 15. of March, and in the yeare of great Ieſu (ſo hee writeth) 1579. ſheweth the great affection his maiſter the Turke togeather with himſelfe beareth to this lande and of our religion

as it is interpreted he ſaith thus: 

                  We know that your ſoueraigne Maieſty among al the Chriſtians haue the moſt ſound religion, and therefore the Christians thoroughout the world enuy your highnes, whō if they could, they would hurt.
               
Wee heare what the enemye reporteth of our God, of Ieſus our Sauiour, and the worde of God which wee profeſſe, Satan is driuen mauger of his bearde, to confeſſe ye truth, the maieſty of our God is ſo great that the celeſtiall terreſtriall and infernall powers vowe thereto, the light, and ſhine of this godheade, is ſo cleare, that Satan with his miſt and darkeneſſe canne not ouerſhadowe it, the worde of God is ſo cleane and pure that the very enemye canne not ſtayne it. What ſhall wee ſaye of the Profeſſours of the ſame? we know what is required at our hands, &amp; it is often repeated in holy Scripture: be you holy for I am holy ſaith the Lorde, learne of me ſaith our Sauiour, Again: 

                  Let your light ſhine &amp;c.
               
               1. Peter. 2. 
               Peter writeth: 

                  ſhew forth the vertues of him that hath called you out of darkenes into his maruelous light.
                
               Paul exhorteth:Coloſſ. 4.
               
               
                  walke wiſely toward them that are without,
               
Againe wee are councelled to bee quiet medling with our owne buſines, working and getting our liuing with our owne hands to what ende?1. Theſſ. 4. 
               
                  That ye maye behaue your ſelues honeſtly towarde them that are without.
               
Hee alſo that will bee Paſtor and gouernour ouer the people, muſt warely walke leaſt the enemy note any bleamiſh in him. Therefore the Apoſtle writeth:1. Timoth. 3 
               
                  He muſt bee well reported of, euen of them that are without.
               
So that neither Iew, nor gentile, Turke, nor Saracen, neither Hereticke or falſe Chriſtian whatſoeuer, may iuſtly charge the Chriſtian faith with the life of the profeſſor.Philip. 2. 
               Saint Paul, exhorteth the Philippians: 
               
                  Doe all things without murmuring and reaſoning, that ye may be blameleſſe, &amp; pure, and the ſonnes of God without rebuke in the middeſt of a naughtie, and crooked Nation, among whom ye ſhine as lightes in the world.
               
This kinde of Chriſtian conuerſation ſhall bringe foure notable thinges to paſſe.  Firſt the Heathens, Turkes, and Saracens, ſeeing this holineſſe of life, will fall to a great wonder,

&amp; admiration, therof writeth Peter:
               1. Peter. 4. 
               It is ſufficient for vs that we haue ſpēt the time paſt of the life after the luſt of the gentiles, in wantōnes, luſtes, drunkennes, in gluttony, drinkings, &amp; abhominable Idolatries wherin it ſeemeth to thē ſtrange that ye run not with them vnto the ſame exceſſe of Riotte. 
                Secondly wee ſhall ſtop the mouthes of ſclaunderous people, as it is written:1. Peter. 2. 
               
                  For ſo is the will of God that by well doing ye may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.
               
A little before: 

                  Haue your conuerſation honeſt among the gentiles that they which ſpeake euil of you as of euil doers may by your good works which they ſhall ſee glorifie God in the day of the viſitation
                
                Thirdly wee ſhall win them that are without as by example this ſeely Saracen which walked of a long time without knowledge of the true God without the light of the glorious Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, the onely ſauiour of the world, and now hauing behelde the ſhine thereof moſt willingly embraceth ye ſame, bleſſed be God for it. Saint Peter exhorteth the wiues to obedience, his reaſon is to great purpoſe: 

                  That euen they which obey

not the worde,
                  1. Peter. 3. 
                  may without the worde bee wonne by the conuerſation of the wiues.
                
                Fourthly God the giuer of all goodnes who with his holy ſpirite guideth man into all felicitie and godlines is thereby bleſſed and glorified. This ende our Sauiour pointed vs to behold when he inioyned vs ſaying: 

                  Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they maye ſee your good workes and glorifie your father which is in heauen.
                  Epheſ. 2. 
                  For wee are the workemanſhip of God (ſaith Saint Paul) created in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good workes (as I ſaide before) which God hath ordained that wee ſhoulde walke in them:
               
But more is the pittye there are byrds which defile their owne neſts, there are looſe Chriſtians, Goſpellers in word, but Atheiſtes in deede.

                  Quali pudore ſuffūditur eccleſia:
                  
                     what a ſhame is this to the Church. (Sayth Cyprian)
               
there is pride, ambition, coueteouſnes,Cyprian. diſſention, debate, ſimonye, vſurye, oppreſſion, crueltye, bloudſhedding, ſchiſme, hereſie, &amp; Idolatrye, crept in among Chriſtians. The enemy ſtandeth without, pointing at the Chriſtians wt ye finger,Froiſſart. Cron. 2. vol. cap. 40. &amp; laughing them to ſkorne. Froiſſart writeth of the Turkes, &amp; Tartarians
               
in ye time of Clement, 7. &amp; Vrban. 6 ſaying: 

                  They doe mocke the Popes whereof one is at Rome, &amp; an other at Auignion, they ſay that the two Gods of Chriſtendome warreth each againſt other, wherby they affirme our law to be the more feeble and the lighter to be deſtroyed &amp; condēned, they lay therto a reaſō: in that they that ſhould exalt the Chriſtian faith are the firſt that miniſheth it &amp; deſtroy it.
                The Earle of Neuers ſonne to ye Duke of Burgoine, cō
               ming from Turkie deliuered vnto the frenche king, &amp; ye Lords of Fraunce this newes from Lamorabaqui ye 
               Turke:
               Cap. 25. 
               
                  his intent is to ſee Rome, &amp; to make his horſe eate otes vpon Saint Peters altar, alſo hee ſaide howe our chriſtian faith was nothing worth but corrupted by the headdes that ought to gouerne them, whereat the Turks made but a mock, wherfore he ſaid it ſhould bee the deſtruction of Chriſtendome.
               
It made Fraunce amazed, and ſome of the Nobility then brake out and ſaid of the Popes: 

                  It was time to abate their pompes &amp; to bring them to reaſon.
               
In the time of Henry the 3. ye chriſtians had geuen the Turks a great foile. The Turke offered peace wt moſt fauorable cōditiōs, &amp; ſaith

               Mathew Paris.
               Math. Pariſ. histor. Angl. in Henric. 3. 
               
                  It was then ſaide and affirmed for truth that the Soldane with his Nobilitie was fully determined to renounce the Law of Mahomet, which is knowne to be moſt filthy, and faithfully to cleaue to the chriſtian faith which appeareth moſt honeſt ſo that they might quietly enioy their lands and poſſeſſions.
               
The Pope by his Legate moſt arrogantly refuſed it. Being denied, the Turke gathereth a great power, and ſaith: 

                  Nunc demum ſpero quod pro ſuperbia eorum confundet Chriſtianos, Dominus ac Deus eorum Ieſus Chriſtus amator modeſtiae &amp; humilitatis. 
                  
                     Now at length I am in good hope that for their pride their Lord and God Ieſus Christ will confound the Christians, for he is the louer of modeſtie and humilitie.
                  
               
The Turke preuayled, the Chriſtians went to wracke. Fridericus the Emperour wrote to Henry 3. bitter letters againſt the pride, ambition, crueltie, exaction, vſurie, with many other enormities of the Church of Rome, calling the ſame, the roote and fountaine of all miſchiefe, the Popes, Inſatiabiles ſanguiſugas, Inſatiable bloud ſuckers,
                concluding

they are to be knowne by their fruites,Mathias A. Michou de Sarmat. Aſian. Lib. 1. cap. 5. 
               Cham the Emperour of Tartarie would not receiue the Chriſtian faith offered vnto him by Innocentius 4, for that the Embaſſadours of the Turke alleadged the ſame to be: 

                  Religionem otioſorum imbecillium, &amp; Idolatrarum, imagines colentium:
                  
                     The religion of idle perſons, of faint, and weake people, and of Idolatrers, worſhipping of Images.
                  
               
This is the credite theſe Images haue brought into the Church, this was a ſtumbling blocke in the waye of this Saracen that he would not be baptized in Spain. Fie vpon Idolatry, filth, and abhomination. Let the Church of God bee ſwept, then will the Heathens, the Iews, the Turks &amp; Saracens the ſooner come in. About the yeare 1237. the Greeke-church fel from the church of Rome vpon ſuch an occaſion. A certaine Archbiſhop orderly elected in Greece came to Rome to be confirmed, he could not be diſpatched afore he hadde paide a certaine ſumme of money, the which hee refuſed to doe, at his returne hee made reporte vnto the Grecians of the abuſes of Rome. The

two Churches iarred the ſpace of 300. yeares vntill the late councell of Baſill, where there was but a colourable reconciliation. Germanus Archbiſhop of Conſtantinople telleth Gregorius 9. the cauſe of their departure, in this ſort: Math Paris in Henric. 3. 
               
                  That, great diſcord, contrarietie of doctrine, ouerthrow of Canons, alteration of rites which the fathers deliuered are cauſes of this particion which ſeperateth thoſe things which at firſt were vnited and ioyned with the coniunction of peace and concord, let the whole world being made one language confeſſe &amp;c.
               
A little after: 

                  And that we may touche the marrowe of the truth: Many mighty and noble parſonages would obey you vnleſſe they feared your vniuſt oppreſſions, your inſolent exactions of riches, your vnlawfull ſeruitude, the which you extort of them that are ſubiect vnto you. Here hence are crueel battailes one againſt the other, deſolation of Cities, ſealing vp of Churchdores, ſchiſme of the brethren, the prieſtly function ceaſing, and a ſtay that God according vnto our duetye bee not praiſed vnder the Climate of the Grecians.
                  
               
Hee writeth the like vnto the Cardinalls, &amp;

concludeth that the Aethiopians, Syrians, Hyberians, Lazians, Alanians, Gothes, Chazarians, all Ruſſia, &amp; Bulgary, hold with the Greeke-church, and becauſe of the aforeſaide enormities, haue did Rome farewell. The Archbiſhop of Antioch about the ſame time calling vnto him a great number of Biſhoppes of Greece excommunicated the Pope, and the Clergye of Rome. The Patriarch of Conſtantinople complained at the councell of Lions to Innocentius 4. face, what a great number of Churches there were in Greece that reiected the Churche of Rome for the abhominations thereof. Papa tacuit: The Pope ſaid not a word.
                Hee might bee iuſtly aſhamed, who glorying in the keyes locketh vp all, ſhutteth out ſuche as would come and receaue the chriſtian faith, but he will neither enter, neither ſuffer others by reaſon of ye ſhamefull ſinnes and wickednes there raigning. If either Heathen, or Iew, or Saracen, ſpeake of the chriſtian faith, immediately he hath Rome in his mouth. Rome cannot be excuſed. And for that

they knowe not the puritie of religion in the reformed Churches beeing corners, &amp; pingles of Chriſtendome, with open mouth they reuile, and ſpeake ill of al, to the great diſhonor of God, and hinderance of the preaching of the Goſpel. There are many nations no doubt that if the truth were opened vnto them they would moſt willingly receaue the chriſtian faith, many hungring &amp; thirſting after the knowledge of the true God. In Turkie they may not call into queſtion the incertainty of Mahomets law it is death: vnder the dominion of the Pope, they may not profeſſe what they know for truth. much like them of whō 
               Auguſtine ſpeaketh,Auguſt. epiſt. 50. that being among the ſchiſmatickes, and heretickes, they durſt not confeſſe the Catholique faith, leaſt they and their houſes ſhould be deſtroyed: Many doe heare and ſee yet are they ſtopped with ſtaines, miſliking the water for the puddle of Rome: O what bleſſinges hath God poured vppon England? bleſſed bee his name therefore. We maye ſaye, as it is in the Goſpell: Many Prophets,
               Luke. 10. 
               and Kinges haue deſired

ſee thoſe things which Englād hath ſeen, and haue not ſeene them. It is to be feared leaſt the vnthankfulnes of the people, the rechleſneſſe in Gods ſeruice,Apocalyp. 2 and the want of Chriſtian lights and works will cauſe God to remooue the candleſticke out of his place, and the light of the Goſpell from among vs, and deliuer it to ſuch a nation (according vnto the parable in the Goſpell) as will bring foorth fruits accordingly.Math. 21. God of his infinite goodneſſe ſhewe mercie vnto his Church, continue the Goſpell, purge all blemiſhes, open the eyes of all Infidels, Iewes, Turkes, and Saracens, bring into the folde all loſt and wandering ſheepe, make of all nations one ſheepefolde, vnder the head ſhepheard and Biſhoppe of our ſoules Ieſus Chriſt, to whome with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, bee all honour and glorie nowe and for euer. Amen
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶After the Sermon ended, the Turke confeſſed in the Spaniſh tongue before the face of the congregation, the Preacher out of Pulpit propounding the queſtions and receiuing the anſwers by skilfull Interpretors, in ſumme as followeth.
            
               
               INprimis, that hee was verie ſorie for the ſinful life which he had lead in times paſt, in ignorance and blindnes, and hoped to obteine pardon in Ieſus Chriſt.
            
            
                Secondly, hee renounced Mahomet the falſe Prophet of the Moores, Saracens and Turkes, with al his abhominations, and bleſſed GOD which had opened his eyes to beholde the truth in Ieſus Chriſt.
            
            
                Thirdly, hee confeſſed there was but one God, he beleeued the Trinitie of perſons, the Father, the Sonne, &amp; the holy Ghoſt, and the ſame to bee one God in vnitie, which is to bee bleſſed for euer.
            
                Fourthly hee confeſſed and affirmed, that hee beleeued verily, that Ieſus

Chriſt was and is the ſonne of God, &amp; God from euerlaſting, the onely true Meſsias, &amp; ſauiour of the worlde, that he ſuffered for the ſinnes of al that beleeue in him, and that there is no way to be ſaued, but onely by the merits of the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt.
            
            
                Laſtly, he deſired hee might be receiued as one of the faithfull Chriſtians, &amp; bee baptized in the faith of the bleſſed Trinitie, promiſing from henceforth newnes of life, and fruits according vnto this profeſſion.
            
               ¶In the middeſt of the congregation, there was a comely Table ſet, couered with a faire linnen cloth, and thereon a Baſen with water. After the congregation had bleſſed God for his great mercies, and after ſundry godly Praiers and Collects, according vnto the reuerend order of holye Church, ſuche as broght him thither, deſired his name might be William, ſo was he baptized: In the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holie Ghoſt.
               
            
            Praiſe be to God.
         
      
   

