
   
      
         
            A nevv discourse of a stale subiect, called the metamorphosis of Aiax: vvritten by Misacmos, to his friend and cosin Philostilpnos
            Harington, John, Sir, 1560-1612.
         
         
            
               1596
            
         
         Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02649
            STC 12779.5
            ESTC S103861
            99839604
            99839604
            4043
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02649)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4043)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 321:6)
         
         
            
               
                  A nevv discourse of a stale subiect, called the metamorphosis of Aiax: vvritten by Misacmos, to his friend and cosin Philostilpnos
                  Harington, John, Sir, 1560-1612.
               
               [28], 120 p. : ill., music  
               
                  Imprinted by Richard Field [and Eliot's Court Press], dwelling in the Black-friers,
                  At London :
                  1596.
               
               
                  Misacmos = Sir John Harington.
                  Identification of Eliot's Court Press from STC.
                  Running title reads: The metamorphosis of Aiax.
                  Identified as STC 12779 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-10
            Ben GriffinSampled and proofread
         
            2004-10
            Ben GriffinText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A NEVV DISCOVRSE
OF A STALE
SVBIECT, CALLED THE
Metamorphosis of AIAX:
            VVritten by MISACMOS, to his friend
and cosin PHILOSTILPNOS.
            
            AT LONDON,
Printed by Richard Field, dwelling
in the Black-friers.
1596.
         
         
            
            
            A
LETTER VVRITTFN
BY A GENTLEMAN
OF GOOD WORTH, TO
the Author of this booke.
            
               SIr, I haue heard much of
your house, of your picturs,
of your walks, of your pōds,
and of your two boats, that
came one by land, and the
other by sea, from Lōdon bridge, and met
both at Bath bridge: all which God willing
(if I liue another sommer) I will come
of purpose to see; as also a swimming
place, where if one may beleeue your brother
Fraunces, Diana did bath her, and
Acteon see her without hornes. But to
deale plainly with you, there be three speciall
things that I haue heard much boasted
of, and therefore would willingliest
see. The one a fountaine stāding on pillers,43. Can.
like that in Ariosto, vnder which you may
dine and suppe; the second a shooting
close with a xij score marke to euery point

of the card, in which I heare you haue hit
a marke that many shoote at, viz: to make
a barren stony lād fruitfull with a litle cost;
the third is a thing that I cannot name wel
without saue-reuerence, and yet it sounds
not vnlike the shooting place, but it is
in plaine English a shiting place. Though,
if it be so sweete and so cleanely as I
heare, it is a wrong to it to vse saue reuerence,
for one told me, it is as sweet as my
parlor, and I would think discourtesie, one
should say, saue reuerence my parlor. But
if I might entreate you (as you partly
promist me at your last being here) to set
downe the maner of it in writing, so plaine
as our grosse wittes here may vnderstand
it, or to cause your man M. Combe (who
I vnderstand can paint prettilie) make a
draught, or plot thereof to be well conceaued,
you should make many of your
friends much beholding to you, and perhaps
you might cause reformation in many
houses that you wish well vnto, that

                  ••
               ill thinke no scorne to follow your good
example. Nay to tell you my opinion seriouslie,
if you haue so easie, so cheape,
and so infallible a way for auoiding such

annoiances in great houses: you may not
onelie pleasure manie great persons, but
doe her Maiestie good seruice in her pallace
of Greenwitch and other stately houses,
that are oft annoyed with such sauours,
as where many mouthes be fed can
hardly be auoided. Also you might be a
great benefactor to the Citie of London,
and all other populous townes, who stand
in great need of such conuayances. But all
my feare is, that your pen hauing beene
inured to so high a discourse,
            
               Of Dames, of Knights, of armes, of loues delight,
            
            will now disdaine to take so base a subiect,
            
               Of vaults, of sinkes, priuies &amp; draughts to write.
            
            But herein let a publicke benefit expell
a priuat bashfulnesse, and if you must now
and then breake the rules de slouilitate morum,
with some of these homelie wordes,
you see I haue broken the ise to you, and
you know the old saying, pens maie blot,
but they cannot blush. And as old Tarlton
was wont to saie, this same excellent
word saue-reuerence, makes it all manerlie.
Once this I dare assure you, if you can
but tell a homelie tale of this in prose as

cleanlie, as you haue told in verse a baudy
tale or two in Orlando mannerly, it may
passe among the sowrest censurers verie
currantly. And thus expecting your
aunswer hereto, at your conuenient
leysure, I commit
you to God this of
1596.
            Your louing cosin.
PHILOSILPNOS.
         
         
            
            THE ANSWER
TO THE LETTER.
            
               MY good Cosin, if you haue heard
so well of my poore house with
the apurtenaunces, it were to be
wished for preseruation of your
better conceit thereof; that you
would not see them at all, they will seeme to
you so far short of the report: for I do compare
my buildings and my writings together, in
which though the common sort thinke there
is some worth and witte, yet the grauer Censurers
do finde many faults and follies; And
no maruell for he that builds and hath gathered
litle, and writes and hath read litle, must
needes be a bad builder, and a worse writer.
But wher as you are disposed either in the way
of praise, or of play, to extoll so much the basest
roome of my house, as though you preferred
it afore the best; your commendation is
not much vnlike his curtesie, that being inuited
by a crabbed-fauourd host to a neat house,
did spit in his hostes face, because it was the
fowlest part of the house. But such as I haue
you shall be welcome to, and if I may know

when you will begin your progresse, I will pray
my brother to be your guide, who will direct
your iestes in such sort, as first you shall come
by a fine house that lackes a mistresse, then
to a faire house that mournes for a maister,
from whence, by a straight waie called the
force way, you shall come to a towne that is
more then a towne, where be the waters that
be more then waters. But from thence you
shall passe downe a streame that seemes to be
no streame by corn fields that seeme no fields,
downe a street no street, in at a gate no gate ouer
a bridge no bridge, into a court no court,
where if I be not at home, you sall finde perhaps
a foole no foole.
            But where as you praise my husbandry, you
make me remember an old schoole fellow of
mine in Cambridge, that hauing lost fiue shillings
abroad at Cardes, would boast he had saued
two candels at home by being out of his
chamber, for such be most of my sauings. Yet
this one point of husbandrie, though it maie
well be called beggerly: yet it is not for all that
contemptible, &amp; thus it was. Finding a faire
and flat field, though verie stonie, as all this
countrey is: I made some vagrant beggers (of
which by neighbourhood of the Bathes, here

comes great store) to gather all the stones that
might breake our arrowes, and finding an easie
meane to water the ground with a fat water,
I haue bettered my ground (as you say) and
quite rid me of my wandring guests, who will
rather walk seuen mile about, thē come where
they shall be forst to worke one halfe houre.
            Now Sir, to come to the chiefe point of your
desire, which requires a more ample answer,
but for a preamble you must be content with
this. You tell me, belike to encourage me, that
my inuention maie be beneficiall, not onely to
my priuate friends, but to townes and Cities,
yea euen to her Maiesties seruice for some of
her houses: trust me I doe beleeue you write
seriouslie as you terme it herein, and for my
part I am so wholly addicted to her hignesse
seruice, as I would be glad, yea euen proud, if
the highest straine of my wit, could but reach,
to anie note of true harmonie in the full consort
of her Maiesties seruice, though it were
in the basest key that it could be tuned to.
And if I should fortune to effect so good a
reformation, in the Pallace of Richmond, or
Greenewich (to which Pallace, manie of vs
owe seruice for the tenure of our land) I doubt
not but some pleasāt witted courtier of either

sex
                  •
                would grace me so much at least; as to say,
that I were worthy for my rare inuētion, to be
made one of the Priuy (and after a good long
parenthesis) come out with chamber, or if they
be learned &amp; haue read Castalios Courtier,
they will say, I am a proper scholer, and well
seene in latrina lingua. But let them mocke
that list, qui moccat moccabitur.
            
            Who strike with sword, the scabbeted them may strike:
            And sure loue eraueth loue, like asketh like.
            If men of iudgement thinke it may breede
a publike benefite, the conceit thereof shall
expell all priuate bashfulnesse; and I will
herein follow the example of that noble Lady,
that to saue the liberties of Couentry, rode
naked at noone through the streetes thereof,Camden in his Britānia.
and is now thought to be greatly honored, and
nothing shamed thereby.
            Further whereas you embolden my pen,
not to be abasht at the basenesse of the subiect
and as it were leading me on the way, you tell
me you haue broken the y
                  •
               e for me, to enter me
into such broad phrases, as you thinke must
be frequent herein: I will follow your steppes
and your counsell, neither will I disdaine to
vse the poore helpe of saue reuerence if neede
be, much like as a good friend of yours and

mine, that beginning to dispraise as honest
a man as him selfe, to a great Noble man,
said, he is the veryest knaue, sauing your
Lordship: But the noble man (ere the wordes
were fully out of his mouth,) said, saue thy self
knaue or be hangd, saue not me. Euen so I must
write in this discourse, sometime indeede as
homely (sauing your vvorship) as you shall
lightly see, and yet I will endeuour to keepe me
within the boundes of modestie, and vse no
wordes, but such as graue presidents in Diuinitie,
Law, Phisicke, or good Ciuilitie, will
sufficiently warrant me.
            Sure I am that many other country
                  •
               men,
both Dutch, French, and Italians, with great
praise of wit, though small of modesty, haue
writtē of worse matters. One writes in praise
of folly. 2. an other in honour of the Pox. 3. a
third defendes vsury. 4. a fourth commends
Nero. 5. a fift extols and instructs bawdery.
6. the sixt displaies and describes Puttana
Errante, which I here will come forth shortly
in English. 7. a seuenth (whom I would
guesse by his writing,This matter is discoursed by Rables, in his 13. chap. of his fift booke. to be groome of the
stoole to some Prince of the bloud in France)
writes a beastly treatise, only to examin what
is the fittest thing to wipe withall, alledging

that white paper is too smooth, browne paper
too rough, wollen cloth too stiffe, linnen cloth
too hollow, satten too slippery, taffeta too thin,
veluet too thicke, or perhaps too costly: but he
concludes, that a goose necke to be drawne betweene
the legs against the fethers,V
                     •
                   moyē de me torcher le culle plus Seigneurial, le plus excellent, le plus expedient que iamais fut veu. is the most
delicate and cleanely thing that may be. Now
it is possible that I may be reckned after these
seuen, as sapientum octauus, because I will
write of A Iakes yet I will challenge of right
(if the Heralds should appoint vs our places)
to go before this filthy fellow, for as according
to Aristotle, a ryder is an Architectonicall
science to a sadler, and a sadler to a stirop maker
&amp;c. so my discourse must needes be Architectonicall
to his, sith I treat of the house it
self, and he but of part of that is to be done in
the house, &amp; that no essentiall part of the businesse:
for they say there be three things that
if one neglect to do them,This may be omitted in reading. they will do themselues;
one is for a man to make euen his recknings,
for who so neglects it will be left euen
iust nothing; as other is to mary his daughters,
for if the parents bestow them not, they
will bestow them selues; the third is that,
which the foresaide French man writes of:
which they that omit, their lawndresses shall

finde it done in their linnen. VVhich mishap
a faire Lady once hauing, a seruing mā of the
disposition of Mydas Barber, that could not
kepe coūsell had spyed it, &amp; wrate in the grossest
termes it could be exprest, vppon a wall,
what he had seen, but a certaine pleasant conceited
Gentleman, corrected the barbarisme,
adding rime to the reason in this sort.
            
            
               My Ladie hath polluted her lineall vesture,
            
            
               With the superfluitie, of her corporall disgesture.
            
            But soft, I feare I giue you too great a tast
of my slouenly eloquence, in this sluttish argument.
VVherefore to conclude, I dare vndertake,
that though my discourse will not be so
wise as the first of those seuen I spake of, that
praises folly: yet it shall be ciuiller then the second,
truer then the third, honester then the
fourth: chaster thē the sift, modester then the
sixt, and clenlier then the seuenth. And that
you and other of my good friends may take the
lesse offence at it, I will cloth it (like an Ape
in purple,) that it may be admitted into the
better cōpany: and if all the art I haue cannot
make it mannerly enough, the worst punishmēt
it can haue, is but to employ it in the house
it shall treat of, only crauing but that fauour,
that a noble man was wont to request of your

good father in law, to teare out my name before
it be so employed; and to him that would
deny me that kindnesse, I would the paper
were nettles, and the letters needles for his
better ease: or that it were like to the Friers
booke, dedicated as I take it to Pius quintus;
of which one writes merily, that his holinesse
finding it was good for nothing else, imployed
it (in steed of the goose necke) to a homely occupation,
and forsooth the phrase was so rude,
the stile so rugged, and the Latin so barbarous,
that therewith as he writes, scortigauit
sedem Apostolicam. He galled the seat Apostolicke:
and so I commend me to you, till
I send you the whole discourse.
            Your louing cosin and true friend.
MISAKMOS.
         
         
            
            THE PROLOGVE
TO THE READER OF
the Metamorphω-sis of AIAX.
            
               GReat Captaine AIAX, as is
well knowen to the learned,
and shall here be published
for the vnlearned, was a
warrier of Graecia; strong,
headdy, rash, boisterous, and a terrible
fighting fellow, but neither wise, learned,
staide, nor Polliticke. Wherefore falling
to bate with Vlisses, &amp; receiuing so fowle
a disgrace of him,Ouid. Meta. lib. 12. to be called foole afore
company, and being bound to the peace,
that he might not fight with so great a
Counseller; he could indure it no longer,
but became a perfit mal-content, viz. his
hat without a band, his hose without garters,
his wast without a girdle, his bootes
without spurs, his purse without coine, his
head without wit, and thus swearing he
would kill &amp; slay; first he killed all the horned
beasts he met, which made Agamemnon
and Menelaus now, more affraid then
Vlisses, whereupon he was banished the
townes presently, and then he went to the

woods and pastures, and imagining all the
fat sheepe he met, to be of kin to the coward
Vlisses, because they ran awaie from
him, he massacred a whole flocke of good
nott Ewes. Last of all hauing no bodie else
to kill, poore man killed him selfe; what
became of his body is vnknowen, some say
that wolues and beares did eate it, and that
makes them yet such enemies to sheepe
and cattell.Lib. supra dicto. But his bloud as testifieth Pouidius
the excellent Historiographer, was
turnd into a Hiacint, which is a verie notable
kinde of grasse or flower.
            Now there are many miracles to be
marked in this Metamorphosis, to confirme
the credite of the same: for in the
grasse it selfe remaines such pride of this
noble bloud, that as the grasiers haue assured
me of their credits, (and some of them
may be trusted for 100000 poundes) the
ruther beastes that eate too greedily hereof
will swell til they burst, the poore sheep
still for an old grudge, would eate him
without salt (as they saie) but if they doe,Salt recouers baned sheepe.
they will soone after rot with it.
            Further I read that now of late yeares,Rabbles lib. 1. cap. 13.
a French Gentleman son to one Monsieur

Gargasier,
               Cōme Gargasier cognoit l'esprit excellent de Gargantua a l'inuētiōd, vntorche cul. &amp; a young Gentleman of an excellent
spirit &amp; towardnesse, as the reuerēt
Rabbles (quem honoris causa nomino, that is,
whom I should not name without sauereuerēce)
writeth in his first booke 13. Cha.
but the story you shall find more at large
in the xiiij. booke of his tenth Decad.Lib. Fictitius This
yong gentleman hauing taken some three
or foure score pils to purge melancholy,
euery one as big as a Pome Citterne, commanded
his man to mowe an halfe acre of
grasse, to vse at the priuy, and notwithstāding
that the owners (to saue their hay
perhaps) sware to him it was of that ancient
house of AIAX, and therefore reserued
of purpose onely for horses of the race
of Bucephalus, or Rabycano, yet he would
not be perswaded: but in further contempt
of his name, vsed a phrase that he had learned
at his being in the low Countreys, and
bad Skite vpon AIAX. But suddenly (whether
it were the curse of the people, or the
nature of the grasse I know not (he was
strikē in his posteriorūs with S. Anthonies
fier; and dispairing of other helpe, he went
on Pilgrimage in hope of remedy hereof
to Iapana, neare Chyna: where he met a

French Surgeō, in the vniuersity of Miaco
that cured him both of that &amp; the Verol,
that he had before in his priorūs; with the
Momio, of a Greciā wēch, that Vlisses buried
in his trauell, vpon the coast of the further
Aethiopia; and so he came back again
by Restinga des ladrones, through S. Lazaro,
and crossing both the Tropicks, Cancer &amp;
Capricorne, he came by Magellanes, swearing
he found no straights there; but came
from thence straight home. And so in 24.
houres saile, and two or three od years beside,
he accomplished his voyage, not forgetting
to take fresh wine &amp; water at Capon
de bona speranza. Yet ere he could recouer
his healthfully, he was faine to make
diuerse vowes (for now he was growē very
religious with his long trauell.) Among
which one was, that in remēbrance of China,
of all meats, he would honor the Chine
of beefe most: an other was, that of all offices
of the house, he should doe honour to
that house of office, where he had cōmitted
that scorne to AIAX: and that there,
he should neuer vse any more such fine
grasse, but rather, teare a leafe out of Holinsheds
Chronicles, or some of the books

that lie in the hall; then to commit such a
sin against AIAX. Wherefore immediatly
on his cōming home, he built a sumptuous
priuy, and in the most conspicuous
place thereof, namely iust ouer the doore;
he erected a statue of AIAX, with so grim
a countenance, that the aspect of it being
full of terror, was halfe as good as a suppositor:
and further to honour him, he changed
the name of the house, &amp; called it after
the name of this noble Captaine of the
greasie ones (the Grecians I should say) AIAX:
though since, by ill pronunciation,
and by a figure called Cacophonia, the accent
is changed, and it is called a Iakes.
            Further when the funerall oration was
ended,Hic desunt non paucae de sermone aeth clerum. to doe him all other complements,
that appertained to his honor; they searcht
for his petigrew, and an excellent Antiquary,
and a Harold, by great fortune,
found it out in an old Church booke in the
Austen Friers at Genoua: and it was proclaymed
on this fashion.Thus farre Ouid.
            
            AIAX sonne of Telamon.Thus much lib. 6. S. Aug. de ciuit. Dei. Ster
                     •
                  utius the God of doung.
sonne of Aeacus.
sonne of Iuppiter.
Iuppiter, aliâs dictus Picus.
sonne of old Saturne.
Aliâs dictus Stercutius.
            
               Which when it was made knowen vnto
the whole fraternity of the brethren, there
was nothing but reioycing and singing,
vnto their god Sarcotheos a deuout Shaame
in honor of this Stercutius the great great
grand-father of AIAX. Which Sonet
hath a maruellous grace in their countrey,
by meanes they do greatly affect the same
similiter desinentia, euery Frier singing a
verse, and a brother aunswering him in the
tune following, amounting iust to foure
and twenty, which is the misticall number
of their order.
            But by the way, if any seuere Catoes take
exceptions, &amp; any chast Lucrecias take offence
at the matter or musick here following,
let them pardon me, that sought but
to keepe decorum, in speaking of a slouenly
matter, and of slouenly men somewhat
slouenly.
            Vos verò viri eruditi si quae hic scurriliter nimis dicta videbuntur,
ignoscite: aequissimum 
                  ••
               im est, vt quam voluptatem
scelerati male saciendo capiant▪ 
               
                  ••
               ndem (quoad fieri potest) male
audiendo amittant▪ Videt
                  ••
                autem cuiusmodi farinae homines
taxare instituimus: 
                  ••
               n plos, doctos, sanctos, continentes, sed lu
               
                  •
               urios
                  •
               s,
hereticos, barburos, impios. Quibus ego me per 
                  •
               mne
                  •
               
vitam ace
                  ••
               imum hostem, vt &amp; verum 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                semper pro
                  •
               i
                  •
               ebor.
Nostis prouerbium, Cretisandum cum Cretensibus, &amp; cert
                  •
               
hoc dignum est pa
                  •
               ella operculum.Such lipp
                     •
                  s such let
                     •
                  uce. Nam similes habere debent labr
                  •
               
lactucas.
            
               
               
                  〈♫〉
               
O Tu qui dans, O tu qui dans, o ra cu la, o-ra-cu-la,

                  〈♫〉
               
scindis cotem no va-cu-la, cu-la, da nostra vt

                  〈♫〉
               
ta-ber-na-cu-la, lingua canant vernacula, cu-la, lingua

                  〈♫〉
               
canant vernacula cula.
            
               
                  〈♫〉
               
O Tu qui dans, O tu qui dans, oracula, oracu-la,

                  〈♫〉
               
scindis cotem no vacula cula, da nostra vt tabernacu-la,

                  〈♫〉
               
cula, vt taberna-cula, lingua canant vernacula,

                  〈♫〉
               
cula, cula, lingua canant verna-cula.
            
               
               1. O tu qui dans oraculae
               2. Scindis cotem nouacula
               3. Da nostra vt tabernacula
               4. Lingua canant vernacula
               5. Opima post gentacula
               6. Huiusmodi miracula
                     •
                  
               
               7. Sit semper plaenum poculum.
               8. Habentes plaenum loculum
               9. Tu serua nos vt specula
                     •
                  
               
               10. Per longa &amp; laeta secula
                     •
                  
               
               11. Vt clerus &amp; plebecula
               12. Nec nocte nec diecula
               13. Curent de vlla recula,
               14. Sed intuentes specula
               15. Dura vitemus spicula
               16. Iacentes cum amicula
               17. Quaegarrit vt cornicula
                     •
                  
               
               18. Seutristis 
                     •
                  euridicula
               19. Tum porrigamus oscula
               20. Tum colligamus floscula
               21. Ornemus vt caenaculum
               22. Et totum habitaculum
               23. Tum culi post spiraculum.
               24. Spectemus ho
                     •
                   spectaculu
                     •
                  .
            
            Then sutable to this himne, they had 
                  •
               
dirge for AIAX, with a praier to all their
chiefe Saints whose names begin with A.

                  
                  Ora pro A IAX.
                  Sauntus Ablabius
                  Sauntus AcachiusSome of these denied the godhead of
Christ with Arrius, some the authority of
Bishops as Aerius which you may see in
Prateolo de vita
                              ••
                           ret
                              •
                           corum.
                     
                  
                  Sauntus Arrius
                  Sauntus Aerius
                  Sauntus Aetius
                  Sauntus Almaricus
                  Saunti AdiophoristaeAlmarieus denied the resurrection of
the body, which is an heresie that mars
all, as S. Paule saith 1. Cor. 15. 14. That
then our faith were vaine.
                  
                  Saunti 11000 Anabaptistae
                  Et tu Sauntiss. Atheos
               
And so ended the blacke Sauntus.
            
            By all which you may see, that it is but
lacke of learning, that makes some fellowes
seeke out stale English Etymologies
of this renowmed name of AIAX. One
imagined, it was called so of blacke iacks;
because they looke so slouenly, that a mad
French man wrote, we did cary our drinke
in our bootes: but that is but a bald Etymology,
and I will neuer agree, that Iacke,
though he were neuer so blacke, should be
thus slaundered. But if you stand so much
vpon your English, and will not admitte
our Greeke, and our Romane tongue, you
shall see I will cast about, to haue one in
English for you. First then, you haue heard
the old prouerbe (age breedes aches) now
you must imagine, that an old man, almost

pound with an vgly Mopsa, sayd, not without
a greatsigh; Oh, what a match were
this, were the woman away? But the deuise
that shall be hereafter discouered, will
so confound this Gentleman with the
strong breath, that saue we cary about vs
some traytors, that are ready to take his
part, he should neuer be able so much as
to blow vpon you. Yet I would haue the fauourable
readers (of what sort soeuer) thus
farre satisfied, that I tooke not this quarrell
vppon me voluntarily, but rather in
mine owne defence; and standing vpon
the puntilio of honour, hauing bene chalenged,
as you may partly see in the letter
precedent, by one, as it seemes, of the
Captaines owne countrey-men: for his
name is Philostilpnos, which I thought at
first, was a word to coniure a spirite, till at
last, a fellow of mine of Cambridge, told
me the Philo was Greeke, and that he
would say in English, that he loueth cleanlinesse.
Now I being bound by the Duello,
hauing accepted the challenge, to seeke
no aduantage, but euen to deale with him
at his owne weapon, entred the lists with
him, and fighting after the old English

maner without the stockados, (for to voine
or strike below the girdle, we counted it
base and too cowardly) after halfe a score
downright blowes, we grew to be friends,
and I was content to subscribe, Yours &amp;c.
And to the end I may aunswer him in the
same language, I am called Misacmos,
which is cosin and ally to his name, and it
signifies a hater of filthinesse, and to all
such as are of kin to either of our names or
conditions, we commend this discourse
ensuing.
            
               Ad Zoilum &amp; Momum.
               Cease maisters any more,
               To grudge, chafe, pine, and freat,
               Lo stuffe for you good store
               To gnaw, chew, bite and eate.
            
         
         
            
            A short aduertisment of the author
to the Reader.
            
               The discourse ensewing is deuided into three partes or
sectiōs (as it were breathing places) least it may seeme
confused, or too tedious to be read all at once.
               1 The first iustifies the vse of the homelyest wordes.
               2 The second prooues the matter not to be contemptible.
               3 The third shewes the forme, &amp; how it may be reformed.
            
            
               1. The first begins grauely, and ends lightly.
               2 The second begins pleasantly, and ends soberly.
               3 The third is mixt both seriously and merily.
            
            
               1 I would pray you to weigh the graue authorities reuerently,
for they are true and autenticall.
               2 I would wish you to regard the pleasaunt histories respectiuely,
for they be honest and commendable.
               3 I would aduise you to vse the mery matters modestly, for
so they may be faultlesse and harmelesse.
            
            
               1 If you meane not to read it, then disprayse it not, for that
would be counted follie.
               2 Till you haue fully read it, censure it not, for that may be
deemed rashnesse.
               3 When you haue read it, say both of vs haue lost more
time then this in our dayes, and that perhaps would
be iudged the right.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE METAMORPHOSIS
OF AIAX.
            
               
                  THere was a very tall and seruiceable
Gentleman, sometime
Lieutenant of the ordinance,
called M. Iaques
VVingfield; who comming
one day, either of businesse, or of kindnesse
to visit a great Lady in the Court; the Lady
bad her Gentlewoman aske, which of the
VVingfields is was; he told her Iaques Wingfield:
the modest Gentlewoman, that was
not so wel seene in the Frēch, to know that
Iaques was but Iames in English, was so
bashfoole, that to mend the matter (as she
thought) she brought her Lady word, not
without blushing, that it was M. Priuie
VVingfield; at which, I suppose the Ladie
then, I am sure the Gētleman after, as long
as he liued, was wont to make great sport.
               I feare the homely title prefixed to this
Treatise (how warlicke a sound so euer it
hath) may breed a worse offence, in some

of the finer sort of readers; who may vpon
much more iust occasion condemne it,
as a noysome and vnsauory discourse: because,
without any error of equiuocation,
I meane indeede, to write of the same that
the word signifies. But if it might please
them a litle better to consider, how the
place we treate of (how homely soeuer) is
visited by thēselues, once at least in foure
and twenty houres, if their digestion be
good, and their constitution sound; then I
hope they will do me that fauor, and them
selues that right, not to reiect a matter
teaching their own ease, and cleanlinesse,
for the homelinesse of the name; and consequently,
they will excuse all broad phrases
of speech, incident to such a matter,
with the old English prouerbe that endes
thus; For Lords and Ladies doe the same. I
know that the wiser sort of men will consider,
&amp; I wish that the ignorant sort would
learn; how it is not the basenesse, or homelinesse,
either of wordes, or matters, that
make them foule and obscenous, but their
base mindes, filthy conceites, or lewd intents
that handle them. He that would
scorne a Phisition, because for our infirmities

sake, he refuseth not somtime the noisome
view of our lothsomest excrements,
were worthy to haue no helpe by Phisicke,
and should breake his deuine precept, that
saith; Honour the Phisition, for necessities
sake God hath ordained him. And he that
would honour the makers of Aposticchios,
or rebatoes, because creatures much honored
vse to weare thē, might be thought,
perhaps full of curtesie, but voide of wit.
               Surely, if we would enter into a sober
and sad consideration of our estates, euen
of the happiest sort of vs, as men of the
world esteeme vs; whether we be noble, or
rich, or learned, or beautifull, or healthy,
or all these (which seldome happeneth)
ioyned together we shall obserue, that the
ioyes we enioy in this world, consist rather
in indolentia (as they call it) which is an auoyding
of grieuances and inconueniences,
then in possessing any passing great
pleasures; so durable are the harmes, that
our first parentes fall hath layd on vs, and
so poore the helpes that we haue in our
selues: finally so short, and momentany
the contentments that we fish for, in this
Ocean of miseries, which either we misse,

(fishing before the net, as the prouerbe is)
or if we catch them they proue but like
Eeles, sleight and slipperie. The chiefest of
all our sensuall pleasures, I meane that
which some call the sweet sinne of letcherie,
though God knowes, it hath much
sowre sawce to it; for which notwithstanding,
many hazard both their fame, their
fortune, their friendes, yea their soules;
which makes them so oft breake the sixt
Commaundement, that when they heare
it read at Church, they leaue the wordes
of the Communion booke, and say, Lord
haue mercie vpon vs, it grieues our hearts
to keepe this Law. And when the Commination
is read on Ashwednesday, wherein
is read, Cursed be he that lyeth with his
neighbours wife, and let all the people say,
Amen; these people either say nothing,
or as a neighbour of mine sayd,Some say amend, and so done, were verie well sayd. 
                  he hem; I
say this surpassing pleasure, that is so
much in request, and counted such a principall
solace, I haue heard confessed before
a most honorable person, by a man of
middle age, strong constitution, and well
practised in this occupation, to haue bred
no more delectation to him (after the

first heate of his youth was past) then to go
to a good easie close stoole, when he had a
lust thereto (for that was his very phrase.)
Which being confessed by him, and confirmed
by many; makes me take this aduantage
thereof in the beginning of this
discourse,Aiak's house preferred before a ba
                        ••
                     die house. to preferre this house I mind to
speak of, before those which they so much
frequent; neither let any disdaine the cō
                  parison.
For I remember, how not long
since, a graue &amp; godly Ladie, and grandmother
to all my wiues children, did in
their hearings, and for their better instruction,
tell them a story; which though I
will not sweare it was true, yet I did wish
the auditory wold beleeue it; namely, how
an Hermit being caried in an euening, by
the conduct of an Angell, through a great
citie, to contemplate the great wickednes
daily and hourely wrought therein; met
in the streete a gongfarmer with his cart
full laden, no man enuying his full measure.
The poore Hermit, as other men did,
stopt his nosthrils, and betooke him to the
other side of the street, hastening from the
sower carriage all he could; but the Angell
kept on his way, seeming no whit offended

with the sauor. At which while the
Hermit maruelled, there came not long
after by thē, a woman gorgeously attyred,
wel perfumed, wel attended with coaches,
&amp; torches, to conuey her perhaps to some
noble mans chamber. The good Hermit
somewhat reuiued with the faire sight, and
sweet sauour, began to stand at the gaze.
On the other side, the good Angell now
stopped his nose, and both hastened himselfe
away, and beckened his companion
frō the place. At which the Hermit more
maruelling then before, he was told by the
Angell, that this fine courtesan laden
with sinne, was a more stinking sauour afore
God and his holy Angels, then that
beastly cart, laden with excrements. I
will not spend time to allegorize this storie,
onely I will wish all the readers may
find as sure a way to cleanse, and keepe
sweete the noblest part of them selues,
that is, their soules; as I shall shew them
a plaine and easie way, to keepe sweete the
basest part of their houses, that is, their
sinkes. But to the intent I may binde my
selfe to some certaine method, I will first
awhile continue as I haue partly begun, to

defend by most autenticall authorities and
examples, the vse of these homely words
in so necessary matters. Secondly, concerning
the matter it selfe, I will shewe how
great, and extraordinary care hath beene
had in all ages, for the good ordering of
the same. Lastly, for the forme, I will set
downe the cheapest, perfectest, and most
infallible, for auoyding all the inconueniences
the matter is subiect to; that hitherto
(if I and many more be not much deceiued)
was euer found out.
               When I was a truantly scholer in the
noble Vniuersitie of Cambridge (though
I hope I had as good a conscience as other
of my pew-fellowes, to take but a litle learning
for my money) yet I can remember,
how a very learned and reuerent Deuine
help this question in the schooles. Scripturae
stylus nō est barbarus. The stile, or phrase
of the Scripture is not barbarous. Against
whom one replyed with this argument.

                     That which is obscenous, may be called barbarous:
                     But the Scripture is in many places obscenous:
                     Therefore the Scripture may be called barbarous.
                  
                  
To which syllogisme was truely answered
(as I now remēber denying the minor) that
though such phrases to vs seeme obscenous,
and are so when they are vsed to ribauldrie,
or lasciuiousnes, yet in the Scripture
they are not onely voyd of inciuilitie,
but full of sanctitie; that the Prophets do
in no place more effectually, more earnestly,
nor more properly beat downe our
pride and vanitie, and open to our eyes the
filthinesse, and horror of our sinnes, then
by such kind of phrases, of which they recited
that, where it is said, that the sinnes
of the people were,
                     
                        •
                     sa. 64. 
                  quasi pannus menstruatae
vniuersae iustitiae nostrae, that a common
or strange woman (for so the Scripture couertly
termeth a harlot) hath her quiuer
open for euery arrow; that an old lecherous
man, is like a horse that neigheth after
euery mare, &amp;c. To which I could adde
many more, if I affected copiousnesse in
this kind; some in broad speeches, some in
couert termes, expressing mens shame,
mens sinnes, mens necessities. Quinque aureos
anos facietis pro quinque satrapis, which
our English of Geneua trāslates very modestly.
Ye shall make 
                     •
                  iue goldē Emeralds

for fiue Noblemen or Princes. Which
word I am sure, many of the simple hearers,
and readers, take for a precious stone
of the Indians, set in gold; &amp; so they shall
still take it for me, for that ignorance, may
perhaps do them lesse hurt in this matter,
then further knowledge; but yet what a
speciall Scripture that is to Gods glory &amp;
their shame, appeares by Dauids prophecie
in the 77. Psalme, where he saith; Percussit
inimicos suos in posteriora, opprobrium
sempiternum dedit illis. He smote his enemies
in the hinder parts, and put them to
a perpetuall shame; in remēbrance whereof,
in some solemne lyturgies, vntill this
day the same Chap. of Aureos anos is read.
               What shold I speake of the great league
betwene God and man, made in Circumcision?
impressing a painefull stigma, or caracter
in Gods peculiar people, though
now, most happily taken away in the holy
Sacrament of Baptisme. What the word
signified, I haue knowen reuerent &amp; learned
men haue bene ignorant; and we call
it very well Circumcision, and vncircumcision,
though the Remists (of purpose be
like to varie frō Geneua) will needs bring

in Prepuse; which word was after admitted
into the Theater with great applause, by
the mouth of Maister Tarlton the excellent
Comedian; when many of the beholders
that were neuer circumcised, had as
great cause as Tarlton, to complaine of
their Prepuse. But to come soberly, &amp; more
nearely to our present purpose; In the old
Testament, the phrase is much vsed of couering
the feet, and in the new Testament,
he that healeth &amp; helpeth all our infirmities,
vsed the word draught; that that goeth
into the man, is digested in the stomacke,
and cast out into the draught. Lastly, the
blessed Apostle S. Paule, being rapt in cō
                  templation
of diuine blisfulnesse, cōpares
all the chiefe felicities of the earth, esteeming
them (to vse his owne word) as stercora,
most filthy doung, in regard of the
ioyes he hoped for. In imitation of which
zealous vehemencie, some other writers
haue affected to vse such phrase of speech,
but with as il successe, as the asse that leapt
on his maister at his comming home, because
he saw a litle spaniel, that had so don,
much made of: for in deed, these be coūted
but foule mouthd beasts for their labors.
               
                  But to conclude these holy authorities,
worthy to be alledged in most reuerent
and serious manner; and yet here also I
hope without offence: let vs come now to
the ridiculous, rather then religious customes
of the Pagans, and see, if this contemptible
matter I treat of, were despised
among them; nay rather obserue, if it were
not respected with a reuerence, with an
honor, with a religion, with a dutie, yea
with a deitie, &amp; no maruell. For they that
had Gods and Goddesses, for all the necessaries
of our life, frō our cradles to our
graues, viz. 1. for sucking, 2. for swathing,
3. for eating, 4. for drinking, 5. for sleeping,
6. for husbandrie, 7. for venerie, 8.
for fighting, 9. for phisicke, 10. for mariage,
11. for child-bed, 12. for fire, 13. for
water, 14. for the thresholds, 15. for the
chimneys; the names of which I doe set
downe by themselues, to satisfie those that
are curious. 1. Lacturtia, 2. Cunina, 3. Edulicae,
4. Potina, 5. Morpheus, 6. Pan, 7. Priapus,
8. Bellona, 9. Aesculapius, 10 Hymen,
11. Lucina, and Vagitanus, 12. Aether, 13.
Salacia, 14. Lares, 15. Penates. I say, you
must not thinke, they would cōmit such an

ouersight, to omit such a necessarie, as almost
in all languages, hath the name of
necessitie, or ease: wherfore they had both
a God and a Goddesse, that had the charge
of the whole businesse; the God was called
Stercutius, as they write, because he found
so good an employment for all manner of
doung, as to lay it vpon the land: or perhaps
it was he, that first foūd the excellent
mysterie of the kind setting of a Parsnippe
(which I will not here discouer, because I
heard of a truth, that a great Lady that loued
Parsnips very well, after she had heard
how they grew, could neuer abide them)
and I would be loath, to cause any to fall
out of loue with so good a dish. Neuerthelesse
(except they will haue better bread
then is made of wheate) they must (how
fine so euer they be) giue M. Stercutius
leaue, to make the lād able to beare wheat.
But the Goddesse was much more especially,
and properly assigned for this busines,
whose name was Dea Cloacina, her statue
was erected by Titus Tacius, he that raigned
with Romulus, in a goodly large house
of office (a fit shrine for such a Saint) which
Lodouicus Vi
                        •
                     es cites out of Lactantius.
                  
But he that wil more particularly enforme
himselfe of the originall of all these pettie
Gods and Goddesses; as also of the greater,
which they distinguisht by the name
of Dij consentes, which are according to
old Ennius verse, deuided into two rankes
of Lords and Ladies.

                     Iun
                           •
                        ,These Gods were of the priuy councel to Iuppiter, 23. Chap. 4. booke. Vesta, Minerua, Ceres
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         Diana, Venus, Mars,
                     Mercurius, Neptunus, louis, Vulcanus, Apollo.
                  
Of all which S. Augustine writes most diuinely,
to ouerthrow their diuinitie; and
therefore I referre the learned and studious
reader, to his fourth and sixt booke de
Ciuitate Dei, where the originall, and vanitie
of all these Gods and Goddesses, is
more largely discoursed: with a pretty quip
to Seneca the great Philosopher, who being
in hart half a Christiā, as was thought;
yet because he was a Senator of Rome,S. Augustine 6. booke 10. chap. L.
was faine (as S. Augustine saith) to follow
that he found fault with, to doe that hee
disliked, to adore that he detested. But
come we to my stately Dame Cloacina, and
her Lorde Stercutius, though these were
not of the higher house, called Consentes;
                  
yet I hope for their antiquitie, they may
make great comparison: for he is saide to
haue bene old Saturne, father to Pycus that
was called Iuppiter; and Cloacina was long
before Priapus, and so long before Felicitie,
that S. Augustine writes merrily, that
he thinkes verily, Felicitie forsooke the Romanes,
for disdaine that Cloacina and Priapus
were deified so long before her; adding
Imperium Romanorum propterea grandius,
quam felicius fuit. The Romane Empire
therefore was rather great, then happie.
But how so euer Ladie Felicitie disdaines
her, no question but Madame Cloacina was
alwayes a very good fellow: for it is a token
of speciall kindnesse, to this day among
the best men in France, to reduce a
Syllogisme in Bocardo togither. Insomuch
as I haue heard it seriously tolde, that a
great Magnifico of Venice, being Ambassador
in France, and hearing a Noble
person was come to speak with him, made
him stay till he had vntyed his points; and
when he was new set on his stoole, sent for
the Noble mā to come to him at that time;
as a very speciall fauour. And for other
good fellowships I doubt not, but frō the

beginning it hath often happened, that
some of the Nymphes of this gentle goddesse,
haue met so luckily with some of her
deuout chaplens, in her chappels of ease,
and paid their priuie tithes so duely, and
done their seruice togither with such deuotion;
that for reward, she hath preferred
them within fortie weeks after to Iuno Lucina,
and so to Vagitana, Lacturtia, and Cunina:
for euen to this day, such places continue
very fortunate. And wheras I named
deuotion, I would not haue you thinke,
how homely soeuer the place is, that all
deuotion is excluded from it. For I happening
to demand of a deare friend of mine,
concerning a great cōpanion of his, whether
he were religious or no, and namely
if he vsed to pray; he tolde me, that to his
remembrance he neuer heard him aske any
thing of God, nor thanke God for any
thing; except it were at a Iakes, he heard
him say, he thāked God, he had had a good
stoole. Thus you see, a good stoole might
moue as great deuotion in some man, as a
bad sermon; &amp; sure it sutes very well, that
Quorū Deus est venter, eorū templū sit cloaca.
he that maks his belly his god, I wold haue

him make a Iakes his chappell. But he that
would in deede call to minde, how Arrius,
that notable and famous, or rather infamous
heretike, came to his miserable
end vppon a Iakes; might take iust occasion
euen at that homely businesse, to haue
godly thoughts; rather then as some haue,
wanton, or most haue, idle. To which purpose
I remember in my riming dayes, I
wrote a short Elegie vpon a homely Embleme;
which both verse and Embleme,
they haue set vp in Cloacinas chappell, at
my house very solemnely. And I am the
willinger to impart it to my friends, because
I protest to you truely, a sober Gentleman
protested to me seriously; that the
conceit of the picture &amp; the verse, was an
occasion to put honest and good thoughts
into his mind. And Plutarke defends with
many reasons, in his booke called Symposeons,
                  Lib. 5. qu
                        •
                     st. 1.
that where the matters them selues
often are vnpleasant to behold, their counterfeits
are seene not without delectation.
               
                  
                  
                     
                        Sprint
                              •
                            non spint
                              •
                           . More feard then hurt.
                  
               
               A godly father sitting on a draught,
               To do as neede, and nature hath vs taught;
               Mumbled (as was his manner) certen pray'rs,
               And vnto him the Diuell straight repayr's:
               
                  And boldly to reuile him he begins,
               Alledging that such prayr's are deadly sins;
               And that it shewd, he was deuoyd of grace,
               To speake to God, from so vnmeete a place.
               The reuerent man, though at the first dismaid,
               Yet strong in faith, to Satan thus he said;
               Thou damned spirit, wicked, false and lying,
               Dispa
                     •
                  ring thin
                     •
                   owne good, and ours en
                     •
                  ying:
               Ech take his due, and me thou canst not hurt,
               To God my pray'r I meant, to thee the durt.
               Pure prayr ascends to him that high doth sit,
               Downe fals the filth, for fiends of hell more fit.
               Wherefore, though I grant many places
and times are much fitter for true deuotion,
yet I dare take it vppon me; that
if we would giue the Deuill no kinder entertainment
in his other suggestions, then
this father gaue him in his causelesse reproofe
(for he gaue it him in his teeth,
take it how he would,) I say we should
not so easily be ouerthrowne with his assaults,
as daily we are,For want of the good take heede. for lacke of due
resistance. But come we now to more particular
and not so serious matter; haue not
many men of right good conceit, serued
themselues with diuerse pretie emblems,
of this excrementall matter. As that in
Alciat, to shew that base fellows oft-times

swimme in the streame of good fortune,
as well as the worthiest.
Nos quoque poma nat amus.
Or as the old prouerbe,
                     Pom
                           •
                        , signifies horsedong as well as apple
                        •
                     . as well as embleme,
that doth admonish men not to
contend with base and ignominious persons.

                     Hoc scio pro certo, quod si cum sterc
                           •
                        re cert
                           •
                        
                     
                     Vinco ceu vincor, semper ego maculor.
                     I know if I contend with dirtie foes,
                     I must be foyld, whether I win or lose.
                  
Which Embleme had almost hindred me
the writing of this present discourse, saue
that a good friend of mine told me, that
this is a fansie and not a fight, and that if
it should grow to a fight; he assured me
I had found so excellent a warde against
his chiefe dart, which is his strong breath,
that I were like to quit my handes in the
fray, as well as any man. But to proceede
in these rare Emblemes; who hath not
read or heard, of the Picture made in
Germanie, at the first rising of Luther?
where to shew as it were by an Embleme,
with what drosse, and draffe, the Pope and
his partners fed the people; they caused
him to be purtraied in his Pontificalibus
riding on a great sow, and holding before

her taster, a dirty pudding: which
dirtie deuise, Sleidan the Historian verie
iustly and grauely, both reports and reproues;
yet it serued a turne for the time,
and made great sport to the people. But
when this May-game was done, an hundred
thousand of them came home by
weeping crosse; so as the poore sow was
not onely sold by the eares, but sould by
a drumme, or slaine by the sword. Yet the
Flaunders cow, had more wit then the
Germane sow: for she was made after an
other sort, viz. the Mirror of Princes feeding
her, the Terror of Princes spurring
her, the Prince of Orange milking her, or
after some such fashion, for I may faile in
the particulars; but the conclusion was,
that Monsieur d' Allanson (who indeede
with most noble endeuour, though not
with so happie successe, attempted them)
would haue pulled her backe by the taile,
and she filed his fingers. And thus much
for Emblemes. Now for poesie (though
Emblemes also are a kind of poesie) I rather
doubt, that the often vsage of such
words, wil make the Poets be condemned;
then that the Poets authorities, will make

the wordes be allowed: but if their example
can giue any countenāce to them, they
shall want none. It is certaine, that of all
poems, the Epigram is the wittiest, &amp; of al
that writes Epigrams, Martiall is counted
the pleasantest. He in his 38. ep. of his first
booke, hath a distichon, that is very plyable
to my purpose; of one that was so
stately, that her close stoole was of gold,
but her drinking cup of glasse.

                     Ventris onus puro,1. 38. nec te pudet excipis auro:
                     Sed b
                           •
                        bis in vitro, charius ergo cacas.
                  
And in the same booke, to the gētlewomā
that had a pleasure, to haue her dogge licke
her lips, as many do now a dayes.
               Os, &amp; labra,1. 74. tibi lingit Mane
                     •
                  a Catellus:
               Non miror merdas, si libet esse can
                     •
                  .
               Thy dog still lickes thy lips, but tis no hurt:
               I ma
                     •
                  uell not, to see a dog eate durt.
               Further in his third booke, he mocks
one of his fellow Poets, that draue away all
good company with his verses, euery man
thought it such a penance to heare them.
               Na
                     •
                   tantos rogo quis ferat labores,3. 44.
               
               Et stanti legis, &amp; legis sedenti,
               Currenti legis, &amp; legis cacanti,
               In Thermas fugio sonas ad aurem, &amp;c.
               Alas my head with thy long readings akes,
               
                  Standing or sitting, thou readst euery wheare,
               If I vvould vvalke, if I would go t' AIAX,
               If to the Bath, thou still art in mine eare.
               Whereby the way, you may note that
the French curtesie I spake of before, came
from the Romaines; sith in Martials time,
they shunned not one the others companie,
at Monsieur AIAX. But now it may
be some man will say, that these wanton
and ribald phrases, were pleasing to those
times of licentiousnesse, and paganisme
that knew not Christ; but now they are
abhorred and detested, &amp; quite out of request.
I would to God with all my heart,
he lyed not that so sayd; and that indeede
Religiō could roote out as it should do, all
such wanton and vaine toyes (if they be
all wanton and vaine) yet I am sure, that
euen in this age, &amp; in this realme, men of
worth, and wit, haue vsed the wordes and
phrases, in as homely sort as Martial, some
in light, some in serious matter. Among
Sir Thomas Mores Epigrams, that flie ouer
all Europe for their wit &amp; conceit, the
very last (to make a sweet cōclusion) is this,

                     Sectile ne tetros porrum tibi spiret odores;
                     Protinus 
                           •
                         porro fac mihi cepe vores,
                     
                        Den
                           •
                        o foet
                           •
                        rem si vis depellere cepe:
                     Hoc facile efficient allia mansa tibi;
                     Spiritus at si post etiam grauis, allia res
                           •
                         at;
                     Aut nihil, aut tantum, tollere 
                           ••
                        erda potest.
                  
               
               Which for their sakes that loue garlicke,
I haue taken some paines with, though it
went against my stomacke once or twise.
               If leekes you leeke, but do their smell disleeke,
               Eate onions, and you shall not smell the leeke:
               If you of onions vvould the sent expell,
               Eate garlick, that shall drown the onions smell,
               But against garlikes sauour, at one vvord,
               I know but one receipt, vvhats that? go looke.
               Now fie, will you name it, and reade it
to Ladies, thus you make them blame me
that meant no lesse. But to come againe
to pleasant Sir Thomas, he hath another
Epigram, that though this was but a
sowre one, I durst as liue be his halfe at
this as at that, and it is about a medicine
for the collicke.

                     Te crepitus perdit ni
                           ••
                        ium, si ventre ret entus,
                     Te pr
                           •
                        pere emissus seruat item crepitus:
                     Si crepitus seruare potest, &amp; perdere nunquid,
                     Terrificis crepitus, regibus aequa potest.
                  
Thus il-fauoredly in English,Non'est bonum luderecum sanctu. for I will tell
you true, my Muse was afraide to translate
this Epigram:It is good to play with your fellows. &amp; she brought me out three
or foure sayings against it, both in Latine

and English:An 
                        •
                     escis lon
                     
                        •
                     as regibus esse manus. and two or three shrewd examples,
both of this last Poet, who died
not of the collicke,He was beheaded. and of one Collingborne,
that was hanged for a distichon of
a Cat, a rat, &amp; a dogge. Yet I opposed Murus
aheneus esto nil conscire sibi, and so with
much a do, she came out with it.

                     To breake a little winde,
                     Sometime ones life doth saue.
                     For want of vent behinde,
                     Some folke their ruine haue:
                     A power it hath therefore,
                     Of life, and death expresse:
                     A king can cause no more,
                     A cracke doth do no lesse.
                  
And when she had made it in this sorie fashion,
she bad me wish my friends, that no
mā should follow Sir Th. Mores humour,
to write such Epigrās as he wrate, except
he had the spirite,Two Apothegmes of Sir Thomas More. to speake two such Apothegmes
as he spake, of which the last
seemes to fall fit into our text. The first
was, when the King sent to him to know if
he had chaunged his minde; he answered,
yea: the King sent straight a counseller to
him, to take his subscription to the fix Articles.
Oh said he, I haue not chaunged my
minde in that matter, but onely in this; I

thought to haue sent for a Barber, to haue
bene shauen ere I had died, but now if it
please the King, he shall cut off head; and
beard, and all together. But the other was
milder, and pretier; for after this, one comming
to him as of good will, to tell him he
must prepare him to dye, for he could not
liue: he called for his vrinall, and hauing
made water in it, he cast it, &amp; viewed it (as
Physiciās do) a prety while; at last he sware
soberly, that he saw nothing in that mans
water, but that he might liue, if it pleased
the King; a pre
                     •
                  i
                     •
                   saying, both to note
his owne innocency, and moue the Prince
to mercy: and it is like, if this tale had bene
as friendly told the King, as the other perhaps
was vnfriendly enforced against him,
sure the King had pardoned him. But alas
what cared hee, (to say truth) what
neede he care, that cared not for death?
But to step backe to my teshe (though
euerie place I step to, yeeldes me sweeter
discourse) what thinke you by Haywood,
that scaped hanging with his mirth, the
King being graciously and (as I thinke) truly
perswaded, that a mā that wrate so pleasant
and harmelesse verses, could not haue

any harmefull conceit against his proceedings,
and so by the honest motion of a
Gentleman of his chāber, saued him from
the ierke of the six stringd whip. This Haywood
for his Prouerbs &amp; Epigrams, is not
yet put downe by any of our countrey,
though one doth indeed come neare him,
that graces him the more, in saying he puts
him downe. But both of them haue made
sport with as homely words as ours be▪
                  M. Dauies. one
of a Gentlewomans gloue, saue that without
his consent it is no good manners to
publish it but old Haywoods sayth:

                     Except wind stand, as neuer wind sto
                           •
                        d,
                     It is an ill vvind blowes no man good.
                  
               
               And another not vnpleasant, one that I
cannot omit.

                     By word without writing one let out a farme,
                     The lessee most lewdly the rent did retaine,
                     Whereby the lesser vvanting vvriting had harme:
                     Wherefore he vowed, vvhile life did remaine,
                     Without vvriting neuer to let thing againe▪
                     
                     Husband quoth the vvife, that oath againe reuart,
                     Else vvithout vvriting you cannot let a cracke
                     God thanke the sweet vvife, quoth he, from my hart:
                     And so on the lips did her louingly smacke.
                  
                  
Such a thing it was, but not hauing the
booke here, and my memorie being no
better then I would haue it, I haue stumbled
on it as well as I can. But now to
strike this matter dead with a sound authoritie
indeede, and in so serious a matter
as vnder heauen is no weightier, to
such a person, as in the world is no worthier,
from such a scholer, as in Oxford
was no learneder, marke what a verse here
is, an Eucharisticall and Pareneticall verse.
He saith:

                     It Italici Augaei stabulum foedum
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         cloacam,
                     Ate purgars Romana
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         tolli.
                  
               
               If he had sayd Stercora, I could guesse well
enough what it had meant, but that the
Greek hath in some eares a better emphasis.
Thus writes their great Cāpiano 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ,
that confoundes all the Puritano Pa pist as.
                  M. Raynolds much more seemly vseth the metaphor, li. 1 c. 8. p. 290.
And yet to say truly, I make no great boast
of his authoritie to my text. If I had alledged
him in Diuinitie, I would haue stood

                     •
                  ustily to it,Iesuitae 
                        •
                     imum in ipsius capt
                        ••
                      re
                        •
                     orquere. and sayd 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , but for verses
in prayse of his Mistresse, there be twentie
of vs may set him to schoole: for be it spoken
without disgrace or disprayse to his
Poetrie, such a metaphor had bene fitter

for a plaine Dame, abhorring all Princely
pompe, and not refusing to weare russet
coates, then for the magnificent Maiestie
of a Mayden Monarke. Beleeue me,
I would fayne haue made him speake good
rime in English, but (as I am a true 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  )
I beat my braynes about it, the
space that one may go with the tyde from
London bridge, downe where the Priest
fell in vpon the mayd, and from thence
almost to Wapping, and yet I could not
couch it into a cleanely distichon. But
yet because I know Mistresse Philostilpnos
will haue a great minde to know what it
meanes, I will tell her by some handsome
circumlocution. His meaning is, that a
Ladie of Ladies, did for zeale to the Lord
of Lordes, take the like paines to purge
some Popish abuses, as the great giantly
Hercules did for Augeus. Now what maner
of worke that was, in the processe of
this discourse one way or other, you shall
see me bring it in, though yet I know not
where will be the fittest place for it: here
yet you see by the way I haue told the mās
meaning reasonable mannerly, yet still me
thinke I can say of his metaphor,

                     
                     That still (me thinke) he vsde a phrase as pliant,
                     That said, his Mistres was for wit a giant.
                  
               
               But I pray you let me go backe againe
to mery Martiall: for I should haue one
more of his, if I haue not lost it, Ad Phoebum.
Oh here I haue it.

                     Vtere lactucis &amp; mollibus vtere maluis,3. 68.
                     
                     Nam faciem durum Phoebe cacantis, habes.
                  
He aduises him to take somewhat to make
him soluble, for his face looked as if he
were asking, who should be M. Mayor the
next yeare. But I thinke this iest was borrowed
of Vespasianus foole, or else the
foole borrowed it of him: but the iest is
worthy to be receiued into this discourse.
This foole had iested somewhat at all the
boord, saue Vespasian him selfe; and belike
he thought, it was ill playing with
edge tooles, and Emperours; but Vespasian
commaunded him, and promised him
franke pardon, to breake a good iest vpon
him. Well Sir (then said the foole) I will
but tary till you haue done your businesse;
whereby he quipped the Emperours ill
feature of face, that euen when he was
meriest, looked as if he had bene wringing

hard on a close stoole. But let vs seek some
better authorities then Epigrams and Iesters:
sure I am I shall finde in historie,
which is called nuncia vetustatis, vita memoriae,
the reporter of antiquities, the life
of memory, many phrases, expressing the
same action, and not thinking their stile
any whit abased thereby. He that writes
the first booke of Samuel tels, that Dauid
did cut off the lap of Saules coate,1. Sam. 24. Spelūca quam i
                        •
                     gressus est Saul, vt purgaret ventrem. &amp; leaues
not to tell, what Saule was then doing.
The writer of Bassianus life telles, how he
was not onely priuily murdred, but murdred
at the priuy. Heliogabulus body was
throwen into a Iakes,S
                        •
                     etonius. as writ
                     •
                  th Suetonius.
Lastly the best, and best written part of
all our Chronicles, in all mens opinions,
is that of Richard the third, written as I
haue heard by Moorton▪ but as most suppose,
by that worthy, and vncorrupt Magistrate,
Sir Thomas More, sometime Lord
Chancelor of England, where it is writtē,
how the king was deuising with Teril, how
to haue his nephews priuily murdred, and
it is added, he was thē sitting on a draught
(a fit carpet for such a coūsel.) But to leaue
these tragicall matters, and come to comicall,

looke into your sports of hauking and
hunting, of which noble recreations, the
noble Sir Philip Sidney was wont to say,
that next hunting, he liked hauking worst,
but the faulconers and hunters would be
euen with him, and say, that these bookish
fellowes, such as he, could iudge of no
sports, but within the verge of the faire
fields of Helicon, Pindus, and Pernasus.
Now I would aske you Sir, lest you should
thinke I neuer read Sir Tristram. Doe you
not sometime (beside the fine phrase, or
rather Metaphor, of inewing a woodcock)
talke, both of putting a heron to the
mount, &amp; then of his s
                     •
                  cing? 
                     •
                  ell of springing
a pheasant and a partridge, and finde
them out by their dropping? Doe you not
further, to iudge of your haulkes health;
looke on her casting? if it be blacke at one
end, and the rest yellow, you feare she hath
the phillanders, if it be all blacke, you shall
see and smell, she is not sound. Lastly, you
haue a speciall regard to obserue, if she
make a cleane mute. Moreouer for hūting,
when you haue harbourd a stag, or lodged
a buck, doth not the keeper, before he
comes to rouse him from his lodging,

(not without some ceremony) shew you
his femishing, that thereby you may iudge
if he be a seasonable deare? And soone after,
followes the melodious cry of the
hounds, which the good Lady could not
heare, because the dogs kept such a barking.
And when all this is done, and you
are rehearsing at dinner what great sport
you haue had: in the middest of your sweet
meates, in comes Melampus, or Ringwood,
that sang the base that morning, and
in the returne home, lighted vppon some
powderd vermin, and layes a chase vnder
the table, that makes all as sweet as any suger-carrion;
&amp; all this you willingly beare
with, because it is your pastime. Thus you
must needes confesse, it is more then manifest,
that without reproofe of ribaldry,
or scurrility, writings both holy, and prophane,
Emblemes, Epigrams, Histories,
and ordinary and familiar communication;
admits the vse of the words, with all
their apurtenaunces; in citing examples
whereof, I haue bene the more copious,
because of this captious time, so ready to
backebite euery mans worke, and I would
forewarne men not to bite here, lest they

bite an vnsauory morsell. But here me
thinke it were good to make a pause, &amp; (as
it were at a long dinner) to take away the
first course; which commonly is of the
coursest meate, as powdred bie
                     •
                  e and mustard,
or rather (to compare it fitter) fresh
biefe and garlicke; for that hath three properties,
more suting to this discourse: viz.
to make a man winke, drinke, and stinke.
Now for your second course, I could wish
I had some larkes, and quailes, but you
must haue such as the market I come from
will affoord, alwaies remembred, that our
retiring place, or place of rende vous (as is
expedient when men haue filled their bellies)
must be Monsieur AIAX, for I must
still keepe me to my tesh: wherefore as I
say, here I will make the first stop, and if
you mislike not the fare thus farre, I
will make the second course
make you some amends.
            
            
               
               THE SECOND SECTION,
prouing the matter not to be
contemptible.
               
                  IT hath bene in the former
part hereof sufficiently proued,
that there is no obscenity,
or barbarisme in words
concerning our necessaries:
but now for the place, where these necessaries
are to be done, perhaps some will
obiect, that it was neuer of that importāce,
but that it was left to each mans own
care to prouide, for that which concerned
his owne peculiar necessitie. It is not so,
for I can bring very aut
                     •
                  nticall proofs out
of auncient records, and histories; that the
greatest magistrates that euer were, haue
employed their wits, their care, and their
cost, about these places; as also haue
made diuerse good lawes, proclamations,
and decrees about the same: &amp; all thereto
belonging; as by this that ensues shall
more plainely appeare. In the handling

whereof. I will vse a cōtrary method to the
former: for I wil begin now with prophane
stories, and end with deuine. First therefore
most certaine it is, that mischiefes
make vs seeke remedies, diseases make vs
find medicines, &amp; euill maners make good
lawes. And as in all other things, so by all
likelyhood in this we now treate of, when
companies of men began first to increase,
and make of families townes, and of towns
cities, they quickly found not onely offence,
but infection, to grow out of great
concourse of people, if speciall care were
not had to auoyd it. And because they
could not remoue houses, as they do tents,
from place to place, they were driuen to
finde the best meanes that their wits did
then serue them, to couer, rather then to
auoyd these annoiances: either by digging
pits in the earth, or placing the common
houses ouer riuers: but as Tully saith of
Metaphors, that they were like our apparell:
first deuised to hide nakednesse, then
applied for comelinesse, and lastly abused
for pride: so I may say of these homely
places, that first they were prouided for
b
                     ••
                  e necessitie, for indeede till Romulus

time I finde little mention of them; then
they came to be matters of some more
cost, as shall appeare in examples following;
and I thinke I might also lay pride to
their charge: for I haue seene them in cases
of fugerd sattin, and veluet (which is flat
against the statute of apparell) but for
sweetnesse or cleanlines,33. Henry 8. For it is no reason M. AIAX should haue a better gowne then his Mistresse. I neuer knew yet
any of them guilty of it; but that if they
had but waited on a Lady in her chamber a
day, or a night, they would haue made a
man (at his next entrance into the chamber)
haue sayd, fo, good speedye. Now, as
scholers do daily seeke out new phrases, &amp;
metaphors; and Tailors do oft inuent new
vardingales, and breeches: so I see no reason,
but Magistrates may as well now as
heretofore, deuise new orders for cleanlinesse,
and wholsomnesse. But now to the
stories, I alledged before, as it were at the
second hand, out of Lactantius; how Titus
Tacius that was king with Romulus, erected
the Statue of the Goddesse Cloacina, in a
great Priuy, made for that purpose. I finde
after this in the story of Liuy, how Tarquinius
Pryscus, a man of excellent good
spirit, but husband to awife of a more excellent

spirit; a man that wan a kingdome
with making a learned oration, and lost it
with hearing a rude one; a king, that was
first crowned by an Eagle, counselled by
an Augure, and killed by a traytor; whose
raigne &amp; his ruine, were both most strāgely
foretold. This worthy Prince is reported
by that excellent historian, to haue
made two prouisions for his city, one for
warre, the other for peace, both very commendable:
for warre a stone wall about
the towne, to defend them from outward
inuasions; and for peace, a goodly Iakes
within the towne, with a vault to conuey
all the filth into Tiber, to preserue them
from inward infection.
               Not long after him raigned Tarquinius,
surnamed the Proud, a tyrāt I confesse,
and an vsurper, and husband to a dragon
rather then a woman: but himselfe surely,
a man valiant in war, prouident in peace,
and in that yong world, a notable politician:
of whom Liuy takes this speciall note,
that comming to the crown without law,
and fearing others might follow his example,
to do that to him, he had done to
another
                     •
                   he was the first that appointed a

a guard for his person, the first that drew
publike matters to priuate hearings, the
first that made priuate wars, priuat peace,
priuate confederacies; the first that lessened
the number of the Senators; the first,
that when any of them died, kept their
roomes voyde, with many excellent Machiauillen
lessons; which, who so wold be
better instructed of, let him read but his
accusing of Turnus, his stratagem against
the Gabians, &amp;c. But the matter I would
praise him for, is none of all these, but only,
because he built a stately temple, and a
costly Iakes, the words be, Cloacámque maximam
receptaculum omnium purgamentorum
vrbis, a mighty great vault to receiue
all the filth of the city. Of which two
works, ioyning them both together, Liuy
saith thus, Quibus duobus operibus, vix noua
haec magnificentia quicquam adequauit.
Which two great works, the new magnificence
of this our age, can hardly match.
Now though Brutus, after in a popular &amp;
seditious oration, to incite the multitude
to rebellion, debased this worthy worke of
his, saying he wasted the treasure of the
realme, and tyred &amp; toyled out the people,

                  in exhauriēdis cloacis, in emptying of Iaxes
(for that was his word) yet it appeares by
the history, that if his son had not defloured
the chast Lucrece (the mirrour of her
sex) Brutus with his fained folly, true value,
and great eloquence, could neuer haue
displaced him. For euen with all his faults
you see, that Brutus his owne sons would
haue had him againe; who laying their
heads together, with many yong gallants,
that thought them selues much wiser then
their fathers; concluded among thēselues,
that a king was better then a Consull, a
Court better then a Senate; that to liue
onely by lawes, was too strict and rigorous
a life, and better for pesantly then princely
dispositions: that Kings could fauour, as
well as frowne, reward, as well as reuenge,
pardon, as well as punish, whereas the law
was mercilesse, mute, and immutable, finally,
they concluded it was ill liuing for
them, where nothing but innocency
could protect a man. Lo Brutus, how eloquently
thy sons can plead against their father;
but thou hast a Iury of sure free-holders,
that gaue a verdite against them,
and thy selfe wast both iudge and shiriffe,

and hastenedst execution.
               O braue minded Brutus! I will not call
thee primus Romanorum, because one was
shent for calling one of thy posterity, vltimus
Romanorum, but this I must truly say,
they were two Brutish parts both of him,
and you; one to kil his sons for treason, the
other to kill his father in treason;Caesar called Brutus son, and sayd to him when he stabd at him, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . and yet
you would both make vs beleeue you had
reason, and why so? forsooth because
Victrix causa placet superis, sed victa Catoni.
That is to say in English, You had great
fortune, and your cosin had great friends,
yet neither died in bed, but both in battell,
onely his death was his enemies aduancement,
and thy death was thy enemies destruction.
But to omit these trifles, and to
returne to my tesh; whereas thou railest against
so great a Prince, for making of so
sumptuous a Iakes, this I cannot endure at
thy hands: &amp; if thou hadst played me such
a sawcy part here in my countrey, first of
mine owne authority,It seems the writer hereof would fain be thought a Iustice of peace. I would haue granted
the good behauiour against you: secondly,
Tarquinius him selfe might haue
Scandalum magnatum against you: &amp; thirdly,
a bill should haue bene framed against

you in the Star chamber, vpon the statute
of vnlawfull assemblies: &amp; then you would
haue wisht you had kept your eloquence
to your selfe, and not when a man hath
done but two good workes in all his life,
you to stand rayling at one of them. For
suppose that Tarquin had giuen me but a
fee, thus would I pleade for him. Maister
Brutus you haue made vs beleeue all this
while, you were but a foole; but I see now,
if one had begged you, he should haue
found you a Bygamus. And whereas you
seeme to disgrace my honorable client, for
making of A IAX, I dare vndertake to
proue it, that your owne lawes, your religions,
your customes, yea your conscience,
is against you, and shews, it is but a meere
calumniation. For to omit Dame Cloacina,
so lately deified, did not the noble Hercules,
whom you Brutus honor as a God, far
ancienter then Quirinus, and Romulus, among
those many labours that eternized
his memory, make cleane Augeus dūghils.

                     Quis non Euristea durum
                     Aut illaudati nescit Busiridis aras.
                  
If the worke haue a basenesse, Tarquinius
but with his purse, Hercules with his

person effected it, leauing a patterne to
posterity both of labour and wit, for by
turning a streame of water on the mickesons,
he scowred away that in a weeke, that
an hundred could scant haue done in a
yeare. Then would I end with some exclamation,
and say, O tempora, ô mores! Oh
times, oh manners! If a man be not popular,
you will straight say, he is proud; if he
keepe good hospitality, you will say he
doth but fill many Iaxes; if he build goodly
vauts for sewers, you will say, he spends his
treasure in exhauriendis cloacis Or rather I
would say, O Hercules come and bend thy
bow against Brutus, that shootes arrowes
through thy sides to slay Tarquinius.Martial. 505 Ca
                        •
                     p
                        •
                     r
                        •••
                     usidi 
                        〈◊〉
                      fertur meacarmina qui
                        ••
                      N
                        •
                     scio si sciero ve ti
                        •
                     i causidice. But
now let me leaue playing the lawyer, and
lawyerlike be friēds immediatly with him
whom euē now I talked against so earnestly,
I meane with Brutus; because indeed sauing
in this one case, I neuer meane to be
of counsell with Tarquin: for such proud
clients will speake vs passing faire while we
serue their turnes, &amp; after picke a quarrell
against vs when we sue for a reward. Now
therefore to go forward with the story.
               When this valiant Brutus had thus

discharged the Kings and Queenes out of
the packe, and shewed himselfe indeede a
sworne and vowed enemy to all the coate
cardes, there crept in many new formes
of gouernment, and euery one worse then
other, namely, Consuls, Dictators, Decemuiri,
Tribunes, Triumuiri, till at last after oft
enterchanges, it came to the gouernment
of Emperours. In all which times, there
were not onely lawes, and speciall caueats
giuen to the great officers in time of war
and danger, Ne quid respab detrimenticaperet,
to looke to the safety of the maine
chance (the cōmon wealth) but also there
were officers of good account, as Aediles,
Praetores vrbis▪
                   that made inquiries de stillicijis,
de aquae ductibus, of reparatiō of houses,
of watercourses, or common sewers,
of which I could recite out of the 43. booke
of the Digest. tit. 23. de cloacis. where you
shall finde: It was lawfull for any man purgare
&amp; reficere cloacam: What officers
were to licence him that would priuatam
cloacam facere, quae habeat exitum in publicum:
What speciall care was to be had of
Tubus and Fistula. Lastly, that nouam cloacam
facere is concedit, cui publicar
                        •
                     
                     ̄ viarum

cura sit. That is, that no man might make a
new Iakes, but he that had licence of the
wardens of high wayes. With much more
which I would cite, if it were not to auoid
prolixity. And from them no doubt was
deriued our commission of sewers, of
which, the best of vs all I hope, will take no
scorne: which commission, though in our
countrey it is chiefly intended to keepe open
the chanels of riuers in the deepe
countrey, that the water may haue free
passage. Yet the very name imports, that
therin is comprised the subiect of my present
Discourse, which in populous townes
had as much neede to be looked to, as the
other, infection being fit to be auoided aswell
as innundation. But now I hasten to
imperiall examples: for though I haue
shewed already some authorities for my
text, out of the practise of the lawes, the
prouident care of Magistrates, the magnificent
cost of kings, the religion (though
false) of pagans. Yet vntill I haue added to
all these, the maiesty of Emperours, and
the verity of Scriptures, I suppose some
carping mouths will not be stopped.
               The first example I meete with among

the Emperours,Some of our rude countreymen English this obtorto collo, hā
                     ging an arse. was a matter rather of
curtesie then cost: and if any man will say,
that I draw this into my Treatise, as it were
obtorto collo, I answere, that in my vnderstanding,
the tale falleth so fit and proper
vnto this discourse, as indeede to haue
brought it into any discourse sauing of AIAX,
I would say it were vnproper and vnciuill.
The argument holdes à min
                        •
                     re ad
maius. Now hearken to my tale. Claudius
Emperour of Rome, and husband to that
filthie Masselyna,
                  Agrippa saith of her, that she lay with 22. seueral mē in 24. houres, at the common stewes. &amp; tādem lassata viris non satiata redijt.
                   (Vilissima quae fuerunt
vel sunt,) she that was worthie, for the
commonnesse of her bodie (be it spoken
with sauing the reuerence of all women
that are or were, saue her selfe) to haue bin
metamorphized into AIAX, rather then
poore Hecuba, for barking at him that kild
her son, into a bitch. This Claudius I say,
though not for cost (as Tarquin) yet for his
curtesie was greatly to be commended: for
a Gentleman one day being talking with
him, and falling suddenly into a grieuous
fit of the cholicke, the poore Gentleman
would not for good manners sake breake
wind, which might presently haue eased
him, &amp; after the disease increased so sore on

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
him that he died. The Emperour enformed
of his death, was much grieued thereat,
specially hearing of the cause, &amp; immediatly
thereupon made it be solemnly proclaimed,
that if any mā hereafter should be
troubled with the cholick, it should not be
taken for ill maners to break wind, though
it were in the Emperours owne company.
Now it may be, some man in disgrace of
this proclamation, will say, that this Claudius
was but a cuckold and a foole. I answer,
that for the cuckold, that was none of
his fault, &amp; if it were a fault, God forbid all
our faults should be seene on our foreheads▪
And for the foole, the old prouerbe
may serue vs, Stultorū plena sunt omnia, the
world is full of fooles. But take heede how
you beg him for a foole, for I haue heard
of one that was begged in the Court of
wards for a foole, &amp; when it came to triall,
he proued a wiser man by much, then he
that begged him. And though I haue small
skill in the law, specially in these prerogatiue
cases, (for I must confesse I studied
Littleton but to the title of discōtinuance)
yet me thinke I should finde a quirke, to
make thē that should beg him haue a cold

sute in the court of wards. For I take it to
be a ruled case, that though a man h
                     •
                  ld
wholly in Capite, put the case by a whole
Knights seruice, or halfe a nights seruice,
yet if he be couert Baron, as Claudius was
(for I am sure his wife ware the breeches)
&amp; being at his foole age of 31. the Custodia
must of course be graunted to the wife, although
the man be plus digne de sang. And
thus much we say, sauing to our selues all
aduātage of exceptiō to the vnsufficiencie
of the bill,Two par
                        •
                     s why Cl
                        •
                     udius was esteemed a foole. Looke Sueton. &amp;c. And without that the sayd
Claudius did fondly to cause a mans hand
to be cut off vpon the motion of a strāger,
and without that he had almost marred all
the pastime he &amp; his friends should haue
had at a Naumachia or sea-game, with
resaluting the slaues that should haue
fought, in good Latin. And lastly, without
that the sayd Claudius at his being in EnglandClaudius was in England.
(though he was counted one of the
best free-holders in Middlesex) could forfeit
any land that he held by the right of
his sword, either in fee-simple, or fee-taile,
either by the socke, or the smocke, to any
other Lady, but the Lady his wife. But alas
Claudius, thy friendes may say, that I am

a bad Lawyer, for all this while I haue done
litle better then confesse the action, but I
care not seeing thou art dead, Mortui non
mordent, and it were fitter now to preach
for thee, then to pleade for thee: well then
for thy gentle proclamatiōs sake, loe what
in sadnesse (if I were to make thy funerall
Sermon) I would say for thee, that howsoeuer
some writers haue wrōged thee with
the name of a foole,He is called foole to his face. in one of thy iudgements
I may liken thy wisedome to Salomon,But hereby hangs a tale. Claudius his iudgement like that of Salomon.
and in one of thy iests, I can compare
thy wit with Diogenes. Asse for example,
a womā on a time disclaiming her sonne,
&amp; pretending that for conscience sake she
must needes confesse a truth, viz. how her
owne child died, &amp; this was a Supposititius,
a substitute in his place, for auoyding of
her husbands displeasure, no euidence appearing
to the contrary, &amp; the next heire
following the matter very hard, by cōplot
with the mother, who remained obstinate
in the tale, Claudius then sitting in iudgement,
seemes to beleeue it, and seeing the
man a comely young man, and she no old
womā, and oft protesting she maliced him
not: he commanded her immediatly in his

presence to marrie him. The malicious
mother driuen to that vnlookt for pinch,
openly confessed her vnnaturall malice, to
auoyde so vnnaturall a mariage; and thus
much for his iustice; now let vs here what
his iest is. A certaine Gentleman that had
his fingers made of lime twigges, stole a
peece of plate from Claudius one day at a
banket; the conueyaunce was not so cleanly,
but one had spied it, and told the Emperour,
&amp; offered to accuse him of it, whereby
his goods might haue bene all confiscate:
but this good Prince would neither
head him nor hang him, no nor so much
as once suffer him to be troubled; onely
the next time he came, he caused him to
be serued in an earthen dish. The Gentleman
being abashed at it, for the dish gaue
him his dinner. Claudius was so far from
laying his crime in his dish, that he sayd,
be of good cheare man, and fall to thy
meate, &amp; whē thou hast dined put vp that
dish too: for I will spare thee that with a
better will then the last, for perhaps thou
hast a minde to poke vp thy dish when
thou likest thy meate well. And so farewell
good Claudius, &amp; when any of my friends

are troubled with the collicke. I hope I
shall make them remember thee.
               The next Emperour that is fit to bring
into this discourse, is Vespasian, though
his predecessour Vitellius, who is noted
to haue bin a passing greater eater, would
(I thinke) haue takē it in good part, to haue
bin offred a cleanly &amp; easie place for egestion
after his good digestion. But to the
purpose. Vespasian before he was Emperour
had borne some other offices, among
the which, one was Aedilis and it is written
of him, that he incurred great displeasure
with Otho thē Emperour, because he had
not seene better to the keeping sweet of
the streets, and caused the filth of them
(according to his office) to be caried to
the places appointed for the same. But afterward
himselfe cōming to be Emperour
(though the Citie of Rome was before his
time sufficiently furnished of Iaxes) yet it
seemed there wāted other places of neare
affinitie to thē (which he found belike whē
he was Aedile by experience) I meane certaine
pissing conduites: and therefore he
caused diuerse to be erected in the most
populous and frequented places of the

Citie, and saued all the vrine in cesternes,
and sold it for a good summe of money to
the Dyers. But though I tell you the tale
thus plainely, you must imagine the matter
was much more formally and sinely
handled, and namely, that there was an Edict
set out in this sort.
               
                  
                     
                        
                           By the Emperour C. Flauius Vespasianus, pater
patriae, semper Augustus, &amp;c.
                           FOrasmuch as his Maiestie hath bene
enformed by sundry credible men, that
great abuse is committed by the irreuerent
demeanure of diuerse persons, ill
brought vp, who without all due respect
of ciuilitie &amp; reuerence, in most vnseemely
manner, shed their vrine, not onely against
the wals of his royall pallace, but also
against the tēples of the Gods &amp; Goddesses.
Whereby not onely vgly and lothsome
sights, but filthy and pestiferous sauours
are dayly ingendred, his Maiestie
therfore as well of a fatherly care of his citizens,
as of a filiall reuerēce to the Gods,
hath to his great charges, &amp; of his princely
boūty &amp; magnificēce, erected diuerse &amp;
sundry places of faire polished marble, for

this speciall purpose, requiring, &amp; no lesse
straightly charging all persons, aswell Citizens
as straungers, to refraine from all other
places, sauing these especially appointed,
as they tender his fauour, &amp;c.
                        
                     
                  
               
               Thus could I haue penned the Edict,
if I had bene secretarie. For it had not
bene worth a figge, if they had not artificially
couered the true intent (which was
the profite) and gloriously set foorth the
goodly and godly pretence (that was least
thought on) viz. the health of the people,
and cleane keeping of the temples. But I
doubt, notwithstanding this goodly Edict,
it will be obiected, that it was condemned
for a base part, by a iudge whose
sentence is aboue all appeale: I meane
that noble Titus, deliciae humani generis,
he that thought the day lost in which he
had done no man good: to answer which,
I would but say as was sayd to him, when
the pissing money was put into the perfumed
purse, suauis odor lucri, the smell of
gaine is sweet. And I dare vndertake, this
answer will satisfie my Lord Maior of Lō
                  don,
and many of the worshipfull of the
Citie, that make sweet gaines of stinking

wares,Oyles, oad, tarre, &amp;c. and will laugh and be fat, and say:

                     So we get the chinkes,
                     We will beare with the stinkes.
                  
But I must find out a better aunswere for
courtly wits, and therefore I say to them,
that according to the discipline &amp; custom
of the Romanes (in my opinion, vnder reformation
of their better iudgements) this
was so honorable a part of Vespasian, that
he was therefore worthy to haue bene deified.
For if Saturnus were allowed as a
God, by the name of Stercutius, as is before
alleaged, for finding a profitable vse of
all manner soyle, I see a good reason (àpaeribus)
that Vespasian should aswell be deified,
for finding a meanes to make money
of vrine, and accordingly to be named Vrinatius,
of Vrina, as the other is, of Stercus,
Stercutius. Further Vespasian was famous
for two true miracles done by him, greater
then all their gods beside euer did.
Now if any take exceptions to his face, because
the foole told him, he looked as if it
went hard with him: trust me it shall goe
hard with me too, but I will find somewhat
to say, for him; and first I will get some of
the painting that comes from the riuer of

Orenoque, which will wonderfully mend
his complexion. Secondly, I will say this,
how bad soeuer his face was, he had something
so good, that a handsome woman
gaue him a thousand crownes, for putting
his seale with his labell to her pattent, and
yet she exhibited the petition (as I take it)
in forma paper, for she was starke naked.
Once this I am sure Suetonius writes, that
when his steward asked him, how he shold
set down that 1000. crownes on his booke,
he b
                     •
                  d him write it among his other perquisites,
in some such sort.

                     
                        It. for respit of h
                              ••
                           age from a louing
tenant to her louely Lord for
a whole knights f
                              •
                           e, recepi—
                        1000, crown
                              ••
                           .
                     
                  
               
               Now for his wit, though I could tell
you two excellent tales, how he deceiued
a groome of his chamber, of his brother,
and how he would needs be halfe with his
horse-keeper, for setting on a shoe on a
horse that lacked none: yet I omit them
both, because many will be too apt to follow
the president, and I will keepe me very
strictly to my tesh, and specially because I
hasten to a most royall example. I meane
of Traian. There is no man (I thinke) that

hath either trauelled farre countreys, or
read forraine stories, but hath either heard
of the famous exploits and victories that
he had, or seene some of the stately and
sumptuous monumēts that he made. This
Traian was Emperor of Rome, and then
Emperor when Rome stood at her highest
pitch of greatnes, a man whose conquests
were most glorious, whose buildings were
most gorgeous, whose iustice was most
gracious, he that stayed his whole armie,
to right the cause of one widdow, he that
created a Magistrate, and deliuering him
the sword for iustice, said to him, vse this
for me as long as I gouerne iustly, but against
me when I gouerne otherwise, he in
whose time no learned mā was seene want,
no poore man was seene begge, hee that
would boast of Nerua his predecessor, of
Plotina his wife, of Plutarke his counceller:
finally, this Traian was so well accomplished
a Prince in all princely vertues, as
no storie, no time, no memorie, in all
points can match him. This most renow
                  
                     •
                  ed
Emperor, hearing there was a towne
in Bithinia, farre off from Rome, and in
a place where he was like neuer to bee

troubled with the euill sauour, that was
much annoyed for lacke of a good conueyance
of the common priuies, thought
himselfe bound (as a father to all his subiects)
to prouide a remedie for such an inconuenience,
and of his owne purse hee
tooke order for making a vault of great
cost and charge in the citie. And for full
satisfaction of the reader herein, I will set
downe the two Epistles, as I find them in
the tenth booke of the Epistles of Plinius
Secundus to Traian Epist. 99.
               Argumentum quaerit an.
C. Plinius Secundus Traiano Imp. S.
Amestrianorum ciuit as, domine, &amp; eligans
&amp; ornata habet, inter praecipua opera pulcherrimam,
eandem
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   longissimam plateam, cuius
à latere per spacium omne porrigitur, nomine
quidem flumen re vera cloaca fedissima. Quae
sicut turpis &amp; immundissima aspectu it a pestilens
est odore teterrimo. Quibus ex causis no
                     •
                  
minus salubritatis quam decoris interest eam
contegi, quod fiet si permiseris curantibus n
                     •
                  
                  bis
ne desit pecunia operi tam magno quam
necessario. Which is thus in English.
               
               Caius Plinius to Traian the Emperour
greeting:The cōtents is, whether he shal couer the water that runs by the towne of Amestris. The Citie of the Amestrians

(my Lord) being both commodious and
beautifull, hath among her principall
goodly buildings, a very faire and long
streete, on the side whereof runneth thorough
the whole length of it, a brooke,
in name (for it is called so) but indeede a
most filthy Iakes; which as it is foule and
most vncleanely to behold, so is it infectious
with the horrible vile sauour, wherfore
it were expedient, no lesse for wholsomenesse
then for handsomnesse, to haue
it vaulted, which shall be done if it please
you to allow it, and I will take care that
there shall be no want of money for such a
worke, no lesse chargeable then necessarie.
Thus writes Plinius Secundus, a Romane
Senator, and as it were a deputie
Lieutenant in the Prouince of Bithinia, to
the great Traian, and I doe halfe maruell
he durst write so, for had it beene in the
time of Domitian, Commodus or Nero,
either Martiall should haue iested at him
with an Epigram, or some secretarie that
had enuied his honest reputation, should
haue bene willed to haue aunswered the
letter in some scornefull sort, and would
haue written thus.
               
                  Maister Plinie, my Lord God the Emperour,Che scrisse taccia 
                        •
                     t piu 
                        〈…〉
                     .
not vouchsafing to answere your
letter him selfe, hath commaunded me to
write thus much to you, that he maruels
you will presume to trouble his diuine
Maiestie with matters of so base regard,
that your father being held a wise man,
and a learned, might haue taught you
better manners, that his Maiestie hath
matters of greater import, concerning
the state of Empire, both for warre &amp;
peace, to employ his treasure in. Thus
much I was commaunded to write. Now
for mine owne part, let me say thus much
to you, that I heard my Lord God the
Emperour say, that if the ill sauour annoy
you, you may send to your Mistresse for a
perfumed handkerchife to stop your nose,
and that some Physicians say, the smell of
a Iakes is good against the plague. Some
such answere as this, had bene like to haue
come from some of those beastly Emperours,
and their filthie followers. But how
did Traian answere it? I will set you downe
his owne letter, out of the same booke, in
the same language.
               
                  
                     
                     Argumentum.
                     Permittit confornicari cloacam.
Tr. Plinio S.
                     
                        Rationis est, mi secunde Charissime, contegi
aquam istam quae per ciuitatem Amestrtanorum
fluit, si detecta salubritati obest, Pecunia
ne huic operi desit, curaturum te secundum
diligentiam tuam certum habeo.
                     
                  
               
               Thus in English. It is good reason, my dearest
Secundus, that the water be couered that
runs by the citie of the Amestrians, if the
want of couering may breede infection.
And for money for the worke, I make no
question, but you according to your accustomed
diligēce, will make prouisiō. Short
and sweet, yea most sweet indeed, because
it was of an vnsauorie matter. But I had almost
forgot to English the argument, and
then folkes might laugh indeede at me,
and thinke I were Magister incipiens with
ans, &amp; say I could not English these three
words, permittit confornicari cloacā; what
the good yeare, what is the same confornicari?
trust me there is a word I neuer read
in Homer nor Aristotle, marry indeede
they wrote but ill Latine, no nor in Tully,
in Liuie, in Tacitus, nor in all the Poets:

what a straunge worde is this? Ho sirra
bring hither the Dictionarie. Which of
them, Cooper? No no, Thomas Coperus
omisit plurima verba. Which then, that
with the French afore the Latin, or Thomas
Thomas? Yea, bring me them two.
What hast thou brought the two dictionaries?
I meant but the two Thomases.
Come old friend Tom,A great officer among the boyes at Eaton, Maister of the rods. Tom, Qui fuer as quō
                     dam
clarae praepositor aulae, you haue made
rods to ierke me withall ere now, I thinke
I shal giue you a ierke, if you do not helpe
me to some English for this word. Looke it
sirra there in the dictionarie. Con, con. Tush
what dost thou looke in the French? thou
wilt make a sweete peece of looking, to
looke for confornicar in the French: looke
in the Latin for fornicor. F, fa, fe, fi, fo, for,
for, foramen, forfex, forica, forma, fornicator,
(now I thinke I am neare it) fornix,
fornicor,Eliots dictionarie and Coopers placed these 2. words, too neare togither. aris, are. There, what is that? A
vault, to vault or arch any thing with a cō
                  passe.
Well said, carrie away the bookes againe,
now I haue it: then thus it is, He alloweth
the vaulting or arching ouer of the
Iakes. Mary Gods blessing on his heart for
his labour, and I loue him the better for it.

Wherfore (most noble Traian) thou mayst
well be called the patterne of all princely
qualities, comely, bountiful, martial, mercifull,
a louer of learning, moderate in priuate
expences, magnificent in publike,
most goodly of stature, amiable, not onely
in thy vertues, but euen in thy vices. For
to say the worst was euer said of thee, these
were all thy faults, ambition, or desiry of
glorie in warres, loue of women, and persecuting
of religion. For so they ioyne
thee, Nero, Domitianus, Traianus, Antoninus,
Pontifices Romanos laniarunt. To
which thus I aunswer without a fee, but
with all my heart: that thy ambition was
so honorable, and thy warlicke humour so
well tempered, that thou didst truly witnesse
of thy selfe, that thou didst neuer enuy
any mans honour, for the confidence
thou haddest of thine owne worth: and all
the world can witnesse, that thou neuer
didst make vniust warre, nor refuse anie
iust or indifferent peace. For that same
sweet sinne of lecherie, I would say as the
Frier sayd, a young man and a young woman
in a greene arber in a May morning;
if God do not forgiue it, I would. For as sir

                  Thomas More saith of Edward the fourth
                     •
                  
he was subiect to a sin, from which, health
of bodie in great prosperitie of fortune,
without a speciall grace, hardly refrayneth.
And to speake vprightly of him, his lusts
were not furious, but friendly, able with
his goodly person, his sweete behauiour,
and his bountifull gifts, to haue won Lucretia.
Besides, no doubt his 
                     〈◊〉
                   was the
lesse, in that he euer loued his wife most
dearely, and vsed her most respectiuely: for
I haue euer maintained this paradox, it is
better to loue two too many, then one
too few. Lastly, for the persecution of thy
time, though I dare not defend it, yet there
is a maxime, inuincibilis ignorantia recusat,
and sure thou didst not know the truth,
and thy persecution was very gentle, and
halfe against thy will, as appeareth by
the 98. Epistle of the tenth booke of Plin.
Epistles, where thou doest vtterly reiect
all secret promoeters, and dost pronounce
against the strict inquisition, Conquirendi
non sunt, &amp;c. Wherefore I doubt not to
pronounce, that I hope thy soule is in heauen,
both because those thou didst persecute
prayed for thee, wishing to thee, as

                  Tertul. saith; Vitam prolixam, imperium securum,
domum tutam, exercitus fortes, Senatum
fidelem, populum probum, orbem quietū.
A long life, a happy raigne, a safe dwelling,
strong armies, a faithfull Senate, honest
people, and a quiet world. Further, it is
written by authors of some credite, that
thy soule was deliuered out of hell, at the
prayer of great S. Gregorie, which though
I am not bound to beleeue,S. Damas
                        •
                     en S. Brigid write this of Traian, beleeue them who list, for though it seem Popish, yet it ministers an argument against some Popish opinions. yet as in loue,
I had rather loue too many thē too few, so
in charitie, I had rather beleeue too much
then too litle. As for that Scripture, ex inferno
nulla redemptio, I haue heard it oft alleaged
by great clerkes, but I thinke it is
in the Epistle of S. Paule to the Laodiceans,
or in Nicodemus Gospell: for I neuer
yet could find it in the Bible. Wherefore
this I will frankely say for Traian, that
whersoeuer I find a Prince or a Peere with
so great vertues, and so few vices, I will
honour him, loue him, extoll him, admire
him, and pronounce this of him; that the
armie is happie that hath such a Generall,
the Prince happie that hath such a councellor,
the Mistresse happie that hath such
a seruant, and thus I end my prophane

authorities, &amp; now I come to the deuine,
wherein I thinke I shall serue you in the
bāket I haue promised you as my self haue
bene serued many times at our cōmencement
feasts, and such like in Cambridge,
that when we haue bene in the middest of
some pleasant argument, suddenly the Bibler
hath come, and with a loud and audible
voyce begun with Incipit libri Deuteronomium,
caput vicesimum ter-cium. And
then suddenly we haue bene all s't tacete,
and hearkened to the Scripture, for euen
so must I now after all our pleasant stories,
bring in as I promised, some diuine authorities,
to the which I pray you let vs with
all due reuerence be attentiue.
               In the aforesaid 23.Authorities of Sripture. Chapter of Deuteronomie,
in the 12. verse, I find this text:
               12 Habebis locum extra castra ad quem
egrediaris ad requisita naturae.
               13 Gerens paxillum in balt
                     •
                  o, cumque sederis
fodies per circuitum, &amp; egesta humo operies
quo releuatus es.
               14 Dominus enim Deus tuus ambulat in medio
castrorū, vt eruat te &amp; tradat tibi inimicos
tuos, &amp; sint castra tua sācta, &amp; nihil in eis
appareat foeditatis, ne derelinquat te. That is.
               
                  12 Thou shalt haue a place without
thy tents, to which thou shalt go to do the
necessities of nature.
               13 Carying a spade staffe in thy hand,Or a trowell.
and when thou wilt ease thee, thou shalt
cut a round turfe, &amp; thou shalt couer thy
excrements therewith, in the place where
thou didst ease thy selfe.
               14 For the Lord thy God walketh in
the midst of thy tents to deliuer thee, and
to giue thy enemies into the hāds, that thy
tents may be holy, and that there appeare
no filthinesse in them, lest he forsake thee.
               But me thinke some may say vpon hearing
of this text, What is it possible there
should he such a Scripture, that handleth
so homely matters? I can hardly beleeue
it; I haue alwaies had a bible in my parlour
these many yeares, and oft time when the
weather hath bene foule, and that I haue
had no other booke to reade on, and haue
wanted company to play at cards or tables
with me, I haue read in those bookes of the
old Testament, at least halfe an houre by
the clocke, &amp; yet I remember not anie
such matter. Nay further, I haue heard a
Preacher, that hath kept an exercise a

ye are togither vpon the bookes of Moses,
&amp; hath told vs of Genesis, &amp; genealogies,
of the arke &amp; the propitiatorie, of pollutions,
of washings, of leprosies, but I neuer
heard him talke of such a homely matter
as this. I answere, It may be so very well.
And therfore now I pray you, sith the text
is so strange to you, giue me leaue to put
you in mind of two vertuous &amp; honest obseruations
out of this (how homly so euer)
yet wholly Scripture. One, to be thankfull
to our Sauiour for his mercies; th'other to
be faithfull to our Soueraigne for her merits.
We may thanke God that al these seruile
ceremonies, which S. Paul calleth the
workes of the Law, as Circumcision, New
moones, Sabbaths, washings, cleansings,
with touch not, handle not, eate not, &amp;c.
are now taken away &amp; quite abolished by
the Gospell, which hath now made Omnia
munda mundis. And as S. Augustine saith,
in steed of ceremonies, combersome, infinite,
intollerable, vnpossible, hath giuē Sacraments,
easie, few, sweet, &amp; gracious, &amp;
hath taught vs in steed of hearing Fac ho
                        •
                     
&amp; vi
                        •
                     es, to say now to him, DaDomine quod
iubes. Secondly, whereas it seemes you

neuer heard this text preached on, you
may blesse in your soule, and pray for her
Maiesties so peaceable and prosperous
raigne, this text being not fit for peace &amp; a
pulpit, but only for warre and a camp. And
therfore though I hope we shal neuer haue
cause to heare such a Scripture preached
of in England, yet those that serue in other
countreys, both haue &amp; shall heare it thus
applyed (and that oft not without neede)
viz. that though now to the cleane all
things are cleane, yet still we must haue a
speciall care of cleanlines, and wholsomenesse,
euen for the things here spoken of,
and if for such things, how much more for
rapes, the
                     •
                  ts, murthers, blasphemies,
things (as God knowes) too common in al
our campes. Ne Dominus Deus noster, qui
ambulat in medio castrorum derelinquat nos.
Least the Lord our God, that walketh in
the midst of our tēts, shold forsake vs. And
euen in the time of the sweetest peace, me
thinkes I could also say, here at home, that
it is an vnreuerent thing, for Churches ordained
for prayer, and church-yardes appointed
for burial, to be polluted and filed
as if they were kennels and dunghils.
               
                  And I haue thought sometime with
my selfe, that if I were but halfe so great
an officer vnder our most gracious Emperesse,
who is in deed worthy, and onely
worthie to be Traians Mistresse, as Plinius
Secundus was vnder that Traian; I
would write for the mending of such a
lothsome fault in my neighbour towne of
Bath (where many noble persons are oft
annoyed with it) as Plinie did for Amestris.
Yet whie may I not by Poetica licē
                     tia,
and by an honest &amp; necessarie figure
(in this age) called Reprehensio, imagine
my selfe for halfe an houre to be Secundus,
and suppose some other, that perhaps at
this houre is not farre from Traians countrey,
to be that worthiest Traian? For
though in the English Grammer, the feminine
gender is more worthie then the
masculine, the which rule I wish long
may hold. Yet lest old Priscian should say
I brake his head when I neuer came neare
him,There is a Comedy called Priscianus vapulās, wher if one should say ignēhanc, Priscian wold cry, his head were broken. I will keepe me in this my pleasant
imitation, within such an honest limitation,
as shalbe free from all iust reprehension,
and write, in steed of C. Pl. Secundus
Traiano Imp. Salutem.
               
               
                  Haec tibi Traiano, terra
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   mari
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   remoto,
               Scribit Misacmos, nulli pietate Secundus.
               
                  The Citie of Bath (my Lord) being both
poore enough and proud enough, hath
since hir highnesse being there, woonderfully
beautified it selfe in fine houses for
victualing and lodging, but decaies as fast
in their ancient and honest trades of merchandise
and clothing: the faire Church
hir Highnes gaue order should be reedified,
stands at a stay, and their cōmon sewer,
which before stood in an ill place, stands
now in no place, for they haue not any at
all. Which for a towne so plentifully serued
of water, in a countrey so well prouided
of stone, in a place resorted vnto so
greatly (being at two times of the yeere, as
it were the pilgrimage of helth to al saints)
me thinke seemeth an vnwoorthie and dishonorable
thing, wherefore if your Lordship
would authorise me, or some wiser
then me, to take a strict account of the money,
by hir Maiesties gratious grant gathered
&amp; to be gathered, which in the opinion
of many, cannot be lesse then ten thousand
pounds (though not to wrong them,
I thinke they haue bestowed vpon the

point of 10000. pounds abating but one
cipher) I would not doubt, of a 
                        ••
                     inate
church to make a reuerent church, and of
an vnsauorie towne a most sweete towne.
               
               
                  This I do the rather write, bicause your
Lordship, &amp; the rest of hir Maiesties most
honorable counsel, thought me once worthy
to be Steward of that towne, but that
the wiser counsell of the towne thought it
not meet, out of a deeper reach, lest being
already their poore neighbor, this increase
might haue made my estate too great among
them. For indeed the 
                        •
                     ee belonging
to it, &amp; some other commodities annexed,
might haue been worth to me de claro vi
                           ••
                        
&amp; modis, per ann
                           •
                        m. CCCClxxx.d.
                  
               
               
                  Moreouer I am to certifie your Lordship,
that the spring taken out of the hot
bath into the priuate, doth not annoy or
preiudice the vertue of the hot bath as hir
Maiestie hath bin lately informed. And it
is not vnnecessarie, for some honorable
persons that come thither, sometimes to
haue such a priuate bath. But now I pray
you let vs hearken to the Scripture, for the
Bibler is not yet come to Tu autem.
               
               I find also in the second &amp; third chapters

of Nehemias, which some call the second
booke of Esdras, where he tels how
no body but he and his asse went to suruey
the citie. Et ingressus sum ad portam
vallis nocte, &amp; ante fontem draconis, &amp; ad
portam stercoris, &amp; consider abam murum Ierusalem
dissipatum &amp; portas eius consumptas
igni. And in the third chapter shewing
who repaired all the ruines, Et portam vallis
aedificauit Hanum &amp; habitatores Zanoe,
ipsi aedificauerunt eam, &amp; statuerunt valuas
eius, &amp; seras, &amp; vectes, &amp; mille cubitos in
muro vsque ad portam sterquilinii. Et portam
sterquilinii aedificauit Melchias filius Rhechab
princeps &amp;c. And the gate of the valley
built Hanum and the inhabitants of
Zanoe, they built it, and they made the
leaues of the gate, and the lockes, and the
hinges, and a thousand cubites in the wal,
euen to the doung gate, and Melchias son
of Rhecab being Prince of Bethacharan
built the doung gate.There is a noble and learned Lady, dowager to the Lord Iohn Russell, that will not name loue without saue reuerence. I would haue saide,
saue-reuerence the doung gate, but that
Nehemias who was a Gentleman well
brought vp, and a courtier, and had beene
a sewer and cupbearer to Artaxerxes,
writes it as I haue recited it.
               
                  But now to the purpose, perhaps you
will saie, that this makes nothing to the
present argument, that the gate is called
Doungate, for we haue a gate in London
called Dougate, that with a little dash with
a pen will seeme to be the same gate, &amp; yet
hath no great affinitie with the matter, &amp;
on the other side, there is a place hath a
glorious title of Queene Hiue, and yet it
was ordained for my lady Cloacina. I grant
it might be so, for so there is a parish by
London called Hornsey, which is an vngratious
crooked name, and yet I verilie
perswade me, that the most glorious or
gratious street in Londō hath more horns
in it sometime either visible or inuisible
then all the other parish. But concerning
the gate in Ieruselagim called Porta Stercoris,
I finde it was so called bicause it laie
on the East side of the Citie, toward the
brooke Cedron, whither all the raine water
of the Citie, and all other conueiances
ran, as they do out of the Citie of London
into the Thames: and that being so, and
the city so populous, the gate might wel be
called Porta Stercoris. Now without the city
I finde mentioned another place ordained

for the like purpose, to carrie out all
such filth as the rain could not wash away,
and had no common passage, &amp; that was
the valley of Hinnon, which seemes by the
map to lie Southeast and by South to the
Temple, and thither, I say, the Scauengers
caried their loding,The Brickils. as they do at London
beyond Golding lane. And therfore in the
new Testament it is called gehenna, and
taken for hell, and if you haue a minde to
know how I come by this diuinitie, trust
me if you will, I come by it as true men
come by their goods. For so it is, that not
long since there dwelt in Bath a schoole-master,
a man whom I fauored much, for
his sake that sent him thither. But he had
not beene there long, but a controuersie
arose betwixt him &amp; some preachers therabout,
among whom we haue too manie
that studie nothing but the controuersies,
and it came after many disputes on both
sides, at last to writing and publishing of
Books. And the schoole-master (though
being no Preacher) wrote a booke with
this title, that Christ descended not into hell:
the very sight of which title, being flat cō
                  tradictorie
to an article of the Creede, I

remember I said of the man as Heywood
saith in his prouerbes, that heerafter

                     He might be of my Pater noster indeed,
                     But sure he should neuer come in my Creed.
                  
And therefore I might repute him as a
good humanist, but I should euer doubt
him for a good deuine. Now as I say, hearing
in these disputes and sermons, diuerse
names of hell throughly sifted. As Ades,
Tartaros, Infernum, Stagnum ardens, and
last of all Gehenna, which last I was most
vsed to, as hauing an old verse when I was
at Eaton, of a Peacocke.

                     Angelus in penna, pede latro, voce gehenna.
                     A bird that hath an Angels plume,
                     A theeuish pace, a hellish tune.
                  
Consequentlie, I obserued, that our honest
&amp; learned Preacher of Bath M. R. M.
first prooued hel to be a local place (if not
circumscriptiue, yet at least definitiue. Thē
he shewed the etymologie of the worde
gehenna to be deriued in Greeke of 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ,
that is, the earth or valley of Hinnon, thē
he told, that this place was as it were the
common dunghill or mickson of the whol
towne, that the Iewes had vsed in this valley,
to make their children passe through

the fire, as a sacrifice to the Deuill, according
to the Psalme of Dauid, they offered
their sonnes and daughters vnto deuils. Finally,
that our sauior to make a more fearfull
impression in their harts, of the paines
of hell indeed, which they know not, vsed
the name of this hellish place, which they
knew that had in it these hatefull hellish
properties, smoke, stinke, horrible cries, &amp;
torment. But least you shuld think I speake
as a parrot, nothing but what I haue heard
an other say, let me adde somwhat of mine
own poore reading, and that shall be this,
that this valley of Hinnon was once for
the sweete aire, fine groues, faire walks, &amp;
greene and pleasant fields, comparable
with any place about Ierusalem, but when
the abhominable Idoll of Moloch was
erected in it, whose purtraiture was like a
king hauing the head of a calfe, al of bras,
&amp; hollow within: vnto which (most inhumanely)
they sacrificed humane flesh, yea
their owne children, &amp; to the end that the
wicked parents might not feele remorse
of the wofull cries of the wretched children,
they daunced a straunge medley
about the fire, hauing musicke sutable to

such mirth, of drums and Iewes harpes
(for I thinke hornepipes and bag-pipes
were not then found out) I say these abhominations
being there committed, the
good Iosias, driuen to vse an extreme medicine
to so extreme a maladie, first burned
and brake all too peeces the horrible
Idoll, and then in detestation of the abuses
there committed, cut downe the fine
groues, tare vp the sweete pastures, defaced
the pleasant walks; and to the end that
all passengers should flie from it, that were
woont to frequent it, he caused all filthie
carrion, dead dogs and horses, all the filth
of the streetes, &amp; whatsoeuer hatefull and
vgly things could be imagined, to be caried
thither. And this ô Iosias was thy zealous
reformation: but alas how little do
some that pretend thy name, participate
thy nature. They pull downe Moloch, but
set vp Baal Peor &amp; Beelsebub, their leane
deuotion thinks the hill of the Lord is too
fat, their enuious eie serues them like Aretinoes
spectacles, to make all seeme bigger,
then it should be, they learne the Babylonians
song in the Psalmes.

                     Downe, downe with it at any hand,
                     
                        Make all thing plaine, let nothing stand.
                  
They care neither for good letters nor
good liues, but onely out of the spoiles to
get good liuings, our good Lord Bishops
must be made poore superintendents, that
they might superintend the goodly Lordships
of rich Bishopricks, &amp; then we that
be simple fellowes must beleeue, that they
offer vs Iosias reformation, wheras indeed
it sauors not of that in any thing but the
ill sauor: for as Iosias defaced a faire field,
and made it spurcitiarum latrinam, so they
would ruinate our cathedrall churches, &amp;
make them Spelunca latronum, as my good
friend Hary-Osto, or mine Host Hary saith
of the Pagan Rodomont, after his host
had ended his knauish tale.

                     He makes the Church (oh horrible abuse)
                     Serue him for his prophane vngodly vse.
                  
Wherefore let them cal themselues what
they list, but if they learn no better lessons
of Iosias, but to turne sweete fields to stinking
dunghils, they shall make no newe
Iaxes in England by my consent, &amp; I hope
my deuise shall serue to mende many that
be now amisse, with an honester &amp; easier
reformation, &amp; I doubt not but the Magistrate

that hath charge to see ne quid respub.
detrimanti capiat, will prouide, least
our receipts prooue deceipts, our auditors
frauditors, and our reformation deformation,
and so all run headlong to gehenna,
where the sport will be torment, the musicke
clamors, the prospect smoke, and
the perfume stinke. Which two last, I
meane smoke and stinke, I haue verily perswaded
me, are two of those paines of hel,
which they call poena sensus:
                  Esa. cap. 3. Eterit pro sua
                     
                        ••
                      adore foe
                        •
                     or. which paine
S. Augustine affirmes may also torment
aerie or spiritual bodies, as partly appeers
in the storie of Tobias, where a wicked
spirit was driuen away with the smoke of
a broyled liuer; and therefore I haue endeuored
in my poore buildings to auoide
those two inconueniences as much as I
may. As for the two other annoiances, that
the old prouerbe ioineth to one of these,
saying, there are three things that make a
man weary of his house, a smoking chimney,
a dropping eues, and a brauling woman.
I would no lesse willingly auoid thē,
but when stormes come, I must as my
neighbors do, beare that with patience,
which I can not reforme with choler, and

learne of the good Socrates, who when
Xantippe had crowned him with a chamber-pot,
he bare it off single with his head
and shoulders, and said to such as laughed
at him for it.
               It neuer yet was deemd a woonder,
               To see that raine should follow thunder.
               And to the intent you may see, that I
am not only groundedly studied in the reformatiō
of AIAX, which I haue chosen
for the proiect of this discourse, but that I
am also superficially seene in these three
other matters of shrewd importance to all
good house-keepers, I will not be dangerous
of my cunning, but I will venture my
pen and my paines, if you will lend but
your eies or your eares, though I perhaps
shall haue more fists about my eares then
mine owne for it. First therefore for the
house, I will teach you a verse for it, that I
thinke M. Tusser taught me, or else now I
may teach it his sonne.

                     To keepe your house dry, you must alwaies in sommer.
                     Giue money to the mason, the tiler and plummer.
                  
For the shrewd wife, read the booke of
taming a shrew, which hath made a number

of vs so perfect, that now euery one
can rule a shrew in our countrey, saue he
that hath hir. But indeed there are but two
good rules. One is, let them neuer haue
their wils; the other differs but a letter,
let them euer haue their wils, the first
is the wise, but the seconde is more in
request, and therefore I make choise
of it.
               Lastly for smoking chimneys, many remedies
haue been studied,One taught an excellent rule to keepe a chimney from smoking, &amp; a priuie from stinking, viz. to make your fire in your priuy, and to set the close stoole in the chimney. but one excellent
and infallible waie is founde out among
some of the great Architectes of
this age, namely to make no fire in them,
and by the same rule they may haue verie
sweete Iaxes too. But the best waie I
haue found, is out of Cardan partly, but
as I think mended by practise of some of
my neighbors of Bath: who make things
like halfe a cloke about the toppes of
the chimneys, with a fane to turne
rounde with the winde, which bicause
they make of wood is dangerous for fire,
but being made thinne of copper plates
or of old kettels will be as light and without

                  
daunger, but this is supererogation,
and more then I promised you. But nowe
to come home againe, though home be
neuer so homely, the fourth annoiance
though it be left out of the prouerbe, may
compare with two of the other three,
which is a stinking priuie, which makes a
man wish somtime, saue for an ornament
of the face (as Heywood saith) to haue no
nose.

                     Most of our sauours be more soure then sweet,
                     A nose then or no nose▪ which is most meet?
                  
And for reformation of this, many I doubt
not, haue ere this beaten their braines and
strained very hard, to haue found out some

remedy; but yet still I find all my good
friendes houses greatly annoyed with it.
               But yet ere I come to discouer this exact
&amp; exquisite forme that I haue promised,
let me adde a word or two out of the
good and wholsome rules of phisick, both
for authorising the homely words so oft vsed,
as for prouing that the matter in their
faculty is specially regarded; for diuers,
that are otherwise very daintie and curious,
yet for their healths sake, will endure
both to heare homely language, to see
sluttish sights, to taste dirtie drugs, and to
shew secret sores; according to the Italian
prouerbe,

                     
                        All confessore medico &amp; aduocato,
                        Non deue tener cosa celato.
                     
                     
                        From your confessor, lawyer, and phisition,
                        Hide not your case on no condition.
                     
                  
No man therefore is either so ignorant, or
so impudent, as either not to know or not
to confesse, that the honorable science of
phisick, embaseth it selfe ofttimes about
the care of this busines. For whereto serueth
I pray you, fiant clysteria, fiant pillulae,
fiant potiones, fiant pessi. But fie on't, it
makes me almost sicke to talke of them,

sure I am the house I treat of, is as it were
the center to which they must all fall first
or last, and many times I thinke first were
wholsomer of the two. But to inforce my
proofes, though shortly yet soundly, I will
not bring any peculiar prescripts out of
Galen and Hipocrates, least you should
oppose against them Asclepiades or Paracelsus,
nor stand long to dilate of the Empiricall
phisick, or the dogmaticall and the
methodicall. Of all which if I should say
all I could, I feare me not so much, that
phisitions would take me for a foole, as
that fooles will take me for a Phisition. I
will therefore set downe as it were certain
autenticall rules, out of a generall Councell
of Phisitions, &amp; that sent by common
consent to a great K. of England, against
which if any Doctor should except, he
must ipso facto be counted an hereticke.
This therefore I finde of my text in that
booke that begins
Anglorum regi scribit schola tota Salerni.
For when he hath beene aduised to make
choice of three Phisitions,
Haec tria mens laeta, requies, moderata diet.
Doctor Diet, Doctor Quiet, and Doctor

Meryman. Then they admonish him of
many particulars, for his health, for his
foode, for his house, &amp;c. Which if they
might with good maners write to a king,
then I may without inciuilitie recite to a
kinseman.

                     Si vis incolumem, si vis te viuere sanum,
                     Curas tolle graues irasci crede profanum,
                     Parce mero caenato parum nec sit tibi vanum,
                     Surgere post epulas somnum fuge meridianum.
                     Nec mictum retine, nec cōprime fortiter anū. &amp;
                     
                     The Salerne schole doth by these lines impart
                     Health to the British king, and doth aduise,
                     From cares thy head to free, from wrath thy hart,
                     Drinke not much wine, sup light, and soone arise,
                     After thy meate, twixt meales keepe wake thine eies.
                     And when to natures needs prouokt thou art,
                     Do not forbeare the same in any wise:
                     So shalt thou liue long time with little smart.
                  
Loe what a speciall lesson for health they
teach, to take your oportunitie so oft as it
is offered of going to those businesses. Thē
soone after to let you know how wholesome
it is to breake winde, they tell fower
diseases that come by forbearing it.

                     Quatuor ex vento veniunt inventre retento,
                     Spasmus, hydrops colica, vertigo, quatuor ista.
                  
But most especially making for my purpose,

both for word and matter.

                     Aer sit mundus, habitabilis ac luminosus,
                     Infectus neque sit, nec olens foetore cloacae.
                  
Which as a principal lesson, to be learned
by builders, I will set downe in verse.

                     A builder that will follow wise direction,
                     Must first foresee before his house he makes,
                     That th'aire be cleare, &amp; free from all infection,
                     And not annoyd with stinch of any Iakes.
                  
For indeed let your house be neuer so well
apparaled, neuer so wel plaistered &amp; painted,
if she haue a stinking breath I shall neuer
like of my lodging. Lastly, there be two
other verses, with which I will end these
schoole authorities.

                     Multiplicant mictum, ventrem dant aescula strictum,
                     Post pyra dapotum, post pomum vade cacatum.
                  
And thus I take it, I ende this part of my
discourse, with a well chosen verse to the
purpose: yet ere you go, take this with you
in prose, that many Physitions doe hold,
that the plague, the measeals, the hemorhoids,
the small poxe, &amp; perhaps the great
ones too, with the fistula in ano, &amp; many of
those inward diseases, are no way sooner
gotten, then by the sauor of others excrements,
vpon vnwholsome priuies. Wherfore

I will nowe drawe to the conclusion
of this same tedious discourse: for it
is high time now to take away the boord,
and I see you are almost full of our homely
fare, and perhaps you haue beene vsed
to your dainties of Potatoes, of Caueare Eringus,
plums of Genowa, all which may
well increase your appetite to seuerall euacuations,
we will therfore now (according
to the phisick we learned euen now) rise &amp;
stretch our legs a litle, &amp; anon I wil put on
my boots, and go a peece of the way with
you, and discourse of the rest: in the mean
time my selfe will go perhaps to the house
we talke off, though maners would, I offered
you the French curtesie, to go with me
to the place, where a man might very
kindely finish this
discourse.
            
            
               
               THE THIRD SECTION,
shewing the forme, and how it
may be reformed.
               
                  NOw therfore to come where
wee left last, for I know you
would faine haue your instructions
ere you go home,
as soone as I haue giuen my
horse some breath vp this hill, I will ride
along with you, so you will ride a sober
pace: for I loue not to ride with these
goose chasing youthes, that poste still to
their iourneies end, and when they come
thither, they cannot remember what businesse
they haue there, but that they had
euen as much in the place they came from.
               These inconueniences being so great,
and the greater bicause so generall, if
there be a way with little cost, with much
cleanelinesse, with great facilitie, &amp; some
pleasure to auoid them, were it not rather
a sinne to conceale it, then a shame to vtter
it? Wherefore shame to them that
shame thinke, for I will confesse frankely
to you, both how much I was troubled
with the annoyance, &amp; what I haue found

for the remedy. For when I found not only
in mine owne poore confused cottage,
but euen in the goodliest &amp; stateliest pallaces
of this realme, notwithstanding all
our prouisiōs of vaults, of sluces, of grates,
of paines of poore folkes in sweeping and
scouring, yet still this same whorson sawcy
stinke, though he were commanded on
paine of death not to come within the
gates, yet would spite of our noses, euen
when we would gladliest haue spared his
company, prease to the faire ladies chambers.
I began to conceaue such a malice
against al the race of him, that I vowed to
be at deadly fewd with them, till I had
brought some of the chiefest of them to
vtter cōfusion. And conferring som principles
of Philosophy I had read and some
conueyances of architecture I had seene,
with some deuises of others I had heard, &amp;
some practises of mine owne I had payed
for: I found out at last this way that is after
described,
                     The principles are these, A
                        •
                     r non penetrat aquam. Natura non 
                        •
                     atitur va
                        •
                     u
                        ••
                     . and a maruellous easie and
cheape way it is, and I dare speake it vpon
my credit, not without good experience,
that though it be neither far fetched, nor
deare bought, yet it is good for Ladies, &amp;

there be few houses that may not haue the
benefit of it. For there be few great &amp; well
contriued houses, but haue vaults and secret
passages made vnder ground, to conuey
away both the ordure &amp; other noisom
things, as also the raine water that fals into
the courts, which being cleanly in respect
of the eie, yet bicause they must of
force haue many vents, they are oft noysome
in regard of the smell. Specially in
houses of office, that stand high from the
ground, the tuns of them drawing vp the
aire as a chimney doth smoke. By which it
comes to passe manie times (specially if
the wind stand at the mouth of the vaults)
that what with fish-water comming from
the kitchins, bloud and garbage of fowle,
washing of dishes and the excrements of
the other houses ioined togither, and all
these in moist weather stirred a little with
some small streame of raine water. For as
the prouerbe is,

                     Tis noted as the nature of a sinke,
                     Euer the more tis stird, the more to stinke.
                  
I say these thus meeting togither, make
such a quintessence of a stinke, that if Paracelsus
were aliue, his art could not deuise

to extract a strōger. Now bicause the most
vnauoidable of all these things that keepe
such a stinking stir, or such a stinke when
they be stirred, is vrine and ordure, that
which we all carie about vs (a good speculation
to make vs remēber what we are, &amp;
whither we must) therfore as I said before,
many haue deuised remedies for this in
times past, some not many yeeres since,
and I this last yeere, of all which I will
make choice only of two beside mine own
to speake off, bicause men of good iudgement
haue allowed them for good, but
yet (as the ape doth his yoong ones) I
thinke mine the properest of them all.
               The first and the ancientest, is to make a
close vault in the groūd, widest in the bottome,
&amp; narrower vpward, &amp; to floore the
same with hot lime &amp; tarris, or some such
dry pauing as may keep out al water &amp; aire
also: for if it be so close as no aire can come
in, it doth as it were smother the sauor, like
to the snuffes or extinguishers wherewith
we put out a candle, and this standes with
good reason, that seeing it is his nature to
make the woorse sauor the more he is stirred,
and nothing makes him keepe a more

stinking stir, then a litle wind &amp; water, surely
there can be litle or no annoiāce of him
in this kinde of house, where he shall lie so
quietly. But against this is to be obiected,
that if there be a little cranny in the wall
as big as a straw, or if the groūd stand vpō
winter springs or be subiect as most places
vnder ground are, to giue with moist weather,
thē at such times it must needs offēd.
               Besides in a Princes house where so
many mouths be fed, a close vault wil fill
quickly; and that obiection did my Lord
of Leicester make to Sir Iohn Young, at
his last being at Bristow, who commended
to my Lord that fashion, and shewed
him his owne of a worse fashion, and told
him that at a friends house of his at Peter
hill in London, there was a very sweet priuie
of that making.
               Another waie, is either vpon close or
open vaults, so to place the sieges or seats
as behinde them may rise tunnes of chimneys,
to draw all the ill aires vpwards: of
which kinde I may be bold to say, that our
house of Lincolnes Inne, putteth downe
all that haue beene made afore it, and is
indeed both in reason and experience, a

meanes to auoid much of the annoyance
that is wont to come of them, &amp; keepeth
the place all about much the sweeter. But
yet to speake truly, this is not sate from all
infection or annoiance while one is there,
as my sense hath told me, for
Sensus non fallitur in proprio obiecto.
Or perhaps by the strict wordes of the statute
it ought to be so, &amp; that but two parts
may be deuised away, and a third must remaine
to the heire, for I dare vndertake,
go thither when you will, your next heire
at the common house, whatsoeuer charge
he is at in the sute, I am sure he may bee
made a sauor, at the least for the 
                     
                        •
                     ertiam
partem aboue al reprises, if the fault be not
his owne. And further, when the weather
is not calme, the winde is so vnruly, that it
will force the ill aires down the chimneys,
and not draw them vp, as we see it doth in
chimneys where fire is made, force downe
the smoke, notwithstanding that the verie
nature of fire helpeth to inforce it vpward,
whereas these moist vapours are apt (euen
of their owne nature) to spreade abroade,
and hang like a deaw about euery thing.
Wherefore though I am but a punie of

Lincolnes Inn
                     •
                  , &amp; the builder heerof was
a bencher, ye
                     •
                   I will vnder reformation,
prefer my deuise afore his, either bicause
it is better, or else out of the common fault
of yoong men in this age, that we thinke
our deuises wiser then our elders. Yet with
this respectiue modestie, that bicause my
deuise as with water, where that cannot be
had, or where houses stand on an exceeding
flat, there I will leaue the worke to
his ouersight, but where any conuenient
current is, and no want of water, there I
would be surueyer, and so to deuide the regiment,
that if for the dry land seruice he
be generall, for the water seruice I will
be Admirall.A true praise of Li
                        •
                     colnes Inne. Yet by the way, I hope all
the Innes of court will gratulate the present
flourishing estate of our Lincolnes
Inne: not so much for furnishing the realm
with most honorable, vpright and well
learned magistrates, great sergeāts, graue
counsellers, towardly barresters, yoong
gallants of worth &amp; spirit sans nombre, but
also (that I may nowe deale with mine
equals, and not with my auncients) with
two such rare enginers,M. Plat set foorth a booke of engines. me for this one
deuise, and Maister Plat for verie manie.

Or if enuie will not suffer them to giue vs
due honor, let vs two M. Plat, at least grace
one another: and I am the willinger to offer
this kindnes to you, bicause I was aduised
by some to haue recommended this
deuise to your illustrations, which I was
very like to haue done, saue that we are of
no great acquaintance, and beside I haue
a little ambitions humor of mine owne to
be counted a deuiser, though to cleare me
of pride, you see my first practice is vpon
so base a subiect, as I hope no body will
enuy me, or seeke to take it from me: as
the sweet Zerbino said to Marfysa, of the
vgly Gabrina.

                     You haue so sweet a peece to carrie by you,Ariost. Cant. 20.
                     
                     As you are sure that no man will enuy you.
                  
And after he had played a worde or two
with them, he concluded,

                     Ben siate accopiati Io iurerei,
                     Se come essa e bella tu gagliardo sci.
                     No doubt you are a fitly matched paire,
                     If you as lustie be, as she is faire.
                  
But when they had done breaking off iests
one on another, and that it came to breaking
of staues, the peerelesse Prince (for
his othes sake) was faine to take that most
hatefull hagge into his protection. And

so I suppose, that some may play in like
sort vpon me and my writing, and say;

                     The writer and the matter well may meete,
                     Were he as eloquent as it is sweete.
                  
But if they do, let them take heed, that in
one place or other of this pamphlet, they
do not pull themselues by the nose, as the
prouerbe is But that you may see M. Plat,
I haue studied your booke with some obseruation:
if you would teach me your
secret of making artificiall cole,Some coniect
                        •
                     re, that stale and cowdoung must effect both these multiplications. and multiplying
barley (though I feareme both
the meanes will smell a little of kin to M.
AIAX) I assure you I would take it verie
kindly: and we two might haue a sute togither
for a monapolie, you of your cole,
as you mention in your booke, and I of M.
reformed AIAX: and if you will trust me
to draw the petitions, you shall see I will
get some of the presidents of the starch
and the vineger, and make it carrie as
good a shew of reason, and good to the
common wealth as theirs doth. As first
for yours I would frame these reasons: I
would shew the excellent commodity of
iron-milles (for if you speake against them
your sute will be dasht straight.) I would

proue how they reduce wilde and sauage
woods, to ciuill and fruitefull pastures. I
would alledge, they are good for maintenance
of nauigation, in respect that euery
ship, what with his cast peeces, ankers,
bolts and nailes, hath halfe as many 
                     •
                  un
of iron as timber to it. I would say, it is a
commodity to the subiect, cōsidering they
sell it for twelue or fourteene pounde the
tun, and when it came out of Spaine or
Holland, it was sold but for eight pound.
The like also I would say for glasse: and so
concluding, that the woods must needs be
spent vpon these two (as doubtlesse they
wil in a short time) then your deuise for artificiall
cole, of how homely stuffe soeuer
you make it, will be both regarded and rewarded.
And thus perhaps making some
great man your half, you may haue an imposition
of a tenth or a fift of euery chaldron
of your fewell. And though it should
poison al the towne with the ill sauour (as
the brew-house by White hall doth hir
Highnes own house, &amp; all Channon row)
yet what for necessitie, &amp; what for fauour,
it should be suffered. And neuer feare that
the price of your cole wil fal by cherishing

of woods, for now Sir Walter Mildmay is
dead, you shall haue few men will busie
themselues about any of these publike inconueniences,The Author could haue said honorable of both, but he takes honesty in this place for the high
                        ••
                      title.
or if his honest successor
would attempt it, he should I feare me,
haue small hope to preuaile, in that which
so honest a predecessor could not.
               Now for my Monapole, I would aske
but this trifling sute, and I would make
these goodly pretences. First, bicause I
haue prooued by good authours, that M.
AIAX is lineally descended of the ancient
house of Stercutius, and to haue liued
long vnder protection of Dea Cloacina, &amp;
to haue been praied for by so manie holie
Saints, I would procure (if the traffique
were as open with Rome as it hath been)
that as his progenitor Stercutius was allowed
for a God, by one of the first Romane
Pontifices Maximi, so M. AIAX
might bee allowed for a Saunt by Pope
Sisefinke, Sextus quintus (I wold haue said)
or one of his successours,Boce
                        ••
                     lo writes that S. Ciapiellet
                           •
                        
                      was canonized. (which if it be so
easie a matter, as Boccacio, &amp; other Italian
authors write, will not be very chargeable)
and then with some of the money
that you gaine with the perfumed cole,

(if you will lende it me, and I will mo
                     •
                  
                  gage
my Bull to you when I haue it, for
paiment) I will erect in London and elsewhere,
diuers shrines to this newe Saint,
&amp; all the fat offerings shall be distributed
to such poore hungrie fellowes as sue for
Monapolies, which being ioyned to the
ashes of your cole, will be perhaps not
vncommodious for lande, and you and I
will begge nothing for our rewarde, but
you as I saide afore,If I had such a graunt, he that were my heres ex asse, would be the richest squire in England. a fift part of euerie
chaldron, &amp; I but the sixt part of an assise
a moneth, of al that will not be recusants,
to do their daily seruice, at these holie
shrines. Nowe if any do obiect it is too
great a sute (for I thinke it would bee the
richest office in England) and saie that it
would amount to more then Peter pence,
&amp; Poll pence to, I would first to stop their
mouthes quickly, promise them a good
share in it, then I would amplifie the seruice,
that in this deuise I do in som respects
to the state of Christianitie, in a matter
that Saint Peter nor Paul neither neuer
thought of. For it is a common obloquie,
that the Turks (who still keepe the order
of Deuteronomie for their ordure do

obiect to Christians, that they are poysoned
with their own dung, which obiection
cannot be answered (be it spokē with due
reuerence to the two most excellent apostles)
with any sentence in both their Epistles,
so fully to satisfie the miscreant
wretches, as the plaine demonstration &amp;
practise of my deuice must needs answer
them. What thinke you M. Plat, is not
here a good plat laid, that you and I may
be made by for euer? onely I feare one let,
and that is this:I protest Misac mos and al
                        •••
                      friends loue 
                        〈◊〉
                      the better 
                        〈◊〉
                      If you call this flattery, I woul
                        ••
                      you would all deserue to be so flattered. I heare by report there
is a woorthy Gentleman, sometime of our
house, that hath now the keeping of the
great seale, &amp; these sutes cannot passe but
by his priuitie, &amp; they say (see our ill hap)
he hath euer beene a great enimie to all
these paltry cōcealments &amp; monapolies,
and further they say of him, that to beguile
him with goodly shews is very difficult,
but to corrupt him with gifts is impossible;
wel, if it be so, all our fat is in the
fire, &amp; let the lean go after. You may make
a great fire of your gaines, &amp; be neuer the
warmer: and I may throw all mine into
AIAX, and be neuer the poorer. Let vs
then make a vertue of necessitie, &amp; sith we

cannot get these monapolies, let vs sai
                     •
                  
we care not for them, and a vengeance on
them that beg them, and so we may haue
millions say Amen to vs, and we shall be
thought the honester men, &amp; seeing I haue
had so il luck in this, I wold no body might
euer haue any more of them, till I make
such another sute. And if M. Plat will follow
my aduise, he shall impart his rare deuises
gratis, as I do this, and so we may one
day be put into the Chronicles, as good
members of our countrey, more worthily
then the great Beare that caried eight
dogges on him when Monseur was heere.A worthy matter to be put into a Chron
                        •
                     cle 
                        •
                     nd fit for such worthy historiographers.
But to leaue Master Plats cole, which
kindled this fantasie in me, and to turne
to my tesh, though I called my selfe by
metaphor an admiral for the water works,
yet I assure you, this deuise of mine, requires
not a sea of water, but a cesterne;
nor a whole Tems full, but halfe a tunne
full, to keepe all sweete and sauorie: for I
will vndertake, from the pesants cottage,
to the Princes pallace, twise so much quā
                  titie
of water as is spent in drinke in the
house, wil serue the turne: which if it were
at Shaftsburie, where water is dearest of

any towne I know, that is no great proportion.
And the deuise is so litle combersome,
as it is rather a pleasure then a
paine, a matter so slight, that it wil seeme
at the first incredible, so sure, that you
shall finde it at all times infallible. For it
doth auoid at once all the annoyāces that
can be imagined, the sight, the sauour, the
cold: which last, to weake bodies, is oft
more hurtfull then both the other, where
the houses stand ouer brookes, or vaults
daily cleansed with water. And not to hold
you in too long suspēce, the deuise is this;
You shal make a false bottome to that priuie
that you are annoyed with, either of
lead or stone, the which bottome shall
haue a sluce osbrasse to let out all the filth,
which if it be close plaistered all about it,
and renced with water as oft as occasion
serues, but specially at noone and at night,
wil keepe your priuie as sweet as your parlour,
and perhaps sweeter too, if Quaile &amp;
Quando be not kept out. But my seruant
Thomas (whose pensil can performe more
in this matter then my pen) will set downe
the forme of this by it self in the end hereof,
that you may impart it to such friends

of yours, as you shall thinke worthie of it,
though you put them not to so great penance
as to reade this whole discourse.
               And that I may now also end your penaunce
that haue taken all this paynes to
read this, that for your pleasure you would
needs perswade me to write; I will not end
adruptly here, but as friends that are vpon
parting in a iourney, chuse a cleanly place
in the high way to take their leaues one of
another, and not in the dirt and myre: so I
                     •
                  
ere we part, will first for the ennobling of
this rare inuention, tell you somewhat of
the place, of the companie, of the meanes,
and of the circumstances, that first put so
necessarie a conceit in my head. For I remember
I haue read that Archymedes
the excellent enginer, (a man in his time
fully as famous in Syracusa, as out M. Plat
is here in England,) was sayd to haue disgraced
him selfe by an vntemperate or rather
vntempestiue ioy that he tooke of a
very worthy and memorable inuention of
his. The storie is thus. Archimedes hauing
long beaten his braynes to find some
way by art how to discouer, what quantity
of counterfaite mixture was put into a

crowne of massie gold, not dissoluing the
mettals, and finding no meanes in long
studie, at last washing him selfe naked in
a bathing tubbe, he obserued still that the
deeper he sunke the higher the water rose,
&amp; forthwith he conceiued (which after he
performed indeed) that by such a meanes
the true quantitie of each mettall might
be found, and the fraud discouered: with
ioy whereof he was so rauished, that starke
naked as he was, he ran out into the streets
crying, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   I haue found it, I haue
found it. At which for the time all the people
were amazed, and thought him mad,
till his inuētion after proued him, not onely
sober, but also suttle. What if some pleasant
conceited fellow should giue out by
way of suppositiō, that possibly the deuiser
of this rare conueyance, was at the time
of deuising thereof, sitting on some such
place, as the godly father sate on at his deuout
prayers, or the godlesse king sate on
at his deuilish practise? as put the case on
the stately stinking priuy in the Inner Tē
                  ple
(where many graue apprentices of the
law put their lōg debated cases to homely
vses) and that with ioy of so excellent inuencion

he ran out with his hose about
his heels, and cried, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  : so might
I be likened to Archimedes, and there be
some perhaps would be so verie fooles to
beleeue it. But lest any idle headed felow
should deuise, or any shalow braind people
beleeue such a tale, I doe before hand
giue the word of disgrace to any that shall
so say, &amp; wil make it good on their persons
with all weapons from the pin to the pike,
that whether it were by my good guiding,
or my good fortune, in the inuētion hereof,
nor in the execution I neuer receaued
such a disgrace as that of Archimedes. For
I assure you the deuise was first both
thought of &amp; discoursed of, with as broad
termes as any belongs to it, in presence of
sixe persons, who were (all saue one) enterlocutors
in the Dialogue, of which I was
so much the meanest, that the other fiue,
for beautie, for birth, for vallue, for wit, &amp;
for wealth, are not in many places of the
Realme to be matched. Neither was the
place inferiour to the persons, being a Castle,
that I call, the wonder of the West, so
seated without, as England in few places,
affoords more pleasures: so furnished within,

as China nor the West Indies scant allowes
more plentie. Briefly, at the very cō
                  ming
in, you would thinke you were come
to the Eldorado in Guiana. And by this I
hope both the inuētion &amp; execution hereof
may be sufficiētly freed from basenesse.
               Yet there remaines one easie obiectiō against
the merite of my good seruice herein,
I meane easie to make, but it will not
seeme so easie to answer, and that is, that
some may say, this may fortune to do well
in many places, but yet there is no depth in
the inuētion: for it is nothing but to keepe
down the ayre with a stopple, &amp; let out the
filth with a scrue, which some will mislike,
&amp; will not endure to haue such a businesse
euery time they come to that house. To
which I answer, that for depth in the inuē
                  tiō,
I affect it not (for I wold not haue it in
all aboue two foot deep.) And though the
prouerbe is, the deeper the sweeter, that is
to be intēded in some sweeter matters, for
the deeper you wade in this, you shall find
it the sowrer. And if it seeme too busie, he
that hath so great hast of his businesse, may
take it as he finds it, which cannot be very
ill at any time. But the old saying was, Look

ere you leape, and the old custome was, that
if a mā had no light to looke, yet he would
feele, to seeke that he would not finde, for
feare least they should finde that they did
not seeke. Further the paines being so litle
as it is, I should thinke him a slouen that
would not by him selfe or his man leaue it
as cleanly as he found it: specially considering
that in Deuteronomie you are told,
God mislikes sluttishnesse, and euery cat
giues vs an example (as houswiues tell
vs) to couer all our filthinesse, &amp; if you will
not disdaine to vse that which commeth
from the Muske Cat, to make your selfe,
your gloues, and your clothes the more
sweet, refuse not to follow the example of
the Cat of the house, to make your entries,
your staires, your chambers, and your
whole house, the lesse sowre. Indeede for
the deuise I grant it is as plaine as Dunstable
high way, &amp; perhaps it will be as cōmō
to, b
                     •
                  t neither of thē shall be any disgrace
to it. For I heard an Italian tell, that in Venice,
after they had had the great losse by
fire in Maximilians time, whē their Arsenall
was burnt with gunpowder, they had
long consultatiō, how to keepe their store

powder from dāger of fire, for feare of like
mischances; at last a plaine fellow (like my
selfe) came and told, that he had deuised a
way, and prayed to haue audiēce. Then he
told them a long tale, but all to this short
purpose, that gunpowder was made of iij.
simples, viz. saltpeeter, brimstone, &amp; coale,
that each of these seuerall, would be easily
kept from fire, and be quencht if they were
kindled, but being compoūd, it blew vp all
in a momēt, if the least sparke did but meet
with it; thē he shewd that the causes could
not be so sudden of vsing powder, but that
the simples being ready, it might soone
be made; lastly that saltpeeter did grow
rather thē wast with lying, whereas being
made into powder, it doth consume, &amp;c.
All which though euery man there knew
before, yet because they had not offered
to put it in practise, they gaue him a reward
for his deuise, and followed therein
his aduise, placing these simples in seuerall
houses, which are so dangerous when
they are compounded, and since that time
they haue bene more annoyd with water
then with fire. Wherefore I assure me the
Magnificoes of Venice would allow of the

deuise, &amp; if I had some idle money, I might
hap be so idly disposed, to put out more
then I will speake of, vpon this returne,
when one of the sonnes and daughters
of S.The Mag. of Venice are called Figliuoli de S. Mar
                           ••
                        
                        ▪
                     
                   Marke had put my deuise in execution,
specially if that Molto Magnificentissimo
were yet aliue, that when his wife
was sicke, and the Phisition was to see her
water, he knew not how to bid her make
water, in wordes seemely for his high state
and her fine eares, that had neuer heard
so fowle a word as that in her life, till his
man tooke on him the matter, and found
a phrase, by circumlocution to signifie
pissing, and neuer once to name it, in this
sort; Chara signora viprego fate quello che
fate dinanzi al cacare. But see see, I would
faine haue bid you farewell, &amp; now we are
againe in our dirtie common place; well
Ile goe with you yet a coits cast farder,
and then vpon the next greene we will bid
farewel, and turne taile, as they say: wherefore
now I will make you onely a briefe
repetition of that I haue sayd. You see first
how I haue iustified the homely wordes &amp;
phrases with authorities aboue all exception.
I haue proued the care euer had of

the matter with examples aboue all comparison.
Lastly, I haue expressed to you
a cleane forme of it aboue all expectation.
Neither doe I praise it as Marchants doe
their wares, to rid their handes of them,
for I promise you, how high so euer I
praise it, I meane not to part with it: for
were I to praise it vpon mine oth, as we
do houshold stuffe in an inuentary, I wold
prayse it in my house, to bee worth 100
pounds, in yours 300 poundes, in Wollerton
500 pounds: in Tibals, Burley, and
Holmbie 1000 pounds, in Greenwitch,
Richmond and Hampton Court 10000.
And by my good sooth, so I would thinke
my selfe well payd for it. Not that I am so
base minded to thinke, that wit and art
can be rated at any price, but that I would
accept it as a gratuity fit for such houses
and their owners.
               For I tell you, though I will not take it
vpon me, that I am in dialecticorum dumetis
doctus, or in rhetorum pompa potens, or
coeteris scientijs saginatus, as doth our Pedantius
of Cambridge, yet I take it, that in
this inuention I shal shew a great practise

vpon the grammar, and vpon this point I
will chalenge all the grammarians, viz. I
say, and I wil make it good, that by my rare
deuise I shall make Stercutius a nowne adiectiue.
Now I know you will set your son
William to aunswere me, and he shall say
no no, and come vpon me with his grammer
rule vt sunt divorum Mars Bacchus Apollo,
virorum, &amp;c. and hereby conclude,
that he is both a substantiue, and that a substantiall
one too, and a Masculine.
               But all this will not serue, for I haue
learned the grammer too, and therefore
Come grammer rules, come now, your power
show, as saith the noble Astrophill. First
therefore I say, his no no is an affirmatiue.
               For in one speech two negatiues affirme.
               Secondly tell me pretty Will, what is a
nown substantiue? That that may be seene,
felt, heard, or vnderstood. Very well, now
I will ioyne issue with you on this point,
where shall we try it? Not in Cambridge
you will say, for I thinke they will be partiall
on my side. Well then in Oxford be
it, and no better Iudge then M. Poeta, who
was cheefe Captaine of all the nownes in

that excellent comedy of Bellum grammaticale.
                  This Comedy was playd at her Maiesties last being at Oxford.
For without all peraduenture, when
he shall here that one of his band, and so
neare about him, is brought to that state,
that he is neither to be seene, smelt, heard,
nor vnderstood, he wil sweare gogs nowns
he will thrust him out of his selected band
of the most substantial substantiues, &amp; sort
him with the rascal rablement of the most
abiect adiectiues. But now Sir that I haue
brought you to so faire a town as Oxford,
&amp; so sweet a companiō as your son William,
I will leaue you to him that made you.
               Now (gentle Reader) you haue taken
much paine,The Epilogue or conclusion. and perhaps some pleasure,
in reading our Metamorpo-sis of AIAX:
and you supposed by this time to
haue done with me: but now with your
fauour I haue not done with you. For I
found by your countenance, in the reading
and hearing hereof, that your conceit
oft-times had censured mee hardly, and
that somewhat diuersly, &amp; namely in these
three kindes.Three reproofs of this pamphlet. First you thought me fantasticall;
secondly, you blamed my scurrility;
and thirdly, you found me satyricall.

To which three reproofes, being neither
causlesse nor vniust, doe me but the iustice
to heare my three answers.
               I must needes acknowledge it fantastical
for me,Answer to the first obiection, of fantasticalnesse. whom I suppose you deeme (by
many circumstances) not to be of the basest,
either birth or breeding, to haue chosen,
or of another mans choise, to haue taken
so strange a subiect. But though I confesse
thus much, yet I would not haue you
lay it to my charge, for if you so do, I shall
straight retort all the blame, or the greatest
part of it, vpon your selfe: and namely,
I would but aske you this question, and
euen truely betweene God and your conscience,
doe but aunswer it. If I had entituled
the booke, A Sermon shewing a soueraigne
salue for the sores of the soule. Or,
A wholesome hauen of health to harbour the
heart in. Or, Amaruellous medicine for the
maladies of the minde. Would you euer
haue asked after such a booke? would these
graue and sober titles haue wonne you to
the view of three or four tittles? much lesse
three or foure score periodes. But when
you heard, there was one had written of

A IAX, straight you had a great mind to
see what strāge discourse it would proue,
you made enquiry who wrote it, where it
might be had, when it would come forth.
You prayed your friend to buy it, beg it,
borrow it, that you might see what good
stuffe was in it. And why had you such a
minde to it? I can tell you; you hoped for
some meriments, some toyes, some scurrility,
or to speake plaine English, some
knauery. And if you did so, I hope now
your expectation is not altogether frustrate.
Yet giue me leaue briefly to shew
you what prety pils you haue swallowed
in your pleasant quadlings, &amp; what wholsome
wormewood was enclosed in these
raisins of the sunne.
               Against malcontents,A briefe sum of the true intent of the booke. Epicures, Atheists,
heretickes, and carelesse and dissolute
Christians, &amp; especially against pride
and sensuality, the Prologue and the first
part are chiefly intēded. The second giues
a due praise without flattery, to one that
is worthy of it, and a iust checke without
gall to some that deserue it. The third
part as it teacheth indeede a reformation

of the matter in question, so it toucheth in
sport, a reprehension of some practises
too much in custome. All which the reader
that is honourable, wise, vertuous, and
a true louer of his countrey, must needes
take in good part. Now gentle reader, if
you will still say this is fantasticall, then I
will say againe, you would not haue read
it except it had bene fantasticall, and if
you will confesse the one, sure I will neuer
deny the other.
               The second fault you obiect,Answere to the second obiection of scurrility. is scurrility,
to which I answere, that I confesse the
obiection, but I deny the fault, and if I
might know whether he were Papist or
Protestant that maketh this obiection, I
would soone answere them: namely thus;
I would cite a principall writer of either
side, and I wold proue, that either of them
hath vsed more obscenous, fowle, and scurrill
phrases,This cannot be denied. (not in defence of their matter,
but in defacing of their aduersary) in
one leafe of their bookes, then is in all
this. Yet they professe to write of the highest,
the holiest, the waightiest matters that
can be imagined, and I write of the basest,

the barrennest, and most witlesse subiect
that may be described.
Quod decuit tantos cur mihi turp
                        •
                      putem?
I forbeare to shew examples of it, least I
should be thought to disgrace men of holy
and worthy memory.
               For such as shall find fault that it is too
Satyricall,Answer to the third obiectiō, that it is too Satyrical or sharpe against the faults of the time. surely I suppose their iudgement
shall sooner be condemned by the
wiser sort, then my writings. For when all
the learned writers, godly preachers, and
honest liuers ouer all England (yea ouer
all Europe) renew that old complaint.
Regnare nequitiam &amp; in deterius res humanas
labi.Seneca.
                  
When wee heare them say daily; that
there was neuer vnder so gracious ahead
so gracelesse members, after so sincere
teaching, so sinfull liuing: in so shining
light, such workes of darkenesse. When
they crie out vpon vs, yea cry indeed, for
I haue seene thē speake it with teares, that
lust and hatred were neuer so hote, loue
and charitie were neuer so colde: that
there was neuer lesse deuotion, neuer
more diuision: that all impiety hath all

impunity: finally, that the places that
were wont to be the samples of all vertue
and honour, are now become the sinkes of
all sinne and shame. These phrases (I say)
being written and recorded, sounded and
resounded in so many bookes and Sermons,
in Cambridge, in Oxford, in the
Court, in the countrey, at Paules crosse in
Paules church-yard: may not I as a sorie
writer among the rest, in a merie matter,
and in a harmelesse manner, professing
purposely, Of vaultes, and prîuies, sinkes
and draughts to write, proue according to
my poore strength, to draw the readers
by some pretie draught,Allusion to the former wordes. to sinke into a
deepe and necessary consideration, how
to amend some of their priuy faultes? Beleeue
it (worthy readers, for I write not to
the vnworthy) A IAX when he is at his
worst, yeeldes not a more offensiue sauour,
to the finest nostrils, then some of
the faultes I haue noted, doe to God and
the world. Be not offended with me for
saying it, more then I am with some of
you for seeing it. But this I say, if we would
amend our priuy faultes first, we should

afterward much the better reforme the
open offences, according to the old prouerbe.
Euerie man mend one, and all would
be amended. Trust me, they do wrong me
that count me Satyricall. Alas I do but (as
the phrase is) pull a haire frō their beards
whose heades perhaps by the old lawes
and canons should be shorne. If you will
say there is salt in it, I will acknowledge
it, but if you will suspect there is gall in it,
I renounce it. I name not many, and in
those I do name, I swarue not farre from
the rule,

                     Play with me,A fit rule to be kep
                              •
                           , and breedes all misrule whē it is broken, specially by honorable persons. and hurt me not:
                     Iest with me, and shame me not.
                  
               
               For some that may seeme secretly touched,
and be not openly named, if they
will say nothing, I will say nothing. But as
my good friend M. Dauies sayd of his Epigrams,
that they were made like dublets
in Birchen lane, for euery one whom
they will serue: so if any man finde in these
my lines any raiment that sutes him so fit,
as if it were made for him, let him weare
it and spare not, and for my part I would
he could weare it out. But if he will be angrie

at it, then (as the old saying is) I beshrew
his angrie hart: and I would warne
him thus much (as his poore friend) that
the workeman that could with a glaunce
onely and a light view of his person, make
a garment so fit for him, if the same workman
come and take a precise measure of
him, may make him another garment of
the same stuffe (for there neede go but a
payre of sheeres betweene them) that in
what sheere soeuer he dwelleth, he may
be knowne by such a coate as long as he liueth.
Well, to conclude, let both the
writer and the readers endeuour to mend
our selues, and so we shall the easier amend
others, and then I shall thinke my labour
well bestowed in writing, and you shall
thinke yours not altogether lost in reading.
And with this honest exhortation
I would make an end, imitating herein the
wisest Lawyers, who when they haue before
the simplest Iurers, long disputed
their cases to litle purpose, are euer most
earnest and eager at the parting, to beat
into the Iuries head some speciall point or
other, for the behoofe of their client. For

so would I, howsoeuer you do with the
rest of the matter: I would I say, faine
beate still into your memorie this necessarie
admonition (which my new takē name
admonisheth me of) to cleause, amend,
                     
                        ••
                     os.
and wipe away all filthinesse. To the which
purpose, I could me thinke allegorise this
homely subiect that I haue so dilated, and
make almost as good a Sermon, as the Frier
did before the Pope, saying nothing
but Matto San Pietro three times,That is to say, What a foole was S. Peter? and so
came downe from the pulpit againe: and
being afterward examined, what he meant
to make a Sermon of three wordes, but
three times repeated before the triple
crowned Prelat, and so many Cardinals.
He told them, they might finde a good
Sermon in Matto San Pietro; as namely,
if heauen might be gotten notwithstanding
all the pride, pleasures, and pompe
of the world, with 
                     •
                  ase, sensualitie and Epicurisme,
then what a foole was S. Peter
to liue so strict, so poore, so painfull 
                     〈◊〉
                  
With which it is possible his auditorie
was more edified, or at least more terrified,
then they would haue bene at a longer

Sermon. But I will neither end with
Sermon nor prayer, lest some wags liken
me to my L.() players, who
when they haue ended a baudie Comedy,
as though that were a preparatiue to deuotion,
kneele downe solemnly, and pray
all the companie to pray with them for
their good Lord and maister. Yet I wil end
with this good counsell, not vnsuting to
the text I haue thus long talked of.
               To keepe your houses sweet, cleanse priuy vaults,
               To keepe your soules as sweet, mend priuie faults.
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

