
   
      
         
            Fratres sobrii estote. I. Pet. 5. 8. Or, An admonition to the fryars of this Kingdome of Ireland to abandon such hereticall doctrines as they daylie publish to the corruption of our holy faith, the ruine of soules, and their owne damnation which sleepeth not, by Paul Harris priest.
            Harris, Paul, 1573-1635?
         
         
            
               1634
            
         
         Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02681
            STC 12812
            ESTC S116531
            99851747
            99851747
            17038
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02681)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17038)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1309:02)
         
         
            
               
                  Fratres sobrii estote. I. Pet. 5. 8. Or, An admonition to the fryars of this Kingdome of Ireland to abandon such hereticall doctrines as they daylie publish to the corruption of our holy faith, the ruine of soules, and their owne damnation which sleepeth not, by Paul Harris priest.
                  Harris, Paul, 1573-1635?
               
               [2], 30, 35-92 [i.e. 82] 84-99 p.   
               
                  Printed [by the Society of Stationers],
                  [Dublin] :
                  MDCXXXIV [1634]
               
               
                  Place and name of publisher from STC.
                  Pages 31-34 missing in number only; page 82 misnumbered 92; page 83 missing in number only.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.
               Church vestments --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-08
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-09
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-09
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               FRATRES SOBRII ESTOTE. 1. PET. 5.8. OR, An admonition to the Fryars of this Kingdome of Ireland, to abandon ſuch hereticall doctrines as they daylie publiſh to the corruption of our holy faith. the ruine of ſoules, and their owne damnation which ſteepeth not.
            By PAUL HARRIS Prieſt.
            
               
                  GALAT. 4.16.
               
               Am I then become your enemy, telling you the truth?
            
            Printed MDCXXXIV,
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               TO POPE VRBANUS VIII. The Epistle of Paul Harris Prieſt.
            
            
               MOST bleſſed Father, in theſe later and worſer dayes are riſen vp among vs from the Orders of the Begging Fryars, men ſpeaking perverſe things, and drawing many diſciples after them, not onely in the matter of the Eleaven Propoſitions, but profiting vnto the worſe, they labour to tranſfer us from him who hath called us unto the grace of Chriſt, unto an other goſpell, teaching the people as well in publicke aſſem
                  •
               lyes as private houſes, theſe wretched and prophane doctrines:

                  1. Whoſoever ſhall dye in the habit of S. Francis ſhall never be prevented with an unhappy death.
                  2. Whoſoever ſhall take the Scapular of the Carmelites, and dye in the ſame, ſhall never bee damned.
                  3. Whoſoever ſhall faſte the firſt Saturday after they have heard of the death of Luiſsa a Spaniſh Nun of the order of S. Clare, ſhall have no part in the ſecond death.
               
            
            
            The firſt of theſe lewde poſitions is taken out of the Chronicle of the Fryar Minors, (for ſo are the Franciſcans called) tom. 1. and fathered upon S. Francis as one of thoſe Legacyes bequeathed by him unto his Order, and by the Friars of his Order indifferently to be communicated to ſo many as ſhall before their death deſire to be put into their habit, which that it may bee the better knowne and notified unto the world, it is commonly printed under the Image of S. Francis, and placed at our Altars, as both my ſelfe and many others have beheld with our eyes in this citty.
            The ſecond is recorded in a certaine ſheet of paper, not much unlike unto a Ballad, printed by the Friar Carmelits: The title whereof is, An abridgment of the Priviledges of the holy Scapular granted by the moſt gracious Queene of Heaven, MARY, unto the Order of the Carmelites. In which Compendium or Briefe, the inſtitute of the holy Scapular (for ſo is it called) is layd downe in theſe words.
            S. Simon Stoc the ſixt Generall of all the Latines of this Order, did receive not without a manifeſt ſigne of the Divine favour, this moſt ſacred Scapular; for when as he had along time with much earneſtneſſe beſought of Almighty God, that by ſome manifeſt token it might appeare that the Friar Carmelites were in the vndoubted protection of the bleſſed Virgin, behold vpon a certain night he ſaw the Mother of God in great glory, who reached downe vnto him this divine Scapular with theſe words: Dilectiſsime fili, hoc recipe tui ordinis ſcapulare, meae confraternitatis ſignū, tibi, et cunctis Carmelitis privilegium, in quo quis moriens, non aeternum patietur incendium. Ecce ſignum ſalutis, ſalus in periculis, ſaedus pacis, et pacti ſempiterni: Moſt loving ſon, receive this Scapular of thy Order, a token of my confraternity, to thee and to all Carmelites; a priviledge, in which who ſo dyes
ſhall not ſuffer ever laſting fire, Behold the figne of ſ
                  •
               lvation, ſafety in dangers, a league of peace and an everlaſting covenant &amp;c. If more can be aſcribed unto him who dyed for mankind upon the Altar of the Croſſe, I leave it to holy Church to determine. And ſuch was the viſion of S. Simon Stoc exhibited by the Carmelites unto the Eſtate, in the caſtle of Dublin in the moneth of Auguſt 1633. by the hands of Edmund Doyle Prieſt. And if any doubt heerof, they ſhall find the very originall with me when ever they ſhall be pleaſed to demaund the ſame. And ſuch is the authentication of the Scapular of the Carmelites evangelized every-where by the Friars of that Order, and repreſented unto the eye at many of their altars by tables of picture. Now if any deſire to know what thing this Scapular is, and have not ſeene the ſame, behold this deſcription. The Scapular is onely two ſquare pieces of cloath of the bigneſſe of two trenchers, The ſorme of a Scapular. the one before pendant upon the breſt, the other behind upon the ſhoulders, from whence it hath the name of Scapular.
            The third Propoſition as touching the Saturdayes faſte of Donna Luiſsa the Nunn of S. Clare, is much inſiſted upon and moſt carefully taught by the Cordeliers or Franciſcan Friars, and particularly by Friar Thomas Babe, who publiſhed the ſame the 29. of Aprill, being the feaſt of S. Peter Martyr, and S. Catherin of Siena, in the yeare of our Lord 1631. in the Cook-ſtreet of Dublin in a publicke audience, whoſe exhortation to the people was to this purpoſe. That forſomuch as a certaine holy. Virgin called Luiſſa of the order of S.Clare had a revelation, that whoſoever ſhould faſt upon the next Saturday after they heard of her death, ſhould never dye in mortall ſin, or of any evill death. The aforeſaid Friar Thomas Babe perſwaded the people then preſent, to undertake ſo holy a pennance, mooved wherewithall
very many (and I ſay ſignanter very many) as they did be loeve his doctrin, ſo did they moſt carefully obſerve the ſame faſte, among whom as chiefe of all the reſt, Thomas Flemming aliàs Barnwell Archbiſhop of Dublin for exaniple unto his flock, and as a prime man of the ſame order obſerved moſt devoutly the ſame, as himſelfe hath not bin aſhamed diverſe times to acknowledge: Neither was that doctrine onely then, but ſundry other times alſo taught by that falſe Apoſtle Friar Babe and his fellowes in diverſe other places of this City and Dioceſſe.
            Moſt holy Father, I meddle not with the matter of Indolgences, neither doe I intend, or ever did, to diſcourſe of that argument. I onely complaine of theſe wicked doctrines; and I doe adjure your ſanctity, in the Name of the crucified, that you confirme your flock in theſe parts, that they be not led away with theſe new doctrines from that faith in which our holy Mother the Church hath bred us from her breſt. I ſay that we be no longer miſ-led by theſe Mendicants who ſeeke to perſwade us theſe carnall fancyes, more ſerviceable I confeſſe unto the belly, then any wayes behoofeful unto the ſoule, but rather as the Apoſtle willeth us, that wee abide in thoſe things which wee have learned, and have beene committed unto us, in no ſort admitting theſe new Apoſtles as ſent from heaven, but rather avoyding them as ſeducers come from hell. For we fooles doe verily beleeve, That he who was borne of the bleſſed and immaculat Virgin God and Man, Ieſus and Emmanuel, who ſuffered ſo many and ſo grievous torments upon the Croſſe under Pontius Pilate, who aroſe glorious from the death, and aſcended into Heaven, that he and no other redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, that he and no other hath cleanſed us from our iniquityes, and wrought our reconciliation for us. And that neither Paul, nor Apollo, nor
the habit of S.Francis, nor the Scapular of the Carmelites, nor Dame Luiſſa the Nun of S.Clare, order (be ſhee never ſo holy a woman) hath waſhed us with her bloud, or was crucifyed for us.
            Moſt holy Father, you have given unto us for the Paſtor of our ſoules, a Friar of the Order of S.Francis, by name Thomas Flemming alias Barnwell, conſecrated Archbiſhop of Dublin; to him our Dioceſan were preſented our complains and grievances in the behalfe of the Clergy of Dublin, againſt the moſt horrid and blaſphemous tenents before-mentioned. I ſay two R. Prieſts in the name of the reſt perſonally appearing before our Archbiſhop, did preſent him not onely with the names of the delinquents, but a catalogue alſo of their witneſſes and proofes which paſſed on the 7. of March in the yeare 1631. in this Citty of Dublin. But what anſwer received the two Prieſts from their Ordinary? Truely none at all, neither to this day have they profited in that ſuit. For verily it is to be feared that this diſeaſe (whoſe nature is to fret like a canker) hath invaded and infected the head no leſſe then the reſt of the body. And we are the rather enduced to beleeve the ſame, for that we ſee theſe errors and corrupt doctrines day lie more and more to prevaile, &amp; to enlarge themſelves eſpecially among the ignorant and common people, alas too eaſie and flexible to be led aſtray: for there are a number of Regulars, eſpecially of the Franciſcans and Carmelites, falſe Apoſtles, who not onely in pulpits preach theſe ertors, but as the Apoſtle ſayth, going from houſe to houſe, ſubvert whole familyes, teaching what they ought not for filthy lucres ſake. For no ſmall profit doubtleſſe doth ariſe unto theſe Poets and Inventours of fable, inſomuch as they may truely ſay with Demetrius the ſilver-ſmyth, Act. 19. De hoc artificio nobis eſt acquiſitio: Sirs you know that our gaine
is of this occupation. For (ſay mee) who in the world is there that beleeves any thing to remaine after death and aſhes, who will not be glad to avoy de the paines of hell? who deſires not to enjoy a bleſſed eternity in Heaven? And I call Heaven and Earth to witneſſe, what thing is there more eaſiethen before death to creepe into a Friars habit? or what more tollerable then to faſt one day, which is no more then having one competent repaſt at noone, to for beare a ſupper at night? Or what is there leſſe troubleſome then to carry two ſquare pannicles or clouts, the one upon his back, the other at his boſome, under his garments (I wis) a carriage not ſo burdenſome, nor comparably ſo painfull, as was that heavy became of the Croſſe which ſweet In svs carryed upon his backe to mount Calvary, and on which the ſalvation of the world did hang. Doubtleſſe if future glory in the world to come, &amp; the aſſurance thereof in this life might with ſo ſmall a labour be purchaſed, who is ſo much an Euclio or ſtreit handed? Who ſo much a Lucian, or an Atheiſt, as would not willingly admit theſe bleſſed Friars bringing ſuch abundance of ſpirituall richeſſe with them, into his treaſury, into his garnell amongſt his heards and flocks, yea into his whole ſubſtance and meanes, not a ſad or an unwilling, but a moſt joyfull giver? Or what woman carefull of her ſoules health, will make ſpare of whatſoever is in her cuſtody or under her hands? her bracelets, her rings, chaynes, Iewels, her cheſts of linnen, her arkes of meale and malt in exchange of ſuch immortall benefits, and to have ſo propitious and preſent gods, albeit our Saviour hath ſaid: Quid commutationis homo dabit pro anima ſua? Mar. 8. What exchange ſhall a man give for his ſould? The ſame truth hath alſo ſaid Math. 7. Angusta eſt porta &amp; via arcta quae ducit ad vitam aternam &amp;c. Narrow is the gate and ſtreit is the way that leadeth unto
life, and few there be that finde it. And our Saviour foreſeeing that there would come in the laſt times of the world ſuch as would endeavour to enlarge that way, and to make that gate more wide, he preſently addeth. Attendite a falſis prophetes, &amp;c. Take you heed of falſe prophets that come to you in the cloathing of ſleep, but inwardly are ravening wolfes, by their frui
                  •
               s you ſhall know them. And what are the fruits ſweet Ieſus) of theſe falſo prophets among us at this day, but to make the gates of Heaven to gape as wide as the gates of hell it ſelfe. For albeit the Apoſtle hath excluded from celeſtiall glory not a few, ſaying, Hoc enim ſcitote intelligentes &amp;c. For underſtanding know this, that no fornicator, nor uncleane or covetousiperſon, which is the fervice of Idols, hath inheritance in the Kingdome of Chriſt and of God: yet will our Friars admin them all, if they once faſte Dame Luiſſaes ſaturdayes faſte. And albeit Chriſt our Lord excluded the man who had not a wedding garment from his Kingdome, yet will the Franciſcan Friar let in any who is cloathed with his habit, and ſo the Carmelite ſuch as are found with his Scapular about their ſhoulders. I ſay, all theſe ſo qualifved ſhall be accepted of, and be admitted as well unto the Dinner of the great King as unto the Supper of the Lambe. Who then can marvell (theſe doctrines ſuppoſed as orthodox, yea as oracles) that we day lie ſee ſo many to be buryed in Friars weeds, ſo many men &amp; women day lie to take the Scapular, witneſſe the regiſter of the Friars Franciſcan and Carmelices, in which their names are carefully recorded, as perpetuall Benefactors unto their Orders. Nay, who is there eſpecially among the Laity (O triſte verbum!) who dare ſo nurch truſt to the ſufferings of our Saviour, and to the merites of his death &amp; paſſion, as they dare be found in the houre of death without that thrice holy Scapular, that ſigne of ſalvarion,
that ſafety in dangers, that league of peace, &amp; of aneverlaſting covenant, in which who ſo dyeth, ſhall never ſuffer eternall fire. All which attributions are incorporated unto the ſaid Scapular by the bleſſed Virgin, if Simon Stoc his revelation be authenticke; yea many among us nor truſting to the habit alone, or unto the Scapular alone, or to the Nunnes faſte alone, will before their death beee furniſhed with them all three together, having wiſely underſtood that of Salomon, Proverh. 4. Funiculus triplex difficile rumpitur: A triple cord is not eaſily broken. In which their proceeding me ſeemeth that yet they ſhew ſome weakenes of faith; for if they did conſtantly beleeve every one of theſe three promiſed ſalvations to be aſſured by divine revelation, as their teachers be are them in hand, ſurely either any of them is ſufficient, or all of them together inſufficient.
            Neither doth it boot the Friars to cloake theſe their errors by ſaying, That theſe doctrines rightly underſtood, do not import every ſinner by keeping ſuch a faſt
                  •
               , by taking ſuch an Habit, or Scapular to be favied, but ſuch onely as be contrite with all for their fins, and are waſhed in the blood of the Redeemer. For neither doe our Friars, in their Semons and exhortations, mention any ſuch condition, &amp;c if they did, yet notwithſtanding the whoſe doctrine of the Sabbaoth faſte, the Habit &amp; the Scapular, (no leſſeblazed by the Friars, then ſuperſtitouſly beleeved of the people) would utterly vaniſh into ſmoake. For why? a perſon ſo diſpoſed and qualifyed, that is penitent for his fimes, and relying upon the redemption of In sas CHRIST is apt for the Kingdome of God, and to receive an inheritance among the Saints and Elect, ſay he be naked of Habit &amp; ſcapular, and not at all acquainted with Donna Luiſſa her ſaturdayes faſt: yea a man ending his dayes in the ſervice of God, and as the Divines ſay in the eſtate of grace can not
miſſe of his ſalvation, had he but a couple of Hawkes-bells about his neck, or if he dyed in his old bootes as well as in ſcapular or habit. If then the Friar thus expounds himſelf. He that dyeth in the habit or ſcapular, ſhall undoubredly be ſaved, alwayes provided that he bein the love and favor of God, verily he might as wel have ſpared ſo much breath to have cooled his broth, I ſay, as to ſpend it upon ſuch a gloſſe as corrupteth and quite over-throweth the text. No no, Mors in olla, There is poyſon in the pot. For theſe preachers deſire no thing leſſe then to be ſo underſtood in their ſermons when they make their Panegyricks of the habit and ſcapular unto the people, for by that meanes they might be in danger not onely to looſe their offerings at the Altar, but that great authority and place which they have in the hearts and affection of the Laity. No rather with all poſſible endeavour they labour to bee beleeved, that by the vertue of theſe raggs, either as cauſes inſtrumentall or infallible ſignes, ſalvation is to be acquired. And heuce it is that the Carmelite Friars dedicate yeerely a day of great feſtivity, namely the 16. of Iuly. unto the honour and reception of the Scapular, as the Franciſcans alſo doe to that parcell of their habit which is the Cord or Girdle. Ar which feſtival times it is lamentable to behold how much the Divine Majeſtie by theſe beggars &amp; their devotoes is prophaned in his creatures:yea truly the world might leſſe admire in theſe diſmall dayes the Sun to be eclipſed, &amp; the rocks to rent, then at the time of our Saviours paſſion, beholding the benefit thereof ſo miſerably defaced by theſe falſe Teachers who in theſe dayes cannot be contented to rob the people of their purſes, but of their ſoules alſo.
            And to the end, they and all thoſe that read theſe my writings may underſtand, that I will not inveigh without juſt cauſe or reprove in words what I am not able by good
Argument to confound: I ſeriouſly demaund of our Friar, what ground they have either from the divine Oracles, Eccleſiaſticall tradition, or monuments of the Fathers, to promiſe this ſecurity and certitude of Salvation, or to determine of the Sons of Adam in particular and by polle that their names are written in the booke of life. I ſay, while yet we are viatotes, et non in ſtatu, Pilgrimes from our Lord, and not arrived at our country. I heare Salomon one of the Secretaries of the Holy Ghoſt ſaying, Prov. 20. Quis poteſt dicere mundum eſt cor meum? Who can ſay my heart is cleane? I heare Iob ſaying, Etiamſi ſimplex fuero, &amp;c. Job. 9. Albeit I be innocent, yet ſhall my ſoule bee ignorant thereof. I heare the Apoſtle ſaying, Philip. 2. Cum meta &amp; tremore veſtram ſalutem operamini. Worke your Salvation with feare and trembling. I heare S. Auguſt. upon the 40. Pſal. ſaying, Scia quod justitia Dei mei maneat, verum an juſtitia mea maneat an non, ignoro, terret me enim Apoſtolus inquiens. Qui exiſtimat ſe stare, videat ne cadat. I know that the juſtice of my God remaines, but whether my juſtice doe remaine or not, I am ignorant. For the Apoſtle doth terrify me ſaying, he who thinkes he ſtands, let him looke to it he fall not. So S. Hierome in his 3. booke upon the Prophet Ieremy. Man ſeeth in the face, God in the heart, and that which unto us doth ſome times ſeeme cleane, in Gods eyes is found filthy. Adde hereunto the teſtimony of S. Ambroſe in his 5. Sermon upon the 118. Pſal. S. Chryſoſt Homil. 87. upon Iohn. S. Gregory lib. 6. epiſt: 22. S. Bede in his Comment. upon the 20. cap. of the Prov. But I may not ommit to ſet downe at large what S. Bernard that pillar of Gods Church in theſe later Centuryes hath left written of this argument, as in many other places, ſo eſpecially in his 1. Sermon de Septuageſima in theſe words; Who can ſay I am one of the Elect? I am one of thoſe
that are predeſtinated unto life: I am one of the children of God? Who, I ſay, can ſay this? When as the Scripture cryeth out againſt him. Man knoweth not whether he be worthy of love or hatred. Certainely therefore wee cannot have, but yet we are comforred with the truſt of hope, that we may not by anxiety of this dubitation be tormented above meaſure. So he. Laſtly to this cloud of teſtimonies out of the ancient fathers, I will adde the uniforme conſent of the moderne Fathers of the Councell of Trent, condemning &amp; anathematizing this certitude of Salvation Can. 15. in theſe words. Si quis dixerit hominem renatum &amp; juſtificatum teneri ex ſide ad credendum ſe certo eſſe in numero praedeſlinatorum Anathem aſit. If any ſhall ſay a man regenerate and juſtifyed to be bound by faith to beleeve himſelf undoubtedly to be in the number of the predeſtinate, let him be accurſed: and in the Can. following, Si quis magnum illud uſque in finem perſeverantiae donum ſe certo habiturum, abſoluta &amp; infallibili certitudine dixerit niſi hoc exſpeciali revelatione didicerit) anathema ſit. If any ſhall ſay, that by abſolute and infallible aſſurance he hath that great gift of perſeverance unto the end, unleſſe he hath learned the ſame by ſpeciall revelation, accurſed be he. So the Councell.
            And ſure no marvaile. Since this preſumption of Salvation is the very food and fewell of all wickedneſſe and impiety, the provocation and incitement to all ſhameleſſe luſts and pleaſures, with which the ſoule once poſſeſſed what further care is to be taken in matters of conſcience: For ſay, That now I have either gotten the habit of the Franciſcans upon my backe, or the Scapular of the Carmelites hanging about my necke, (a moſt preſent antidote againſt hell and damnation) what have I henceforth to doe with the commandements of God and Holy C
                  ••
               rch? Why ſhould I feare for the time to come to looſe the
reynes unto my unbridled paſſion, or to ſet ſayle which way the ſtreame of my miſplaced deſires doe carry mee headlong? I ſay what cauſe have I further to wage warre with vice, or longer to reſiſt the ſweete allurements of Evill. Yea what ſhould hinder me to ſay with Salomon (having run the ſame courſes with him) Eccleſ. 2. All things which my eyes have deſired, I denyed them not: neither did I forbid my heart to enjoy all manner of pleaſures.
            
            Theſe be the thoughts, theſe the labours of the minde, theſe the diſcourſes of the underſtanding which doe often burſt out into the lipps and tongues of men entangled in theſe intricacyes of error. And what Moſes have wee among us to put himſelfe as a wall and a bulwarke for the houſe of Iſrael? Who ſhall paciſie theſe congregations of Abiram? Who ſhall conſume and burne up this new fire of the ſonnes of Aaron with a better flame? Where is Elias, or where is Micheas to reprove theſe falſe Prophets, of pleaſing but perilous lyes. Where is that Apoſtle of Chriſt? Who ſhould confound theſe falſe Apoſtles with an Apoſtolicall zeale? Scarſe is there one Peter to be found among us to oppoſe himſelfe to theſe Simons. Scarſe one Paul to deliver up theſe Hymeneus and Alexanders unto Satan, that they may learne not to blaſpheme. For tell mee, who is there among the Clergy, at leaſt in this our Northerne Iland, divided from the reſt of the world, that is either willing or able to goe againſt theſe Regulars, moving ſo irregularly out of their owne proper ſpheares? Nay rather, who is there among us not carryed head-long by theſe their raptand violent motions, into the aforeſaid errors? If not in expreſſe termes of approbation, at leaſt by a ſhut up cye, and a ſealed lip, of a ſilent connivance? One circumvented by fraud, another detained by feare of diſpleaſure, the third won by benefites, the moſt or all of us
drawne to a farre more penicious diſſimulation then was that of Barnabas condemned by the Apoſtle. For albeit the Prieſts of the Clergy in theſe parts are leſſe refractary unto Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, yea truely farre more obedient unto the lawes and beheſts of holy Church then the Regulars, yet not much more learned I confeſſe, and in number farre inferiour unto them, as may be ſeene in this principall Citty of Ireland, in which there be onely ſix paſtors, but of Regulars not much ſewer then a hundred, albeit by reaſon of their ebbing and flowing, their frequent excurſions cauſed by their manifold negotiations in every corner of the Kingdome, their out-gates beyond the ſeas, and back againe returnes, it is as hard to deſine what number they be of, as to count how many froggs there were in the ſecond plague of Egypt, yea to ſuch a potency they are growne, and that in a ſhort ſpace in this Kingdome of Ireland, that what cauſe ſoever they take in hand, be it juſt or injuſt, Eccleſiaſticall or Temporall, they will, nay they muſt be Conquerours; ſo united among themſelves, ſo backt with powerfull friendſhips, ſo animated with forraine correſpondencyes, not to ſpeake of ordinary conſanguinityes and affinityes, foſter-ſhips, and goſſip-fhips, ſo intayled not onely to the Commons, but unto the greateſt Familyes, by taking in of Youths into their Convents, May des into their Cloyſters, furniſhing Merchants with cuſtome, purchaſers with moneyes upon morgages &amp; rent charges, abſolurely ruling in all matters of Contracts and matrimoniall cauſes, managing the aſſay res of rich Widdowes, but ſeldom (I confeſſe) helping them to husbands. 
                  For ſo they might be debarred frō
                   Eſtates, Legacyes, and Executorſhips At the pillow of every rich man, eſpecially when he is about to make his Will, ſerving in that buſineſſe both for ghoſtly Fathers, Councell, and Cleark, by reaſon of which imployments, &amp; what elſe may either be honourable or
profitable unto them, they are aſcended unto that height of authority, that if they ſhould tell us, the crowes were white, and the ſwans black. (though we could not beleeve them) yet ſhould wee not dare to gainſay them, or to conteſt with them.
            For as it is the nature of plenty to beget proſperity, and this, pride, ſo our Regulars at this day are arrived at ſuch an unmeaſurable greatneſſe, through plenty and popular eſtimation, as they are not onely a terrour unto the inferiour Paſtors of Gods Church, but even unto Biſhops and Cardinals. Nor will I except thee O Pope Vrbanus! who not once (as we are credibly informed from the city) haſt complayned of their inſupportable pride and inſolencies, ſaying to ſuch as complayned of their injuryes: I marveil not that they wrong you, for they wrong my ſelfe. And as theſe Regulars are awfull unto the Clergy, ſo no leſſe fearfull are they unto the Laity, who therefore yeeld them ſuch attribution, as either they hope their friendſhip to bee an advantage unto them in the proſequution of their ends, or they providently fore-ſee how much the malice of a powerfull enemy may bee prejudiciall unto them in the ſame kinde. So as be who thou wilt, friend or foe, the Friar will benefit himſelfe by thee. If thou be his friend and well-willer; he gaynes by 
                  •
               hy. love. If his adverſary, then alſo for feare of diſpleaſure and offence, like unto thoſe Lawyers whom Caſsiodorus upon the 73. Pſal. ſayth, Apud cauſidicos etiam ipſum ſilentium venale eſt, ac lingua corum damnifica niſi funibus argenteis ligetur. With Layers their very ſilence is vendible, &amp;their ongues are harmefull unleſſe they be tyed with ſilver chaynes. But truely as in the naturall body, when any one part or member groweth into an exorbitant bigneſfe beyond due ſymmetry and proportion, the reſt of the members become ſick and feeble, &amp;
the whole body 
                  〈…〉
                in the Ec
                  •
               l
                  •
               ſihft
                  •
               
               call or Politicke. Sody may inſtand with the ſafety thereof to permit ſo great a party, and ſo intrinſecall a faction as are our Regulars in Ireland, to ſwell to ſuch a bulke, as exceeding the bonds of due proportion, they draw unto ther ſelves the humors of the feſt of the body to the deſtruction of the whole.
            Neither in writing theſe things moſt holy Father, is my meaning other, then was the ſoop
                  •
                of that thrice renowned Archbiſhop of Armagh, &amp; Primate of all Ireland, commō
               ly called by Writers, Armachanus; by the Inhabitants of this Countrey, S. Richard of Dundalke, in his oration at Avinion, made before Pope Innocentius Sci his Card
                  •
               nalls in theſe words: Pater ſanctiſsime &amp;c. Moſt holy Father, in the beginning of my Speech I doe proteſt that I doe not intend to averre, or raſhly affirme any thing which may bee contrary unto the Chriſtian Faith, or Catholieke doctrine; &amp; that my meaning is not to preſſe or perſwade the deſtruction of the Mendicant Orders approved by holy Church &amp; confirmed by the See Apoſtolicke, but rather to perſwade, that they may be reduced &amp; brought 
                  •
               acke againe unto the purity of then firſt inſtitution; alwayes minded to ſubmit my ſelfe unto the cenſure of your Holines. So Armachanus.
            
            And ſo Imindefull of my duty &amp; obforvance unto the thay-re of sl
                  ••••
               , am bold to ſpeake 
                  •
               nnco my: Lord of ſuch affay es us may conc
                  ••••
                the w
                  •
               ll
                  ••
               áre) of ſoules, &amp; the good of this Church of Ireland, in which I now have almoſt lived for the ſpace of theſe 
                  •••
               my yeares! And the rather I hold my ſelfe bound ſo to 
                  〈◊〉
               , fo
                  •••
               at 
                  ••
               mnot igno
                  •
               an
                  •
               , but know right we blow your How living among ſo many protectors of R
                  〈7 letters〉
               ders, ſo muny Generals, ſo many Patrons, pro
                  〈7 letters〉
                &amp;c agents for them; ſcarce
ſhall you heare a word of ſincere truth, without many gloſſes &amp; Commentaryes of moſt corrupt additions; yea &amp; for one verity, a maſſe of forged &amp; deviſed fables, eſpecially from theſe remote Regions, &amp; as you call them in Rome Tramontane Provinces. Yea ſuch is the miſery &amp; calamity of Princes &amp; great Perſonages, as well Eccleſiaſticall, as Politick, that ſeldome by the care doe they conceive that birth which with all their hearts they defire not to be vitall &amp; long-lived, that is, ſeldome hearing what they would not heare. Such multitudes there are of paraſites &amp; flatterers, who ſuggeſt unto their ſences nothing but what is rare, glorious, &amp; above meaſure gratefull, who for to pleaſe, they holde it but little inferiour to immortality.
            Nevertheleſſe ſuch hath beene my breeding and education from mine infancy, which together with my yeares hath growne up with mee, and is now confirmed in more then a declining age, that I rather deſire to live poore with the Philoſopher, and feed on coleworts in this my tubb, then to act the flatterer with Ariſtippus, and ſurfet on pleaſures in the Court of Alexander. And forſomuch as now for many yeares we have had your Ho. amoſt vigilant paſtor, &amp; a lover of truth. I held it not ſo much to concerne my ſelfe, as the whole Church of Ireland, to intimate theſe no ſmall or triviall matters unto you. For as it is our parts to open, if not the imperfections &amp; ſmaller exceſſes of our brethren, (which, charity would rather have concealed, then revealed) yet certes ſo ſoule, ſo into be rable, ſo manifeſt adulterations of our holy faith, we can not, we ought not, woe dare not ſmother, which happily if wee ſhould, the very ſtones would cry &amp; rore them out in your eares. So doubtleſſe to you holy Father it belongs to apply holeſome remedyes to theſe diſeaſes, to powre wine
and oyle into theſe wounds, to aſſwage the tempeſt of theſe raging Seas, to chaſtice with your paſtorall ſtaffe theſe butting rammes, which lead the following flocke aſtray unto hurtfull and uncouth paſtures, orif they contemne to heare your voyce, to cut them off from the reſt of the fold, by the Eccleſiaſticall Sword of your cenſures, that the good bee not infected by the fellowſhip of the bad, the ſound by the diſeaſed.
            Theſe things are expected by the Church of Ireland from ſo great a Paſtor, by him to be governed, to be cheriſhed, to be defended, to be enlarged. And ſo the Prince of Paſtors to his Vicar and to his flock on earth be ever propitious, whoſe power over him and his writings is willingly acknowledged by
            
               PAVL HARRIS.
            
            
         
         
            
            
            
               A FAMILIAR DISPVTATION WITH THE FRYARS, PROPOVNDED BY THE AVTHOR
            
            
               CAP. I.
               
                  AND thus gentle Friars, having (as you ſee) made my moane to Pope Vrbanus 8 of your falſe and ſeditious doctrines, the pillars of your pride and ambition, and no ſmall revenew unto your Garnells, Cellars, and Kinchins. Give mee leave to ventilat and diſpute the aforeſaid cafe of the Habis, Scaputar, and Faſt, a little more familiarly with your ſelves as my equalls. The end and butt I ſhoot at (if God ſo bleſſe my endeavors) is to undeceive ſuch poore ſoules among us, as hitherto have beene inveigled and beſotted with theſe your dreames and pleaſant fantaſies: ſince it is my part no leſſe to conſute orror, then to teach true doctrine, and to diſcover: ſuch falſe: apoſtles, as ſeeke to tranſtorme themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt. And albeit ſome happily will hold it a labour needl
                     •
                  ſſe, to oppoſe theſe ſenceleſſe tenents, which like unto ill plaſtred walls, threatning their owner nine, dan not long ſubſiſt: yet others, (and peradventure with more reaſon) will alſo judge my endeavours bootleſſe, and to no purpoſe, for that in moſt mens opinions, theſe: doctrines are ſo faſtned, or rather (as I may ſay) ſo rivetted, and
wedged into the heads and hearts of the people, as it may rather become the labour of the Apoſtie, then any other Paul to diſſolve, and to remove the ſame, according to that of divine Petrarch, alte radicates errores nonfacile eſt extirpare. De vi
                        •
                     ſol. lib. 1. Errors deeply rooted, are not eaſily pull'd up. Forſomuch then as theſe ſupernaturall prerogatives aſcribed unto the Hubit, Seapular, and Donna Luiſſa her faſt, are all of them built upon viſions and revelations, and we are taught by the holy Ghoſt from the mouth of the Apoſtle, 2. Cor. 11. That Satan can tranſfigure himſelfe into an Angell of light, and therefore are admoniſhed by the ſame Apoſtle not to be circumvented by him, whoſe operation conſisteth in all power and lying ſignes and wonders, and in all ſedmong of Iniquity. I demaund then of you O Regulars, and eſpecially of you Gray Friars and Carmelites, how you come to know, that forſomuch as S. Fraugis, and S. Simon Stec, might as well as many other Saints have beene deluded, and abuſed by Satan in this kind: that not withſtanding theſe revelations of theirs, were heavenly and divine, and for ſuch, to be taken and beleeved, and not rather illuſions of that enemie of mankind, Cui mille ſunt nomina, &amp; wille nocendi artes, Who hath a thouſand names and meanes of deceiving. For ſay, that S. Francis, and S. Simon Stec be canonized Saints, yet not all that is written by them, or of them is canonized truths. And therefore as wicked men and women in the Scriptures have beene honoured with divine viſions, and revelations, as Balaam, Pharaoh, Saul, Nebuch aduczar, Pelats wife, and the Sybills, ſo have many of Gods ſervants beene deceived by ſtrong illuſions to beleeve lyes. Examples whereof we have ſtore as well in the Dialogues of S. Gregory written above a thouſand yeares agoe, as in that more ancient legend of the holy men and Eremites of Paleſtina, Egypt, and The
                     
                        •
                     ais, written by Palladius within the firſt foure hundred yeares after Chriſt, to omit infinite others in hiſtoryes of later times. Nay S. Francis himſelfe ſeemes not to have beene priviledged in this kind, I ſay, from being abuſed with falſe revelations. For as wee reade in the Chronicle of the Friar Minors: He having under him a Vicar generall whoſe name was Helias. It was revealed unto him by Almighty God, that the aforeſaid Friar ſhould both dye out of the Order, and be damned, in reſpect whereof the holy Faaher S.

                  Francis did ever after ſo diſ affect the aforeſaid Fryar, that he could not endure to behold him. Yet not many linesafter in the very ſame sap. it is reported how the ſame S. Francis had a revelation from heaven, that the aforeſaid Friar Helias ſhould doe pennance for his ſinnes, and not be damned at all. This ſhall you reade in the Chronicle of the Friar Minors, tom. 1. cap. 118. And ſuch as will take paines to peruſe S. Brigids revelations, &amp; conſerre them with our legends of Saints lives, ſhall finde innumerable examples of like kind. One Saint having a revelation directly contrary to what hath beene revealed unto another. Notwithſtanding that there is but one God, one truth. And we may be enduced or rather enforced to beleeve, that theſe revelations, viſions, and apparitions of S. Francis, and Simon Stoc (if any ſuch were) were meere ſatanicall illuſions, &amp; no divine revelations, for that they promiſe that certitude and aſſurance of ſalvation in this life, which is repugnant to ſacred Writt, the uniforme conſent of the Primitive Fathers, the uniforme conſent of Generall Councells, and the beliefe both of our holy Mother the Church, and all her obedient children even unto theſe times, as I have aboundantly proved in my Epiſtle to Pope Vrbanns, and not neceſſary heere to be repeated againe. And therefore I will conclude this firſt point with that of the Apoſtle, Golat. 1. That if an Angell from heaven ſhall come and preach unto us contrary to what we have received, Anathema ſir.
               
               But yet to give ſcope to a more full and ample diſcourſe of this Argument, let us admit for the preſent that S. Francis, and Simon Stoc had received by divine revelation: That whoſoever ſhall dye in the habit of the one, and the ſcapular of the other, ſhould undoubtedly be ſaved, (for it may not bee denyed but ſuch certitude may be had by divine revelation) Examples we have of the Scriptures of the two glorious Apoſtles, S. Peter &amp; S. Paul, of S. Mary Magdalen, &amp; ſome others, for the arme of our Lord is not ſhortned, nor his power abridged. Yet (ſay I) conformable to the doctrine of holy Church (as afterward ſhall bee prooved) that this can be no aſſurance, or ſecurity unto others, who are not partakers of the ſaid viſions, and revelations to beleeve that doctrine; becauſe what is of divine authority unto one, is but of humane and ſallible authority unto another. For ſay that Peter knoweth a thing
to come by certaine &amp; divine revelation, yet the ſame ſhall be to Patrick but onely a humane relation, received from the lips of Peter a mortall man, ſubject to error and miſtaking, to deceive, and to be deceived, and being but in via, &amp; non in termine, peccable in thought, word and deed: and therefore we ſee the Church (whoſe wiſdome is from the holy Ghoſt) never to canonize any perſon, though reputed never ſo holy, while they are in the fleſh, and till ſuch time as their ſanctity be atteſted by ſignes, and wonders from heaven. As then S. Francis before his converſion was of life &amp; converſation like unto others of his rank, &amp; quality, &amp; not much ſcrupulous of the offence of God, till he came unto the age of twenty five, as may appeare both by the firſt words of his Teſtament. Quia cùm eſſem in peccatis &amp;c. as alſo by his life written by Bonaveniure. So albeit I confeſſe the ad and better part of his life, after his converſion, &amp; dedicating himſelfe unto the ſervice of God, was as a threed more evenly ipun, then the former, yet not altogether without ſome knotes, as may be knowne by his own confeſſion, when on a time ſo journing in the pallace of the Cardinall De Sta Cruce and in the night-time being beaten of the Devills, he repayred in the morning to the preſence of the aforeſaid Cardinall, to whom he related what he had endured, and then added, Men that know me not, repute me as a Saint, but behold how the devills who know me well, doe handle and chastice me for my ſinnes. So he. Chron, fras, minor, toni, I, cap. 13. Out of all which I doe inferre, that a viſion, or revclation is not therefore authenticall, or to be believed, becauſe ſuch a perſon, who after 
                     •
                  is death was canonized for a Saint, did in his life-time avouch the ſame, either by word, or writing, becauſe it is neceſſary for my p
                     •
                  ucent aſſent unto ſuch viſions or revelations, that the ſame be canonized for ſupernaturall &amp; infallible truths, which cannot be but by authority of holy Church, which hath canonized for certaine and infallible verities, no other mens workes, ſayings, or writings, then thoſe of the Prophets and Apoſtles, as that Angelical Doctor S. Thomas hath in theſe words, Innititur fide: nostra rev Lationi Apoſtolis &amp; prophetis factae qui canoric
                        •
                     s linos ſcripſerunt, non autem revelationi ſi qua fuit aliis doctoribus facta, 12 
                  q. 1.8. 2d. 2dum. Our faith is grounded upon revelation made unto the Apoſtles, and Prophets, who wrote the canonicall
bookes, not to revelation (if any ſuch was made) to other Doctors. For which doctrine he cites alſo S. Aug. in his Epiſtle unto S. Hierom Epiſt. 14. in theſe words: Solis enim ſcripturarum libris qui canonici appellaneny, didici hune honorem deferre, 
                        •
                     t unllum autherum corum in ſcribendo erraſſe aliquid firmiſſime credam. Alios autem it a lego ut quantalibet fanctitato, doctrinaque prepolleant. non ideo verum putem, quod ipſi it a ſenſerunt vel ſcripſerunt. Onely to the books of Scripture, which are called canonicall, I have learned to give that honour, that I moſt firmely believe, that none of the Authors thereof have erred in writing, but other writers I ſo read (that with how great ſanctity, or learning ſo ever they doe excell,) I doe not therefore believe a thing to be true, becauſe they have ſo judged, or ſo written. So S. Aug.
               
               Now future glory in Heaven being a ſupernaturall object, cannot by humane knowledge or morall certitude be aſſured unto us, but either not all, or by divine faith, which though not cleare and evident, yet excelleth in certitude and infallibility all ſcientificall knowledge whatſoever. And this I ſay to anſwere thoſe who happily in defence of their errors, in the aforeſaid revelations, will ſay, that albeit indeed they be not to be believed by a divine and a ſupernaturall faith, yet may they be certaine unto us, exáio tapite, that is, from ſome other topicall argument, which in truth is as much, as if they ſaid nothing, preaching an infallibility of the aforeſaid viſions, and revelations, then brought unto cheir juſtification, they anſwere us with nothing but hiſtoricall legends (and I pray God not rather fabulous) and meere humane poſſibilityes. When the poore ſoule in the meane time truſting unto habits and ſcapulats, as Oracles of truth, &amp; rockes of a ſure foundation, at the evening and percloſe of life, findes it ſelfe irreparably deceived, &amp; in puncto deſcondit in infernum: in a moment for misbeliefe ſiukes downe to hell, whence neither the habit of S. Francis, nor the ſcapular of the Carmelites, nor the ſaturday faſte of Dame Luiſſa ſhall be able to fetch it our. And becauſe that Dives can not obtayne of Abraham that one ſhould come from the dead &amp; ſignifie unto his brethren what entertainment theſe habit &amp; ſcapular wearers, ſinde in the next world; Our Friars doe the leſſe regard what Moſes &amp; the Prophets, what the Apoſtles, Fathers, and Generall Councells
teach, for not being convicted of their 
                     ••
                  rours by experimentall knowledge of the dead, they leſſe reck on of any other proofe, demonſtration, or argument, which not withſtanding wee will not ſpare further to urge againſt them, or whatſoever elſe may conferr to the demolition of this ſo deſp
                     •
                  rat an error, poſſeſſing the laſt act of mans life, and making the ſame moſt tragicall. For as it is truly ſaid, Quod in bello non bis peceatur, A man ſhall never offend the ſecond time in warre, and why? becauſe by c
                     ••
                  ath the ſecond error is prevented. So with much more reaſon, yea with ruth and compaſſion may it be ſaid of a Chriſtian dying in mi
                     •
                   beliefe of a matter of ſuch conſequence, as concernes his eternall woe or welfare, non bis peceatur. He cannot twiſe offend. An error concluded in death 1
                     •
                   ſingular, is ſolitary, and unaccompanyed, no reparation by repentance to bee hoped for, the doore of life being alſo the doore of mercy, which once ſhut is never more to be opened.
               Marvaile not (good Reader) that I labour in confronting ſo horrid a doctrin: for if by all my endeavours I draw but one ſoule by the eares out of this ſinke and pit of error, it ſhall well become my profeſſion, &amp; the diſciple of him who ſought the ſtray ſheep, and finding it. brought it home into the fould upon his ſhoulders, or at leaſt I ſhall avovde that cenſure of S. Bernard, ſaying, Cadit aſinno, &amp; invenit qui ſublevet: sadit anima, &amp; non eſt qui man um apponat: The aſſe falls into the ditch, and there is one ready to pull him out: the ſoule falls, and there is none to put to his helping hand. Bernard ſuper Cantica.
               
               The abſurdity then of this doctrine of the habit and ſcapular (befides what hitherto hath beene ſaid) may in this alſo appeare. That if they performe what they promiſe, and what their revelations doe import. That is certitude and aſſurance in this life of glory, &amp; ſalvation in the next, they ſurpaſſe in eſticacy all the Sacraments of the Church, what ſoever have been or dayned by divine authority, and practiſed by Chriſtians ſince the Primitive times, untill the second comming of Chriſt. For the Sacraments of the New Teſtament by our Saviours inſtitution, doe on
                     •
                  ly conferre grace &amp; predent iuſtification, (having all their vertue, &amp; e
                     •
                  ticacy from the merit of his paſſion) ex opere operato, &amp; non ponenti obicem, onely as inſtrumentall cauſes conferred on ſuch partakers of them, as thorough
their indiſpoſition either of misbellefe or complacencie in ſin, doe put no impediment or barre unto their ſpirituall and ſupernaturall operation. They who deſire to ſee the proofes of this doctrine, from Scriptures, from Councells, the Greeke and Latine Fathers, &amp; the Schoolemen, I remit them among many others, unto the ſecond tome of Tho-Waldenſis, or William Lindanus his Panopli
                        •
                     , or The. Stapleton his Doctrinalia, or Cardinall Bellarmine de ſacramentis lib. 2. cap. 3.5. &amp;c.
               
               Now then (ſay I) albeit this be very much that our Saviour hath done for us in the Inſtitution of the Sacramonts, yet far more hath S. Francis &amp; Sirnon Stoc done for us by the habit &amp; ſcapular, becauſe he who this day is cleanſed from his ſins, &amp; juſtified by the vertue &amp; divine operation of the Sacraments, may after again fall into the like, or more grievous ſinnes, &amp; for the fame be damned, as of the, contrary: he who at this time abuſeth the Sacraments by reaſon of the indiſpoſitions above mentioned, may afterwards be penitent for the ſame, and by the comfort and helpe of them attaine his ſalvation, as may clearely appeare by the Apoſtles doctrine and admonition unto the Corinthians as touching the uſe and abuſe of the Euchariſt, 1. Cor. 11. Now I ſay that by our Friars doctrine, the habit &amp; the ſcapular are farre more effectuall unto ſalvation, then any one of the 7. Sacraments, or all of them put together. can be. For whether the habit &amp; the ſcapular worke in the nature of the Sacraments, by couferring the firſt or ſecond grace ex opere operato, they doe over and beſides conferre the grace of perſeverance, &amp; the perfection of all grace, which is glory. And this neither the baptiz
                        •
                     d, nor the conformed, nor the houſelled, nor the ordered, nor the penitent, nor the marryed, nor the annointed can promiſe unto themſelves, by which it is manifeſt; that in theſe mens doctrines the Babis &amp; the ſcapular infinitely excell all the vertue of the Sacraments, and ſo accordingly to be held &amp; eſtermed, as indeed in many mens eyes and opinions at this day they are.
               But now happily theſe patrons of the habit &amp; ſcapular preſſed, or rather oppreſſed with the weight of theſe arguments, and being aſhamed to aſcribe the divine work
                     •
                   of the Sacraments unto ſhadowes of no greater authority, or antiqui
                     •
                  y, then the viſions of S. Francis, &amp; S. Simon Sto
                        •
                     
                   will happily tell us by way of a qualification
of theſe their abſurd aſſertions. That the habit &amp; the ſcapular doe indeed reſemble the Sacraments: But how? onely ſo far forth as they are ſignes of future beatitude in the next world, without having any vertue or efficacy of effecting what they doe ſignifie. For whereas the 7. Sacraments of the Catholicke Church are indeed ſignes, yet not baſe, &amp; naked, but withall operative, that is as ſecondary &amp; inſtrumentall cauſes working that grace which they ſignifie, and ſignifying that grace which they worke. The habit &amp; the ſcapular (will theſe men ſay) are ſignes of another kind onely foreſhewing &amp; ſignifying beforehād that happines &amp; glory which ſhal befal al ſuch as ſhalbe foūd in the houre of death inveſted with them, albeit they no way concurre to the production of the aforeſaid glory, either by ſupernatural, phyſicall, or morall influx. And of this kind of ſignes, we have examples in the Scriptures not a few.
               Such was the Raine bow Geneſ. 9. placed by Almighty God in the clouds after the Flood, for a ſigne unto Noah and all mankind, that he would never more deſtroy the world by water, albeit the Rain-bow was no cauſe of any ſuch effect at all.
               Such was the Fleece of Gideon both wett and dry. Iudg. 6. a ſigne unto him from God, that the Madianites &amp; Amalekites ſhould be conquered by his hand.
               Such was the Sun 4. Reg. 20. going back ten degrees in the diall of King Ez
                        •
                     chias a ſigne given unto him by the Prophet Elias, that he ſhould recover of his infirmity.
               And to omit many other ſignes like unto theſe, of which the Scriptures are plentifull, ſuch was that ſigne of victor that appeared unto Constantin the Great, being to encounter with Maxentius the tyrant when in the sky hee ſaw a moſt bright Croſſe with this circumſcription, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . In this overcome. Euſeb. lib. 1. de vita Conſtant. Albeit not that ſigne of the Croſſe, which appeared unto Constantin, but he in whoſe hands all victoryes are, ſeconded by humane meanes, was the cauſe of gayning that battayle.
               And ſo indeed it is ſaid of the divine ſcapular in that ſayned revelation of Simon Stec, Ecec ſignum ſalutis, ſalus in periculis, foedus pacis, &amp; pacts ſempiterni: Behold the ſigne of ſalvation, ſafety in dangers, a league of peace, and of an everlaſting covenant. Say then,
that we admit of this qualification of theirs, and take it for granted, that the habit &amp; ſcapular be but bare ſignes onely ſignificative &amp; not operative, and onely of the nature of thoſe foure ſignes laſt mentioned. Yet muſt we needs confeſſe them to bee ſignes of farre more excellency, &amp; of a greater importment, in reſpect of their ſupernaturall object, which is glory, I meane then either the Rain-bow in the clouds, or Gideo
                        •
                     s Fleece upon the ſloore, or the retrograde Sun in Ezechias horologe, or Constantin his Croſſe with the Emblem thereof, In 
                        •
                     oc vince, In this overcome. For that theſe were but ſignes and pledges of temporall bleſſings, as ſecurity from inundations, victory in warre, bodily health, and the like.
               But S. Francis legacy bequeathed unto his Friars is, that whoſoever dyes in their habit, ſhall not periſh of any unhappy death.
               
                  Simon St
                        ••
                     
                   of the ſcapular is, That whoſoever dyes therein, n
                        •
                     nquam patietur incendium ſempiternum, He ſhall never ſuffer eternall fire.
               Dame Luiſſa her Saturday faſt is, That who ſo performes it, ſhall not end his dayes in mortall ſin.
               Theſe (I wis) are ſignes not of any worldly benefits, or temporall bleſſings, but of that Crowne of immortality which attends all ſuch as have beene victorious in this our Chriſtian warfare. For if the ſoule that better part of Man be of a divine being, and immortall as the beſt Philoſophers have taught: and if it be of that precious eſteeme with God, as he is ſaid in the Scriptures to bee amator animarum, a lover of ſoules. And our bleſſed Saviour the Redeemer of ſoules, could ſay, Mar. 8. Quid enim proderit bomini? &amp;c. What ſhall it boot a man to ga
                     •
                  ne the whole world, and to looſe his owne ſoule? And if King Ezechias was ſo tender of his corporall health, as he deſired that the ſame ſhould be confirmed unto him by a ſigne from Heaven, which was a pledge farre more liefe and deare unto him then was that plaſtet of figs applyed unto his ſore, a ſecon
                     •
                  lary cauſe of his health. No marveile then though a poore ſinner ſhould prize a ſigne from Heaven, an aſſured pledge of eternall ſalvation, before all other treaſure upon earth, yea before all other helpes and meanes conducing thereunto.
               Alas then, if it be true that theſe men tell us, Why was not S. Francis, and Simon Stoe no ſooner with us? Why did poors ſinners
miſſe theſe ſo precious ſignes and pledges of their ſalvation for a thouſand &amp; two yeares ſince Chriſt? Or why ſince there have beene habits &amp; ſcapulars from the dayes of S. Baſil, &amp; S. Auguſtine, &amp; S. Benedict, that none of them had that divine influence, or ſignification as the gray habit of the Minors, &amp; the two ſquare patches ex quolibet panno of the Car
                        ••
                     clites, the former not five hundred yeares old, and the later not ſo much. But not to lament the times of greater antiquity. Alas, &amp; well away. Where was this bleſſed habit &amp; ſcapular the day wherein S. Bernard dyed, in which it is reported that of 30 thouſand perſons, who then departed this life, onely S. Bernard &amp; two moe were ſaved, for ſo S. Vincentius the Dominican enformeth us in his 6. ſermon de Septuag. fró a viſion made unto an holy Ermite, ſometime Deane of Langres in France, as alſo Martinus Polonus in his promptuary of examples, cap. 18. Or after that time againe, and within the date of theſe ſo myſticall weeder, where were theſe helpes &amp; divine comforts ſo farre tranſcending all ſacraments, and ſacramentalls, when as in the yeere of grace, 1343. a holy Ermite ſaw in a viſion the ſoules of men &amp; women falling as faſt into hell as ever ſnow came downe from the clouds, and onely three to mount up to Heaven, namely the ſoule of a Biſhop &amp; of a Charter-houſe Monke, and of a Roman Widow. This ſhall you reade lib. de 
                        •
                     rt
                        •
                      Carthuſienſi in the time of Innocentius the ſixt of that name, Surely it ſeemes that either in thoſe dayes there wanted Preachers to publiſh theſe miraculous graces of the habit and ſcapular, or people to beleeve them. Or elſe we muſt ſay, that the ſhops wanted friſes &amp; woollen cloath to make them of. Or Taylors to cut them out, which for my part I will as ſoone believe, as the woods of Arden in Germany to want theeves &amp; Freebooters, or the Gardens of Egypt to want Leekes &amp; Onions, which ſome of the Egyptians worſhipped as their gods, as may appeare by that verſe of Invenal. Sat. 15.
               
                  Porrum &amp; cepe nefas violare, ac frangere morſu:
                  O ſanctas gentes, quibus bac naſcuntur in hor tis
                  Numina.
               
               To chaw an Onion or a Leeke is held a foule offence: O holy people whoſe gods doe grow, but wot you whence? Their gardens.
               
               And I pray God, That many among us, who would bee eſteemed very good &amp; perfect Chriſtians, yeeld not more honour unto the creatures (albeit they make them not their gods) then they ought, or may ſtand with the integrity of our holy faith.
               But to returne to our Argument: (For I purpoſe to leave no reaſon pro, or contra indiſcuſſed, which may ſerve to diſcover the vanity of theſe aforeſaid Revelations, with which ſo many ſoules both have beene, and are at this day abuſed.) And firſt for that Legacy of S. Francis, grounded upon a viſion, or Revelation. That whoſoever dyeth in his habit, ſhall never be prevented with an unhappy death. I perſwade my ſelfe, beſides what already hath been ſaid, that it is a meere fiction &amp; an lmpoſture of his Friars of later times, untruly fathered upon the Saint, for the maintenance of their bellyes.
               And firſt it is held as moſt probable, That S. Francis had no certaine or particular habit at all, either of this or that cloath, or colour: but onely courſe and of ſmall price, ſuch as might beſt ſort with poverty, &amp; pennance, as may appeare by his rule cap. 2. in theſe words, Fratres omnes veſtimentis vilibus induantur, &amp; poſſint eis repeciare de ſaccis &amp; alijs pecijs cum benedictione Dei. Let all the Fryars be clad with courſe clothing, &amp; they may patch them with ſackcloth, &amp; other patches on Gods bleſſing. And this which our Friars doe hold to be a precept of the rule, or equipollent to a precept, may ſeeme to be confirmed by the practice of the Order, for ſee wee not the Capuchins to weare a diſtinct habit from the Cordeliers, agreeing in nothing but onely in colour? The Capuchin having a large friſe coat to the foot, with a piece of courſe canvas ſquare, one halfe yard upon the back, girded unto him with a rude maſſie rope, with a great knot before, &amp; unto this coat ſowed a ſteepled hood, or ca puch, from whence they have the name of Capuchins, of well-neere two foot long, from the baſis to the conus, &amp; over this coat they have a cloake of the ſame friſe, comming litle below the waſte.
               When as the Cordelier profeſſing the ſame Order of S. Francis, &amp; the ſame rule, hath a coat of much better friſe, without that ſquare canvas on the back, with a hood or a capuch not ſteepled at all, but round, &amp; fitted unto his head, a girdle of a cord, from whence hee
hath his name of Cordilier, the ſame handſomely wrought with many artificiall knots, orderly placed by equall diſtances, a ſleeve, O heavenly wide, which beſides the arme will well containe a couple of Cheeſes quartered, or a Gamon of bacon a-piece, or as many Puddings as would well neere ſerve a whole Convent of Friars for their break-faſt, &amp; over all this they have a cloak of the ſame friſe deſcending almoſt unto the foot. Obſerve then how different theſe habits be, &amp; yet thoſe Franciſcans againe which are of the reformation of S. Diego, they have a diſtinct habit both from the Capuchin &amp; Cordelier. Sith then each of theſe deny the other to have the habit of S. Francis, I then demaund of our Friars, which of theſe habits? or is it all of them that hath the bleſſing, that whoſoever dyes in them ſhall never be prevented with an unhappy death? But what was the true habit of S. Francis, or which of the reformations have got it, I make account they will agree upon it when my fingers grow all of one length, &amp; then happily my ſelfe will be as credulous as others to believe them.
               Now againe it is to be obſerved, That this revelation of the habit is not to be found in the life of S. Francis at all, notwithſtanding his life was written by many &amp; moſt of them of his own family &amp; order, as firſt &amp; ſoone after his death by S. Bonaventure, neither is it in the Bull of his canonization of Pope Greg. 9. nor yet in the Roman Breviary or any other Legend of later time, either of Lippolo, or Lippomannus, or Villiegas, or laſt of all by Friar Luke Wadding, a Cordilier, living this day in Rome. In all which Legends of the aforeſaid authors, matters of farre leſſe couſequence (I wis) are not forgotten, &amp; yet not word of this great benefit of the habit to be read in them.
               Beſides, is it not a thing to be admired &amp; wondered at, that S. Francis leaving ſuch a golden legacy unto the world, that whoſoever dyed in the habit of his order ſhould be ſaved, that himſelfe was not carefull to dye in the ſame, as well for example unto poſterity, as alſo to be partaker of that ſecurity of ſalvation with other Chriſtians. For we reade in the firſt tome of the Chronicle of the Priars Minors, cap. 71. That S. Francis when he perceived the houre of his death approaching, ſtript himſelfe all naked, and then caſt himſelfe upon the ground, making an exhortation to his

                     〈4 pages missing〉
                  
                  brethren to perſiſt conſtant in the love of God, &amp; the profeſſion of holy poverty, till ſuch time as the Guardian (whom he obeyed) underſtanding the deſire of the holy Father, taking preſently an habit with the cord &amp; linnea breeches, brought them unto him, ſaying: Father, take this habit which I lend you with the cord and breeches, that you may be buryed there with to cover your nakedneſſe. And it is there ſaid, that S. Francis contentedly took the breeches, but not the habit, for that he deſired to conforme himſelfe unto our Saviour, who dyed naked upon the Croſſe.
               Laſtly, how can this aforeſaid revelation of the habit ſtand with any truth, or probability, when as dayly experience condem 
                     •
                  eth the ſame of crrour &amp; falſhood, &amp; therefore more like to be ſome belly-invention of his diſciples, apoſtating from the rule and diſcipline of their Founder, then any wiſe authorixed by S. Francis, who doubtleſſe was a holy man, &amp; who in his life-time did ſee, &amp; did both condemne &amp; lament with great griefe of mind, the manyfold diſorders of his followers, and the prevarication of his rule, as may appeare by ſundry paſſages of the hiſtory of the Friar Minors, whoſoever will take the paines to peruſe the ſame.
               I ſay then, that ſetting aſide all other reaſons, ſenſe it ſelfe &amp; experience doth ſufficiently confute &amp; convince of moſt into lienable falſhood that doctrine of our Friar Minors, namely that whoſoever dyes veſted with their habit, ſhall never be prevented of an unhappy death. For firſt if it be underſtood of temporall duaſters, &amp; calamityes in death, theſe fraile bodyes of ours having ſo many windowes to admit them, according to that of the Tragedian, Eripere vitam nem
                        •
                      non homini potest, at nemo mortem, mille ad hane aditus patent. Seneca in Hippol. Every one may deprive us of life, but none can debarre us of death, which hath a thouſand gates. Among which calamityes attending our ends, if ſudden death be reckoned for one, (as it ſeemes by the doctrine of holy Church to be) we being taught to pray: A ſubitanea &amp; improviſa morte libera nos domine: From ſudden and inexpected death deliver us good Lord, What ſhall wee ſay of that ſubtile Doctor among the Franciſeans, Johaunes Duns Scotus, who being Apoplecticus, or ſubject to the palſy, and ſuppoſed in one of his fits to be dead, was buryed
alive, as appeared at the returne of his abſent companion, who being acquainted with the nature of his diſeaſe, cauſed his body to be taken up, which was found all broken &amp; bruiſed with ſtriving to recover himſelfe from his ſepulchre, whoſe fate is reported by Paulus I vi
                        ••
                     
                   in theſe words: Apoplexiâ correp
                        •
                     us Scot us panas perſolvis It a qu
                        •
                     dem at nimis festinato funere promortuo tumulatus, cum redeubte vita ſoro morbi impetum natura diſcuteret, frustra ad petendaw opem mi
                        •
                     era
                        •
                     il
                        •
                      mugitu adito pulſatoque din ſepulchri lapide eliſo tandem capite pe
                        •
                     ier
                        •
                     t. Scotus taken with an Apoplexy, had his puniſhment. ſo as buryed for dead too haſtily, when as nature too late had diſgeſted the force of his diſeaſe, and life returning, in vaine deſiring holp, &amp; yeelding a miſerable roaring, &amp; often beating the ſtore of his grave, at length his head being violently bruiſed, he periſhed. So Iovius. Whoſe fate wanted not alſo a Poet to expreſſe the ſame in verſe, as followeth:

                     
                        
                           Quod nulli hominum un quans accidit viator
                        
                        
                           Hic Scot us jaceo ſemel ſepultus,
                        
                        
                           Et his mortuus: omnibus ſophistis
                        
                        
                           Argutus magis, at que captioſus.
                        
                        
                           Ianus Vitalis apud lovium.
                        
                     
                     
                        What chanc'd before to none,
                        I am forced to bemoane:
                        O thou that paſſeſt by,
                        Lo Scotus where J lye,
                        Who twiſe though being dead,
                        Was once but buryed,
                        Of me ſome (doubt not) ſay,
                        And ſure I thinke they may.
                        Each Sophiſt I out-went
                        In captious argument.
                     
                  
               
               This and much more as touching the fate of Scotus may you read in Bzovius in his continuation of Ceſur Baronius his Annalls in the years 1494. But not to wade into any further ſea of examples. Spaine will tell you how many Friar Minots have been caſt away by ſh
                     •
                  pwrack in their voyages unto the Indyes, My ſelfe in the yeare 1610, in the territoryes of Lerma in Cantle, with many othors (the whole town in a manner going forth to the ſame) beheld
the murdered body of a Franciſcan Friar, a ſtranger to that place, who was ſuppoſed to have had moneyes, &amp; being robbed of them, was alſo ſlaine, &amp; his body hid among the ſtanding corne neere unto the gate of the towne of Le
                        •
                     ma. But ſome peradventure will ſay, that ſudden death is not to be numbred among unhappy, or diſaſterous fates at all. For ſo much as we read, that Iulius Caſar diſputing of that argument the day before he was ſlain in the Senat-houſe, was of opinion, that an inexpected death was to be preferred before any other. Sueton, in Iulio. And a Princely writer of theſe times, in his expoſition upon the Lords prayer, ſeemes not to diſallow of that death which yeelds leaſt trouble unto the ſenſe. So as in theſe mens opinions, not a ſudden, but an unprovided death is that which is to be miſliked, conformable to that of Sapient 4. Iuſtus ſi morte praeoccupatus fu
                        •
                     rit, in refrigerio e
                        •
                     it. The juſt man though he be prevented by death, he ſhall be in a refreſhing. And by their leaves, I would ſay, that the death which is inexpected, may well be ſuſpected, &amp; feared to be unprovided. And therefore (for my part) I pray God that death may knock at my doore along time before he enter, ſtill leaning unto the old Intanyes, A ſubitanea &amp; improviſa morte libera nos Domine: From a ſudden, &amp; an unlooked for death, good Lord deliver us. But to leave this point to thoſe who have more leiſure to diſpute it: whether a ſudden death is to be numbred among miſerable deaths or no?
               Let us come unto a ſecond, wherein I demand, whether a death inſ
                     •
                  icted by the hand of Iuſtice, may not juſtly be numbred among unhappy deaths. And I thinke none will deny it, forſomuch as Peter hath ſaid, Nemo autem veſtrum paetiatur ut homicida, aut fur, &amp;c. Let none of you ſuffer as a murderere or a thiefe, &amp;c. If then we find Friars of the order of S. Francis, who for their crimes &amp; demerits have been ſentenced at the barre of Tribunalls, to in famous &amp; diſhonorable deaths, How then have their habits priviledged them? Or where is that legacy of S. Francis, that who ſo dyeth in the habit of his Order, ſhall never be prevented with an unhappy death? If any be ſo curious as to enforme himſelfe in this affaire. I ſhall not need to ſend him either unto the Italian Guittiardin, or to Spaniſh &amp; French Hiſtory, or further then unto the Annalls of

                  England, &amp; for no larger a time then betwixt the Norman Conqueror, &amp; King Henry 8. Where he ſhall find examples moe then a good many, of that kind. I ſay of Friars of the Order of S. Francis who have bin put to ſhamefull deaths by the hand of Iuſtice. And the ſame neither for building of Churches, nor miniſtring of Sacraments.
               But ſome will ſay. That ſtill I come ſhort of the marke, &amp; of what was intended, ſo long as I inſiſt onely in theſe temporall calamiti
                     •
                  s that accompany the death of the body, which with how terrible a countenance ſoever they looke upon their patients, by any miſery, or caſualty deprived together with their lifes, of the benefit of the, Sacraments, yet we know not but ev
                     •
                  n in their laſt agony, or before continued unto their end thorough the abundant mercy of God they might be found penitent, &amp; truly contrite for their fins, &amp; ſo as (in that deſpicable &amp; wretched a paſſage unto the eyes of the world) they might be able to ſay, Tranſivimus per ignem &amp; aquam, &amp; eduxiſti nos in refrigerium. We have paſſed thorough fire &amp; water, &amp; thou haſt brought us into a refreſhing. So as ſtill to make good that propheticall prediction fathered upon S. Francis by his Friars, ſuch as dye in their habit, whether by death ſudden, or deſerved, they ſhal alwayes dye happily. Since no death is to be held abſolutely miſerable, excepting that one which carryes with it, Peccatum ad mortem. Of which the Apoſtle S. Iohn. Est peccatum ad mortem, non pro illo dico ut roget quis. 1. 
                     •
                  oh, 5. There is a ſin unto death, I ſay, that for it no man aske. Which ſin by S. Auguſtines judgment is finall impenitency. I a
                     ••
                  irme (ſaith he). That a ſin to dea his to leave faith working by charity, even till death. Decorrept. &amp; gratia, cap. 12. And the ſame doctrine he teacheth De civicate Deilib. 21. cap. 24. So then the laſt refuge of our Friars is, that ſetting apart 
                     •
                  ll other kindes of death, of which none can be defined to be abſolutely miſerable, ſuch as dye in their habit ſhall never dye impenitent, but truly contrite for their ſins, by which they ſh
                     •
                  ll be ſe
                     •
                  ure from the ſecond death, &amp; the eternall ſeparation from the bleſſed viſion of God. So S. Francis his ſuppoſed revelation of the habit, &amp; Simon Stoc of the ſcapular, doe concurre in this. In quo quis moriens, non patietur incendium ſempiternū, In which whoſoever dyes ſhall never ſuffer eternall fire.
               
               As then we have hitherto proved &amp; inſtanced by many exaples, that notwithſtanding the habit of S. Francis, there hath not wanted ſuch as have periſhed both by ſudden, &amp; infamous deaths. So now in the laſt place it remaines (to take away all tergiverſation) to manifeſt unto the world (which ſome will ſay is a hard tax,) That divers Friars ending their dayes in the habit of S. Francis, have bin ſubiect even unto this laſt &amp; worſt kind of death, joyned with finall impenitency &amp; obduratneſſe in ſin, &amp; conſequently according unto the doctrine of holy Church, can no wayes be held to have dyed happily. And albeit no man in this life may judge another mans ſervant, for that as the Apoſtle ſayth, he ſtan
                        •
                     s or falls unto his owne Lord, to whom all judgment both of quick &amp; dead is reſerved. And that ordinarily none comes back from the next world to tell us, how they fare, according to that of Iob. 16. Ecte enim brevi anni tranſennt, &amp; ſemitam per quam non revertar ambulo. Loe our yeares paſſe ſwiftly, &amp; I walke the path by which I ſhall not returne. Notwithſtanding in our Writers of the Acts &amp; Monuments of Saints. we find nothing more common, or familiar then viſions or apparitions made unto the living, as touching the eſtare &amp; condition of the deſunct: ſomerev ealed to be in glory, ſome in Purgatory, others damned: As whoſoever will peruſe that large vo umt of S. Brigids revelations, or Caſarius, or Speculum exemplorum, or Capgravins, or the Chronicle of S. Francis, or any of our later legendary collectors, will witneſſe with me. But ſetting all theſe aſide, which for mine own part, as I doe not wholly reject, depriving them of all credit &amp; authority. So neither is my faith ſo ſtrong, as to admit into my Creed very much of what I read of that kind. Conſidering that if the belly hath in all times bin a great Maſter of Art, according to that of the Poet, Venter magiſter artis, ingenijque largitor: The belly is a Maſter of Art, &amp; a ſupplyer of Invention. So above all other in the ſchoole of our Monkes &amp; Mendicants hath the ſame bin not onely a Maſter of Art, but even Doctor Cathedrations, A Doctor of the Chayre, pabliſhing both by voyce &amp; writing whatſoever might be ſerviceable unto the Genius of the place.
               Omitting then all Viſions, Revelations, &amp; Apparitions. I heare our Saviour ſaying, that there is Spiritus blasphemia, there is a ſin
againſt the Holy Ghoſt which ſhall never be forgiven, I heare the voyce of the ſame truth ſaying Iohn 3. Such as believe not, are judged already. I heare the beloved Diſciple ſaying, 1. Iohn 5. Eſt peccatum ad mortem, there is a ſin unto death, for which I ſay that none doe pray. I heare S. Aug. ſaying De Civitate Deilib. 21. cap. 24. If there be any that perſiſt till death in impenitency of heart, doth the Church now pray for them, that is, for the ſoules of them that are departed? I heare alſo Concilium Braccarenſe primum cap. 34. forbidding to pray for ſuch as dye in deſperation, or misbeliefe, or kill themſelves. Tell me then you who pretend to be obſervantes, and the moſt ſtrict imitators of S. Francis, what ſhall we ſay of ſuch of your order, as have bin mnrdered in flagranti delicte? you know my meaning. Of ſo many as have bin executed for Iudaiſme by ſentence of the Inquiſition? eſpecially in Spaine &amp; Portugall, of which ſort in Lisboa, there was a Friar Minor in the yeare 1610. who was burned in his habit upon a ſtage, &amp; dying obſtinate in his infidelity till the laſt breath, cryed loude &amp; often in a lamentable, &amp; dying voyce, Deus, Deus mens, ad te de luce vigilo. O God, O my God, from the light doe I wake unto thee. What ſay you to others of your Order, who preventing the courſe of nature have murdered themſelves? Have you forgotten? or can you ever forget that wofull ſpectacle which hapned in the perſon of Excuſe me that in my Arcte. maſtix I called him George Barnwell,
                   
                  Thomas Barnwel a Franciſcan Friar, who upon S. Iohn day in Chriſtmaſſe, in the yeare 1630, hanged himſelfe in the Orchard of Temple Og, ſcarſe two miles diſtant from the city of Dublin, upon the bough of an apple-tree, not onely in the habit of his order, but uſing for that execrable ſervice, the cord of his habit, with which he girt his loyns? What voyce is there then ſo wicked? or pen ſo prophane as to publiſh theſe men &amp; the like to have dved happily? No rather may they ſay, Quid profuit nobis habitus aut ſcapulare? What hath the habit or the ſcapular proſited us? or wherein have they helped us? for ſave that in our life-time they were beneficiall unto cur bellyes, the confidence that we had in them after death, hath deprived both our bodyes of Chriſtian buriall, &amp; our ſoules of the prayers &amp; ſuffrages of the Church, and of all faithfull people.
               Now then to conclude this Chap. with are capirulation of ſuch argunents, as have bin alledged in the precedent diſcourſe, againſt
the doctrine of certaintie of ſalvation by Habits, Scapulars, &amp; the Luiſſian faſt. Firſt then (gentle reader) thou haſt ſcene the ſame refuted à priore from authority of the Church, Scriptures, Councells, &amp; Fathers. Secondly à poſteriore thou haſt beheld the abſurdity &amp; falſity thereof layd open before thee ad oculum, by very ſenſe &amp; experience in all ſuch kindes, ſorts, &amp; varietyes of death as by Chriſtians in all times have bin held miſerable, unhappy &amp; ignominious: of all which, Friars in their Habits have bin ſenſible, &amp; ſufferers. And therefore that doctrine of theirs muſt needes remaine voyde of all truth. That whoſoever dyes in their habit, ſhall never be prevented with an unhappy death.
               And yet theſe be our Apoſtles, &amp; Miſſionaryes ſent from Rome to convert Nations, and to reduce them to the Catholick faith. Such Apoſtles &amp; Preachers, as doubtleſſe ſhall never turne any, unleſſe it be fooles into mad men. Truly Friar Miſſionaryes, if theſe be the ſignes of your Apoſtleſhip, &amp; this the Goſpell you preach, ſooner ſhall you catch a Hare with a Tabor, then convert a Proteſtant into a Roman Catholicke. If among the ſavage Indyes you preach theſe doctrines, I know not what credulity you may purchaſe: but if in theſe parts you ſeeke to gaine ſoules, &amp; to bring ſuch as are aſtray into the right way, doubt leſſe it muſt be by other doctrines, then Habits and Scapulars.
               
               Non obtuſa adoo gestamus corda Britanni.
               We Britans live not in ſo groſſe anayre, though much unto the North, but that we can diſcerne of colours, who preacheth Chriſt, &amp; who themſelves: and if the former had bin till this day, as well applyed as the latter, happily that lapis ſcandali, that rock of offence, at which ſo many have ſtumbled, had bin before this time removed. You Mendicants enter heere among us, with ſpecious &amp; glorious titles of Legantine, &amp; Miſſionary power. You tell us, you are ſent to labour in the Vineyard, to worke in the harveſt, but what ſayes the Proteſtant? when he ſees all you labour is but to eat the grapes, &amp; to cull out the beſt ſheaves, when they finde all your preaching turned into begging, or at leaſt there unto tending. Mary (ſay they) Theſe be thoſe who preach themſelves, and not Chriſt Ieſus. And ſay they not truly? You tell us you are ſent from Rome to aſſiſt the Prieſts and the Paſtours ingoverning and
feeding of their flocks, but verily in all parts of this Kingdome, it is well underſtood what ſlockes you looke after. O how well it becomes the Franciſean &amp; the Dominican, after they have ſhamed the poore people on a Sunday morning out of their meanes, the weeke after to gadd thorough the Pariſhes, &amp; to gather in their muttons, and hearde them together.
               
                  Compulerantque greges Coridon &amp; Thirſis in unum. and after to expoſe them to ſale one with another at 12. pence the head, in every Barony of this Kingdome. Gentlemen expecting when the Friars ſheep paſſe by, or where they keepe the market, hoping what they got ſo eaſily, they will not rate too highly. And as dextrous as they be in bringing home the ſtrayed ſheep, ſo no leſſe diligent are they in ſeeking the loſt groat. It is a laudable cuſtome of the Church commanded by expreſſe Canons, that all Chriſtians ſhould communicate at leaſt once a yeare, &amp; the ſame at Eaſter at the hands of their owne Paſtor, &amp; this is called the Paſchall Communion, at which time as by the precept of holy Church, all that are come to the yeares of diſcretion doe participate the bleſſed body &amp; blood of our Saviour in the holy Euchariſt, ſo commonly doth every one according to their devotion &amp; ability, make their offering: which offering the good people in this Countrey commonly lay downe upon the Altar, &amp; it is indeed the chiefe maintenance that the Paſtor hath for all the yeare after. But thinke you this poore groat can eſcape the Friars gripe No, for now the holy weeke approaching, the Friar Limitour beftirs himſelfe, &amp; the weeke commonly before, &amp; after Eaſter, hee viſits all the Pariſhes of his limits, &amp; he either addreſſes himſelfe unto the Oratory of the Pariſh Prieſt, or elſe himſelf makes a Rande
                        ••
                     us in ſome principall part of the Pariſh, where he ſayes Maſſe, heares confeſſions, receives all he can procure to make the Paſchal Communion with him, having all the yeare before prepared and perſwaded the people, that by reaſon of their Indults &amp; priviledges from Rome, they ſhall aſ well ſatisfie the precept of the Church in communicating with him, as at the hands of the I'aſtor. Neither dare the Pariſh Prieſt conteſt with him, for the Friar is not unprovided of his friends, who will make good all his pretentions, ſo as if the Prieſt give but the leaſt oppoſition, hee ſhall not onely not
prevayle, but he ſhall have the frowne of the beſt of his Pariſh happily all the yeare after. And thus the groat loſt by the Prieſt, is found by the Friar, &amp; where was it all this while, but upon the Altar, cloſe by the Candleſtick. This is that good aſſiſtance, &amp; this the help which the Pariſh Prieſt at Eaſter gets by the Friars induſtry, who having found the groat, returnes home, &amp; there rejoyeeth with his fellowes, who in other Pariſhes have done the like ſervice, putting the ſurplus of their gettings into the hands of their ſyndieus or Treaſurer (of which every Convent hath one) and I pray God ſuch Treaſures be reſerved for good purpoſes.
            
            
               
                  CAP. II. The Authors Apology, and a defence of his Writings.
               
                  BVT now I wot well what our Mendicants with all their faction both in privat &amp; publick ſpeeches, will thunder out againſt me. Is it well done for a Catholick man to diſcover the faults of Church men? A Prieſt of his brethren? Were it not better that theſe enormityes were covered with Conſtantius his purple robe, themto be aſcan dall &amp; a by-word unto ſo many Atheiſts, &amp; misbelieving Sectaryes as theſe times doe yeeld 
                     •
                  o Did not the Prophet David when he heard of the overthrow of Saul &amp; lonathar, &amp; their ſlaughter upon the mountaines of Gilbon, cry out with great lamentation, Nolite enunciare in Gath, neque annuncietia in compitis Aſcalon, 
                        〈◊〉
                      fortè latentu filin Philiſtin, n
                        •
                      exulten
                        •
                     ili
                        •
                      incircumci ſorum, O pisbliſh it not in Gath, nor preach it in the ſtreetes of Aſcalon, left peradventure the daughters of the Philiſtins doerejoyce, and the daughters of the incircumciſed triumph.
               To all which &amp; what elſe they can ſay againſt theſe my proceedings, I anſwer with S. Gragary, Melius ast ut ſcandalum, or
                        ••
                     tur, quam 
                        •
                     t veritas relinquatur. Better it is that ſcandall ſhould ariſe, then that truth ſhould be forſaken. And is it poſſible (ſay I) to refixe error, &amp; not to name it? to reprove vice, &amp; not to tell what
colour it is of? Have I done otherwiſe in theſe my proceedings, then the Prophets of God, who oppoſed themſelves unto ſuch Prophets, as for a piece of bread would propheſie pleaſing things in the cares of the people? Or then the Apoſtles of our Saviour, who both by word &amp; writing did confound the falſe Apoſtles, who entred in among them to corrupt the truth, &amp; to adulterat the Goſpell of the Kingdome? And hath not this beene the practice of the Paſtors of Gods Church in all times? Did not S. Athanaſius, S. Hilary, &amp; S. Aug. moſt bitterly inveigh againſt the Arian Heretiques? S. Hierom againſt lovintan &amp; Vigilantius? S. Beruard againſt Abaylardus? Nay, not againſt falſe teachers onely, but againſt vitious, &amp; corrupt livers alſo, have the aforeſaid Fathers lanced out into the depth of moſt ſharp reprehenſions, not ſparing the vices either of Church, or Laymen, of their dayes? And why ſhould I in a like cauſe bee fearefull to imitate ſo great examples? to rebuke ſuch falſe Prophets as ſacrifize not unto the Creator, &amp; his providence, but unto their own fiſhing-nets, lines, &amp; hookes, the fancyes &amp; inventions of their own braines? To oppoſe ſuch as call themſelves Apoſtles &amp; are not, but are found lyars? And why ſhould I more feare the face, and frownes of a Friar, then S. Antony of Padna, a principall Preacher among the Friar Minor? or S. Bondventure ſome time generall of their order, then S. Francis himſelſo in ſtitutor of the ſame Order?
               Of whom the firſt hath theſe words. Heu quant 
                        •
                      ſciſſura, &amp;c. Alas, how great diviſions, how great ſchiſmes, how great diſſentions are there in Religion! &amp; truly where theſe be, there is nothing but contention in the Chapter-houſe, diſſoluteneſſe in the Quire, murmuration in the Oloyſter, &amp; wantonnoſſein the Dormitary. So Antony de Padua in his Sermon upon Sexageſima Sunday.
               S. Bonaventure. Cùmſecundùm patres laudantur wonachi in caſollis, &amp;c. When as, according to the Fathers. The Monkes are praiſed to have dwelt in cotts, &amp; poore habitations, What is the matter now, that you build high &amp; ſtately, houſes, ſumptuous Monaſteryes, you purchaſe large &amp; ſpacious Courts. When as being poore &amp; beggars you ought to be contemners of all worldly
things. So S. Bonaventure q. 6.
               
               
                  S. Francis was ſo farre out of love with his owne Friars, as ſeeing them in his owne dayes no leſſe a bound in wickedneſſe, then in number, he left off to be thein generall Miniſter, gave them over (as his words are) to the devills to be their tormentors both in this world, &amp; in the other for the prevatication of that rule hee inſtituted, &amp; the tranſgreſſion of the vowes of their profeſſion All which &amp; much more to the ſame purpoſe ſhall you read in the 1. Tome of the Chronicle of the Friar Minors, the laft Chap.
               What ſhall 1 ſay of Iohannes Lanſpergius, the Carthuſian Monk, who in a certain Sermon which he preached unto the Congregation of Friars, relating the miſerable conditiō of Regulars, he utrereth ſuch things as are hardly to be beloeved that a Catholick man would publiſh. I will report his words as they lye, and they be theſe: Perijt religio, perijt reguluris bon
                        •
                     s, parumque abest hodie apud nonnullos, ut monachum non recenſeant inter Christiants. Religion is periſhed, Regular honour is periſhed, &amp; many are not farre from accounting a Monke ſearce among Chriſtian men. So Lanſpergius. &amp; not many lines after: Non abſque gemitu lo quendum ast, &amp;c. It is not to be ſpoken without griefe, &amp; with the licence of you &amp; all good men. So great hath been, &amp; is at this day the coldneſſe of the moſt in religious Orders, ſo great their diſſoluteneſſe, ſo great their diſcord, ſo great their faction, &amp; to be ſhort, ſuch ſelfe love, &amp; ſo little mortification of their evill paſſions, that it hath obſcured the very name of all good men; for if you looke into their lives, ſetting aſide certain exteriour ſignes &amp; badges of religion in their habits, nothing may you find or heare in them, wherein they goe beyond worldings, What marvayle then is it, if ou Lord hath given us up to an hiſs, to a mock, a wonderment &amp; laughingſtock to all Nations? I ſay what marvaile is it if we be accounted inforiour both in name, &amp; eſtimation to men of the world, ſince what Monke is there who goes beyond them either in devotion, piety, or morall honeſty. So Lanſpergius with much more to that purpoſe in the place above alledged.
               
                  Laurentius Iuſtinianus ſometime a Canon Regular, afterward Patrick of Venise, De Obedientiacap. 19. Saint mute
                        •
                      oenobia
                        •
                      &amp;
                  
                  utinam non numer oſior pars) que non ſanctor um habitacula, ſed latronum dicenda ſu
                        ••
                      ſpelunce, ſpectacula demonum, &amp; officine vitiorum. There be many Convents, &amp; I would to God not the greater part, that are not to be called the habitation of Saints, but the denns of theeves, the hant of devils, and the ſhops of vices.
               S. Brigid (not the Virgin of Ireland, but the widow of Swedland, lib. 4. Revel, cap.) much lamenteth the deformation of Religion in her time, I am tristitia eſt, religioſorum Regulas setnore mutatas in deteſtabiles abuſiones, &amp; minime teneri ſient Aug. Dominicus, &amp; Franciſcus ex inspiratione ſpiritus ſancti dictaverunt. It is a heavineſſe to behold the rules of religious to be changed into deteſtable abuſes, &amp; not to be obſerved as S. Aug. Dominick and Francis have by the inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt ſtayd them downe. The ſame S. Brigid condemning the avarice of Regulars, bringeth in our Saviour deteſting the ſame in theſe words: Recepetunt decem mandata mea, &amp; compoſucrunt in hos unum verbum: Quid est hoc anum verbum? Porrige mann
                        •
                     , &amp; a
                        •
                      pecuni
                        •
                     m. I
                        •
                     o nunquam ſitiantur do obtentis. They have received ten commandements from me, &amp; they have reduced them all into one word, &amp; what is that one word? Forſooth ſtretch forth thy hand, and give money, yea they are never ſatiſfied with what they get. So S. Brigid.
               
               And Thomas Walſingham a Monk of S. Benets order, and of the Abbay of S. Albons, ſetting forth the condition of the Friar Mendicants in his time, a moſt pious, &amp; a learned Authour, hath theſe words: The begging Friars unmindfull of their profeſſion, have forgot to what end their orders were inſtituted, becauſe their Law-givers, &amp; Founders (moſt holy men) would therefore have them poore, &amp; altogether free from the poſſeſſion of temporall things, that they might have no impediment to hinder them from ſpeaking the truth, or any thing they might ſeare to looſe for the ſame. But now while they envy ſuch as have poſſeſſions, approving the faults of greatment, nouriſhing the common people in error, &amp; eating the ſins of them both, in ſeeking of poſſeſſions, who have 
                     ••
                  nounced poſſeſſions, in hoarding up of money, who have ſworne to perſevere in poverty; they call good, evill; &amp; evill. good; ſeducing Princes with flattery, the people with lyes, and
drawing both of them with themſelves aſtray, they have in ſuch fort ſtayned that their profeſſion of truth, by their unhappy lives, that in theſe dayes in every ones mouth it is a good argument, holding as well in forme as matter: This fellow is a Fryar, and therefore a Lyar. Even as true as that, This thing is white, and therefore hath a colour. But that we may not be thought to have written theſe things of malice, let all of us acknowledge our ſelves to be in fault, &amp; let us amond what willingly we have done amiſſe, &amp; beſeech the God of peace and love, moſt devoutly, that peace &amp; truth may be in our dayes. So that holy Monk Thomas Walfingham in the reign
                     •
                   of Richard 2. fol 226. hee lived in the dayes of Henry 6. and dyed in the yeare 1440.
               
                  Atmathanus that glory of the Iriſh Church both for ſanctity &amp; learning, Archbiſhop of Armagh, &amp; Primate of all Ireland, commonly knowne by the name of S. Richard of Dundalks, ſpeaking of the great diſorders of the begging Friars of his time, eſpecially of the Franciſcans, hath theſe words, by which may bee underſtood how ſoone &amp; even in thoſe primitive &amp; better times of their obſervance, they deflected from the vowed rule of their Founder. When as the rule of S. Francis (ſayth Armachanus) commaunds after this manner, Pracipio formiter fratribus univerſis &amp;c. I doe firmely commaund all Friars, that they have not any ſuſpected fellowſhips, or counſells with women, neither that they once enter into the Monaſteryes of Nuns, excepting thoſe to whom eſpeciall licence is granted from the See Apoſtolick, neither that they be goſſips of men, or women, leſt by ſuch occaſion among the Friars, or of the Friars, ſcandall may ariſe. But of the contrary (ſayth my Author) The Friars have gotten licence to heare the moſt ſecret councells of women, of Ladies, &amp; of others without diſtinctiò, yea with their heads very ſubmiſſively bowed unto the womē heads, not following the footſteps of holy Iob, who ſayd, Pepigi f
                        •
                     dus cum oculis m
                        ••
                     ne cogitarem de virgine: I made a covenant with mine eyes that I ſhould not thinke of a Virgin. So as now-a dayes thorough ſuch familiarity they can play the Philoſophces with moſt beautifull Dames in their chambers, by occaſion whereof ſuch ſeandalls thorough the world are riſen of the Friars, as I will not
declare the ſame. So Armachanus in his Defenſorium Curatorum, about the midſt, with much more to the ſame purpoſe: he deceaſed in the Papall Court of Avignion, with opinion of great ſanctity, in the yeare 1360. Cal. Doce
                        •
                     b. But I muſt not omit what the ſaid Author ſetteth down in that his Oration which he pronounced before Pope Innocentius 6. &amp; his Cardinalls, againſt the Friars at Avignion as touching the abuſe of their priviledges, making them an inſtrument of Covetouſneſſe in theſe words.
               The Pariſhioner may reaſonably judge, that as concerning due &amp; profitable pennance to be enjoyned him for his ſins, the Paſtor or Pariſh prieſt is a judge leſſe to be ſuſpected, &amp; more indifferent then the Friar. For that the penitent cannot ſuſpect, nor hath any, ground to imagine, that his Paſtor by hearing his confeſſion doth expect any temporall lucre, or profit unto himſelfe, for ſo much as all things neceſſary for his maintenance according to the Law of God, &amp; holy Church, are annexed unto his office, But as for the Friars it is not ſo, becauſe as in that appellation which they made againſt me in England, it is contayned according unto their foundation, as they avouch, that not withſtanding they are priviledged to heare the confeſſions of all ſuch as wil confeſſe unto them, they are bound to moſt ſtrict poverty, &amp; begging, whereupon the Pariſhioner may probably ſuſpect, that verily the hope of gaine, &amp; of the relieving of his poverty, is the cauſe why the Friar heares his confeſſion, &amp; thus he may reaſon with himſelf in his mind. Wherfore ſhould that beggar that ſits there, heare my confeſſion? &amp; ſo defiſt from ſeeking things neceſſary for his maintenance, unleſſe he expected from me ſuch a ſupply? And forſomuch as poverty is a motive to ſin, by meanes where of his want may be ſupplyed, according to that of Solomon, Prov. 30. Poverty and riches give me not, but onely ſo much as ſhall be neceſſary for my maintenance, leſt happily being full I may be emiſed to deny thee, &amp; to ſay, who is the Lord? and forced by poverty ſhould ſteale and forſwe are the name of my God. It followeth that forevery kind of ſin, the Friar will impoſe upon, me almes-deedes, by which his poverty may be relieved, &amp; ſo ſhall not I be ſpiritually cured. For our Saviour, when as his Diſciples asked him: Why could not we caſt him out I (ſpeaking of the
devill) he anſwered: This kinde of devill is not throwne out but by prayer and fasting, Math. 17. Whereupon it is inferred, that as to every corporal diſeaſe, a particular medicine is to be applyed, which kind of medicine that beggar attending onely his neceſſityes (as I may well think) will never miniſter unto me. And this reaſon is thus confirmed. For that it ſufficiently appeares, that ſince the Friars have obtained a priviledge of hearing confeſſions everywhere thorough the world they have builded beautifull Monaſteryc
                     •
                  , and Princely Pallaces. The cauſe whereof ſeemeth to be their grant of hearing Confeſsions: for that before ſuch power given unto them, they were not able to build ſuch houſes. Again it is never heard, that tho Friars either for building of bridges, or repayring of high-wayes, or Pariſh Churches, doe enjoyne almes upon their penitents. Neither doe the Friar Minors impoſe almes to be beſtowed upon the Dominicans, nor the Dominicans upon the Minors. Every one applying all unto themſelves &amp; unto their owne order. Wherefore it may be probably judged, that private lucce &amp; gaine is the cauſe why ſuch a begging Friar is ſo careful to heare the confeſſion of the Layman, that he neglects his time of begging, &amp;c. So Armachanus.
               
               Cardinall Bellarmine (for learning &amp; piety in this age not infetiour to many, &amp; I know not whether to any) lamenting the miſerable face of religious orders of theſe times, in a moſt devout treatiſe which he compoſed but a little before his death, called Gemitus Columba, lib, 2. cap. 6. hath theſe words: Multiplicari coeperunt Regulares ſine numero &amp;c. Regulars have begun to be multiplyed without number, &amp; many of them not called by God unto the eſtate of perfection, but enduced by other motives, have repleniſhed Monaſteryes, &amp; that of Eſay is fulfilled: Thou haſt multiplyed the Nation, but not increaſed their joy. Hence ſo many, ſo grievous ſcandalls knowne unto all which yeeld plentifull matter unto the Dove of bewayling the looſneſſe, I will not ſay the corruption of religious Orders themſelves, as they be at this day. So the Cardinall.
               
                  Ichannes Petrus Camus Biſhop of Bellay, that great omament of the French Church, both for piety &amp; learning, in his booke called

                  The 
                        •••
                     ltua
                        •
                      Director, part 4. cap. 7. in ſhewing the difference twixt Paſtors &amp; Mercenaryes plainly demonſtrateth ou
                     •
                   of the words of our Saviour: That the Regulars who in theſe times would be eſteemed the onely Maſters in Iſrael, advancing themſelves above the ordinary Paſtors of Gods Church, aſſuming unto themſelves the firſt parts, as in perfection of life, ſo in ruling &amp; feeding that ſlock which our Saviour hath purchaſed with his own blood, are in truth no Paſtors at all, but playne Mercenaryes, &amp; hirelings, &amp; for ſuch onely to be held &amp; reputed: his words are theſe, which proceeding from ſo grave an Author, are worthy both to be read and pondered.
               Paſtors as well Biſhops as Curats, are by ſtate obliged to expoſe their lives for the ſheep committed unto their charge. Let us concerning this point give care unto the divine ſentence, which cannot be denyed without impiety, nor contradicted without blaſphemy. There is no greater charity then to give his life for his friends. Let us now adde here unto the deſcription of the true &amp; good Paſtor delivered unto us in the 10. Chap, of the Ghoſpell of S. Iohn, from the lips of our Saviour himſelfe: Bonus pastor animam ſua
                        ••
                      dat pro vibus ſuis: The good Paſtor or ſheepheard giveth his life for his ſheepe, which is as much as to ſay, is obliged to give it. Mercenarius out em, &amp; qui nonest paſtor: But the hireling, &amp; he that is not the ſheepheard. Behold how our Saviour diſtinguiſheth the Mercenary or hireling from the Paſtor, &amp; how he makes it apparant that the Mercenary is not the Paſtor, &amp; that he who is Paſtor is not Mercenary: He addeth, Mercenarius autem, &amp; qui non eſt Pastor, cujus non ſuut oves propria: The hireling, &amp; who is not the ſheepheard, &amp; the owner of the ſheep. In which words the Mercenary or hireling is plainly deſcribed to bee the party to whom the ſheep appertaine not. So as he who hath no ſheep of his owne, &amp; ſerveth notwithſtanding the ſheep, is no Paſtor at all, but onely a ſervant, a mercenary fellow, &amp; a meere hireling, without any flock of his owne. Let us follow the Text. Mercenarius videt Inpum venientem, &amp;c. He that is the Mercenary ſeeth the Wolfe comming, &amp; flyes, &amp; the Wolfe devoures &amp; diſperſeth the ſheep. Now I would faine know who is he that flyeth? Whether
the Paſtor &amp; he that hath curam animarium, the care of ſoules, or the Friar who hath no charge. He who is obliged by ſtate &amp; condition, &amp; by divine law to an actuall reſid
                     •
                  n
                     ••
                  ? What ſtorme ſoever happens, be it of plague, of warre, of famine, of perſecution, of hereſie, or any ſuch like? Or he that is not typed to any cure, or charge, &amp; not having any obligation, may retire himſelf from thoſe afflicted places, may forſake his countrey, the place of his abode, &amp; live where he likes beſt, yea &amp; who peradventure may think with himſelfe, that it is but to tempt God, to expoſe himſelfe raſhly to the hazard of his life without any neceſſary obligation, according as it is written, Qui amat periculum, peribit in illo. He who loveth danger, ſhall periſh therein. Let us now put the laſt finger to this Evangelicall deſcription of a Shepheard, and of an hireling. The mercenary or hireling (ſayth S. Iohn) ſlyes, &amp; he giveth a reaſon of his flight, Quia mercenarius oſt, becauſe hee is an hireling, and that the ſafety of the ſheepe concernes him not, becauſe he is not charged with them. But the true Paſtor who underſtands that the blood of his ſheep muſt be required at his hands, and that their ſalvation becomes a part of his owne, amazed with ſo many threats uttered by the Prophets againſt the bad Paſtors, who abandon their flockes in time of neceſſity, he awakes his ſollicitude, he revives his courage, he expoſeth himſelfe to labour, and danger, inclining his heart to all the juſtifications of our Lord, for the retribution which he expects from him alone. Let us now obſerve how our Regulars behave themſelves, who are ſent unto this worke onely by delegation, by miſſion, of aſſiſtance by extraordinary commiſsion, as troopes of reliefe, and voluntary labourers. This laſt ſufficiently declares. Mercenarius autem fugit &amp;c. The hireling flyes, becauſe he is a hireling, &amp; hath no care of the the ſheep. So as if he do labor in feeding of them, his labour is but voluntary, &amp; mercenary, &amp; accordingly (as it often happens) moſt pittifully performed. For as the Regulars onely governe ſuch ſoules as of their owne election, without any obligation commit themſelves unto their conduct, ſo on their part have they the choyſe in this great harveſt, of what eares of corne they pleaſe, in this great draught of fiſhes, which they like beſt, caſting the reft
into the water, to ſend them back unto their proper Paſtors. In ſo much as the people doe make uſe of them ſo long as they pleaſe, ſo doe not they ſerve the perſons of the world, but ſo long, &amp; in ſuch ſort as they think beſt, the place of their reſidence being that which is conformable unto their liking, like unto wandring ſtars, (to uſe the phraſe of the Apoſtle) whoſe influences worke not ſo ſtrong impreſsions, forſomuch as they caſt not their beames, but by way of paſſage, whereas the ſixed ſtarrs are the ayme whereby all Mariners direct their Navigations. So this moſt learned &amp; holy Biſhop.
               Well then, underſtanding reader (Odi enim prophanum vulgar &amp; weceo) Thou ſeeſt what authors, how many, and of what quality, who all flouriſhed ſince the comming in of the Mendicants) have ſharpned both their tongues &amp; pens, againſt their diſordered and wicked lives. Whereas then ſome (&amp; thoſe not of vulgar apprehenſions) have taxed me of indiſcretion for inveighiug in my bookes againſt the faults of Eccleſiaſticall perſons, my ſelfe being of the ſame rank &amp; profeſsion, for my part I underſland not their language. For I have alwayes heard that the maintaining of pubſique errours in doctrine, &amp; not the refuting of them, the committing of manifeſt impieties, and not the reproving of them, to be ſcandalous. And the Apoſtle gave this charge unto Timothy: Peccantes coram omnibus argue, ut et caeteri timorem habeant, I. Timoth. 5. Such as ſin publickly reprove, that others may feare. Theſe men (I ſee) doe wiſh me much good, for they would have meo more wiſe, more learned, &amp; more vertuous then S. Bonaventure, then S. Ʋincent, then S. Anthony of Padua, then S. Richard of Dundalke, then Thomas Walſingham, then Lanſpergius, then Laurentius Inſtinianus, then Cardinall Bellarmine, then Petrus Camus, Biſhop of Bellay, then many others, who have laboured in this kind, and whom for brevityes ſake I am forced to omit. Might theſe then make to the life pictures of our deformed Regulats, with their black pencills of a deep reproofe, &amp; ſhall not I be permitted to draw one ſmall line in their tables? Shall theſe to the face of the world, &amp; in the eyes of this ſun, ſtrip &amp; whip the Friar at their pleaſure, &amp; ſhall not I be licenſed to lay on one ſingle laſh? Or is it
that they have received already their 40. ſtripes ſave one? Might theſe ſpirituall Phyſicians make deep inciſions, &amp; lance them with words more piercing then any two-edged ſword, &amp; may not I be allowed to rub their galled backs with one dramme of vinegar? Might theſe Prelars &amp; Prieſts thunder in every pulpit againſt their errors, &amp; abuſes, &amp; not ſo contented, leave their invectives in their workes &amp; monuments to be read of poſterity? Mene mutire nefas? And may not I utter one little word, but preſently I ſhall beſerved with a citation from the ſpirituall Court, the Court of conſcience? Nolite annunciate in Geth, neque annuncietis in compitis Aſcalon, &amp;c. O publiſh it not in Geth, nor preach it in the ſtreetes of Aſcalon, leſt peradventure the daughters of the Philiſtines do rejoyce, &amp; the daughters of the unci. cumciſed triumph. For Lord, who ſees not how miſtaken, &amp; miſapplyed that text is to the purpoſe that theſe men would draw it. Wiſt not David that the death of Saul &amp; Lonathas, &amp; that victory in which the Philiſtines prevayled againſt the houſe of Iſrael, could not be concealed from Goth, nor Aſcalon, or any other City, or habitation of the Churches enemies? But David the more emphatically to expreſſe his griefe in that deſolation &amp; heavineſſe of the ſynagogue, in the ſlaughter other Princes &amp; people, uſeth that manner of threane or lamentation, aggravating that dayes calamity in conſideration of the great content, joy, &amp; triumph that it would miniſter unto the Philiſtines their victorious enemyes.
               So let us never perſwade our ſelves, that our publique errors either in doctrine, or manners can be concealed from thoſe who are of a diverſe beliefe from us, neither theirs from our knowledge, ſo long as we live together in the ſame common-wealth, or border one upon another. I ſpeak of publick &amp; notorious exceſſ
                     •
                  s, for I never was of opinion that any perſonall or privat delict, the concealment whereof is neither prejudiciall unto the Church, Common-wealth, or a third perſon may be manifeſted or diſcloſed, to which doctrine all divines applaud, grounding the ſame upon divers texts of holy writ, among which this is one, Prov. 11. Qui ambulat fraudulenter, revelat arcana, qui autem fidelis eſt celat amici commiſſum. He who walkes fraudulently, reveales ſecrets; but he
that is faithfull conceales the fault of his friend. And in the Goſpell, Math. 18. Si peccaverit in to frater &amp;c. If thy brother ſhall offend fend thee, goe &amp; rebuke him between thee &amp; him alone &amp;c. See for this S. Thomas 22 2 ae. q. 68.1.3. &amp; q. 70.1.2. And in this ſence no donbt it was that Conſtant in the Great, that firſt Chriſtian Emperor, moſt Chriſtianly ſaid: That if he ſaw an Eccleſiaſticall man to doe what was indecent, or amiſſe, he would cover him with his purple robe, meaning he would ſo conceale his faults, as neither the delinquent ſhould receive diſhonour, nor the Church ſcandall thereby. As for manifeſt &amp; knowne offences, we heare what almighty God hath ſaid by his Prophet Eſay 58. Clama, neceſſes, quaſi tuba exalta vecem tuam &amp;c. Cry out &amp; ceaſe not, advance thy voyce like a Trumpet, declare unto my people their wickedneſſe, and unto the houſe of Iacob their offences: ſtill by his Prophets complaying of ſuch Paſtors, who like unto dumbe doggs either could not, or would not open againſt the manifeſt vices &amp; corruptions of thoſe to whom they were ſent. And the Apoſtle exhorteth his ſcholler Timothy as to exhort, intreat, and beſeech, ſo to blame, reprove, &amp; correct, &amp; that by his owne example, who ſo little feared the face of man, as to comply with his Apoſtleſhip, he would freely &amp; publickly reprehend ſuch as were manifeſt ſinners, &amp; eſpecially falſe teachers he would rouſe out of their dens, &amp; place the in the ſight of the ſun. So 2. Tim. 3. having made a long Catalogue of publique offences &amp; offenders, which then infeſted the Church, concludes, Et hos devita ex his enim ſunt &amp;c. And theſe avoyd. For of theſe there be who ruſh into mens houſes, &amp; lead away ſilly woemen into thraldome, loaden with ſins, &amp; drawne away with many deſires, alwayes learning, &amp; never attayning the knowledge of the truth &amp;c. And this not onely, or alwayes in generall, but ſometimes he would deſcend unto particulars, not ſparing to rebuke notorious ſinners by name. For example in the Chap, following. Demas hath for ſaken me, and is gone into Macedonia. Alexander the Copper-ſ
                        ••
                     yth hath ſhe Wed me much evill, our Lord will reward him according unto his Workes.
               
               And this I thought fit by way of an Apology to alledge in my defence, as well for this preſent Treatiſe now penned, as alſo for
ſuch other bookes, as I have heretofore written againſt the moſt knowne, &amp; notorious errors, &amp; abuſes of the Mendicants, eſpecially of this Country, and Kingdome, with which I will conclude this Chapter.
            
            
               
                  CAP. III. The power of the Scapular and Habit ever the ſoules in Purgatory.
               
                  IF bleſſednes be the end &amp; ſummum bonum of the reaſonable creature, conſiſting in the cleare viſion &amp; full fruition of the Creator, as our holy faith teacheth us. Two wayes after this life may a man be deprived of this bleſſed viſion thorough his owne default: Either eternally, which is a full ſeparation of the creature from the bleſſed viſion of God the Creator. Or a ſuſpenſion for ſome time. The former hath with it an abdication unto eternall puniſhment. Diſcedite à me maledicti in ignem aeternum. Depart from me ye curſed into hell fire. The ſecond hath onely a deputation unto the purging fire. Si cujus opus arſerit, detrimentum patietur: ipſe enius ſalvus erit ſic samen quaſi per ignem. If any mans worke burne, he ſhall ſuffer detriment, but himſelf ſhall be ſaved: yet ſo as by fire. Now if the doctrine of our Friars be good divinity, all matters of the ſoule after this life are moſt ſweetly accommodated. Firſt, for hell we have ſeen in the former. Chapter, the fire thereof quite extinguiſhed only by dying in the Carmelites Scapular, or the Franciſcans Habit, ſo as a ſoule furniſhed with either of thoſe commodityes, may ſay with the Poet:
Contempt aeque jacent, &amp; ſine luce faces.
               
               Now in this Chapter it is conſiderable whether they be not as forcible to quench the flames of Purgatory, which if they doe, I am labor in fine eſt. We have no more to do, but like Ioviall lads to paſſe our dayes Lucanicè in al pleaſures, &amp; delights, &amp; a fig for what may betide us after death. The ſecond doctrine then of our Carmelites is, that whoſoever dyes in the Scapular, he is not only freed ab incendie
                  
                  ſempiterne, from everlaſting fire, but alſo ab igne Purgateris, from the purging fire, at leftafrer his departure within eight dayes after incluſivè, &amp; that is the longeſt terme. For theſe be the words of their pretended indulgence (I ſay pretended) for undoubtedly it was never authorized by the See Apoſtolicke. The works are theſe, as they lye in that former abridgment of their priviledges cited in the beginning of this work, and falſty fathered upon Clement 7. Pope of that name. Die quo à ſaeculo hujuſmodi purgatorium acceſſerint ipſa virgo glorioſa Dei genitrix Maria ſabbatho ſequenti poſt illorum confratrum, ſeu religioſerum ac ſororum obitus viſitando, à poenis Purgatory hujuſmodi corum animas liberabit. By reaſon of this double Hujuſmodi, I confeſſe I am not ſo good a ſcholler, as to make any ſenſible conſtruction in Engliſh of theſe words, notwithſtanding that I have both learned my Grammar, &amp; have my ſelfe compoſed one. But yet we find by their ſermons, conferences, bookes,&amp; diſputations, that upon thoſe words the Friar Carmelites conclude that by the benefit of the Scapular, every ſoule that is adjudged unto Purgatory, whoſe body in death was invefted therewithall, by the miniſtery &amp; viſitation of the bleſſed virgin, &amp; under her conduct ſhalbe delivered thence the next ſaturday after their deceaſe, which (as I ſaid before) muſt needes be at the longeſt terme within eight dayes after death. Yet ſith the paines of Purgatory are ſo grievous, happy (ſay I) be they who dye on Friday night, becauſe the day following they ſhall be delivered thence. Now you muſt know that none have authority to give you this ſo holy a Scapolar, but ſuch a Prieſt as is of the Order of the Carmelites. They have alſo in the aforeſaid Treatiſe, another priviledge granted (as they ſay) by Pope Nicholas the 4. &amp; Pope Innocentius the 4. (but it is not to be believed, but rather what Thomas Walſingham writ, cited in the former chap. That to be a friar and a lyar is all one.) The priviledge is this: That whoſoever ſhall give an almes, or an nights lodging unto a Carmelite, ſhall have a plenary indulgence of all their ſins.
               Another priviledge they father upon Pope Vibanus 6. &amp; Nicholas 5. That whoſoever ſhall call the Friar Carm
                        •
                     lites, the brethren of the bleſſed virgin of mount Carmel, ſhall have ten yeares of Indulgence.
Here is no ambition to be called the brethren of the bleſſed Virgin the Mother of God, &amp; Vncles unto our Saviour? To the imitation of which ſpirituall kinred &amp; alliance, it is very like that our Ignatian Friars, or Ieſuites, albeit with more modeſty, doe call themſelves the fellowes or companions of our Saviour. And of all Friars, I know none of ſo conſpicuous deſcents, &amp; of ſo great a blood &amp; houſes, as theſe two, the Carmelites to be the brethten of the bleſſed Virgin: The Ignatians to be the companions of Ieſus. But why not? ſince our Saviour hath ſaid, Math. 12. Whoſoever ſhall doe the will of my Father that is in Heaven, he is my brother, and ſiſter, and mother. Sith then our Saviour is contented to admit into his kinred ſuch as ſhal do the will of his Father without exception of perſons of what quility ſoever, from the Cedar to the Hyſſop, from the Pope to the Sexten, from the Prince to the Beggar. To what end are theſe reſtrictions? theſe ſingularityes of ſtiles &amp; titles importing a limitation, or rather a kind of an excluſion of their brethren from ſuch ſpirituall prerogatives, eſpecially our Saviour having left them to the generall extent of a Quieun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      fecerit voluntatem patris mei: Whoſoever ſhall doe the will of my Father, he is my brother, ſiſter, &amp; mother. For tell me, why ſhould not a cobler under a ſtall, or a poore woman ſelling her bunch of radiſh about the ſtreetes, who have a care to live in the feare of God, aſſume theſe ſtately &amp; honorable ſtiles, as well as either Carmelise; or Ieſuite? Albeit (I confeſſe) it would nothing become them ſo to do. Our Saviour bids us, when we have done our beſt endeavours, ſay we are unprofitble ſervants. The Pope calls him ſelfe ſervum ſervorum dei, the ſervant of Gods ſervants. The Publican is commended for not lifting his eyes to Heaven, but knocking his breſt, and calling himſelfe a ſinner. The Prodigall Child hold it too much to be called his fathers ſon. The invited Gueſt is commanded to take the loweſt place at the table. And we know who ſaid to the Apoſtles, contending which of them ſhould be the greateſt. Quicunque voluer is inter vos maior fieri, ſit veſter minister, &amp;c. Math. 23. He that would be the greateſt among you, he ſhall be your ſervant. And he that exalteth himſelfe ſhalbe humbled, and he that humbleth himſelfe ſhalbe exalted.
               
               And albeit it pleaſeth our Saviour ſometimes to grace his followers with high ſtiles, and termes full of love &amp; honour, as he who knoweth the worth and merit of all his ſervants: as for example, to call them his friends, his brethren, his fellow-heires, his children, his diſciples, his ſervants. Yet it becomes not poore ſilly &amp; wretched man, who either knowes his own miſery in this valley of teares or is more miſerable in being ignorant thereof, to approach nearer unto his Creator, then the Portall of Pulvis &amp; cinis. Shall I ſpeake unto my Lord being but duſt &amp; aſhes? not knowing whether in this life he be worthy of love, or hatred, a veſſell of honour or diſhonour, but that whatſoever good he hath, is by grace from Heaven, &amp; not of himſelfe.
               And ſo much for the power of the Carmelites Scapular in matters of Purgatory. The ſumme of all whoſe doctrine in this point is: That the bleſſed Virgin the Mother of God, deſcends from Heaven every Saturday (but whether before noone or after, it is uncertaine) to deliver all ſuch as have dyed in the Scapular the week before. The occaſion of which ſuppoſed priviledge (as far as I can conjecture) was this: The Carmelite Friars hearing that the Franeiſcans did preach and publiſh unto the people: That S. Francis every yeare upon his feaſt day (which falls upon the 4. of Octob.) comes down from Heaven, and deſcending into Purgatory, carryeth away with him all thoſe who the yeare before dyed in his habit, and deſiring by all meanes that their Scapular might not be inferiour, but rather in greater requeſt &amp; eſtimation then the habit, &amp; thinking a yeare too long a time for poore ſoules to be tormented in thoſe flames, they obtained a priviledge (as they tell us, but moſt falſly) from the Sea Apoſtolick, that their ſcapulariſts ſhould ſtay no longer then a week at the moſt, but every Saturday ſhould be delivered thence. So as I do not a little wonder wherfore the Friars of S. Francis Order in Limericke of late, ſhould with ſo great vehemency, and as it were with a new heat, ſet on foot that former pre
                     •
                  ended indult of a yearely manumiſſion upon S. Francis day of all ſuch as dyed in their habit be
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  e. The particulars of which hiſtory, curious Reader, if thou deſire to under ſtand, I will not ſpare to impart unto thee, and that in ſuch manne
as was related unto me by them who were eye, and c
                     •
                  re-witneſſes of the whole buſineſſe, with all the circumſtances thereunto belonging.
               
                  Philip Horrow Pariſh Prieſt of S. Iohn Baptists in the South part of Limerick, ſecond Vicar generall unto the Biſhop of Limericke, whoſe name is Ri. Arthure, preached upon S. Francis his day, the 4 of October, namely 1633, in the houſe of the Franciſcans, and among many other prayſes of S. Francis, ſaid, that the Saint did every S. Francis day deſcend from heaven to Purgatory, and deliver from thence all the ſoules of ſuch as have taken S. Francis habit in their life-time. This was contradicted by the Dominitans and the Ieſuites of Limericke, &amp; thereupon the Vicar generall Philip Horrow was called before the Biſhop, &amp; before his adverſaryes, &amp; being queſtioned about that doctrine which he had delivered, He ſaid, for his part he did not firmely believe it, but yet he cited two authors of the Franciſcans for it. Theſe were Onuphrins Mariſcal, &amp; Bartholomens Piſanus, whereupon he and his adverſaryes were reconeiled, &amp; by the Biſhop enjoyned not to ſpeak any more of that opinion. But the Guardian of the Franciſcans in Limericke Friar Francis Wolf hearing this, prepared himſelfe to preach of that ſubject on the 29, of December laſt, which is the Sonday infra oc
                        •
                     avan
                        •
                      Nativitatis Domini, but the Biſhop hearing therof (being moſt vigilant &amp; carefull of the peace &amp; concord of his flock) ſent his Arch-deacon Father Iordan Bourk, &amp; Father William Sauvegan his Chantor firſt to intreat the ſaid Guardian, not to ſpeak any word of that controverſie, &amp; next to command him not to preach thereof. The which meſſage they delivered unto the ſaid Guardian upon Saturday night before his Sermon, and he with ſome coloured ſpeech made them believe he would obey: yet the next morning, he preached the ſame opinion with great vehemency, &amp; cum ſale mordicante againſt the other Regulars. Heereupon the Biſhop called all his Clergy of the Citty, and the Regulars together, the 15. of Ian. very late at night, &amp; there the Regulars, eſpecially Friar Terence O Brian, Prior of the Dominicans, in Limerick, and Friar William Crah, ſuperiour of the Ieſuites alſo in Limerick, accuſed the ſaid Guardian of the Franciſcans, aſwell
for that opinion, as alſo for his unſeemely language againſt others that gainſayd that doctrine, whereupon the ſaid Guardian, after ſome frivolous excuſes given by him, was commaunded by the Biſhop, not to preach any more within his Dioceſſe, without his eſpeciall licenſe. He cited no moe Authors for the ſame opinion but thoſe which were cited by the Vicar Philip Horrow.
               
               And thus have you the true relation of ſuch troubles as hapned among our Church-men of Limerick this laſt Winter about the priviledges of the Franciſcan habit, in which as in a map, you firſt behold the venters &amp; broachers of falſe doctrines in the perſon of the Vicar general, &amp; the Guardian of the Franciſcans. In the ſecond place is preſented unto you the office of a good Paſtor, &amp; the carefull performance of his duty in the Biſh. of the Dioceſſe. Thirdly you are to obſerve the còmendable obedience of the Vicar general unto his Ordinary, being admoniſhed of his fault. Fourthly you may note &amp; deteſt the intollerable pride &amp; ſchiſmaticall diſobedience of Friar Francis Wolfe, Guardian of the Franciſcans, who being praadmoniſhed by the Dioceſan not to preach ſuch doctrins; and counterſayting a faygned obedience, did notwithſtanding tranſgreſſe his commandement, to the notable ſcandall of Gods Church, &amp; the ruine of his own conſcience. Laſtly you may obſerve ſome laudable oppoſition made againſterror, &amp; falſe doctrin, by the accuſation of the Prior of the Dominicans, and the ſuperiour of the Ieſuites.
               
               Now I would know of our Friars, and eſpecially of Friar Francis Wolf Guardian of the Franciſcans of Limericke, what priviledge or indult they have from the Pope to preach ſuch doctrines as are inhibited them by the Biſhop in whoſe Dioceſſe they live, contrary to the decree of the Councell of Trent, ſeſſ. 5. cap. 2. Si vero. And both the rule of S. Francis cap. 9. and the aforeſaid Councell forbidding them at all to preach contradicente Epiſcopo, the Biſhop not giving way thereunto, ſeſſ. 24. cap. 4. But experience from time to time hath taught us, that they be too violent and headſtrong to be ruled by any Church law. Neither let the Reverend Biſhop of Limericke be troubled with their diſobedience unto him. For the Pope himſelfe ſhall not be able to commaund them
further then ſtands with their own good liking. To which purpoſe, it ſhall not be from the purpoſe to ſet down what that reverend, pious, and learned Biſhop of Bellay in France, Iohannes Petrus Camus obſerved at his being in Rome in the late dayes of Clement 1. And I will uſe his own words as they lye in the 32. Cap. of his booke De operibus Monachorum.
               
               Being on a time in Rome in the dayes of Pope Clement 8. whoſe memory is in benediction, and in a ſweet odour of ſanctity, for his verity, equity, and manſuetude, who being much urged, (not to ſay importuned) with many queſtions and diſputes touching the Habits and Beards of Cloyſter-men, he had a reſolution to bring unto the raſor, and unto the hood, all ſuch as call themſelves Regulars, and who live in communityes, &amp; obſerve Monaſtick vowes. This gave ſuch an Alarme to them who had taken the Cap &amp; the Habit of ſecular Clergy, the Ieſuites, and Theatines, &amp; an other ſort who had made choyce for their character the long Beard, I mean the Conventualls, Carthufians, and Capuchins, that it was much to be feared, that the good Pope (whoſe name is in veneration thorough all Chriſtianity) had not felt the effect of thoſe mortall Litanyes, with which ſome Monkes doe threaten thoſe who are not favourable unto them. For ſure had he but touched the checkes of the one with the razor, &amp; had thruſt the heads of the other into an hood, he had tryed their reſignation &amp; obedience to the quick. but to avoyde troubles, &amp; jealouſies, the good Pope held it better to let that buſineſſe ſleep, then to taſt the humours of his froward &amp; diſcontented children. So the Biſhop.
               But of much more terrible conſequence was that other caſe which hapned in the ſame moſt bleſſed Popes dayes, my ſelfe being then in Spaine, in Sevil of Andaluſia, about the yeare 1600, for Pope Clement 8. being to determine the Controverſy De Anxili
                        •
                     s, ſo long debated, and yet depending undecided twixt the Dominicans and the Ieſuites. The Ieſuites to give a diſturbance to that work, &amp; to caſt it quite from off the Hingells (leſt it ſhould be judged againſt themſelves) cauſe it to be diſputed thorough all their Colledges of Spaine &amp; Portugall, and that in printed and publick concluſions. Quod non erat de fids: Quod Clement Papa octa
                     
                        •••
                     
                  
                  
                  cra
                        •
                      caput Eccleſiae: That it was no point of faith, That Pope Clement 8. was head of the Church. And becauſe the Spaniards in their diſputes make uſe of their owne language, yea much more then of the Latin: and there being many Cavallero's, aed men of great faſhion then preſent, as well as of the vulgar, according to the manner of ſolemne diſputations, there went a tumultuous buz among the Laity in their meetings and converſations, Qu
                        •
                      Diabolo, El ſanto padre no es Cabeza de Igleſia? What the di
                     •
                  ell, is not the holy Father the Head of the Church? So as the Inquiſition held it neceſſary under paine of Cenſures, to inhibit thoſe queſtions and diſputes. And in truth the good old Pope fearing by ſuch diſputations, to be diſputed out of his chayre, was contented to ſurceaſe from any further proceſſe in that aſſayre.
            
            
               
                  CAP. IV. That the Regulars of this Kingdome are neither Roman Catholiques, Protestants, nor good Subjects, and therefore neither by the Church nor commonwealth to be permitted to live among them.
               
                  FIrſt that the Regulars are no Roman Catholiques, it may appeare by what hath already bin diſputed in the matter of the Habit, Scapular, and the Luiſſian Faſt, aſcribing ſalvation unto them, contrary to the faith of holy Church, beſides the maintenance of the Eleven Propoſitions, of which they have bin both convicted &amp; judged in their booke lately made by Edmundus Vrſulanus, cenſured &amp; condemned at Rome, contrary to which cenſure the ſaid book is allowed &amp; approved of by all the Friars of this Kingdome. And for ſo much as the Friars are not conformable on the other ſide unto the Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in this Kingdome. And I could never learne that his Majeſty was pleaſed to allow of any third Religion within his Dominions, I ſay, more then the approbation of the Proteſtants, and
ſome gratious tolleration of the Catholicke, no more then he is pleaſed to allow of Arianiſme, Neſtorianiſme, Pelagianiſme, and the like hereſies. In conſideration whereof whenſoever it may ſeem good unto the King and the State, what cauſe can be imagined, why the Friars of this Kingdome may not be proſequuted as moſt peſtilent hereticks and ſeducers? Neither is there want of preſidents and examples in the Proteſtant Churches, of ſuch proceedings againſt infamous heretickes. For ſo in Berne of Helvetia was Valentinus Gentilis an Italian heretick adjudged unto the fire. Servetus a Spaniard in Geneva. In the dayes of Queen Elizabeth, Hacket &amp; Legat executed in London for Arianiſme: others in Norwich, Penry hanged at Th
                        ••
                     ford. Greenwood and Bar
                        •
                     
                   in Lincolnes-Inn-fields; all of them for maintayning and publiſhing of Browniſme. But if it bee thought better to thoſe that ſit at the helme of Government to ſhew more mercy, then may they bee ſent out into exile after their predeceſſors thoſe falſe Monkes Prebinus, Milianus, Probinianus, who by Pelagius the Pope were baniſhed into remote Ilands, as we read in Gratians decres. 16. q. 1. Prebinum. For one way or other it ſeemes neceſſary that the Kingdome ſhould be purged of them, who to enrich themſelves and make-up their Monarchy, regard not what ſlyding ſtayres they make the people to deſcend from Chriſtianity, to Atheiſme. And albeit the beginnings have bin marvailouſly neglected, and neither the cookarice cruſhed in the egg, nor theſe Harpyes in their firſt hatch, yet better late then never, before they grow to a ſtronger head, and not ſo eaſie to be ſuppreſſed. And ſo much briefly for the exorbitant hereſies of our Regulars, condemned both by the Catholick and Proteſtant, by which ſeparation from both, they have framed a new no. Church unto themſelves, worthy no where to be admitted.
               In the ſecond and laſt place I am to prove according unto my promiſe, That the Friars of this Kingdome are no good ſubjects, &amp; ſo alſo in that reſpect rather deſerving puniſhment, then either favour or protection from the State under which they live. And ſo I argue. In thoſe better and more religious times of our Anceſtors, and when the Catholick faith did moſt flouriſh in Great Britaine,
                  
                  ta
                        •
                     ne, and the Iles adjacent, Cùm terra 
                        •
                     rat unius labij, when our Kings, Biſhops, Nobles, and Commons were all of one heart and lipp in the worſhip and ſervice of God; when the Canons, Lawes, and beheſts of holy-Church were in moſt rigorous obſervance, yet even then and in thoſe dayes, no Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Prelate took upon him, or might by vertue of any Eccleſiaſticall calling or dignity, to baniſh either out of the Land, or any one diſtrict Diocceſſe, or County, any of the Kings ſubjects of what calling ſo ever, or for what cauſe ſo ever. And albeit Metropolitans, Biſhops, Arch deacons, &amp; other Prelats were of as great power, &amp; as ample juriſdiction in thoſe times, as any of their ſucceſſours have been ſince; yet notwithſtanding all ſuites againſt eccleſiaſticall perſons, of what quality or degree ſoever, in civill and ſecular cauſes, as debts, rents, revenewes, leaſes, inheritances, and the like, were both commenced &amp; determined in the Kings temporall Courts, &amp; not at all in the Biſhops Conſiſtoryes, as appeareth both by the ancient Lawes of theſe Kingdomes, &amp; the conſent of the learned profeſſours thereof, who all with one voyce, as well Catholickes as Proteſtants, doe at this day agree in the premiſes.
               Notwithſtanding all this, our new titulary Biſhops, eſpecially ſo many of them as are ſent unto us out of the Friaryes beyondſeas, together with the whole Regulariſm
                     •
                   of this Kingdome, doe ſtoutly maintaine, both by doctrine &amp; practice the contrary. Firſt, that they have power to baniſh; if they bee Arch-biſhops, out of their Provinces; if Biſhops, from out their Dioceſes, not only for offences, but even ad nutum, &amp; indicta cauſa, at their own will and pleaſure, without either examination or determination of cauſe, any of the Kings ſubjects, aſwell of the temporall, as eccleſiaſticall eſtare. Secondly, they teach, &amp; practically maintaine, that whenſoever the Defendant is a Clergy man, not only in eccleſiaſticall 
                     •
                  anſes; but as well in temporall &amp; civill, as debts, morgages, leaſes, rents, &amp;c. they are to be impleaded before the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, in which they live, &amp; not in any of the Kings Courts at all. In defence and juſtification of both which paradoxes, Tho. Flemwing, titulary Archb. of Dub in, ſtiffly perſiſting, (for that indeed within the Dioceſe of Duklin, he had practiſed both thoſe points)
notwithſtanding that his errour was with much mildues and learning, both out of the Canon, &amp; Common-Lawes opened unto him by one of his Majeſties Privy Councell, yet can he not to this day be reclaymed, but remaines moſt wilfull &amp; obſtinat in his former practiſed error. His Friars perſwading him to offer himſelfe a ſacrifice in defence thereof, laying an imputation upon all ſuch as complaine of this his tyranny, that they ſeek his bloud. Not doubting but one way or other to prevayle in this his uſurpation, notwithſtanding what oppoſition ſoever of the higher powers againſt him.
               And like unto this our Archbiſhop Flemming is another Franciſcan, the preſent Biſhop of Downe, of the houſe of Maggennes, a man in his behaviour more like an Italian Bannito, or ſome deboſht Ruffian, then a ſacred Biſhop, as may well be ſeen by his fantaſtique acouſtrements coupled to his Vlti
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   manners, having his locks hanging over his rich face, &amp; down his ſhoulders, even to the center of his back, ſtrouting himſelfe at every third word upon his tip-toes, as if he were angry at his parents for not making him a foot longer. And if any think my pen hath wronged him in this rough draught, let them make a pilgrimage unto him, he lives not above two dayes journey from Dublin, &amp; if they find him not as I have preſented him, let them come unto me, &amp; tell me of it, &amp; I will congratulat with them his reformation. This Hugh Magennes tranſformed firſt into a Friar, &amp; after into a Biſhop, retaining ſtill the firſt ſavour &amp; ſeaſoning of the pot, meeting lately witha Clergy man of theſe parts, asked him: Now, what doth Cadde
                        •
                     
                   &amp; Harris? do they live ſtill in Dublin? Yes. Were I their Biſhop, concutiens illustre capus, (as if every haire of his head was able to tranſport them beyond the Aequinoctiall,) I would ſend them further off. O ne ſavi magne ſacerdos. by your favonr my Lord, Caddell &amp; Harris are civill men, &amp; as they be Catholique Prieſts, ſo are they the Kings liege ſubjects, &amp; may live in Dublin, or where elſe they think good, within his Majeſties Dominions, ſo long as it pleaſeth the State to permit them, being far frō yeelding to the new uſurped tyranny, which your Friar Biſhops have of late brought into this Kingdome, contrary both to the Common
&amp; Canon Law, as hath bin demonſtrated unto them, not only in my late Treatiſe againſt The. Flemming his Excommunucation, but ſince that again moſt learnedly vivâ voce in the Caſtle of Dublin, by ſuch as had the examination of the cauſe. Neither is it to be thought that his Majeſty will endure ſuch a diminution of his honour by any one Friar, or the whole pack of them together. In the mean time God help the poore Prieſts who live under the Friar Biſhops, to whom if they do not yeeld in theſe &amp; the like practiſes, they ſhall preſently heare. 
                     Ʋeteres migrate coloni: you ſhall no longer live in my Dioceſſe, which thunder-clap was firſt heard in Dublin, but afterward roared into other Dioceſſes, yea ſuch vexation they find (eſpecially Prieſts of the beſt parts &amp; deſeres) under the Friar Biſhops, as to redeem their vexation, &amp; to purchaſe their peace, they are contented to forſake their Pariſhes, &amp; poore entertainments, and to betake themſelves unto other Dioc
                     •
                  ſſes, where the Clergy-Biſhops governe, leaving all to the Friar, who defires to doe all, and have all. And for this cauſe is it, (together with ambition, and an unbridled luſt of domineering) that ſo many Friars at this day do hunt after Biſhopricks, as weare credibly informed both from Paris &amp; Rome, no fewer then eight of them, to the admiration of ſtrangers, &amp; deteſlation of all modeſt men, importuning the Pope to be made titulary Biſhops of this Kingdome, there being ſearce ſo many places vacant, which if they do obtaine, the utter ruine of the Clergy in thoſe Dioceſſes can not be prevented, whom they will not faile to ſupplant, &amp; to furniſh their places with Friars, each one of his own order, as we heare dayly to be practized in the next Dioceſſe of Kildare, whoſe Biſhop being a Dominican Friar, creates his Friars, Pariſh Prieſts, contrary to the Law of holy Church, and continued practice thereof till theſe times. But ſee the pollicy of this tyrant Biſhop, or rather Tyrones Biſhop of Kildare, for at Tyrones interceſſion was he nominated, (as himſelfe canno: deny) having firſt written unto the Pope, as is credibly reported, &amp; beleeved by us, that no Biſh. ſhould be named by his holineſſe in this Kingdome, but ſuch as by Tyrone from Flanders ſhould be commended unto him. I ſay, this Roſſ Magogean, titulary Biſhop of Kildare, in excuſe of making
his Friars Paſtors, &amp; Pariſh Prieſts, contrary unto the Lawes of the Chruch, tells ſuch as expoſtulate the matter with him, that of neceſſity he is inforced ſo to do, for that out of the body of the Clergy he wants Prieſts of ſufficiencie for thoſe places. O bleſſed God! having firſt diſcontented, baniſhed, wrangled, and clampered all Prieſts of worth out of his Dioceſſe, &amp; having firſt procured that deſolation, makes afterward his own fact an excuſe of his own wickedneſſe. Shall Machiavell ever be dead ſo long as this Friar is alive?
               To ſuch miſerable termes is the Clergy of this country brought, That if the Pope perſeveres as he hath begun, to ſend us either Biſhops made of Fryars, or of the Friars creatures, there is an end of the Secular Prieſthood, which is of Chriſts inſtitution, and hath continued in the Ch
                     •
                  rch ſince the Apoſtles times, till this unhappy tyranny of the Friars hath corrupted both the doctrin and government of the Church, &amp; hath turned all things topſy-turvy among us. If any deſire to know the names &amp; number of our preſent Friar Biſhops of this Kingdome, they be as follow: Them. Flemming aliàs Barnwell, aliàs White Archbiſhop of Dublin Franciſcan. Boethius Igan Biſhop of Elfin, Franciſcan. Hugh Magenues Biſhop of Downe, Franciſcan. Roſſ Magoghagan Biſhop of Kildare, Dominican. Patrick Cumberford Biſhop of Waterford, Auguſtin, which laſt is the only indifferent Friar Biſhop unto the Clergy, of all that ever yet were ſent into this Kingdome. Some others we have, who albeit they were elected out of the body of the Clergy, yet becauſe ſtanding upon their own feet, they were not able to reach the apple of Epiſcopall promotion, they mounted upon the Friars ſhoulders, &amp; by their alone meanes have obtained the ſame, and for that cauſe are litle more loving unto the Clergy, or leſſe beloved of the Friars then the former, holding it a point of gratitude, &amp; the leaſt kind of remuneration for ſo great a benefit, to be at the beck and command of that Friar, whether it be Wadding the Cordelier, or any other, by whoſe ſollicitation they received their nomination unto a Biſhop rick, bound ever after to tread in their ſteps, &amp; to run their courſes. But fure for my part I ſhould think the ſame Church-pollicy, which is practized
in Rome, in debarring Friars theſe 50. yeares &amp; upward from the Apoſtolicall Chaire, might bee obſerved thorough the whole Church, as beſt beſeeming the Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchy, &amp; the government thereof: I mean the Clergy to be governed by the Clergy, the Friars by the Friars, without making ſuch a mixture of governments, as we ſee at this day: one Dioceſſe ruled by a Clergy Biſhop, another by a Franciſcan, the third by a Dominican &amp;c. which is rather to lay a corner ſtone of diſcention, then any foundation of unity, to plant a ſeminary of diſcord &amp; contention, then a nurſery of peace &amp; concord, &amp; the ſame not only for the preſent, but even deſcending unto poſterity.
               For example in this Dioceſſe of Dublin we have for the preſent Thowas Flemming Archbiſh. a Friar by all meanes ſuppreſſing and perſequuting h
                     •
                  s poore Clergy, wearing out all the moſt auncient, &amp; ſu
                     •
                  ficient I'rieſts of his Dioceſſe; &amp; to the end he might with more facility at chieve his ends, he hath Iately procured a Bull frō 
                  Rome, the ground of this Buſt is, for that all benefices of this Kingdome, for want of due collation, are held to be in the lapſe, &amp; devolved thereby unto the gift of the Pope, by which is conferred unto him the right of patronage &amp; preſentation, of all the Benefices, Rectoryes, Vicaryes, Capellania's, yea not them only, but the collation of all Digaityes, places of Channons, Prebends, or what elſe belongs unto the Cathedrall, or Collegiat Churches, within his Dioceſſe, all at his diſpoſition, will, &amp; command, either to conferre, or to be vacant, as he doth the Dignityes of S. Patricks and Trinity Church, for feare of creating a Chapter, which one time or other might look into his game. Some Pariſhes he conferres (eſpecially upon his white diſciples in titulum, others, &amp; the moſt with amovibility ad nutum, to the end they may be more ſerviceable unto him. All to give a free ſcope &amp; an uncontrouleable licenſe unto his galloping Friars to commaund all, among whom there is not a Lay brother, who was but yeſterday an horſ
                     •
                  -boy, but will threaten the graveſt Prieſt of his Dioceſſe with a removeall from his place, if he diſtaſt him.
               And verily the preſent government of the Clergy in this, and ſuch Dioceſſes, as the Friar Biſhops do rule, makes me call to mind
that tyranny of the Danes, as well heere in Ireland as in England, to whoſe violence, not only the Republique in generall, but every private family was obnoxious, having their eſpialls and intelligencers in every place &amp; corner of the countrey, in ſo much as unto the baſeſt groome among them, for feare of his diſpleaſure, the honeſt ſubject was in ſuch thraldome, as he would be glad to give him the beſt place at his table, &amp; to feed him even ex adipe frumenti; with the beſt morſells he had, &amp; to call him at every word, My Lord Dane, whence it comes to paſſe, that in theſe dayes, we call by contraction every idle vagabond, a Lordan, borrowed I ſay, from that lubber of a Dane who was appointed to domineer in every mans houſe. Yea (if my memory faile me not, which is the firſt faculty of the mind that decayes in old-age) it is written in ſome of our Chronicles, that if an Engliſh man had been upon the midſt of a bridge, &amp; had ſeen a Dane make towards the ſame, though a musket ſhot before him, the Saxon would have returned back again, &amp; have left the bridge unto the Dane to have paſſed over. And even ſuch Lordanes for all the world be our Iriſh Friars, helping to devoure the fruits of the earth, for which moſt of them never ſwert in any lawfull vocation, abſolutely commaunding the whole houſholds in which they live, &amp; all too little to doe them ſervice, reſpect, &amp; honour. Thoſe that be houſe-keepers do more feelingly then my ſelfe underſtand the diſcommodities of the ſaucy and malapert carriage of theſe ſturdy beggars among them.
               It was on a time, when a Friar of S. Francis Order comming to a Gentle-mans houſe, ſeated within the ſmoak &amp; proſpect of Dublin &amp; finding the gate ſhuts for why? the Goodman of the houſe with all his family were ſet to dinner, neither was there written over the gate.
               Porta patens eſto nulli, clauderis honefto.
               The Friar ſeeing-himſelfe thus prevented, &amp; his ſtomack perſwading him that he was in extremeineceſſity of his dinner, he betook himſelf unto the hammer of the gave, &amp; ſo belaboured the broad payle, as I know not whether Brontes the great Smithy man, with his biggeſt hammer fetched from his right care, could lay weightier ſtroakes upon his anvill. But ſo it was, as the Friar found the
proverbe true. Venter non babet aures, the belly hath no cares; and no admiſſion or anſwer could he get, notwithſtanding that propter improbitatem, by reaſon of his importunity he perſwaded himſelfe, had they bin all in bed, &amp; faſt in ſleep, they would have riſen &amp; miniſtred unto him. And no queſtion but as his hands did labor at the hammer, ſo did many a cogitation hammer in his braines, ſometimes bewayling the declining of hoſpitality thorough the Kingdome, the hardneſſe of rich mens hearts: ſomtimes again bethinking him of the vertue of perſeverance, comforting himſelfe with theſe &amp; the like promiſes: Petite &amp; accipietis, pulſate &amp; aperietur vobis: Aske &amp; you ſhall receive, knock &amp; it ſhall be opened unto you. But nothing did more trouble the Friars mind, then when he fell into conſideration of that Legacy of S. Francis, written under his Image commonly at their altars. That in what place ſo ever his Friars ſhould be, they never ſhould want neceſſary food, or rayment, the truth of which Legacy he found his ſtomack now to call in queſtion. O how often did he examine the gates, whether the weather, or wormes, or time more conſuming then either wormes, or weather, had made any little windowes, by which he might eſpy ſome bleſſed body to paſſe over the baſe court within, but all in vaine, for aſſoone might hee have looked thorough the ribs of the Trojan horſe. What will you have of it? Laſa patientia ſit furor, wronged patience turnes into fury: the Friar gathers up a number of ſtones, as David did when hee went to let fly at Golias his head, though far bigger, for this Friar is alufly bouncing Cordilier, &amp; not ſuch a ſhrimpe as David was, theſe he throweth againſt the gates of Droncondran with many a vengeance upon all thoſe who keep their gates ſo cloſe ſhut againſt Friars: but alas, as Priams darts rebounded back when they arrived at Pirrhus his armor of proofe, accuſing the weak &amp; feeble arme of the thrower: So did the ſtones which Friar Iohn Preſton ſent againſt the aforeſaid gate, leaving ſome few dints of his doughty choller, but nothing which might relieve his hunger. At laſt the Friar all malecontent, betakes himſelfe unto his palfrey, and with a froward kind of patience, purſued the reſt of his journey. But time paſſing on with ſwift, though ſilent paſes, not long
after he meetes with old Iohn Bath, (whoſe ſoule God pardon,) he relates what a challenge he made him, what documents he gave him, among which I remember, this was one: What wiſt you, but that the beſt and deareſt friend you have might have bin at your gates at that houre? It is againſt the lawes of hoſpitality, &amp; the cuſtome of Ireland to ſhut their doores at meale time &amp;c, but betwixt us both, he either forgot to tell me, or I to demaund, what ſatiſfaction was made for that error. And now I wot well, what the Friar will ſay, or others for him: Alas Mr 
                  Harris, is this all you have to ſay againſt that ancient Guardian, and now a definitor of his Order. It ſeemes if you had worſe, it ſhould out. O no, I keep the reſt for my Booke De illustribus viris &amp; fuminis S. Franciſci per Hibernian, which I hope ere long ſhall ſee the light, If they amend not. And now betaking my ſelfe unto a more ſerious diſcourſe, I will conclude this Chapter.
            
            
               
                  CAP. V. Whether it be true Martyrdome to dye in defenes of the two former Tenents, held both in Theory and Practiſe by our Archbiſhop Tho. Flemming, and his Friars.
               
                  MVch doth our Archb. Flemming glory, that in and for the defence of the libertyes of the Church, he is perſequuted both of the State, &amp; ſome of his own profeſſion: But for his part, as they ſeek his bloud, ſo is he moſt ready and willing with S. Thomas of Canterbury, for the immunityes &amp; priviledges of the Church, to lay down his life, that ſo he may aſpire unto the glorious Crown of Martyrdome, And ſure if the Pope &amp; Cardinals in Rome were as forward as he &amp; his Friars be here, I perſwede my ſelfe he would be canonized before his death, &amp; ſo be a ſecond S. Thomas. But then how a Martyr? There indeed would be the difficulty. And therefore the State may do well in the mean time to make him a Confeſſour; That is, to acknowledge
his fault, &amp; preſumption, in violating ſuch lawes, as both Church &amp; Common-wealth in all ages from our very cradle of Chriſtianity in theſe Kingdomes have maintained, conformable to the Law of God, &amp; fitteſt for government, as I have abundantly declared in my Book againſt the Archbiſhop Flemming his Excòmunication. And this I ſpeak in excuſe of his firſt error, the mother whereof had it bin iguorance, might by an humble ſubmiſſion bin made pardonable. For indeed Thomas Flemming was taken frō his Friary of Lovayn at the age of 30. years, &amp; ſo was ſuddenly advāced unto the ſecond Primacy of Ireland, humane negotiation of interpoſed mediators, Erigens e ſtercore pauperem, ut ſedeat cum principibus, cum principibus populi ſui: rayſing him from the dunghill, even to ſit with Princes, with the Princes of his people; to whom if that power which could in a moment elevat &amp; ſet him aloft, had alſo furniſhed him with parts befitting government, there had bin no cauſe of complaint. But the man was taken as he was, &amp; in a new mould could not now be caſt. A Friar he was, and to have a Friar Archbiſhop of Dublin was the ambition of all the Friars in Ireland, whom they preſumed, &amp; therein were not deceived, that he would ever ſmell of the firſt humour with which he was ſeaſoned. Notwithſtanding David taken from the flocks, &amp; from behind the bagged ewes, as himſelf confeſſeth, Pſal. 77. Suſtulit cum de gregibus, &amp; de poſt foetanies accepit cum: &amp; advanced unto the ſcepter of Iſrael, did not after look back, either to the Rams, or to the Ewes, or their yong ones, he left behind him, but as Salomon ſayth of a Wiſe man, he had alwayes his eyes in his head, he looked before him, forgetting what was paſt, endevouring to performe with that preſent eſtate to which he was called, having (I con feſſe) this advantage, that he who rayſed him, had both the power &amp; will to beſtow upon him the ſpirit of wiſdome, and all other giſts &amp; graces neceſſary for ſo high a calling. By which we may take knowledge by the way of that diſtinction: Inter voluntatems: boneplaniti &amp; permiſſionis handled by the Schoolmen, &amp; in particular by S. Tho. 1a. 2 ae qi 19. q.
               
               Now then Tho. Flemming by Gods permiſſion rayſed unto the ſecond See of Ireland at the age of 30. &amp; as it was determined by
his brethren &amp; Camerado's in the Friary of Lovaine, to extirpate the Clergy of the Dioceſſe of Dublin, &amp; in their place to bring in the Friars, a plot though not very ancient, yet before him invented by an VIſter Friar called Hugh Cavall, reſiding in Rome, &amp; deſigned by this preſent Pope 
                     Ʋrbanus 8. about tenne yeares agoe, Archbiſhop of Armagh, &amp; Primat of Ireland, &amp; to which purpoſe the aforeſald Hugh Cavall obtayned a Bull by moſt ſiniſter information, to make his Friars Pariſh Prieſts thorough the Dioceſſe of Armagh, but being prevented by death before he could pay his way, &amp; bid his friends farewell in Rome (albeit not two houres before his death he writ a letter unto the Pope, beſeeching him to nominat in his place Friar Rob. Chamberlaine, for ſo they call him, albeit a moſt Iriſh &amp; a tyronicall Friar of Lovaine) a ſucceſſour was deſigned in his place, a Prieſt of the Clergy called Hugh O Reyly the preſent Metropolitan of Armagh, &amp; Primat of all Ireland, who being a man not ſo wedded to Friarly plots againſt the Clergy (albeit in many reſpects obnoxious unto them) that policy of making Friars Paſtors, either ended in the firſt Hugh, or at leaſt hath taken a time of breathing in the ſecond Hugh.
               
               But our young Friar Flemming an Archbiſhop of 30. yeares, (though now neere 40.) nothing doubted to under-go that burden, which Milo himſelfe was ſcarce able to beare, &amp; in a prepoſterous zeale he would, yea that he would, without either Bull or Breve, baniſh the Secular Prieſts out of his Dioceſſe, which to performe, (litle ſeen in the Canons of the Church, &amp; leſſe in the common Lawes of England) not diſtinguiſhing the Keyes from the Sword, nor Regall power, from Epiſcopall juriſdiction, like a Preſter Iohn King of the Aethiopians, he preſently baniſheth 3. Prieſts, in his opinion the moſt fuſſicient of all his Dioceſſe, &amp; theſe living in Dublin, the mother Citty of all Ireland, not doubting but they once ſent away, all the reſt would be glad to kiſſe his hands, and to depart with his benediction. Vpon ſuch lofty termes ſtood our Archbiſhop, leaning his head upon the elbow of his Regulare brachium, his Friarly arme, an Arme, or rather an army always ready &amp; preſt to ſecond ſuch attempts, as Epiſcopall juriſdiction could not ſupport, yea to ſuch an over-weening preſumption did he and his
Friars at laſt arrive, relying upon their own conrage &amp; ſtrength, as they doubted not to complaine unto the temporall Magiſttate, &amp; bring their matter unto the Caſtle of Dublin, confident that the State would joyne with them, to the ratification of the baniſhment of the Prieſts, for which cauſe, after that a Lay-man had firſt broken they ce, &amp; made the way for them, there appeared plaintiffs William Malone, aliàs Morgan, alias Browne, Ieſuite; Iohn Preston Franciſcan: Patrick Brangan, &amp; Edmund Doyle a payre of Prieſts adhering unto the Friars faction, all theſe (I ſay) preſented themſelves before a grave Counſellour of State (for as then the Lord Deputy was not arrived) before him they accuſe Mr 
                  Doctor Caddell, &amp; my ſelfe Paul Harris, (for the third whoſe name is Doctor Cabil, had made his peace before with the Archbiſhop) they lay to our charge facta &amp; infecta, but all in the cloudes of generality, as thoſe uſually do, who meane to calumniat, &amp; to deceive, alledging that we were diſobedient, turbulent, ſeditious, facticus, of unquiet ſpirits, enemyes to peace. In concluſion, ſuch as did trouble all Iſrael, and therefore not to be tollerated, or longer endured. But it was their chance (good hap for us) to come before ſuch a Iudge as held it neceſſary to keep one eare for the Defendants, &amp; firſt to heare our anſwers before he condemned us, having underſtood that of the Morall Philoſopher, elegantly expreſſed by the Tragedian: Qui statuit aliquid, parte inandita altera; aquumlicet ſtatuerit, hand aquus fuit: who determines any thing, either party unheard, though what he determines be juſt, yet himſelfe is not juſt. Seneca in Medea. Wherefore it pleaſed that honourable Gentleman, after he had given audience unto our Adverſaryes, firſt to ſend for me Paul Harris, to underſtand what I could anſwer in my defence, not having in nine yeares before beene within the Caſtle-gates of Dublin, and next after hee ſent for Peter Caddell, who (as I take it) before that time had never ſeen the in fide of the Caſtle, and having heard our Apology, the Bells for the preſent were ſtayed, &amp; that great heat of haſty exile began to coole-Soon after this, was the happy arrivall of the preſent Lord Deputy, before whom (upon petition) both the Archbiſhop Flemming, &amp; we the Prieſts were commanded to appeare, and our grievances
propounded, were grationſly heard. And for that time diſmiſſed with grave advice, how to frame our obedience unto the Lawes of God &amp; the Kingdome, and the Archbiſhop Flemming in particular was moſt ſeriouſly required to reforme his errours, but he ſtanding upon his juſtification, &amp; wanting at that rime, (as it ſeemed unto us) the gift of utterance; &amp; expreſſion of himſelfe, whether not acquainted with ſuch an audience, or that he was not provided of his Anſwers, he deſired againe to be heard, and ſoone after by the Lord Deputy his command, we were remitted unto the hearing of the now Lord Biſhop of Derry, &amp; Sir George Radotiffe Knight, before whom all our cauſes were examened at full, according unto the Canons of the Church, and the ancient and immemorable Lawes of theſe Kingdomes. And the Archbiſhop Flemming convicted, partly by his own confeſſion, &amp; partly by witneſſe, that he had offended in theſe two points.
               
                  First in taking upon him to baniſh the Kings ſubjects by Epiſcopa
                        •
                      authority out of his Dioceſſe.
               
               
                  Secondly, in erecting a new Tribunall, and drawing all cauſes of Eceleſiasticall men, though meerely civill and temporall unto his Conſistory, there onely under paine of Excommunication to be heard and determined.
               
               Neither can the aforeſaid Thomas Flemming parallel his cauſe with S. Thomas of Canterbury, I appeale to all ſuch as have written the Legend of his life and death, whether it be Capgravius, the Breviary, or our Engliſh Chronicles, neither out of any other Hiſtory ſhall our Friars ever be able to prove, that in both, or either of thoſe two points, there was any controverſy at all betwixt King Henry the ſecond, and Thomas Becket. Thomas Flemming the Friar, being the firſt &amp; onely Biſhop, ſince the converſion of theſe Nations to Chriſtianity, that ever was bold to teach, maintaine, or practiſe the ſame, for which auſe if he ſhould ſuffer death (notwithſtanding all the ruiſſian-like boaſts of him, &amp; his Friars) hee ſhould dye a malefactor, &amp; not a martyr. But the little feare of any ſuch puniſhment to befall him, cauſeth him &amp; his Fryats ſo to triumph over thoſe who to their power have, &amp; alwayes will endeavour to maintaine that harmony &amp; concord, which time out of
mind hath beene twixt the Lawes of the Kingdome, &amp; the Canons of holy Church. And verily our hope is in God, and next in thoſe to whoſe hands the Sword of Iuſtice is committed, that they will not ſee the Church in her ancient Lawes, the King in his honour, or the ſubject in his right any longer prejudiſed by ſuch our Circumcelliones &amp; wandring limitours, as are able by their buſie inſinuations, perſwaſions, negotiations, if they be no ſooner ſuppreſſed &amp;c. towards whom to uſe lenity would be but cruelty, and the ſeverity of Iuſtice the greateſt benefite of Mercy.
            
            
               
                  CAP. VI. An Apology of the Author for the ſharpneſſe of his stile.
               
                  SOme ſay, there is too much gall in my Inke, eſpecially writing againſt thoſe that be domestici fidei, of the houſhold of faith, who albeit they had wronged me, my friends, or the Clergy, yet ought not I to exceed moderamen incul patae tutela, the moderation of a faultleſſe defence, that is, ſo defending my ſelfe, as not unneceſſarily offending others, &amp;c.
               Alas, &amp; will not theſe men yet underſtand, that I write not at al againſt any of the Churches children or family, but only ſuch as S. Peter inveigheth againſt in his 2. Epiſt. 2. allwing, unſtable ſoules, having their hearts 
                        •
                     xe
                        •
                     ciſed with avarice, the children of male diction leaving the right way, have erred, following the way of Bal
                        •
                     am of Boſor, which loved the reward of iniquity, &amp;c. Such wandring ſtars of which S.Iude ſpeaketh, who retaine nothing but their erraticall motion, having loſt both light, heat &amp; influence. Such as S. Iohn in his firſt Epiſt. chap. 2, diſcovereth, ſaying: They went out from us, but they were not of us. Search the Scriptures, and tell me, were not the Prophets of the Old Teſtament ſharp, even to ſcoffing and bitter taunting againſt the falſe Prophets? Did not our bleffed Saviour in the Goſpell, reproying both the doctrine, &amp; lives of the Seribes and Phariſees eight times in one chapter, cryout: Vae vobis
                  
                  Scriba &amp; Phariſei hypocritae! Woe be to you, Scribes &amp; Phariſees hypocrites: calling them ſerpents, and generation of vipers. Read the Epiſtles of S. Paul &amp; the reſt of the Apoſtles unto the Churches, conſider what ſtile they uſed, againſt the enemies of the Faith which they planted, how edgy, how galling, how biting I Come down to the Fathers, peruſe S. Aug. againſt the Mantschees, Caleſtius or Iovinian, S. Hierom againſt Vigilantins, Helvidius, and Ruffinus &amp; tell me: Whether they bang them not, with a ſtile more ſtinging then a whip of Scorpions? Alas gentle reader. What I have brought in this, or any other of my bookes, is but ale, and cakes, to what the Fathers, and other champions of the Church, even to theſe times have written againſt the enemyes of our holy faith.
               But ſome will ſay, That all the Friars are not ſuch as I have reported them to be, for which cauſe I ought to have made a diſtinctiō twixt the good &amp; bad, the corne, &amp; chaff, the ſheep, &amp; wolves &amp;c. And not ſend them all to the devill together in one bagg, as I have done. For God forbid ſay theſe men, (&amp; then they thinke they ſpeak very wifely) but there be ſome good, holy, &amp; vertuous men among them, both orthodox in beliefe, &amp; irreprehenfible of life. No, by the rood (ſay I) not one, there is not a right believer among them, &amp; conſequently not a good liver: for if vertue and falle worſhip can walk together, then both Turk &amp; Iew may be good &amp; holy. I confeſſe there are indeed a number of ſmooth fellowes to be tound among the Regulars, who have nothing but Euge Obelle in their monthes, ſuch as can dexterouſly act G
                        ••
                     to the Paraſits part on every ſtage, prayſing what you prayſe, &amp; diſliking what you miſlike, who in the preſence, or in the procuring of a benefactor, ſi dixerit aſtuo, ſudant. If he, by whom they expect a benefit, ſhall ſay, he is very warme, the Friar will ſwear
                     •
                   by his hood, that for his own part he ſweates down-right, knowing that a benefactor is a moſt delicate piece, &amp; muſt be tenderly handled. I confeſſe alſo ſome of them to be very morall, &amp; in the outward man not to be reproved, and yet being infected with herefie, are farre from true piety. Neither heerein do they goe beyond Ari
                        •
                     s and thouſands of his ſect. What vice or corruption of manners can
be layd to the charge of Novatus, or his diſciples? Pelagius, Vigilantius, and many moe, whoſe lives we find little or nothing taxed by ſuch as in their writings have condemned them, yet were they moſt vile &amp; wretched heretiques notwithſtanding what morality or ſeeming holineſſe ſo ever appeared in their outward converſations according to that of S. Aug. in Pſal. 4. Vbi ſana fides non eſt non poteſt eſſe vera juſtitia: where there is not a ſound faith, there can be no true juſtice. And it hath bin the cuſtome of heretickes from time to time (obſerved by the Fathers) under the vaile of formall ſanctity to ſhadow their wicked doctrines. Now our Friars be of two ſorts, both naught, and both miſbelievers. Either the Inventors and publiſhers of thoſe damnable doctrines above refuted, or ſuch as being their diſciples do adhere unto them partakers of the ſame misbeliefe. For if I could find but one Friar among them, that would diſclay me thoſe errors, that would either write, or preach, or any way publiſh in his perambulations, the errors of his fellowes: Oh how I would ſtroke his head, and embrace him! how I would exempt him from the leaven, &amp; corruption of his fellowes, &amp; would glory in his converſion! But O fearefull is that ſaying of the Apoſtle S. Iohn in his ſecond Epiſtle ſpeaking of the doctrine of the Church. Si quis venit ad vos, &amp; hanc doctrinam non affert &amp;c. If any man come unto you, &amp; bring not this doctrine, receive him not into thy houſe, nor ſay, God ſave you, unto him. For he that ſayth unto him, God ſave you, (Note the conſenting unto others in ſin) communicateth with his wicked workes. Now experience teacheth us, that not only the learned Friar, but the unlearned, and the lay-brother: yea the more unlearned, the more zealous, itchy, &amp; buſie are they in divulging among the ignorant people theſe ſalvations of habits, &amp; ſcapulars, hawkes bells, and hobby-horſes. How then can the one be more excuſed then the other? Or why ſhould they not all bee put in one faggot, and ſent to the fire together?
               So much then for the Friar. But yet my ſcrupulous reader deſires to be further ſatisfyed, and that is in a ſecond point, demaunding as thus. How can you Paul Harris be excuſed for being ſo harſh in your writings, and ſo diſreſpective unto your Ordinary, as
may appeare by ſundry paſſages both of this, and other of your Bookes, eſpecially being a Prieſt of his Dioceſſe, &amp; living within the compaſſe of his juriſdiction. Ought not a good Prieſt with all reverence &amp; reſpect, both in his words and writings, to ſhew duty and obedience unto his Biſhop? according to that of S. Paul, Ohedite praepoſitis veſtris: Obey your ſuperiours and ſuch as be ſet over you. And S. Hierom ad Neopotianum. Esto ſubjectus Pontifici tuo, &amp; quaſi parentem animae tuae ama. Bee obedient unto thy Biſhop, and love him as the parent of thy ſoule.
               To which I anſwer. That indeed ſuch is the priviledge of Biſhops by the Lawes of holy Church, that none may either cenſure them, or publiſh &amp; declare them to be hereticks (ſpeaking of ſuch declaratiō as is intēded by the Canon but only the Pope, neither before ſuch declaration, according to the common opinion doth a Biſhop looſe his juriſdiction or the power of a Paſtor over his flock, or in any of his three Cenſures; Excommunication, Suſpenſion, or Interdiction. Yet notwithſtanding all this, if a Biſhop ſhould obſtinatly maintaine, and publiſh any doctrine condemned by the Church in a Generall Councell, the leaſt Prieſt in his Dioceſſe might be ſo bold to call him an heretick, &amp; both preach and write againſt him, for example of Arianiſme, Donatiſme, Pelagianiſme, &amp; the like, &amp; yet remaine ſubject to his juriſdiction notwithſtanding. For the voyce of the Church, which is the voyce of God, is to be firſt heard and obeyed, and to be preferred before any other. And it is the rule of S. Aug. Ser. 6. de verbis Domini. Vbi duo ſuperiores mandant oppoſita, inferiori non eſt obede
                        •
                     ndum. Where two ſuperiours, for example, a Generall Councell, and a Biſhop, command oppoſite things, the Inferiour is not to be obeyed. And conformable to this, is that concluſion of S. Thom. 2.2. q. 104.5. Subditiiu
                        ••
                     s tantummodo ſuperioribus ſuis obedire tenentur, in quibus ipſiſuis ſuperioribus ſubjiciuntur, &amp; in quibus ipſi ſuperiores ſublinior is poteſtatis praecepeo non adverſantur. Inferiours in ſuch things alone, are bound to obey their ſuperiours, in which they are ſubject unto their ſuperiours, and wherein thoſe their ſuperiours, goe not againſt the precept &amp; command of a power higher then is theirs. So S. Thom. And in the corps of the aforeſaid concluſion, he illuſtrateth the
ſame doctrine out of S. Aug. ſer. 6. de verbis Domini. by example of the Captaine, the Proconſull, the Generall, and God. Where neither the Captaine againſt the command of the Proconſull, nor the Proconſull againſt the precept of the Generall, nor the Generall againſt the command of God is to be obeyed by the ſubject.
               But now ex abundanti. What will you ſay? If The. Flemming Archbiſhop of Dublin did firſt exempt himſelfe from all power &amp; paſtorſhip over his Prieſt Paul Harris? Is Paul Harris then any longer his ſubject? Sure by the rule of Relatives: If he be not my Paſtor, I am no ſheep of his paſture, I have either forgotten my Logick, Orby the ſame rule &amp; reaſon, that he diſchargeth himſelf of all cure, care and command over me, he exempts me alſo from all obedience and ſubjection unto him. Reade then what followeth, witneſſed by the firmes, and ſubſcription of theſe two Reverend and grave Prieſts, both living at this day within the Dioceſſe of Dublin.
               
               
                  
                     Wee whoſe names are heere under ſubſcribed, doe testify: That in our preſence, Tho. Flemming Archbiſhop of Dublin did renounce all correſpondency either by word or writing with Paul Harris Priest, celling us plainly, that thence for ward be never would receive either letter or petition from him, or would meddle in any matter of his, for him, or against him: but wholly diſclaimed all juriſdiction and power over him, wiſhing us to ſignifie ſo much unto therefore ſaid Paul Harris, which accordingly wee did.
                     
                        
                           May 24. anno 1631.
                           
                        
                        PETER CADDELL Prieſt. WILLIAM SHER GOLD Prieſt.
                     
                  
               
               After this againe, two of his Friers having threatned violence unto my perſon: I ſent a petition unto Tho. Flemming Archbiſhop by the hands of two worſhipfull Aldermen my friends, beſeeching him that he would by his authority, and the Lawes of holy Church, provide for my ſecurity. His anſwer unto them was, That he would have nothing to doe with me in any cauſe whatſoever, which Aldermen will not refuſe at this day to iuſtify the ſame.
Laſtly, having certaine bookes detained from me by a Pariſh Prieſt, &amp; a Friar Carmelite, I ſent my complaint again unto him, by the hands of a Friar of his own order, (for unto his own preſence he would not admit me) whoſe name is Iohn Parry, but after hee underſtood than the petition came from me, he neither would read or touch it, but did grow into choller with the Friar for preſenting it unto him. Behold the equity, the mildneſſe, the longanimity of a Friar Biſhop, his charitable &amp; prudent government, his care of adminiſtring juſtice unto a Prieſt of his charge. But I was a ſtranger, &amp; muſt be ſtrangely uſed, &amp; in place of protection made a prey, not onely to the wild beaſts of the foreſt, but even unto the petulant and ſturdy rams of the flock; by all which it appeares that I may truly ſay &amp; complaine, as Almighty God did of the Ifra elites unto Samuel, 1. Reg. 8. No
                        ••
                     te abjecerant, ſed me. They have not caſt off thee; but me, that I ſhould not trule over them. I have not caſt off my Biſhop, or with-drawne my obedience from him, but he hath caſt off me: of which ſort of deſertion I perſwade my ſelfe he will not be able to alledge a preſident in the whole Church of God. Well, the Vine being thus forſaken of his ſtay, the ſheep deprived of the care of his ſhepheard, as if with Daniel I had bin throwne into the Lyons den. Lord, whoſe tongues were not untyed? whoſe teeth not ſharpned againſt me? Imo &amp; in me pſallebant qui bibebant vinum. Well, I then found by experience what formerly I had heard: That a man may live without father or mother, but not without Iuſtice. So then it hapned. As concerning my bookes unjuſtly detayned from me, no other remedy appearing, I repayred for juſtice unto the preſent Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of the Kings Bench, to him I addreſſed my petition. And by meanes of his honourable command, I recouered them out of the hands of the injuſt detayners. But what followes upon this. Verily as the Poets faigne, that in ſome ſtormes all the windes have blowne at one time, according to that, Vna curuſque, Notuſque ruunt, &amp;c. So now all the whole Regulariſme of this Kingdome from the foure corners thereof; Monke, Dominican, Franciſcan, Auguſtine, Carmelite, Capuchin; Ieſuit, with all their followers, God knowes what an hideous tempeſt they rayſe againſt one poore
Prieſt, how they rage, how they ſtorme? And now the Friar Thom, Flemming who before had diſclaymed me for a ſheep of his flock, &amp; would intermeddle in no cauſe of mine with me, or againſt me, begins to aſſume a-freſh his Epiſcopall juriſdiction over me, and divulgeth me both in publick and private aſſemblys, to be excommunicate, and why forſooth? for bringing the Prieſt Brangan by a warrant (in the cauſe of my bookes) before a ſecular Tribunall: Vpon this, no man hence forward muſt eat or drinke with Paul Harris, no man may converſe with him, no man muſt ſalute him, or bid God ſave him. For why? Incidit in canonem. He is fallen within the penalty of the Canon. Nay rather, Incidit in latrones, He fell into the hands of a company of the eves, who wounding him, and leaving him halfe dead, he had utterly periſhed, had not the good Samaritan taken compaſſion of him. Now albeit I have handled this matter in my late anſwer unto Thom. Flemming his Excommunication, yet for that this diſcourſe drawes me ſo aptly into the ſame controverſie (a point of ſuch debate at this day twixt the Clergy and the Regulars) it ſhall not be from the purpoſe to enlarge my ſelfe with ſome few additions, to what in my former bookes hath beene delivered upon this Argument, as in the Chap. following.
            
            
               
                  CAP. VII. The state of the Queſtion is this: Whether in theſe Kingdomes under the government of the King of Great Brittainy. A man conventing an Eccleſiasticall perſon in a cauſe meerely civill before the tempotall Magiſtrate, hath ipſo facto incurred Excom, De Iurc.
               
               
                  THe Biſhop, (I will not ſay) with all his Clerks, but with all his Friars maintaynes, the Artirmative. In confirmation wherof they all
                     •
                  dge thoſe known texts of the Canon and Councels, cap. ſivero lo. primo
                  
                     〈1 page missing〉
                  
                  
                  de ſont, excom. e, ſi Index leisus co tit. Lib. 6. in extr. Martim ad reprimendum, 11. q. 1. where it is ſaid that no Clarke may be convented before a ſecular judge either for cauſe civill, or criminall. So Concil. Chalcedonsan. 9. 
                     
                        •
                     dgathènſe can, 32. Carthag. 3. can. 9. &amp;c. Bulla cene.
               
               For anſwer herennto I ſay that thoſe and diverſe other texts out of the Canon may be alledged to that purpoſe. For I acknowledge (as in my booke unto the Excommunication) that regularly ſpeaking no ecclefiaſticall perſon may be convented, or empleaded before a temporall Iudge in any cauſe eccleſiaſticall, civill, or oriminall. Yet ſince humane lawes are not obligatory till ſuch time as they be received, according to that. Leges inſtitnuntur cum promulgantur, confirmantur, dum approbantur Diſtinct in iſtis § prox. Lawes are then ordayned when they are publiſhed, but confirmed, when they are approved, yea and being received, and approved, may not only by the Law-makers bee repealed, or by priviledge diſpenſed withall, but alſo by a contrary cuſtome abrogated, according to that Dilect. 4. de Arbitris, cap. 2. Extra. de Conſuetudinibus. Locorum conſuetudines ubirationabiles ſunt juri ſcripto derogare poſſunt. The cuſtomes of places being reaſonable may derogate from the law written, and ſuch is the doctrine of S. Aug. in his epiſtle ad Caſulanum cited by S. Tho. 1.2. q. 97. ar. 3. Mos populi Dei, &amp; inſtituta majorum prolege ſunt tenenda, &amp; ſicut prevaricatores legum divinarum, it a &amp; contemptores conſuetudinum eccleſiaſticarum coercendi ſunt. The cuſtome of Gods people, and the ordinances of our anceſtors are to be held for a law, and as the tranſgreſſors of divine lawes, ſo the contemners of eccleſiaſticall cuſtomes are to be puniſhed. They who deſire more reaſon and authority for the confirmation of this point, let them read the Angelicall Doctor, 1. 2. q. 97.3. Alſo 2.2. q. 79.2. and q. 100. 2. and it hath the conſent of all Divines.
               Firſt then ſince it appeareth by the Regiſters of ſpiritual courts, that eccleſiaſticall perſons from time to time have beene convented in caſes eccleſiaſticall before eccleſiaſticall Iudges, as in matter of doctrine, ſacraments, benefices, tents. &amp;c.
               And ſecondly ſince it appeareth by the Regiſters of the ſame
courts, to ſuch as will looke into them, that eccleſiaſticall perſons have uſually beene convented in cauſes criminall before the ſaid Tribunals, as felonies, rapes, murthers; &amp;c. and either found innocent cleered, or guilty puniſhed, and in crimes capitall degraded, and ſo delivered unto the ſecular arme.
               And thirdly ſince it doth not appeare by any Regiſter or other teſtimony to be produced for theſe thouſand yeares and upward, that any civill cauſe, as matter of lands. In heritances, debts, leaſes, ſales, rents, purchaſes, &amp;c. have beene ſued, or ſentenced in any court of Biſhops, Archdeacons, or their officialls, by vertue of any eccleſiaſticall power, or juriſdiction whatſoever. But of the contrary is manifeſt, and will well appeare by the records of the Kings Courts, by bookes of the common law, and their reports in every Kings raigne, that in the caſes above mentioned, both Biſhops, Prieſts, Abbots, Priors, Superiours of Convents, in behalfe of their ſubjects, and all ſorts of eccleſiaſticall perſons, both male, and female, have had their trialls in the aforeſaid caſes before the ſecular Tribunalls: (witneſſe both the Canoniſt, and the Common Lawyer) I ſay, theſe grounds conſidered, It is evident to any man of common ſence, and underſtanding, that either that Canon which in theſe civill actions drawes the plea unto the eccleſiaſticall court of Biſhops, or any other ſpirituall Iudges, was either in theſe kingdomes never received: or if it were at any time in obſervance, by cuſtome beyond all memory was abrogated. Neither neede wee to marvaile thereat, for ſo much: as there wants not examples as well as doctrines leading us thereunto.
               For firſt, not to ſpeake of the Canons of the late counſell of Trent. We ſee the Bull of Pius quintus de Cenſibus in few places beſides Italy, and Spaine, in viridi obſervantia, in due obſervance. And why? becauſe it is not received.
               What Canon or Law of the Church more generall, then that diparitas cultus derimit matrimonium. Difference of religion, that is where one party is a true beleever, the other an Infidell or hereti
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   diſſolveth matrimony. And yet Lib. 1. é 9. A
                        •
                     or. lib. 8. Mor. s. 11.
                        •
                     .5. 
                  Becann
                        •
                     
                   the Ieſuit tells us, that the Catholickes of Germany marrying with the Lutherans incurre no ſuch impediment, neither before nor after matrimony, And why?
Becauſe (ſaith he) that law of the Church was either among them never received, or if ſo, by contrary cuſtome aboliſhed.
               Againe Panor with Felinus in e, vniver ſitabis. As alſo Decius in e. dilectis num. 3. de Appell. tells us, that ſuch lay men as by command of the Eccleſiaſticall ludge ſhall torture thoſe whoſe perſons are priviledged from violence by that Canon, Si quir ſuadome diabola, &amp;c. or for correction and puniſhment of their offences, ſhall beat ſuch Monkes, or Friars with rods, ſtaves, or clubs, as well the eccleſiaſticall Iudge ſo commanding, as the lay perſons executing his ſentence, doe both of them incurre the Canon, and are excommunicated ipſo facto de Iure, And yet Graphius a grave writter, and a monke of S. Benets order in his deciſionibus aureislib. 2. cap. 49. excuſeth as well the one, as the other, the Iudge as the executioners, by reaſon of a contrary cuſtome practiſed in France and now of late brought into Italy, and maintaines this cuſtome contrary to the law, yea to be more reaſonable then the law it ſelfe, namely that men of the laity, rather then of the Glergy, ſhould be uſed as executioners in the aforeſaid caſes. Thoſe who deſire to ſet moe examples of this nature, let them read Sotus de Iure &amp; Iustitia, Suarez, or Leſſius of the ſame Argument.
               Now then to come home unto our caſe in hand, I meane, of civill cauſes commenced, pleaded, and determined in the Kings Courts, the defendants being as well eccleſiaſticall, as lay perſons in theſe Kingdomes of Britanny. May we not perſwade our ſelves that a cuſtome ſo univerſally received, and without interruption continued ſince the Converſion of the Saxons under Pope Gregory the great, and King Ethelbert of England, for the ſpace of a thouſand yeeres and upward, may not take place of the Canon that ſayth, Preiſts in all cauſes muſt be preſented before eccleſiaſticall Iudges. Cap. Qualiter de Iudicijs? eſpecially it being no leſſe a law, and a Canon of the Church (as hath beene before obſerved) That the cuſtomes of places being reaſonable, may derogate from the law written, Ext. de conſuetudinibus, declared above by ſome examples. Now then muſt I needes bee foreed to beleev
                     ••
                   that all our Kings, Biſhops, Nobles, Iudges, and Magiſtrates, by whoſe authority Eccleſiaſticall perſons were convented in civill cauſes before
ſecular Tribunals for a thouſand yeares and upward, did all live and dye excommunicated, throwne out of the Church, as periſhed members, without hope of ſalvation, when as among our Engliſh Kings themſelves, ſixe of them were canonized Saints, of which honor no other kingdome of the earth can glory, namely, King Oſwald, Etheldred, Edmund, Richa
                        •
                     d, Edgar and Edward the Confeſſour, many Biſhops, as S. Auguſtine, S. Anſelme, Dunſta
                        •
                     , Thomas all Archbiſhops of Canterbury, Richard of Yorke, Cutbe
                        •
                     t of Dureſme, Thomas of Hereford, &amp;c. Alas while theſe and the reſt of our country men were bound in the ſetters of Excommunication, where were our gray and blacke Friars? and the other zealous Regulars, whoſe parts it was at the leaſt after their arrivellto have anmoniſhed both prince, and people of their errors, to have preached and publiſhed bookes, condemning that practiſe, ſo co
                     •
                  ary to the lawes (as theſe maintaine) of holy Church, was the Pope and Roman court alſo aſleepe, for ſo many ages? and would not enforme their ſpirituall children of ſo great a violation of the Canon had they miſliked thereof? Nay rather is it not the univerſall conſent of all divines, together with the Canon it ſelfe. That the permiſſion of the Pope in any Church law, ſeeing the ſame either from the beginning not to be obſerved, or by contrary cuſtome antiquated, and notwithſtanding is ſilent, and makes no oppoſition thereunto excuſeth the ſubject from ſin, as preſumed to approve and allow of the ſaid practiſe. See for this glan cap. in iſt is §. leges diſt. 4. &amp; in c. de treu. &amp; pace, &amp; in cap. cum multi 15. q. ult.
               
               For ſo much then, as it is certaine, that as well eccleſiaſticall as ſecular ſuperiours may oblige their ſubjects (albeit never ſo unwilling) to obey their iuſt lawes, ſo often then as they ſee the ſame lawes not to be obſerved, and paſſe it over in ſilence, they ſieme thereby contented therewithall, and ſuch ſilence, and taciturnity of the Law-giver may by the ſubiect according to the former rules be expounded a full conſent and approbation of his practiſe. Adde hereunto the obſervation of a late Engliſh Franciſcan, whoſe true name I underſtand is Dampart, and his uſurped Franciſcus à ſincta Clara, in his late booke Deus, Natura, Gratia, in which as my country man Edmund Bunny laboured in his treatiſe tending
to Pacification, to reconcile the Roman Catholiques to the Proteſtant profeſſion. So this Friar of the contrary, by his gloſſes and paraphraſticall expoſitions, labours to draw the Articles of the engliſh confeſſion, to the Catholicke and Roman doctrines. But let the Friar wring, and wreſt till he be weary, he ſhewes himſelfe but a time ſerver, a ſlatterer, and a meere Alchimiſt, adulterating both the doctrine of them, and us, and ſeeking to pleaſe both, (a inſt reward for ſuch a worke) contenteth neither, of whom it may be ſaid, as of the dead ſerpent ſtretched all along upon the graſſe. Amo ſic vixiſſe oportuit, yea ſo thou ſhouldeſt have lived. The ſerpent all his life long lives crooked, onely after death is ſtraight, ſo are many at this day both in their lives and doctrines very crooked, onely death teacheth them how they ought to have lived themſelves, and how to have taught others, to the example of the Apoſtle, 2. Cor. 2. Non enim ſumus ſicut plurimi adulterantes verbum Dei, ſed ex ſinceritate, &amp;c. For we are not as very many adulterating the word of God, but of ſincerity, and as of God, before God in Chriſt we ſpeake.
               Well I muſt not forget for all my digreſſió wherefore I brought the Friar upon the ſtage namely for a teſtimony againſt his fellow Triars of this kingdome to ſhew how unlike to untuned Virginalis their wires doe jangle: theſe maintaining that civill actions againſt a Prieſt muſt be heard, and determined in the Biſhops conſitory, the Engliſh Friar in the Kings courts, for which he produceth his authors. His words are as follow in his paraphraſe upon the 27. article, Confeſſ. Anglicana. Regibus autem nostris furſſe ſic eonceſſum jus nominand
                        •
                     , &amp; providendi, de beneficys teſtatur poſt alios Harp
                        •
                     feldius ſeculo 14 furſſe etiam aliam conſuct
                        ••
                     dinem ex privilegio ort am immemorialem cauſas Clericorum cognoſcendi, patet ex deciſione Rotae, 804. ut communiter citatur. To our Kings was granted the right of nomination, and proviſion of benefices, as after others witneſſeth Harpſfeild in the 14. age. As alſo another cuſtome time out of minde ſprung from a priviledge of taking knowledge of the cauſes of Clergy men, as appeareth by the deciſion of the Rota, as it is commonly cited. So the Engliſh Friar. This Do. Harpſfeild, as I take it, was Archdeacon of Canterbury in Queene Mary
                  her dayes, and continued the eccleſiaſticall hiſtory of England frō Venerable Bode his time to his owne. Deciſiones Rota are the very life, and quinteſſence of the Canon law, ſo called from a known office in Rome called the Rota. But neither of theſe bookes are with me, for which I uſe the Friars quotation.
               And now the infirmity of my body not permitting me to proceede further, which for the ſpace of theſe 2. moneths hath much afflicted me, and dayly encreaſing upon me, I am forced thus abruptly to breake off rather then to make an end. Beſeeching almighty God of his infinite mercy to grant me, and all my Adverſaryes, and all thoſe who profeſſe the name of Ieſus Chriſt to live and dye in true faith, hope, and charity. And ſo hoping to ſee the good things of our Lord in the land of the living, I take my leave of the world.
               
                  Mundus non mundar, ſed mundus polluit. Ergo
                  Qui manet in mundo, Quomodo mundus erit!
               
               But how truly may I ſay with old Tobias, Great art thou, O Lord, who doſt wound and heale, who brings unto the gates of death, and backe againe, Tob. 13. And ſo while yet we have time, operemnt bonum ad omnes, let us do good to all, eſpecially to the domeſtiques of faith, as the Apoſtle adviceth us. It being the office of a good paſtor, as well to ſeeke the ſtray ſheepe, as to feede the ninety and nine.
            
            
               
                  CAP. VIII. An Objection anſwered.
               
                  THere remaines then a difficulty to bee removed, for ſome will well allow of my precedent diſcourſe, were it not for one blocke which lyes in their way, confeſſing indeede, that in all cauſes meerely civill Clarkes were anciently empleaded in the Kings temporall courts. Neither (ſay
they) was this to be miſliked, ſo long as theſe kingdomes did ſtand conſtan
                     •
                   in the profeſſion of the Catholique and Roman religion, but fince they have declined therefrom; and that the Magiſtrates are now of an other opinion, and profeſſion in the ſervice of God, then in thoſe times they were. That of the Apoſtle ſeemes to take place writing to the Corinthians who having received the law of our Saviour, did notwithſtanding in their wordly controverſies draw one another unto the heathen tribunals, Sic nonest inter vos ſapiens quiſquam? &amp;c. So is there not among you any wiſeman that can judge betweene his brother? but brother with brother contendeth in judgement, and that before unbeleivers. 1. Cor. 7. Now therefore (ſay theſe men.) It is not lawfull in theſe countryes (rebus ſic ſtantibus) to draw clergy men to the ſecular tribunals of Proteſtant judges.
               To which I anſwer. That the Argument which concludes more then it ought, is alwayes vitious, and that reaſon which may bee retorted upon the arguer, is ever inconſiderately propounded. For if that paſſage of the Apoſtle were a precept, and ſo binding under ſinne to obedience, then not onely the Eccleſiaſti
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   but the lay Catholicke might not bee compelled to anſwer before ſuch Magiſtrates, forſomuch as S. Paul ſpeakes generally of all the faithfull without any diſtinction. And therefore our Rhemiſts according to the univerſall conſent of the fathers doe underſtand the words of the Apoſtle in the nature of a Councell, and not of a commaund. And happy (I confesse) it were, if that Apoſtolicall councell and advice were followed, namely that controverſies and ſuits 'twixt parties, which are many times commenced for light cauſes, and more out of ſtomacke, malice, and revenge, then of good conſcience, might be compoſed at home by friends, and neighbours, ſine ſtrepitu forenſ
                        •
                     , without this lawyerly pleading at the Barre, the benefit whereof is commonly ſmall and uncertaine, but the diſcommodityes both great, and apparant, as loſſe of time, expence of money, with much diſquietneſſe and vexation of minde. But this is a happineſſe rather to be wiſhed, then ever to be expected among ſuch variety of wills, hnmours, and diſpoſitions, as the world more then ever abounds withall. But to hold it abſolutely unlawfull for
Chriſtians to wage law before publicke tribunalls as it is at this day the hereſie of the Anabaptists. So to deny that the Roman Catholickes may convent or bee convented in the courts of ſuch magiſtrates under whom they live, notwithſtanding what difference ſoever in matter of religion, ſmells very ſtrong of the hereſie of Wicliffe condemned in the Councell of Conſtance. Forſomuch as it is the conſent of all divines, that no variety of opinion, no error in faith, no infidelity deſtroyes or takes away the power of the civill magiſtrate, either ſupreame, or ſubordinate. Such obedience then as heretofore was due unto Catholicke princes by their ſubjects, the ſame is no leſſe due unto their ſucceſſors of what opinion in matters of faith ſoever they be. Religion being but accidentall and not at all eſſentiall unto civill principality ordained by God for the politicke and peaceable government of mankind, according to that: Per me Reges regnant, &amp; legam conditores juſtadesernunt. Prov. 8. By me Kings raigne, and thoſe who make lawes determine juſt things. If then clergy men were lawfully convented in civill actions before Catholicke princes, and Magiſtrates, in times paſt (as hath beene proved) ſo no leſſe alſo may they bee before Proteſtants at this day, and the contrary doctrine of our Friars and their followers, is but a corner doctrine, and of no good ſubjects. And if not of their owne choiſe and free election, it were both good for the Church and common wealth and alſo for themſelves, that they might be forced both to live and teach conformable to their holy inſtitutes, and ſo happily there would bee an end of all Controverſies 'twixt the Clergy and them.
            
            
               
                  An Epistle of the Author unto Thomas Flemming alias Barnwell Archbiſhop of Dublin.
               AS I began with an Epiſtle unto Pope 
                     Ʋrbanus 8. now ſitting at the helme of S. Peters Bar
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  . So it will not be impertinent by reaſon of ſome late occurents to conclude with an Epiſtle unto Tho. Flemming Archbiſhop of Dublin in the behalfe of the poore diſtreſſed Clergy of his Dioceſſe. If any marvaile wherefore I doe addreſſe my letters unto him rather in print, then in private, the
cauſe is, (as I have declared in the 6. chap.) That upon what humour, or by whoſe perſwaſion I know not, he refuſeth to receive any letter from me, ſent unto him by any private meſſenger. Yet what I publiſh in print, I finde that he moſt diligently peruſeth. Now for that my deſire is, he ſhould read what I write, whether I be his friend, (as I perſwade my ſelfe I am.) Or his Adverſary (as he ſuppoſeth,) yet even from an Adverſary ſome benefit may bee reaped. Elſe had Plutarch never writ his booke, Deutilitate ab inimico capienda. Of the commodity to be made of an enemy. Nor ever had S. Monica the mother of that great S. Aug. beene taught to drinke water, had not her ſhrewd may de in her anger called her a wine bibber, as S. Aug. himſelfe tells us in the 9. booke of his Confeſſ. chap. 8. You ſee then how I endeav our to comply with the Archbiſhops humour, and that to the example of diverſe holy, and learned men, who have divulged unto the world thoſe very ſame Epiſtles which they have directed unto particular perſons without any private miſſion, or ſignature ſometimes commending their good actions, ſometimes reproving their bad. So S. Hicrom, ſo S. Bernard admoniſhing not onely Biſhops, and Abbates, but even Popes, and princes of their exceſſes. But it will bee ſaid that they were Saints, and I a poore ſinner: yet (ſay I) they were not knowne by that ſtile, when they wrote thoſe Epiſtles, but with much more humility then doubtleſſe is in me, they confeſſed themſelves to be ſinners, and ſo of ſinners became Saints. But to our purpoſe.
               
                  
                     S. Paul writing unto Titus whom hee had made Biſhop tells him, that therefore he left him in Crete to place Preiſts by cittyes as he appointed him. Tit. 1. 5. and in the ſame chap. he ſheweth of what quality and condition thoſe Prieſts ſhould be. Me thinks in S. Paul I heare the Apoſtolicall father Pope 
                           Ʋrbanus 8. commaunding Tho. Flemming whom hee made Archbiſhop, and ſent into Ireland, that he ſhould make and conſtitute prieſts in his dio eſſe. And ſo indeede, it cannot be denyed but he hath done, for beſides what hath paſſed in the country, we obſerve that in this citty of Dublin in place of F. Tho. Coyle Paſtor of S. Michaells, and in place of F. Luke Rochfort, ſometimes paſtor of S. Andeons he hath conſtituted
F. Patricke Brangan and F. Edmund Doyle (I ſay) upon the deceaſe of the 2. former, who in their life time converſed with ſuch commendations in the houſe of God, which is his Church, as they have left behinde them a ſweet odour, as well of their paſtorall, as perſonall vertues among us, inſomuch as their names and memoryes remaine gratefull to poſterity. Now if thoſe their ſucceſſors before mentioned doe in all vigilancy, charity, chaſlity, ſobriety, and longanimity, aemulate their predeceſſors, then neither will the Archbiſhop I know, who deſigned them unto thoſe eminent places the 2. eyes of his epiſcopall See, nor the preſent Incumbents themſelves be offended with me, for inſerting their names into this my Epiſtle, neither neede they to bluſh, or bee aſhamed thereof, for ſo much as the Apoſtle ſayth that ſuch Prieſts as governe well their flockes are worthy of double honour eſpecially they who labour in the word and doctrine, and to whom, no doubt it ſhall be ſaid in that day, Euge ſerve bone &amp; fidelis quia in pauca fuiſti fidelis, &amp;c. Well done good and faithfull ſervant, for that thou haſt been faithfull in ſmall matters, I will ſet thee over great, enter into the joyes of thy Maſter. And ſo much for thoſe 2. Rectories or paſtorſhips, conferred as wee have ſeene by the Ordinary, and upon what perſons.
                     Now ſo it hapned againe as within theſe few weekes a third pariſh alſo became vacant by the deceaſe of the late Incumbent Fa. William Donagh in S. Thomas streete the ſuburbs of Dublin. And it is worthy our conſideration to obſerve how our Archbiſhop ever like himſelfe proceeded in the collation thereof. Wee finde that Popes ſometimes by way of proviſion, as the Canoniſts tearme it, to places of great dignities, as Archbiſhopricks, and the like have in the life time of the Incumbents nominated their ſucceſſors, who upon the vacanſie, were to take poſſeſſion of them. So (I take it) that Anſelmus, and after him Lanfrancus was preferred to the See of Canterbury. To which imitation happily Tho. Flemming. Dioceſian of Dublin (either to ſhew the ſuperaboundance of his paſtorall care, or elſe to let the world underſtand how little he regards what opinion his clergy conceives of him) made a deſignation of 4. ſeverall Prieſts to that one Paſtorſhip, the profit whereof
will hardly pay for a mans chamber and diet by the yeare, and this he did during the life of the Incumbent, who deceaſing, one of the 4. enjoyes it, the other 3. are fruſtrated, and what conceive they of this their Archbiſhops dealing, but that they were meerely deluded, and gulled by him, pretending great care of their preferment, and minding no thing leſſe. Sure if a farmer of Fing all ſhall paſſe his promiſe in any matter of moment unto 4. of his neighbours, which can be made good but unto one, I wot well he ſhall be called but a couzening churle. If a Gentleman or a noble man ſhall do the like, mens cenſures happily may be more civill in tearmes, but their opinions not a whit the better. For as their equals will diſreſpect them, ſo their inferiours will bee ſure to ſet their blacke markes upon them. But for a man not only of a noble family, but a Prieſt, and an Archbiſhop whoſe perſons are held ſacred, to bee found either with guile in their lips, or gifts in their hands, What can we ſay? but liſting up our voyce with our Saviour in admiration. Filius hominis veniens putas inveniet fidem in terra? Luke 18. The Son of man comming doe you thinke he will finde Faith upon earh.
                  
               
               It is not I. It is not I. who reveiles pudenda mei patris. No, no I would be ſorry ſo to doe, but even Sem and Iaphet, no leſſe then Cham have done it. Decantant
                        •
                     r per vrbem in trivys &amp; compitis, in all converſations, his letters, his firmes, his ſeales, his ſubſcriptions are read, are peruſed, are ſeene, are cenſured, For ſo it followeth.
               
                  
                     To his loving friend, M. Iames Archbald theſe bee delivered.
                     Deare father, Send for Fa. De lamar, and deliver him this encloſed, and let him by his friends labour to get the good Will of the beſt of the pariſh, in caſe Fa. William dyeth, as you write he is like to doe, but let none ſee the encloſed untill he dyes, and let not Fa. William know of it, fearing to trouble the good man, whom God comfort, as wiſheth your aſſured. Tho. Barnwell. This preſent Sunday.
                  
               
               
               The Letter encloſed in the former, is, as followeth.
               
                  
                     To his very loving friend, M. Martin Delamar. theſe at Cromlin bee delivered.
                     
                     LOving Fa. To my great griefe, I vnderſtand, Fa. William Donough to be dangerouſly ſicke, I pray you looke to him, and his pariſh, and if God do call him to himſelfe, I doe heereby give your R. in that pariſh the ſame power to minister paſtorall ſacraments, and uſe paſtorall function, as he formerly had, but I hope God will lend him a little longer unto us. His holy will be done. Recommend the next pare of your pariſh to Cromlin to Fa. Ri. Glackney the reſt neere Palmerſton to Fa. Quin, untill I thinke further of the matter. So deſiring God to aſſiſt good Fa. William, I rest your aſſured. Tho. Barnwell. Aprill 20. 1634.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Notwithſtanding the Prieſt Dela Mar, forall theſe faire promiſes made unto him in his letter, was diſappointed of the Pariſh, and another placed therein. And it ſeemeth albeit the Archbiſhop ſubſcribed the letter he writ him. Your aſſured Thomas Barnwell yet it was but a complementall and a ceremonious aſſurance. For the good prieſt found it nothing reall at all, as the event proved. Some are of opinion that when the Archbiſhop intends otherwiſe then he writes, he then ſubſcribes Tho. Barnwell, but when he writes as he intends, then he ſubſcribes his letters, Tho. Flemming, Is ne animis caleſtibus astus? May wee thinke ſuch heatheniſme to rule in heavenly mindes? O no! charity would make a more pious conſtruction of ſuch a prelates actions. Wherefore I am rather perſwaded that the Archbiſhop never failes to make good his word or promiſe unto any (of which from time to time I confèſſe, he is more challenged then all the Biſhops in Ireland) (I ſay) that he never violateth or breaketh the ſame, either as hee is Tho. Flemming, or Tho. Barnwell, or as he is of a noble houſe, or
as he is a Prieſt, or as he is an Archbiſhop, but onely as he is a Friar, to which ſort of people, either lying is eſſentiall, or ſure in many mens opinions proper, quarto mode, and even in the Iudgement of that moſt pious and learned Monke Tho. Walſingham ſpeaking of the Friars in theſe words (not now firſt by me alledged) In tantum etenim illam veritatis profeſſionem ſuam perverſe vivendo macularunt, ut in dicbus iſt is in one cujuſtibet bouwn ſet argumentum, teneus tam de forma, quam materia. His eſt frater; Ergo mendax. ſicut &amp; illud. Hoe eſt album: Ergo coloratum. They have in ſuch ſort ſtayned that their profeſſion of truth by their unhappy living, that in theſe dayes in every ones mouth it is a good Argument, holding as well in forme as matter. This fellow is a friar, Ergo a lyar. Even as to ſay. This thing is white, and therefore hath a colour. So Tho. Walſingham in the raigne of Richard 2. fol. 266.
                     But ſome will ſay Cuibonam? To what end ſhould the Archbiſhop uſe ſuch doubling, or to whoſe benefit in conferring of benefices are the waters allwayes ſo troubled among us? I anſwere, therein lyes a miſtery not yet reveiled unto babes. You know S. Paul wiſheth that in the Churchall things bee done Ad adificationem, I. Cor. 14. and ſo it is with us, but how? Ad adificationem Regularium, to the building up of the Friars Monarchy, and deſtruction of the Clergy, for this is the common Antiphona ſung in the Iriſe Church in theſe dayes, 
                           Ʋp with the Friars: and, Downe with the Priests. Now for our Archbiſhop albeit unto ſtrangers, &amp; ſuch of the laity as take no notice of his proceedings, theſe things are hidden and obſcure, yet the Prieſts of the Hierarchy who have ſummered and wintered him now theſe ten yeares, doe feelingly underſtand the drice of his deſignes. Neither in any thing doth he more ſervice unto the Regular orders then to make theſe embroylements in the conferring of paſtorſhips.
                     For firſt by theſe anticipate promiſes of one pariſh unto many (none ſuſpicious of any promiſe made unto other then himſelfe) our prelate obſerves, which of them is moſt ſerviceable and dutifull unto his Friars, which of them is the beſt benefactor with their friends to him, &amp; his order, which of them is likeſt to prove â Iohannes ad oppoſitum to the reſt of his owne body, and to prove
the moſt factious againſt the Clergy, in ſiding with the Friars on whom henceforward he is to have his whole dependance.
                     Secondly, by this precollation of benefices unto many, ſede nondum vacante the Ordinary finds which of them is like to prove the moſt gratious unto the pariſhioners and which of them is the moſt like to draw the good liking, love and affection, of the laity unto him. For that prieſt ſhall be aſſured (notwithſtanding all his golden promiſes) to goe without the pariſh. For it is againſt the Friars greatneſſe that any ſhould be more pleaſing unto the people then their ſelves.
                     Thirdly, by this conferring of Cures afore-hand unto divers parties ignorant one of another. It may be expected that every one of them armed with a promiſe from the Biſhop and he happily a far off in ſome friary in the country when they fall voyde, that theſe competitors may enter into ſome ſcandalous conteſtation one with another, every one thinking himſelf wronged by the other, an occaſion which the Friars will not omit to take hold of, to traduce them both in private and publicke aſſemblyes, and for their ſakes the reſt of the Clergy as men ſeditious, factious, contentious, covetuous, eſpecially to and before the laity, and all to alienate their mindes from them, like unto greedy millers every one ſtriving to draw the griſe unto their owne mills, notwithſtanding that the ſame Friars have beene the plotters and incentors of all thoſe differences.
                     Laſtly, let it be alwayes remembred as a golden rule and the moſt principall maxime of their pollicy, that the moſt inſufficient pretender of any cure be the man that ſhall be ever preferred: experience by induction of examples hath furniſhed us with that knowledge, for a Prieſt whom God hath bleſſed with talents of learning &amp; good parts is an Aristides, not fit to live in Athens, but rather to be baniſhed per oſtraciſmum, For it is concluded by our Regular Biſhops that the Friars muſt ſhine amidſt ſuch blind curates, Tanquam lunainter minora ſidera, like the moone among the leſſer ſtars.
                     You ſee my Lo. I am no flatterer, neither is the diſcontent of miſſing a benefice under you that makes me ſo plaine with you, for notwithſtanding
that I have lived in this kingdome now very neere theſe twenty yeares, you know neither myſelfe, nor any other for me, did ever motion ſuch a buſines unto you. And albeit (I heare) ſome have wiſhed you to thruſt a ſteeple into my mouth, and therby to ſilence me, yet (I ingenuouſly confeſſe) ſooner ſhould old Eleazarus eat ſwines fleſh, then that I would ſwallow the ſame; Not but that to be a paſtor of ſoules is an honourable vocation in Gods Church, but that I am now too old, to be a Friars horſeboy. No, no let us have no new faſhions in church governmēt, the old is the beſt, &amp; ſuch as was ordained by our Saviour. Let us keepe our old prieſts, &amp; ſend back theſe ſwarmes of friars over unto their monaſteries where they may live according unto their holy Inſtitutes, &amp; not here to vagabūdare per tabernas &amp; popinas, ſelling their merits, their prayers, their penances &amp; mortifications, yea not only of their own perſons, but of their whole orders, and that under large ſealed patents, unto Cookes for diet, to merchauts for broad cloath ſuits, to gentlemē for horſes, &amp;c. beſides oppreſſing a poor country with ſuch ſhameles begging, as little differeth frō meere rapine &amp; extortion. The church may ſubſiſt, yea, flouriſh without friars, but not without prieſts, as for many ages it hath done. For be they white, black, or gray, they are of a latter inſtitute then the prieſts, theſe being the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles, &amp; the 42. diſciples, they of S. Francis, Dominick &amp; Ignatius. &amp; of a diſtinct hierarchy. If I be a Iohn Baptist &amp; preach in the wilderneſſe without profit: That is not my fault, but the fault of them that wil not amend their faults. It were more pleaſing &amp; contentfull to me to come in spiritu lenitatis, in the ſpirit of mildneſſe, then in the rod of correction. If the ſubject were ſo diſpoſed. Let thoſe for whoſe good I take all theſe paines both in health &amp; ſicknes, reforme their manners, &amp; I will ſoone alter both my voyce &amp; ſtile, &amp; I wiſh with all my heart that I had cauſe to ſay with th'Apoſtle, If I have made you ſad, either by my bookes, or by my Epistle, it repenteth me not, for that you were ſo made ſad unto repētance. Wel to conclude all in oneword. Paul may plant &amp; Apollo may water, but God is he, who gives the encreaſe, to whoſe bleſſings I humbly commend theſe my poore endeavours, my ſelfe, my friends, my perſecutors.
                     
                        From the Cell of my ſolitary recollection, who wiſheth your-Hon: all-happineſſe PAUL HARRIS. Pr.
                     
                  
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            I Heare, that ſome of our divines (if worthy that name) take great exceptions unto me, for calling the Catholicke Biſhops of Ireland, Titulary Biſhops, by which tearme they underſtand no true Biſhops at all. But ſure if I had beene able to have put wit into their heads as well as a booke into their hands, they had beene freed from that error. Let them then conſult with the Canon, or if they have it not, let them look into Bellar. de Clericis lib. 1. cap. 17. And they will finde this to be a good argument, teneus tam de 
                     〈◊〉
                   qua
                     •
                   de materia. Hic eſt epiſcopus titularis. Ergo verus: even as that. Hic eſt parochus. Ergo preſbiter. But I am no better then my predeceſſours, as many as have expoſed themſelves to publicke conſures by their writings. For all of us may ſay with Terentianus Manrus.
            
            Pro captu lectoris habene ſua fata libelli.
         
         
            PAge 28. lin. 2. read a thouſand owo hundred. pag. 29. lin. 20. for cis, read ea. pag. 49 for Patricke, read Patriarch. pag. 88. lin. 21. for unlike, read like.
            
         
      
   

