
   
      
         
            A proclamation of vvarre from the Lord of Hosts. Or Englands warning by Israels ruine shewing the miseries like to ensue vpon vs by reason of sinne and securitie. Deliuered in a sermon at Pauls Crosse Iuly the 23. 1626. By William Hampton Master of arts, and preacher of Gods word.
            Hampton, William, 1599 or 1600-1677.
         
         
            
               1627
            
         
         Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02612
            STC 12741
            ESTC S120499
            99855695
            99855695
            21197
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02612)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21197)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1025:12)
         
         
            
               
                  A proclamation of vvarre from the Lord of Hosts. Or Englands warning by Israels ruine shewing the miseries like to ensue vpon vs by reason of sinne and securitie. Deliuered in a sermon at Pauls Crosse Iuly the 23. 1626. By William Hampton Master of arts, and preacher of Gods word.
                  Hampton, William, 1599 or 1600-1677.
               
               [6], 43, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Norton for Mathew Lawe and are to be sold for the signe of the Fox in Saint Paules Church-yard, neere Saint Austens Gate,
                  London :
                  1627.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2008-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-06
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-07
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-07
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A PROCLAMATION. OF VVARRE FROM THE LORD OF HOSTS.
            OR ENGLANDS warning by ISRAELS ruine: Shewing the miſeries like to enſue vpon vs by reaſon of Sinne and Securitie.
            
            Deliuered in a Sermon at Pauls Croſſe Iuly the 23. 16
                  •
               6.
            By WILLIAM HAMPTON Maſter of Arts, and Preacher of Gods Word.
            
               
                  LVKE 13.3.
               
               Except yee repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe per
                     •
                  ſh.
            
            
               
                  Ier. 26.13.
               
               Therefore now amend your wayes and your workes, and heare the voyce of the Lord your God, that the Lord may repent him of the Plague, that he hath pronounced againſt you.
            
            LONDON, Printed by Iohn Norton for Mathew Lawe and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Fox in Saint Paules Church-yeard, neere Saint Auſtens Gate. 1627.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HOnourable, and moſt nobly deſcended, CHARLES Lord HOVVARD, Baron of Effingham, Earle of Nottingham, Lord Lieutenant for the County of Surrey, grace be multiplied with encreaſe of honour in this world, &amp; euerlaſting glory in the future world.
            
               Right Honourable,
            
            
               WHen Socrates his Schollers brought euery one rich gifts to him in token of thankefulnes, among the reſt,Sen. de ben. lib. 1. cap. 8. hee had one called Aeſchines, whoſe hearty affection was as great to him as any of the reſt, but hee wanted meanes to giue: whereupon he ſpake thus; I haue nothing, O Socrates, to giue vnto thee worthy thy ſelfe, but that one thing

which I haue in my poſſeſsion I freely giue, namely, I giue my ſelfe vnto thee. When I call to minde, the many and noble fauours receiued from your honour, I wiſh I could expreſſe my thankfulnes in a more reall manner then my ability will permit; but hauing nothing worthy your ſelfe, with Aeſchines I giue my ſelfe to your Lordſhips ſeruice. At this time I offer this poore mite of my weake endeauours to your honourable Patronage; A worke not fit the Preſſe, neither did I intend (had I not bene encouraged to it by your honours approbation of it, in hope it may redound to the publike good,) euer to haue publiſhed it. Such as it is, it proceeded ex mero motu, out of a hearty deſire of Gods glory, and my Countries ſafety. It meets with the ſecurity and iniquitie of the time; and if it may

rowze vs from the one, or the other, or both, I ſhall thinke my time well beſtowed. A double reſpect makes it due vnto your Honour: Firſt the author of it, my particular obligation; becauſe my labours in the Goſpell being firſt countenanced, and daily encouraged by your honour, you may of right challenge this, as the firſt fruits to bee offered vnto you. Secondly, the ſubiect of it; becauſe your Lordſhip (as I attendant in your Honourable houſe can witneſſe, being daily acquainted with your wiſhes and praiers) following the ſteps of your loyall and thrice renowned Father, deſire nothing more, then the furtherance of Gods glory, the ſafetie of his roiall Maieſtie, and wellfare of your Countrie; all which, and nothing elſe this aimeth at: It is all my praier, all my deſire. Thus

ceaſing further to trouble your Lordſhip at this time, with my daily and heartie ſupplications to the Father of mercies, for your ſelfe, together with your ſecond-ſelfe, your religious Lady in whom you are happy, beſeeching him long to continue that bleſſed knot, with aſmuch happines as euer he beſtowed on Abraham and Sarah, or Iſaac and Rebekah; and to multiply all thoſe bleſsings on you which Iacob wiſhed to his deareling Ioſeph;
               Gen. 49. verſ. 25. heauenly bleſſings from aboue, and earthly bleſsings from beneath, bleſsings of the breaſts, and of the wombe, I commit you to his mercifull and bleſſed protection.
            
               Your Honours moſt obliged and obſeruant Seruant and Chaplaine William Hampton
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A PROCLAMATION OF WARRE, From the Lord of Hoſts.
            
               
                  
                     DEVT. 28. ver. 49, 50, 51.
                  
                  49 The Lord ſhall bring a Nation vpon thee from far, euen from the ende of the World, flying ſwift as an Eagle; a Nation whoſe tongue thou ſhalt not vnderſtand.
                  50 A Nation of a fierce countenance, which will not regard the perſon of the olde, nor haue compaſsion of the young.
                  51 The ſame ſhall eate the fruit of thy Cattle, and the fruit of thy Land vntill thou bee deſtroyed, and hee ſhall leaue thee neither Wheate, Wine, nor Oyle, neither the increaſe of thy Kine, nor the ſtockes of thy Sheepe, vntill he haue brought thee to nought.
               
            
            
               IT was the opinion of Licurgus that wiſe Law-giuer of the Lecedemonians, that there was no better way to keepe men in good order, then to vſe partly threats, and partly promiſes; partly rewards, and partly puniſhments: and in a well-gouerned Common-wealth he thought the one as needfull as the other. GOD Almightie, that great and wiſe Law-maker of heauen and earth, hath appointed by theſe two meanes, Praemiis &amp; Poenis, by rewards and puniſhments,

to keepe the common-wealth of the whole world in good gouernment, and to bring men to obedience to his holy commandements: for after he had in the 20 of Exodus giuen his moſt ſacred Precepts: that he might the rather ſtirre men vp to keepe, and obſerue them: in the 26. Chap. of Leuiticus, and alſo in this Chapter, hee propoundeth certaine bleſsings, and curſings, menaces and promiſes, rewards and puniſhments, as moſt forcible motiues to winne them to obedience. From the third verſe to the thirteenth, bleſſings are promiſed to the obedient; from the fifteenth to the ende of the Chapter curſings are denounced againſt the diſobedient. Wherein we may note, what a gradation God doth keepe in inflicting puniſhments on ſtubborne ſinners: firſt, he trieth by his leſſer and lighter chaſtiſments, to make them turne vnto him; and if they will doe no good, then hee comes with the Sword to conſume, and cut them off from the face of the earth:Pſal. 71 12. as the Prophet Dauid ſpeakes, if a a man will not turne, God will whet his Sword. Thus much we ſee in this Chapter; but more plainly in the 26. of Leuiticus, where firſt he threatens to chaſtice them with the Famine; if that will not amend them, he threatens to encreaſe their puniſhment, and to ſend the Peſtilence among them; If that will not reforme them, then in the laſt place he giues them ouer to the Sword as it is v. 25. of that Chap. If yee will not for theſe things be reformed by me (meaning the Famine and Peſtilence) but walke ſtubburnly againſt me, then will I alſo walke ſtubbornely in mine anger againſt you, and I will chaſtiſe you ſeuen times more according to your ſinnes, and I will bring a Sword vpon

you that ſhall auenge the quarrell of my couenant, and ye ſhall be deliuered vp into the hands of your enemies.
            
            Beloued, God hath tryed by the two former puniſhments, by the Famine, and by the Peſtilence, to winne vs of this Land vnto his obedience: we haue had of late many deare yeares, wherein a number, eſpecially the poorer ſort haue pinched for it: wee haue had the laſt a dying yeare, Annum mortalem, wherein thouſands, and ten thouſands haue fallen in our Streetes. Now if theſe things reforme vs not, (as GOD knowes there is yet little reformation ſeene) wee are next in order to expect the Sword, Warre, and the calamities thereof to deſcend vpon vs; our Enemies to inuade, and ouer-runne vs, vnleſſe GOD bee the more mercifull vnto vs. So the Lord here menaceth his owne choſen people, deare Iſrael: (and we may apply it to our ſelues, if we walke in their ſteps;) if they will not amend by his former puniſhments, then he will ſtirre vp a forraigne foe to inuade them.
            
               The Lord ſhall bring a Nation vpon thee from farre, euen from the end of the World, flying ſwift as an Eagle, &amp;c.
            
            Which Text is a Proclamation of Warre, or a Commination of a fearefull Inuaſion; wherein we may note;
            Firſt, Who proclaimes this Warre? It is Iehouah the Lord.
            
            Secondly, Againſt whom he proclaimes it? againſt his owne people, his beloued Iſraell: Yet if they offend him, and ſinne againſt him, hee will raiſe vp Warre againſt them. Vpon thee.
            
            Thirdly, Who hee imployes in the execution of

his wrath, to puniſh his diſobedient ſeruants?

                  
                     A ſtrange Foe.
                  
                  
                     A ſtrong Foe.
                  
                  
                     A ſterne Foe.
                  
               
            
            1 A ſtrange or forraigne Foe; A Nation from farre, from the end of the World, whoſe tongue thou vnderſtandest not.
            
            2 A ſtrong Foe: compared in my Text to an Eagle, to a flying Eagle: becauſe as an Eagle is the ſtrongeſt of all Birds, ſo this Nation: ſecondly, to a flying Eagle, becauſe as an Eagle being on her wings is able to ouer-top any other fowle, ſo this Nation being in Armes, is able to ouer-match any other Nation.
            3 A ſterne Foe: Which will ſhew no reſpect, no mercy, no fauour neither to olde nor young: A Nation of a fierce, or cruell, or barbarous countenance, which will not regard the perſon of the old, nor haue compaſſion of the young.
            Laſtly, the dreadfull deſolation that ſhall follow this inuaſion, the calamity that ſhall befall the Inhabitants of that Land, then Enemies ſhall leaue them nothing, they ſhall take all that euer they haue from them; their Goods, their Cattell, their Corne, their Sheepe; and ſhall put them either to cruell death, or to ſuch ſlauery and bondage, that they ſhall haue no pleaſure in their life, but ſhall wiſh rather to dye then Iſue; as it is verſ. 66. &amp; 67. Thy life ſhall hang before thee, and thou ſhalt feare both night and day, and ſhalt haue no aſſurance of thy life: In the morning thou ſhalt ſay, Would God it were euening; and at euening thou ſhalt ſay, Would God it were morning, for the fear of thine heart which thou ſhalt feare, and for the ſight of thine eyes which thou ſhalt ſee.
            
            
               Firſt, I begin with him, who is α and ω, the beginning and end or all our actions, yea of all things, and that is, who proclaimes this Warre: It is Iehouah the Lord.
            
            But this may ſeeme a ſtrange Paradox to ſome; that that God, who is Deus pacis, the God of peace, ſhould ſtirre vp Warre and diuiſion, and ſet Nations together by the eares vpon the face of the earth: that God who is not onely Bonus, ſed ipſa bonitas, good, but goodneſſe it ſelfe, ſhould be Author mali, the Author of euill, the raiſer of Warre, which is omnium malorum peſsimum, of all euils the greateſt. To vnlooſe this knot, the Schoole affords an olde diſtinction of malum culpae &amp; malum paenae: or as Tertullian ſpeakes, lib. 2. cont. Marcionem, pag. 180. Malum delicti, et malum ſupplicij: or as Saint Auguſtine diſtinguiſeth in other words, but to the ſame effect. Tomo ſexto. Contra Adimantum, cap. 26. Malum quod facit homo, et malum quod patitur homo. Euill which man doth which is ſinne, and euill which man ſuffereth, which is the puniſhment of ſinne: Concerning the former, euill as it is ſinne, God is by no meanes the Author of it; and therefore accurſed, for euer curſed to the pit of hell be that abominable doctrine, which the Church of Rome doth ſlanderouſly, and blaſphemouſly caſt vpon vs, that wee make God the Author of ſinne; for wee defie and renounce it from the bottome of our hearts as a moſt ſinfull Doctrine. But concerning the latter, euill which is the puniſhment of ſinne, God is the Author of that: All afflictions &amp; calamities which are the rewards of ſinne, are ſent vpon man by the mighty hand of God: Famine a great euill; yet

the Prophet tells vs God ſends that; A fruitfull Land he maketh barren,
               Pſal. 107.34. 
               for the wickedneſſe of them that dwell therein. The Peſtilence a great euill, yet God ſends that; we reade 2 Sam. 24. He ſent a Plague in Iſrael, whereof died more then threeſcore thouſand, in leſſe then three dayes. So digitus Dei, the finger of God hath beene lately ſeene in our Land, eſpecially in this Citie, ſcourging vs for our ſinns. This ſtroke came nor by chance; It was the hand of heauen that ſmote vs; and it is none but his omnipotent hand, that hath healed vs: Bleſſed be his great name for it. Warre a great euill; yet GOD ſendeth that vpon a ſinfull Nation: as'tis hee alone that giues peace to his children, and cauſeth Warres to ceaſe in all the world: So 'tis he alone that raiſeth Warre, and bringeth a reuenging Sword vpon the ſinfull ſonnes of men: This ſhould teach to prepare, and arme our ſelues with patience to endure it, if it doe come, becauſe a Domino eſt, it is from the Lord, it is the Lords doing; the wicked, our Enemies are but his inſtruments: the rod of his fury, a ſword of his to puniſh ſinners: he ſets them on worke; O Aſhur, the rod of my wrath! I will ſend him to a diſſembling Nation, and I will giue him a charge againſt the people of my wrath to take the ſpoile, and to take the prey, and to tread them vnder feete like the mire in the ſtreete, Iſa. 10.5.6. And in my Text, The Lord ſhall bring a Nation vpon thee. What? Vpon Iſraell? His deare Iſraell? his beloued Iſraell? his choſen people? his inheritance? his ſanctified ones? his peculiars? his fauorites? thoſe whom he pickt and cull'd out of all Nations? Thoſe on whom he beſtowed more pretious tokens of his loue, then on any other? Will hee deale ſo

hardly with them? Will he reiect them? Will he deſtroy them? forſake them? Yes, if they forſake and reiect him, he will: God is not tyed to any Nation, or to any people, longer then they tye themſelues to his obedience, and to his ſeruice:1 Chron. 15.2. 
               Dominus vociſcum dum vos cum Domino, The Lord is with you, while yee are with him, and if yee ſeeke him, he will be found of you; but if yee forſake him, he will forſake you. So good Azariah fore-warn'd them, and as he fore-told, ſo it came to paſſe, this curſe was executed to the full; for when they forſooke the Lord, and gaue themſelues ouer to follow ſtrange Gods; the Lord forſooke them, and giue them ouer into the hands of Strangers; they which hated them were Lords ouer them, their enemies oppreſſed them, and had them in ſubiection; hee brought vpon them, A ſtrange Foe, a ſtrong Foe, and a ſterne Foe, (firſt vpon Iſrael, becauſe they firſt fell from him, then vpon Iudah) euen the Babylonians, who in
               
                  ••
               ded their Land, waſted their Countrey, ruinated their Citie, burnt their Temple, deſtroyed all their goodly Buildings, ſlew their young men with the Sword, euen in the middſt of their Sanctuary, and ſpared neither yong man, nor virgin, ancient, nor aged, led many thouſands of them into moſt miſerable ſlauery and captiuity; tooke the King himſelfe priſoner, changed his chaines of gold into chaines of braſſe, and fetters of iron; kill'd his Princes, and all his Nobles, ſlew his ſonnes before his eyes, put out his owne eyes, &amp; kept him in moſt pittifull bondage all the dayes of his life; as you may ſee more at large, 2 Chron. and the laſt Chap. Ier. Chap. 52. And if you enquire after the cauſe of all this miſchiefe,

you ſhall finde it to bee their ſinnes, their diſobedience to Gods commaundements, their contempt of Gods word, their ſleighting of Gods Meſſengers, their abuſing of his Prophets. GOD (whoſe mercies are more in number them all our ſinnes) out of his infinite compaſſion was loath to deſtroy them, unwilling to ſee their ſubuerſion; and therefore he vſed all meanes for their conuerſion: hee ſent vnto them by his meſſengers the Prophets, riſing early, and ſending (ſaith the Text) for he had compaſſion on his people, and on his habitation: but they mocked the meſſengers of God, they deſpiſed his words, they miſuſed his Prophets, vntill the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his people, and till there was no remedy, 2 Chro. laſt Chap. ver. 15.16. His long ſuffering waited for their conuerſion, ſo long as there was any hope, as a Phyſitian ſeeing any hope of life in his 
                  〈◊〉
                Patient, will not giue him ouer; but finding him pa
                  ••
                
               
                  •
               ecouery leaues him: So God ſeeing no hope of reformation, ſeeing there was no other remedy, ſo ſeeke them, giues them ouer to their owne 
                  ••
               ſt
                  〈…〉
               , bring vpon them a Nation from far, a ſtrong Nation, 
                  ••
               e
                  •
               ce and cruell, the King of the Caldeans with all his armed troopes, who brought vpon them all theſe calamities. And after 70 yeares of captiuity being expired, hee brought them into their owne Land againe, and reſtored them to their former and flouriſhing ſtate: but becauſe they continued not ſtedfaſt in his couenant, but rebelled againg him, reiected his word, crucified the Lord of life, refuſed his Goſpell; he brought vpon them an Enemy more cruell then the former: euen the flying Eagle (as it is in my Text) the Romane Emperour;

who brought vpon them all the curſes threatned in this Chapter; Warre, Famine, (in ſo much that the tender and dainty women were glad to eate their owne children (as Ioſephus relates)Ioſeph. de bell Iud. lib. 7. cap 3.
                as it was foretold, verſ. 57.) diſperſion, deuaſtation, a finall deſolation Thus is my Text fulfilled in your cares; the curſe is executed; Canaan is inuaded; Iudah is gone into captiuity; Ieruſalem is troden downe, the pleaſant Land lyes waſt: Quid hoc ad nos? And what is this to vs will ſome ſay? Yet it neerely concernes Vbi ingentia beneficia, &amp; ingentia is peccata, ibi ingentia ſupplicia: If partaking with them in Gods benefits, wee partake of their ſinnes, wee may iuſtly feare to partake of their puniſhments: Let vs a little paralell our eſtate with theirs: Gods mercies were great to them, no leſſe to vs. His louing kindneſſe toward them appeared in foure things:
            In freeing them from the bondage of the

                  1. ſoule,
                  2. body.
               
            
            In giuing them bleſſings for the

                  3. body.
                  4. ſoule.
               
            
            1 He brought them out of the Land of Aegypt, from the bondage of Pharaoh: Aegypt was a Land full of Idolatry, and ſuperſtition; the people there worſhipped Deuils, they worſhipped mē, they worſhipped beaſts, they worſhipped plants, inſteed of God: From this Idolatrous Land, God freed them, which was a great mercy: but he hath done more for vs; though he hath not brought vs out of an Idolatrous Land, yet he hath taken Idolatry out of our Land, he hath cleanſed it, and ſwept ſuperſtition from it.
            
               2 He deliuered them from the bondage of Pharaoh, who did but tyrannize ouer the body onely, but he hath releaſed vs out of that cruell bondage of that proud Pharaoh of Rome, who doth tyrannize both ouer the bodies and ſoules of men. He ſhewed wonders for them in the deepe, leading thorow on foote as through a wilderneſſe, drowning and ouerwhelming their enemies in the middeſt of the Sea: The like he did for vs in 88. confounding the inuincible Armado of Spaine, which came with open mouth to make a prey of vs all: neither did he only with Iſrael ſaue vs out of the water, but alſo out of the fire; when a tormenting Tophet was prepared, with Gun-powder and much Wood, to blowe vp and conſume with one blaſt, both our King and Kingdome; and wanted but fewe howres for the execution of it; then did he moſt mercifully diſcouer it, and deliuer vs from that infernall and helliſh plott: ſo that we may ſay of this Land, as the Prophet of Ieruſalem: Is not this a brand taken out of the fire? Zach. 3.2.
            3 GOD ſeated them in a fruitfull Land, a moſt pleaſant, and delightfull Land, the Land of Canaan, a Land flowing with milke and honey: ſo hee hath planted vs in a moſt plentifull and fertile land, the abundance and bleſſings whereof, (as one ſaid, who did for a while abſent himſelfe in forraigne parts,) are perceiued magis carendo quam fruendo, rather by wanting, then by enioying them: no Nation vnder the cope of heauen, hauing ſuch plenty of all Gods bleſſings, both for the preſeruation, and ſuſtentation, and delectation of mans life, as our land affordeth; therefore no meruaile, if the Pope and

his adhaerents, compaſſe ſea and land; vſe all the trickes, and plots they can deuiſe, by treaſon and treachery, by open hoſtility and priuy conſpiracie, to gaine this Iland into their tyrannie, out of which that triple crown'd Father ſuck'd ſo much ſweetneſſe: for it is the eye of Europe, and ſtore-houſe of Chriſtendome: And as it was ſaid, that the Prouince of Purgatory did yeeld as much reuenue to the Popes treaſury, as heauen and hell both: ſo it is thought, that that man of ſinne, and his generation of Vipers, Monkes, and Friars, Abbots and Priors, in our fore-fathers time, did ſucke as much fatneſſe out of this Kingdome, as out of all Chriſtendome: no wonder then, if they beſtirre themſelues for it; 'tis a ſweet bit; terra frugifera, a fruitfull land, fitly reſembling the land of Canaan.
            
            4 But the head of all Gods mercies to thē conſiſted in beneficio animae, in doing the ſoule a good turne: in reuealing his will, his word, his truth, his lawes and ordinances vnto them: the Prophet reckons it an vnſpeakable fauour; He gaue his word vnto Iacob, his ſtatutes and ordinances vnto Iſraell, hee hath not dealt ſo with euery Nation, Pſal. 147.19. Such is Gods goodneſſe vnto vs alſo, hee hath made knowne his word, his will, his truth, his Goſpell to vs in moſt plentifull manner: he hath not dealt ſo with euery Nation; no not with any Nation: no Nation in the world hath ſuch ſtore of heauenly Manna, ſo much knowledge of the truth, ſo much preaching of the Word, ſo much glorious light of the Goſpell of peace as we haue. Thus we ſee, we goe hand in hand with them in the firſt ſtep, wee haue receiued Ingentia beneficia, infinite, vnſpeakable benefits and

mercies as well as they. Let vs now ſee if wee haue not Ingentia peccata, as great ſinnes as euer they had: would I could ſay wee haue not. Haue wee beene more thankfull to God for his fauours? more obedient to his commandements then they? Would I could ſay we haue. God hath beene as gracious to this Vineyard of England, as euer hee was to the Vineyard of Iſraell, both in planting, in pruning, in watering, in hedging, in defending it: but we haue not yeelded the fruites, the Grapes he expected: I feare, I may ſay with Moſes, wee haue returned to him, the fruits of Sodome and Gomorrah, our Grapes, are Grapes of gall, our cluſters are bitter, our Wine is the poyſon of Dragons, and the cruell gall of Aſpes, Deut. 32.32. Sinne and wickedneſſe, vnthankfulneſſe, iniquity, impiety, theſe are the Grapes, theſe the fruites: neuer ſo much knowledge and light abounded, and yet neuer ſo many workes of darkneſſe: neuer ſo much Preaching, neuer ſo little performing; neuer did men know the will of God more perfectly, neuer did men doe the will of God more careleſly. And as it was ſaid, there was neuer leſſe wiſedome in Greece, then when the ſeauen wiſe men liued there; ſo it is thought, there was neuer leſſe piety, neuer leſſe charity, neuer more iniquity in our Land among moſt men; then now when the light of the Goſpell ſhines moſt gloriouſly amongſt vs. O barren, vnfruitfull, vnprofitable Vineyard! May we not feare that God will now indiſpleaſure forſake it, breake downe the hedge thereof, and let in the wilde Bore to roote it vp, and the wilde beaſts to deuoure it? Hath Iſraell felt his rod, and may not England feare his ſcourge? Are we more deare

to him then they were? Or is hee more tyed to vs, then to them? O no: if we partake of their ſinnes, we may expect their plagues. The time would bee too ſhort for me, to trace all the ſinfull ſteps wherein we haue followed them: onely this I may ſay, there was no ſinne knowne among them, which doth not abound among vs. Wherefore as the Prophet comparing Iudah with Sodome and Samaria, affirmes that ſhee was corrupted in her wayes more then they both, and had iuſtified them by her ſinnes, ſo if we looke into the ſinnes of our Land, we ſhall finde that ſhee hath iuſtified and exceeded both Sodome and Samaria, and Iudah alſo in her filthineſſe. O ſinfull England! Sodome thy ſiſter hath not done,Ezek. 16.48.51. neither ſhee, nor her daughters, as thou haſt done and thy daughters, (for ſurely Sodome neuer knew the painting and pranking, and pride of our Land) neither hath Samaria nor Iudah itſelfe, committed halfe of thy ſinnes, but thou haſt multiplied thine abominations more then they. Yet Sodome, and Samaria, and Iudah, are ruinated; and haue drunke the cup of Gods fury long agone: and doeſt thou ſleepe ſecure, O wretched England, without any feare? Sure thy iudgement ſleepeth not. When Calice was taken from England, by the French men, in the time of Charles the fift: one asked the Engliſh men, in ſcorne, and deriſion, when they would winne Calice againe? a wiſe Captaine hearing it, made anſwere, Cum veſtra peccata erunt noſtris maiora: When your ſinnes ſhall bee greater then ours; meaning, that whenſoeuer God giueth any land ouer to the ſword to be inuaded and ruinated, it is for the wickedneſſe of the Inhabitants, for the ſinnes of the Land: but now Noſtra peccata maiora, our ſinnes exceede the

ſinnes of Iſraell; may wee not more then feare to taſt of the ſame ſauce with Iſrael, Ingentia ſupplicia, infinite huge puniſhments as well as they? Neuer did our Land (as I can read) enioy ſo long a peace, and neuer did men make ſo ill vſe of ſuch a bleſſing. Often hath it beene afflicted with this calamitie of Warre and Inuaſion; Firſt, it was ouerrunne by the Romans, then by the Picts, then by the Saxons, then by the Danes, then by the Normans: and if we examine the records of thoſe times, wee ſhall finde it alwaies imputed to ſinne; Sinne the cauſe of all the miſerie: Gildas an ancient Hiſtorian writing of the deſtruction of the Britaines by the inuaſion of the Saxons, ſaies it was for their ſinnes; and reckoning vp a Catalogue, in the ende he ſhutteth vp all with this ſad Epilogue: Non igitur admirandum eſt degeneres tales, patriam illam amittere quam praedicto modo maculabant: It was therefore no wonder at all to ſee, that ſuch degenerate and wicked men did loſe that countrey, which they had ſo polluted by their ſinnes. And in another ancient Hiſtory (written as the Author ſaith, ad cautelam futurorum, for the warning of future ages, inſtanced by maſter Fox.) I finde the inuaſion of the Danes,
               Maſter Fox Acts and Monu. pag. 126. aſcribed to the like cauſe: In primitiua quidem Anglorum Ecleſia, &amp;c. In the primitiue Church of the Engliſhmen, Religion did moſt clearely ſhine; but in proceſſe of time, all vertue ſo decayed, that in fraud, in treachery none ſeemed like vnto them, piety was neglected, iniquity reſpected: wherefore Almighty God brought vpon them (Pagan and cruell Nations like ſwarmes of bees, which ſpared neither women nor children; as Danes, Norwegians, Gothes, Suevians, Vandals, and Friſians, who deſtroyed their ſinnefull Land from one ſide of the Sea to the another, from man alſo vnto beaſt.
            
            
               And may we not feare the like ſcourge now? haue not we contaminated, and polluted this Land, by our abominable and horrible ſins, more then euer they did? their ſins were ignorāces, ours preſumptiō: theirs omiſſiō, ours rebellion: the ſins of our Land are greater now, then euer they were: I am perſwaded if our Forefathers were now aliue, they would be aſhamed &amp; bluſh to ſee ſuch a degenerate &amp; ſinfull poſteritie: As St. Paul told the Corinthians, there was fornication, &amp; ſuch found among them, as was not named among the Gentiles; ſo there is ſuch &amp; ſo much wickednes foūd now among vs in our land, as was ſcarce euer heard or named among our anceſtors: They had Plus conſcientiae, minus ſcientiae: we, Plus ſcientiae, minus conſcientiae; more cōſcience, though leſſe ſcience then we; we haue more ſcience, but leſſe conſcience then they. We haue iuſtified them, they were righteous in reſpect of vs; Their hoſpitality is now conuerted into riot &amp; luxurie; their frugality, into pride &amp; prodigalitie; their ſimplicitie, into ſubtilty; their ſincerity, into hypocriſie; their charity, into cruelty; their chaſtitie, into chambring; their modeſtie, into wantonnes; their ſobrietie into drunkennes; their Church building, into Church-robbing; their plaine dealing, into diſſembling; their workes of compaſſion and mercy, into workes of oppreſſion and bribery: It is now almoſt growne out of faſhion to bee an honeſt man. Mirandum eſt degeneres nos: It is a wonder, and a great wonder, that ſuch a degenerate generation as this, ſuch a corrupt and ſinfull Nation as we, who haue ſo farre exceeded our forefathers in all wickedneſſe, ſhould not loſe this Countrey which we haue ſo defiled with our ſinnes? Miranda Mi, cricordia! Gods mercy is to bee wondred at, that

he hath ſpared vs ſo long: It is his mercy, and nothing but mercy, that we are not conſumed. Sinne is now in vltimo gradu, at the higheſt pitch that may be: Sathan (I thinke) cannot make ſome more ſatanicall, more ſinfull: our ſinnes cry lowder then the ſinnes of Sodome; they aſcend higher then the ſinnes of Niniueh; wee may expect a iudgement at hand, euen that iudgement, which GOD here denounceth againſt Iſraell: for when his two other rods, Famine, and the Peſtilence, will not ſerue the turne; to make vs turne, then the Sword muſt haue his turne; although our ſecurity tell vs no, yet our ſinnes cry, it will be ſo. The bane of many Nations hath beene too much ſecurity: Ieruſalem flattered her ſelfe, with peace, peace: and would by no meanes be perſwaded the Enemy ſhould ſet foot there, till the Enemie had troden her vnder foote: who would haue beleeued that the Enemie and Aduerſarie, ſhould haue entred into the gates of Ieruſalem? Lam. 4.12. God graunt the ſame be not the ouerthrow of our Kingdome: Ah ſecure people that we are! wee will not (with Thomas) beleeue; till wee feele and ſee: we are ſicke of their diſeaſe, we thinke our ſelues as ſafe as they: when the meſſengers of God told them the danger was neere, they were as farre from beleeuing it, as you are now in London:
               Ier. 36.23.24. Thoſe that heard the words of Ieremiahs rowle, denouncing an inuaſion at hand, were neuer moued at it: Iehoiakim tooke the rowle, cut it with a Pen-knife, caſt it into the fire; that was all the reckoning they made of it, ſuch is the ſecurity of theſe times; our words ſeeme to many as Lots to his ſonnes in law; as though wee mocked: or as the

womens to the Diſciples, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , as an olde wines tale, Luke 24.11. They make but a mock and ieſting ſong at all our warnings; which makes mee more to feare, and tremble to think, that the iudgement is at hand, becauſe men are ſo inſenſible of it; God (I feare) hath blinded the eyes, and fatted the heart of this people, (as hee dealt with Iſraell) that we might haue no ſence, nor feeling of our enſuing miſery, and ſo ſeeke no meanes to preuent it. It may be you thinke there is no danger this Sommer; be it ſo, God graunt. But yet if wee deferre our repentance, it will not long be deferred, and it may come before wee looke for it: it is the Spaniſh policie to barke leaſt, when they bite ſooneſt, and ſoreſt.
            This was the deſtruction of the Amyclaeans; they, as wee, ſtoode in feare of an inuaſion; diuers times it was noyſed abroad, that the Enemie was comming, and nigh at hand. Whereupon the Citie was rayſed, &amp; much troubled: and ſtill they found it to be a falſe rumour: whereupon the Citizens of that place like wiſe men, made a prouident law, that no man vpon paine of death, ſhould any more bring ſuch newes of the Enemies comming; ſhortly after the Enemy came indeede: and then all being ſecure, and careleſſe, and vnprouided, &amp; no man daring to bring tydings for feare of the law, the Citie was vnawares ſurpriſed, the Citizens taken, and all cruelly murthered. The people of our Land are almoſt of this condition, they cannot endure to bee told the danger they are in; it is vnpleaſing newes: GOD graunt when wee are ſecure, and thinke our ſelues moſt ſafe, the Enemie be not vpon vs: The Lord for his mercies ſake (as he hath put it into the heart

of his faithfull Seruant, our moſt gracious Soueraigne, to be carefull to prouide for our defence and ſafety,) ſo moue the hearts of the people to furniſh him with ſupplies ſufficient for the performance of it, before it be too late; better part with ſomthing, nay with halfe, then loſe all, liues and all.
            O when I call to minde the raigning, and crying ſinnes of our Land; being now ripe, like the Harueſt of the earth, ſpoken of in the Reuelation; I cannot but feare that God will ere long, (vnleſſe our hearty repentance preuent it) command his Angell, to thruſt in the great and ſharpe ſickle to cut vs downe. When I call to minde, how little we haue profited by his former puniſhments; eſpecially by the laſt yeares iudgement, and by his mercy, in taking it ſo ſoone away; I cannot but tremble to thinke, that hee will ere long (vnleſſe our generall conuerſion turne it away) execute this curſe here threatned, and already executed on Iſraell; bring vpon vs a Nation from farre, a forraigne inuaſion; a ſtrange foe, a ſtrong foe, and a ſterne foe: Now if euer, the Ignatians cry, let Spaine ſet foote in England: and now if euer, we haue cauſe to feare. Firſt, A ſtrange foe.
            
            A Nation ſtrange vnto vs many wayes; ſtrange by ſcituation, farre remote; ſtrange in affection, bearing an innate grudge vnto vs; ſtrange in Religion; ſtrange in condition; ſtrange in language; ſtrange in manners; euery way ſtrange vnto vs.
            A ſtrange and forraigne inuaſion, a thing dreadfull to this Kingdome, it hauing ſo often ſmarted by it; and the burnt childe feares the fire. But it may be more dreadfull to vs now, then euer; becauſe we

haue within vs, many home-bred and domeſticall enemies, who will betray vs; who (as we may iuſtly feare) will ioyne hands with this forraigne foe, in working our confuſion. Wee haue eſpecially two domeſticall foes, who make a forraigne foe more to be feared:—

                  
                     Peccata.
                  
                  
                     Papiſtae.
                  
               
            
            Firſt, our ſinnes, they are our chiefe, capitall Enemies; becauſe they worke God to be our enemie: Perditio tua ex te O Iſrael: Thy deſtruction, O England, will come from thy ſelfe; the Snakes which we breed in our owne boſomes, will be the firſt that will ſting vs to death. Solum peccatum homicida; Sin alone is the murthrer, the bloud-ſucker that (I feare) will ouerthrowe all: this was the knife that cut the throate of Adam and all his poſteritie: Sinne it was, and nothing but ſinne, that cauſed the old world to be drowned, Sodome to be burned, Pharaoh to be plagued, Corah to be ſwallowed, Achan to be ſtoned, Haman to be hanged, Iudah to be captiuated: Sinne, and nothing but ſinne, thruſt Caine out of mans preſence, man out of Gods preſence, Adam out of Paradiſe, Angels out of Heauen. When Nicephoras Phocas had built a mighty wall about his Pallace, for his owne ſecuritie, in the night hee heard a voice crying vnto him;Cedren hiſt pag. 542.
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                though he built as high as the clowdes, yet the Citie might eaſily be taken, there was a Traitor within it, that would betray it, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the ſinne within would ouerthrowe all: So imagine we were what we are not: imagine we were as well prouided, as I could wiſh we were; as ſtrong as we could deſire;

Imagine our Name were ready; all our Shipps tigged, manned, and victualled; all our Ports and Block-houſes fortified; all our Coaſts guarded; all our Beacons watched; all our Caſtles repaired; all our men Armed; and our Land inuiron'd with a wall of iron round about: yet it is to be feared, we haue a Traytour within that will betray vs all, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the euill, the ſinne which is within the Land will ſpoyle all, vnleſſe we repent, vnleſſe God bee mercifull vnto vs. There are eſpecially three ſinnes, which are great enemies to the State; to the ſtrength and welfare of this Kingdome; and which (vnleſſe, they be in time ſuppreſt) will gnaw the very heart ſtrings thereof aſonder; Pride, Gluttony, Drunkenneſſe; vpon which three, more is conſumed waſtfully, then would maintaine a ſtrong and ſufficient Army, able to withſtand any forraigne force: the Drunkards idle expences would ſerue to victuall the Ships; the Gluttons ſuperfluity would feede a Campe; our exceſſe in apparell would ſhorethen cloath an Army.
            The ſecond domeſticall foe, that makes a forraigne foe more dreadfull to vs, are the Papiſts; falſe-hearted, Spaniſh-hearted Papiſts I meane; who haue a tongue for the King, and a heart for his enemies; Iacobs voyce, Eſaus hands: who if the day ſhould come, would bee glad to ſet their helping hand to cut the throat of their natiue Country.
            If all were true within our ſelues, we neede nor ſo much to feare a forraigne Enemy; but what a weake and vnſtable thing, Regnum diuiſum, is, our Sauiour tells vs, it is feeble, impotent, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , it cannot ſtand, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , it comes to deſolation, Math.
               
12.25. One ſaid of the Thracians, that they were the ſtrongeſt Nation of the world; and yet they were but weake: Strong and weake too, how could that be? Yes: they were ſtrong, ſo long as they were true among themſelues, and ioyned and vnited all their forces together: they were weake, being diuided, and at variance one againſt another. Wee are like the Thracians; ſtrong and weake: wee haue the name of a powerfull, and ſtrong Nation; and this were true, if we were all true within our ſelues, and held altogether in one: but conſidering the faction and diuiſion which is in our Land; conſidering how many well-wiſhers the Spaniard hath, and what a potent party the Pope hath in this Land, wee are but weake. And herein lyes all our feare, all our Enemies hope: for if we haue falſe brethren amongſt vs; who will bee ready at euery turne to open the dore, and let the Thiefe in: if we haue flye Foxes, who will ſhew the way, for the wilde Bore to deſtroy, and wilde Beaſts to deuoure: If we haue Vipers, who will reioyce to gnaw out the bowels of their owne mother: If there be Canaanites in the Land, who will be prickes in our ſides, and thornes in our eyes; a ſnare and deſtruction to vs; who, if the time ſhould come, would riſe againſt vs, and help our Enemies; we are but weake, we haue cauſe to feare. Ieruſalem had not ſo ſoone beene wonne by Veſpatians ſonne, had it not beene for ciuill diſcord within the Citie; and nothing more to bee feared for the ruine of our Nation, then ciuill diſſention, domeſticall foes. Therfore let vs vſe the beſt means we can, for the diminiſhing, &amp; ſuppreſſing of them: for the firſt domeſticall foe; ſinne; we may euery

one ſet a helping hand, to the ſuppreſſion of it: euery man will bee ready to perſecute and execute a Traytour; let vs make ſpeede to execute this archtraytour ſinne; let vs hate it in others, loathe it in our ſelues: whatſoeuer ſins we find ourſelues guilty of, let vs now at laſt forſake them; kill, mortifie, &amp; crucifie them: ſo ſhall we not neede ſo much to feare a forraign foe, if this domeſticall foe be cruſh'd vnder.
            And though it lye not in euery mans power to ſubuert the ſecond, yet let vs pray vnto God to conuert them: as for thoſe which will not be conuerted, let vs beſeech God to continue it in the heart of his Maieſtie, and the Magiſtrates, whō it concernes, to curb them and keepe them vnder: not to let them haue the reines too much at liberty, leſt they take head; &amp; like a pampred Palfry throw their Rider, &amp; bring a ruine to their King and Country in the end.
            But imagine they ſhould all proue true Subiects, and abhor to giue any ayde to a forraigne foe: (yet how can they be truſted, hauing ſo often tript?) but imagine the Leopard ſhould change his ſpots, and the black More his skinne; imagine they ſhould become new men, and refuſe to ayde the Spaniard in the Popes quarrell, and at the Popes commaund; yet we haue cauſe ſtill to feare: for this Enemie is of ſufficient power himſelfe alone. It is a ſtrong foe: which was the ſecond property. Compared in my Text to an Eagle, to a flying Eagle: What is the ſtrength of Spaine the world knowes; of what power hee is ioyning his Forces with the Eagle, (I meane with the Emperour whoſe Armes and Enſigne is the Eagle,) Chriſtendome hath felt by wofull and ſorrowfull experience: What hath Spaine
               
of late dayes vndertaken with the Eagle, or for the Eagle, or vnder the Enſigne of the Eagle, but they haue effected it, and gone thorough with it to the purpoſe? Bohaemia is ſubdued, Sileſia vanquiſhed, Morauia conquered, the Palſ graue oppreſſed, the Laut-graue diſtreſſed, Breda ſacked, and all by the combination of Spaine with the Eagle.
            
            The Spaniard is now ſtronger then euer hee was: all this time of our long peace, wherein wee haue ſlept ſecurely, in vtramque aurem, without any feare, without any care, neuer thinking of a wett day to come; they haue done all they can to ſtrengthen themſelues, and to prepare for this time of war: all this whil that we haue ſought &amp; ſued for peace, they haue more then made themſelues ready for battell: their huge Armado in 88. was nothing to the number of Ships which now they haue. So that comparing our weakneſſe, with their ſtrength; their skilfulneſſe, with our vnaptneſſe; their readineſſe, with our want of experience; their ſedulity, with our ſecuritie; our danger is great: we haue no better refuge, then to fly to the mercy &amp; protection of the Almighty, who hath hitherto mightily defended vs. Ariſe therefore, O Lord God of Hoſts, maintaine thine owne cauſe, and fight for vs; bee thou aſſiſtant to the Armies of our Friends and Allies; proſper thou the Worke of that renowned King of Denmarke, who is now in the Field, to fight thy bartell, ô proſper thou his handy worke: for if they ſhould miſcarry or ſit ſtill for want of ſupply, wo be to vs; in the next place haue at England, looke to thy houſe Dauid:
            
            Tua res agitur paries cum proximus ardet.
            
               
               Gebal, and Ammon, and Amalek; Spaine, and the Pope, and the Eagle, would all flye vpon vs; combine and conioine all their forces to deuoure vs. GOD therefore in mercy looke downe from heauen vpon vs, helpe, aide, defend, and deliuer his poore Church; For if they ſhould get the Maſterie, wee muſt expect no mercy: It is a Sterne Foe: which was the third property. A Nation of a fierce, cruell, or barbarous countenance, which will not regard the perſon of the olde, nor haue compaſſion of the young.
            
            Fierce and cruell they are, as being Papiſts; more cruell as they are Spaniards: The rudiments of their Religion teach them to bee bloudy and cruell towards vs;Alco
                     •
                  a Azoar. 2.3.6. Vid. Phil. Morn. lib. de veritat. relig. Chriſt c. 33. p. 608. For as Mahomet in his Alcharon, promiſeth the higheſt ſeat in heauen, to him that kills moſt Chriſtians, Interficite diſperdite, quo maior ſtrages, eo dignior &amp; inſ
                     •
                  gnior in Paradiſo locus: Kill them. ſlay them, ſpare them not, the more of them ye deſtroy, the more worthy and eminent place ſhall yee haue in Paradiſe. So the Pope and Ieſuits make it a matter meritorious to kill Proteſtants, (Heretickes as they pleaſe deſpightfully to terme vs) yea the more of vs they murther, the more glorious reward they ſhall haue in heauen.
            More cruell, as they are Spaniards; The very grimme lookes of a Spaniard threatens bloud and ſlaughter; like the Wolfe they ſucke cruelty from their mothers breaſts: The Spaniſh Nation (ſaith Quicchiardine) are couetous, and deceitfull, and where they be at libertie, exceeding outragious, tyrannous, and very proud and inſolent▪
                Where they are Conquerours, they put all to the Sword, and nothing ſufficeth them but bloud. I call bleeding India to witneſſe

what I ſay: where this cruell Nation hath exerciſed ſuch barbarous tyranny, and made ſuch infinite effuſion of humane bloud, as it ſeemes incredible ſuch monſters ſhould liue in the ſhapes of men:Crudelitat. Hiſpan in Indies patrat. Hiſpaenice conſcript. per epiſcop Bar thol. Caſa
                     •
                  
                  ̄, natione Hiſpanum, latine excuſ. Francoſurti. 1598.
                I will relate onely the words of their owne Writers, that ye may not thinke it a calumniation caſt vpon them. Bartholomaeus Caſas or Caſaus, a Biſhop of their owne, who liued in that Countrey, and was (as he ſaith) oculatus testis, an eye witneſſe of their doings, hath written a Booke of it, Dedicaring it to the King of Spaine; out of which, giue mee leaue to produce ſome inſtances.
            Hee there affirmes that neuer ſince the beginning of the World, was ſuch an hauocke of people made, as the Spaniards haue made in the Indies.
            
            
               
                  Pag. 7.
               That more then ten Realmes greater then all Spaine, with Arragon and Portugall, and thoſe repleniſhed with multitudes of people, as any Countrey in the world, are all turned into a Deſert: that of three Millions in Hiſpaniola, they left ſcarce three hundred aliue.
               
                  Pag. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               That within the ſpace of 40 yeares, 50 Millions of People were deſtroyed.
               
                  Pag. 6. 
               So ſoone as the Nation was diſcouered, the Spaniards like Wolues, and Lions, and Tygers long famiſhed, entred, and did nothing but teare them in peeces, and murther, and torment them by cruelties neuer heard or ſcene before. In three moneths they
               
                  Pag. 25. 
               ſtarued to death 7000. children:
               
                  Pag. 96. 
               they threw downe from the top of a mountaine ſeauen hundred men together, and daſh'd them all to peeces.
               
                  Pag. 4. 
               At one time they murthered 2000 Gentlemen who were Lords ſonnes, and the flowre of all the Nobilitie.
               
                  Pag. 82. 
               They cut of the Noſes and Lips of 200 at one time, and ſo ſent them to their fellowes, a ruefull ſpectacle to behold.
               
                  Pag. 
                  
                     ••
                  . 
               They would lay wagers

who ſhould moſt nimbly, and with moſt dexterity butcher men. 
               
                  Pag. 67. 
               They traced the miſerable people like horſes, and made them carrie their ſtuffe; who dying vpon the highwayes for feebleneſſe, when they were layd on with ſtaues, and had their teeth broken out with the pommels of their ſwords, to make them riſe from the ground where they lay for faintneſſe, would ſay, I can doe no more, kill mee here out-right, I deſire to dye. 
               
                  Pag. 31. &amp; 78. 
               When any one fainted vpon the way with hunger and thirſt; they would not vouchſafe to beſtowe ſo much labour as to vnchaine him; but ſtrike off his head, leauing that in one place, the body in another. 
               
                  Pag. 20. 
               They would make them carrie a hundred weight, one hundred or two hundred miles together, wherewith their backes and ſhoulders were wrung, and galled like our pack-horſes. 
               
                  Pag. 8. 
               They vſed them not as Beaſts, but as the dung, and filth of the earth.
            
            
               When they had wrought all day in the Mines (ſaith Sequanus) at night if they miſſed neuer ſo little of their taske, 
               Praefat. ad Anton. Auguſt. praefix. ante Oſer. de geſt. Eman. pag. 15.
                
               they were ſtripped ſtarke naked, bound hand and foote to a forme, ſcourged all ouer with whip-cord, or a Bulls Pizzle, then ſcalding Pitch was powred on them: and laſtly, their bodies thus rent with ſtripes, were waſhed ouer with Salt and Pepper, and ſo they lay.
            
            The fore-said Biſhop proteſteth, 
                  Pag. 35. 
               that no tong
                     •
                  e, skill, knowledge, or induſtry of man is able to recount the dreadfull doing of theſe capitall enemies of mankind; the actions which they committed were neither of Christians, nor of men, but of deuils. 
               
                  Pag. 9. 
               Any Captaine durſt aduenture to rauiſh the greateſt Queene, or Lady in the Country.
            
            Such was the mercileſſe cruelty of this blood-ſucking generation, that they tooke none to mercy: 
                  Pag. 10. 
               They ſpared no age, no ſexe, not women with childe,

nor ſuch as lay in Child bed, but would rip vp their bellies, and choppe them in peeces. 
               
                  Pag. 11. 
               They would plucke ſucking Infants from their Mothers breſts, and taking them by the heeles, daſh cut their braines againſt the Rockes, or hurle them into the Riuers. 
               
                  Pag 99. &amp; 108. 
               They trained vp Maſtiue dogs, of purpoſe to rend in peeces, and deuoure the people, and for that end, fed them with mans fleſh, hauing a waies a great number of Indians fetterd in chaines whom they murthered like Swine, as their dogs needed, to feed on them. And he telleth of one 
                  Pag. 60. 
               Who wanting dogs meate, tooke a ſucking Babe from the mother, and chopping off the armes and thighes, fed his Doggs firſt with them, then with the reſt of the body before her face.
            
            Yea they did not onely feed their doggs but alſo themſelues with mans fleſh; 
                  Pag. 50. 
               Whole Armies of them liuing ſometime like Cannibals, eating nothing but the fleſh of the Indians; For prouiſion whereof an ordinary Shambles was kept in the Campe, of the fleſh of men, and young children, which they roſted, and fed vpon; yea and many times, men muſt be cruelly butchered onely to haue their hands and feet, which the Spaniard counted a dainty daſh. Theſe are the relations of their own Biſhop.
            
               
                  Pag. 46.
               In the Prouince of Guatimala, the Prince accompanied with his Nobles, welcomed them with Muſicke, and the richeſt gifts the Countrey affoorded: The Spaniards (after their vſuall cuſtom) demanded Gold; they made anſwere, they had it not: (for indeed their Countrey yeelded little, or none:) and for no other offence but this, they burnt them all ali
                     •
                  e.
            
            
               
                  Pag. 29.
               Another Prince of his owne accord, in kindneſſe, brought them a great preſent of Gold, and they in requitall ryed him bakward faſt to a ſtake, with his feet hanging

ouer a gentle fire, to make him confeſſe more: he ſent home for all he had; yet they were not ſatisfied, but would haue more: the poore Prince not hauing wherwith to content thoſe vnſatiable Horſe-leaches; they kept him in that vnmercifull &amp; cruell torture, till the marrow dropped from his bones, and ſo he died. A pittifull reward for ſuch a courteſie.
            To auoide ſuch like cruelty of theirs, the poore people would hang themſelues, with their wiues and children about them; the women deſtroy their conceptions, and in griefe and deſpaire daſh their owne childrens braines againſt the ſtones, leſt they ſhould fall into the Spaniards hands: Some of them profeſt, that if the Spaniards went to heauen when they were dead, they would neuer deſire to come there; As the 
               
                  Pag. 28. 
               Prince of the Iſle of Cuba, who being tyed to a ſtake to be burnt, a Franciſcan came to him, telling him of God, and of the Articles of our faith, which if hee would beleeue, he might goe to heauen to eternall happineſſe; if not hee muſt goe to hell to euerlaſting torments. The Prince after a little pauſe, asked the Friar, Vtrum etiam Hiſpanis caelorum ianua pateret, If the Spaniards went to heauen? Yea, quoth the Friar; O ſaid the Prince, (without any further deliberation) then will not I goe to heauen, but rather to hell, where I may once be free from that cruell Nation. Theſe are the words of their owne Biſhop, who writeth ten times more in deteſtation of it to the King of Spaine, 
               
                  Pag. 100. proteſting oftentimes that hee doth not ſet downe the thouſandth part of the cruelties vſed: and we may the rather beleeue him, becauſe many other who write the Indian Hiſtory, relate the like cruelties. This it was that made Benzo, who liued alſo in the Countrey, and

was an eye-witneſſe of their actions, to cry out; Benz. hiſt. Ind. 
               O quot Nerones, quot Domitiani, quot Commodi, quot Baſſiani, quot immites Dioniſij, eas terras peragrauere? O how many Neroes and Domitians, and ſuch like vnmercifull tyrants haue harrowed thoſe Countries? Is not this the Nation ſpoken of in my Text, of a fierce and cruell countenance, not reſpecting the olde, nor pittying the young?
            Now if they vſed ſuch cruelty againſt thoſe poore people which neuer did them hurt, what would they doe with vs, againſt whom they beare an imbred hatred, againſt whom they are ſo inraged? Thoſe people neuer offended them, the foreſaid Biſhop affirmeth 
                  Pag. 19. &amp; 101. That during all the time they were murdered, and made away ſo cruelly, they neuer committed any one offence againſt the Spaniards, that deſerued puniſhment by the Law of man. Now if they vſed ſuch Barbarous tyranny againſt them, what wil they doe with vs, by whom they are prouoked and ſtirred vp? Aſſuredly, if our Land ſhould fall into their hands, (which GOD for his mercy, and compaſſion ſake avert) they would not onely put all the chiefe Inhabitants to the Sword, (for that were not a death bad enough) but inuent ſtrange, exquiſit, and new found tortures for Engliſh-men, ſuch is their monſtrous ſpleene toward vs.
            Let no man promiſe better to himſelfe; their cruelty extends to their friends, as well as to their foes: in the Powder-treaſon Innocents and nocents ſhould haue beene blowne vp both together: the Duke Medina profeſt, that his ſword knew no difference, betweene Catholikes and Heretickes: and howſoeuer ſome in our Land flatter themſelues, and

repoſe great confidence in the Spaniſh Nation; yet if they ſhould haue the day, themſelues may chance to rue it: their hands would bee heauy vpon them alſo, neither would there be any reſpect of perſons; Papiſts as wel as Proteſtants ſhould all to the ſlaughter: they would ſpeede no better then the Catholickes did at the ſack of Antwerpe; the Spaniſh ſword ſhould ſpeede and haſten their iourney to the other world: or than thoſe falſe hearted Britaines did, who called in a forraigne Nation, the Saxons, to helpe them againſt their lawfull Soueraigne; but they in ſtead of ayding, deſtroyed them; expulſed them out of their Land; diſpoſſeſſed Vortigerne the vſurper of his kingdome; ſlew at one meeting two hundred, ſeauenty one, of the chiefe Barons and Nobles: the Britaines fearing no ſuch Treachery; for they had paſt promiſe each to other to come vnarmed; but the Saxons brought priuie kniues which (the watch-word being giuen) they ſheathed in the bodies of the Britiſh Lords: ſuch fidelity would theſe men finde in the Spaniards, ſhould they bee Conquerers, who now wiſh ſo much for their ayde and aſſiſtance: they are too politicke to truſt them, that were vntruſty to their naturall Prince: Religion then would make no difference; Religion is the leaſt thing they care for; Religion is but a cloake for their couetouſneſſe and boundleſſe ambition: they haue a deeper reach in all their enterpriſes. Dominion, and Soueraignety. Religion was pretended in their Weſt Indian voyage, the glory of God and the conuerſion of Infidels; but the miſerable people found the contrary, by a wofull experience of many their houſes, Cities, Countries, ſacked, ranſacked,

turned vpſide downe, and the duſt of all their ground moſt narrowly ſifted &amp; ſearched, that a wedge of gold was Deus Chriſtianorum, the God of the Chriſtians. And this they would hold aloft, and make proclamation among themſelues, Eu Deus Chriſtianorum! Behold the God of the Chriſtians! Propter hoc è Caſtella in terras noſtras venere: For this they came out of Caſtile into our Land; for this they are at warre among themſelues; for this they kill and deſtroy one another.
            This it is, or ſome ſuch matter, that makes their teeth ſo water at our Land; the riches, the plenty, the fertility thereof: their poore hungry dyet in Spaine, feeding for the moſt part vpon colde Sallets, and ſower ſawces, graſſe and hearbs, fine Oranges and Lymonds, ſharpens their appetites to our abundance, and full meales. O, if wee could but once game little England, wee might feede like Farmers; the world were all our owne: we ſhould then haue ſuch a Store-houſe, to furniſh our Armies with Munition and Prouiſion, that wee would quickly bee Lords of all Chriſtendome, and make our King the Catholicke King indeede. The Lowe-Countries would be but a breakefaſt, France but a dinner, all Chriſtendome beſide but a ſupper, for theſe rauenous Harpies. And this is the beſt can be expected from them; to haue all that euer we haue taken from vs: if the Tyger ſhould loſe his fierceneſſe, and the Wolfe his bloodineſſe; if they ſhould extend vnwonted clemencie, and take ſome to mercy; yet they muſt looke to loſe all, and to be made Slaues and Vaſſalls: for this is the calamity that followes the Inuaſion: The ſame ſhall eate the fruit of thy Cattell,

and the fruit of thy Land, vntill thou be deſtroyed, and he ſhall leaue thee neither corne, wine, nor oyle, neither the encreaſe of thy Kine, nor the flockes of thy ſheepe, vntill he haue brought thee to nought.
            
            A calamity incident to an inuaſion, to a conqueſt: the natiues of a vanquiſhed land, muſt looke for no better, then to loſe all; if they eſcape with life, it is the mercy of the Enemie.2 Reg. 24.13. When Iudah was inuaded and ouer-runne by the Babylonians, all the riches of the Land became a prey vnto the Enemie; the Church treaſure, the Kings treaſure, and all things elſe; the Princes, and Nobles, and all the chiefe Inhabitants loſt their poſſeſſions, were put to death, or made bond-ſlaues; onely ſome of the poore of the Land, were left to be Vine dreſſers, and Husbandmen, to till the Land for the vſe of their Enemies. But what neede wee goe ſo farre for examples? Looke but backe to the laſt Conqueſt of our Land by the Normans: though they ſubmitted, yet did not the Conquerour diſpoſe of all things at his pleaſure? Search our Chronicles, ye ſhall finde it ſo;M. Fox act. &amp; mon. p
                     •
                  . 155. &amp; 165. vlt. edit. Hee gaue away all the poſſeſſions of the Engliſh men to his owne followers, and Souldiers, in ſo much that they were forced to hold it vnder them, as their Slaues and Vaſſalls; hee altered the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the Land: rooted out all the Engliſh Nobility, left ſcarce one houſe of them ſtanding;Hen. Hunting. lib. 6.
                (as Henry Huntington affirmes) permitted no Natiue to beare any office of rule or honour, in the Church or Common-wealth: burthened them with intollerable exactions; yea, to ſuch calamities were they brought, that for many years after, it was counted a great ſhame to be called an Engliſh man.
            
               But all this was mercy, in reſpect of that miſery, which theſe men would bring vpon vs, ſhould they be Conquerours: they would not only take all from vs; caſt vs out of our poſſeſſions; make vs their ſlaues and vaſſalls; alter the lawes and cuſtomes; extirpate all the Nobility: neither ſhould it onely be counted a ſhame to be called an Engliſh-man, but they would roote out the very name of an Engliſh-man, from vnder heauen; and bring vs euen vnto nought, (as it is in my Text) ſuch is their monſtrous and implacable malice toward our Nation.
            Where then, O where are the hearts of men, that they haue no ſence, nor feeling of this? Shall wee reſemble thoſe worldlings of whom St. Auguſtine complaines, Fortius diligentes resſuas, quam ſeipſos: Loue our wealth more then our ſelues, more then our liues, more then our wiues, more then our children, more then our Country, more then the Goſpell? Shall we hazard the loſſe of all, houſes, lands, liuings, liues, liberties, freedome, religion, rather then part with any thing? Shall we chuſe rather to haue it all, our ſelues and all, fall into our Enemies hands; then beſtow the leaſt part, in offending our Enemies, in defending our ſelues? O no: God forbid: Let Conſtantinoples miſery bee our warning; they ſmarted for it; let vs take heede, left we drink' of the ſame bitter cup.
            When that Imperiall Citie was beſieged by Mahomet the great; the good Emperour did what hee could to the vttermoſt of his power,
                  Ric. Knowlles his Turkiſh Hiſtory, in the life of Mahomet the great. for the defence thereof: ſolde the very Church Plate, and all his Iewels to pay the Souldiers: and hauing no more left of his owne, with teares in his eyes, he beſought his

couetous Subiects to lend him ſupplies; or elſe all would be loſt, there was no remedy: They all pleaded pouerty, and ſtill proteſted they had it not; they w
                  •
               r
                  •
                growne poore for want of Trading: and thus by their backwardneſſe in not ſupplying their Soueraigne, and couetouſneſſe in keeping in their money was that famous Citie loſt. For when the Turkes had taken it, they found it to be the richeſt thing of the world; for Treaſure, Money, Plate, Iewels; meeting in priuate mens houſes with whole Cheſts full of gold: wherewith they were ſo enriched, that 'tis a Prouerbe among them at this day, if a man grow ſuddenly rich, Hee hath beene at the ſacking of Conſtantinople. They became a wonderment vnto the Turkes, that men hauing ſuch abundance, would part with nothing for their owne defence: for if they had in time beſtowed ſome ſmall part at the Emperours requeſt, they might haue ſafely enioyed the reſt, and not beene made a prey vnto their Enemies: whereas by their cloſe-handedneſſe they loſt all, and fell into moſt lamentable bondage. It would make ones heart bleed to read the ſtory of it: Thoſe that were not ſlaine, were at the Souldiers diſpoſe; what, of whomſoeuer he could lay hands on, was his owne: the noble Gentlewomen and great Ladies, with their beautifull Children, who lately flowed with all worldly wealth, and pleaſure, became the poore and miſerable bond-ſlaues of moſt baſe and contemptible Raſcalls, who made no more reckoning of them, then of dogges (as the ſtory ſaith.) There might the Parents ſee the wofull miſery of their beloued Children, the Children of their Parents; the Husband the ſhamefull abuſe of his Wife,

the Wife of her Husband. The great Turke feaſting his Baſſaes and chiefe Captaines for many dayes together, cauſed, at euery Banquet certaine of the chiefe Captiues, both men and women, of whom many were of the Imperiall ſtocke, to be in his preſence cruelly put to death, as he and his Turkes ſate banquetting: ſawcing his meate with the bloud of the Chriſtians, chearing himſelfe with their miſery; deeming his Feaſts much more magnificent, with that dolefull muſicke of the dying Captiues: which cruelty he vſed euery day, till hee had deſtroyed all the Grecian Nobility, and all the chiefe Citizens. A pittifull calamity! wee condemne them of folly, and ſay they deſerued no better: God graunt the world condemne not vs of the like folly, and ſay we deſerue worſe; becauſe we are armed, being warned: their miſhap ſhould be our caueat: If we doe not in time take heede, it is like to fare with vs, as it did with them. I feare we keepe our wealth, for our Enemies to make merry with: If we part not with ſomething for our owne defence, wee are in danger to loſe all, as wel as they: and to come to worſe bondage and miſery; more mercy is to bee expected from the very Turkes, then from the bloudy Spaniards.
            We haue a moſt gracious King, (whom the King of heauen long preſerue with a proſperous and happy Raigne; and let all good Chriſtians ſay, Amen) who is more carefull and deſirous of our ſafety and happines, then we our ſelues: his wants are great, his expenſes greater for the common good: what charge he is at, both at home, and abroad cannot be vnknowne vnto vs: he hath a ſtrong and powerfull

enemy, which wants neither meanes, nor malice. O let not vs diſcourage him by our backwardneſſe; Vltrapoſſe, non eſt eſſe; he hath, he doth, he will doe what he may, more he cannot. There is a thing called, nervus Belli, without which Warre cannot ſubſiſt: If we ſhrinke in theſe ſinewes, and withdrawe the nouriſhment, will not the whole body be in danger to come to ruine? And verely (from my heart I ſpeake) vnleſſe He be in time ſupplied, wee ſhall all rue it: the Spaniard will reioyce to worke vpon ſuch an aduantage. That man were mad, that would not part with a penny to enioy a pound; and al the world will condemne our Nation, if we loſe our Countrey for lacke of defence, hauing ſuch meanes to defend it. It is euery mans caſe, let vs all lay it to heart.
            I haue heard of a Marques of Brandenburge, who was wont to ſay, he had in his Countrie, three Monaſteries which were three Monſters: one of the Dominicans, who had abundance of Corne, and yet had no Land to ſow; another of the Franciſcans, who were full of Money, and yet receiued no Rents: the third of Saint Thomas order, whoſe monkes had a great many Children, yet had no wines. Wee are like to be a Monſter, and wonder, a Prouerbe, and a common talke to all people, as it is verſe 37. For vnleſſe our Soueraigne be ſupplied, that ſome courſe may ſpeedily be taken for our defence, wee ſhall haue neither Lands, nor Rents, nor Money, nor Corne, nor Wiues, nor Children, nor any thing elſe in ſafety, but all will fall into our enemies hands: Lord open our eyes, that we may ſee the danger we are in, and in time prouide for it, leſt when it be too late, wee wiſh wee had. When you ſee this ſtrange, ſtrong,
               
and ſterne Foe at your gates; your Countrey waſted, your Houſes fired, your Citie beſieged: when you heare the clangor of the Trumpet, the clamor of the wounded, the clattering of the harneſſe, the beating of the Drumme, the roaring of the Ordnance, the thundring of the Cannon: when you ſee your wiues rauiſhed before your faces, your friends ſlain, your children murdered, your Infants daſhed againſt the ſtones, or broached on the Pike; and all the Land made nothing but the Shambles of Castillian and Ignatian Butchers; then you will wiſh (but alas too late) would to GOD wee had in time beene warned; would we had parted with halfe our eſtates, rather then loſe all, and come to this lamentable ſlauery and miſery. God in mercy put it into all our hearts to conſider ſeriouſly of it; that euery man according to his ability, may condeſcend vnto the neceſſitie of the time.
            Now for a concluſion: All that hath beene ſpoken, may ſerue as a ſtrong motiue, to ſtirre vs vp with ſpeed to turne vnto God, that hee may turne vnto vs, and turne from vs this fearefull calamitie: Let vs repent heartily, and cry vnto him mightily, to ſpare vs, to be mercifull vnto vs. Vnceſſant praiers, repentant teares are moſt powerfull to procure Gods mercy, to diuert his iudgement: he is mercifull and will receiue our Prayers; he is pittifull and will regard our teares. His Sword was once drawn againſt Niniueh, a fearefull doome pronounced; Yet fourty dayes and Niniueh ſhall be deſtroyed. The King, and his Nobles, and all the people fall to repentance; they faſt, they pray, they humble themſelues to ſackcloath and aſhes: their ſinnes cry for

iudgement, their repentance for mercy: there was a contention betweene them, which ſhould out-cry the other: their wickedneſſe aſcends vp on high, knockes at heauen gate, clamours lowd in the eares of God; Iuſtice, my Lord, vengeance, vengeance. Their repentance aſcends higher, and cries lowder in the eares of God; mercy, good Lord, mercy; ſpare vs, O ſpare vs, we beſeech thee. Repentance gets the victory; GOD is not ſo much enclined to iudgement, as to mercy: he regards not the cry of ſinne, if he once heare the cry of ſinners: he accepts their ſorrow and humiliation; he puts vp his ſword, hee holds his hand; hee ſees them turne from their wicked wayes, and he turnes from his fierce wrath: he ſees them repent of their euill deedes, and he alſo repents of the euill hee pronounced againſt them. The ſinnes of our Land like the ſinns of Nintueh, are aſcended vp on high, and cry alowde for reuenge to the GOD of heauen: but our religious King hath proclaim'd a Faſt; hee and his Nobles haue led the way; if we, with him, and them, ſend vp repentance, and prayers, and teares, to cry alowd in Gods eares; they will dull the cry of our ſinnes, that he ſhall not heare it; and dull the edge of his ſword that it ſhall not wound vs.
            Wicked Ahab had grieuouſly ſinned, and a terrible ſentence was paſt vpon him; yet vpon his repentance though it were but ſuperficiall in outward ſhew,1 King. 21.19. GOD was mercifull and ſpared him: Seeſt thou not (ſayes God to Elijah) how Ahab is humbled before me? becauſe he ſubmitteth himſelfe before mee, I will not bring that euill in his dayes, but in his ſonnes dayes will I bring euill vpon is houſe. If God were ſo

mercifull to that wicked man vpon his falſe &amp; fained repentance, how much more if we turne vnto him, with true &amp; vnfained repentance will he be mercifull to vs, &amp; not bring this euill in our daies?
            A ſecond meanes to diuert this iudgement, is vnceſſant prayer: wonderfull is the force of praier with the God of heauen: when the Moabites and Ammonites, and they of mount Seir, came vp againſt Ieruſalem with an huge Army; the people were amazed, not knowing what to doe, for they were not able to ſtand before ſuch a multitude in battell: Iehoſophat proclaimes a Faſt, the people all fall to their prayers;2 Chro. 2
                     •
                  . deſire GOD to ayde, defend, and deliuer them: O Lord God of our Fathers, art not thou in heauen? and raigneſt not thou ouer all the Kingdomes of the Heathen? and in thine hand is power and ſtrength, and none is able to withſtand thee: O our God, wilt not, thou iudge them? for there is no ſtrength in vs to withstand this great multitude, neither doe wee know what to doe; but our eyes are toward thee. And ſuch was the force of their prayers, that GOD gaue them the victory without fighting any ſtroke: the Lord himſelfe became the Warriour, and laid ambuſhments for their Enemies, (ſaith the Text) and made them ſheath their ſwords in one anothers bowels, till they were all deſtroyed.
            When Senecharib came into the land of Iudah with a mighty Hoſt;2 Chron. 32. and tooke the ſtrong and defenced Cities thereof: Hezekiah and the people what did they? In the firſt place they vſed the beſt meanes for their ſafety; they ſtopped vp the fountaines of water, that their Enemies might

not bee refreſhed therewith; they built all the broken wall, they raiſed vp the Towers, they repaired Millo in the Citie of Dauid, they made many Darts and Shields, they muſtered the people of the Land, and ſet Captaines ouer them: teaching vs what to do; It is not enough to ſit ſtill, and cry, Lord haue mercy vpon vs, without vſing meanes for our defence and ſafety; for GOD workes by meanes be it ſmall or great; and therefore Hezekiah vſeth the beſt meanes hee can, to withſtand and keepe out the Enemie: and then he and his people pray vnto God for a good ſucceſſe, and rely on him, as then ſureſt ſtay for help and deliuerance: Feare not, neither bee afraid of the King of Aſhur; nor for all the multitude that is with him, for there be more with vs, then with him; with him is an arme of fleſh, but with vs is the Lord our GOD, for to helpe vs, and to fight our battels. And the Lord ſeeing their confidence, and hearing their prayers, gaue them a meruailous deliuerance; ſent forth a Captaine out of his owne Hoſt, a holy Angell which in one night ſlew an hundred ſomeſcore and fiue thouſand of their Enemieſ. So through this ſtrong and ſterne foe ſhould come againſt vs; yet let vs not be diſmayed, if we repent heartily for our ſinnes, pray earneſtly vnto God, truſt to him; no doubt but hee will in mercy looke vpon vs, and worke ſome meanes for their confuſion, as hee did in 88. beyond our expectation: there bee more with vs then with them; GOD is on our ſide; it is his quarrell; he will defend his Church, if we continue

conſtant in his ſeruice, feruent in prayer.
            One Moſes by prayer, ſaued a whole Nation, from a fearefull deſtruction: when the people forgetting Gods commandement, made them a God of gold, and worſhipped it, and ſo prouoked the holy one of Iſraell, that hee was minded to make a cleane riddance, and conſume them vtterly for it. Moſes ſtepping into the gap, and praying for them, ſtayed his hand. The people ſinne, God is angry, drawes his ſword, lifts vp his hand to ſtrike; and Moſes lifts vp his hands in prayer: and ſo long as he prayes, God cannot ſtrike, his hands were held by Moſes prayers:Exod. 32.11. 
               Let me alone, Moſes, (ſaith God) let me alone, that my wrath may waxe hot againſt them, for I will conſume them at once, but I will make of thee a mighty people.
            It ſeemes Moſes by his prayers did hinder and hold God backe from deſtroying Iſraell; prayer is like a chaine or manacle to tye the hands of an angry Lord: Vincit inuincibilem, It ouercomes him, that ouercomes all things. And therefore Moſes he ſtill prayes, O Lord turne from thy fierce wrath, and change thy minde from this euill toward thy people: and ſuch was the power of his prayer, that GOD altered his ſentence, turned from his anger, deſtroyed them not as he had intended.
            Though Gods anger bee kindled againſt this Land for our ſinnes, yet if ſome Moſes doe ſtand in the gap, if ſome holy, deuout, and faithfull men doe intercede for it, no doubt but God will bee mercifull: And herein lyes our ſtrongeſt conſolation;

for as God would haue ſpared ſinfull Sodome if there had bin but fifty, but fiue and forty, but forty, but thirty, but twenty, nay but tenne righteous therein: So, vndoubtedly, it is for ſome good peoples ſake that GOD hath ſpared vs ſo long: for though many are ſinfull, yet it is to be hoped, there is here and there a Moſes that holds vp his hands; here and there a Lot that grieues for the ſinnes of the time; here and there an Abraham that makes requeſt for Sodome: for their ſakes GOD ſpares the whole, let them continue conſtant in Gods ſeruice, zealous in prayer; yea, let vs all betake our ſelues to earneſt, and hearty prayer, for now it is time and more then time ſo to doe. Spare vs good Lord, ſpare vs wee beſeech thee: O remember not our olde ſinnes and offences, but haue mercy vpon vs, and that ſoone, for elſe wee are like to come to great miſery; helpe vs O God, of and ſaluation for the glory of thy name, O deliuer vs and be mercifull vnto our ſins for thy names ſake. Or as the Prophet Ioel exhorts, Let the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord, (yea and all the people) weepe betweene the Porch and the Altar in the Lords houſe; and let them ſay, Spare thy people, O Lord, ſpare thy people, and giue not thine heritage into reproach, that the Heathen ſhould rule ouer them.
            
            Let not this furious, bloud-thirſty, and cruell Nation, worſe then the Heathen, euer ſet footing in this Kingdome, or haue dominion ouer vs: but let the Crowne flouriſh vpon his head, on whom thou haſt vouchſafed in mercy to place it; the man of thy right hand whom thou haſt made

ſtrong for thine owne ſelfe: cloath his Enemies with ſhame and confuſion: be as a wall of fire to him and his Realmes: Let thoſe that riſe vp againſt him, be like Siſera and Iabin, who periſhed at Endor, and became as the dung of the earth, make them and their Princes like Oreb and Zeb, yea make all their Princes like as Zeba and Zalmana; O my God, make them like a wheele, and as the ſtubble before the winde. Let them fall vpon the edge of the ſword, that they may be a portion for Foxes: ſo ſhall the King reioyce in thy ſtrength, exceeding glad ſhall he be of thy ſaluation. For why he putteth his truſt in thee; and in thy mercy, O thou moſt high, let him not miſcary. So we that be thy people, and Sheepe of thy Paſture, ſhall giue thee thankers for euer, and will be ſhewing forth thy praiſe from one generation to another. So ſhall thy name be glorified, thy Son magnified, thy truth defended, thy Goſpell propagated, thy poore Church comforted: which we humbly beſeech thee to graunt, (O Father of mercies, and God of all conſolation) for our bleſſed Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt his ſake; to whom with thee and thy holy Spirit, three glorious perſons, one eternall, omnipotent God, be giuen all honour, glory, praiſe and power, now and euermore.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

