
   
      
         
            Late nevves out of Barbary In a letter written of late from a merchant there, to a gentl. not long since imployed into that countrie from his Maiestie. Containing some strange particulars, of this new Saintish Kings proceedings: as they haue been very credibly related from such as were eye-witnesses.
            Late newes out of Barbary
            R. S., fl. 1613.
         
         
            
               1613
            
         
         Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02724
            STC 12857.2
            ESTC S118846
            99854053
            99854053
            19460
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02724)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19460)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 575:09)
         
         
            
               
                  Late nevves out of Barbary In a letter written of late from a merchant there, to a gentl. not long since imployed into that countrie from his Maiestie. Containing some strange particulars, of this new Saintish Kings proceedings: as they haue been very credibly related from such as were eye-witnesses.
                  Late newes out of Barbary
                  R. S., fl. 1613.
                  Harrison, John, fl. 1610-1638.
                  G. B., fl. 1613.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  [By George Eld] for Arthur Ionson,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1613.
               
               
                  Two letters, the first signed "R.S.", the second "G.B.".
                  Editor's foreword signed: I.H., i.e. John Harrison.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-C⁴.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Running title reads: Newes from Barbary.
                  Formerly STC 1377. Identified as STC 1377 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Morocco --  History --  1516-1830 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Late Newes out of BARBARY.
            
               IN A Letter written of late from a Merchant there, to a Gentl. not long ſince impolyed into that countrie from his Maieſtie.
            
            Containing ſome ſtrange particulars, of this new Saintiſh Kings proceedings: as they haue been very credibly related from ſuch as were eye-witneſſes.
            (*⁎*)
            
            Imprinted at London for Arthur Ionſon. 1613.
         
         
            
            
            An Aduertiſement to the READER.
            
               HAuing receiued this Letter following out of Barbary, from an honeſt Engliſh Merchant, who hath long time ſoiourned there, very religious, wiſe and diſcrect, and ſo knowne among the Merchants: with whom alſo my ſelfe conuerſed many moneths, during my abode in that countrie; and therafter ſhewing it as a matter of newes to ſome friends, I was at length importuned to make it common, in reſpect of the noueliy: eſt natura hominis nouitatis auida; and (as the Prouerbe is) Africa ſemper aliquid apportat noui. Thereby to ſatisfie, if not all (which) was wont to bee the Poets taske: Populo vt placerent quas feciſſet fabulas); yet at leaſtwiſe thoſe, who haue nought elſeAct. 17. 21 to doe, (like thoſe Athenians in the Acts) but either to tel or heare ſome newes: Howbeit, I hope, it mayſerue to ſome good vſe alſo for vs Chriſtians of theſe laſt daies, vpon whom the ends of the world are come: to ſee how buſily the Diuell actethForty yeers (ſayth this new ſaintiſh king or Prophet of his) &amp; then Chriſt muſt come to iudgement, as in the letter. his laſt part, now in this laſt age of the world, &amp; playeth his prize, for that he knoweth he hath but a ſhort time, 40. yeers by his own calculation, pronouncing before hand his owne condemnation. For the Lord hath ſo done his marueilous workes that they ought to be had in remembrance: And ſo

ought the deuils workes too, though in another kind, &amp; a Latere (as I may ſay) for he is the Ape &amp; imitator of God (transforming himſelfe into an Angel of light) neither can he doe any thing of himſelfe, but by Gods permiſsion as he hath power, commiſsion, and authority from him. And therein alſo many times he plaieth the Mountibank, obtruding for true and effectual workings (as the Apoſtle tearmeth them) many falſe and feigned deluſions. And whether true or falſe, his end is ſtill to deceiue, and vent his lying arts, doctrines of deuils; and therefore in ſcripture worthily ſtiled the father of lies: and his miracles, which hee worketh for confirmation thereof, lying wonders. And by theſe his ſleighty conueiances, ſometimes winding heere, ſometimes there, hath this ſubtle ſerpent gon frō about time to time, compaſſing the earth, to and fro, and walking in it to deceiue the world. And not onely the world (I meane the children of diſobedience and miſbeleefe) but if it
               Mat. 24. 24 
               were poſſible euen the very elect. And ſuch muſt bee (or rather is) the comming of Antichriſt in this laſt age of the world whereof we haue beene ſo long ſince forewarned: (little children it is the laſt time &amp;c.) Whoſe comming (as the ApoſtleIoh. 2. 18.  2.Theſſ. 2. 9. deſcribeth it) is by the effectual working of Sathan with all power and ſignes and lying wonders &amp;c. And therefore God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions that they ſhould beleeue lies: that all they might bee damned which beleeue not the truth &amp;c. O the miſerable eſtate of al miſbelieuers,

whom the deuil hath thus blinded to their vtter condemnation, which ſleepeth not. And ſuch is the ſtate and condition of theſe miſerable Moores giuen ouer beyond meaſure, to theſe idle &amp; ſuperſtitious vanities (ſo Dauid calleth them) I hate all them that hold of ſuperſtitious vanities) blind propheſies dreams, necromancy and ſuch like, wherein theſe Saints profeſse themſelues, and hold the people in ſuch awe for feare of their curſes (which many times fall out accordingly: (the deuill working together) as if they were Popes, ſuch is their ſoueraignety. As by this example yee may ſee, one of theſe fanaticall Saints now become a King. Scilicet his Babilon dextris: euen by theſe and ſuch like arts, did that ſpirituall Babylon, at the firſt that great Whore ſpoken of in the Reuelation,Reue 17. 1. 2. Theſſ. 2. 3. 
               that man of ſinne, the ſonne of perdition, now ſitting as God in the Temple of God, and ſhewing himſelfe that he is God) vnder the like pretence come to the height of his ſupremacy, not only making himſelfe a King, but inſulting euen ouer Kings and Emperours: not caring (as the prouerb is) neither for King nor Keiſer, but exalting himſelfe againſt God, and all that is called God: hat is to ſay Kings and Princes. Be wife now therfore ye Kings, whether Chriſtian or Heathen, the vſe is generall to al, beware of theſe Saints for all their hypocriticall ſhew of Holineſs. Saints in profeſſion but Deuils in practiſe. His Holineſſe catexochen; euen that holy one of Rome, (for ſo the word Saint ſignifieth: a Holy one)

               nam ſi hic mali eſt quidquam (I ſay no more) they are capital enemies to the thrones of Kings. Inſtance this Saint who (forſooth) vnder a colour of Holineſse, and ſimplicity, armed with moſt ſtrong deluſions, euen from the Deuill himſelfe) yee ſee what wonders he hath wrought againſt Mully Sidan, yea and what greater hee promiſeth: operae pretium eſt audire.
            
            But when that bridge appeareth in the mouth of the Straights, as he propheſieth, and he with all his troupes ariue in the Popes Dominions (the Pope and he in the Liſts together) then we ſhal ſee whether deuil is the ſtronger. The Lord preſerue his people from their deuilliſh deluſions. And ſo after this long Preface (too long I muſt needs confeffe for ſo ſhort a diſcourſe, but that I tould not wel cut it ſhorter) I referre it to the cenſure of the wiſe to make vſe of: beeing the chiefe and maine motiue, with the aduiſe and approbation of ſome godly Perſons, Preachers and others, why I haue publiſhed it, Which (if I finde acceptable) I may (perhaps) bee encouraged to reuiſe ſome papers of my owne, all this while throwne aſide, as touching the affaires and ſlate of that country, falling within the compaſſe of my daily obſeruation, during that my imployment
                  •
                with other accounts of my time not altogether idlie ſpent there, hauing now, but too good a leaſure (ſince the loſſe of ſo hopefull a Maiſter) for ſuch a purpoſe, God ſend vs an other comforter. And ſo once more farewel gentle Reader.
         
      
      
         
            
            Laus Deo in Saphia, 
                  the 9. of September. 1612.
            
            
               GOod Sir, in moſt hearty manner I commend mee vnto you, with deſire of your good health, and all other content to your hearts deſire, which the Lord grant you: Amen.
            Since my laſt vnto you, here is great alteration in this gouernment, as I account you haue vnderſtood before now. And becauſe Maſter N. and Maſter F. haue beene here, and heard, and ſeene what hath paſſed, I doe referre the diſcourſe to conference: For I aſſure my ſelfe they will viſit you. Yet I will make bold to trouble you, to aduiſe of ſome perticulers as followeth.
            The tenth day of May was the battaile betweene Mulley Sidan, and our new King

               Mulley Om Hamet ben Abdela; not farre from Marocus betwixt the mountaines, and the City both ſides very ſtrong: Yet in mans iudgement Mulley Sidan of moſt force in horſe and foote, and three and thirty peeces of good field ordnance. The other no ordnance, and a few peecemen:Larbies are the country people dvvelling in tents. Brebers thoſe that inhabite the mountaines. Azagies are a kind of darts. his chiefeſt force Larbies of Sahara, a place diſtant hence twenty daies iourney.
            Theſe armed with Launces, demy Launces and Azagies, and many Larbies that came in to him, by the way as he came ſome hee forced, ſome voluntary. And at the day of battaile his people beganne to bee diſmaied, perceiuing Mulley Sidan, was very ſtrong. But hee encouraged them, ſaying, as they had found that come to paſſe which formerly hee told them, ſo now they ſhould ſee the like and bid them not feare his ordnance, for onely three peeces ſhould goe off, and doe no harme: the reſt ſhould take fire, but not ſhoote a bullet, and hee would bee formoſt, and goe in the face of the ordnance, and finding his wordes true, then at his commaund to fall vppon his enemies.
            
               So hauing ſatisfied his people with theſe perſwaſions ſent ſpies to know where Mulley Sydans ordnance lay, and ſo came right before it, with all his troopes. And comming within daunger, at Mulley Sidans commaund, they gaue fire, hauing both Moores and Chriſtians that knew how to mannage his ordnance.
            So three peeces went off, and did no hurt. But the bullets hard ſing in the ayre a great height, and the reſt of the ordnance tooke fire, and burnt out the powder, but ſhot no bullet that remained in, ſo comming nearer, the Musketiers plaied vpon them, with foure thouſand ſhot, yet hurt no man.
            So then they came on, and Mulley Sidans people gaue way and fled. They purſued them, and ſlue Mulley Abdela ben Hammet, Alkaide Hammet, Benzebeere, and many moe Alkaides, and betweene foure and fiue thouſand people. So put his people in to Marocus, and lay himſelfe in the field.
            Hee hath not entered into Marocus, neither purpoſeth till he haue deſtroied his enemies, and put peace in his country. So Mulley Sidan fled &amp; came down to Saphia, with

               Sidan, fled and came downe to Saphia,Hackam is a chiefe officer in a City. with his Hackam, Abdela Kather, Abdela Sadocke and the Iew Benwaſh, and a few others (beſides his mother and women, and iuggedge) Heare made account to gather a head againe, and to giue a new battaile. But in vaine the Larbies made a faire ſhew and came in to him, and receiued ſome money, cloth, and linnens from him, and ſo would haue betraied him.
            Whereupon he hauing ſome of his brother Mulley Shecks children with him, (to make friendſhip with his brother) ſent him his children and wrote to him very kindly. So betweene them I account is peace. So ſtaied heere ſo long as he durſt: for that Mulley Om Hammet perſued him. Whereby hee was forced to fraight a ſhip of Marſelle is heere in port, with a French Ambaſſador, who came to him vpon buſſineſſe out of France, and a Fleming that was in the roade: and tooke his Treaſure and luggage, ſome Women and Children, ſome Alcaids and Seruants, and Benwaſh and his followers, and went for Santa Cruz and there Landed in Sus: and from thence to Tarradance and there ſince remained, what force he hath or of his

proceeding wee here know not the certaintie.
            Some fewe dayes after his departure, came our new King into theſe parts, halfe a dayes iourney from Saphia, and all the Larbies came into him &amp; ſubmitted themſelues, and he receiueth al in to fauor, pardoning what paſſed: For, hee ſayth, hee comes to make peace, and is ſent from God, becauſe of thee euill gouernment of Mulley Hammets ſonnes the Xeriffes; andKinred of Mahomet which they challenge. to ſtabliſh their Prophets religion, that was decaied, and to fight againſt the Chriſtians, and recouer thoſe parts of Chriſtendome the king of Spaine holds from them: as Granada, Andaluzia, &amp;c. and tels his people they ſhall yet ſee greater wonders come to paſſe, where they ſhall acknowledge he is ſent of God; he promiſeth them Spaine, Italy, and France: and hauing put peace in theſe countries, there muſt now appeare a bridge in the mouth of the ſtraights, which hath been in former time, (and ſo recorded in their writings) &amp; ſunk in the ſea. Now in his time it muſt appeare to carrie ouer the Moores: and hauing gayned theſe countries, he muſt raigne forty yeeres, and then muſt com Chriſt, whom they call Sidie Nicer: and he muſt ſurren▪
               
der all to him; for he muſt iudge the world, and then all muſt end.
            But for England, Flanders, or other parts they haue not to doe, they will haue friendſhip with vs, and deſire trade and traffique with vs in loue and friendſhip, and would haue his myracles and acts made knowne abroade the world: I was in his Almahalla at firſt fowre dayes, and ſpakeOr Camp. with him, and ſaw his behauiour; and found him very humble and courteous, with many good ſpeeches; and pittying the iniuries all the Chriſtians haue by the ill gouernment of his Predeceſſors, or Vſurpers as he counted them. A man of ſome thirty ſix yeers, very ciuill, very plaine in habit, a courſe tucke vpon his head of died callico,Or turbon. A long looſe garment much like an Iriſh mantle. a holland Shirt, an Alheick of lile grogram, a plain ſword by his ſide, hanged with a plaine leather thong: a man of great wiſdome and learning, as none like amongſt them, and a good Aſtrologer, a great Polititian. And hath drawne vnto him Alkaide Azus, of whom you haue heard the principall Councellor of the land, Shecke Zimbie, Shecke Glowie, and many other Saints and principall men: and ſince his comming maried the Widow of Mulley Bufferris. And now diuers libels in Larby verſe againſt

               Mulley Sidan and his proceedings, and of further miſery muſt come vnto him, till he and his race be conſumed. And for his gouernment at Morocus placed his Hackam to ſee euery one haue peace, and a very honeſt man for iuſtice: So Morocus is in peace and quietnes; and amongſt the Larbies he demands his due, either corne, horſe, cattell, or money; and tels them he coms to put peace amongſt them; neither to rob thē, nor yet to loſe his right; not to giue them pay, but force them to ſerue him, as need requireth, if they yeelded not to ſuch conditions, his ſword ſhould force them: he came amongſt them as a gueſt, and was to be entertained by them, and not to giue them to gaine their fauour. By which ſpeeches, myracles paſt, and policy, hee hath made them all tremble; ſo he puts all to ſilence: Som cōtent themſelues, of the greateſt in former time, to heare and ſee, ſhew obedience and ſay nothing: others change with the time, and haue great imploiments, and profeſſe loialty to him, and renounce their old Maſter; what the euent may be I know not: for, we haue learned, the hearts of Kings are in the hands of the Lord, he turueth them: as riuers of waters which way hee pleaſeth.
            
            
               But hauing been in his Almahalla, ſeeing the manner of it, his plainneſſe and policy, mixt with a ſhew of mercy and a kind of Saintiſh gouernment, I feare mee it will come to paſſe, according to the Fable in Aeſop, when the Frogs deſired a King, a blocke was throwne downe into the water, which daſh at the firſt made them feare him, but lying ſtill they grew familiar, and ſunned themſelues vpon him, and grew in diſlike; ſo had the Storke: But it were to be wiſhed they would now content themſelues, when peace and iuſtice is offered. If he do continue it is like to be with trouble and bloud-ſhed; for already the people begin to diſobey, and the Shabenites, Mulley Sidans Or Kinred. 
               Caſt, are got to the mountaines neare Marocus, and haue procured ſome of thoſe Mountainers. Brebers (as we rearme them) to ioine with them; and one Mulley Om Hammet Bolaſſad, and theſe haue robbed to the gate of Marocus; wherupon this King ſent forces to expell them, but found them ſo ſtrong that they durſt not meddle with them: wh
                  •
               reupon was forced to rehale his Almahalla ſome fifteen daies ſince, and is gone towards the Mountaines, where at this preſent hee is neere Frugo: and what hath paſſed ſince we know not, only expect

euery howre to heare ſome good newes that he may preuaile; but here it is greatly feared, becauſe many of his owne people be departed from him: and thoſe Larbies he caried along with him out of theſe parts, run away and returned, ſo if he loſe, the other bee the friends of Mulley Sidan, and he is expected againe: But the beginning and riſing of this king and his procedings are very ſtrange. He is a great ſaint and learned in the lawe, and was ſought vnto by many the principalleſt of the land for his bleſſings, and fauour, according to their ſuperſtition; he findes it in ancient books writ of him by way of prophecy, that ſuch a man of that place named Meſſae (whence he is) by name Mulley Om Hamet ben Abdela, ſhould bee ſent at this time, to put peace in the country, and to reuiue their law, and put out the race of Mulley Sidan, and name of Xeriffes: and ſo to raigne forty yeers till Chriſt come to iudgement: his beginning muſt be, hee muſt ſtrike vp a drum hee ſhould finde in that Zowie at Miſſa, and thenOr Saints houſe. ſhould repaire vnto him people, to make him king. The manner of his proceedings, and what encounters hee ſhould haue, and what he found written, all the Talbies and learned men now do confeſſe to find the ſame written in their bookes. At his beginning he put forth only one tent and a kitchen: ſo reſorted

to him the Shrokies, a ſaintiſh people in their lawe, but otherwiſe in behauiour very Sauages. Theſe without pay came to him, to the number of 150. or 200. at moſt; and with their helpe hee brake Alhadge Lemiere, and his forces, ſeruants of Mulley Sidan, beeing 5000. ſtrong; ſo more of the ſayd Shrokies came to him, to the number of 5000. &amp; with them and ſuch people as ioined with him in the way, he ouerthrew Mulley Sidans forces thriſe before the battell.
            And ſo came to ſome ſtrong places in the Mountaines, neuer brought to ſubiection in the time of Mulley Sidan, nor his father: Thoſe with-ſtood him, but hee ouercame them and made them pay him what he demanded, ſerue and obey him; ſo forced the principalleſt Shecks in the countrie to come to him. After this marched towards Morocus, and by the way was to paſs a riuer; and the daie before he warned his people, in paſſing ſuch a riuer no man to take vp water in their hands to drinke, if he did he would die. After comming to the riuer weary and hot, many not remembred, or not regarded his words, but tooke vp water in their hands, drunk, and anon after dyed, the reſt all eſcaped, which ſtrooke a feare into them to breake his command, and a perſwaſion that hee is more then a man: For they ſay hee

is their Fatamie, that is, a Sauiour. Next in comming to Morocus, diuers great Saints and Sheckes reſorted together, and would goe to viſit him, that they might ſee what hee was, and vnderſtand whether that which paſſed was true or not. So comming, after ſalutations, hee told them they came to enquire and ſee what newes, and what wonders hee did, and ſo meant to depart.
            Now therefore, beeing men of account and Talbies hee would ſatisfie them, that they might ſatisfie others. So appointed them a time to come againe, and to bring ſuch bookes, hee nominated, with them; ſo they did: Then he vvilled them to turne to ſuch places, and reade what they found written of him; ſo they did. To wit, both his name, his beginning, and courſe he was to take, and withall found written ſeauen ſpeciall markes, or ſignes, hee muſt haue vppon his bodie, a wart aboue his right eye, a blacke tooth before, a bunch of hayre growing betweene his ſhoulders, a ſigne of a ring in the palme of his right hand, the ſigne of a ſpurre vpon the outſide of his right legge; the reſt I remember not.
            But theſe and the reſt hee ſhewed them which ſeeing they did honor him and ſwore

to him to ſerue him, and to liue and die with him, or in his cauſe.
            Next comming to a place named Dets in the mountains very ſtrong, where much people were gathered together againſt him ſo that ſome of his owne people began to faint and be afraied: hee bad them feere nothing for that before to morrow they ſhould ſee there was more with him then againſt him: ſo that night, he cōmanded to take vp his Almahalla &amp; march towards that place Dets: ſo they did, and all night long to the thinking of al his people, there marched another Almahalla greater then theirs, and went before them: and comming to the place Dets vanniſhed away, and at ſight of it his enemies fled, leaſt the place and goods al to the ſpoile, ſo comming thither had the ſpoile of all without fighting. This our country man M. W. affermeth with diuers others vpon ſolemne oth to haue ſeene. At his being in theſe parts, my ſelfe with others went to welcome him: he entertained vs very kindly, &amp; told vs he would ſhew the Engliſh what fauour he could, and permit them free trade, willing vs to take knowledge that he was ſent by Gods appointment to releeue the oppreſſed as wel Moores and ſtrangers, as Chriſtians, and al ſorts, and what we had ſeene and heard to aduertiſe, ſaying wee ſhould ſee yet

more ſtrange matters come to paſſe, then what had paſſed. His meaning as we gather is, the conquering of Spaine, France and Italy; with which oppinion hee poſſeſſeth the fooliſh and credulous Moores. Now hauing bin tedious to trouble you with ſuch news as the time affoords (not al but part as it comes into my memory) I pray you take it in good part: the cenſure hereof I leaue to your wiſdome and confideration. For my owne part I am perſwaded, they bee deluſions of the diuell done by witch-craft, and permitby the Lord, to ſeduce them to further error, God deliuer vs Chriſtians well from among them, and grant vs the vſe, and true knowledge of his holy word preached in Chriſtian countries which heere wee want, and the vſe and comfort of his holy Sacraments to the ſealing vp of our faith in Chriſt Ieſus Amen.
            
            I am ſorry I haue nothing for remembrance, to preſent vnto you, but God willing when the time betters I will not bee forgetfull: in the meane time, I pray you accept of theſe few lines in good part. So reſting euer at your ſeruice, I commit you to Gods holy tuition who bleſſe you in this world with health and content, and in the world to come with eternall ioy, Amen.
            
            
               Your louing friend to command.
R. S.
            
         
         
            
            
               An other letter receiued from an other friend, at the ſame time dated the tenth of September.
            
            GOod Sir pardon me in that at my going away, I came not to take my leaue of you: the ſhip went downe two daies ſooner than I made account off. But for all your courteſies alwaies towards mee, I heartily thanke you and remaine your debter &amp;c. For the ſtate of this country, and of the wars of this new King, I know Maſter S. hath enlarged you more than I can a great deale. But for all this, and the troubles Mulley Sidan hath had, it is thought he will be king again, and that in ſhort time: ſtaying but for a new Moone to giue battaile. This Saint or king told his Shrokies which came with him at firſt, his comming was to take Mazagant, Sute and Tanger, not to fight againſt the Moores vnleſſe they would reſiſt, and not let him take the Chriſtian townes. Hee ſaid againe that Mulley Sidan and his followers were Chriſtians, one who robbed all men without reaſon, killed and ſlue many men vpon no occaſions, but in his angry minde. And withall ſaid hee dranke wine, and eate oppium, therefore ſaid it could not bee but

that hee was an Vnſrony, which amongſt them they hold to bee an vniuſt, or vngodly man as they ſay wee Chriſtians are. His Shrokies two thouſand fiue hundreth almoſt all footmen, with no peeces, but halfe Launces: that was their weapons, bareheaded men. Neuer in their liues they weare ſhert, or cloth to their backes, but an Alheik. Which Shrokies haue left this king; and are all gonne for their country. This kings forces are of Larbies, which are horſemen: euery day they flee from him more and more. As Alkaid Syde, whom you knew Alkaid of this place, is come from him with ſixe hundreth horſe. So that very ſhortly Mulley Sidan is expected to come heare againe. And thus with my commendations to your good ſelfe, and all our good friends I commit you to the Almighty.
            
               Yours aſsured to command.
G. B.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            SInce the writing (and almoſt printing) of theſe two letters, there is newes come (and that for certaine as I am giuen to vnderſtand) that Mulley Sidan is defeated againe, and hath loſt this laſt battaile: ſo the Saint victorious ſtill. What the euent of all theſe troubles may bee it is hard to geſſe. This country hauing beene ſo long time (euerſince the death of old Mulley Hamet) ſo vnſetled, and ſubiect to ſo manifold alterations: ſo many yeeres, almoſt, ſo many alterations of gouernment: The crowne imperiall toſſed to and fro, from one to another, as it were a tennisball rather then a diadem. Non vnquam tulit documenta, fors maiora
               Seneca. 
               quam fragili loco ſtarent ſuperbi: And that may ſerue for another vſe: a finall vſe of all, either that hath paſſed, or may hereafter fall out: whereof if any thing elſe come to my hands, worthy obſeruation, I ſhall not withhold it, to make the reſt anſwerable to the Preface.
            
         
      
   

