
   
      
         
            The tragicall life and death of Muley Abdala Melek the late King of Barbarie With a proposition, or petition to all Christian princes, annexed therevnto: VVritten by a gentleman imployed into those parts.
            Harrison, John, fl. 1610-1638.
         
         
            
               1633
            
         
         Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A02730
            STC 12860
            ESTC S116606
            99851822
            99851822
            17114
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A02730)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17114)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:19)
         
         
            
               
                  The tragicall life and death of Muley Abdala Melek the late King of Barbarie With a proposition, or petition to all Christian princes, annexed therevnto: VVritten by a gentleman imployed into those parts.
                  Harrison, John, fl. 1610-1638.
               
               [6], 24 p.   
               
                  [By J.P. Waelpots?],
                  Printed at Delph :
                  Anno 1633.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Iohn Harrison.
                  Printer's name conjectured by STC.
                  In this copy a3,4 are cancelled and replaced by one leaf signed A3.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               [Àbd al-Malik ibn Muḥammad, --  Sultan of Morocco, d. 1578] --  Early works to 1800.
               Persecution --  Morocco --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-02
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-07
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2004-07
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
TRAGICALL
LIFE AND DEATH OF
MVLEY ABDALA MELEK
the late King of Barbarie. With
A PROPOSITION, OR PETITION TO ALL
Christian Princes, annexed therevnto:
VVritten by a Gentleman imployed
into those parts.
            
            
            Printed at Delph, ANNO 1633.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE MOST
ILLVSTRIOVS, AND HOPEFVLL
young Prince CHARLES Prince Elector
Palatine of the Rhyne, &amp;c.
            
               MOST ILLVSTRIOVS PRINCE,
The great respect I receiued from your Highnes at
Leyden two severall times after my comming out of
Barbarie, and the great desire your Highnes expressed (as becometh Princes) to vnderstand, and be informed in foraigne
afaires, and the State of other countries, hath encouraged me
(hauing novv againe been imployed into that countrie) to
present to your Highnes, for a Nevv-years-gift, this short
relation, of the life, &amp; death of the late King Muley Abdala
Melek, as vvas related to me by vvaie of discourse onlie, at
seuerall times, by those vvho for the most part vvere eyevvitnesses:
Oculati testes. VVhich also may serue your Highnes
for matter of discourse, and further information likewise, to
discerne betwixt a blessed Christian gouernment, vvhereunto
God hath ordained you, and a cruell tyrannous Mahometan
gouernment (as is the Turkish,) vnder vvhich those miserable
mis-belieuers: yea and manie Christians likevvise there in
most miserable slauerie, groane: the Lord deliuer them
from it. And giue vs grace to make vse of it: both Prince.

people, and acknovvledge our owne happines. Prince, vvho
commaund ouer Christian, obedient, and dutifull subiects:
and subiects vvho liue vnder so peaceable, and Christian a
gouernement, bona si sua norit agricola, free from tyrannie,
rebuel: as, and tumults, vvhereunto that countrie of Barbaric
hath this long time been subiect. Such is the miserable state,
and condition of tyrannie, and of tyrants, euen of Kings: as your
Highnes may perceiue, by the sodaine, fearefull, and miserable
end of this King: qualis vita sinis ita: his life vvas bloodie, and
so it ended in blood, in his owne blood. And thereafter may
your Highnes, and all other yong Princes, vvho haue so good
tuitors, and ouerseërs to informe them learne: (as that famous
Buchanan tuitor to your grand Father King Iames of blessed
memorie, in his epistle dedicatorie before his Tragaedie called
Baptistes, admonisheth, vvorthie to be read ouer, and ouer,
and remembred of all yong Princes, his vvords, as I remember,
are these) maturé odisse quod tibi semper est fugiendum.
VVhich I pray God both your Highnes, and all other Princes
may remember, and make vse of. Hoping your Highnes vvill
accept of this small present out of a Barbarous countrie, for
vvant of a better. vvhither I should haue returned, for the
releasse of the remainder of my poore countrymen, in captiuitie
vnder the new King Muley Elvvalid, vpon a new treatie.
Hauing alreadie been a means to releasse aboue two hundreth
and threescore from Sallie: and threescore mee as yet remaining
vnder this king at Morocco, and Sallie, by them taken
againe vpon a late breach: besides vvhat are dispersed vp and
dovvne the countrie: all promised by that King to be releassed
vpon his treatie. VVhither (I say) I should haue returned
long before this time, longed, and long looked for by those poore
captiues.Isa. 51. 14 
               For the captiue hasteneth to be loosed &amp;c. as it

is in the Prophet. But vvhether I shall returne at all: or those
poore captiues be loosed, or releassed at all, is in Gods hands:
vvho can make their verie enemies,
               P
                     •
                   46 
               and all those that haue
caried them avvaie captiues, to pitie them: othervvise no hope
at all. And so I leaue them to Gods mercie: and both them, &amp;
all others in like distresse, both there, and elsvvhere, to your
Highnes, and all other Christian princes to commiscrate, according
to a proposition, or petition, I haue hereunto annexed,
highlie concerning them in honour to consider of: vvhich is also
in Gods hands: For the hearts of Kings (as Salomon saith) are in
Gods hands, he turneth thē vvhich vvaiesoeuer he pleaseth.
In the meane time (as my dutie is, hauing been imployed in
these affaires) I can but sollicit, and petition, though vvithout
effect, in hope contrarie to hope: hauing hitherto receiued
so small encouragement: but discouragements: and so goe on
mourning still, and like to doe: finis vnius mali gradus futuri.
One crosse after an other still readie to receiue me, VVhich I
must beare patientlie, so commaunded, so resolued: To take
vp the crosse of Christ, and follovv him vvhither soeuer he
commaundeth, from one conntrie to an other, from one part of
the vvorld to an other, and to the vvorlds end. Quem statues
finem Rex magne laborum? And so goe on mourning still,
as I haue don these manie years. Hoc continuis agimus annis:
a countinuall mourner euer since the death of prince Henry my
maister, novv renewed by the death of your Royall Father, &amp;
that renovvmed King of Svveden, vvho died that verie day
of the month prince Henry died,The 6. Stilo 
                     〈◊〉
                   in The 1
                     •
                   Stilo novo. Zec. 12 12. the 6. of Nouember: the date
after the povvder plot, ominous. For both vvhich the vvhole
church of Christ hath cause to mourne, and that continuallie,
not onlie outvvardlie, but invvardlie euerie familie a part: as
vvas that great mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of

Megiddon. For that good King Iosiah,
               
                  
                     •
                  2. 18. continuallie, continuis
annis euen to posteritie: to be continued (I say) as vvas that,
for these two so good Kings, so sodainlie, &amp; so vntimelie taken
avvate. To mourne (I say) continuallie, and invvardlie for
our sins, vvhich are the cause of these disasters: Verus luctus
est occultus: that is the true mourning: so to condole, and
mourne. And so let vs continue our mourning, and goe on
mourning still: euerie familie a part, euerie true Christian a
part, to beare a part, in this so great a mourning, vvith our
deare mother the church: that comfortles Rachel, vvho vveepeth
for her children, and vvill not be comforted because
they are not. Yea, let the vvhole church of Christ renevve
her vveeping, and mourning againe, till it Echo againe, not
onlie the last vvords, vltima verba (as it is in Seneca) Sed
totos reddat Troiae gemitus) for her children first, and last
taken from her, one after an other, because they are not.
Queene Elizabeth of famous memorie, is not. King Iames,
is not. Prince Henry; is not And the other hopefull young
prince Henry your brother, is not. Your Royall Father, the
King of Bohemia, is not. The King of Svveden, is not.
Hovv is the valiant man fallen that deliuered Israel? Besides
other vvorthies: the old prince of Orange, and others, they
are not. Yea manie other poore Christian soules, of late slaine,
massacred, perished, and lost, both vnder the Antichristian &amp;
Mahometan tyrannie, they are not. For vvhom the vvhole
church of Christ hath cause to mourne: neuer more cause, neuer
more seasonable. VVherunto now I betake myself, euen to praiers
and teares the vveapons of Gods church: VVhich shall be the
second part. And my Account hereafter mentioned, the third,
and last:Isa. 51. If God permit, and other obstacles hinder not.
And so rest Your Highnes humble seruant,
            
            
               IOHN HARRISON.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE LIFE
AND DEATH OF
MVLEY ABDALA MELEK,
the late King of Barbarie.
            IF Plutarch (vvho did vvrite, and paralel the lives, and
acts of the most famous men of those times) vvere
novv living, to vvrite and paralel on the contrarie the
lives and acts of the most infamous men of the vvorld, I
think he vvould haue much adoe to finde out a fit match,
either auncient or moderne, vvherevnto to paralel the
late King of Barbarie Muley Abdala Melek: yea rather I
thinke he vvould leave him vnparalel'd. And so must I,
only setting dovvne so much as in that short time I staid
at Morocco (vvhich vvas but tvvo monthes) hath been related
to me by vvay of discourse, by such both of our ovvne
nation and others as vvere for the most part eye-vvitnesses,
vvhich is scarce the hundreth part of his cruel acts, and
mad-pranks he plaid in that short time of his raigne:
vvhich vvas scarce foure yeares, mad-pranks I may call
them, for so is he commonlie called the mad King.
            He vvas Son to Mulay Sidan by a negra, so by complexion
a molato: The Mores in that respect vvhether of vviues
or concubines making no difference of succession, but
commonlie the eldest, though by a concubine, carieth the
crovvne: and sometimes the yonger getteth the blessing
from the elder: quo iure &amp;c. capiat qui capere potest.
            
            He vvas extraordinarilie giuen to drinke vvine and

strong drinke, vvhich added to his naturall disposition:
(vvhich needed not) inclyned to crueltie euen from his
infancie. Of a manlie stature: and of a most couragious
disposition. A good horseman, vvith his launce &amp; target;
vvould euer be the first man in the face of his enemies:
vvho indeed durst neuer look him in the face, but presently
faces about: his svvord making vvaie for him vvhich waie
soeuer he vvent. Such vvas his resolusion, viam inveniam
aut faciam. So that it may be doubted vvhether his courage,
or crueltie vvere greater: and in these tvvo respects,
I vvil be bold to saie (as before) not to be paraleld by any.
As by these fevv passages, gessing at Hercules by his foote,
may easelie appeare. And euen before he vvas King began
to play his prize like, Hercules furens, his arme and svvord
still in action, cutting and killing at his pleasure vpon euery
slight occasion.
            At one time he killed one of his ovvne blood (the
blood royall) onlie for tasting a litle of his svveet meates
by stealth. Sweet meates must haue sowre sauce. An other
(the chieffest of the cast of the Shebanites allied vnto him
by mariage of his Praedecessours into that cast) hauing
vvronged one of his servants,A cast is a tribe or kinred. he taketh some fevv of his
servants, not aboue ten at the most vvith him, goeth desperatlie
among all the Shebanites to the 
                  •
               ent of this man,
being the valiantest amongst them all, challenged him of
the vvrong: vvho slighted him (being then not King)
mounted on horsebacke, discharged his pistoll at him but
missed, whō presently this yong Prince drawing his sword
slue hand to hād maugre al the Shebanits, &amp; came of cleare
            An other time a Levantado or rebell (one of their saints)
comming against his Father Muley Sidan vvith 3000. horse,
like to surprize him on a sodaine, he vvith his drums, musik

and ensignes, and not aboue fortie horse, vvent out against
him, chardged so furiously, as put them, al to flight: pursued
the victory, &amp; (as they say) vvith his ovvne hand vvounded
the Levantado that he dyed, his head after brought in, to
Muley Sidan, hanged vp in the Alcasaua, and quarters likevvise
on the vvals of Morocco, on the gates of the citie. Hauing
be ore challenged his Father of neglect, and too much
securitie: of vvhom not only his enemies, but euen his Father
(as they say) stood in feare, yet his Father calling him
Father. Such is the praeposterous maner of the Moores, to
call their eldest Son Father, out of a reuerence (as they say)
they giue to him being the first born, &amp; to be (as it seemeth)
Pater familias, Father of the familie for the time to come,
other reason I can not giue of their praeposterous inversion
of that relation, (or rather confusion) for the Father, to call
his Son Father. Our Heauenly Father I am sure did not so,
the King of Kings: Thou art my Son, &amp;c. as it is in the
Psalmes. Nor Dauid the King in that his patheticall expression
of his Fatherly affection, far beyond theirs, yea beyond
all expression: Absalon my Son, my Son. After his comming
to be King some of the frends of the Leuantado hauing
by stealth taken dovvne his quarters to bury them, he
commanded a great number of the neighbours heads who
dvvelt neere there aboutes to be cut of, executing many
vvith his ovvne hands as he met them in the streets.
            And not long after immediatlie vpon the death of his
Father, being nevvlie proclaimed King, his brother Muley
Flvvallid (this King) comming against him vvith a great
force, better affected of the comminaltie than the other,
in respect of his crueltie: (vvhich they greatlie feared,
and not vvithout cause, as aftervvards they found)

               Muley Abdala Melek giuing order first for his ordnance, to
be dischardged, immediatlie after himself, being the first,
man (hauing but a fevv horse) chardged so furiouslie, and
so throughlie, as he rovvted them all▪ vvhervpon his brother
fled tovvards Sallie, but not long after vvas betrayed
&amp; brought back againe by Alkaid Hamuda dvvelling neare
Azamore, vvhose horma or sanctuarie he tooke, invited and
encouraged by him to some further attempt: but indeed
betrayed, vvho after vsed him in a verie base &amp; vnseemlie
manner, stripping him, beating him, and carying him,
chained vpon a horse to the King. VVherevpon the King
(they say) vvhen he savv him relented, yea vvept, not
vsing any extremitie, but rather out of his lion-like magnanimitie,
contemning vvhat either he, or any other had
don, or could doe against him. Yet did his brother liue in
continuall feare, diuers times threatned by the King in his
mad humor, sending to him to prepare himself, and to
knovve vvhat kinde of death he vvould dye: but by mediation
of his sisters and others still put of. At one time
(the King being at Saffia) in his drunken humor, the sentence
pronounced, and an Alkaid presentlie sent tovvards
Morocco, vvhere his brother was then prisonner to execute
it: but the next morning the King comme to himself, and
by mediation (as before) reversed, and a messenger dispatched
to countermaund the other, vvhom he ouertooke
but at Tansift a riuer vvithin foure myles of Morocco, commanded
vpon his life to ouertake him: the other making
no great hast, othervvise it had been executed.
            One time at Saffia his Almahalla or campe (vvherein
his brother Muley Semyn vvas then) comming to pitch
neare thereaboutes, he in steed of a vvarning piece to

remoue further of, shot a bullet amongst them. An other
time (as I heard) in iest among the market folke: yet did
no hurt but killed an asse.
            An other time in his Almahalla (hauing been all the
daie abroad drinking as he vsed) and coming riding in late
at night vpon the spur, as he passed by the ordnance,
vvhereof the English had the chardge, he commaunded on
the sodaine svvearing a great English oath, giue fire: vvhich
they presentlie did, they durst doe no othervvise: so shot
avvaie his ovvne vncle being in companie vvith him all
to peeces,
            His yongest brother, yea and his ovvne yong sonne,
sometimes vvould he hang vp by the legs, and beate them
vvith his ovvne hands. No merveile then if he vvere cruell
to others, being so vnnaturall to his owne flesh and blood.
            Euerie daie must see blood (blood shed) vvere it but of
a hen, els not satisfied. Possessed (as some of the Moores
haue told me manie are, &amp; that he vvas) vvith a she deuill,
frequent amongst them as (it seemeth) amongst the heathen
in times past, vvhereof a heathen philosopher writeth a
set treatise of Incubus and succubus. And the partie vvho
told me this said, that one daie going a hawking hauing
other Moores vvith him, one follovving a good distance
in the high vvaie, on a sodaine stood still, and not long after
they savv a smoake arise in the same place, vvhereat they
vvondered, &amp; vvent back, finding the man much amazed.
Asking the reason, he said a vvoman met him there verie
faire &amp; in good attyre, vvho offered herself to be his wife,
he ansvvered, he had one alreadie, she replyed he might
take an other (for so the Moores may by their lavv) being
verie importunate vvith him: at length looking dovvnevvards

perceiued her clubbed feet, &amp; vvhat she vvas, wherevpon
he vvent back, and absolutly refused, and therevpon
she vanished in that maner in a great snuffe. The man
presently therevpon falling sick, and so continued a good
vvhile. Hovv true this is I can not say, but vvas reported
to me verie seriously, and for a certaintie. But of this I am
sure that the deuill can transforme himself into an Angel
of light: much more take vpon him the shape of a man,
or a vvoman, as God permitteth to delude those that obey
not the truth. And this likevvise I knovve to be true and
certaine, that he is both a lyer (the Father of lyes) and a
murderer from the beginning: euer a thirst, and neuer satisfied
vvith blood. And therefore no merveile if this tyrant
vvere so possessed as before, that euerie daie he must see
blood els not satisfied. And if euery day, hovv much blood
may be thought he shed in that time of his life &amp; raigne.
            Sometimes he vvould cut of mens heads vvith his
ovvne hands, and vvith his ovvne sharp svvord, saying,
those vvhom he commaunded did not cut them of vvell,
and at once: vvhich don vvould aske one of the Englishmen
if it vvere not vvell done, he must say yea Muley. Yea
six or seauen mens heads in one day.
            Once by euermuch drinking distempered in his bodie,
hauing his armes and hands benummed, his Doctor persvvaded
him to enter into a bath. After his bathing meeting
vvith one of his concubines, drevv out his svvord and
cut of her head, to trie the strength of his arme if it vvere
sound againe. Also an other for going out of her bite or
chamber to the next doore to one of her fellovves, for the
Moores are iealous euen of their vvomen, and vvill not
suffer them to companie together.
            Made one man stand still vvhile he threvv stones at his

face, threatning if he offered to stir or moue he vvould cut
of his head. So likevvise abroad in the fields, ofttimes
vvould cause some one of his seruants to lie dovvne grovelling,
&amp; sit vpon him in steed of a stoole a vvhole night
together drinking: and the man durst not for his life stir.
And some to stand by him vvhole daies and nights vvithout
moouing hand or foote, othervvise vvould haue cut of
their heads.
            VVould cause men to be drubbed, or beaten almost to
death in his presence, vvhich vvas but a common &amp; gentle
correction, fiue or six hundreth blovves at once, and after
they must kisse the ground, &amp; giue him thanks. To whom
in this particular, &amp; others likevvise, I may paralel a great
Lord in this part of the vvorld: vvho (hauing slaine an other
in a privat duell, and, vpon iust occasion offered, taxed by
one to vvhom he had don vvrong, disgracing, &amp; disabling
him, and that in an open assemblie, &amp; displacing him too:
and therefore had the partie reason there also to right himself,
and reply, par pari referre, and disable him likevvise for
shedding of blood, vvhich by the Lavv of God is murder)
caused the partie to be committed to prison (closse prisoner
at the first) and there kept, and fed vvith the bread of affliction,
till in the end he vvas forced: (his imprisonment, and
punishment both of bodie and purse, besides the disgrace,
no sufficient satisfaction) to kisse the ground, that is, make
an humble submission, and subscribe that he had offended,
and abused his Lordship vvith opprobrious, and vnciuill
language &amp;c. that is to say, that the Lavv of God is an opprobrious
&amp; vnciuill language, vvhich saith: He that smiteth
an other vvith an instrument of yron, that he dy is a murderer
&amp;c. vvhich submission he novv vtterly disclaimeth, as most
blasphaemous against God &amp; his Lavv, &amp; don of infirmity,

and by dares of imprisonment, hauing no meanes at all to
maintaine himself any longer in prison, but there to starve:
praying God to forgiue him, and them likevvise vvho imposed
it. To vvhom (euen to that great God) that great
Lord ought rather to make submission, for violating his
holie Lavv, as David did, (a King and vvas not ashamed.)
I haue sinned &amp;c. yea and after fell to the ground, and
kissed the ground vvith manie teares. Therefore is he a
saint in heauen: and Muley Abdala Melek, and all such
bloodie tyrants, &amp; murderers (vvithout repentance) deuills
in hell. For Topheth is praepared of old euen for Kings, and
Lords too if they repent not: For vvith God there is no
respect of persons. Nor vvas vvith this King Muley
Abdala Melek, in the cruell course of his tyrannie: vvherevnto
all, both great and small, vvere subject.
            Yea he vvould, cause some to be beaten on the soles of
their feet, and after make them run vp, and dovvne among
the stones, and thornes. And so also vsed some that vvere
lame, &amp; hurt, pulling of there shooes, &amp; making them run
barefooted in such places: or els vvould cut of their heads.
            Did cause one of his Alkaids (his chieffe falconer) to
be drubbed and beaten, manie hundreth blovves on the
buttocks (as himself told me) and after forced him to
ride in that painfull maner after him a havvking. Also
the same Alkaid told me, that the girth of his sadle being
broken, and he allighted: an other Alkaid comming to
help him, and holding his stirrop, the King called that
Alkaid to him, and caused him to be drubbed for holding
his stirrop, and not long after the like occasion falling out
againe, caused the same Alkaid to be drubbed againe, for
not holding his stirrop.
            
               
He run a mans thigh thorovv vvith his launce to the
saddle, and after because he vvas not able to ride after him a
pace, giue him tvvo or three hundreth blovves.
            VVould vvith his sword cut and flash men for his pleasure,
and after himself giue them plaisters to cure them.
            VVould cast men to the lions to be devoured, an other
of his torments.
            To one among the rest he promised that if he vvould
fight vvith them, and could escape he should be perdoned:
vvhich he did manfullie (as I vvas told) beating them from
him either vvith stones or som such meanes clearing himself,
yet af
                  •
               er vvas put to death
            Some he caused to be rastrar'd, or dragged by the feete
at the horse heeles, their back and head against the stones:
as he did the Hacam of Morocco (the chieffe officer of that
citie) round about his Almahalla or camp till he died.
Others iointed, their fingers, and toes first cut of by euerie
jointe, armes and legs, &amp; so head and all. An other hanged
vp by the priuie members, one caused to sit vpon him to
vveigh him dovvne: and vet the man liuing.
            Another (a hole digged in the ground) set in the earth
vp to the head, as Schollers in some places use to shoote
at the cock at Shrouetyde: so did he cause the captiues vvith
their peeces to shoote at this poore mans head. They all
missing, he himself came neere vvith his ovvne peece and
shot him, calling him a deuill because they all missed him.
            He cut of a Moores head (a church man, or Sexton) for
crying on the church tovver or steeple, and cursing all that
did drinke vvine, forbidden by their lavve. An other also
for crying and singing more then vsuall. For the Moores
haue noe bels, but in steed thereof, these cryers to call them

to their devotions: in the name of God, one God, the
great God, and his Prophet Mahomet, the Messenger of
God. Some say this mad King did once threaten that he
vvould haue one of the Friars, French or Spanish, to sing
masse before him: vvhich I thinke vvould haue pleased
him little better.
            He caused a French captiue to turne Moore, and be cut,
that is made an eunuch, onlie for extolling the King of
France to be one of the greatest Monarches of the vvorld.
An other, vvho kept his horse, neuer vvithout slashes and
vvounds. An other Frenchmans doublet vvith a paire of
sizers did he cut all ouer in slashes vvith his ovvne hands,
saying, he vvas novv a right French Cavallero, like to the
rest.
            If in his drunken humor abroad in the fields (as he vvas
seldome sober) he did fall from his horse, all his Alkaid
                  •
               
and seruants must doe the like, and lie dovvne, and doe as
he did. Much like the catching of the dotterill: and not
offer to rise or get on horseback till he did, nor to hold his
stirrop, or come neare him all the vvhile, if they did he
vvould giue them blovves. One of his Alkaids, for some
such like offence, caused he to sit 24. houres on he top of
his tent in the Almahalla (as it vvere on the pillorie) for
all men to gaze vpon. And novv and then vvould he giue
them a pill called Shishai (the effect vvhereof is to make
men merie drunke) to make himself sport. But indeed his
onlie sport vvas in cutting of mens heads, and (as before)
in shedding, and seeing of blood. No one day escaped but
one or other sacrificed in most bloodie manner to this
vnsatiable deuill: and she deuill together, if that opinion
of the Moores be true, as before.
            
               
On a time the Christian captiues, at Saffia the port town,
had laid a plot to breake the prison, and escape by sea in a
boate, but in the acting thereof vvere discouered, all taken
and beaten in most pitifull maner to make them confesse
the Authors, most of them Spaniards, and French: the
chieffe plotter a Spaniard (as it seemeth) of some account,
called Don Pedro, vvho vvas sent for to the King (then in
his Almahalla) vvho therevpon called all the English, and
others to kneele before him, setting the Spaniard also right
before him. Then said to the English, youe see this mis beliuer
that vvould haue run avvaie, if any of youe be like
minded, run sure, and cleare avvaie: othervvise, if youe be
taken see here your doome. Then caused he first the Spaniards
eares to be cut of one after an other: then his nose:
then his lippes one after an other: then his mouth, on both
sides slit vp to the eares: then his fingers disiointed one
from an other: vvhich don the King fell a laughing, ha,
ha, ha. Then said the Spaniard to him (hauing all this while
looked him in the face &amp; indured it verie manfullie) novv
Tyrant doe thy vvorst. vvherevpon presentlie he cut of his
head. So dyed this valiant champion, euen in death
triumphing ouer his tyrannicall tormentors.
            An other time a Moore being brought before him for
some misdemeanor fearing death, said vnto him: Muley,
I haue liued all the daies of my life hitherto a Christian,
if thou vvilt novv pardon me, I vvill turne true Moore
againe. His meaning vvas that he had liued a vvicked, and
levvd life, as many Christians haue don, and doe, both
in that and other countries, I speake it to their shame,
vvhereby the name of Christ, &amp; his religion is scandalized,
and blasphaemed: but yet, notvvithstanding that his

confession, that he had liued a Christian, and profession
to turne Moore againe, (that is to say,) to lead a godly life,
vvas executed. For vvith this King there vvas no respect
of persons, or religions, or occasions great or small. Sins
veniall, or mortall all one, that is to say mortall, Occasions?
nay oft times vvithout any occasion at all but onlie as he
met vvith any by accident, in his drunken and deuilish
humor, vvould try (as before vpon his ovvne vvomen) the
strength of his arme, and goodnes of his svvord and chiefflie
vpon his ovvne nation vvithout respect of persons: he
had no minions, or favorits at all: one good propertie in
him. VVhat shall I say. But (as an Alkaid telling me of
these and other his mad and tragicall acts exclaimed) a
deuill, a deuill. His Alcasava, or court the verie picture of
hell: vvhich made the greater and better forte to flee away
into the mountaines, or stand vpon their guard a far of:
like those vvylie foxes in AEsop seeing all foote steps going forvvard
into the lions den, but fevv or none retrorsum, back
againe. And those that did, hovvling, and crying, vveeping,
and vvayling sighing, and vvringing their hands, either
for themselues, or their friends. This vvas the dailie, and
dolefull musick both vvithin and vvithout: the verie gates
of hell. Friends? nay rather fiends, daylie tormenting one
an other. For so vvould he commaund his Alkaids, and
servants to drub one an other at his pleasure, &amp; cut of one
an others heads too.
            He vvould commonlie say in a iesting maner, that it
seemed to him whensoeuer he executed any of the Moores,
that they had tvvo or three heads: meaning to cut of but
one, he left none: vvishing (as it seemeth) like that Romane
tyrant, that all the Romanes had but one neck, he

vvould cut them all of at once: So Muley Abdala Melek, the
Moores, of vvhom he vvas Flagellum, the onlie vvhip that
euer vvas. And (as some thinke) the best King for the
Moores that euer vvas: requiring not a blocke, but AEsops
storke to keepe them in subiection, they othervvise prone
to rebellion, affecting alteration, and innovation: as their
refran or proverb is:Cus-cus a dish of meat in great request with them. 
               Everie day a new cus-cus, euerie day a
nevv vvife, and euerie day a nevv King.
            
            And though he vvas thus cruell and tyrannous to the
Moores, and others, yet did he favour much and respect the
English, to vvit the captiues, both before and after he vvas
King. Making one of them once to ride behinde him, but
vvithall bidding him not sit too closse to him for filling
him full of lyce. Threatning sometimes, but yet neuer
giuing any of them so much as a blovve. VVho in his fathers
time were kept in chaines both by the neck and legs,
but he comming to be king releassed them, and made
them, his gunners, giuing them free leaue to goe vp and
dovvne vvhere they vvould at their pleasure, and doe almost
vvhat they vvould: and not a Moore that durst controll
them, but rather stood in avve of them. Though their
allovvance but short, yet, hauing that libertie, they made
the better shift. And somtimes the king himself in a good
humor vvould giue them money: yea, and sometimes in
his mad humor. Yet did he cause some English boyes perforce
to turne Moores, cutting them, and making them
capadoes, or eunuches: but aftervvards (as they say) repented,
saying: he vvould neuer more force Englishmen
to turne Moores, for he found them better seruants to
him being christians, then Moores: for that being christians
they vvould stand by him, and stay vvith him: but

being Moores run avvaie from him, hauing more libertie
and opportunitie.
            And as he vvas (as I may say contrarie to his nature)
thus favourable to the captiues, so vvas he likevvise to the
Merchants, or others that came as hoare. He being at Saffia
one time standing vpon the vvals, an English boate comming
as hoare, he called to one of the men to come to him:
vvho, not knovving him to be the king, al the while stood
talking vnto him vvith his hatt on his head in Spanish,
after the King going into the castle, called one of the English
captiues to him, asking him if his countriemen had
no better maners? bidding him gofetch the partie to him,
vvho being come, the King vvould say nothing to him, but
only made him to attend there a good time, and caused the
English captiue vvhom he loued vvell, to be committed
to prison in the others steed, and chaines to be put on him.
But the next day sent for him, causing his svvord to be restored
to him, and so, in a mad humor, made him, both
vvith his svvord about his side, and chaines about his legs,
to vvalke after him round about the vvals, talking, and
iesting vvith him familiarlie as he vvas vvont: and then
after this chaines also vvere taken from him. This onlie he
did in iest, to teach Englishmen good maners against an
other time. But to the Moores his iests vvere in good
earnest, a vvord and a blovve.
            At the same place at Saffia, he vvould take the vvomen,
a vvashing at the sea side vpon the sands, set them vpon
their heads, &amp; cause vvater to be powred (vvith reverence
be it spoken) into their vnseemly parts, to see if it vvould
come out at the mouth againe.
            He mustered all the faire vvomen in Morocco: (vvhereof
it seemeth he had a Catalogue) causing them all at once, &amp;

on a sodaine to come forth into his great garden, called
Monsarat: (being a mile in length, planted vvith Orange,
and lemmon trees, and all kinde of fruits) and there pitch
their tents for 14. daies together: praetending a pilgrimage
vvith his vvomen to Gometta, tovvards the hils of Atlas,
no man to come neare them (no not their husbands) but
only their negras, &amp; seruing maids: himself onlie vvalking
the round, all these vvomen dailie and nightlie sitting, and
attending in their tent doores as he passed by to vievv
them: modestie m
                  •
               y not repeat the rest. At Gometta
there is the monument of Siddie Blabbas one of their great
saints, and there a great stonne, vpon vvhich the Moores
vse to rub their bellies, saying it cureth the chollicke and
diuers other diseases. Som Christians say this Siddie Blabbas
vvas saint Augustine, and that vpon this ston he preached:
both vvhich savour of superstition. But Muley Abdala
Melck had no such devotion, for he vvent not there at all,
nor those vvomen neither, almost famished and starved
vvith hunger, and cold: for no man durst come neare them
all that time to bring them any provision. This vvas one
of his tragicomicall parts.
            One of the Englishmen vvhom he loued aboue the rest,
vvho had the chardge of one of his chieffe horses, vvhich
vvas verie vnrulie, &amp; vvould bite any man that came neare
him, therfore alvvaies fast tyed vp: the king comming into
his rovva, or stable, &amp; spying some thing amisse about the
horse, vvould not strike the Englishman, but commanded
the horse to be let loose, &amp; the Englishman to stand fast by
him, suffering the horse to bite him at his pleasure, euē the flesh frō his armes: durst not stir till the king called to him.
An other time, the same Englishman complayning to him,

that he had nothing to eate saue barlie, the King caused
the horse his Sabadera or bag in vvhich they vse to giue
them provander, to be hanged about the English mans
necke full of barlie: (as they doe vpon their horses heads)
and so made him eate the barlie like a horse. An other time
the King, hauing taken offence at some thing, threatned
to kill the Englishman, and that vvithout delay: an Alkaid,
vvilling to saue his life, offered the King I knovve not how
manie hundreth Duccats for him, to buy him of the King.
VVhy thou foole (said the King) doest thou thinke I
meane to kill him? No, I vvould not for so manie thousand
Duccats: but to the Moores (as I said before) his iests,
and threats vvere in good earnest.
            One of his Negros vvhom he loued, and called brother,
hauing offended him, being in his Obadia, that statelie
pallace, vvalking in his garden, a little paradise, in the middest
vvhereof are diuers pleasant tankes or ponds, he caused
him to be cast into one of them, forbidding any to
come neare him to help him out againe: at length, hauing
vvalked a turne or tvvo, bade one goe pull him out: vvho
brought him vvord he vvas drovvned. VVhat my brother
drovvned, said he? Goe pull him out, and burie him: there
vvas all the mourning.
            An other he caused to eate his ovvne excrement: asking
hovv it relished. Yea he himself cut a peece of the brawne
of a mans arme vvhom he had killed, broyled it on the
coales,Gago frō whence al their gold cometh conquered by his praedecessors. and did eate it.
            The King of Gagoes son, not ouer a day or tvvo before
the Kings death (some say the same day) drinking together,
because he vvas not able to pledge him so much as he
drunk, being all aqua vitae (for so must euerie one doe as

he did, and drinke as he did) caused the vvhole bole full of
aqua vitae to be giuen him backvvard like a glister, till it
reversed in their faces againe that gaue it. Hauing not long
before made him to stand tvvo daies, and tvvo nights in
the vvater. And before throvvne dovvne an other of the
sons from the vvals of Saffia, and broke his thigh.
            Vnder a colour of going a hawking, vvould lie vvhole
daies, and nights abroad in the fields a drinking: And before
his death manie daies, &amp; nights together. God hauing
bereaued him of his vnderstāding as he did Nebuchadnezer,
and driuen him from men to dwell vvith the beasts of the field.
Yea he himself not long before, hauing driuen avvaie from
him all his most trustie servants, (saue one or tvvo) committed
to prison: And vvithall a vvatchfull dog vvhich he
loued, &amp; fed vvith his ovvne hand, for some small offence
he tooke, likevvise committed to prison vvith them: commaunding
he should but haue so much bread, and vvater a
daie. All these his vvatchmen at once sequestred from him,
and the other so ouer toyled, &amp; vvearied vvith vvatching
day &amp; night: (perhaps also vvearie of him as vvere others:)
all seemed to conspire his death. Plotted (as it seemeth)
before by some of the Elchies, or renegadoes, vvhom the
King had threatned the next time he came to his house in
Morocco to cut, and make Eunuches, to the number of two
hundreth: vvhereof they vvere sore affraid. And therefore
one among the rest (a Frenchman as is reported)
vvatched his opportunitie vvhen the King came back to
his tent at night (hauing been all the day abroad a drinking)
and vvith a peece chardged vvith tvvo chained bullets,
shot him in by the fundament, and privie members
into the bodie, as he vvas lying along in his tent. A iust

iudgement of God, in respect of that glister of aqua vitae
he gaue to the King of Gagoes Son: &amp; threatning likevvise
the elchies as before.
            As also in respect of that abhominable impudent and
filthie act he did at Saffia to those poore vvomen. But
chiefly (vvhich God in the end vvill punish vpon those
Mahometans, both Turks and Moores) in causing poore
Christians (boyes and others) to be circumcised perforce,
yea cut, and made eunuches. A iust iudgement of God
(I say) of all those Tyrants, both Turkes, Moores, and
others, to be trembled at: and so I leaue him.
            Immediatly after his death his younger brother Muley
Elvvallid vvas saluted King: being at that time a prisoner
in the Alcasaua, the Kings house in Morocco, expecting
dailie nothing els but death. VVherevpon some of his
frends (as at such a time, and in such a case all are frends, &amp;
happie he that can be the first; and svviftest Messenger)
running in all hast to the prison doore, and crying out
aloud to him to come forth: he thinking it had been to
execution, to be put to death: lingering, &amp; excusing himself,
that he vvould but take leaue of his vvife, and make
himself readie (vvhich he did only to die) they calling, and
crying more and more, at length he came forth, and so
vvas pregoned, and proclaimed King of a prisoner (I say)
on a sodaine become a King. Of a far more soft nature, &amp;
disposition than his brother: yet cruell and Tyrannous to
poore Christians, and to the English, vvhom of late he
hath most Barbarously entreated some of them. Eight at
once taken, and circumcised perforce: beaten, vvounded,
and one mans head almost cut of, to make them turne
Moores, and forsake their faith. The rest fearefull, dailie

expecting the like measure: as by letters latelie vvritten
from the Merchants there may appeare: vvhich I reserue,
vvith other passages, to a further account, leauing them to
his mercie, vvhich indeed is crueltie: For the mercies of the
vvicked are cruelties: and him and them to God to iudge
betwixt them, which in time might haue been preuented,
by a seasonable dispatch long since expected: the losse of
so manie poore Christian soules, as necessarie I dare say
as some other dispatches: if the bodies, and soules of
Christians be esteemed of any value novv a daies: as they
are in Gods sight right precious: precious in the sight of
the Lord is the death of his saints.
            
            And novv vvill I addresse my selfe (vvith this Proposition:
and petition herevnto annexed) to Christian
Princes, to condole, and commiserate the distressed, or
rather desperate estate of these most miserable, or rather
more than miserable, creatures, if more may be: not only
the English, but all other nations, vvho this long time
haue indured a most miserable, and intollerable slauerie
vnder these infidels, both Turks, and Moores, and are like
to doe more and more if not prevented: VVhich I pray
God at length they may take into their Christian consideration.
AMEN.
         
         
            
            A PROPOSITION, AND PETITION TO ALL CHRISTIAN
Princes, and States, Professours, and Defenders of the true
Christian faith, against all Antichristian povvers and
principallities: As vvell the Pope, and his adherents, as
the Turk, &amp; his Vassals, the Mahometans: both the one, &amp;
the other, novv in these last daies, to be vtterly destroyed:
and the Kingdome of Iesus Christ to be erected neuer to
be destroyed: but to indure, and triumph euen to the end
of the VVorld, according to Daniels Prophecie 2. 44.
And our Sauiours likevvise: Mat. 24. 14. This Gospel of
the Kingdome shall be preached in all the vvorld, for a
vvitnes vnto all nations, and then shall the end come.
            MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES,
Hauing been heretofore diuers times imployed
into Barbarie, for the redeeming of poore Christians
out of Slauerie, and other affaires: and hauing been
an eye-vvitnes of those great miseries, or rather indignities,
don to those poore Christians in those Countries by
that Barbarous people: indignities (I say) not to be vttered,
not to be expressed, but rather vailed ouer: as did that painter
the sorovvfull, and mournefull, or rather more than
mournefull countenance of that heathen Prince for his
daughter, adiudged to be sacrificed to that heathen Goddesse,
or rather Idoll: by no painters pensill to be expressed.
More than mournefull (I say) maiora lachrymis: so manie
poore Christians dailie taken by those infidels, Turks and
Moores, and caried captiues into those cruell lions dens, as

sheepe appointed for the slaughter: bought and sold in the
merket, as beasts, and not men: and devoured by those
blooddie monsters: vvhose soules lie vnder the Altar, daily
sacrificed to those heathen deuills, crying: Hovv long, o Lord
holie and true, doest thou not iudge, and auenge our blood on
them that dvvell on the earth? Yea beaten, and tormented
euen to death, to make them forsake their faith: as not only
men, but children also haue been forced, (and are daily)
taken perforce (I say) and circumcised, yea made Eunuches,
and so disabled at once, both from being men, and Christian
men, &amp; othervvise most shamefullie abused by those filthy
sodomites, not to be vttered. Quis Italia fando &amp;c. temperet
a lachrymis? Indignities (I say) maiora lachrymis, don, not
onlie to those poore Christians, but euen to Christ Iesus
himself, and his vvhole Church, and so to be apprehended,
vvithout any Nationall difference: vvhose members vve all
are, and ought to haue a fellovv-feeling of one an others
miseries, or els vve are no Christians at all, nor vvorthy
that name. I say, hauing been an eye-vvitnes of those great
miseries, and indignities don to the poore members of
Iesus Christ, (and consequently to himselfe:) as a poore
member of his bodie, I could not but be sensible thereof.
And present the bodies, and soules of those poore members
of Christ (like that Leuite in the booke of Iudges) dismembred,
cut in peeces, and quartered, to the eyes likevvise
of all the tribes of Israel: that is to say, the vvhole
church of Christ, both Prince and people, of vvhat nation
soeuer, all members of that his mysticall bodie, &amp; all alyke
interest therein: obliged, like the Israelites, to ioyne together
as one man, to right, and revenge, euen vvith the
hazard of their liues, &amp; estates, these so great injuries, and

indignities: consider of it, take aduice, and speake your mindes.
Open thy mouth for the dumme in the cause of all those that are
appointed to destruction. Those poore sheepe appointed for
the slaughter: the slaughter both of bodie, &amp; soule bought
vvith so deare a price, vvhose blood els vvill be required:
required (I say) at the hands of all those, to vvhom God
hath giuen power, &amp; meanes, (For to vvhom much is giuen
of him much shall be required) but vvant hearts, and mindes
to right, and redresse it: speak your mindes. Consider of it
(noble Princes and States) by your Embassadors one vvith
an other, both for the present hovv to relieue all those
poore soules that are in miserie, both vnder the Turks and
Moores: and hovv to prevent the miseries of others for the
time to come, like to be taken by their ships at sea more
and more, and made slaues, that is to say more than miserable:
if not preuented. VVhich a fevv good ships, (had
Christian Princes considered of it all this time, and been so
minded (that is to say of one minde hinc illae lachrymae)
might haue prevented: and may yet for the time to come.
To youe I speak (most noble Princes and States) that are
of one minde: consider of it take aduice, &amp; speak your minds.
And in youe to the whole church of Christ: let it be a freevvill
offering, both of Prince and people to Christ Iesus,
tovvards this so Christian, honourable, and charitable a
vvorke. A seacond redemption of his poore distressed
members, out of the hands of those infidels, verie easie to
be tamed, and subdued: &amp; vvith no great chardges to any,
out of a voluntarie contribution of manie. And (if I vvere
vvorthie to advise, and this my proposition, and petition to
take effect) this free vvill offering, or contribution, to be deposited
in the hands of the Lords the States Generall of the

vnited Prouinces, and the Prince of Orange: vvho haue so
great store of ships, and can most convenientlie manage
such affaires by sea: and are so noble, and so honourable,
as no doubt they vvould advance it to the vtmost. That so
this sacred seruice, being managed by one vndertaking
State, consisting of so manie vvise States-men, and prudent
Senators, may by Gods blessing receiue better successe, than
those expeditions in former times, frustrated by the dissention
of diuers Princes vndertakers: as in the Turkish history
may appeare. The greatnes of vvhich Monarchie novv
dravveth to a period: (as that of Rome,) magnitudine laboranssua:
both the one, and the other, (as I said before)
novv in these last daies to be finallie destroyed: and the
Kingdome of Iesus Christ to be erected, neuer to be d
                     •
                  stroyed,
&amp;c. I speak not these things of my self, neither doe I now
come from my self, but haue the holy Prophets, Apostles,
and Disciples of my Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus for my
vvarant. And in his name onlie, and no other, euen from
the King of Kings doe I novv come: (I magnifie my imployment)
more than an Embassadour, and yet vvithall a
petitioner, to treat, and entreat in the behalfe of his poore
afflicted members, vvho are not able, buth vvith prayers,

and teares, to treat, or entreat for themselues. Open thy
mouth for the dumme in the cause of all those that are appointed
to destruction. There is my commission: there is my
vvarrant. And I must in dutie, and vvill, stand vpon it,
it standing so highlie vpon the King my maisters honour,
the King of Kings: expecting novv hovv I shall be receiued:
the successe vvhereof I refer to him. And so conclude
vvith prayers, &amp; teares the vveapons of Gods church:
Quid enim nisi vota supersunt. Praying God to put into the
hearts of Christian princes, vvith one mind to fulfill his vvil:
for the finall destruction, both of that Antichristian, &amp; this
Mahometan tyrannie: and the finall establishment of his
aeternall Monarchie neuer to be destroyed. AMEN,
AMEN.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

